<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1447 (27 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1447.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">decision of administrative appeals tribunal to grant or not grant a stay not a 'decision' for purposes of the act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">no sufficient doubt as to judgment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">leave to appeal refused</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application for leave to appeal from a decision of Buchanan J of 22 September 2006, which upheld an objection to the competency of an appeal to the Court pursuant to s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) (the AAT Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The decision appealed from was the refusal by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal (the Tribunal) to stay a decision of the Social Security Appeals Tribunal, which had affirmed a decision of the delegate of the Minister to cancel the applicant's disability support pension pending hearing of the substantive appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The short ground of the decision of his Honour was that a decision to grant or not to grant a stay is not a decision for the purposes of s 44 of the AAT Act according to a long line of authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 There is no serious reason for doubting the basis for the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">I should say, however, that even if there were some basis for challenging that approach in principle, the difficulty faced by the applicant in his application for leave is that, even if the refusal of a stay is a decision for the purposes of s 44, it is a discretionary decision against which it is very difficult to mount any attack absent some fundamental error in the approach of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The form of the notice of appeal to the Court, which was under consideration by his Honour, discloses no such error of principle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">4 His Honour considered whether the jurisdiction pursuant to s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) might assist the applicant to side-step the line of authority referred to above, but, as his Honour indicated, no ground was advanced before him which would indicate any arguable basis for establishing jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">For what it is worth, it seems to me the same thing can be said of any possible application of the Administrative Decisions Judicial Review Act 1977 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">5 Furthermore, the issue is likely to prove academic in the sense that a hearing of the substantive proceeding before the Tribunal is to take place in early December.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">There is very little possibility of an appeal to this Court being heard before February, so it would essentially be overtaken by events in any case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">It may be that if the Tribunal were to reserve its decision, it is not beyond the bounds of possibility that the application for a stay might be renewed at that stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">I do not mean to indicate any view about that possibility, but it could be explored.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">6 For these reasons, in my opinion, this is not an appropriate case in which to grant leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The application for leave to appeal is dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Associate:

Dated: 7 November 2006

 
 The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Ms D Watson of Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 
 The Second Respondent submitted 
 
 Date of Hearing: 27 October 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 October 2006 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1447.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>