<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MLC Lifetime Company Limited and MLC Limited (No 2) [2006] FCA 1367 (19 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1367.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">schemes to amalgamate life insurance business</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">failure to comply strictly with certain procedural steps did not adversely affect policy holders</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">terms and conditions of policies to remain unchanged</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">actuarial evidence that neither transferring nor receiving policy holders adversely affected</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">no objection to implementation of the schemes by apra</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">schemes confirmed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">insurance</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 On 28 September 2006 I made orders confirming two schemes of amalgamation pursuant to s 194 of the Life Insurance Act 1995 (Cth) ('the Act').</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The first is the amalgamation of the life insurance business of MLC Lifetime Company Limited ('Lifetime') with part of the life insurance business of MLC Limited ('MLC') ('the Lifetime Scheme').</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The second is the amalgamation of the life insurance business of National Australia Financial Management Limited ('National') with part of the life insurance business of MLC ('the National Scheme').</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">These are the reasons for making those orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 Confirmation of the schemes is required by s 190(1)(b) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That section provides that '[n] o part of the life insurance business of a life company may be...amalgamated with the business of another life company...except under a scheme confirmed by the Court '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The applicants are ' life companies ' within the meaning of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">They applied to the Court for confirmation of the schemes pursuant to s 193(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 National Australia Bank Limited ('NAB') is the ultimate parent company of the applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The evidence of Ian Crow and John Reid, directors of Lifetime, is that the purpose of the schemes is to simplify the NAB Group's life insurance business by the two amalgamations whereby: &#8226; Each Lifetime policy and National policy (other than certain reinsurance policies entered into by Lifetime) will become a life insurance policy referable to an MLC statutory fund.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">&#8226; All assets referable to those policies will become assets of the relevant MLC statutory fund.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">&#8226; The policy liabilities in respect of those policies, all other liabilities of Lifetime's general and ordinary branch, and all other liabilities of National's statutory funds will become policy liabilities and other liabilities of the relevant MLC statutory fund.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">
 Principles 
 
 4 The principal object of the Act is to protect the interests of owners and prospective owners of life insurance policies in a manner consistent with the continued development of a viable, competitive and innovative life insurance industry (s 3(1)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">One means adopted to achieve this objective is the regime in Pt 9 of the Act for supervision of the transfer or amalgamation of life insurance businesses by the Court (s 3(2)(f) ; Re Royal &amp; Sun Alliance Life Assurance Ltd [2000] FCA 1259 ; (2000) 104 FCR 37 at [3] ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">5 In exercising its supervisory jurisdiction under Pt 9 of the Act, the Court has a discretion to refuse a scheme or confirm it with or without modification (s 194).</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Confirmation of a scheme pursuant to s 194 is not a mere formality ( ANZ Life Assurance Company Limited and ING Life Limited [2005] FCA 806 at [4] ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The Court must have regard to the object of protecting the interests of policy holders ( Re Royal at [3]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">It must ensure that the scheme will not be prejudicial to the interests of policy holders and that policy holders are properly safeguarded ( NULIFE Insurance Ltd v Norwich Union Life Australia Ltd [2005] FCA 1635 at [24] ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">
 Procedural Steps 
 
 6 Section 191 of the Act and Pt 9 of the Life Insurance Regulations 1995 (Cth) ('the Regulations') provide that an application for confirmation of a scheme may not be made unless certain steps have been taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The purpose of the steps is to ensure that details of a scheme are brought to the attention of the Australian Prudential Regulation Authority ('APRA'), the public and affected policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The steps are to be completed before the Court is moved for orders ( Re Royal at [10]; Re Armstrong Jones Life Assurance Ltd (1997) 74 FCR 160 at 163).</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">7 Evidence was adduced and comprehensive written submissions advanced by the applicants to establish their compliance with the procedural steps.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">I was satisfied that the steps were undertaken and it is necessary to refer to three matters only.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 First, s 191(2)(c) of the Act required an approved summary of each scheme to be given to every affected policy holder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On 17 August 2006, I made orders pursuant to s 191(5) of the Act dispensing with the requirement that the applicants send summaries of the schemes to MLC policy holders affected by the Lifetime Scheme or the National Scheme or to Lifetime and National policy holders for whom the applicants had no current mailing address ( MLC Lifetime Company Limited and MLC Limited [2006] FCA 1259 (' MLC Lifetime (No 1) ').</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Between 21 August 2006 and 25 August 2006, approved summaries of the schemes were sent by post to Lifetime and National policy holders other than those for whom the applicants held no current address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It follows that s 191(2)(c) of the Act was complied with.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">9 Secondly, s 191(2)(b) of the Act and the Regulations required the applicants to publish Notices of Intention ('Notices') to seek confirmation of each scheme in a form approved by APRA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The Regulations required the Notices to be published in the Commonwealth Gazette and ' one or more newspapers, approved by APRA , circulating in each State and Territory in which there is a register of life policies that includes the relevant policy of an affected policy owner ' (reg 9.02(1)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The Notices were to be published before the schemes were released for public inspection (reg 9.02(3)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">10 The schemes were released for public inspection on 21 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Notices in respect of the schemes were published in the Commonwealth Gazette and 12 newspapers approved by APRA on 18 August 2006 and 19 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">However, owing to a miscommunication, the Notices were not published in the Daily Telegraph (one of the approved newspapers) until one day after the schemes were released for public inspection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">11 I did not consider that delay to be fatal to the applications ( Re Royal at [18]; Re Armstrong Jones Life Assurance Ltd (1997) 74 FCR 160 at 162).</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The Notices were published in New South Wales in three other approved newspapers prior to the public inspection period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Public inspection of the schemes was also extended in New South Wales from 8 September 2006 to 12 September 2006 to compensate for the delay in publication in the Daily Telegraph .</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">For these reasons, I was satisfied that the delay did not adversely affect policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">12 Thirdly, the applicants informed the Court that, in two newspapers, an incorrect telephone information number was included in the Lifetime Scheme Notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">While it is unfortunate that this error occurred, I was also satisfied that it did not adversely affect policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The correct telephone number was listed elsewhere in the Notice and contact details for the applicants' solicitors were also included.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The public inspection details in the Notice were correct, as were two website addresses provided where a copy of the scheme, the scheme summary, and the actuary reports could be obtained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">I was satisfied that an affected policy holder who saw the Notice would have readily been able to obtain further information about the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 Assessment of the schemes 
 
 13 The schemes have been assessed by two actuaries, one of whom, Mr Clive Aaron, is independent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The other, Mr Kevin Allport, is the appointed actuary of MLC, Lifetime and National pursuant to s 93 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">As I noted in MLC Lifetime (No 1) at [7] and elaborate upon below, the overall conclusion of the actuaries is that the schemes will have no adverse effect on policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">The schemes are conditional on the appointed actuary certifying, immediately before the schemes take effect, that there has been no material change affecting the applicants' solvency and capital adequacy positions since 30 June 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">As at 21 September 2006, the evidence of the appointed actuary was that there has been no material change in the applicants' circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">14 Copies of the schemes and the actuaries' reports were provided to APRA in accordance with the Act and the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">APRA is a significant participant in proceedings for confirmation of a scheme ( Re Royal [24]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">It informed the Court that it has no objection to the implementation of either scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That was a factor of material significance in the exercise of the Court's discretion to confirm the schemes under s 194 of the Act ( The Application of Commonwealth Life Ltd [2003] FCA 637 at [13] ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">15 Significantly, the costs of the schemes will not be borne by policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">16 Lifetime and National will continue to exist after the schemes are implemented and have given undertakings to the Court to maintain their current telephone and email addresses for at least 12 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">
 MLC policy holders 
 
 17 No owners of policies continuing in MLC will have the terms of their contracts altered or affected by the implementation of the schemes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The appointed actuary's conclusion is that MLC policy holders will not be adversely affected as a result of the schemes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">His conclusion is supported by the independent actuary, who concluded that the benefit expectations of MLC policy holders will not be adversely affected by the schemes and the schemes should not materially affect their security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">18 The evidence of Steve Tucker, a director of MLC, is that a Committee of the Board of Directors of MLC resolved to authorise the schemes in the expectation that: &#8226; A marginal reduction in expenses and anticipated efficiencies arising from the schemes will assist MLC to maintain premiums, charges and fees at competitive levels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">&#8226; MLC policy holders will enjoy the additional security of a larger life insurance company with greater overall amounts held in its statutory fund.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">
 Lifetime and National Policy Holders 
 
 19 The terms of policies issued by Lifetime and National will also remain unchanged, other than the substitution of MLC for Lifetime and National as policy issuer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">As with MLC policy holders, the appointed actuary's conclusion is that Lifetime and National policy holders will not be adversely affected as a result of the schemes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The independent actuary's view is that the benefit expectations of Lifetime and National policy holders will not be adversely affected by the schemes and that the schemes should not materially affect their security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">20 The evidence of Mr Crow is that a Committee of the Board of Directors of Lifetime resolved to authorise the Lifetime Scheme in the expectation that: &#8226; Efficiencies resulting from the Lifetime Scheme will marginally reduce ongoing administration and governance costs, resulting in marginally higher profits and ultimately marginally higher bonuses to Lifetime's ordinary branch policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">&#8226; The security of participating Lifetime policy holder returns will increase.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">&#8226; Lifetime's direct branch policyholders will enjoy the additional security of a larger life insurance company with greater overall amounts held in its statutory funds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">21 The evidence of William Webster, a director of National, is that a Committee of the Board of Directors of National resolved to authorise the National Scheme in the expectation that: &#8226; Efficiencies resulting from the National Scheme will marginally reduce ongoing administration and governance costs to allow for premiums, charges and fees to be charged to National policy holders at competitive levels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">&#8226; The larger size of the MLC funds will allow for a greater level of diversification of management styles and exposure to asset classes, thereby resulting in an improved risk and return profile for National policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">&#8226; National policy holders will enjoy the additional security of a larger life insurance company with greater overall amounts held in its statutory fund.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">
 Submissions of policy holders 
 
 22 The Court was grateful for the assistance of three policy holders who appeared to make submissions at the hearing of the applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">
 Ms Monaghan 
 
 23 Ms Monaghan is an MLC policy holder who informed the Court she has held policies with MLC since 1963 and 1964.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Her primary concern, as I understood it, was that MLC policies would not cover contingencies covered prior to the schemes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">A second concern raised by Ms Monaghan was that MLC life insurance assets and liabilities would be mixed with general insurance assets and liabilities to the detriment of MLC policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">24 Confirmation of the schemes was sought on the basis that the terms and conditions of MLC policies would remain unchanged and the actuarial evidence is that the security benefits, investment returns, unit price and reasonable expectations of MLC policy holders will be unaffected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">On that basis, I was satisfied that MLC policy holders would not be adversely affected by reason of the matters raised by Ms Monaghan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">
 Mr Bray 
 
 25 Mr Bray is a Lifetime policy holder and his submissions addressed the Lifetime Scheme only.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">His primary concern related to the suspension of the practice of policy holders drawing and repaying loans against the value of their policies as a result of the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">According to Mr Bray, Lifetime personnel informed him in July 2006 that the practice of granting such loans had been suspended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">He sought an adjournment of these proceedings pending the provision by MLC and Lifetime of a statement explaining why the granting of loans had been suspended and whether that practice would be reinstated in the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">26 In response to Mr Bray's concerns, Mr Reid gave evidence that Lifetime's decision to suspend the practice of granting these loans was wholly unrelated to the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">He explained that the decision was made in response to management concerns that the practice of entering loans may not comply with regulatory requirements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">He also explained that the Lifetime board's current policy is that the granting of loans will be reinstated if those regulatory concerns can be overcome.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">27 Mr Reid's evidence as to the policies of the Lifetime board is not evidence of the policies of the MLC board.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">However, it is condition of the Lifetime Scheme that MLC will maintain, subject to periodic review, the policies of the Lifetime board in place at the time the scheme takes effect (cl 6).</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">As was confirmed by the applicants' solicitor, this would include Lifetime's policy of reinstating policy loans if regulatory concerns can be overcome.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">On that basis, I was satisfied that confirmation of the Lifetime Scheme will not affect the likelihood of the practice of granting policy loans being reinstated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">28 Mr Bray also submitted to the Court that he held general concerns regarding the standards of communication between Lifetime and MLC and policy holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">In particular, Mr Bray noted that neither Lifetime nor MLC had disclosed to Lifetime policy holders that the effect of the Lifetime Scheme was to reverse an earlier scheme, confirmed by the Court in 1997, whereby MLC transferred part of its life insurance business to Lifetime.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Mr Bray did not suggest that the interests of Lifetime policy holders would be prejudiced by reason of the Lifetime Scheme reversing the earlier scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">29 The evidence of Mr Crow is that the benefits identified in 1997 for separating the life insurance business of MLC and Lifetime diminished following the acquisition of MLC and Lifetime by the NAB Group in June 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Mr Crow's evidence is that the policies written by MLC and Lifetime have become increasingly similar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I was satisfied by the explanation given for the reversal of the earlier scheme and that policy holders were not adversely affected by Lifetime's failure to give them specific notice of that fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">
 Mr Tucker 
 
 30 Mr Tucker is a Lifetime policy holder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">His concern related to a decline in bonuses paid to him under a policy issued to him in 1972 and whether that decline would continue, or worsen, as a result of the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">31 The evidence of the appointed actuary is that the investment strategy, investments, investment earnings and approach to determining bonus rates adopted by Lifetime will be unaffected by the implementation of the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">His conclusion is that the reasonable expectations of Lifetime policy holders in respect of benefits payable will be unaffected by the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Accordingly, I was satisfied Lifetime policy members would not be prejudiced in relation to the bonuses payable to them following implementation of the Lifetime Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">
 Conclusion 
 
 32 The evidence is that the terms of the policies issued to Lifetime, National and MLC policy holders will remain the same and that policy holders will not be adversely affected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">APRA does not oppose the schemes and policy holders will not bear the cost of their implementation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">In these circumstances, I was satisfied that the interests of owners and prospective owners of life insurance policies were protected and orders to confirm the Lifetime Scheme and the National Scheme were made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">
 
 
 I certify that the preceding thirty-two (32) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Associate:

Dated: 19 October 2006


 Counsel for the Applicants: I M Jackman SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Freehills 
 
 Solicitor for the Australian Prudential Regulation Authority: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 26 September 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 October 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1367.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>