<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1324 (11 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1324.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">carriage of goods by sea</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">contract for cargo</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether binding contract</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">correspondence of offer and acceptance of terms</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether charterparty conditional upon existence of cargo contract</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether wrongful repudiation of charterparty</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">meaning of force majeure event</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">whether force majeure event existed due to non performance of a contract by another party</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether impractability of performance amounts to prevention of performance</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">admiralty &amp; maritime jurisdiction</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">admiralty &amp; maritime jurisdiction</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 

 
 1 In these proceedings it is alleged by Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd ('Hyundai MM') that a charterparty agreement came into effect between it and Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd ('Dartbrook') on 29 March 2004 whereby Dartbrook agreed to charter a ship from Hyundai MM for the carriage of 65,000 metric tons (10 per cent more or less) from Newcastle, New South Wales to the port of Masinloc in Zambales, Philippines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">It is now accepted by the other defendants, Marubeni Thermal Coal Pty Ltd ('Marubeni'), Anglo Coal (Dartbrook) Pty Ltd ('Anglo Coal') and Ssangyong Resources Pty Ltd ('Ssangyong'), that Dartbrook was acting for them in connexion with the charterparty and the agreement for the sale of coal to National Power Corporation ('National Power').</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Hyundai MM alleges that Dartbrook wrongfully repudiated the charterparty on about 14 April 2004 and that it accepted that repudiation on 16 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Hyundai MM seeks damages for the breach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 Marubeni and Ssangyong allege that the charterparty was conditional upon an agreement for the sale of coal being concluded and that no binding agreement was reached with National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">This last mentioned issue also has relevance to the cross-claim by Marubeni and Ssangyong against Dartbrook and Anglo Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">3 In the event that it is held that there was an agreement for charter with Hyundai MM, the defendants put in issue whether it was ready, willing and able to perform in accordance with the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">In particular they questioned whether Dartbrook's repudiation was so clear as to absolve Hyundai MM from actual performance under the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Each of the defendants contend that Dartbrook's inability to ship the coal was for reasons beyond its control and constituted a force majeure event, within the meaning of the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">4 In the event that Hyundai MM succeeds in its claim to damages, the basis upon which its damages is to be measured is disputed by the defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">At issue is whether Hyundai MM was obliged to use a vessel and seek a substituted cargo and whether that forms part of its proof of damage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">5 As to the quantum of the damages sought by Hyundai, principal amongst the issues raised by the experts is the question as to the likely daily rate of hire of a vessel which complied with the requirements of the charterparty and was available at the relevant time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Some more minor issues remained at the conclusion of the hearing as to allowances which should be made for contingencies and the length of time for the voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6 Anglo Coal, Marubeni and Ssangyong were joint venturers in a coal mining operation and Dartbrook was their agent for the sale of that coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Dartbrook seeks an indemnity from the joint venturers in accordance with its Sales Representative Agreements with them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Marubeni and Ssangyong deny that Dartbrook is entitled to an indemnity, because Dartbrook was guilty of wilful misconduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">That misconduct is identified as the entry into the charterparty as agent when a contract for the sale of the coal to National Power had not been concluded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Other issues raised by these defendants on the cross-claim against Dartbrook were not pursued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">An application for leave to amend that claim was refused in the course of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">7 Anglo seeks orders for indemnity and contribution as between the joint venturers in proportion to the subject of their joint venture agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Marubeni and Ssangyong claim an indemnity from, or damages against, Anglo Coal on the basis of its misleading conduct, namely its failure to inform them of Dartbrook's proposal to enter into the charterparty in the circumstances mentioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">
 THE JOINT VENTURE 
 
 8 Although Anglo Coal and Ssangyong are not named in the Dartbrook Joint Venture Agreement document dated 14 December 1993, it is common ground between the defendants that they were parties to it with Marubeni at the relevant time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The objects of the joint venture included the exploration, production and processing of coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The recitals record the existence of a mining lease with respect to land in New South Wales, a reference no doubt to the Dartbrook Coal Mine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Pursuant to cl 2.9 each party was to indemnify the other from any claims arising out of, or in connexion with, the joint venture agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Clauses 2.11 and 2.12 provided:
 ' Severalty 
 
 
 2.11 The rights, obligations and liabilities of the Parties with respect to the Joint Venture and the carrying out of the objects thereof are several and not joint or joint and several.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Each Party is entitled only to a share corresponding to its Interest of any benefits from the Joint Venture and is liable only for a share corresponding to its Interest in all obligations and liabilities incurred by a Party or the Manager on behalf of the Joint Venture 
 
 
 Indemnity and Contribution 
 
 
 2.12 If at any time a Party becomes liable in relation to the performance of the objects of the Joint Venture as contemplated by Clause 2.1 to an extent greater than that specified in Clause 2.11, the other Parties shall indemnify that Party in respect of the excess, so that the Parties bear that liability inter se in accordance with Clause 2.11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">' 
 
 
 There is no dispute that the parties' interests under the joint venture agreement were respective: Anglo Coal 77.5 per cent, Marubeni 15.5 per cent and Ssangyong 7 per cent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">9 Dartbrook was appointed as agent of the joint venture under three Sales Representative Agreements with the other three defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The agreements are in identical terms and two of them are dated 30 October 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Shell Coal (Dartbrook) Pty Ltd, Showa Coal (NSW) Pty Ltd and Marubeni are named as parties to the agreements in evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Shell Coal subsequently changed its name to Anglo Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">It may be that Showa Coal became Ssangyang.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It is not in dispute that the three defendants entered into agreements in those terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">10 Pursuant to the agreements, Dartbrook was appointed as agent for the sale of coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">It had responsibility for all matters relating to the coal belonging to the joint venture between the point where it was received for delivery and the point at which it passed to a purchaser or other person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Dartbrook was authorised to negotiate in good faith and to enter into agreements for the sale of coal and attend to its shipment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Pursuant to cl 12.1 of the agreements, and subject to cl 12.2 and cl 12.3, the joint venturers were to indemnify Dartbrook.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Clause 12.1 was in these terms: 
 
 
 '12.1 Subject to Clauses 12.2 and 12.3, JV Participant shall indemnify and hold harmless DCS against and shall pay all claims, demands, actions, costs (including costs as between solicitor and client as well as between party and party) losses, damages and expenses whatsoever (collectively 'claims and losses') which may be made or brought against DCS or incurred or suffered by it arising out of any Sales Contract entered into by DCS or any charterparty, bill of loading or other contract entered into by DCS in relation to its performance of a Sales Contract or in any other way arising out of or in relation to the performance by DCS of its obligations under this Agreement whether or not any such claims and losses are caused by or arise from the negligence or other tortious act or omission of DCS, its directors, employees or agents or the breach of this Agreement by DCS or in any other manner whatever and whether or not any such claims and losses are made, brought or recovered against or incurred or suffered by DCS as a direct result or as a consequence of all or any of those causes (and whether or not any of those consequences is reasonably foreseeable or not) and whether or not any intervening cause (whether reasonably foreseeable or not) alters the nature or increases the extent of any such claims and losses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">' 
 


 
 Clause 12.2 provided: 
 
 
 '12.2 (a) The indemnity in Clause 12.1 does not extend to claims and losses which arise from the wilful misconduct of one or more of DCS's directors, employees or agents other than independent contractors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The term 'wilful misconduct' means any act or omission (including a negligent act or omission) done or omitted with deliberate or reckless disregard for foreseeable and harmful consequences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">
 
 (c) DCS indemnifies the JV Participant against any claim, action, damage, loss, liability, cost, charge, expense, outgoing or payment which the JV Participant pays, suffers, incurs, or is liable for in connection with: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) any unauthorised representation made or warranty given by DCS in connection with the JV Participant's Coal; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) any breach of, or default under, this Agreement by DCS.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">' 
 
 
 
 


 NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN DARTBROOK &amp; NATIONAL POWER 
 
 11 Ms Jerene Tan was employed as a marketing manager for Anglo Coal, based in Brisbane.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">She was responsible for international sales of coal from the Dartbrook mine and the Drayton mine in the Hunter Valley, New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Although Dartbrook was usually the company selling the coal from the Dartbrook Mine, in this case the contracting party was to be Anglo Coal because the buyer, National Power, had previously dealt with that company and sought it out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It is not however suggested that it was not Dartbrook, through Ms Tan, which was responsible for the negotiations for the sale of coal, as the joint venture would require.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">12 In early March 2004 Anglo Coal's agent in the Philippines was approached by National Power, which expressed an interest in purchasing about 60 000 metric tons of thermal coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The amount of coal to be purchased was limited by the maximum draft at the destination port in the Philippines, Masinloc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">National Power was seeking to load a Panamax class vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">13 Nearly all coal sold by Dartbrook was sold on an FOB basis, with the purchaser bearing the costs of transporting the goods from the loading port to its overseas destination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">On 10 March 2004 Ms Tan sent offers for the sale of coal from each of the Dartbrook and the Drayton mines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The Dartbrook offer, of 50-70 000 metric tons, was for a price of US$55 per metric ton and was to be FOBT Newcastle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The offer was said to be open until 15 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">The offer was the subject of discussion between Ms Tan and Ms Dayao of National Power in the Philippines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">At these meetings National Power requested that Anglo Coal resubmit its offer on the basis that Anglo Coal would become responsible for arranging and paying the costs of shipping the coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The sale of coal from either of the mines on this basis was rare.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">It was however agreed that Anglo Coal would charter a vessel and that the final price of the coal would include the charter freight rate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">14 On 17 March 2004 Ms Tan submitted a further offer on the basis requested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The quantity of coal was said to be 65 000 metric tons (+/- 10 per cent) at US$86 per ton.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The laycan at load port was 15 to 30 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The conditions of sale included one that National Power be responsible for demurrage at both loading and discharge ports, the latter being Masinloc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">The offer was open until 18 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">15 On 19 March 2004 National Power attempted to accept the lapsed offer at $85.70 per metric ton with 'the terms and conditions of regular supply contract with National Power' to be applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Ms Tan did not acknowledge the acceptance out of time and says that the terms proposed by National Power would have been unacceptable in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">Negotiations continued as to the specification of the coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">16 On 23 March 2004 Ms Tan sent a further offer in writing to sell the same quantity of coal for $85.70 per ton.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">The terms she proposed included demurrage at US$45 000, with National Power to be responsible for demurrage at the discharge port.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">The contractual specifications with respect to the coal were in the same terms as the offer of 10 March 2004 except in one respect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">The other contractual terms differed in some respects from the earlier offer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The offer was said to be open until close of business that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Ms Dayao called Ms Tan and asked for an extension of time because she was travelling.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The Vice-President, Logistics, of National Power also wrote to Ms Tan on the same day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">He said that he understood that the terms and conditions of her letter of offer had been discussed at an earlier meeting between her and Ms Dayao on 15 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">He advised that the terms and conditions were acceptable, subject to written confirmation by Ms Dayao when she returned from China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Ms Tan wrote to National Power on 24 March 2004, extending the time until the following day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">17 On her return Ms Dayao had further discussions with Ms Tan regarding the cargo specifications in the offer of 23 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">After that further negotiation Ms Tan made a written offer to National Power dated 25 March 2004 ' which will supersedes [sic] all previous offers made to National Power Corporation ... ' for the same quantity of coal at: 
 
 'US$85.70 per tonne basis 7040 kcal/kg GDB C &amp; F Masinloc 
 (FOBT price is US$54.70 per tonne) 
 (Freight is US$31 per tonne and will be invoiced on BOL tonnage)' 
 
 
 Anglo Coal was said to be submitting the offer, with Dartbrook named as the seller.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Demurrage was the same as that contained in the offer of 23 March.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The contractual specifications for the coal referred to total moisture of 10 per cent and ash of 12.5 per cent, amongst other things.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">These were relevant to the penalties which might be deducted from the base FOBT price.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">Towards the conclusion of the letter of offer, under the heading ' Other Terms and Conditions' it was said that 'All other terms and conditions are to be mutually agreed in a new contract' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">18 By letter of the same day, 25 March 2004, National Power advised that it accepted the proposal 'on the following basis' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Seven items were listed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">The FOBT price was to be $54.50 per ton, but the rates for demurrage and freight listed were the same as those in Ms Tan's letter of offer under reply.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">There was to be acceptance of a nominated vessel by National Power within 24 hours.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Other matters listed related to the specifications for the coal and the penalties which would apply and included a change from 10 per cent moisture to 12 per cent and a penalty was to apply if the ash content exceeded 12 per cent, whilst Ms Tan's letter of offer had specified it at 12.5 per cent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Attached to that letter was a document entitled 'Price Adjustments on Coal Quality' which provided formulas for an adjusted contract price having regard to the guaranteed moisture content.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">The letter concluded ' We hope the above will finally secure the contract between Anglo Coal and NPC' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">19 On 26 March 2004 Ms Tan wrote to Ms Dayao listing the discharge terms and conditions for the coal shipment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">These were terms not previously notified in writing by Ms Tan but she says that she had discussed them with Ms Dayao.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">On the same day she wrote to personnel at Dartbrook and advised: 
 'We finally concluded 65kt to National Power Corporation (NPC) Phillippines at FOB US$54.50!</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">This is for lifting in late April'04.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">As NPC only want the deal on C&amp;F basis, we have to enter a C/P with the Hyundai Marine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">The costing is as follows: 
 
 Demurrage base on 14 days (worst case) = US$45K x 14 = $630,000 
 Less: 
 Margin from Freight quoted to NPC: U$2.275 x 65,000mt - $47,875 
 _______ 
 Net cost $482,125 i.e US$7.42/mt 
 
 FOB net of demurrage = US$54.50 less US$7.42 = US$47.08 ...' 
 
 20 The President of National Power wrote to Ms Tan in the following terms in a letter dated 29 March 2004:
 'This is to confirm acceptance of your revised offer to supply and deliver 65,000 MT +/- 10 per cent of Dartbrook Coal at US$85.50/MT at load port laycan of April 15-30 2004 as contained in your letter dated 25 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 
 We also wish to confirm that all other conditions as advised by Ms Elisa L. Dayao Manager Fuel Management Department, in our letter dated 25 March 2004 (Ref.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">N0.FMD-04-025) shall be applied for this contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">' 


 
 21 Ms Tan says that the change in the freight rate from $85.70 to $85.50 had been discussed between her and Ms Dayao in the period 25 March to 29 March 2004, as had the coal specifications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">I infer that this is said to have occurred prior to the receipt by her of National Power's letter of 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">It is likely that the letter was sent by facsimile transmission, since that was the course followed by National Power with its other letters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">The time at which it was received by Ms Tan is not apparent and she was not questioned on this point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">22 On 1 April 2004 Ms Tan contacted Ms Dayao concerning the nomination of the vessel the Tian Bai Feng and asked whether it was suitable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">A reply dated 2 April was received, advising that it was, subject to certain conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">They were four in number and ranged from Anglo Coal securing a waiver if the Philippine flag vessel was not available; Anglo Coal assuming responsibility for any claim or conflict due to the vessel's arrival at Masinloc outside the delivery window of 20 to 29 May 2004; Anglo Coal assuming responsibility for any time and cost lost should the vessel exceed the maximum draft; and Anglo Coal assuming responsibility for any damages to National Power facilities attributable to inconsistency of vessel specifications with the contract provisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">Ms Tan says that she did not understand the reference to Anglo Coal's liability, in the event that the vessel exceeded the maximum draft, to be a rejection of the vessel nominated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Ms Tan responded in writing the same day, advising that the guarantees requested could not be given; that there were already stipulations in the earlier letter of offer of 25 March 2004 concerning the waiver for non Philippine flag vessels; and, generally, that the shipment was to be performed according to the terms and conditions contained in that letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">National Power was advised that the Tian Bai Feng had been nominated, details of it were provided and their confirmation of its acceptance requested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">On the same day Ms Tan advised that the charterparty had been finalised with the shipowner, incorporating the discharge terms outlined in the letter of 26 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">23 On about 3 April 2004 Ms Dayao advised Ms Tan that there was heavy congestion in the port of Masinloc and National Power required the coal to be delivered in a timeframe which would allow an adequate supply of coal to be maintained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">Ms Tan approached Hyundai MM which agreed to change the laycan period to between 26 April and 8 May 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">National Power was so advised on 5 April 2004 and its draft agreement requested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">24 National Power forwarded its proposed contract document which contained many terms different from those previously agreed to and which were unacceptable to Anglo Coal, Ms Tan says.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">On 7 April 2004 she sent a draft sales agreement between Anglo Coal, as an agent for Dartbrook who was said to be agent ' for the Dartbrook Joint Ventures '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">The document followed the terms of the letter of offer of 25 March 2004, but the price was that referred to in National Power's letter of 29 March 2004, US$85.50 per ton; the FOBT price US$54.50 and the figures for moisture and ash content were listed at 12 per cent, as had been required in that company's letter of 25 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">The discharge terms contained in Ms Tan's letter of 26 March 2004 were also included in the draft document.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">On 8 April Ms Tan forwarded a chronology of the negotiation concerning the agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">This appears to have occurred in response to discussions about National Power's proposed contract document.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The terms of the chronology suggest that she believed acceptance of the terms proposed by Anglo Coal had occurred on 25 March and acceptance was reconfirmed on 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">She asserted that Anglo Coal's letter of offer provided that all other terms and conditions of the shipment were to be mutually agreed in a new contract, but that the terms proposed by National Power, over and above those contained in the letter of offer, were unacceptable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">She said that if National Power was unable to accept the proposed agreement 'which reflects the terms agreed in the offer letter' then Anglo Coal gives notice that it will be required to cancel the charterparty Agreement with the shipowner which would result in loss being incurred by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">National Power was asked to reconsider its position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">25 Over the following week Ms Tan attempted to 'finalise' the coal sales contract with National Power but was unable to do so in terms acceptable to Anglo Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">National Power attempted to impose new and onerous terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">On 14 April 2004 she wrote advising National Power that if it did not sign the draft agreement by 15 April 2004 she would be obliged to cancel the charterparty with the shipowner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">She warned that should costs, charges and damages be suffered by Anglo Coal, it reserved its right to claim them from National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">The agreement was never signed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">On the same day Ms Tan advised the ship's broker:
 '... we regret that due to the end-user requiring conditions over and above than [sic] what was agreed on the accepted offer, we are not able to conclude a contract with the end-user for the performances of the above ... ' 


 
 and cancelled the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">26 No action was ever taken by Anglo Coal against National Power for breach of the agreement .</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">
 THE CHARTERPARTY 
 
 27 Ms Tan engaged Anderson Hughes, shipbrokers in Brisbane, with respect to the chartering of a ship by Dartbrook.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Anderson Hughes in turn contacted Hyundai MM and advised that they had been approached with respect to a cargo of coal from Newcastle to Masinloc in the period 15 to 30 May.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">The offer received from Hyundai MM was passed on by Anderson Hughes to Ms Tan on 17 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">It was said to be open until the afternoon of the following day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">The account was nominated as Anglo Coal but advice of the full official name was requested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The vessel was to be a Panamax bulk carrier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">The owners were to nominate a final performing vessel 10 days prior to the vessel's departure at the loading port, at the latest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">The cargo quantity was 65 000 metric tons with 10 per cent and the voyage from Newcastle to Masinloc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">28 On 22 March 2004 Ms Tan advised the brokers of acceptance of the Hyundai MM quotation subject to a final charterparty agreement to be agreed upon and 'reconfirmation from our customers (National Power) on our offer and discharge terms' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Negotiations then ensued as to the terms of the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">In the midst of them, in an email from Anderson Hughes of 25 March 2004, it was pointed out to Ms Tan that the charterers may well ask what the connexion between Anglo Coal and Dartbrook was and might even ask for some further explanation respecting the two companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">This apparently came to pass because in an email on the same day Anderson Hughes advised Mr Yang as follows:-
 'Dartbrokk [sic] is a mine which is JV between 
 
 Anglo Coal 77.5 percent 
 Marubeni 15.5 percent 
 Ssangyong 7 percent 
 
 Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd is sales company on behalf of the JV.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">' 
 
 29 On 29 March 2004 a 'full recap of the concluded fixture' was sent by Anderson Hughes to Hyundai MM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">It is not in dispute that Hyundai MM and Dartbrook were in agreement as to all necessary matters at this point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">30 The document which was then forwarded was in the form of the Americanised Welsh Coal Charter ('Amwelsh 93') and bore the date of 29 March 2004, although it was provided by the shipbrokers to Hyundai MM on 2 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">It is not signed by Dartbrook, which appears as the charterer, but no point is taken about this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">Dartbrook accepts that it had agreed to the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">Hyundai MM was described in the pro forma document as:
 ' Owners of ......... (flag) vessel TBN ......' 
 
 ('To be nominated').</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">It was to proceed to one safe berth in Newcastle, New South Wales and to there load:
 '... in such safe berth as they shall direct, a full and complete cargo of coal as contracted under the relevant sales contract, tons of 2240 lbs /1,000 kilos* 65,000 .. 10% more or less in the Owners' option;' 
 
 31 Upon being loaded the vessel was to proceed to Masinloc 'at seawater arrival draft of 14.0 metres' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">Freight was set at the rate of US$29.50 per ton.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">Notice of the date of the vessel's expected readiness to load was to be given on ' 12/7 days ' and the time for loading was not to commence until 15 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Lay time was to cease on completion of loading and also on completion of dischargement (cl 6(g)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">32 In cl 10 'Demurrage/Despatch' it was said that Dartbrook had the option of keeping the vessel on demurrage at the loading and/or discharging port(s).</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Demurrage was to be paid by the charterers to Hyundai MM at the rate of US$45 000 per day or pro rata for part of a day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Clause 29 permitted Dartbrook to have the privilege of transferring part or whole of the charterparty to others, 'guaranteeing to the Owners due fulfilment of this Charter Party' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Clause 30 dealt with the address commission, which was set at 3.75 per cent on gross freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">Attached to the form of charterparty were special conditions in the nature of rider clauses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">33 Clause 33 contained provisions as to the nomination of a vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">It provided that ' the Owners are to provide the performing vessel ' within or a period prior to the vessel's estimated time for arrival at the loading port.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">The vessel could be rejected if it did not comply with the description of the vessel in the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">34 Clause 34 contained the description of the vessel, which the owner was to guarantee was ' owner/managed/chartered or controlled ' by it at all times.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">The draft of the vessel was described in subcl (C) as 'loaded saltwater draft maximum 14 metres' and subcl (K) provided that the vessel was to be of such size, draft, air draft and other dimensions 'to permit it safely enter, berth, lay alongside, load and discharge and depart always safely afloat from loading and discharging ports' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">It was to be the responsibility of the owners to establish the applicable size, draft and other requirements at the loading and discharging ports and berths 'and to ensure that the Vessel is loaded so as to comply at all times with such requirements (see also 'Description of Vessel' clause )' (cl 35(A)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">Clause 35(B) provided that if the owners or the master permitted the vessel to be loaded with a quantity of cargo so that on arrival at any discharging port it had a draft in excess of the permissible entry draft at that port, Dartbrook was to have the right to require the vessel to proceed to that port or some other port for the purpose of lightening or effecting a complete or partial discharge of cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">The owners were to pay the costs if that were necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">35 Clause 41 gave Dartbrook the option of loading at other east coast Australian safe ports.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">Clause 45 contained the force majeure clause, which was in the following terms:
 ' 45.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">FORCE MAJEURE 
 
 Neither party shall be liable for any failure to perform or delay in performing its obligations under this charterparty (except for the payment of money due), nor shall laytime or time on demurrage count, where the party is being delayed, interrupted or prevented from doing so by reason of any Force Majeure Event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">
 
 For the purposes of this charterparty, the term "Force Majeure Event" means: 
 
 
 
 (A) Any strike, labour difficulty, lock-out, stoppage, dispute or difference with workmen, long shore men, railways or railway men, Lightermen, Tugboatmen, Maritime Union of Australia Labour or other hands essential to the provision or loading or discharging of the cargo or the working of the Vessel or connected with the mining, production, port or facility services at loading or discharging port or any transport and/or handling of the cargo whether inland or at the loading or discharging port or facilities; 
 
 (B) Acts of God, accident, breakdown of machinery or equipment, fire, explosion, flood, earthquake, landslip, ice, frost, snow, fog, bad weather at the mines, production or processing works or Shippers' or Receivers' works or ports or facilities, whether loading, discharging or transportation facilities; 
 
 (C) Rebellion, revolution, blockade, or any acts of any Government or any subdivision or agency thereof, acts of public enemies, embargoes, civil commotions, insurrections, political disturbances, epidemics, quarantine, riots, acts of the Queen's enemies, arrest and/or restraints of rulers, princes and people, acts of pirates or robbers by land or sea; 
 
 (D) Inability to obtain or delays in securing transportation facilities, stoppages of the Shipper's fuel supply, hindrances of whatsoever nature in mining production, processing, loading or shipping of products occurring without the negligence of the Charterer; and 
 
 (E) Any other cause, whether or not of the nature or character specifically enumerated above, which is beyond the control of such party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">
 
 
 
 The Charterer shall not be liable for any negligence, default or error in judgement of trimmers or stevedoring employed in loading and/or discharging the cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">
 
 Salvage and/or towage for Owner's sole benefit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">The Vessel is not liable for losses through explosion, bursting of boilers, breakage of shafts, or any latent defect in the machinery or hull not resulting from want of due diligence by the Owner of the Vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">
 
 The Shippers and/or Charterers and/or Receivers shall not be liable in damages or otherwise responsible for failure or delay in delivery or loading or in discharging if prevented, delayed or obstructed by any Force Majeure Event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">In the event of the cargo not being available through any Force Majeure Event, the Vessel has the liberty to sail without the cargo, or sail with any cargo forming part or parcel of the intended shipment on expiration of reasonable notice of Owners' intention so to do in order to enable the Vessel to keep her itinerary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">
 
 In the event of a Force Majeure Event arising: 
 
 
 
 (i) The affected party shall give the other party prompt written notice containing particulars of such cause or causes except for minor events, and shall take all reasonable steps to minimise any delay so caused; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) The performance of the suspended obligations shall be resumed as soon as practicable after such Force Majeure Event is removed or has ceased.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">' 
 
 
 CHARTERPARTY NOT PROCEEDED WITH 
 
 36 The vessel first nominated to perform the charterparty, the Tian Bai Feng , was to travel from Tobata in Japan for Newcastle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">Hyundai MM subsequently agreed to cancel this nomination and to nominate another vessel at a later date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">In their email of 5 April 2004 it was further agreed that the charterparty be amended to read that there be a new laycan from 26 April to 8 May.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">Other terms of the charterparty were to remain unchanged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">Mr Hwang of Hyundai MM said that he agreed to cancel the nomination because he wished to promote goodwill and was looking to further trade with Dartbrook.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">37 Discussion concerning a further nomination followed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">The shipbroker advised Hyundai MM that the Australia port authorities required 14 days notice of any arriving vessel and the charterers would appreciate a vessel having an estimated time of arrival of 27 to 30 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">38 Hyundai MM searched for an appropriate vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">On 13 April 2004 Mr Hwang received advice, which presumably he had requested, from Ferrobulk, a shipping broker, of a vessel which would be available in Taiwan at Kaohsiung on 20 or 21 April.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">The daily hire rate would be US$35 000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">The vessel was the Szare Szeregi .</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">Mr Hwang says that the hire rate was viewed as the owner's opening proposal and ' in view of the favourable redelivery area, we were optimistic that we could persuade owners to agree a lower rate of hire around US$32 000 --- US$35 000 per day '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">Those negotiations did not develop, no arrangement was entered with the owners and no nomination was made because, on the following day, the charterers advised that they were not proceeding with the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">39 On 14 April 2004 Ms Tan advised Anderson Hughes:
 'I refer to our numerous telephone conversations regarding the above charterparty for loadport laycan in Newcastle of 26 April --- 8 May 2004 to Masinloc, Philippines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">The receivers (NPC) no longer agrees to accepting delivery of the proposed coal cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">Unfortunately, Anglo will not be able to load the proposed cargo for this shipment as it will not be accepted by NPC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Furthermore, we are unable to offer an alternative to HMM such as a different discharge port.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">Therefore, we have no alternative but to give HMM notice that NPC refuses to accept delivery of the cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">Consequently, Anglo does not require this shipment/charterparty or any substitute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">This situation with NPC is not going to change, so both Anglo and HMM must act accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">We hope that HMM are sympathetic and understand our situation, which is beyond our control.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Kindly advise HMM urgently on this situation and let us know if they have any suggestions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">Thank you.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">' 


 
 This advice was passed on to Hyundai MM by the shipbroker in the late afternoon of 14 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">Mr Hwang responded that Hyundai MM might hold the charterer responsible for any consequences resulting from its non-compliance with the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">He enquired whether it proposed any alternative cargo, per cl 41 and asked for a response by ' 0100 GMT/15/Apr./2004 '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">40 On 15 April 2004 Anderson Hughes advised Hyundai MM that they were instructed, that the charterers would not be loading cargo ' as per c/p dated 29/3/04, including any other options pursuant to clause 41 due to circumstances beyond charterers control '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Mr Hwang responded on 16 April 2004 that it was understood that the charterers had no intention of abiding by the voyage charterparty and intended to cancel it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">As a result Hyundai MM had no choice but to claim all losses and consequences which might follow.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">41 Ms Tan says that when it became apparent that National Power would not be bound by the terms of the coal sales agreement, she attempted to find alternate cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">She contacted two parties unsuccessfully.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">The email transmissions concerning these enquiries appear to commence in about late April and late June 2004 respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">She said that she did not consider it possible to find a new cargo on a CFR basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">42 On 20 May 2004 Anglo Coal was advised that Hyundai MM claimed damages in the sum of US$841 074.85.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">
 WAS THERE A CONTRACT FOR THE SALE AND TRANSPORT OF COAL?</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">
 
 43 Hyundai MM pleaded an alternative basis for an award of damages in the event that a contract for the sale of the coal was found not to have been concluded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">In that event it would rely upon representations as to the existence of such a contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">It does not now seek to pursue that allegation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">44 Dartbrook and Anglo Coal do not dispute that an agreement came into existence with National Power by 29 March 2004, albeit one which was subject to the terms being restated in a fuller or more precise form, but not different in effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">It therefore belonged to the first class of contracts referred to in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; (1954) 91 CLR 353 at 360, by which the parties intended to be immediately bound to performance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">45 Marubeni and Ssangyong however deny that an agreement between Dartbrook and National Power was concluded and allege that Ms Tan knew that it was not in place on 29 March 2004 when she concluded the charterparty agreement with Hyundai MM. Evidence as to her true understanding about the coal sales agreement is relevant to the allegations of wilful misconduct on the part of Dartbrook, which may affect its entitlement to an indemnity from these defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">46 Marubeni and Ssangyong contend that there was a lack of correspondence between the offer and acceptance with respect to a number of contractual terms: the price for freight; the FOBT price; the specifications as to the moisture and ash content of the coal; the terms as to the nomination of a vessel; and the terms and conditions as to discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">Alternatively it is submitted that any binding agreement was made subject to a formal contract being agreed between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">This can be seen from the reference, at the foot of the letter of 25 March 2004, to ' all other terms and conditions are to be mutually agreed in a new contract '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">The formal contract was never agreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">47 Mr Lewis is one of the persons having expertise in the shipping industry, who was called as witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">He was called by Marubeni and Ssangyong to review the actions of Ms Tan by reference to usual practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">Some of his criticisms were based upon a misunderstanding as to what was being communicated; others were considered by Mrs Richards, who gave evidence for Dartbrook and Anglo Coal, not to reflect usual practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">In particular she said that it was often the case that agreements were concluded without documentation being finalised and signed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">In the end result I did not understand Marubeni and Ssangyong to seek to rely upon much of what Mr Lewis had said in his reports.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">The majority of it was not in any event directed to the matters pleaded and upon which these defendants ultimately addressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">The issues came down to two: whether there was a contract concluded between the parties; if it had not, whether Ms Tan is likely to have understood that to be the case when she committed Dartbrook to the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">48 Ms Tan gave evidence that the contractual negotiations occurred in a fast-moving market and involved a considerable amount of discussion and communications by email and facsimile transmission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">Ms Tan said that this occurred on almost a daily basis in the period between 25 March to 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">It was submitted that this evidence should not be accepted as credible because it was not contained in Ms Tan's affidavits, and a considerable time had been spent carefully proofing her as to the evidence she was able to give.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">I do not consider the evidence to be unreliable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">I see no reason to disbelieve Ms Tan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">It is correct to observe that the affidavit, which deals with the negotiations, focuses upon the sequence and contents of the written correspondence passing between Ms Tan and National Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">For good reason it was no doubt considered by Ms Tan and the solicitors preparing the affidavits that the written communications between 25 and 29 March 2004 inclusive contained the terms and conditions the subject of agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">The affidavit refers to oral discussions had by Ms Tan at some, but not all, points.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">She is said to have travelled to Manila for discussions early in the process and to have had a further discussion with Ms Dayao of National Coal which led to the letter of offer of 25 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">It would be surprising if there had not been substantial discussion about the communications passing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">The written exchanges, for the most part, mostly confirm this to have been the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">It may be accepted that by the time Ms Tan sent the letter of offer dated 25 March 2004, she and Ms Dayao had had considerable negotiations and had largely agreed upon the terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">49 National Power sought to improve its position on the price of the coal at an earlier point, when it purported to accept the offer of 17 March 2004 at US$85.70 per ton.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">It was this figure that Ms Tan included in her letter of 25 March 2004, together with an FOBT price of US$54.70 per ton and freight at US$31.00 per ton.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">Ms Tan says that the reference to a figure of US$85.50 per ton in National Power's letter of 29 March 2004 was to the figure agreed in the negotiations which took place between 25 and 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">This is confirmed by a number of factors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">The letter of 29 March 2004 refers to acceptance of Ms Tan's ' revised offer ', implying some discussion other than that in the written communications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">Consistent with its change to the coal price, National Power had changed the FOBT price in its letter of 25 March 2004, which responded to the letter of offer of the same day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">This appears to have been accepted as the basis upon which the parties were proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">That agreement on these figures had been reached by 26 March 2004 is confirmed by Ms Tan's advices to personnel at Dartbrook.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">50 Ms Tan also explained that the specifications for the coal continued to be discussed in this period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">To an extent National Power's letter of 25 March 2004 contained counter offers as to some of the specifications as well as to the price, as discussed above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">National Power required the moisture content of the coal to be changed from 10 per cent to 12 per cent and the limit of the ash content reduced from 12.5 per cent to 12 per cent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">That letter also included a reference to a further condition, that a nominated vessel be accepted by National Power within 24 hours.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">There is no reason to think that these matters were not discussed and agreed upon prior to National Power's letter of 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">It confirms that all the matters referred to in the letter written by Ms Dayao on its behalf on 25 March 2004 were to form part of the agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">51 On 26 March 2004 Ms Tan added the terms and conditions relating to discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">It was pointed out in submissions for Marubeni and Ssangyong that they are not referred to in National Power's letter of 29 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">Ms Tan however says that she had discussed those matters with Ms Dayao prior to sending the letter of 26 March.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">This accords with the terms of that letter which commence with the words ' we list the following discharge terms ... '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">This does not suggest that further negotiations are being entered into, but that the letter is listing matters which have already been discussed and finalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">52 By 25 March 2004 discussion on all topics, including terms relating to discharge, was likely to have been complete.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">The concluding words of the letter of that date from Ms Tan do not suggest that it was not intended that it take effect as an agreement until a formal contract was prepared.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">Further discussion then ensued as to the terms relating to freight rate and the coal specifications, initiated by National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">Variations were agreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">Whilst Ms Tan says that negotiations continued in the period from 25 to 29 March 2004, it is likely that they were completed by the time she wrote, in self-congratulatory terms, to personnel at Dartbrook on 26 March, advising that the letter had been finalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">National Power's letter of 25 March 2004 had predicted this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">National Power's letter of 29 March 2004 appears to be in the nature of confirmation of what had passed between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">53 The conduct of the parties after 29 March 2004 also confirms the existence of a binding agreement between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">A vessel was nominated by Ms Tan within two days of the last communication about the contract and acceptance of the vessel was provided the following day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">When National Power sought some additional conditions, the position taken by Ms Tan, that the terms of the shipment had been agreed, was firm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">This was not disputed by Ms Dayao, who proceeded on 3 April 2004 to negotiate a change in the laycan period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">It is true that National Power thereafter produced a draft contract document which contained terms and conditions quite different from those agreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">It is not possible nor necessary to draw any inference about whether National Power was motivated by the belief that it was entitled to do so or by the desire not to proceed with the contract for the sale of the coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">More relevant is the conduct of Anglo Coal and Dartbrook, through Ms Tan, which was consistent with a binding contact having been finalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">When it became apparent that National Power might not be intending to fulfil its obligations under that agreement, Ms Tan warned that if she was obliged to cancel the charterparty, and Anglo Coal suffer loss in consequence, a claim might be made against National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">I do not draw any inference to the contrary about Ms Tan's state of mind from the references in her emails to the shipbroker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">She was no doubt aware that her advices would be passed on to Hyundai MM and she was hoping to extricate Dartbrook from a potential claim for damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">The letter was understandably expressed in neutral terms and accepted to place the matter beyond Dartbrook's control.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">The letter is written in terms which simply express a commercial event, one which it is hoped Hyundai MM will accept.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">54 It was submitted for Marubeni and Ssangyong that Anglo Coal or Dartbrook could not have believed that it had a concluded agreement, because no legal proceedings was brought against National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">The submission tends to overlook the prospect that the principals for whom Dartbrook was acting themselves may have done so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">I put that to one side.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">It was suggested, in response to the submission, that the failure to do so may have been because of uncertainties of litigation in the Philippines, which assumes the proceedings could not have been brought in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">It is not necessary to determine that issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">It is just as likely, in a case such as this, that the decision not to sue National Power was a commercial one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">It does not necessarily reflect Anglo Coal's view as to its prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">In any event it says nothing about whether a contract was concluded in fact nor about Ms Tan's state of mind.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">
 WAS THE CHARTERPARTY CONDITIONAL UPON A CONTRACT BETWEEN ANGLO COAL AND NATIONAL POWER?</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">
 
 55 For completeness I will deal with the question whether the charterparty was conditional in the way in which some of the defendants contend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">56 Marubeni and Ssangyong allege that cl 1 conditioned the charterparty to the existence of a contract for the sale of the coal to be shipped.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">This follows from the specification in cl 1 that the cargo of coal was ' as contracted under the relevant sales contract '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">There was no sales contract and therefore no cargo to load.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">57 Dartbrook and Anglo Coal did not contend that cl 1 excused them from performance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">It was conceded by them, correctly in my view, that the words in cl 1 refer to the description of the coal as may appear in a sales contract and that they do not disclose an intention that a sales contract must be in existence before any obligations arise under the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">58 A contract for charter may be made conditional upon the charterer obtaining cargo for the agreed loading period, such that a failure to obtain it relieves both parties of their obligations conditionally agreed: see J Cooke et a., Voyage Charters' , 2 nd edn, LLP, London, 2001 at par 1.23.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">Mrs Richards, confirmed that such an agreement, one ' subject to stem ', is not uncommon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">This makes it less likely that the words relied upon by Marubeni and Ssangyong were intended to bear the meaning contended for.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">Dartbrook did not require a clause in the necessary terms and there was nothing in the parties' communications to suggest that it was sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">It may be inferred that the parties did not intend to take that course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">
 WAS THERE A FORCE MAJEURE EVENT?</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">
 
 59 Dartbrook and Anglo Coal submit that the refusal of National Power to perform the sales agreement excuses them from performance of the charterparty under the terms of cl 45 and in particular sub-cl (E).</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">The words of the clause that are the focus of this condition are that 
 'Neither party shall be liable for any failure to perform ... its obligation under this Charter Party 
 ... 
 where the party is being ...prevented from doing so by reason of any Force Majeure Event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">' 


 
 Such an event is defined by sub-cl (E) as ' any other cause ...' 'which is beyond the control of such party' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">It is submitted that a purchaser's refusal to proceed with the contract, and to take the coal, prevented Dartbrook from delivering coal, within the terms of the clause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">The submission for these defendants is that their obligation under the charterparty was to provide coal for delivery at Masinloc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">What was contemplated was not a small cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">It could not be said to have been practical for the defendants to perform the charterparty absent a purchaser or some other person willing to take delivery of that coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">In every practical sense, it is submitted, the refusal of the buyer to proceed with the contract prevented the defendants from performing the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">60 Impractability of performance is not generally recognised as a ground of discharge of a contracting party's obligations: E McKendrick, Force Majeure and Frustration of Contract , 2 nd edn, LLP, London, 1995 at pp 24-25; G Treitel, Frustration and Force Majeure , Sweet and Maxwell, London, 1994 at par 6-021.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">To the extent that it has been accepted as a ground by American courts, Treitel at par 6-020 observes that they have become increasingly reluctant to regard the increased cost or difficulty of performance as sufficient for this purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">The assertion that force majeure ' includes every event which is beyond the control of the parties' (see L D'Arcy, Schmitthoff's Export Trade: The Law and Practice of International Trade, 9 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 1990 at p 199) has been regarded as too wide: McKendrick at p 8 footnote 41.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">In PJ van der Zijden Wildhandel N.V. v Tucker [1975] 2 Lloyd's Rep 240 the sellers were entitled to cancel the contract if they did not effect shipment in time by reason of war, flood, fire or storm or ' any other cause beyond their control '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">This was held not to protect them when their supplier let them down, since the event did not prevent them from performing by other means.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">61 There is no doctrine in English law which corresponds with the doctrine of force majeure in French law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">The use of the words in contracts have required English and Australian courts to give them some meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">The characteristics by McKendrick at pp 24 --- 25, which have been recognised by the courts as constituting a force majeure event have regard to something which is: 

(a) irresistible;
 
(b) unforeseeable;
 
(c) external to the person claiming discharge; and has
 
(d) made performance impossible and not merely more onerous or difficult
 

 
 (and see Treitel at par 12 --- 017).</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">In the present case (a) (b) and (d) are not present.</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">62 In any event the submission for Dartbrook and Anglo Coal ignores the need to construe each force majeure clause by reference to its words, having due regard to the nature and general terms of the contract: Lebeaupin v Richard Crispin and Co [1920] 2 KB 714 per McCardie J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">Here the objective of Dartbrook was to load the specified cargo of coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">The obligation was not dependant upon the existence of a particular purchaser, as previously discussed, and could be fulfilled without a sale to National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">Clause 45 requires that Dartbrook be prevented from performing that obligation before it is excused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">The clause itself gives examples of what may amount to prevention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">It includes ' hindrances of whatsoever nature in mining production ' with the rider that they not be caused by the actions of Dartbrook itself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">The requirement that Dartbrook be prevented from performance, in practical terms, implies causation between the event and the inability to perform.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">Some force majeure clauses have been recognised as operating in this way (see Treitel at par 12 --- 019).</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">Nothing in National Power's refusal to proceed with its contract prevented Dartbrook from providing coal for delivery to Masinloc in accordance with the charter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">The ' practical ' considerations, to which Dartbrook and Anglo Coal point, are indicative of matters which may affect a party which considers itself to be at risk of loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">Proceeding with the charterparty may not have been to their advantage, but there was nevertheless a choice open with respect to performance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">They were not prevented from performance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">They considered it not be in their interests to do so and chose not to perform.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">
 HYUNDAI MM'S ABILITY TO PERFORM THE CONTRACT 
 
 63 In their defences Dartbrook and Anglo Coal alleged that Hyundai MM would not have been able to perform its obligations under the charterparty because it could not have secured a ship meeting the requirements of the charterparty within the time required for performance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">Those defendants alleged that they would not have accepted the nomination of the ' Szare Szeregi ', or a like vessel, because it did not conform to the description of the vessel required under the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">Further particulars of the allegation identified the requirement as to the maximum draft of the vessel as relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">After some evidence was given on that matter I was informed that this allegation was no longer pursued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">There was evidence that the Szare Szeregi would have been able to discharge the maximum load at Masinloc and that there were other vessels meeting the requirements of the charterparty which were likely to have been available at the relevant time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">64 Dartbrook and Anglo Coal sought to raise an issue as to whether Hyundai MM was ready and willing to perform the contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">An averment to this effect, on the part of a plaintiff, is usually taken as implied: Hensley v Reschke [1914] HCA 88 ; (1914) 18 CLR 452 at 467 (' Hensley v Reschke') .</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">Whilst a plaintiff is absolved from further performance, upon their acceptance of a wrongful repudiation by the other party, it is nevertheless necessary for them to show that they were ready and willing to perform their part of the bargain, and this includes their ability to perform: Peter Turnbull and Co Pty Ltd v Mundus Trading Co (Australasia) Pty Ltd [1954] HCA 25 ; (1954) 90 CLR 235 at 253 ( 'Peter Turnbull and Co' ); Hensley v Reschke at 467.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">The only allegation of inability to perform was that mentioned above and related to the vessel's draft.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">Dartbrook and Anglo Coal also submitted that Dartbrook's repudiation may not have been so clear as to amount to a refusal to perform.</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">It was said there was a question whether ' the failure of Dartbrook necessarily conveyed to HMM that, even if HMM performed its obligations, Dartbrook will still not perform its obligations '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">If Dartbrook had not clearly done so, it would follow that performance by Hyundai MM was not excused: see Peter Turnbull and Co at 246, 252 ; Mahoney v Lindsay (1981) 55 ALJR 118 at 119, referring to Jones v Barkley (1781) 1 Dougl.</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">684; 99 E.R.</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">434.</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">65 Marubeni and Ssangyong's position on this issue was not entirely clear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">They did not plead that Hyundai MM was unable to perform, but alleged that Dartbrook was entitled to repudiate pursuant to cl 33(D) of the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">That clause permits rejection of a nominated vessel if it does not comply with the requirements of the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">These defendants, in written submissions, did not pursue the allegation and sought merely to adopt the position taken by Dartbrook and Anglo Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">In argument they did not contend that Ms Tan could have rejected the Szare Szeregi .</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">66 The additional matter sought to be raised by Dartbrook and Anglo Coal may be dealt with shortly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">Dartbrook's repudiation was clearly made in the advice from Ms Tan of 14 April 2004, which was passed on to Hyundai MM by the shipbrokers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">When Hyundai MM queried Dartbrook's position, it was told that Dartbrook would not be loading cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">The repudiation was accepted by Hyundai MM by its communication of 16 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">67 I turn then to the question as to how Hyundai MM's damages are to be measured.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">
 THE MEASURE OF DAMAGE 
 
 68 Hyundai MM seeks to prove its damages following upon breach of the charterparty by reference to the consideration due to it under the charterparty (contract freight), together with any demurrage which may have become due to it, from which is to be deducted the expenses of hiring a vessel to perform the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">Dartbrook and Anglo Coal contend that where there has been a failure, on the part of a charterer, to deliver cargo the ' normal rule ' applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">It is expressed as the difference between contract freight and market freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">There is to be deducted from the freight due under the charterparty the amount that could have been earned by Hyundai MM's ship carrying other cargo in the period in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">They plead that Hyundai MM's loss is attributable to its failure to find alternative employment for its ship.</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">In this regard the ship might be either one owned by it or hired in.</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">They also contend that it is not for the defendants to prove that that income could have been made, but for Hyundai MM to prove that it was not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">The other defendants join in these arguments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">69 At the heart of the submissions for the defendants are the decisions in Cobelfret (UK) Ltd v Austin and Butta (Sales) Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Brownie J, 24 February 1988); Cobelfret (UK) Ltd and Anor v Austen and Butta (Sales) Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales Court of Appeal, Kirby P, Priestley JA, Meagher JA, 5 April 1991) (' Cobelfret ').</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">It is submitted that that case involves the application of the normal rule to a case such as this and that it recognises that the plaintiff is under an obligation to seek alternative employment for the vessel which was intended to be used under the charter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">This forms part of its proof of damage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">70 In Cobelfret the charterparty required the delivery of coal over a lengthy period and a number of voyages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">The charterer failed to deliver the required quantity of coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">It was necessary for the trial judge, in assessing damages, to construct a number of theoretical voyages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">71 Cobelfret was the owner of some ships, held others on time charter and at other times hired vessels for voyages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">Its claim for damages was based upon the gross freight it would have earned under the charterparty, deducting only the cost of chartering a vessel, from time to time, as the contract required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">This approach accords with that taken by Hyundai MM in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">It did not calculate any net profit it could have made by reason of one of its own vessels, or vessels it already had on time charter, being freed from performance under the charterparty and used in another profit-making endeavour within the charter period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">72 Brownie J found that about 80 per cent of the vessels used in performing the charterparty would have been vessels obtained by Cobelfret on voyage charter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">The balance used would have been its own vessels or vessels which it had on time charter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">Neither Brownie J nor the Court of Appeal considered that Cobelfret's claim as formulated to be inappropriate where vessels of the first kind were utilised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">So far as concerned the theoretical charter using its own or time-chartered ships however, it had not shown what profits it had, or could have, earned by using those (two) ships for other cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">His Honour found that it was likely that they would have made a profit, but he was not in a position to know what it was.</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">His Honour treated these profits as a contingency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">The correct approach, the Court of Appeal held, was to deduct two voyages from the calculation of damages on the basis that they were not the subject of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">His Honour's approach otherwise and the measure of damages employed were held to be correct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">73 In the Court of Appeal Priestley JA, with whom the other members of the Court agreed, was principally concerned with the content of the rule stated by Scrutton on Charterparties , 19 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 1984 at pp 395-396 as:
 'So, where a charterer refuses to load, the older cases indicate, as the ship owners measure of damages, the loss of profit on the charter (ie the freight to be earned less expense of earning it), against which the ship owner must give credit for what profit he can earn by a substituted employment of the ship.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">And it was said that he must mitigate the damages by accepting such substituted employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">It would be more accurate to say, and nowadays it is thought would be said, that his true measure of damages is the loss of profit he sustains by breach of the charterparty less the profit he can earn by using the ship elsewhere during the same period, just as a servant's damages for wrongful dismissal are the wages he would have earned under the broken contract less what he can earn elsewhere by being set free.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">' 


 
 and whether the requirements of mitigation have become incorporated into the normal measure in more modern times, as suggested in McGregor on Damages, 15 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 1988 at pars 172-3, 179-96.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">His Honour appears to have accepted both statements as reflecting the modern approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">Cobelfret did not deny the correctness of this approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">It argued that there could be a deduction of market freight only in very limited circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">His Honour considered what possibilities were open, following upon the defendant's breach, and held that the only circumstance where Cobelfret could not have earned income from its two vessels was if no cargo had been available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">This would provide the only basis for making no deduction from the contract freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">74 Scutton on Charterparties , 20 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 1996, Art 193 at p 394 says that in an action against a charterer for not loading a cargo the measure of damage is:
 'the amount of freight which would have been earned under the charter after deducting the expenses of earning it and any net profit the ship made, or might, have earned during the period of the charter on a substituted voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">' 


 
 and goes on to say that if the expense of earning freight on a substituted voyage of the same duration is the same as on the chartered voyage, the same result is arrived at by taking the difference between the charterparty rate of freight and the market rate of freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">In relation to the duty to mitigate (at Art 192, p 388, note 4) the authors say that a plaintiff is under a duty to mitigate its loss and damages will not be awarded for losses that it could reasonably have avoided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">In relation to the 'so-called duty' reference is made to Sotiros Shipping Inc v Sameiet Solholt (The Solholt) [1983] 1 Lloyd's Rep 605.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">There Sir John Donaldson M.R.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">said (at p 608) that a plaintiff is under no duty to mitigate his loss despite the habitual use by lawyers of the phrase ' duty to mitigate '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">As a matter of causation however a loss may be directly attributable to a breach of contract ' unless avoidable by some reasonable further action ', and that is a question of fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">Scrutton (at note 4) continues in the same terms as the previous edition (at [73] above).</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">75 McGregor on Damages, 17 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003 at par 27-062 deals with the 'growth of the modern measure ' of damages where there has been a failure to supply cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">The author says that:
 'The normal measure of damages may be stated today as the contract rate of freight less the market rate of freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">This is calculated by taking not the gross amounts of the contract and the market freights but the net amounts after the costs of earning the freights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">The market freight is deducted on the ground that this sum was or could have been earned by the defendant on the claimant's refusal to supply cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">This is in accordance with general principles and in particular with the measure of damages in an action for non-acceptance of goods sold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">However, this measure allowing for the deduction of market freight developed slowly in carriage contracts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">' 
 
 In connexion with contracts for the sale of goods, Carter on Contract , Vol 2, Butterworths at par 41---380 notes that the prime facie rule, which relies on a comparison of market price and contract price, assumes that the plaintiff will (or should) mitigate loss by going into the market.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">G Treitel , The Law of Contract, 11 th edn, Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003 at p 977 says that where a seller fails to deliver, the buyer must go into the market at the relevant time to buy substitute goods.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">This requirement finds expression in legislation concerned with the sale of goods.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">76 McGregor (from par 27-063) traces the development of the rule.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">The general rule as to the measure of damage is taken to have been stated and applied in Smith v M'Guire (1858) 3 H&amp;N 554; 157 E.R.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">589, and as ascertained by the calculation of:
 ' ... the freight to be earned, and the deduction of the expenses which the shipowner would be put to in earning it; and what the ship earned (if anything) during the period which would have been occupied in performing the voyage, ought also to be deducted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">' 
 
 In that case Martin B expressed some doubt as to whether the shipowner was obliged to look for employment for his ship, but McGregor regards this as being wrong ' now that the rules as to mitigation have been worked out, and the contrary view is stated in later cases ' (at 27-065).</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">Scrutton is of a similar opinion (at Art 192, p 389 footnote 31).</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">McGregor refers to statements in Aitken Lilburn v Ernsthausen [1894] 1 QB 773 and Wallems Rederij A/S v Muller [1927] 2 KB 99, to the effect that the shipowner is bound to search out other cargo or otherwise he would not be able to recover full damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">77 McGregor points to the difference between stating the measure of damages as ' contract rate of freight subject to mitigation ' and as ' contract rate less market rate of freight ' as lying in the practical matter of onus of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">Suggesting the latter as the ' modern rule ' (at par 27-066), the author explains that the effect is that a claimant will recover only contract rate less market rate unless the claimant can prove that in the particular circumstances substitute freight was not, and could not reasonably have been, earned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">He cites two decisions as apparently supporting the modern rule: Rheinoel v Huron Liberian Co. (The Concordia C) [1985] 2 Lloyd's Rep 55 (' The Concordia C ') and SIB International v Metallgesellschaft Corp. (The Noel Bay) [1989] 1 Lloyd's Rep 361 CA (' The Noel Bay ').</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">78 In the Concordia C the ' guiding principle ' confirmed by Bingham J (at 57) was that ' the owners damages should be such sum as would put them in the same financial position as if the Rheinoel charter had been performed, ' noting that the principle is easy to state but far from easy to apply.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">In applying that principle it was considered necessary to reduce the net revenue which the owners would have earned under the charter by the net amount which they did in fact earn during its currency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">In the The Noel Ba y Staughton LJ at 363 likewise described the shipowner's entitlement as taking into account the money they in fact earned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">79 None of the cases which make reference to a substituted cargo and an obligation, on part of the shipowner, to obtain it, suggest that there is a ' rule ' to that effect which is of universal application, applying in every case involving a failure to supply cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">The reference in the ' rule ' to the deduction of market freight, which was or could have been earned, expresses no more than what a shipowner, having a vessel available for the charter, would do in the ordinary course of business and acting reasonably.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">It is assumed that the shipowner would go into the market and obtain a substitute cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">Likewise where a shipowner breaches a charterparty it is assumed that the charterer will charter a substitute vessel and this is reflected in statements of the ' normal ' measure of damage: Koch Marine Inc v D'Amica Societa Di Navigazione A.R.L (The Elena D'Amico) [1980] 1 Lloyd's Law Rep 75 (' The Elena D'Armico ').</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">It is the operation of mitigation principles which are responsible for the rule.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">This was pointed out in Golden Strait Corporation v Nippon Yusen Kubishika Kaisha (The Golden Victory ) [2005] 1 Lloyd's Law Rep 443 (' The Golden Victory ') (appeal dismissed [2005] 2 Lloyd's Law Rep 747).</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">It is not therefore to be seen as stating a new principle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">80 A general, but not universal, rule as to damages must, in any event, give way in a particular case to solutions which fairly compensate a plaintiff: Johnson v Perez [1988] HCA 64 ; (1988) 166 CLR 351 at 355 -356.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">In The 'Golden Victory ' Langley J considered that the ' normal measure ' referred to in The Elena D'Amico , was merely a prima facie rule and the ' governing principle ' remains that the measure of damage is the loss directly and naturally resulting, from the breach of contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">The application of principles relating to mitigation must be understood in this light.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">81 Hyundai MM owns ships and charters ships both on long and short term.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">Part of its business is the carriage of cargo by hiring vessels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">In the present case it had contracted as an owner, but the vessel to be nominated was not limited to one of its own vessels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">Clause 34(A) of the charterparty recognises that the vessel might be provided from any such source.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">Its terms reflect the concern that Hyundai MM have control of the vessel used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">82 The situation with respect to Hyundai is similar to that of Cobelfret .</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">A factual difference however is that it was known that Cobelfret would have two ships on time charter for the purposes of the charterparty in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s430">They were at their disposal and able to be used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s431">It was obliged to mitigate for this reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s432">This accords with the approach taken in the cases referred to above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s433">The basis upon which the ' rule ' proceeds is that there is a vessel available for use.</sentence>
<sentence id="s434">That circumstance, and the shipowner's failure to use it for substituted cargo, are the only grounds for a conclusion that the loss claimed against the charterer was not a consequence of the breach of contract, but flowed from the shipowner's unreasonable inaction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s435">83 If it could be concluded that Hyundai MM had available to it a ship to take substitute cargo a short time after 16 April 2004, the profits that ship could have earned must be taken into account against contract freight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s436">This accords with what might be expected in practice, as Mrs Richards said.</sentence>
<sentence id="s437">An owner would simply be pursuing revenue for ' his fleet '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s438">It is simply a matter of comparing income streams.</sentence>
<sentence id="s439">It will be recalled that Scrutton, 20 th Edn, Art 193, makes an observation to similar effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s440">At a practical level there would have been no reason why a shipowner with a vessel available could not have gone into the market for substitute cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s441">At the relevant time there was more cargo than ships available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s442">84 Mrs Richard's view, that Hyundai MM would have had a vessel available, appeared to have two bases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s443">She considered that in a fleet such as Hyundai MM's a vessel could be made available by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s444">The second was that Hyundai MM should have maintained the fixture on the Tian Bai Feng , not the least because it was at a good price.</sentence>
<sentence id="s445">The latter does not provide a basis for an assumption that a vessel was available at the date of acceptance of repudiation, or shortly thereafter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s446">It is not even relevant to mitigation, since Hyundai MM could not have known, when it agreed to alter the laycan dates and not take a fixture on the vessel, that Dartbrook would later repudiate the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s447">85 In my view the basis for the rule, upon which the defendants rely, is the existence of a particular factual situation --- one where, as a result of the charterer's repudiation, the shipowner has a vessel available for use.</sentence>
<sentence id="s448">In these circumstances the ordinary application of rules as to mitigation require the shipowner to seek another cargo for that vessel to limit the loss at which would otherwise suffer, or explain why that was not possible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s449">The rule does not itself create a factual situation pertaining to the shipowner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s450">It does not operate, like a rule of evidence, so as to create an assumption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s451">Each case, where damages are claimed because of a failure to deliver cargo, will turn upon its own facts and the evidence relating to the position of the shipowner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s452">Where it is not apparent that the shipowner would have had a vessel available, the rule does not operate to require it to prove that it did not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s453">In a case such as the present it is for the defendants to allege and prove that the shipowner was in a position such that it could reasonably have avoided some of its loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s454">86 The defendant's submissions themselves reflect the state of the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s455">They were required to submit in the alternative: that either Hyundai MM could have used its own vessel or that it should have used a vessel hired by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s456">The latter submission recognises the likelihood that that is what Hyundai MM intended to do in this particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s457">By the time the charterparty was terminated Mr Hwang had sought out two vessels to hire for the voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s458">No vessel had been fixed when the breach occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s459">The state of the evidence did not permit the application of the rule.</sentence>
<sentence id="s460">87 In my view the ' normal rule ', which may apply where cargo is not delivered and which requires a shipowner to find substitute cargo, has no application in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s461">
 MITIGATION OF DAMAGE 
 
 88 I deal with this topic although it seems to me that the defendants may well be taken to have abandoned it, in favour of an outcome based upon the ' normal rule ' to which reference has been made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s462">89 Mrs Richards made the general comment, in her second report, that there were numerous other cargoes and vessels available to Hyundai MM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s463">This was said in the context of the issue relating to the rate of hire derived from reports of fixtures.</sentence>
<sentence id="s464">I did not understand Mrs Richards at this point to say that Hyundai should have chartered another vessel, since her view was that it would use its own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s465">She was dealing with the case as presented to her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s466">If that was her view, it was contrary to the other expert evidence and that of Mr Hwang.</sentence>
<sentence id="s467">90 Neither Mr Lewis nor Mr Everton considered it to be usual practice to fix upon a vessel without having a cargo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s468">Although the market at the time favoured owners, its movements may now be viewed in hindsight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s469">There was a real risk that Hyundai MM would expose itself to a greater loss if it did so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s470">Finding cargo takes time and in the prevailing market it would not be sensible to seek out a cargo and then find a vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s471">91 The defendants have not identified a course of action open to Hyundai MM which it could be said it should reasonably have taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s472">
 THE QUANTUM OF DAMAGES 
 
 92 Mr Everton produced two calculations for loss of profit (Ex 28) --- one based upon the use of the Szare Szeregi and the other on the Tian Bai Feng .</sentence>
<sentence id="s473">The Szare Szeregi was not likely to have been used and some questions have been raised about her operational ability.</sentence>
<sentence id="s474">The Tian Bai Feng is considered by Mr Everton to fairly represent a conforming vessel of the class required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s475">I do not understand this to be disputed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s476">In particular Mrs Richards subsequently accepted that other vessels available were able to carry the quantity of cargo this vessel could.</sentence>
<sentence id="s477">The voyage income is therefore: 
 
 Freight: 71,500mt x US$29.50 --- 3.75% 2 030.153.13
 Demurrage: 10.94 days x US$45 000 --- 3.75 % 474 012.00 
 US$2 504 165.13 
 
 
 Whilst Mrs Richards and Mr Lewis earlier disputed the likelihood of demurrage being payable, this was not maintained in submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s478">


 
 93 The principal issue in the calculation of damage concerned the cost which Hyundai MM would have incurred in hiring a vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s479">The daily rates which the experts said would likely have been incurred were US$35 500 (Mr Everton); US$37 000 (Mrs Richards) and US$37 500 (Mr Lewis).</sentence>
<sentence id="s480">Hyundai MM's own calculation was based on US$32 000 per day, which Mr Hwang considers he would have achieved if negotiations in connexion with the fixture of the Szare Szeregi had concluded, although he conceded in his evidence that the outcome may be as high as US$35 000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s481">Mr Everton considered that Mr Hwang's approach was somewhat optimistic, given in particular that the fixture report of the vessel on 15 April 2004, for a trip which also had redelivery to the Philippines, was at the rate of US$35 500 per day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s482">Hyundai MM nevertheless submitted that it could have achieved a lesser price, either because of its market power or experience and success-rate in negotiations, as evidenced by the rate it achieved for the Tian Bai Feng .</sentence>
<sentence id="s483">No such inference could however fairly be drawn from the evidence, such as it was.</sentence>
<sentence id="s484">94 Mr. Everton considered that the daily hire of US$35 500 was fairly representative of rates with respect to other available vessels which met the requirements of the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s485">The reports of the fixtures do not bear that out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s486">Of the eight qualifying vessels identified as qualifying, other than the Szare Szeregi , five were available at the relevant time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s487">The average rate of hire of those vessels was US$37 500.</sentence>
<sentence id="s488">95 Although Mr Everton's evidence on the usefulness of the earlier fixture of the Tian Bai Feng as a guide varied somewhat, I understood there to be general consensus amongst the witnesses that the rate at which it was fixed was well below market levels at the time and not appropriate to be used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s489">96 None of the witnesses suggested that the daily rate could be ascertained with precision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s490">A difference of US$2000 or US$2500 is however of some significance to the claim and may imply that there is some distinction drawn by the charterers with respect to vessels or advantages with respect to redelivery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s491">97 The dry cargo market was operating at high levels and high freight rates were evident in the period when Hyundai MM would have had to fix upon a vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s492">The fixtures of vessels which conformed to the requirements of the charterparty suggest the figures for which Mrs Richards and Mr Lewis contend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s493">The rate at which the Szare Szeregi was fixed was alone in this class.</sentence>
<sentence id="s494">Possible reasons were advanced for this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s495">Mrs Richards suggested that it was because the vessel would be known to be less economical and take longer on a voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s496">Mr Everton considered that the difference in the rates was explained by the fact that the vessels fixed at between US$37 000 and US$38 500 had a redelivery at Japan and not the Philippines, as was the case with the Szare Szeregi .</sentence>
<sentence id="s497">Redelivery to the Philippines would be more attractive since it positioned a vessel better to be redeployed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s498">Mrs Richards disagreed with the approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s499">It is not possible to reach a firm conclusion as to the reason why the Szare Szeregi's rate of hire differed from others in the market at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s500">98 Since the rate of hire for the Szare Szeregi differs from the average of rates for vessels reported in the period when Hyundai MM would have fixed a vessel, the question which arises is whether Hyundai MM was likely to have been able to conclude a fixture of it, albeit at the rate of US$35 500.</sentence>
<sentence id="s501">If such a finding is not possible, the only other conclusion open is that the rate it would have to pay for other vessels of the requisite class and specifications was in the order of US$37 500.</sentence>
<sentence id="s502">I do not consider the evidence permits the finding that Hyundai was likely to have succeeded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s503">It is possible that it may have done so, but equally possible that, given the demand for vessels and the short time in which negotiations had to be concluded, Hyundai MM would have been outbid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s504">Its opening offer was considerably lower than that sought by the owners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s505">The rate reported as obtained by them was even higher.</sentence>
<sentence id="s506">There is nothing to suggest that it was more likely than not that Hyundai MM would have succeeded in obtaining the fixture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s507">The rate of US$37 500 should be applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s508">99 At the conclusion of the trial differences of opinion remained with respect to a few assumptions upon which voyage expenses, in addition to hire, should be calculated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s509">The first of these was the amount allowable for the contingency that some further anticipated costs would be incurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s510">Mr Everton had already allowed 5 per cent for contingencies on expenses, for potential delay at sea, as had Mrs Richards.</sentence>
<sentence id="s511">Mrs Richards allowed another two days for the potential for time lost in port, but conceded that it was not appropriate where the vessel was on demurrage once there had been a delay in Newcastle, which seemed likely on the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s512">Mr Lewis allowed another day for contingencies, but this was for the same reason that Mr Everton and Mrs Richards had allowed 5 per cent, namely delay in the voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s513">No basis was shown for a further increase in the figure for contingencies, particularly when an extra day's costs was said by Hyundai MM to represent something in the order of US$40 000 and the defendants did not dispute this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s514">100 Mr Everton assumed, for the purposes of his calculations of the cost of the voyage, that the delivery leg would be a distance of 4392 nautical miles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s515">Marubeni and Ssangyong relied upon Mr Lewis' opinion that it would be 4442.8 miles, the average of the length of the voyage of the five vessels referred to in connexion with rates of hire.</sentence>
<sentence id="s516">The difference is some 50 nautical miles, about 3.5 hours.</sentence>
<sentence id="s517">If those defendants were correct in this contention, the expense could increase in the order of US$5000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s518">The principal reason for the difference in the figures is that the voyage to which Mr Lewis has regard had delivery from China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s519">The Tian Bai Feng would have been delivered from Japan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s520">The evidence suggests a number of other vessels would have also been delivered from Japan, as Mr Lewis acknowledged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s521">They may have been delivered from a port closer to Newcastle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s522">No reason was shown why, in these circumstances, a vessel was more likely to have been delivered from China and why it was necessary to add to the allowance already made for contingencies with respect to the voyage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s523">101 The next point taken by these defendants relates to the cargo leg of the voyage between Newcastle and Masinloc, which Mr Everton calculated as 3972 miles and Mr Lewis calculated at 4018 miles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s524">I see no reason to doubt Mr Everton's figure, which was derived from a website used by the industry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s525">Mr Lewis merely used Hyundai MM's figure, but it was not explained why it was more reliable or included what it is.</sentence>
<sentence id="s526">102 With the adjustment to the rate of hire following my finding, the calculation with respect to this expense is: 
 47.64 days x US$37,500 --- 3.75% = US$1 719 506.25
 
 Allowing for the other voyage expenses, calculated by Mr Everton at US$288 670.40, the net profit on the voyage which Hyundai MM has lost is US$495 988.48.</sentence>
<sentence id="s527">
 JUDGMENT AGAINST DARTBROOK?</sentence>
<sentence id="s528">
 
 103 There is no doubt that Anglo Coal, Marubeni and Ssangyong are liable to Hyundai MM as the principals for which Dartbrook contracted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s529">The question arises as to whether Dartbrook is itself liable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s530">104 In the charterparty Dartbrook was shown as the charterer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s531">The document itself, concluded on 29 March 2004, contained no reference to Dartbrook's principals, the three joint-venturers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s532">The shipbrokers however had obtained information about the parties to the joint-venture and that Dartbrook sold its coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s533">It passed this information on to Hyundai MM on about 25 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s534">105 Generally speaking, where a party signs a contract without qualification as to the capacity in which they are signing, they are taken to be contracting personally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s535">This may be otherwise where disclosure of the agency is made, but it needs to be clear that the party is acting as agent in the legal sense: Treitel , Law of Contract at p 727.</sentence>
<sentence id="s536">In Universal Steam Navigation Co v James McKelvie and Co [1923] AC 492 an agent was not held personally liable where they had signed ' as agent '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s537">The question was what that meant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s538">Lord Sumner (at 501-502) considered that, in the circumstances of the case, the words could only mean: ' I am not liable but someone else is and he only '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s539">On the other hand the words ' This vessel was chartered on behalf of ...... for account of ... ' was not held to mean that the parties intended the agent not to be liable as charterer: Tudor Marine Ltd v Tradax Export S.A. (The Virgo) [1976] 2 Lloyd's Rep 135.</sentence>
<sentence id="s540">106 In the present case there was no qualification made by Dartbrook as to the capacity in which it contracted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s541">The knowledge of a third party of the existence of the principal is not sufficient to excuse an agent from liability: Stanley Yeung Kai Yung v Hong Kong and Shanghai Banking Corporation [1981] AC 787 at 795.</sentence>
<sentence id="s542">To do otherwise would permit oral evidence to contradict the written agreement: Basma v Weekes [1950] AC 441 at 451.</sentence>
<sentence id="s543">In the present case there is nothing to suggest that the parties intended that Dartbrook not be liable as charterer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s544">Even if one were to have regard to Hyundai MM's state of knowledge, it could not be assumed that it understood Dartbrook was not intended to have that liability.</sentence>
<sentence id="s545">It merely knew that it was acting for the joint venture in connexion with its sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s546">
 DARTBROOK'S INDEMNITY 
 
 107 Marubeni and Ssangyong however deny that Dartbrook is entitled to be indemnified as agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s547">The grounds for this have now reduced to one, wilful misconduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s548">Clause 12.2 of the sales representative agreement excludes an indemnity where there has been such misconduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s549">' Wilful misconduct ' is defined, for the purpose of the clause, as ' any act or omission (including a negligent act or omission) done or omitted with deliberate or reckless disregard for pursuable or harmful consequences '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s550">The allegation however depends upon the conduct of Ms Tan in agreeing to the charterparty on 29 March 2004, at a time where there was no sales contract with National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s551">Insofar as the denial of an indemnity requires knowledge, it was Ms Tan's belief that she had concluded an agreement with National Power on 26 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s552">Even if the agreement did not come into effect until National Power's confirmation of 29 March, there is no evidence that it came into effect on that day but after the charterparty was agreed upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s553">The argument for Marubeni and Ssangyong does not rely upon fine timing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s554">The evidence would not permit such a finding in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s555">Rather their case was put upon the basis that no binding agreement was ever reached with National Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s556">I have found to the contrary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s557">Dartbrook is entitled to be indemnified in accordance with cl 12.1 of the sales representative agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s558">That indemnity extends to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s559">
 CLAIMS AGAINST ANGLO COAL 
 
 108 There is no dispute between the three joint venturers that the joint venture agreement governs the extent of the indemnity and contribution each should provide to the other in the event that they are held liable to Hyundai MM. Marubeni and Ssangyong however seek an indemnity and contribution or damages from Anglo Coal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s560">It is alleged that it knew or can be taken to have known, of Dartbrook's actions because of the control it had over that company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s561">It therefore knew when Dartbrook intended to commit to a binding charterparty with no corresponding sales contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s562">It was obliged to inform the other joint venturers and a failure to do so amounted to misleading and deceptive conduct, it is alleged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s563">The findings made with respect to the contract being concluded with National Power remove any factual basis for this allegation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s564">
 JUDGMENT, INTEREST AND COSTS 
 
 109 There will be judgment for Hyundai MM against all defendants in the sum of US$495 988.48.</sentence>
<sentence id="s565">Hyundai also foreshadowed a claim for interest at the rates provided by the Rules of Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s566">It was not clear whether this was intended to refer to a pre-judgment claim for interest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s567">I will give liberty to apply within seven days for that purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s568">Hyundai should also have its costs including reserved costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s569">The question is which defendants should bear them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s570">110 Costs were reserved on 3 May 2005 by Spender J when the second set of trial dates was vacated because Dartbrook had decided to join the joint venturers to the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s571">It could have done so at an earlier point and I do not understand it to dispute that, as between it and Hyundai MM, it should pay the costs thrown away.</sentence>
<sentence id="s572">111 Dartbrook however is entitled to an indemnity for costs generally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s573">I do not see why the indemnity would not apply to the reserved costs and no defendant has suggested that they do not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s574">Marubeni and Ssangyong submit that they should be liable for costs only after their joinder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s575">That would be the usual course, but in any event Dartbrook is entitled to be indemnified with respect to the costs it incurred by being sued on the charterparty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s576">112 In relation to Hyundai MM's costs, there will be orders that Dartbrook pay Hyundai MM's costs up to and including the date of the joinder of the other defendants and the costs reserved on 3 May 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s577">All defendants will be ordered to pay Hyundai MM's costs thereafter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s578">113 On the first cross-claim there will be an order that the other three defendants indemnify Dartbrook with respect to its liability to Hyundai MM for damages and costs and an order that they pay Dartbrook's costs of defending the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s579">Marubeni and Ssangyong should pay Dartbrook's costs of the claim against them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s580">114 On the second cross-claim, there will be an order that Anglo Coal, Marubeni and Ssangyong indemnify each other and contribute to the judgment sum in the proportions of 77.5 per cent, 15.5 per cent and 7 per cent respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s581">Marubeni and Ssangyong will pay Anglo Coal's costs on the cross-claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s582">115 There will be orders dismissing the third cross-claim by Marubeni and Ssangyong against Dartbrook and Anglo Coal and that they pay Dartbrook and Anglo Coal's costs on that cross-claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s583">116 There will be liberty to apply which respect to any matter required to be dealt with by order in accordance with these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s584">
 I certify that the preceding one hundred and sixteen (116) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Kiefel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s585">Associate:

Dated: 11 OCTOBER 2006

 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr J Sexton SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Thynne and McCartney 
 
 Counsel for the First &amp; Third Defendant: Mr K Fleming QC 
 
 Solicitor for the First &amp; Third Defendant: Blake Dawson Waldron 
 
 Counsel for the Second &amp; Fourth Defendant: Mr M Speakman QC 
 
 Solicitor for the Second &amp; Fourth Defendant: Dibbs Abbot Stillman 
 
 Date of Hearing: 6, 7, 8, 9, 12 and 13 December 2005 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 October 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1324.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>