<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rhodes v Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2006] FCA 1220 (8 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1220.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">review of decision of aat which affirmed decision of australian fisheries management authority to cancel fishing permit relating to southern shark fishery in bass strait region</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">interpretation of 2003 southern and eastern scalefish and shark fishery management plan and offshore constitutional settlement to extent either imposed 'limited entry' or 'no new permits' policy</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether tribunal erred in finding as relevant to refusal to grant fishing permit enforcement of afma's cost recovery procedures</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">claim of denial of natural justice in relation to processes implemented by australian fisheries management authority up to time of cancellation of applicant's fishing permit</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">Rhodes v Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2006] FCA 1220 (8 September 2006) 

 [ Home ] [ Databases ] [ WorldLII ] [ Search ] [ Feedback ] Federal Court of Australia You are here: &nbsp; AustLII &gt;&gt; Databases &gt;&gt; Federal Court of Australia &gt;&gt; 2006 &gt;&gt; [2006] FCA 1220 

 [ Database Search ] [ Name Search ] [ Recent Decisions ] [ Noteup ] [ Download ] [ Help ] Rhodes v Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2006] FCA 1220 (8 September 2006) 
Last Updated: 11 September 2006 
 FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 

 Rhodes v Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2006] FCA 1220 
 


 ADMINISTRATIVE LAW --- review of decision of AAT which affirmed decision of Australian Fisheries Management Authority to cancel fishing permit relating to Southern Shark Fishery in Bass Strait region --- interpretation of 2003 Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Fishery Management Plan and Offshore Constitutional Settlement to extent either imposed 'limited entry' or 'no new permits' policy --- whether Tribunal erred in finding as relevant to refusal to grant fishing permit enforcement of AFMA's cost recovery procedures --- claim of denial of natural justice in relation to processes implemented by Australian Fisheries Management Authority up to time of cancellation of applicant's fishing permit 


 Fisheries Management Act 1991 (Cth) ss 17 , 32 , 38 , 39 
 Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth)


 Offshore Constitutional Settlement 
 Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Fishery Management Plan 2003 


 Re Drake and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1979) 2 ALD 634 discussed
 Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs v Gray (1994) 50 FCR 189 discussed
 Re Green and Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2004] AATA 426 ; (2004) 81 ALD 194 referred to
 Legione v Hateley [1983] HCA 11 ; (1983) 152 CLR 406 discussed
 Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1963] HCA 41 ; (1963) 113 CLR 475 discussed
 National Companies and Securities Commission v News Corporation Ltd [1984] HCA 29 ; (1984) 156 CLR 296 referred to
 R v Small Claims Tribunal and Homewood; Ex parte Cameron [1976] VR 427 referred to
 Cameron v Cole [1944] HCA 5 ; (1943) 68 CLR 571 referred to
 Hoskins v Van Den-Braak (1998) 43 NSWLR 290 referred to
 Clements v Independent Indigenous Advisory Committee [2003] FCAFC 143 ; (2003) 131 FCR 28 referred to
 Gribbles Pathology (Vic) Pty Ltd v Cassidy [2002] FCA 859 ; (2002) 122 FCR 78 discussed




 DAVID JOHN RHODES v AUSTRALIAN FISHERIES MANAGEMENT AUTHORITY 
TAD 31 OF 2005

 CONTI J 
 8 SEPTEMBER 2006 
 SYDNEY 
 IN THE FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 
 NEW SOUTH WALES DISTRICT REGISTRY TAD 31 OF 2005 

 ON APPEAL FROM THE ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL CONSTITUTED BY ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR DAVIS 

 BETWEEN: DAVID JOHN RHODES 
 Applicant AND: AUSTRALIAN FISHERIES MANAGEMENT AUTHORITY 
 Respondent 

 JUDGE: CONTI J DATE OF ORDER: 8 SEPTEMBER 2006 WHERE MADE: SYDNEY 

 THE COURT ORDERS THAT: 

 The application for review by way of appeal from the decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal made on 27 July 2005 be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The applicant pay the respondent's costs of the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">










Note: Settlement and entry of orders is dealt with in Order 36 of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">IN THE FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 
 NEW SOUTH WALES DISTRICT REGISTRY TAD 31 OF 2005 
 
 ON APPEAL FROM THE ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL CONSTITUTED BY ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR DAVIS 

 BETWEEN: DAVID JOHN RHODES Applicant AND: AUSTRALIAN FISHERIES MANAGEMENT AUTHORITY Respondent JUDGE: CONTI J DATE: 8 SEPTEMBER 2006 PLACE: SYDNEY 

 TABLE OF CONTENTS 
 

 The context of the present proceedings for appeal by way of administrative review of a decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal, and of the prior decision-making of the respondent Australian Fisheries Management Authority leading to that review This is an appeal in the nature of administrative review of the reasons for decision of Associate Professor B W Davis AM, a part-time member of the General Administrative Division of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ('the AAT'), given on 27 July 2005 in Hobart.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">That decision of the AAT reviewed an earlier decision made by a delegate of the Australian Fisheries Management Authority ('AFMA'), an authority recently formed to administer fisheries management on behalf of the Commonwealth under the Offshore Constitutional Settlement of 2000 ('OCS'), being a decision made on 11 July 2001 to cancel fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">26978 relating to the Southern Shark Fishery ('SSF'), which permit had been issued by AFMA to the applicant Mr Rhodes on 1 March 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Mr Rhodes testified as to being a fisherman for some 35 years prior to the establishment of the OCS, having held a Tasmanian state shark gillnet license ever since such State license system was established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Mr Rhodes' fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">26978 had somewhat incongruously allowed Mr Rhodes a quota of zero or nil kilograms of gummy and school shark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Subsequent to that essentially adverse decision of AFMA of 11 July 2001, made adversely to him, Mr Rhodes applied on 29 September 2003 to AFMA for a new permit in relation to the SSF, which application was however rejected on 12 November 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Mr Rhodes thereupon requested a review specifically of the latter rejection decision, but that review was dismissed by AFMA on 29 January 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">It is appropriate that I record in temporal sequence the steps taken by the parties to present to the AAT the issues purportedly arising for resolution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">I say 'purportedly' because Mr Rhodes' outline of submissions in chief, AFMA's submissions in response and Mr Rhodes' submissions purportedly in reply present a somewhat confused picture of the issues to be addressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The AAT proceedings were commenced against AFMA by a handwritten application for review presented by Mr Rhodes to the AAT on 23 February 2004, and were made referrable solely to that most recent above decision of AFMA of 29 January 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The threadbare basis of the application was stated in Mr Rhodes' handwriting as follows: 
 
 believe I am entitled to a permit for various reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">I was under financial difficulties at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">' 
 
 Ultimately Mr Rhodes proposed five issues for resolution by the AAT and subsequently AFMA proposed three differently framed issues for resolution by the AAT, with the consequence of a somewhat uncertain extent of joinder of issues.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Accordingly the issues arising for ultimate resolution by the AAT fell for resolution largely in accordance with what the parties individually presented as their respective perceptions of the issues arising.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Counsel for Mr Rhodes contended in written submissions to the Federal Court, by way of threshold summary, that the AAT erred principally by: (i) incorrectly construing the Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Fishery Management Plan 2003 ('the SESS Management Plan') and the OCS as imposing a 'no new permits' policy upon AFMA; (ii) incorrectly finding as relevant to the refusal to the grant of a permit generally the enforcement of AFMA's cost recovery procedures; (iii) incorrectly finding that in the course of cancelling permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">26978 AFMA had afforded Mr Rhodes natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">
AFMA attacked the formulation of each of those three contentions as not raising questions of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">AFMA disputed that any such policy as in (i) above was implemented in any event, and further that (ii) would have to be reformulated to read, 'whether the AFMA's cost recovery procedures were a relevant consideration to the decision whether to grant the [applicant] a new fishing permit', in order to be capable of raising a question of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Further, it was contended by AFMA that (iii) above disclosed a failure on the applicant's part to appreciate the nature of the Tribunal's task.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Subsequently to the filing of the initiating process on 23 February 2004, AFMA provided to the AAT on 13 July 2004 a statement of the issues arising before the AAT framed in chronological sequence of the material events which had occurred between 1 March 2001, when Mr Rhodes was granted a Southern Shark Fishery ('SSF') permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">26978, and 29 January 2004 when AFMA determined that Mr Rhodes' Gillnet Hook and Trap Fishery ('GHATF') permit application would not be granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">In the meantime AFMA had cancelled Mr Rhodes' SSF Permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">26978 on 11 July 2001 as above stated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">On 6 April 2004, AFMA had caused to be filed in the AAT a so-called Section 37 Statement, purportedly pursuant to s 37 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth), which referred to 'Relevant Decision of 12 November 2003' of AFMA and the 'Reviewable Decision of 29 January 2004', and which particularised the background to both decisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The submissions of the parties on the present appeal focused largely on the documents which I have recorded and reviewed in these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">I should add for completeness that on 13 August 2004, Mr Rhodes filed in the AAT proceedings below a document headed 'Statement of Fact (sic) and Contentions' which: (i) denied the receipt of correspondence addressed by AFMA to him during April and May 2001 (though not correspondence of 1 March and 21 March 2001); and (ii) asserted failure on AFMA's part 'to comply with its statutory obligation to undertake a s 65 review of the applicants quota allocation by 6 June 2001' (see par 6 of the Statement of Fact).</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">In contrast somewhat to that Statement of Fact and Contentions of 13 August 2004, there was filed on behalf of Mr Rhodes on 24 August 2005 a notice of appeal to the Federal Court which purportedly raised 15 'questions of law', the fifteenth dividing into three segments, and additionally particularised 17 'grounds relied upon'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">That notice of appeal was expressed in generalised or unspecific terms, and the orders sought thereby did not substantially reflect relief of the scope which might normally be available in proceedings for administrative review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Once again, AFMA characterised that pleaded material of Mr Rhodes as seeking no more than merits review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">In the result, the Federal Court was not presented with mutually agreed issues arising on the present appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Moreover I would observe that much of what I have recorded above, as presented by Mr Rhodes, was somewhat confusing as well as unspecific.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">In any event, it was the AFMA decision of 12 July 2001 to cancel Mr Rhodes' SSF permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">26978 that became largely the focus of initial controversy, and it is AFMA's ultimate refusal of 29 January 2004 to reinstate the cancelled SSF permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">26978, and to refuse a new permit to Mr Rhodes which the principal submissions of the parties to the appeal seemingly addressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Circumstances leading to the cancellation of Mr Rhodes' Southern Shark Fishery (SSF) permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">26978 effective from 11 July 2001 Mr Rhodes was described in evidence placed before the Tribunal as a professional fisherman of some 35 years experience, whose fishing operations had been conducted primarily in waters of the Bass Strait region surrounding Flinders Island and other adjacent islands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">His recognition in the Tasmanian fishing industry was said to be exemplified by his service on working groups relating to the Tasmanian rock lobster fishery, the Tasmanian scallop industry advisory committee and the Southern Shark Industry Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Mr Rhodes had apparently held a Tasmanian State shark gillnet license since the time the original Tasmanian State licensing arrangements were put in place, being arrangements which required the payment of licensing fees on an annual basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The Tribunal recorded that shark fishing had been taking place for many years in the waters off the coasts of the States of Victoria, Tasmania and South Australia, and that the species harvested were largely gummy shark and school shark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The Tribunal further recorded that '... there have been concerns over many years about depletion of biomass due to catch rates, slow growth rates of the species, and the fact that they produce few young at a time' , and that it was a consequence of those concerns that the management of the SSF was ceded by those States to the Commonwealth in the year 2000 as part of the OCS arrangements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Prior to that time, and since the 1980's, the SSF had been the subject of a number of management initiatives, which included industry consultation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Following industry consultations in the 1990's, namely the 1997 Southern Shark Fishing Management Advisory Committee and the 1999 Southern Shark Allocation Advisory Panel, an agreement was reached that quota allocations should be assessed on the basis of each fisherman's best three years of verified catch in respect of the period of four years from 1994 and 1997 inclusive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The Panel published its final report on 15 July 1999, in which the need to identify any 'exceptional circumstances' was acknowledged for the purpose of assessment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Those circumstances were apparently never defined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Also identified by that Advisory Panel was the need to take into account factors which might create inequalities amongst particular fishing entitlements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">By Memorandum of Understanding bearing date 17 November 2000 signed on behalf of the Commonwealth of Australia, AFMA and the States of South Australia, Tasmania and Victoria, arrangements were entered into 'with respect to The School and Gummy Shark Fishery in Waters Relevant to [those States]'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Amongst the objectives of that Memorandum of Understanding appearing within clause 12 thereof was the following: 
 
 ensuring individual fishers in a fishery, who come under the Commonwealth's jurisdiction as a result of OCS Arrangements, are treated on a fair and equitable basis with all other fishers in the school shark and gummy shark fishery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">' 
 

By clause 14, it was declared that '[a]ll licensed fishers... may apply for a Commonwealth shark fishing concession under this Memorandum' , and further that 'AFMA will give the above listed fishers 60 days, from notification, to apply for a Commonwealth shark fishing concession' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">By clause 15, it was stipulated that '... school shark and gummy shark will be managed by determining the total allowable catch (TAC) of each species, allocating the Commonwealth component of the TAC to individual Commonwealth fishing concession holders as individual quota...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">By clause 16, it was further stipulated that '[t]he initial allocation mechanism to apportion the TAC of school shark and gummy shark amongst the... sectors within the [SSF]...' was to be as thereafter particularised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">By clauses 36 to 39, it was stipulated inter alia that AFMA would 'restrict Commonwealth shark fishing concessions to their area of access as stated on their previous State and/or Commonwealth fishing concessions' , reference being made to the purpose of the management restrictions of those provisions to address 'the concerns of AFMA, [nominated Tasmanian State Departments] and Tasmanian fishers and Commonwealth fishers that there be no increase in demersal fishing capacity within coastal waters, due to the potential impact [that] an increase could have on the stocks of State managed scale fish species and potential impacts on the school shark entering nursery areas' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Mr Rhodes applied on 19 December 2000 to AFMA for a Commonwealth fishing permit for the catching of school and gummy shark by completing a four page pro forma document headed 'Application for Fishing Permit' , which stated his postal address as 'c/- Lady Barron P.O.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Flinders Island Tas 7225', and his location as '1331 Coast Rd Lady Barron Tas 7255'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Incidentally but insignificantly, AFMA misspelt 'Barron' in a number of its subsequent communications and documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Disclosed by Mr Rhodes on that application form was his telephone, mobile and fax numbers respectively, his fishing vessel details inclusive of reference to its name 'Silver Spray' , its length of 49 feet, its breadth of 16 feet and its weight of 32 tonnage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The method of dispatch of that application form to AFMA adopted by Mr Rhodes was by way of facsimile transmission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The application fee prescribed on that AFMA form of application was $170.00, and the address for return of the completed form to AFMA was specified as its post office box number or its fax number in Canberra.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Mr Rhodes tendered payment of only the sum of $80.00 in the context of dispatch of his application to AFMA, and informed AFMA that he would pay the balance of $90.00 at a later time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Whether payment of that balance was ever made does not seemingly appear from the documentary material in evidence, but as matters transpired, any such shortfall in payment would not seem to have been material in any event to the subsequent decision-making of AFMA complained of by Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">On 1 March 2001 AFMA sent a pro forma notification in response to Mr Rhodes' application, which attached what was identified as a ' Fishing Permit' numbered 26978 for 'Commercial Fishing' in relation to the 'Southern Shark Fishery' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The form of notification was in a standard printed form and included 'PERMIT ATTACHMENT B', which contained the following : 
 
 attachment shows the trunked weight of school shark and gummy shark allowed to be taken under the authorisation of your fishing permit, subject to the conditions on that permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">
 
 amounts relate to your entitlement of quota species, resulting from initial allocation or from the transfer of quota, or to trip limits which have been imposed on certain species.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">
 
 attachment should be retained at all times with your fishing permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">
 
 new attachment will be issued after any transactions involving transfer of quota are completed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">
 
 you have any questions please contact me on: 
 
 (unstated but already appearing at top of letter) 
 
 02 6272 5426.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Registrar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">' 
 

However that fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">26978, to which of course I have already referred, recorded Mr Rhodes' quota of kilograms for each of gummy shark and school shark as zero.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">That attached document constituting fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">26978 bearing date 1 March 2001, and addressed of course to Mr Rhodes, contained the following: 
 
 Fishing Permit authorises the use of the boat specified in Schedule 3 by the Fishing Permit holder, or a person acting on behalf of the permit holder, for the activity specified in Schedule 1 and subject to the conditions specified in Schedule 4 of this Fishing Permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">' 
 


Schedule 1 referred to a 'Start Date' of 1 March 2001 and an 'Expiry Date' of 31 December 2001, and the nominated licensed 'Activity' specified in Schedule 1 was that of 'Commercial Fishing Southern Shark Fishery 3 Gillnets' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Reference was made in Schedule 3 to the description of Mr Rhodes' vessel named 'Silver Spray' as having the township of Lady Barron as its 'Home Port' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Next appeared in the permit was a 'Declaration' in the following printed terms:
 
 
 
 
 to Sub-section 32(1) of the Fisheries Management Act 1991 I, as an Authorised officer of the Australian Fisheries Management Authority, hereby: 
 
 grant a Fishing Permit to the holder described above authorising the use of the boat described in Schedule 3 for the activity described in Schedule 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">
 
 
 
 state that the Fishing Permit shall have effect for the period specified in Schedule 1 and shall be subject to the conditions specified in Schedule 4 and any variations to the conditions as notified in writing to the Fishing Permit holder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">' 
 
 
 
 The 'Area of Waters' nominated in Schedule 2 to the permit for Mr Rhodes was as set out below, once more in printed form: 
 
 In coastal waters relevant to the State of Tasmania.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">
 
 (B) In the area of waters bounded by the line, commencing at the point of Latitude 40 o South, Longitude 140 o 57.9' East; running thence south along the meridian of Longitude 140 o 57.9' East to its intersection with the outer limit of the Australian Fishing Zone; thence generally southerly, easterly and northerly along that outer limit to its intersection with the parallel of Latitude 39 o 12' South; thence west along the parallel to its intersection with the meridian of Longitude 143 o 40' East; thence south along that meridian to its intersection with the parallel of Latitude 40 o South; and thence west along that parallel to the point of commencement, excluding area (A) above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">' 
 
 
 

Reference again appeared to '... school and gummy shark' as the subject of the permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Schedule 4 to this purported fishing permit granted to Mr Rhodes set out conditions as to minimum specifications of fish weight allowable for retention (and thus for sale) by him as permit holder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Conditions 1, 2 and 3 of Schedule 4 included the following (there were altogether 27 conditions contained in Schedule 4): 
 
 --- CONDITIONS 
 
 This Fishing Permit allows fishing by the methods, and subject to the restrictions specified in Attachment A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">
 
 
 
 This Fishing Permit allows the taking or carrying of gummy shark (Mustelus antarcticus) and school shark (Galeorhinus galeus).</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">Any school and gummy shark taken under the authority of this Fishing Permit must exceed 45 centimetres when measured in a straight line from the middle of the posterior edge of the aftermost gill-slit to the ventral insertion of the caudal fin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">
 
 
 
 This Fishing Permit only allows fishing for a quota species if: 
 
 
 
 (a) the weight specified in the Quota column 1 (seasonal quota holdings) of the species limit table in Attachment B in relation to that quota species is greater than zero; and 
 
 (b) the total trunked weight of fish taken is less than the weight specified in the Quota column of the species limit table in Attachment B in relation to that quota species.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">....' 
 

Attachment A specified permissible fishing gear, inclusive of nets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Attachment B related to 'Species Limits' , which referred to the two nominated species of gummy shark and school shark, but however with zero kilograms designated to each by way of 'quota' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The reason for zero being recorded for each of those nominated shark species would appear to have been at least not solely for the reason that Mr Rhodes had made no payment, punctually or at all, of the Southern Shark Fishery levy of $400.00 (being an exaction separate from the earlier application fee of $170.00) the subject of an AFMA invoice or statement bearing date 5 March 2001 attached to the standard printed form of notification of 1 March 2001 ( ante ) addressed to him care of 'Lady Baron Post Office Flinders Island Tas 7255'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I have said 'at least not solely' because according to [41] of the Tribunal's Reasons for Decision, '[i]t was because he had no verified catch data for the period 1994-1997 that he was granted zero quota' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">Nevertheless the subsequent correspondence emanating from AFMA, to which I will shortly refer, indicates that non-payment of the $400.00 levy appears to have been a reason for cancellation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The accompanying 'remittance advice' contained the statement '[i]f you have any queries regarding this levy notice or you wish to enter into an arrangement to pay the levy, please call Mrs Leslie May...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">There was no suggestion in the evidence that any such payment arrangement was sought, much less made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Mr Rhodes responded to those zero quota allocations by lodging on 20 March 2001 in handwritten letter form a so-called 'appeal for a Quota allocation for The Southern Shark Fishery' upon the basis of 'exceptional circumstances', which he thereafter sought to particularise in the terms set out below: 
 
 '... 
 
 the qualifying period I was principally involved in rock oyster and scallop fishing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Because we had no factory or ice making facilities on the Island I was severely limited to shark fishing operations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The availability of airfreight when needed also was detrimental.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">I made efforts to move and sell shark but after several attempts gave up and used my catches for rock lobster bait.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Most of my catches were recorded in my log-books at the time and were submitted to the Tasmanian Fisheries.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">
 
 have had extensive involvement in the shark fishery and was principally involved in this fishery when we had an operational factory on the island.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">In fact my first vessel was the Doris Cruise which was purchased from Brian Bailey complete with gear when the NZ mercury issue was on about 30 years ago.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">I was heavily involved in shark fishing with the "Frances Drake" when P.K.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">Oysters operated a factory here.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">Since then I have had the "Curlew", "Veronica May" and "Silver Spray" and have had shark fishing gear aboard these vessels until recently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">I own two hydraulic spools and have recently bought a 20 ton freezer so that I could operate commercially again because of our isolation and the problems with freight and ice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">
 
 is a list of my catches during the qualifying period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">This can be verified by the Statistics Section, Marine Resources Division Department Primary Industries Water and Environment TAS.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">
 
 trust you will treat my appeal in a fair and equitable manner...'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">
 


Details of 'catches of school and gummy shark' made by Mr Rhodes in relation to the period of time from February 1994 to December 1997 were thus attached to his notice of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">Payment of the levy of $400.00 had still not been made by Mr Rhodes to AFMA, which appears to have remained the case, so far as the evidence stands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">
 
 
 
 AFMA promptly acknowledged, by letter to Mr Rhodes of 21 March 2001, the foregoing request for reconsideration of the non-allocation of any shark quota as notified to him in AFMA's letter of 21 March 2001, and stated that the delegate therein named would '... now undertake a reconsideration of this matter... under [section] 165 of the Fisheries Management Act 1991 '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Section 165 of the Management Act is headed 'Reconsideration by AFMA and right to review by Administrative Appeals Tribunal'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">In the meantime systematic reminders for payment of the management levy of $400.00 were sent by AFMA to Mr Rhodes (Levy Reminder Notices of 21 March 2001 and 9 April 2001 are in evidence), with no response however, as I have foreshadowed, by way of payment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">On 9 May 2001, AFMA wrote to Mr Rhodes and thereby suspended his SSF fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">26978 for the reasons therein set out, being reasons framed as follows (the emphasised words below reflect the format of the original text): 
 
 records indicate that $400.00 SSF Fishery management levy relating to fishing permit no 26978 remains unpaid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">I must inform you that in accordance with AFMA's policy on these matters, this fishing permit is SUSPENDED from the date of this letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">You are NOT permitted to operate in this fishery for the period that the suspension remains in force.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The relevant AFMA fisheries management and compliance sections have been notified of this situation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">
 
 action is consistent with advice provided to you on the levy overdue notice you were sent 9-Apr-01.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">You were advised that you had failed to make your first payment before or on its due date, and had forfeited the right to pay this levy by instalments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">The full levy amount outstanding is now overdue and incurring a penalty charge of 20% per annum, accumulating daily for each day the levy remains unpaid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">You were also informed that failure to pay this levy within 14 days of the due date (23-Apr-01) would result in your fishing permit being suspended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">
 
 suspension of your fishing permit will remain in force until the outstanding levy is paid or you have entered an arrangement to pay, or your fishing permit is cancelled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Upon payment of the remaining management levy or entering into an arrangement, the suspension will be revoked and your fishing permit reinstated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">You will then be sent an invoice for the 20% per annum penalty that is payable on overdue level payments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">
 
 have 7 days from the date of this letter to either pay the outstanding levy of $400.00, or enter into an arrangements to pay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">If you do not do so by 17-Apr-01, your fishing permit will be CANCELLED and the debt will be passed to the Attorney Generals Department for legal action to commence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Further, this non-payment means you will no longer be eligible to conduct any future fishing activity on the basis of having held this permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">
 
 you are not satisfied with this decision you may within 21 days from the date of this letter request AFMA to reconsider this decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">The 21 day period may be extended if you apply in writing to the Managing Director, Australian Fisheries Management Authority, PO Box 7051, Canberra Mail Centre, ACT 2610, prior to the expiry of the 21 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">If you are not satisfied with the outcome of that reconsideration you may, subject to the provisions of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 apply to the Commonwealth Administrative Appeals Tribunal through the registry in your State for a review of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">
 
 you wish to discuss this matter further, please call the Senior Licensing Officer, Leslie May...</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">' 
 


It will be seen that although the license suspension was expressed to take effect immediately, cancellation of the license was said to follow in the event of non-payment of the levy of $400.00, or absence of 'an arrangement' in that regard, within seven days, which would be by 16 May 2001; however the letter required payment by 17 April 2001, doubtless because of some unexplained delay in dispatching the letter forthwith upon composition thereof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">No such payment of $400.00 appears to have ever been made by Mr Rhodes, as I have already foreshadowed, nor was there any response by Mr Rhodes to that AFMA letter, so far as the evidence extends.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">In any event, any such shortcomings in the composition of the AFMA letter were effectively superseded by the AFMA communications which followed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">The communications from AFMA to Mr Rhodes which thereafter followed are summarised below: (i) Letter of 25 May 2001 from AFMA to Mr Rhodes, which once more foreshadowed automatic cancellation of his permit for non-payment of the $400.00 levy, in the absence of payment thereof this time by 5 June 2001 or his 'mak [ing] contact with' the senior licensing officer/writer of the letter; (ii) Letter of 12 July 2001 from AFMA addressed to Mr Rhodes, which stated that '[y]ou have been given ample time to pay this levy and AFMA has been more than reasonable in providing you with opportunities to meet your obligations' , and further that '... your fishing permit, no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">26978 is cancelled, effective today (11 July 2001)...' , and ' [y]ou are now no longer eligible to conduct any fishing activity in the Southern Shark Fishery...' ; and (iii) Letter of 2 August 2001 from AFMA to Mr Rhodes, which confirmed cancellation of his permit, and which purportedly '... terminated the reconsideration of [your] shark quota allocation' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">
There is no evidence of any response by Mr Rhodes to those letters, other than what is recorded below.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">On 26 February 2002, Mr Rhodes wrote to AFMA and sought to explain his absence of response at least to its letters of 9 and 25 May 2001, due to the 'legal and financial difficulties' of his matrimonial disputes, asserting that 'I did reply to either that letter [of 25 May 2001] or that letter... of the 9 th May 2001 within a short period stating that I was having legal and financial difficulties because of my ex-wife...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">He asserted that he 'intended to pay the levy when I could afford to' , and that he was entitled to the allocation of 'the quota' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">He explained that 'at the time I had employment picking gumnuts for seed on a remote island and was virtually uncontactable until Sept...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">He further asserted that he never intended to surrender his State (Tasmanian) license, because he wanted to retain the right 'to fish for shark in the future as I had for most of my life' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">He requested the grant of the permit he had previously applied for, being a permit which he said he assumed was being held in suspension until the levy was paid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">There was no basis in the AFMA letters to support that claimed assumption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">No payment of the $400.00 levy was subsequently tendered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">There was no immediate response from AFMA to that letter of Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">Moreover there remained a further apparent hurdle of Mr Rhodes to overcome, being the absence of what the Tribunal found below to have been the non-provision by him of any 'verified catch data from the period 1994-1997' , and hence the allocation notified to him on 1 March 2001 of a 'zero quota' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">It is appropriate to record, at this stage of my narrative of events, that the Tribunal found 'considerable difficulty in accepting the applicant's version of events' , and further that '[t]he Bass Strait Islands are not large relative to mainland Tasmania and the Tribunal knows from personal experience it is possible to penetrate most areas of Flinders, Clarke and Cape Barren Islands within 24-48 hours, thus "remoteness" is limited' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">The Tribunal further found that Mr Rhodes 'made little or no attempt to monitor mail during visits to Cape Barron township' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">The Tribunal further recorded that Mr Rhodes testified that '... he assumed non-payment of fees would be treated merely as a temporary expedient, with him meeting his obligation when he could' , but further found that '[t]he implications of non-contact and non-compliance with provisions of the legislature should have been obvious to him, especially when regularly advised to contact AFMA if he had queries or problems' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Those adverse findings of the Tribunal were in my opinion open to be made from the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Promulgation of Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Fishing Management Plan ('the SESS Management Plan') --- Mr Rhodes' subsequent application for participation by way of grant or reinstatement of fishing permit under the auspices of the Plan --- decision or reconsideration decision of AFMA On 5 September 2003 the SESS Management Plan was promulgated under s 17 of the Fisheries Management Act 1991 ('the Management Act') which empowered AFMA to establish 'plans of management for all fisheries' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Hence that promulgation occurred more than two years after the cancellation of Mr Rhodes' fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">26978.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">Section 5 of the SESS Management Plan set out its 'objectives' , which include by par (a) 'to implement efficient and cost-effective fisheries management of the fishery on behalf of the Commonwealth' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">Section 6 was headed 'Measures by which the objectives are to be attained', paras (c) to (f) thereof reading as follows: 
 
 implementing a scheme of entitlements for people to fish in the fishery consisting of boat SFRs and fishing permits; 
 
 determining reference points for maintaining ecologically sustainable stocks of each species taken in the fishery; 
 
 determining harvest strategies for quota species that will maintain their numbers above reference points, and setting TACs consistent with these harvest strategies, taking account of information from relevant management advisory committees and fishery assessment groups; 
 
 setting TACs, and determining harvest strategies and reference points, for non-quota species;' 
 

The statutory abbreviation SFR refers to 'statutory fishing right', and a 'boat SFR ' is defined by the SESS Management Plan to mean '... a statutory fishing right that allows the holder of the right to use a nominated boat to fish in an area using the method specified in the certificate of grant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">' The meaning of TAC has earlier been indicated (ie total allowable catch).</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">Section 7 of the SESS Management Plan, headed 'Performance criteria against which measures taken may be assessed (Act s 17(5)) ', stipulated by subpar (j) of sub-clause (1) thereof as follows:
 
 
 The performance criteria against which the measures taken may be assessed are as follows: ... 
 
 that access to the fishery is limited through regulating the number of fishing concessions; ....' 
 
 Section 61 of the SESS Management Plan headed 'Transitional --- general' contained transitional provisions as to engagement 'in fishing in the fishery' in favour of permit holders, until the later publication of a gazettal in effect to the contrary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">Section 62 of the SESS Management Plan, headed 'Transitional --- quota species' , provided as follows: 
 
 The notice published under section 61 may provide that this section has effect, for a quota species, from the day on which section 61 ceases to have effect until the day specified in a notice published in the Gazette under subsection (2) for that species.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">
 
 For each quota species for which this section has effect, AFMA must publish a notice in the Gazette stating that this section ceases to have effect on a day specified in the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">
 
 The day specified in a notice under subsection (2) must not be earlier than the day on which the notice is published.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">
 
 Despite section 20, a person may engage in fishing for a quota species for which this section has effect in a part of the area of the fishery if the person holds a boat statutory fishing right or fishing permit that authorises the person: 
 
 (a) to fish in that part of the area of the fishery; and 
 
 (b) to take an amount of fish of that species.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">' 
 


Section 20 of the SESS Management Plan stipulated as to the entitlement to 'fish in the fishery for a non-quota species' , being an entitlement which required by subsection (1) the holding of 'a fishing permit or boat statutory fishing right granted in relation to the fishery...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">Of course Mr Rhodes had ceased to hold as from 11 July 2001 his former statutory fishing right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">It appears that on or about 29 September 2003, Mr Rhodes filled out and sent to AFMA a standard form of application for fishing permit under the Management Act, whereby he sought permission to fish in relation to a 'Proposed Area of Operation' , for 'flathead' , 'pike' and 'gummy shark' , though no reference was made to school shark, for what that may matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">Details of his boat 'Antagonist' , his proposed fishing gear, proposed type and area of operation and his Tasmanian State license details were provided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">The application was entered on the AFMA licensing register on 2 October 2003 and bore a handwritten note of 14 October 2003 that 'David [Rhodes] will fax a letter with reasons why this permit should be renewed' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">On or about 14 October 2003, Mr Rhodes had a telephone conversation with an AFMA officer identified as 'Megan', in which he apparently sought to explain his delay in making application for what he described as his Commonwealth 'entitlement'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">Mr Rhodes also wrote at about that time an undated letter to AFMA, stamped as received on 15 October 2003, 'concerning my application to activate my shark permit which [AFMA] said had been cancelled' , and narrated the hardships, financial and otherwise, to which he claimed to have been subjected, and asserted in conclusion that 'I can now afford to pay the necessary fees' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">A yet further communication was sent by Mr Rhodes to AFMA, which was marked as received by AFMA on 20 October 2003, and outlined the exigencies of what he claimed to have been his 'severe financial hardship' , including the fact that ' [t] he sale of my house was unavoidable because the bank had taken all steps to foreclose and the matter had been to court...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">AFMA replied at length to Mr Rhodes by its letter of 12 November 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">That letter of AFMA referred to 'your application for a fishing permit in the Gillnet Hook and Trap (GHAT) Fishery and the request to reinstate your previous Commonwealth entitlement 26978' , and asserted that '... your application for a new permit [would be treated as] separate from your request to reinstate your previous entitlement' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">AFMA set out its decision and reasons therefore in summary as follows: 
 
 have reviewed the [Management Act], [the OCS] arrangements between the Commonwealth and the State of Tasmania for both scale fish, school and gummy shark species, the [Management Plan] and the current management arrangements for the GHAT Fishery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">I have also considered AFMA's limited entry policy which prohibits the issue of new permits in formally managed fisheries.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">The GHAT Fishery is a formally managed fishery, therefore, on the basis of this limited entry policy your application has been refused'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">
 

Thereafter AFMA spoke of its reasons for decision, inclusive of the need to limit the number of operators in 'efficient and responsible fisheries' '... as a necessary first step in any management of fishery resources' , and to do so '[e]ven where there has not been concern that overfishing may be occurring' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">AFMA also observed that '[i]n the absence of control, open access systems will invariably lead to over-exploited resources and declining returns for all participants' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">The letter indicated an unwillingness to reinstate Mr Rhodes' so-called 'previous fishing entitlement 26978', [and referred in that regard to] 'the length of time that has passed since the cancellation' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">The letter concluded that '[i]f you are still not satisfied after AFMA has reviewed this decision, you may then ask the [AAT] to review the decision' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">Mr Rhodes faxed to AFMA on 12 December 2003 a handwritten request bearing date 9 December 2003 as to 'reinstatement...' of 'my previous Commonwealth entitlement 26978 in the GHAT'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">Mr Rhodes explained that he had not previously made 'full payment' because he had been under severe financial pressure, largely by reason of his marriage breakdown, and of a consequential property settlement in favour of his wife and a threatened bank foreclosure, and further of his subjection to high costs of repair to his fishing vessel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">He asserted that '[r]e-instatement of entitlement 26978' would '[n]ot increase the total catch of the Shark fishery because it is now Quota managed' , and would '[h]elp reduce the overall catch because all shark caught will [cease] to be covered by quota...' , and would also '[r]educe waste, dumping and degrading associated with the urge to tax the value of fish under the bycatch provision' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">He thus made the claim, seemingly by implication, that any such reinstatement in his favour would be covered by the existing GHAT quota.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">He pressed for reconsideration as to his entitlement to 'my Commonwealth permit' , in particular because (to cite the text of his testimonial evidence in that regard): 'I qualified for my original State 3 net entitlement; I did not elect to hand my State entitlement in for financial reward; I applied for transition from the State to Commonwealth fishery; My gear allocation and catch history would have been taken into account for future management of the fishery; I paid the original application fee and advised that I was not in a [position] to pay the management levy but would do so as soon as possible; I believed my permit was being held in abeyance until the levy was paid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">' As to the last of the above factors, I have already referred to what seems to have been my uncertainty as to whether the original permit application fee of $170.00 was ever paid in full; no documentary or other material as to payment in full was tendered by Mr Rhodes in support of the assertion above as to payment of 'the original application fee' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">As to non-payment of the SSF Fishery management levy, Mr Rhodes claimed that he never received from AFMA during April, May or June 2001 correspondence to the effect of any warning of suspension or cancellation of his fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">26978 if he did not pay the levy, but so much is at odds with the text of the AFMA correspondence I have earlier identified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">During that period of time, it was Mr Rhodes' assertion incidentally that he was not living within any locality for effective communication, having been then engaged (as I have already recorded as to his claim in that regard) in a remote area of the Flinders Island in picking gumnuts for seed, and also on another island.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Extracted below is Mr Rhodes' concluding explanation made in that letter of 9 December 2003, in relation to that acknowledged delay in payment which preceded his formal request to 'consider my circumstances and situation carefully and consider my application' : 
 
 did contact AFMA when I thought I would be in a financial situation to pay my fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">I had several phone calls with Leslie May explaining my situation and circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">As my financial situation did not improve until recently I was not in a position to pursue the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">From explanations given during these calls I believed the permit would be re-issued when all necessary fees were paid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">
 
 did not think that I was in danger of losing my entitlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">I assumed the Commonwealth had a similar process to Tasmania where licences could be held in abeyance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">Had I known that I would lose the entitlement I would have made every effort or arrangement to secure it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">Why would I let a permit with a value be lost when I could have accepted money as reimbursement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">I am returning to fishing and will be taking shark as part of my catch.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">I just hope reason prevails and that my access to the shark fishery is reinstated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">' 
 


 
The theme of the letter as to his subjective beliefs is at least not wholly consistent with the material events which I have earlier recorded from the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">By a comprehensive letter dated 22 December 2003 to Mr Rhodes, AFMA recorded '... your facsimile [was] received 15 December 2003 requesting a consideration of AFMA's decision to refuse to reinstate your Gillnet, Hook and Trap Fishery permit number 26978' , and thereafter stated that 'AFMA will now undertake a reconsideration of this matter, as provided for under subsection 165 of the [Management] Act, with (sic) the 45 day review period commencing on 15 December 2003, being the date the submission was received' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">The letter further stated inter alia that '[t]he delegate may require further information on your circumstances in relation to the review than what you have already provided...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">However there is no evidence of any such information being so sought subsequently by or on behalf of AFMA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">Incidentally, subsections 165(5) and (6) of the Management Act, relating to AFMA's obligations to reconsider its decisions, read as follows: 
 
 AFMA must, within 45 days after receiving the request, reconsider the relevant decision and may make a decision: 
 
 (a) in substitution for the relevant decision whether in the same terms as the relevant decision or not; or 
 
 (b) revoking the relevant decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">
 
 Where, as a result of a reconsideration under subsection (5), AFMA makes a decision in substitution for or revoking the relevant decision, AFMA must, by written notice given to the person who made the request under subsection (2) for the reconsideration: 
 
 (a) inform the person of the result of the reconsideration; and 
 
 (b) give the reasons for the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">' 
 
 A six page internal file minute dated 9 January 2004 of the Acting Senior Licensing Officer to the Ministerial delegate (Mr Lippapis), headed 'Section 165 reconsideration of AFMA's decision to refuse reinstatement of permit no 26978' , set out the background to the controversy which arose in relation to Mr Rhodes; there was reference in that regard to the authority of s 32(1) of the Management Act to suspend or cancel for non-payment of levies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">The internal file minute also observed that '[a] permit holder has 21 days in which to appeal this decision, under section 165 of the AFMA, and in failure to do so, AFMA does not have any discretion to reinstate a permit after a permit has been cancelled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">Reference was also made to subsection 39(1)(c) which permits a cancellation of a fishing concession for non-payment of 'any fee, levy, charge or other money relating to the concession' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">Also recorded in that file minute were segments concerning the 'History of the GHAT Fishery ', reasons for 'The Need for Limited Entry Management' , the 'Issues' arising in relation to Mr Rhodes and finally the 'Recommendations' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">Two concluding matters relating to this AFMA decision were recorded as follows: 
 
 A removal of the limited entry policy may significantly add to the concerns surrounding the status of school shark stocks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">
 
 Granting this permit is inconsistent with the objectives of the current SESS management plan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">' 
 
 
 

As earlier indicated, the foregoing abbreviation SESS is for 'Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Management Plan'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">The recommendations made by the minute were 'not to reinstate permit no 26978 or issue a new GHAT permit...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Subsequently on 29 January 2004, AFMA's delegate conveyed to Mr Rhodes reasons for not reinstating his cancelled SSF permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">26978, and for not issuing to him a new permit for the 'Gillnet, Hook and Trap Fishery' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">The delegate explained his decision-making role to be to satisfy himself as follows: 'that the policy in place is legally valid, 
 
 
 
 if found to be valid, examine the decision under review to ensure that it has been made in accordance with that policy; and 
 
 
 
 consider whether there are strong reasons or special circumstances relating to your individual situation which may justify the departure from that policy in your case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">' 
 
 
 

On the same day as the above letter of 29 January 2004 was written, but apparently prior to completion of the letter, a brief file note was made by an AFMA officer (not identified but inferentially being the writer of that letter) which included the following:
 
 
 asked Mr Rhodes how long he had been on the remote island.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">Mr Rhodes stated he was there for 6 months and returned home at around August 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">' 
 
 Under the heading 'Has the Decision Under Review Been Made In Accordance With This Policy', the following answer was recorded by the delegate: 
 
 The decision to not reinstate permit number 26978 is consistent with there being no provision under the Fisheries Management Act 1991 to reinstate a cancelled permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">The second decision to not issue a new permit is consistent with Section 7(j) of the Southern and Eastern Scalefish and Shark Fishery Management Plan where "access to the fishery is limited through regulating the number of fishing concessions".</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">' 
 

Under the heading 'My Decisions' the following then appeared, after citation of s 39(1)(c) of the Management Act (to which I have already referred and the full text whereof is later extracted):
 
 
 decision is that the cancelled permit cannot be reinstated as there is no provision under the Fisheries Management Act 1991 to reinstate a cancelled permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">The only option is for AFMA to issue a new permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">' 
 

I do not understand that restricted interpretation to have been challenged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">Under the heading 'Special Circumstances Relating To Your Individual Situation Which May Justify A Departure From That Policy' , the following conclusion was set out by AFMA (the emphasis to the extent of non-italics below was that of the author of the letter of 29 January 2004): 
 
 I empathise with your situation of financial &amp; marital difficulties at the time, the facts are with regard to: 
 
 Financial hardship preventing payment of levies 
 
 
 
 When the levy notices were issued to you, although you state that you advised AFMA of financial difficulties at various times, a financial arrangement was not made with AFMA nor referred to.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">A financial arrangement could have prevented the cancellation of your permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">
 
 Harsh treatment regarding Clause 39(c) [the reference below should be of course to section 39(1)(c)] stating AFMA "may cancel" your permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">
 
 
 
 Letters dated 9 May 2001 and 25 May 2001 from AFMA are acknowledged as having been received by you at that time, in your letter dated 26 February 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">Although Clause 39(c) states "may cancel", these letters have clear warning that your permit will be CANCELLED, and offered the option to enter into a financial arrangement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">
 
 you state that you wrote to AFMA re one of these letters, your letter was not received by AFMA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">You also state that AFMA's further several attempts to contact you had failed due to being employed on a remote island where you were virtually uncontactable .</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">From dates provided by you in your letter dated 26 February 2002 and your telephone call today 29 January 2004, I estimate the period of time you were on the remote island to be between either February or March 2001 and August or September 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">The situation of your permit was not followed up on until your letter dated 26 February 2002 where you state: 
 
 "It wasn't until last week that I came across your letter of 25 May 01 that I realised I had not received a reply to my response, hence the phone call from me regarding the status of my permit which I assumed was being held in suspension until the levy was paid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">" 
 
 You also state: 
 
did not think that I was in danger of losing my entitlement assumed the Commonwealth had a similar process to Tasmania where licenses could be held in abeyance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">Had I known that I could lose the entitlement I would have made very effort to secure it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">" 
 
 from AFMA clearly stated the consequences if the levy was not paid or a financial arrangement was entered into.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">These warnings had warned of the loss of the entitlement and correspondence from AFMA did not state of the ability to hold a licence in obeyance (sic) .</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">
 
 previous fax from you to AFMA on 21 March 2001 requesting an appeal for quota allocation in the Southern Shark Fishery at the same period of time you were on the remote island, requested receipt confirmation by phone which was honored (sic) by AFMA on the same date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">I believe the same attempt to ensure your entitlement was safeguarded would be to request a receipt of the letter to AFMA which has gone missing, and if this receipt had not been received shortly after by you that you would have made contact with AFMA sooner than your letter dated 26 February 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">' 
 

AFMA concluded the letter by drawing attention to Mr Rhodes' right to seek a review of its decision by the AAT within 28 days, being a right of review which Mr Rhodes exercised by filing an application for review by the AAT on 23 February 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">There is no evidence of any response from Mr Rhodes to that letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">AFMA put in issue to the Tribunal various aspects of Mr Rhodes' version of events and of the claims which he put forward, and in particular his assertion that his permit was cancelled without having been provided with an opportunity to respond to the threat or prospect of suspension or cancellation of his license.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">His initial request for review was said by AFMA to relate (in substance) to the absence of availability to him of a quota, and not to the cancellation of his permit or to the circumstance that he was unable to satisfy the quota allocation criteria based on his catch history between 1994 and 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">The Tribunal recorded in its decision of 27 July 2005 in that regard that 'AFMA sent many reminder notices and attempted to contact him from March 2001 onwards, to which [Mr Rhodes] did not respond' , and that '[i]t was not until February 2002 that he was in contact with AFMA once more' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">The documentary material which I have reviewed supports the circumstances so outlined by AFMA and recorded by the Tribunal respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">AFMA pointed out that Mr Rhodes' '... new application, dated September 2003, was rejected because by then a "limited entry" policy was in force' , and contended that all of its decisions were lawfully made, '... and with ample opportunity for Mr Rhodes to make his case which he failed to do' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">Relevant provisions of the Fisheries Management Act 1991 (Cth) ('the Management Act') not already extracted in these reasons AFMA referred to the text of the provisions of the Management Act in relation to the following subjects in particular, the relevance whereof has or will become apparent: (i) the obligation of AFMA to prepare a plan of management (s 17) and to issue a public notice so as to enable representations to be made in relation thereto; subsections (5) and (6) are reproduced below: 
 
 ... a plan of management for a fishery is to set out: 
 
 the objectives of the plan of management; and 
 
 (b) measures by which the objectives are to be attained; and (c) performance criteria against which the measures taken may be assessed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">
 
 
 
 Without limiting the operation of subsection (5), a plan of management for a fishery may: 
 
 determine the method or methods by which the fishing capacity of the fishery or a part of the fishery is to be measured, which may be or include, but are not limited to, a method based on a particular area, a particular species or type or a particular quantity of fish, a particular kind, size or quantity of fishing equipment, a particular number of boats, a particular period of fishing, or any combination of the above; and 
 
 determine, or provide for AFMA to determine, the fishing capacity, measured by that method or those methods, permitted for the fishery or a part of the fishery in respect of a particular period or periods; and 
 
 provide for the management of the fishery by means of a system of statutory fishing rights, and other fishing concessions; and 
 
 contain a description of the fishery by reference to area, fish species, fishing methods to be employed or any other matter, and 
 
 subject to section 28, formulate procedures to be followed for selecting persons to whom fishing concessions are to be granted including, in the case of fishing rights: 
 
 the holding of an auction; or 
 
 the calling of tenders; or 
 
 (iii) the conducting of a ballot; and 
 
 
 
 (e) specify the kind and quantity of equipment that may be used in the fishery; and 
 
 
 
 (f) specify the circumstances in which a statutory fishing right may authorise fishing by or from a foreign boat; and 
 
 
 
 (g) impose obligations on the holders of fishing concessions; and 
 
 ....' 
 

 It was not contended by Mr Rhodes that the SESS Management Plan contained any provisions not explicitly or implicitly authorised by s 17;
 
 
 
 
 (ii) the authority of AFMA to grant fishing permits and the scope of that authority pursuant to s 32, subsections (1) and (1)(C) whereof reading as follows: 
 
 AFMA may, upon application made in the approved form, grant to a person a fishing permit authorising, subject to subsections (1A), (1B), (1C) and (1D), the use by that person, or by a person acting on that person's behalf, of an Australian boat for fishing in a specified area of the AFZ or a specified fishery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">... 
 
 The permit does not authorise the use of an Australian boat unless the boat complies with any conditions to which the permit is subject.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">' 
 
reference above to 'AFZ' is to the Australian fishing zone : (see s 4)); 
 
 (iii) the power of AFMA to suspend fishing concessions inclusively for non-payment of 'any fee, levy, charge or other money relating to the concession...' by way of written notice, s 38 headed 'Suspension of fishing concessions' containing subsections (1)(a) and (b)(i) reading as follows: 
 
 AFMA may, by written notice given to the holder of a fishing concession, suspend the operation of the concession if: 
 
 (a) any fee, levy, charge or other money relating to the concession is not paid as it becomes due; or 
 
 
 
 (b) it has reasonable grounds to believe that: 
 
 
 
 (i) there has been a contravention of a condition of the concession; 
 
 ....' 
 

 (to that subsection I would additionally set out below subsection (2) of s 38, the operation of which is raised contentiously in a later context:
 
 
 '(2) Subject to subsection (3), where a fishing concession is so suspended (otherwise than for the reason mentioned in paragraph (1)(a)), the suspension, unless it is sooner revoked, ceases: 
 
 (a) if proceedings for an offence against this Act in relation to the alleged act or omission because of which the concession was suspended are instituted against the holder of the concession, or a person who acted on behalf of the holder of the concession, within one month after the suspension --- on completion of the proceedings; or 
 
 (b) in any other case --- at the end of one month after the suspension.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">') 
 
 (iv) the power of AFMA to cancel by notice in writing any fishing concession if 'any fee, levy, charge or other money relating to the concession is not paid or the holder does not enter into an arrangement satisfactory to AFMA in relation to the money within such period as is prescribed after the time at which such fee, levy, charge or other money became due...' (s 39(1)(c)); (v) the prohibition against engagement in commercial fishing in an Australian fishing zone unless 'the person is, or is acting on behalf of, the holder of a fishing concession, or a scientific permit, that is in force authorising commercial fishing at that place' (s 95(1)(a)(i)); and (vi) the collection of levies, inclusive of interest thereon at 20% per annum upon the amount of levy from time to time remaining unpaid (s 112).</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">Grounds of application for review of AFMA's decision advanced by Mr Rhodes --- the issues which arose for decision-making by the AAT The AAT summarised the grounds for review of the AFMA decision of 29 January 2004 the subject of Mr Rhodes' application originally made to the AAT as follows: (i) a denial of natural justice occurred at the instance of AFMA by the suspension and cancellation of Mr Rhodes' permit before he was granted an opportunity to present his case; (ii) AFMA had knowledge of Mr Rhodes' financial difficulties and exceptional circumstances at the material times; (iii) it was inappropriate to apply rigidly the so-called 'no new entrants policy' to Mr Rhodes, given his long term involvement in the shark industry; (iv) the zero quota allocation to Mr Rhodes was irrational and against the economic efficiency objective; (v) there were cogent reasons to waive the so-called 'extant policy' of AFMA and grant Mr Rhodes a quota based on his 'catch history', for instance his possession of a Tasmanian shark license for many years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">
It may be seen that aside from the first ground for review above, which was unspecifically framed, those grounds for review did not at least readily constitute or reflect questions of law, but addressed factual or circumstantial matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">AFMA's response, as summarised by the AAT, was that the primary matter which the AAT was required to address as decision-maker was the cancellation of the fishing permit, and whether that cancellation had been lawfully made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">AFMA's contention advanced broadly to the AAT was that the asserted circumstances the subject of the grounds of review so propounded by Mr Rhodes 'did not exist', on any close analysis, as viable grounds for administrative review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">Apart from the first ground of review recorded above, that AFMA contention would appear to be correct in principle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">The Tribunal recorded AFMA's summary of the principal issues in substance and reality arising at the instance of Mr Rhodes as follows: (i) should Mr Rhodes be granted a Gillnet Hook and Trap Fishery ('GHTF') permit pursuant to section 32 of the Management Act?</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">(ii) should AFMA's limited entry policy that there not be granted any additional numbers and scope otherwise of permits be applied in Mr Rhodes case?</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">(iii) were there any circumstances in Mr Rhodes' case that would amount to cogent reasons for not applying the policy?</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">
As to issue (ii) above, 'additional' connoted and continues to connote additionally to the ceiling or totality of the capacity and scope the subject of all existing concessions or permit quotas or holdings existing at the time of the Management Act taking effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">The issues tendered for consideration by the respective parties on the present appeal, and particularly those advanced by Mr Rhodes, may be seen to have controversially involved at least certain factual disputes conceivably requiring resolution on the merits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">The Tribunal observed incidentally in par 5 of its Reasons for Decision that 'the standard of proof is on the balance of probabilities and to the reasonable satisfaction of the Tribunal' , being an observation which does not appear to have been challenged by either party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">The following concluding submissions of counsel for the respective parties assist to provide some broad insight into the nature and scope of the issues which were presented to the AAT for resolution: 
 
 Dr O'Connor's final written submission canvassed a wide range of issues and claimed there were a number of deficiencies in AFMA policy and procedures which had penalised his client who had not been afforded natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">Dr O'Connor argued that the limited entry policy had not been clearly articulated and there were cogent reasons to depart from existing policy by recognising the exceptional circumstances Mr Rhodes had faced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">He was critical of unreasonable catch verification procedures and [submitted that] the viability and economic efficiency of the industry would not be affected if the applicant was granted a permit and small quota.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">
 
represented AFMA in the AAT proceedings] 
 
 AFMA's final submission emphasised that although the decision under review related to cancellation of permit 26978 on 12 July 2001 and the subsequent refusal to issue a new permit in 2003, the applicant had not appealed against permit cancellation in 2001 and 2002, but focused almost entirely on the issue of quota.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">There was no power to reinstate a permit once cancelled and Mr Rhodes' application for a new permit in September 2003 was correctly refused under a valid limited entry policy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">
 
 
 
 The applicant had complained about injustice, but had engaged in the sale and purchase of substantial assets in the period 2001-2003 but never paid requisite fees and levies that amounted to a few hundred dollars.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">The applicant had made personal choices about which fish species to target and must have been aware that verified catch history was essential in the shark industry, yet relied solely upon logbooks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">While he mentioned exceptional circumstances once, he had failed to provide any substantial evidence about such a claim, so there were no cogent reasons for AFMA to depart from the catch verification process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">The 2003 SESS Management Plan was valid and AFMA was required to operate within its provisions and related policy documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">AFMA's decisions were thus lawfully made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">' 
 
 
 
 Whether the Tribunal incorrectly construed the SESS Management Plan and Offshore Constitutional Settlement as imposing a 'no new permits' or 'limited entry' policy upon AFMA --- the implications of that policy in relation to Mr Rhodes' contentions and AFMA's responses It was contended by Mr Rhodes in the present proceedings that the '[t]he reviewable decision of AFMA in relation to the issue of a new permit [to Mr Rhodes] found that AFMA was required to refuse the application for a permit on the basis that the SESS Management Plan imposed a policy of no new permits'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">That basis was said to be evident from section 7(1)(j) of the SESS Management Plan, the brief text of which I have earlier reproduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">It was contended by Mr Rhodes that '[t]he AAT found that AFMA was bound by the SESS Management Plan to limit the number of permit holders, so was required to refuse Mr Rhodes' application as he was a new entrant to the fishery'; so much was said by Mr Rhodes to have been found by the AAT to have been 'expressly contemplated by the OCS arrangements'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">However, so the contentions of Mr Rhodes developed, section 7(1)(j) of the SESS Management Plan ( ante ) '... did not impose a policy upon AFMA to refuse Mr Rhodes' application for a new permit', but comprised only one of 'several very general performance criteria [referring thereby to part of the section 7(1) heading] and did no more than reflect the fact that the fishery is managed by AFMA by the use of permits and quotas'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">So much was said by Mr Rhodes to be reinforced by the list of '... measures by which the objectives are to be attained' (as described in the heading to s 6 of the SESS Management Plan, and in particular those the subject of pars (c) and (e) thereof which I have earlier extracted).</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">Mr Rhodes argued accordingly that '[n]othing in these provisions required AFMA to refuse Mr Rhodes application'; my attention was drawn in that regard to [83]-[84] of the AAT's reasons for decision which I would now reproduce below: 
 
 Counsel for the applicant has raised a number of other concerns which will now be dealt with serially.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">The applicant has argued that the 2003 SESS Management Plan is invalid and any quota allocation under it is invalid as there is no articulated limited entry policy in existence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">This is a somewhat surprising claim, given that limited entry into the Commonwealth shark fishery has existed since 1988 because of rapid decline in shark biomass.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">A management plan in April 1988 created a limited entry gillnet fishery, reducing nominal capacity and resulting in some restructuring of the fishing fleet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">In April 1991 the number of nets in the fishery was further reduced by a third and controls on the long-line fishery, which took 25 percent of the catch were introduced in 1994 through hook permits, which were allocated according to prescribed entry criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">The area of the fishery was extended under OCS arrangements in 2000 but the OCS arrangements expressly contemplated no increase in fishing capacity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">
 
 The 2003 SESS Plan contemplated continuation of the policy of limited entry into this fishery, as Section [7(1)(j)] required AFMA to regulate (limit) the number of permit holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">This was an express reinforcement of the policy and AFMA was bound by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">When the applicant sought a new permit in September 2003 he should have been aware any decision would be based on extant policy at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">He perhaps believed he was not a new entrant, having operated in the shark industry for many years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">However this was not really the case; when permit 26978 was cancelled in July 2001 he was advised it was not feasible to reinstate the permit as no such provision existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">He was also informed that non-payment of requisite fees and charges meant that once the permit was cancelled he could no longer use it as a basis for making further applications in the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">He was permitted 21 days in which to apply for reconsideration of this decision, but did not do so, being incommunicado at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">' 
 
 
 
 I should record in any event that in the context of its reasons for decision at [83]-[84] above, the AAT was undertaking its response to what it recorded there as Mr Rhodes' argument that the SESS Management Plan was 'invalid [because there was] no articulated limited entry policy in existence' , (something which the AAT pointed out to be 'a somewhat surprising claim, given that limited entry into the Commonwealth shark fishery has existed since 1988 because of rapid decline in shark biomass '), and further that s 7(1)(j) of the SESS Management Plan 'required AFMA to regulate (limit) the number of permit holders' , by way of 'an express reinforcement of the policy' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">I have of course earlier reproduced the brief but important text to s 7(1)(j) of the SESS Management Plan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">Reference was made in that regard by the AAT to inter alia pars (c) and (e) of s 6 of that Plan, which I have also earlier reproduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">The AAT's reasons drew the inference that '[w]hen [Mr Rhodes] sought a new permit in September 2003 he should have been aware any decision would be based on extant policy at the time' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">Those submissions of Mr Rhodes restated AFMA's case at a wider level than that which AFMA formulated in its submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">That case to my understanding was to the effect that: (i) Section 7(1) of the SESS Management Plan authorised the limitation of access through the regulation of the number and extent of fishing concessions granted for the time being, that being within the scope of the policy that was implemented; (ii) AMFA's rejection of Mr Rhodes' case was open to be made upon the operation of the SESS Management Plan correctly construed, and in the light of the circumstances otherwise prevailing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">Mr Rhodes' submissions proceeded nevertheless that 'nothing in the OCS arrangements imposes such a policy' of regulation of the number of permit holders, Mr Rhodes referring in that regard to what appeared in the Memorandum of Understanding of 17 November 2000 ( supra ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">Instead, so Mr Rhodes' submissions continued, the Memorandum of Understanding contemplated that 'the fishery will be managed by determination of total allowable catch for quota species, allocation of that [TAC] quota to permit holders, and making such quota transferable'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">Reference was made by Mr Rhodes to page 11 of the AFMA document headed 'Southern Shark Fishery 2001 Management Arrangements' issued in January 2001 relating to the transferable nature of quotas, and to the register of quota holders, the leasing, selling or buying of quotas '[i] n the expanded SSF' , and also to the opportunity open to persons having '... no school and/or gummy share quota assigned to [their] shark fishery concession...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">However it is to be observed that such opportunity was explicitly limited by those 'Management Arrangements' to an ability '... to catch non-quota species in the fishery'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">The endeavour of Mr Rhodes to establish an absence of authority of AFMA to regulate the number of permit holders for the time being to the extent that AFMA contended, and to quantify their respective quotas, was unpersuasive in my opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">Similarly the endeavour of Mr Rhodes to establish that the AAT erred in construing the SESS Management Plan and the OCS arrangements as imposing a so-called 'no new permits policy' upon AFMA was I think unsupportable in the light of that documentation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">The essence of that policy is clearly to be distilled from the text of the Memorandum of Understanding of 17 November 2000 entered into between the Commonwealth and the relevant States, and subsequently of the SESS Management Plan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">In reaching those conclusions, it becomes perhaps unnecessary for me to consider, in the circumstances postulated by Mr Rhodes, the scope of operation of the general law relating to the formation and promulgation of Ministerial policy as a guide to the exercise of administrative discretion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">Nevertheless I would record in that context the principles restated by Brennan J (as then President of the AAT) in Re Drake and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1979) 2 ALD 634 at 640, as follows: 
 
 are powerful considerations in favour of a Minister adopting a guiding policy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">It can serve to focus attention on the purpose which the exercise of the discretion is calculated to achieve, and thereby to assist the Minister and others to see more clearly, in each case, the desirability of exercising the power in one way or another.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">Decision-making is facilitated by the guidance given by an adopted policy, and the integrity of decision-making in particular cases is the better assured if decisions can be tested against such a policy can diminish the inconsistencies which might otherwise appear in a series of decisions, and enhance the sense of satisfaction with the fairness and continuity of the administrative process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">
 
 course, a policy must be consistent with the statute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">It must allow the Minister to take into account the relevant circumstances, it must not require him to take into account irrelevant circumstances, and it must not serve a purpose foreign to the purpose for which the discretionary power was created.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">A policy which contravenes these criteria would be inconsistent with the statute....' 
 
 Reference may also be made in that regard to Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs v Gray (1994) 50 FCR 189 at 206, where French and Drummond JJ, referring to Re Drake, observed as follows: 
 
 place of government policy in the Tribunal's decision-making will depend upon the interests of good government and consistent decision-making on the one hand and the ideal of justice in the individual case on the other.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">But its decision must be the result of an independent assessment of all the circumstances of the particular case and not the uncritical application of policy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">' 
 
 Purportedly by way of reply, Mr Rhodes contended that AFMA did 'not point to any properly articulated statement as to what is said to be its "limited entry" policy, in a form that the AAT or this Court can properly assess such a policy: 
 
 as being lawful by reference to the structure and operation of the [Management Act]; and 
 
 as being applicable to the circumstances of Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">' 
 


 
I do not think that to be correct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">In any event, upon that somewhat sweeping and unspecific footing, Mr Rhodes contended that '[t]here is therefore no policy within the scope of Drake ' and further that '[t]o the extent such a policy might be implied from various matters found in the evidence... such a policy when properly construed does not treat [Mr Rhodes] as a "new entrant" in any relevant sense'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">I have difficulty in distilling the implications of either contention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">The policy is articulated or reflected both explicitly and implicitly for instance in the provisions of sections 7(5)(1)(j) and 62(4).</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">The objective circumstances were that Mr Rhodes did not tender payment of the management levy of $400.00 at any material time, his fishing permit relating to the period of time from 1 March 2001 to 31 December 2001 was suspended on 9 May 2001 and cancelled on 12 July 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">After those events had occurred, Mr Rhodes merely forwarded to AFMA a form of application for fishing permit, and did so without any tender of payment of fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">It was next asserted by Mr Rhodes that '[n]othing can be taken from the events prior to the OCS arrangements (1985 to 2001) in relation to boat and net numbers as affecting [Mr Rhodes]', and that '[w]hatever policy may have been in place, it was expressly overridden by the OCS transfer of jurisdiction from Tasmania to the Commonwealth'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">The first limb of that assertion was not seemingly supported in relation to either boat numbers or fish net numbers, and the second limb purportedly propounded a proposition without any apparent, much less reasoned, support.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">It was then asserted by Mr Rhodes that 'OCS arrangements required the Commonwealth to treat Tasmanian fishermen on a fair and equitable basis with Commonwealth fishers', and further that the same 'expressly permitted Tasmanian Shark Gill Net and Hook fishermen to apply for a Commonwealth fishing concession'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">Those provisions originated in the Memorandum of Understanding of 17 November 2000, clause 12(g) thereof reading as follows: 
 
 ensuring individual fishers in a fishery, who come under the Commonwealth's jurisdiction as a result of OCS arrangements, are treated on a fair and equitable basis with all other fishers in the school shark and gummy shark fishery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">' 
 
 However that opportunity for equal participation was not open-ended at least in the sense of accommodating prospective or aspirational entrants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">Thus clause 14 of the Memorandum of Understanding, under the sub-heading 'Commonwealth School Shark and Gummy Shark Management', required 'listed fishers' within '60 days, from notification, to apply for a Commonwealth shark fishing concession' , and clause 15 thereof recorded that 'AFMA has taken a decision, in accordance with its legislative objectives, that school shark and gummy shark will be managed by determining the total allowable catch... of each species, allocating the Commonwealth component of the TAC to individual Commonwealth fishing concession holders as individual quota and making this individual quota transferable'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">Moreover clause 16 stipulated for '[t]he initial allocation mechanism to apportion the TAC of school shark and gummy shark... sectors within the Southern Shark Fishery', and for '... the appropriate formula(e) for the allocation of Individual Transferable Quotas... for school shark and gummy shark amongst Southern Shark Fishery permit holders within each of the sectors...' , pursuant to recommendation 'by an independent allocation advisory panel, which was charged with the task of recommending a result which ensures that all operators in the fishery are treated on a fair and equitable basis in the allocation process...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">However so much did not declare or envisage contextually that the allocation process would remain open to newcomers, if otherwise qualified to apply as 'licensed fishers' , subsequent to the operation of '[t]he initial allocation mechanism' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">I should add importantly for completeness in relation to the immediately foregoing theme that under the heading 'Management Of School Shark And Gummy Shark In Waters Relevant To Tasmania' and the subheading 'School and Gummy Shark Management in Commonwealth Waters ', the Memorandum of Understanding stipulated inter alia as follows: 
 
 AFMA will restrict Commonwealth shark fishing concessions to their area of access on their previous State and/or Commonwealth fishing concessions... 
 
 ... 
 
 The above restrictions are required due to the concerns of AFMA, the Tasmanian Department of Primary Industries, Water and Environment, Tasmanian fishers and Commonwealth fishers that there be no increase in demersal fishing capacity within coastal waters, due to the potential impact an increase could have on the stocks of State managed scale fish species and potential impacts on the school shark entering nursery areas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">' 
 
 
 

The reference above to '... no increase in demersal fishing capacity...' may be observed in particular.</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">It was next submitted emphatically by Mr Rhodes that there was nothing contained within the OCS arrangements that imposed any 'no new permits policy', notwithstanding the apparent implications which I have already cited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">I was referred generally to what appears in the twelve paged Memorandum of Understanding (which I have already partly reviewed), and further generally to the 'Arrangement Between The Commonwealth And State of Tasmania, In relation To The By-Catch Fishery For School And Gummy Shark To Be Managed Under State Law In Waters Relevant To Tasmania' made on 13 December 2000, and the 'Arrangement Between The Commonwealth And The State of Tasmania In Relation To The Fishery For School And Gummy Shark To Be Managed Under Commonwealth Law In Waters Relevant To Tasmania' also made on 13 December 2000, and to an Article headed 'Stock assessment and risk analysis for the school shark (Galeorhinus galeus) off southern Australia' compiled by Andre Punt and Terence Walker (Manuscript received 3 October 1996 and accepted 7 February 1997) comprising 11 pages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">The problem for Mr Rhodes in those regards however was his status in the light of the suspension of his SSF permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">26978 by AFMA on 9 May 2001 and the cancellation thereof by AFMA subsequently on 2 August for non-payment of his $400.00 SSF Fishery management levy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">Nevertheless, so the submissions of Mr Rhodes continued, 'the OCS Memorandum of Understanding contemplates the fishery will be managed by determination of total allowable catch for quota species, allocation of that TAC quota to permit holders and making such quota transferable' , Mr Rhodes referring generally again to clauses 14 to 16 of the Memorandum of Understanding of 17 November 2000, and to page 11 of the Southern Shark Fishery 2001 Management Arrangements of January 2001 appearing under the heading 'Is Quota Transferable?'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">That begs the issue as to restrictions imposed elsewhere in relation to the permit holders to be the subject of such allocations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">It was submitted further by Mr Rhodes in the present context that '[a]part from the 2003 Management Plan and the OCS arrangements, there was no evidence before the AAT of any promulgated policy of the Minister or AFMA to refuse applications for fishing permits in the SESS Fishery'; it was said by Mr Rhodes in that regard that '... cases such as Re Green and Australian Fisheries Management Authority [2004] AATA 426 ; (2004) 81 ALD 194 are distinguishable'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">To provide a brief key to an understanding of the ratio in Re Green, I extract below the headnote, which would at least not seem to lend support to Mr Rhodes' contention in that regard: 
 
 relevant AFMA policy did not have the status of Ministerial policy, or policy adopted by a body such as the Australian Fisheries Council comprising the relevant Commonwealth and state ministers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">However, the policy was settled and adopted by the AFMA board after consultation with key stakeholders, and should be given great weight by the tribunal and should be applied unless it was unlawful or unless there were cogent reasons militating against its application in the circumstances of the particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">' 
 
 It was acknowledged by Mr Rhodes that '[w]hen determining the quota to be allocated to individual fishing permits, considerations of management by way of the TAC [ie total allowable catch] quota, and environmental concerns invoking the precautionary principle, may well be relevant', and I was referred in that regard to AFMA's letter of 12 November 2003 to Mr Rhodes, which concluded with AFMA's statement of an inability '... to reinstate your fishing permit 26978' , to which letter I have already referred in some detail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">However there additionally appeared in that letter the further statement that '[l] imiting the number of operators in a fishery has been widely adopted through the world as a necessary first step in any management of fisheries resources' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">AFMA furthermore cited 'Technical Guidelines for responsible fisheries 4' , being a United Nations Food and Agriculture Organisation's 1997 publication, which contained reference to the factor that '... limited access is widely considered to be essential for efficient and responsible fisheries' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">In the same context, AFMA further cited the 1992 'Inter-governmental Agreement on the Environment' , entered into by the Commonwealth, State and Territory Governments in Australia, where in par 3.5.1 the following appeared: 
 
 there are threats of serious or irreversible environmental damage, lack of full scientific certainty should not be used as a reason for postponing measures to prevent environmental degradation...</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">' 
 
 It was in the context essentially of what I have summarised in the present segment of these reasons that Mr Rhodes contended boldly that '[i]t was inconsistent with the objectives of the [Management Act], the SESS Management Plan and the OCS arrangements to refuse Mr Rhodes' application on the basis that he was, at the time of the application, not the holder of a current permit'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">I have experienced considerable difficulty in distilling any such themes of assistance from those materials in favour of Mr Rhodes' contentions propounded by counsel, and which I have sought to summarise or reproduce in these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">Mr Rhodes' submissions raised, as a further basis for the grant of the administrative relief sought by him, the subject of a so-called 'cost recovery policy' asserted by Mr Rhodes to have been wrongly adopted by AFMA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">My attention was drawn however to the written outline of evidence of Mr Wilson, AFMA's senior manager of compliance policy, where under the heading 'Why the Applicant should not be granted a new permit' , the following appeared: 
 
 The grant of a new permit would in effect replace the cancelled permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">There are several reasons why the Applicant should not be granted a new permit in the fishery, namely: ` 
 
 the grant of a new permit in place of the cancelled permit would subvert AFMA's compliance and enforcement initiatives and diminish the threat of suspension and cancellation of a concession as a real enforcement tool, in terms of both fisheries management and levy collection; 
 
 
 
 the grant of a new permit in place of the cancelled permit would subvert the AFMA's ability to charge and collect levies for and on behalf of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">This would enable and promote levy avoidance; 
 
 
 
 the grant of a new permit in place of the cancelled permit would be contrary to AFMA's cost recovery objective in that a concession holder could avoid paying for management costs under the user pays principle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">This would allow a concession holder to opt-out of a fishery to avoid costs associated with complex and controversial management changes, such as the introduction of ITQ and re-enter the fishery at no cost upon the changes being finalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">This is inconsistent with the principle that resource users should pay for costs directly related to the management of their fishing activities; 
 
 
 
 AFMA has consistently applied the limited entry policy to this Fishery unless there are cogent reasons raised by an Applicant as to why they should be granted a permit; 
 
 
 
 it is open to anyone seeking access to the Fishery to either purchase or lease a permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">' 
 
 
 

Largely upon that footing, Mr Wilson's testimony sought to draw the following conclusions:
 
 
 to not apply the limited entry policy to Mr Rhodes on the basis that his permit was cancelled due to non payment of his 2001 levy (after he was given ample opportunity to do so) would be inequitable to all other operators who have continued to pay their levies within the requisite time period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">The tier one levy payable for a permit in the SSF and its successor fisheries has increased substantially for the period from 2001: 
 
 2001 - $400 in addition to the prescribed amount for quota species; 2002 - $1,011.70 in addition to the prescribed amount for quota species; 2003 - $1,466.36 in addition to the prescribed amount for quota species; 2004 - $1,513.59 in addition to the prescribed amount for quota species; 2005 - $1,808.43 in addition to the prescribed amount for quota species.</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">' 
Whether however it is necessary for AFMA's present case to rely on that further evidentiary material is another matter, since the material would appear to be somewhat peripheral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">Mr Rhodes next submitted, in relation to what he described as the view [of AFMA] that '... cost recovery was a relevant ground to refuse the application for a permit', that the same was 'inconsistent with the proper construction of the Management Act', yet contrary to that thesis, so Mr Rhodes continued, the AAT appeared to pursue that view in the course of its reasoning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">I was referred in that regard by Mr Rhodes to par 34 of the AAT's reasons for decision below, where a summarised account of the testimony of AFMA's senior compliance manager was cited to the following effect: 
 
 tendered a proof of evidence outlining recent developments in shark policy but dealing in more detail with cost recovery procedures and provisions for dealing with unpaid or overdue levies, instalment payment arrangements, the suspension or cancellation of permits and reasons why the applicant should not be granted a new permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">He emphasised there were a number of inbuilt safeguards by AFMA to prevent or correct error and check that legislative provisions were being fully followed' 
 

Mr Rhodes observed that the Management Act contained 'specific provisions dealing with recovery of levies and other charges', including the so-called penalty for non-payment provisions of s 112 thereof involving an interest rate of 20% per annum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">It was pointed out by Mr Rhodes moreover that by s 113 of the Management Act, headed 'Recovery of levy and other amounts' , the levy and interest are recoverable as debts due to the Commonwealth, and moreover that where instalment plans are in place, failure to pay an 'instalment results in the entire amount of [the] levy becoming due and payable immediately', pursuant to s 111 of the Management Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">I have not gained material assistance from the material cited in this paragraph.</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">It was in the context of those levy and charge collection provisions of the Management Act that Mr Rhodes further submitted that '[w]here the Act has expressly provided for the penalty to be imposed for failure to pay a levy, it is an improper exercise of power by AFMA [to] seek to impose a further penalty on Mr Rhodes by refusing to issue him a new permit', and further that '[h]ad Parliament intended that cancellation of a permit be permanent, it would have made specific provision to that effect'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">It was further submitted by Mr Rhodes that '[t]he cost recovery argument also ignores the ability of AFMA under section 32(6) to impose conditions on the issue of a permit', and further that '[i]f there are outstanding levies or other obligations, the permit could be made conditional upon the applicant first discharging his outstanding levy obligations'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">Whether a logical stopping place in terms of viable and convenient economic management may be articulated in support of that contention must be at least difficult to encapsulate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">It is a common feature of contractual remedies of cancellation of entire contractual rights on default of payment of a liquidated sum that the same crystallise ipso facto , and are exercisable subject to whatever formalities of notice may be stipulated by the governing contract or any statutory stipulation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">Treating the failure to pay levies as fatal to Mr Rhodes' application was said by Mr Rhodes in any event to misconstrue the discretion vested in AFMA under s 32 of the Management Act, that being described as not a matter of cost recovery but effecting in substance a forfeiture which in private law would give rise to relief for unconscionable conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">Qualification for relief of that kind would normally be at least formidable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">Mr Rhodes invoked the decision of the High Court in Legione v Hateley [1983] HCA 11 ; (1983) 152 CLR 406, but the analogy is hardly in kilter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">That well known High Court authority concerning relief against forfeiture related to a purchaser by instalments originally of vacant land, in circumstances where the purchaser erected subsequently a home on the land at a time when the land had not been fully paid for, and hence in circumstances where upon termination of the contract for default in payment of the purchase price for the vacant land, 'the vendors will receive an ill-merited windfall' (per Gibbs CJ and Murphy J at 429).</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">In my opinion the loss of the statutory privilege in the nature of the present fishing permit by reason of non-payment of periodic levies geared to the continuance on foot of the permit would not constitute sufficient analogy with the principles of the general law concerning forfeiture of property or proprietary rights in circumstances where the statutory entity gains no proprietary or pecuniary advantage and is merely enabled or assisted to perform its statutory functions and obligations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">Whether breach of natural justice occurred on AFMA's part This further issue was raised by Mr Rhodes by way of challenge to the exercise by AFMA of its power of cancellation of Mr Rhodes' fishing permit for reasons of so-called 'non-payment of fees or levies'; it was acknowledged that '[i]n determining the scope of the obligation of natural justice, the statutory framework is of crucial importance'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">I was referred by Mr Rhodes to the High Court decision of Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1963] HCA 41 ; (1963) 113 CLR 475, where in the reasons for judgment of Kitto J at 502-4, his Honour considered whether the Taxation Board of Review was '... legally bound to conform to the principles of natural justice in dealing with a reference in a case under s 136' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">Kitto J made the prefatory observations that '[a] legal obligation so to act arises in respect of many statutory powers...', there being '... no words which are of universal application to every kind of inquiry and every kind of tribunal...', but '[w]hat the law requires in the discharge of a quasi-judicial function is judicial fairness' , which is '... not a label for any fixed body of rules...,' and '[w]hat is fair in a given situation depends upon the circumstances' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">The statutory context of the then Income Tax and Social Services Contribution Assessment Act 1936-1958 (Cth), which was of course in focus in Mobil Oil , is significantly removed from that of the Management Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">Mr Rhodes sought support additionally for the operation in principle of the rules as to natural justice from the dictum of Brennan J in National Companies and Securities Commission v News Corporation Ltd [1984] HCA 29 ; (1984) 156 CLR 296 at 326, where his Honour observed as follows: 
 
 the limits of a statutory function are ascertained the interests which are apt to be affected by the performance of the function can be identified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">Then it is possible for a court to say --- in the absence of express statutory provision --- what has to be done to be fair to those whose interests are apt to be affected by the performance of the function.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">The terms of the statute which creates the function, the nature of the function and the administrative framework in which the statute requires the function to be performed are material factors in determining what must be done to satisfy the requirements of natural justice....' 
 

Those considerations render formidable the task of establishing the operation of the rules of natural justice in the present statutory context where the basis for prospective qualification would be the same for all applicants, that being the holding of an existing shark permit conditional of course upon payment of the permit fee or levy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">It was submitted by Mr Rhodes next that under s 38(2) of the Management Act, '... where a permit has been suspended for reasons for non-payment of fees or levies, such suspension continues until revoked, and is not subject to the one month limitation in other cases'; I have earlier reproduced the text of that subsection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">However the operation of s 38(2) must be also read in the light of the authority of cancellation additionally conferred upon AFMA and addressed in s 39(1)(c) of the same legislation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">It was said further by Mr Rhodes that '[t]he real question here is whether AFMA ought to have taken the further step of cancellation of the permit without affording Mr Rhodes actual notice of its intentions and a reasonable opportunity for him to be heard before the decision was made', and in that regard, '[r]easonable prior notice is a cardinal principle of natural justice'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">The insuperable obstacle standing in the way of the efficacy of that submission of Mr Rhodes is the scheme of the abovementioned s 39 of the Management Act, which independently authorises cancellation 'whether or not [AFMA] has previously suspended the fishing concession...'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">I was nevertheless referred to a number of authorities which I will address below, none of which in my opinion accommodate the present statutory context and circumstances involving AFMA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">The first was R v Small Claims Tribunal and Homewood; Ex parte Cameron [1976] VR 427, which related to an extension of the scope of a claim for breach of contract based upon an alleged misrepresentation without the respondent to the proceedings having been given notice of the misrepresentation as the basis for that extended claim, and therefore having been extended an opportunity to meet that case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">The second was Cameron v Cole [1944] HCA 5 ; (1943) 68 CLR 571, where there had occurred an omission, albeit inadvertent, to notify a debtor of an adjourned hearing date of a bankruptcy petition, and where an order for sequestration nevertheless was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">The third was Hoskins v Van Den-Braak (1998) 43 NSWLR 290, where a person was held entitled to have a judgment set aside unconditionally, in circumstances where the claim on which the judgment was based was not served on that person or on anyone retained on that person's behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">The fourth was Clements v Independent Indigenous Advisory Committee [2003] FCAFC 143 ; (2003) 131 FCR 28 at [33] , where it was held that written notice of a hearing date did not reach an applicant for relief in time, and an incorrect recording of his telephone number had frustrated attempts to communicate with that person by telephone, and further that the tribunal decision-maker was unaware of the absence of notice of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">As I have already observed, none of those particular cases involved the operation of a statutory scheme such as Mr Rhodes must here address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">It was next contended by Mr Rhodes that '[a]n important factor relevant to the scope of natural justice is the consequence of the decision'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">In Gribbles Pathology (Vic) Pty Ltd v Cassidy [2002] FCA 859 ; (2002) 122 FCR 78 at 117, Weinberg J enunciated the following principle: 
 
 is well established that the seriousness of a decision for an affected individual is one of the main considerations determining the application of procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">Generally speaking, the requirements of procedural fairness will be heightened in proportion to the gravity of the consequences involved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">' 
 

It was said in that context that if AFMA was right to refuse Mr Rhodes a new permit on 'no new permits' or 'cost recovery' grounds, the consequence of cancellation of his permit would be his effective expulsion from the fishery, that being described as 'a very serious consequence to Mr Rhodes'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">Apart from the particular elements of the statutory scheme here relevantly required to be adjectivally observed, there was here involved an absence of response on his part over an extended period of time involving what the Tribunal characterised in terms of inevitable consequences 'obvious to him' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">The reality of Mr Rhodes' circumstances of default was such as to render attenuated his invocation of the scope of natural justice inherent in the submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">A further matter submitted by Mr Rhodes not to have been considered by the AAT, but nevertheless said to have been relevant to the circumstances in which he found himself to be placed, was that his long involvement in the industry, and the potential effects on him of any decision to cancel the permit, gave rise inherently to a legitimate expectation of procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">The submission begged the question at least as to what was inherently unfair procedurally in the nature and extent of the steps taken and processes implemented by AFMA which merely conformed to the steps and processes required to be put in train in relation to any industry participant who was placed in the same vulnerable position as Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">A yet further factor said here to have prevailed in Mr Rhodes' favour against any cancellation of his permit was a lack of urgency in relation to the making by AFMA of its cancellation decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">It was submitted by Mr Rhodes that there was no good reason for AFMA to have made that decision in relation to the cancellation of the permit within a matter of 'weeks after the suspension'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">It was further submitted that the Management Act expressly contemplated the indefinite suspension of a permit, and there was no requirement even to consider cancellation after a suspension.</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">However it was plainly within AFMA's prerogative to determine whether it should exercise juridical powers and remedies which had crystallised in operation to the extent that it deceased to be appropriate in the contextual circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">Mr Rhodes next submitted that he had been already prohibited from fishing prior to the cancellation of his permit, yet interest on the unpaid levies would continue to accrue at a penal rate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">No benefit to AFMA was therefore obtainable from cancellation of the permit, other than AFMA's view that it could thereupon terminate the need for so-called 'internal reconsideration', and that such motivation on AFMA's part would have been improper in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">It was further submitted that this would have a 'very adverse effect' on Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">It was not however a condition to AFMA's lawful exercise of regulatory authority to endeavour to divine the particular implications of a permit cancellation personal or peculiar to a defaulting permit holder, so long as the requirements of the stipulated procedure were observed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">In that regard the AAT found it sufficient in any event that AFMA had made attempts to communicate with Mr Rhodes prior to the cancellation, such attempts consisting of AFMA's letters of 9 May 2001 and 25 May 2001, calling a telephone number listed on AFMA records, and requesting on 5 June 2001 that the local police get in touch with Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">Mr Rhodes submitted in any event that since the AAT did not find that he received any of that AFMA correspondence or had any actual notice of AFMA's intention to cancel the subject permit, and further that the AAT expressly refused to make any finding that Mr Rhodes had deliberately avoided potential creditors, or had received what was described as 'financial correspondence', those factors should have rendered inapplicable any issue otherwise arising as to Mr Rhodes' absence of response to AFMA's communications related to Mr Rhodes' default.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">Instead it was contended by Mr Rhodes that the AAT took the view that his ignorance of AFMA's intention to cancel his permit was unreasonable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">To the extent that that contention did have juridical significance, which I am unable to accept in any event, it is not possible to divine any basis for the extremity of the course which AFMA should have supposedly pursued in an endeavour to communicate relevantly with Mr Rhodes, and to do so prior to exercising its legal rights and remedies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">In conclusion, Mr Rhodes submitted that given the very serious implications to him in terms of permanent or temporal deprivation of his fishing concession, the lack of any urgency from the perspective of AFMA, and the structure of the Management Act in terms of ss 38 and 39 thereof relating to 'suspension and cancellation of fishing concessions' respectively, natural justice required AFMA to ensure that Mr Rhodes had actual notice of its intention to cancel the permit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">It was further concluded that he should have been afforded thereafter reasonable opportunity within which to make submissions in relation to the exercise of AFMA's discretion as to the course which it proposed to implement consequentially upon Mr Rhodes' default.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">That concluding submission assisted to illustrate the extent to which Mr Rhodes persevered with his endeavours for curial intervention in his favour, but a similar adverse response is warranted to that appearing in the preceding paragraphs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">No natural justice precedent having conceivable operation in relation to the present circumstances was cited by Mr Rhodes in support of the present or any of his preceding contentions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">Nor did Mr Rhodes demonstrate what he would have accomplished in reality by way of establishing the operation of a fishing concession as a consequence of his being able ex hyposesi to fund the unpaid levy at the material time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">Conclusions The submissions of AFMA arising for consideration in the present proceedings related essentially to each of the following AAT decisions: (i) that made on or about 11 July 2001 for cancellation of shark fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">26978 for non-payment of the $400.00 levy, and notified by communication of that date to Mr Rhodes; (ii) that subsequently made on 11 November 2003 by way of refusal to reinstate that permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">26978, and notified by communication of that date to Mr Rhodes; and (iii) that further made on 29 January 2004 by way of refusal, or confirmation of earlier refusal, to reinstate that permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">26978, and also by way of refusal to issue any new permit, and notified by letter of that date to Mr Rhodes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">
As I have earlier recorded, the AAT treated the AFMA decision-making the subject of review as the decision made on 12 July 2001, but it is apparent from [87]-[90] of the AAT's reasons that the decision-making in dispute was more comprehensively expanded subsequently by the succeeding decisions of AFMA purportedly notified to Mr Rhodes on 12 November 2003 and 29 January 2004 respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">I would accept Mr Rhodes' three foundation contentions, recorded in [4] above, as raising in principle questions of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">The true interpretation of the 2003 Management Plan, to the extent that the same arose rightly for consideration, and being in the nature of governmental regulation, would have inherently raised questions of law for consideration by the AAT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">Moreover to the extent that any irrelevant considerations may be shown to have been taken into account by AFMA for the purpose of its relevant decision-making, so much may well have so operated as to have rendered that decision-making ineffective according to law; it appears however that no vitiated decision-making relevantly took place on AFMA's part.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">As to the issue raised as to breach of natural justice on AFMA's part, so much would have also involved inherently a question of law; however I do not think that Mr Rhodes articulated with precision or at all any material circumstances reflective of any cause of action relevantly for breach of natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">The task of securing a successful review of AFMA's decision-making complained of was inherently formidable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">The case of Mr Rhodes presented on the appeal to the effect that the AAT misconstrued the SESS Management Plan as purportedly limiting the number of permit/holders, and further that the AAT refused Mr Rhodes' application for review by reason of his purported status as a new entrant to the SSF, and yet further that so much was wrongly found by the AAT to have been expressly contemplated by the OCS arrangements, was in each of those aspects misconceived in the light of the evidence I have reviewed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">One of the principal contexts to Mr Rhodes' present application for review by way of appeal has been summarised earlier in these reasons, that being the high level governmental Memorandum of Understanding of 17 November 2000 and the policy reasons underpinning its introduction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">Another was Mr Rhodes' quota allocation subsequently of zero kilograms in relation to both school and gummy shark, as a consequence of his lack of demonstration of any verifiable catch.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">The permit issued to Mr Rhodes, albeit for a zero kilograms allocation, was subsequently cancelled in any event for non-payment of the levy of $400.00 imposed on him; his reasons given for that non-payment were found by AFMA to be inadequate on the basis of relevant evidentiary material, and the inferences reasonably open to be drawn therefrom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">In the course of my consideration of the evidence relating to those critical areas of controversy, I have already detailed the AFMA evidence adduced in the proceedings which provided strong support for the conclusions open to be drawn in its favour, being evidence which Mr Rhodes has not succeeded in rebutting or otherwise in showing to be ineffective.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">As I have further foreshadowed, I am unable to accept Mr Rhodes' case to the effect that either the SESS Management Plan or the OCS arrangements imposed upon AFMA any 'no new permits' policy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">Factors operating persuasively in rebuttal of that case of Mr Rhodes may be identified from the following circumstances in outline which I have earlier identified and discussed: (i) The limited extent of the provisions of the Memorandum of Understanding made between the Commonwealth and the relevant States as to allowance for 'exceptional circumstances' , and as to treatment of individual fishers 'on a fair and equitable basis' (see in particular clauses 12 and 14 to 16 thereof), both in the context of the policy adopted by the relevant governments as to 'no increase in demersal fishing capacity...' ; (ii) the provisions of the SESS Management Plan as to the TAC to be allocated to individual concession holders respectively, and as to restrictions in terms of permissible extent of harvesting of relevant areas in conformity with allocations of quantified quotas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">Nor have I been able to accept the contention of Mr Rhodes that the AAT found incorrectly, as relevant to the refusal to grant Mr Rhodes a permit quota, the enforcement of AFMA's cost recovery procedures.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">As I have earlier pointed out in particular in [4] and [16] above, the formulation of that contention by Mr Rhodes in terms of any such finding was misconceived, in that as has been earlier traced in detail in these reasons, what was granted by AFMA to Mr Rhodes on 1 March 2001 was fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">26978 on the footing of a quota of zero or nil kilograms of gummy and school shark, because he provided no verified catch data to AFMA for the yearly term of 1994-1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">As I have indicated further in [19]-[20] above, that fishing permit no.</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">26978 was cancelled effectively as from 11 July 2001 because of non-payment of the $400.00 levy, with the consequence that Mr Rhodes became ineligible from that time to conduct commercial fishing activity in the SSF.</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">As to Mr Rhodes' case that AFMA did not afford to him natural justice in relation to the processes implemented by it up to the time of cancellation of his fishing permit, no viable basis has been demonstrated in that regard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s430">What was required generally of prospective participants in the SESS Management Plan was the holding of the requisite permit upon which periodic levies would be duly imposed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s431">Understandably non-payment of levies carried the sanction of cancellation of fishing permits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s432">The evidence demonstrates that no payment was made by Mr Rhodes of his initial levy of $400.00 applicable to the three year period from February 1994 to December 1997, crystallisation in enjoyment of the relevant shark fishing permit involved being based upon payment of that levy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s433">The case at first instance conducted before the AAT, and also conducted on the present review by this Court by way of appeal, developed its respective complexities, partly because the AAT pleadings were filed virtually contemporaneously and were not such as to reflect what was precisely in issue between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s434">Seemingly as a consequence, Mr Rhodes sought to raise issues on the present appeal which were widely encompassing, and at least some of which were susceptible to characterisation as being outside the scope of legitimate administrative review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s435">Nevertheless I have endeavoured to address each of the issues in accordance with appropriate principles as to administrative review, notwithstanding the extent to which the same involved disputes on the merits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s436">In my opinion, the grounds of the appeal advanced by Mr Rhodes have not been established, and the appeal must be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s437">

 I certify that the preceding seventy-four (74) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Conti.</sentence>
<sentence id="s438">Associate:
Dated: 8 September 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: Dr AJ Greinke 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Thomson Rich O'Connor 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: DS Mortimer SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Deacons Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 27 and 28 April 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 8 September 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1220.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>