<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Westpoint Corporation Pty Ltd (ACN 009 395 751) (includes Corrigendum dated 24 February 2006) [2006] FCA 135 (16 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/135.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">winding up application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">insolvency</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">winding up proceedings commenced by asic</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether one set of liquidators should be appointed to companies which are part of a group of insolvent companies</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">company insolvent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">winding up orders made on insolvency grounds</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">one set of liquidators appointed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 This is an application for the winding up of Westpoint Corporation Pty Ltd ('the company').</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">On 24 January 2006, receivers and managers were appointed to the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">On the same day the sole director of the company, Mr Norman Carey, appointed Mr Ian Francis and Mr Michael Ryan, of Taylor Woodings, as administrators of the company and they have acted as administrators of the company since then.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 The application for winding up is brought by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission ('ASIC').</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The ground upon which the application is brought is that the company is insolvent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The application is supported by the Australian Taxation Office, a major creditor, and is also supported by the receivers and managers of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The administrators do not oppose the making of the winding up order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3 The affidavits which are relied upon by ASIC and the various parties that have been given leave to appear are as follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">ASIC relies upon the affidavits of Mr R Gomm of 19 December 2005, Mr K Chin of 19 December 2005, 23 December 2005 and 20 January 2006, Mr S Mullins of 7 February 2006, Mr D Jackson of 7 February 2006 and the affidavit of Mr J Herbert of 16 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The Deputy Commissioner of Taxation relies upon the affidavits of Ms N Rice of 23 December 2005 and 6 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The receivers and managers of the company rely upon the affidavit of Mr O Zohar of 10 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr O Zohar is one of the receivers and managers of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">4 I have given leave to two companies, North Sydney Finance Limited (In Liquidation) ('North Sydney Finance') and Emu Brewery Mezzanine Limited (In Liquidation) ('Emu Brewery Mezzanine') to appear and make submissions at this hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Mr Jones and Mr Weaver have been appointed as the liquidators of each of the respective companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Each company is one of a number of companies within the Westpoint group of companies, referred to in the papers as mezzanine companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The mezzanine companies are companies that borrowed money from members of the public and on-lent that money to companies within the Westpoint group of companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The mezzanine companies are the beneficiaries of guarantees by the company for the repayment of those loans so that the mezzanine companies, and claim to be creditors of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The liquidators have filed proofs of debt of $12,370,370.40 in respect of North Sydney Finance and $25,288,098.98 in respect of Emu Brewery Mezzanine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">5 The reason why I have given leave for those companies to appear today is because there is a controversy as to who should be appointed as liquidators of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The liquidators of those companies wish to make submissions only in relation to this controversy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">6 The controversy arises because Mr Herbert and Mr Read, with the support of ASIC, have consented to act as liquidators of the company; and the administrators, Mr Francis and Mr Ryan have also indicated that they are prepared to act as liquidators of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Mr Jones and Mr Weaver in their capacity as liquidators of North Sydney Finance and Emu Brewery Mezzanine support the appointment of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan as liquidators of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">They rely upon the affidavits of Mr Jones of 14 February 2006 and two affidavits of Mr Francis dated 9 February 2006 and 15 February 2006, respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">7 There were also notices of intention to appear given by some persons claiming to be creditors to oppose the winding up, but no appearance has been made by those persons today and so no affidavits are read.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">8 Mr Colvin SC, on behalf of ASIC, has asked me to exercise my discretion under s 467(3) of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) to dispense with the requirement under r 5.5(3) of the Federal Court (Corporations) Rules 2000 ('the Corporations Rules'), with respect to the time for the filing and serving of the consent by Mr Herbert and Mr Read to act as liquidators of the company, which was filed and served one day late.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">I will make the order dispensing with compliance with r 5.5(3) of the Corporations Rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">9 There is no opposition to the making of an order winding up the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">On the undisputed evidence of Mr Zohar, the company is what he describes as 'hopelessly insolvent' with an estimated deficit of $451 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">I will, therefore, make orders for the winding up of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">10 It is necessary to now consider the question of who should be appointed as the liquidators of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The relevant evidence in relation to this issue is as follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Mr Herbert and Mr Read are the provisional liquidators of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd, a company which is one of a large number of companies which are related to the company and which are referred to as the Westpoint group of companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">There is evidence from Mr Herbert and Mr Zohar that the affairs of the company are substantially intertwined with the affairs of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd.
 
11 There is also the evidence of Mr Francis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">He has stated that there are at least seven separate loan accounts between the company and Westpoint Management Pty Ltd in its own right and in its capacity as trustee of the 297 Murray Street Trust, the 60 Market Street Trust, the Paragon Apartments Trust, the Warwick Cinema Syndicate Trust, and in its capacity as the responsible entity of two separate managed investment schemes being the Warnbro Fair Syndicate Trust and the Paragon Commercial Syndicate Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Mr Francis goes on to depose that the balance of those loan accounts, as set out in the books and records of the company to which he has had access, appear to be as follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">In its own right, Westpoint Management Pty Ltd is a creditor for $1,010,446.91, the 297 Murray Street Trust is a debtor of $14,358,045.90, the 60 Market Street Trust is a debtor of $16,458,041.56, the Paragon Apartments Trust is a debtor of $324,065.96, the Warwick Cinema Syndicate Trust is a debtor for $20,729.41, the Warnbro Fair Syndicate Trust is a debtor for $1,457,463.85 and the Paragon Commercial Syndicate Trust is a creditor for $954,781.36.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">12 Mr Francis also says that there are some charges which have been given in relation to those debts which may not be valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">13 Further, Mr Francis says that on 3 February 2006 he was approached by Mr Greg Nairn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Mr Greg Nairn said words to him to the effect that, he was the only director of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd, and he was going to apply to Court on 6 February 2006 for the appointment of a provisional liquidator to Westpoint Management Pty Ltd and that he wanted Mr Ryan and Mr Francis to act as provisional liquidators of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd. Mr Francis says that, after having given the matter some consideration, he said to Mr Nairn on 3 February 2006 words to the effect that given the position of the loan accounts between the companies and the issues of the charges, he and Mr Ryan would not be able to accept the appointment because he considered there was a conflict of interest given their role as administrators of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">14 Further, in his evidence, Mr Francis says that his firm, Taylor Woodings, has undertaken a considerable amount of work since the commencement of the administration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">He says that he and his staff have performed in excess of 1000 hours of work in relation to the administration of the company, and he says that in particular, they have spent over 590 hours investigating the affairs of the company, and reporting to the creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Mr Shaw, on behalf of North Sydney Finance and Emu Brewery Mezzanine, has taken me to an annexure to the affidavit of Mr Francis which indicates that the amount of money which is said to be chargeable in respect of those investigations is $153,230.00.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">15 As a consequence of carrying out that work, Mr Francis has produced a draft report to creditors which he has exhibited to his affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">This indicates that a fair amount of work has been done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">However, and significantly, Mr Francis has included the following paragraph in his executive summary of that report.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">At par 2.2 Mr Francis says:
 
 'This report is based on a review conducted of certain books of the Company and files held by Freehills (the Company's legal adviser prior to our appointment) and meetings and discussions with the Company's former senior executives.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Given the limited time since our appointment, the size and complexity of the Westpoint Group, in respect for which the Company acted as a central treasury and conducted most cash transactions, and the books and records being held by the Receivers who have limited our access to the relevant financial information, it has not been possible to conduct a complete review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">As such this report should be considered as a preliminary report of our findings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">A more detailed investigation will be undertaken by the Liquidator, should one be appointed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">' 
 

16 Mr Herbert has said in his affidavit that he has been asked by Mr Jackson of ASIC whether the appointment of Mr Read and himself as liquidators would lead to additional costs to the creditors of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Mr Herbert has said that he believes that the appointment of himself and Mr Read as liquidators will not lead to further costs to the creditors of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">One reason he gives for this view is that if appointed he and Mr Read propose to request the files of Taylor Woodings, the administrators' firm, and use the information on those files.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">He also says that, to the extent that there is a need to undertake work to replicate work undertaken by Taylor Woodings, he undertakes to the Court that he and Mr Read will not seek approval of costs or fees from creditors of the company in respect of this work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">17 Mr Herbert goes on to say that through his limited investigations of the affairs of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd to date:
 
 '...it would appear that the operating systems, document control, management systems, directorships and other matters relating to these to have been undertaken in common.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">I believe that my appointment as liquidator, together with Mr Read, will allow significant synergies to be offered to the creditors, reducing costs of the liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">' 
 

18 I deal now with the submissions of the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">19 Senior Counsel for ASIC, made submissions in support of the appointment of Mr Herbert and Mr Read as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">He submitted that the company is part of a group comprising a large number of companies and Mr Herbert and Mr Read were already in control of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd - another of the companies in the group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">He submitted that a factor which should be taken into account in considering whether to appoint Mr Read and Mr Herbert, is that the affairs of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd and the company are substantially intertwined, and that the on-going investigations would be assisted if there was one set of liquidators in respect of both companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">Further, he submitted that the appointment of the same persons as liquidators to the companies in a group of companies would be more efficient and would reduce the costs of the administration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">It was in the interests of creditors, generally, if expenses were reduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">20 Senior counsel also submitted that there was no real conflict between the roles which Mr Herbert and Mr Read might have to perform as liquidators of the company and as provisional liquidators of Westpoint Management Pty Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">He submitted that the authorities are to the effect that it is desirable that where companies in a group go into liquidation, to the extent that it is possible to do so without there being a real conflict of interest, one liquidator should be appointed to the companies in liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Mr Colvin SC relied upon the following observations of Lehane J in the case of Re Chilia Properties Pty Ltd, (admin apptd) (1997) 154 ALR 179 at 180 ('Chilia') :
 
 '...it is well established that in the absence of any real, as opposed to theoretical, conflict of interest it is generally desirable that the external administration of a group of companies should be placed in the hands of one administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">' 


 
21 Mr Colvin SC further submitted that, where there were dealings within a group of companies between companies that were under the effective control of the same persons, in assessing real conflict, a distinction should be drawn between dealings which affected the interests of external creditors and other external interests, and those which did not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Mr Colvin SC also submitted that it is well accepted that the courts would appoint a single liquidator to a group of companies, notwithstanding that there might be some possible theoretical conflict, on the basis that if a real conflict emerged during the course of the administration, that the liquidator could then make alternative arrangements as to how to deal with the real conflict.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">The fact that there might be a theoretical conflict should not be an inhibition on the appointment of a single liquidator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">22 Further, senior counsel for ASIC, submitted that a relevant consideration to be taken into account is the expressed position of the creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">He said that the secured creditor, represented by the receivers and managers of the company and the Australian Taxation Office both supported the appointment of Mr Herbert and Mr Read as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">23 Mr Colvin SC also acknowledged that in their capacity as administrators Mr Francis and Mr Ryan had carried out work in relation to the affairs of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">However, he said that there is a difference in the nature of the work performed in discharge of the duties of an administrator, and the work that a liquidator would be required to perform.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">He said that a substantial amount of the work which was carried out by Mr Francis and Mr Ryan was in discharge of their duties as administrators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">24 Mr Colvin SC also submitted that the Court should take into account that these administrators were appointed to their position by a director of the company and this could give rise to the spectre of a lack of independence on the part of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">25 Mr Thomson who appeared on behalf of the receivers and managers of the company, also made submissions in support of the appointment of Mr Herbert and Mr Read.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">He said that in the event that there were two sets of liquidators appointed, one to the company and one to Westpoint Management Pty Ltd, the receivers and managers would have to deal with two firms of insolvency practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">This would increase the costs of the receivership with the consequence that on the termination of the receivership there would be less money available to the unsecured creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">He submitted that having different liquidators would result in inefficiencies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">26 Mr Thomson also referred to Sisu Capital Fund Ltd v Tucker [2005] EWHC 2170 (Ch) ('Sisu Capital') particularly at pars 103-115, of the judgment of Warren J, in support of the proposition that courts are not inhibited by the fact that there might be theoretical conflicts, where considering whether to appoint a single liquidator to a number of companies within a group of companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">27 Mr Thomson made the similar arguments to those advanced by Mr Colvin SC against the proposition that because Mr Francis and Mr Ryan had already undertaken work in investigating the affairs of the company, it would be more efficient if they were appointed as the liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">He also submitted that if Mr Francis and Mr Ryan were appointed there might be some suspicion that they were not sufficiently independent of Mr Carey, because Mr Carey had appointed them to the position of administrators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">28 Mr Shaw, for North Sydney Finance and Emu Brewery Mezzanine, made submissions in support of the appointment of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">29 Firstly, he submitted that there could be no perception of lack of independence on the part of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan arising from the fact that they and been appointed as administrators by the sole director of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">He submitted that was a frequent occurrence for administrators who had been appointed by the directors with the object of putting together a deed of company arrangement, subsequently to become liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">He then pointed to the fact that there were already a significant number of insolvency practitioners appointed to the various companies in this group that are in external administration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">30 He also submitted that the appointment of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan would promote efficiency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">He said that much of the work in respect of the investigation of the company's affairs has been done and that there was, therefore, an advantage in appointing the incumbent administrators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">He said that Mr Herbert and Mr Read recognised that if they were appointed they would have to undertake further work to catch up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">He submitted that it would be more efficient to appoint persons who did not have to catch up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">31 I have come to the view that Mr Herbert and Mr Read should be appointed as liquidators for the following reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">32 Firstly, I agree that the observations made by Lehane J in Chilia , referred to above, state the principles to be applied in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">The principles are also reflected in the following observations by Hoffmann J (as he then was) in Re Arrows Ltd [1992] BCC 121, which were cited with approval by Warren J in Sisu Capital :
 
 '...It is by no means uncommon in the case of the insolvency of a substantial group of companies for cross-claims and conflicts of interest to arise between companies within the group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">That does not usually deflect the court from appointing a single firm of insolvency practitioners in the first instance to deal with the whole insolvency of the group, leaving the question of potential conflict of interests to be dealt with if and when it arises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">' 
 
 
 
 

33 I accept the arguments advanced by Mr Colvin SC and Mr Thomson that in the situation where there is no obvious and real conflict but there is a possibility of a theoretical conflict, a court should not thereby be inhibited from appointing a single set of liquidators when that would advance the efficiency of the liquidation, and result in fewer fees being charged in respect of the liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">34 I am not satisfied that on the evidence that is before me that there is any real conflict in the sense that that concept is recognised in the cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">There is no evidence the appointment of Mr Herbert and Mr Read to the position of liquidators of the company would adversely affect the interests of external creditors or other external interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The evidence of Mr Francis as to the inter-relationship between Westpoint Management Pty Ltd and the company does not demonstrate any such prejudice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">35 I am also confident that in the event that any real conflict does emerge that the liquidators will approach the Court and seek directions in relation to how to deal with that conflict, as is foreshadowed in the authorities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">36 Secondly, as to the question of the extent of work that has already been done, I accept that the administrators have done some good work in relation to the investigation of the affairs of the company as is evidenced by the draft report to creditors of 13 February 2006, exhibited to the affidavit of Mr Francis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">However, as is recognised in that document itself, the amount of work which will be required to be done in the conduct of a liquidation of this size and of this complexity would be substantially more than has already been done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Therefore, the fact that there has been some work done in investigating the affairs of the company, does not, in my view, operate as a decisive factor in favour of appointing the administrators as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">37 Further, the position that is deposed to by Mr Herbert in his affidavit that no fees will be claimed in relation to any catching up, operates as a significant factor to counter any concerns relating to any duplication of work that may arise from appointing Mr Herbert and Mr Read as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">In my view, the synergies which will be achieved by appointing them as liquidators to the company outweigh any difficulties that might be associated with any catching up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">38 Thirdly, I accept that whilst the expressed views of the creditors are not decisive they should be taken in to account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">In this case, however, there are some creditors who opposed the appointment of Mr Herbert and Mr Read, and some who favoured it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Accordingly, I do not regard this factor as a decisive factor in my determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">39 Finally, it was submitted that Mr Francis and Mr Ryan should not be appointed because, having been appointed by Mr Carey, there would be a perception of lack of independence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">I do not take that factor into account because I do not accept that submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">I accept the submission of Mr Shaw that it is often the case that administrators are appointed as liquidators, notwithstanding that they are initially appointed as administrators by the directors of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">There is no evidence before me which could cause me to question the independence of Mr Francis and Mr Ryan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">40 I will make orders in terms of the minute of orders provided to me by ASIC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">I certify that the preceding forty (40) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Siopis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">Associate:

Dated: 23 February 2006


 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr C G Colvin SC 
 
 Solicitors for the Plaintiff: Australian Securities and Investments Commission 
 
 Counsel for the Defendant: Mr J A Thomson 
 
 Solicitors for the Defendant: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation: Ms E Chong 
 
 Solicitors for the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation: Australian Taxation Office 
 
 Counsel for North Sydney Finance Limited (In Liquidation) and Emu Brewery Mezzanine Limited (In Liquidation): Mr D B Shaw 
 
 Solicitors for North Sydney Finance Limited (In Liquidation) and Emu Brewery Mezzanine Limited (In Liquidation): Shaw &amp; Associates 
 
 Counsel for the Administrators: Mr A R Beech SC 
 
 Solicitors for the Administrators: Tottle Partners 
 
 Date of Hearing: 16 February 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 16 February 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/135.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>