<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Vans, Inc. v Offprice.Com.Au Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 137 (22 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/137.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for leave to appeal against decision of docket judge refusing an application to enter summary judgment in favour of applicant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">no prima facie defence shown on the evidence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether summary judgment ought to be refused where a respondent merely seeks to put applicant to proof of its case</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">significance of recent enactment of s 31a of federal court of australia act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">effect of the formula 'no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding'</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">application for leave to appeal granted.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 WILCOX J: 
 
 1 This is an application for leave to appeal against a decision of Finkelstein J, made on 3 February 2006, dismissing an application for summary judgment against one of four respondents, in respect of all of whom the applicant made allegations of infringement of trademark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">That respondent is the second respondent, Marjory Pty Limited ('Marjory').</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I understand the applicant is likely to discontinue its action against the other respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 The action concerns shoes that bear the applicant's trademark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">There was evidence before Finkelstein J that the shoes are counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That evidence came in an affidavit made by Larry Bendo Anastacio, an employee of a company associated with the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Mr Anastacio set out his experience in detecting counterfeit 'Vans' products and gave detailed reasons why, in his opinion, the subject shoes are counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3 There was no evidence contradicting Mr Anastacio's opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">However, the third respondent, Michael Wagner, who was concerned, at least at one stage, with the management of Marjory, said the shoes were purchased from a business in Hong Kong, Warner Shop Limited ('Warner'), which he believed to be authorised to sell Vans footwear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Mr Wagner said he believed the goods were 'genuine footwear made by or under the authority of the Applicant'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">4 There was also some evidence of a hearsay nature, but admitted by his Honour, that a paralegal, employed by the respondents' solicitors, telephoned Warner in Hong Kong and was told that, for the past two years or so, Warner had been selling Vans products which were purchased from Joint Power International Limited ('Joint Power'), an authorised Vans dealer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The paralegal then rang Joint Power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">She was told that Joint Power was an authorised distributor of Vans products, and that Warner Shop was one of the clients to whom it supplied Vans products.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 As was submitted by Mr D Shavin QC, who appeared with Ms M Barker on behalf of the applicant for leave, this evidence does not provide a defence to the claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">However, it shows a provenance of the shoes that is consistent with the possibility that they are not counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Of course, it would be possible for an authorised dealer also to sell counterfeit goods.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">There is no material to say whether this happened in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The point made by Mr B Fitzpatrick, counsel for Marjory, is that this is a matter requiring investigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">6 In reasons for judgment delivered on 3 February 2006, Finkelstein J mentioned the recently enacted s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Subsection (1) of that section reads as follows:
 
 'The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if: 
 
 (a) the first party is prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and 
 (b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">' 


 
7 Mr Shavin referred me to several cases in which members of this Court have entered summary judgment in favour of applicants claiming trademark infringement on the basis of, similar evidence to that of Mr Anastacio.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Typically, such evidence involves a person familiar with the particular applicant's products inspecting the subject goods and offering an opinion that they are counterfeit, for reasons then expressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">It was put to me that this case raises an important question of principle: whether the Court should continue to apply the approach taken in those cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 It is important to remember that every application for summary judgment must be determined on its own merits and according to the facts of the particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">No two cases are factually identical; although, no doubt, it was correct for Mr Shavin to say that solicitors who regularly act for trademark owners tend to file similar affidavits in each case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">9 Finkelstein J was unhappy about the decisiveness of the evidence put before him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">He did not say Mr Anastacio's evidence should be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">At para 20 of his judgment, Finkelstein J expressly said he did not doubt that Mr Anastacio believes the goods he inspected were counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">However, his Honour added:
 
 '... he did not produce original Vans shoes so that I myself could undertake the comparison (if needs be, assisted by the witness) and so determine the correctness of his evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">I think this is a matter that should be investigated at a trial rather than relying on the applicant's untested evidence, especially in a situation where there is some possibility that the goods are not counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">' 


 
10 I have sympathy with the view expressed by Finkelstein J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">There is much to be said for the principle that a party, against whom proceedings are taken, is entitled to its/his/her day in court to test that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The principles in force before the enactment of s 31A would, I think, have required the rejection of a summary judgment application in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It is sufficient for me to refer to authorities such as Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">11 The strength of the application for leave to appeal is, in my view, the recent enactment of s 31A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">There is a real question as to the effect of the formula, 'the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">It can rarely be said there is no prospect of a party successfully defending a proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">There is almost always a possibility that the case of the party bearing the onus of proof will break down at trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">If s 31A is to be construed so as to exclude summary judgment where there is only this possibility, then, as Mr Shavin says, it is difficult to see the point of its enactment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Also, it should be borne in mind that subs (3) of s 31A goes on to say that:
 
 'For the purposes of this section, a defence or a proceeding or part of a proceeding need not be: 
 (a) hopeless; or 
 (b) bound to fail; 
 for it to have no reasonable prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">' 


 
12 It seems to me it is, at least, arguable that the effect of s 31A is that there can be summary judgment for an applicant, notwithstanding the possibility that the applicant's case will break down at trial; in other words, it is now not enough for a party resisting a summary judgment application to seek merely to put the other side to proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">If that view is correct, there is a firm basis for believing that Finkelstein J may have overlooked the significance of the new section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">13 In fairness to his Honour, I repeat that he did mention s 31A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">He set out its terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">However, he seems not to have put to himself the statutory question: whether he was satisfied that Marjory has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Had he asked himself that question, he would have been able to answer it in the negative only by saying there was a possibility that the applicant's case would break down.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Such an answer would then have raised the question whether that it is now enough.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">14 My mind has fluctuated in relation to the fate of this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">As a general principle, judges should not give leave to appeal in relation to a pre-trial ruling by a docket judge on a matter of practice and procedure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">His Honour has made directions designed to facilitate a trial in April.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Particularly in the case of a trial that is expected to be short (as in this case), it is usually preferable to bring on the trial, rather than to have appeals about summary judgement and strike out applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Moreover, if leave to appeal is granted, it will be necessary, in order to avoid the trial coming on before the appeal, for there to be a stay of the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Judges should not lightly interfere with the orderly handling of another judge's docket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">It should not be enough that the judge hearing the leave application feels doubt about the wisdom or legal correctness of the docket judge's order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">There ought to be something more.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">In this case, there is something more.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">I have been persuaded, not only that there is sufficient doubt about the application of s 31A , in his Honour's approach, for me to conclude that it is at least fairly arguable that he fell into legal error, but also that the case has some general significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">There is a real question as to whether (and if so how) the new section affects the approach previously taken by judges of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">So far as I am aware, this would be the first occasion on which a Full Court would have had the opportunity of considering that matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">Given the number of applications for summary judgment made in this Court, it seems desirable that there be early consideration of the section at a Full Court level.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Accordingly, I have decided to accede to the application and grant leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">15 It follows that I should also order that the directions given by Finkelstein J on 17 February 2006 be stayed, pending determination of the appeal or earlier order of a judge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The appropriate order in regard to the costs of this application is that they be costs in the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">I certify that the preceding fifteen (15) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Wilcox.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">Associate:

Dated: 7 March 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr D Shavin QC with Ms M Barker 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr B Fitzpatrick 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: W Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 22 February 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 February 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/137.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>