<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Microsoft Corporation v RP Distribution Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1842 (22 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1842.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for default judgment pursuant to o 35a</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">respondents failed to enter appearance, file defence and appear at directions hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">application allowed.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">copyright</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 In this matter, I have read the submissions of the applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">I note that there has been repeated default by both respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I have also had regard to the correspondence and emails in the history of the proceeding and, having considered the affidavits that are before me, I consider it appropriate to make orders in terms of the short minutes of order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 So far as the question of additional damages is concerned, there has been no opportunity to ventilate this and, in the circumstances, I am prepared to award half the amount of the compensatory damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">In reaching this conclusion, I have taken into account the fact that substantial costs have been incurred and will be the liability of the respondents under the orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 Accordingly, I make orders in accordance with the short minutes, except that in relation to the issue of additional damages, I award half of the compensatory damages sought which equates to an amount of $15, 047.50.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">
 
 I certify that the preceding three (3) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tamberlin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Associate:

Dated: 24 January 2007


 Counsel for the Applicants: P W Flynn 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicants: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 No appearance on behalf of the Respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Date of Hearing: 22 December 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 December 2006 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1842.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>