<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Eastlands Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1702 (6 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1702.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">insolvency</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">winding up</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">failure to comply with statutory demands</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">presumption of insolvency</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">members of inter-company group</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">evidence by common director of financial arrangements within inter-company group</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">insufficient to displace presumption</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">winding up orders made</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">appointment of liquidators as receivers of assets of trusts of trustee companies</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 Introduction 
 
1 By an application filed on 29 June 2006 the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC) applied for the winding up of thirteen companies in the Westpoint Property and Finance Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application was based upon the failure by the companies to comply with statutory demands issued by the receivers and managers of Westpoint Corporation Ltd (Westpoint Corporation) in respect of the amounts of loans said to be owing by each of them to that company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 Failure to comply with a statutory demand gives rise to a presumption of insolvency and in winding up proceedings based on such failure the presumption operates except so far as the contrary is proved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 In addition to demonstrating non-compliance with the statutory demands, ASIC has adduced evidence about the financial circumstances of each of the companies so far as that appears from accounting records of the Westpoint Group to which ASIC has had access.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">That evidence does not displace the presumption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">In addition, oral evidence was given by Mr Carey, the common director of each of the companies to the general effect that the financial records relied upon by ASIC were not complete.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Mr Carey's principal contention was that there were unrecorded offsets in favour of various of the respondent companies against their loan accounts with Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">His evidence, however, did not do more than raise possibilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">It certainly did not displace the presumption flowing from the failure to comply with the statutory demands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The Court is obliged to give effect to that presumption by the provisions of the Corporations Act 2001(Cth) (the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">4 In the circumstances, ASIC will be granted the necessary leave to make the applications and winding up orders will be made against each of the respondent companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">In respect of those companies which are the trustees of trusts identified in the ASIC evidence, the liquidators will also be appointed as receivers of the trust assets subject to liberty to the receivers and any beneficiaries of the trusts to apply for directions relating to the exercise of the receivers' powers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">ASIC has leave to amend its application for the purpose of seeking the orders for the appointment of receivers to the trusts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Procedural background 
 
5 On 29 June 2006 ASIC filed an application in which it sought orders for the winding up of each of the thirteen respondent companies in insolvency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The application was brought under Pt 5.4 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">An application of this kind can be made under s 459P of the Act by ASIC but only with the leave of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The Court must be satisfied, before giving leave, that there is a prima facie case that the company the subject of the winding up application is insolvent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">In this case the contention that the companies are insolvent is based upon a statutory presumption flowing from their non-compliance with statutory demands for the payment of moneys said to be owing to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">6 It is not in dispute that, on instructions from Oren Zohar of KordaMentha, a receiver and manager of Westpoint Corporation, statutory demands under s 459E of the Act were served on the first to twelfth respondents on 10 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">A statutory demand was served on the thirteenth respondent on 15 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">In each case the demand was supported by an affidavit verifying that the amount of the debt claimed was due and owing by the company to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">7 The verifying affidavits depended upon examination of the books and records of Westpoint Corporation by Mr Zohar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The amounts said to be owing in each case were as follows: 
Eastlands Pty Ltd $3,612,913.02
Goldtag Pty Ltd $ 567,962.32
Westpoint Money Management Pty Ltd $1,999,867.80
Asset Build (Aust) Pty Ltd $ 249,244.18
Cinema City Development Pty Ltd $1,223,314.75
Westpoint Consulting Group Pty Ltd $ 172,525.16
Jetstone Pty Ltd $ 22,302.14
Network Company Pty Ltd $1,277,606.59
Pagelight Nominees Pty Ltd $ 55,800.65
Kingdream Pty Ltd $ 874,142.45
Juson Pty Ltd $ 18,357.60
Bridgeview Holdings Pty Ltd $1,297,256.94
Westside Brisbane Development Pty Ltd $ 123,939.16

The demands were not satisfied and no applications made to set any of them aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The verifying affidavits did not set out the transaction or transactions which gave rise to the debt but in each case the deponent, Karen Price, stated her belief that there was no genuine dispute about its existence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">According to the affidavit of Mr Zohar, sworn 21 November 2006, there had, at that date, been no response to the statutory demands and as of that date the amount of the debts remained due and payable to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">8 The respondents were represented, on the hearing of the winding up application, by Norman Carey their common director who was given leave to represent them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Mr Carey had applied to strike out the application in August 2006 on the basis that it was invalid for failure to comply with s 459Q of the Act which requires verification, by affidavit, of the currency of the debts at the time of the making of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">On 16 August 2001 that motion was dismissed --- Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Eastlands Pty Ltd (No 1) [2006] FCA 1101.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Other interlocutory orders refusing leave to issue certain subpoenas and requiring ASIC to provide a list of documents in its possession relevant to the question of solvency were made on the same day --- Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Eastlands Pty Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1193.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">9 At the commencement of the substantive hearing counsel appeared for the respondents and applied for an adjournment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">That application was refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Counsel, whose instructions were limited to the application for an adjournment, then withdrew and Mr Carey represented the respondent companies in person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">10 At the hearing ASIC relied upon a number of affidavits including those of Oren Zohar and ASIC investigators, Kevin Chin and Richard Gomm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It also relied upon the affidavit of Wendy Chan, formerly an assistant accountant with Westpoint Corporation and David McEvoy, a partner in PricewaterhouseCoopers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The affidavits went variously to the records of intragroup debts in the books of Westpoint Corporation, the financial position of the respondents as disclosed in computer databases held by Westpoint Corporation, the way in which the accounting system operated, the service of the relevant statutory demands and of the originating process and supporting affidavits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">There were no affidavits relied upon by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">However Mr Carey gave oral evidence at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">11 At the commencement of the hearing Mr Carey indicated that he did not wish to contest the application so far as it related to the following companies: 
Goldtag Pty Ltd 
Westpoint Money Management Pty Ltd
Asset Build (Aust) Pty Ltd
Cinema City Development Pty Ltd
Network Company Pty Ltd
Kingdream Pty Ltd

In each of these uncontested cases the service and lack of satisfaction of the relevant statutory demand established a presumption of insolvency under s 459C(2) of the Act and thereby the prima facie case necessary to warrant the grant of leave to ASIC, under s 459P, to make these applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The evidence, together with the presumption, was thereby sufficient to support the winding up orders sought by ASIC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Statutory framework 
 
12 Part 5.4 of the Act deals with winding up in insolvency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Section 459A provides that, on an application under s 459P, the Court may order that "... an insolvent company be wound up in insolvency".</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">13 The concept of solvency is defined in s 95A of the Act which provides: 
 
 '(1) A person is solvent if, and only if, the person is able to pay all the person's debts, as and when they become due and payable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 
 (2) A person who is not solvent is insolvent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">' 
 

14 Section 459C provides for presumptions to be made in certain proceedings and relevantly to the present purpose they are as follows: 
 
 '(1) This section has effect for the purposes of: 
 
 (a) an application under section 234, 459P, 462 or 464; or 
 
 (b) an application for leave to make an application under section 459P.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">
 
 (2) The Court must presume that the company is insolvent if, during or after the 3 months ending on the day when the application was made: 
 
 
 
 (a) the company failed (as defined by section 459F) to comply with a statutory demand; or 
 ... 
 
 
 
 (3) A presumption for which this section provides operates except so far as the contrary is proved for the purposes of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">' 
 

15 Section 459P identifies the parties who may apply to the Court for a company to be wound up in insolvency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">These include ASIC (s 459P(1)(f)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">By s 459P(2) an application by ASIC may only be made with the leave of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">A condition of such leave is that the Court be "... satisfied that there is a prima facie case that the company is insolvent,..." (s 459P(3)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">That leave may be given subject to conditions (s 459P(4)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">16 Section 459F of the Act sets out the circumstances in which a company is taken to fail to comply with the statutory demand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">It provides: 
 
 '(1) If, as at the end of the period for compliance with a statutory demand, the demand is still in effect and the company has not complied with it, the company is taken to fail to comply with the demand at the end of that period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">
 
 (2) The period for compliance with a statutory demand is: 
 
 
 
 (a) if the company applies in accordance with section 459G for an order setting aside the demand: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) if, on hearing the application under section 459G, or on an application by the company under this paragraph, the Court makes an order that extends the period for compliance with the demand --- the period specified in the order, or in the last such order, as the case requires, as the period for such compliance; or 
 
 (ii) otherwise --- the period beginning on the day when the demand is served and ending 7 days after the application under section 459G is finally determined or otherwise disposed of; or 
 
 (b) otherwise --- 21 days after the demand is served.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">' 
 
 
 

17 Section 459Q deals with the formal requirements for an application relying upon failure to comply with a statutory demand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">This section provides: 
 
 'If an application for a company to be wound up in insolvency relies on a failure by the company to comply with a statutory demand, the application: 
 
 
 
 (a) must set out particulars of service of the demand on the company and of the failure to comply with the demand; and 
 
 (b) must have attached to it: 
 
 (i) a copy of the demand; and 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) if the demand has been varied by an order under subsection 459H(4) --- a copy of the order; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) unless the debt, or each of the debts, to which the demand relates is a judgment debt --- must be accompanied by an affidavit that: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) verifies that the debt, or the total of the amounts of the debts, is due and payable by the company; and 
 (ii) complies with the rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">' 
 
 
 

18 Section 459R requires an application for a company to be wound up in insolvency to be determined within six months after it is made, albeit the Court may by order extend the period within which an application must be determined but only if it is satisfied that special circumstances justify that extension and the order is made within the relevant six month period, or the last extension thereof (s 459R(2)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The time limited by this section expires on 29 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">19 Section 459S limits the grounds upon which a company may oppose an application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">It provides: 
 
 '(1) In so far as an application for a company to be wound up in insolvency relies on a failure by the company to comply with a statutory demand, the company may not, without the leave of the Court, oppose the application on a ground: 
 
 
 
 (a) that the company relied on for the purposes of an application by it for the demand to be set aside; or 
 
 (b) that the company could have so relied on, but did not so rely on (whether it made such an application or not).</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">
 
 
 
 (2) The Court is not to grant leave under subsection (1) unless it is satisfied that the ground is material to proving that the company is solvent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">' 
 

20 Division 5 of the Court's Corporations Law Rules govern winding up proceedings including applications under Pt 5.4 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Rule 5.3 provides: 
 
 'An application for leave to apply to the Court for an order that a company be wound up in insolvency may be made at the same time as the application for an order that the company be wound up in insolvency is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">' 
 

Rule 5.4 sets out the requirements for an affidavit in support of an application for winding up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Where the application is made in reliance on a failure by the company to comply with a statutory demand, the affidavit must: 
 
 
 
 '(a) verify service of the demand on the company; 
 
 (b) verify the failure of the company to comply with the demand; and 
 
 (c) state whether and, if so, to what extent the debt, or each of the debts, to which the demand relates is still due and payable by the company at the date when the affidavit is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">' 
 
 

21 Rule 5.5 provides for the filing of the consent of an official liquidator who would be entitled to be appointed as liquidator of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Rule 5.6 requires notice of the application for the winding up order to be published.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Procedural irregularity in originating process 
 
22 Where an application for the winding up of a company in insolvency relies upon the failure by the company to comply with a statutory demand the application is required by s 459Q to: 
 
 (a) set out particulars of service of the demand on the company and of the failure to comply with the demand; and 
 (b) have attached to it: 
 (i) a copy of the demand; 
 
 
 (ii) if the demand has been varied by an order under subs 459H(4) --- a copy of the order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">
 

The application is also required to be accompanied by an affidavit verifying that the debt or the total of the amounts of the debts is due and payable by the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">23 Section C of the application set out particulars of service of the demand on each of the respondents as required by s 459Q(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">It also asserted the failure of each to pay the amounts of the debt demanded or to secure or compound for that amount to the reasonable satisfaction of the receivers and managers of Westpoint Corporation within 21 days after the demands were served on the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">These particulars were stated globally thus: 
 
 
 '2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The demands and accompanying affidavits were served by Alex McLean, a Senior Associate at Corrs Chambers Westgarth, who delivered them to the registered office of the respondents at Level 9, 160 St George's Terrace, Perth in the State of Western Australia on 15 March 2006 in relation to the thirteenth respondent and on 10 March 2006 in relation to the other respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">A copy of each of the demands and the accompanying affidavits, marked "A" to "M", are attached to this originating process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Each respondent failed to pay the amounts of the debt demanded or to secure or compound for that amount to the reasonable satisfaction of the receivers and managers of Westpoint Corporation Pty Ltd within 21 days after the demands were served on the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">' 
 
 

24 Contrary to the requirements of s 459Q(b) the application did not have the statutory demands and affidavits attached.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">However at the time it was served it was accompanied by the affidavits of Oren Zohar and Alexander Jason McLean, sworn 29 June 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Each of those affidavits annexed copies of the demands and accompanying affidavits as annexures "OZ1" to "OZ13" and "AM1" to "AM13" respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The omission to attach the relevant demands to the application was obviously the result of oversight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">At the time of service each of the respondent companies received two copies of each demand and affidavit as annexures to the affidavits of Zohar and McLean.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">25 In Lavercombe v Auscott Ltd [2006] NSWSC 867 ; (2006) 58 ACSR 586, Barrett J said (at [6]): 
 
 'As to the apparent non-compliance with s 459Q(b)(i), it cannot be contended that it caused the application to be a nullity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">In circumstances where the necessary document was in fact annexed to the supporting affidavit rather than the contemporaneously filed originating process, the non-compliance was a "defect or irregularity in connection with the application" as referred to in s 467A(a) and, since no injustice could conceivably have been occasioned, the court was bound by s 467A not to dismiss the application merely because of the non-compliance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">' 
 

26 In this case ASIC submits that no injustice could conceivably have been occasioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">If there were substantial injustice the time to raise it was at the time of the application to strike out the proceedings for failing to comply with s 459Q of the Act made on 16 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">That application went to the sufficiency of the backing affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">I accept that this is a case in which there is no substantial injustice arising from non-compliance with s 459Q(b)(i) and on that basis will entertain the application notwithstanding the non-compliance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">27 In so doing I apply s 467A which provides:
 
 'An application under Part 5.4 or 5.4A must not be dismissed merely because of one or more of the following: 
 
 
 
 (a) in any case --- a defect or irregularity in connection with the application; 
 
 (b) in the case of an application for a company to be wound up in insolvency --- a defect in a statutory demand; 
 
 
 
 Unless the Court is satisfied that substantial injustice has been caused that cannot otherwise be remedied (for example, by an adjournment or an order for costs).</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">' 
 

Having regard to s 467A it is unnecessary to make any order under s 1322(4) as was also suggested by ASIC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">ASIC's evidence 
 
28 The submissions by ASIC outlined the evidence upon which it relies in relation to each of the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">The factual outline in its submissions, with respect to each of the respondents, was supported by reference to the relevant parts of the affidavits filed in support of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">It is convenient to refer to that outline in respect of each of the contested applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">It is not necessary to repeat individually the reference to the basis upon which the debts were asserted, the service of the statutory demands, the non-compliance with those demands and the currency of the relevant debts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Eastlands Pty Ltd (Eastlands)
 
29 Eastlands has two issued shares, one held by Heca Nominees Pty Ltd (Heca) and the other by Mr Carey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Mr Carey is the company's only director.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">30 Eastlands is trustee of the Eastlands Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The computer database containing the financial records of Westpoint Corporation and associated companies was kept on a "Triumph" accounting system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">According to Mr Richard Gomm, an ASIC investigator, who examined records obtained by ASIC from that system in relation to Eastlands, its business records are almost exclusively concerned with its role as trustee of the Eastlands Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">The records relating to the Trust, as appears from Mr Gomm's affidavit of 16 October 2006, indicate that: 
 
 (a) Eastlands Unit Trust earned no income and incurred expenses leaving a net loss before tax of $4,417.50 for the seven months to 31 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">(b) At 31 January 2006 the Eastlands Unit Trust had: 
 (i) net liabilities of $761.68 by way of a bank overdraft or debit; 
 (ii) non-current assets comprising: 
 an investment in land at Innamincka Road $178,000
 motor vehicles and office equipment $270,000
 a loan to the Quartz Trust $3,714,295
 loans to various Westpoint subsidiaries and related trusts
 (iii) current liabilities of: 
 Westpoint Corporation $3,594,000
 Bowesco Pty Ltd (Bowesco) for the Dyson Family Trust $216,650
 (iv) non-current liabilities of $96,440;
 (v) net negative assets of $220,460.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">

31 ASIC relied upon company information for Quartz Nominees Pty Ltd (Quartz Nominees) which is the trustee of the Quartz Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">It submitted that the value of Eastland's loan to Quartz Nominees ought to be discounted entirely as the largest asset of Quartz Nominees was its right to indemnity from the trust assets which were in the form of loans to businesses or investments in shares in other companies and units in trusts in the Westpoint Property and Finance Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">These had not been made available and were unlikely to be made available to assist Eastlands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">Westpoint Consulting Group Pty Ltd (Westpoint Consulting Group)
 
32 The Westpoint Consulting Group has two issued shares, one held by Heca and the other by Mr Carey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">Mr Carey is its sole director.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">33 The company is the trustee of the Westpoint Consulting Group Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">The most recent accounts for the company related to the period ending 30 June 2003 and showed that it earned no income and incurred no expenses but held $2 contributed capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">It had trust liabilities of $165,477.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">As with Eastlands, the business records of the company related exclusively to its role as trustee of the Westpoint Consulting Group Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">34 Mr Gomm set out the result of examination of the Triumph accounting system for the Westpoint Consulting Group Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">This indicated: 
 
 (a) For seven months to 31 January 2006 the company earned no income and incurred no expenses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">It had accumulated losses for prior periods of $161,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">(b) As at 31 January 2006 the Unit Trust had: 
 (i) cash on deposit of $2,497.57;
 (ii) non-current assets comprising loans to Quartz Trust of $712,000; 
 (iii) current liabilities to Westpoint Corporation $172,500;
 (iv) no non-current liabilities; 
 (v) net positive assets of $539,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">


ASIC relied upon information about Quartz Nominees, the Quartz Trust Deed and Triumph system records relating to the Quartz Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">It submitted that, as in the case of money owing to Eastlands, the value of the company's loan to the Quartz Trust ought to be entirely discounted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">35 Westpoint Consulting Group had also executed guarantees and indemnities in favour of a number of so called Mezzanine finance companies associated with the Westpoint Finance and Property Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">The guarantees related to borrowings from other companies within the Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The relevant Mezzanine companies are in liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">The relevant debtor companies are under external administration in that receivers or liquidators have been appointed save for Cinema City Development which, as already noted, is one of the respondents to these proceedings which is not contested in the winding up application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">The debts of the debtor companies to the Mezzanine finance companies were due and owing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">The Triumph system accounting information for the debtor companies acknowledged their obligations to the Mezzanine finance companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">The liquidators of the Mezzaine companies had issued notices, under the loan agreements, to the debtor companies that the loans were immediately due and payable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">They have also issued demands to Westpoint Consulting Group and other guarantors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">The demands against Westpoint Consulting Group exceed $287 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">36 On 7 April 2006 Westpoint Consulting Group sent a letter indicating that no payment would be made on its behalf under the guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">It gave three reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">The first was that the guarantees were uncommercial transactions and were voidable under s 588FE of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">The second reason was that they did not provide a requisite commercial benefit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">The third reason was that they were limited to the amount of the loan agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">The solicitors for the Mezzanine finance companies have not accepted these contentions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">ASIC points out that even if confined to the loan agreements, the debt recoverable under the guarantees would be $80 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">The guarantors of the same debtor companies have not paid the demands received.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">According to the Triumph system accounting information the other guarantors are unlikely to be in a position to meet those demands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">Jetstone Pty Ltd (Jetstone)
 
37 Jetstone has two shares issued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">One is held by Bowesco.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">The other is held by Tarlina Pty Ltd. Norman Carey is the only director of Jetstone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">38 Jetstone is the trustee of the Jetstone Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Its business records relate almost exclusively to its role as trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">According to the Triumph system accounting information the financial position of the Trust as at 31 January 2006 was as follows: 
 
 (a) For the seven months to 31 January 2006 the Jetstone Trust earned no income and incurred expenses leaving a net loss before tax of $7,875.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">(b) As at 31 January 2006 the Trust had approximately: 
 (i) current assets of $232,766 constituted largely by deposits;
 (ii) no other significant non-current assets; 
 (iii) current liabilities of:
 Westpoint Corporation $22,300
 Bowesco for the Dyson Family Trust $232,666
 (iv) no non-current liabilities; 
 (v) net negative assets of $21,214.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Pagelight Nominees Pty Ltd (Pagelight Nominees) 

39 Pagelight Nominees has issued one share which is held by Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">Norman Carey is its only director.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">40 The Triumph system accounting information for Pagelight Nominees indicates the following, according to the affidavit of Mr Gomm sworn 16 October 2006: 
 
 (a) For seven months to 31 January 2006 Pagelight Nominees earned income and incurred expenses, leaving a net profit before tax of $37,761.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">(b) As at 31 January 2006 Pagelight Nominees had approximately:
 (i) cash on deposit of $8,475.69 at a bank account and trade creditors of $4,400;
 (ii) no non-current assets; 
 (iii) current liabilities of: 
 Westpoint Corporation $62,757
 other debts $1,243
 GST $15,920
 (iv) no non-current assets; 
 (v) net negative assets of $65,800.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">

41 It appears from the general ledger that Pagelight Nominees operated as an agent for members of the Westpoint Group to arrange printing and publishing needs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">Apart from a very small number of external clients it was reliant upon Westpoint Corporation which is now in receivership and in liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">Juson Pty Ltd (Juson)
 
42 Juson has two issued shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">Both are held by Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">It has two directors, Norman Carey and his sister, Karen Carey-Hazell.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Juson is the trustee of the Juson Unit Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">Its business records relate almost exclusively to its role as trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">43 According to the affidavit of Mr Gomm sworn 16 October 2006 the Triumph system accounting information for the Juson Unit Trust indicates the following: 
 
 (a) For the seven months to 31 January 2006 the Trust earned no income and incurred no expenses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">(b) As at 31 January 2006 the Trust had approximately: 
 (i) cash on deposit of $60 at a bank account; 
 (ii) no other non-current assets; 
 (iii) current liabilities of: 
 Westpoint Corporation $18,358
 Eastlands for the Eastlands Trust $1,074
 Quartz Nominees for the Quartz Trust $20,950
 (iv) no non-current liabilities; 
 (v) net negative assets of $39,234.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Bridgeview Holdings Pty Ltd (Bridgeview) 

44 Bridgeview has two issued shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">One is held by Heca Nominees Pty Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">The other is held by Mr Carey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">The company has two directors who are Mr Carey and his sister, Karen Carey-Hazell.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Bridgeview is the trustee of the Bridgeview Family Trust.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">Again, its business records relate almost exclusively to its role as trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">45 According to Mr Gomm's affidavit of 16 October 2006, the Triumph system accounting information for the Bridgeview Family Trust indicates the following: 
 
 (a) For seven months to 31 January 2006 Bridgeview Family Trust earned no income and incurred no expenses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">(b) As at 31 January 2006 the Trust had approximately:
 (i) cash on deposit of $10 at a bank account; 
 (ii) non-current assets being:
 formation expenses $12,000 
 loan to Matheson Holdings $4,226,881
 loan to Benalong Holdings $8,847,320
 (iii) current liabilities of:
 Westpoint Corporation $1,297,256
 Matheson Trust $900,934
 Eastlands Trust $445.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">(iv) non-current liabilities: 
 deferred income $10,901,449
 (v) net negative assets of $13,919.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">Westside Brisbane Developments Pty Ltd ( Westside Brisbane Developments) 

46 Westside Brisbane Developments has two issued shares held by Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">Mr Carey is its sole director.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">47 The Triumph system accounting information for Westside Brisbane Developments indicates the following: 
 
 (a) For seven months to 31 January 2006 Westside Brisbane Developments earned no income and incurred no expenses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">(b) As at 31 January 2006 the company had approximately: 
 
 
 (i) non-current assets represented almost exclusively by work in progress related to "Westside" of $12,672 and a small GST credit;
 (ii) current liabilities of: 
 Westpoint Corporation $13,939.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">(iii) no other non-current liabilities;
 (iv) no equity as the assets equalled the liabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">
 


According to Mr Gomm's affidavit, Westside Brisbane Developments entered a "put and call option" with Ozton Pty Ltd to purchase property at 36 Duncan Street, West End, Brisbane by paying the fees and calling for the property by the call option expiry date, which was 20 September 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">The Triumph system accounting information indicates that the fees were not paid and the option was not exercised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">The property continues to be owned by Fibre Containers (Queensland) Pty Ltd. 

 Mr Carey's evidence 
 
48 Mr Carey gave oral evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">He described himself as the Group Managing Director for the Westpoint Group and said he is a director of each of the respondent companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">The Group has been in existence since about 1985.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">He is a certified practising accountant and has held that qualification for about 20 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">49 Mr Carey began by describing what he called the business model under which the Westpoint Group operated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">The Group operated its business "across a value chain".</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">Westpoint Corporation "provided central services ...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">It charged significant fees against development projects carried out by the Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">It would also engage the services of service providing businesses within the Group to carry out various aspects of project development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">50 Mr Carey contended that ASIC's evidence was not based upon financial accounts but what were in effect "general ledger printouts".</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">ASIC had taken intragroup loan amounts from the general ledgers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">He said: 
 
 'General ledgers are in fact in the accounting process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">You start with journals, post ledgers to a trial balance, and then you produce financial, statements being the profit and loss and balance sheet ...'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">
 

The general ledger was a reflection of a trial balance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">Within the Group there was a business unit called Group Financial Control that oversaw all the accounting, administration and financial functions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">The Group Financial Control operated on a month by month basis updating intragroup accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">Primarily it took into account the costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">From time to time income would be "... brought to account in relation to these companies for their services".</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">By "income" Mr Carey explained, he meant income earned by Westpoint Group companies for the provision of services to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">The effect of his evidence was that the Triumph system accounting figures relied upon by ASIC in connection with the solvency of the respondents did not paint a true picture because it did not disclose moneys owing to the companies, but not entered in the system, for services provided to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">51 Mr Carey was asked whether members of the Westpoint Group invoiced Westpoint Corporation for their services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">He said invoices would be rendered "often on a six-monthly basis and sometimes on a 12-monthly basis".</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">Such invoicing would frequently occur at the end of the financial year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">There was no need to invoice on a monthly basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">The businesses operated internally in providing services to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Income attributable to member companies providing services to Westpoint Corporation had not been booked to the general ledger.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">52 Asked about the function of Eastlands, Mr Carey described it as "a bit of a mixed bag".</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">He said it "... wasn't a specific business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">It carried out activities from time to time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">Some of the other companies were more specific.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">The activities it carried out included marketing as an aspect of project management.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">53 Mr Carey said that Westpoint Consulting Group showed a loan of $172,000 owing to Westpoint Corporation according to ASIC's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">He asserted that during the relevant period it had earned income well in excess of that amount by carrying out work on the Emu Brewery project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">The company had not "booked" that income.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">Jetstone acquired properties for the development of two Lone Star Restaurants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">It carried out "substantial work in relation to those [two properties] but [had] not booked the income".</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">He described Pagelight Nominees as "the multimedia business within Westpoint".</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">It provided promotional and advertising services that would be charged to the various projects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">It prepared brochures, display material, display suites and the like for property development projects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">Juson also carried out work in relation to project management including the set-up of display suites.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">54 Westside Brisbane Developments had acquired an option to purchase property in Brisbane for a development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">It carried out "due diligence" work on the proposal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">This was the "type of stuff" which was done with lawyers and cost "tens and tens of thousands of dollars".</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">It prepared cashflow feasibility studies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Somehow this work was able to be transmuted into a service provided to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">Just how it could be so characterised did not emerge with clarity from Mr Carey's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">The assignment of the option held by Westside Brisbane Developments would have been directed to a special purpose development "vehicle", ie another company in the Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">Westside Brisbane Developments would be able to raise a charge within the Group for the preparatory work that it had done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">55 Mr Carey's evidence in relation to Bridgeview was confusing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">He said there was an error in the accounts relied upon by ASIC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">The true position was that Bridgeview did not owe Westpoint Corporation any money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">The debt attributed to Bridgeview was in fact owed by Forestview Nominees Pty Ltd (Forestview).</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">Counsel for ASIC correctly pointed out that this was, in effect, a challenge to the debt underlying the statutory demand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">56 In cross-examination Mr Carey said that there were between 20 and 30 accountants working for the Westpoint Group throughout Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">Their responsibilities included the preparation of "journals" which was the starting point for the posting process of the Triumph accounting system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">He said that while some of the businesses didn't use the Triumph system, by and large "...</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">Triumph was the major general ledger package...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">It was put to him that transactions on the Triumph accounting system reflected journal entries prepared on the basis of primary legal or other documentation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">As to that he said: 
 
 'Of my own knowledge I can't say, because I wasn't involved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">However, as an accountant that is how I suspect it operated, yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">" 
 

He personally had not entered any particular transactions on the Triumph system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">57 Mr Carey said in cross-examination that there was a series of financial managers in each of the businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">There was dual reporting to those financial managers, to Mr Rundle who was his Chief Financial Officer, and to Mr Nairn who was assisting him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">He did not see the summary reports himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">Most of the reporting that came to him was on a systematic basis of costing systems and not necessarily off the accounting system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">He ran the major projects, but his interest was in the committed costing system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">Mr Carey expanded a little on the way in which he received information about the operation of companies in the Group: 
 
 'The information I was receiving throughout the year was management accounts and management accounts are quite different to financial accounts and --- and that is the point being made here, is that it seems to me that your client is relying on general ledgers as though they were financial accounts and they simply aren't.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">They are just running balances to that point in time and clearly accounting --- accounting is like a lot of things.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">It is only as good as its input, so as I'm saying, if invoices were not journalised or invoices, the income hadn't been booked, they wouldn't have been journalised and therefore that income wouldn't have been shown in the general ledger.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">' 
 

Mr Carey agreed that the final accounts for the companies in the Group would use as their starting point the Triumph system accounting information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">58 Westpoint Corporation was described by Mr Carey as the "central treasury" for the Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">If a member of the Group incurred an expense such as a debt to a subcontractor that debt would be paid by Westpoint Corporation and recorded as money owing by the member company to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">At the same time the member company would record in its balance sheet a corresponding asset in the form of work in progress.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">59 An example of the preceding process appears in the accounts for Westside Brisbane Developments taken from a Triumph printout.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">This showed work in progress of $12,671 and a loan from Westpoint Corporation of $13,939.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">Mr Carey agreed that as Westside Brisbane Developments was incurring expenses in relation to its project they were paid by Westpoint Corporation and a loan in that amount was acknowledged by Westside Brisbane Developments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">He agreed also that work in progress appearing on the balance sheet of the member company would be "transferred across to the income side as costs of goods sold, to work out profit".</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">This "income" would not necessarily be paid in cash.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">Westpoint Corporation would simply "alter the loan account balance".</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">60 Mr Carey was pressed in cross-examination with the proposition that any debts owing by Westpoint Corporation to a member company would not be recoverable because Westpoint Corporation was in liquidation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">He maintained however that the debts owed to Westpoint according to the Triumph accounting system could be offset by debts owed by Westpoint for "income" which had not been recorded by way of invoices from the member companies or adjustments to the loan accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">61 Mr Carey was directed to a record of reductions in the Pagelight Nominees' loan account with Westpoint Corporation for the period 1 July 2005 to 31 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">There was no "income" shown for the months of December 2005 and January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">He was asked whether Pagelight Nominees had done work in subsequent months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">He said he could not answer in specific terms as he did not have access to the relevant documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">He considered, however, that the company would have been owed more by Westpoint Corporation than the sum of $55,800.85 which it was said to owe to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">This was because of work that Pagelight Nominees had done on the Emu Brewery development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">The amount of that work was substantial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">Someone called "Sean" had been managing the Pagelight Nominees' business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">Mr Carey said he had not been in contact with Sean in connection with the winding up application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">Having been refused an adjournment of the hearing of the application he had been "caught by surprise".</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">Nor had he spoken to Mr Rundle or Mr Nairn in connection with the Westpoint Corporation accounting system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">He did not think they would necessarily have been able to give him details about the precise position of the particular company because they were not managing its business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">62 Mr Carey was asked about the services provided to the Westpoint Group by Eastlands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">He agreed that it had provided management services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">Asked if it had any employees he said that Westpoint Corporation "employed everyone for and on behalf other entities" (sic).</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">Some of Westpoint Corporation's employees did work which entitled Eastlands to render an account to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">He himself had done work on account of Eastlands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">This work had not been billed to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">63 As to Bridgeview and the alleged error in the attribution of liabilities as between Bridgeview and Forestview, Mr Carey was unable, in cross-examination, to explain with any precision how that error occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">He said: 
 
 '...I am saying to you as a director, I am saying that that payment was paid by Forestview, it wasn't paid by Bridgeview and therefore, Forestview should owe Westpoint Corporation, not Bridgeview.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">' 
 

 Whether winding up orders should be made 
 
64 Each of the respondents has failed (as defined in s 459F) to comply with a statutory demand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">There is therefore a presumption that the Court must adopt, pursuant to s 459C(2), that each of the respondents is insolvent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">The presumption applies to satisfy the condition of a prima facie case of insolvency necessary to ground ASIC's application for leave to apply for each of the respondents to be wound up in insolvency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">65 I am satisfied that ASIC should be granted leave to apply to wind up these companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">It has been put in a position, because of orders made affecting companies in the Westpoint Group generally, to access the information and records necessary to assess the circumstances of member companies in the Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">All of the respondents are effectively under the control of one man, Mr Carey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">Beyond the particular interests of individual creditors of the respondents there is a wider public interest, if Group members be insolvent, that they be wound up with as little expense to creditors as possible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">ASIC which can bring this application against all the respondents at the same time is not confined, as an individual creditor would be, to a particular respondent or respondents owing money to the creditor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">It is appropriate that ASIC be granted leave to bring the application and, given the common features of the evidence relied upon and the common control of the respondents, to join them in the one application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">66 The affidavit evidence relied upon by ASIC, to which reference has been made earlier in these reasons, has generally disclosed that the presumption of insolvency, based on the failure to comply with the statutory demands, is not displaced by what appears from the records of the Westpoint Group to which it has referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">67 Mr Carey's evidence, if accepted, could raise questions about the completeness of the financial picture painted by the Triumph accounting system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">It raises the possibility that there may be unrecorded offsets against the debts recorded as owing to Westpoint Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">That evidence however does no more than raise the possibilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">It might have been a basis for setting aside the statutory demands, but no application of that kind was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">His evidence, taken at its highest, does not displace the presumption of insolvency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">It does not, in terms of the Act, "prove the contrary" in the sense defined in s 95A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">68 In my opinion each of the respondents is to be taken as insolvent and no discretionary basis is disclosed for refusing to make the winding up orders sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">69 ASIC also seeks, by way of amendment to its application, the appointment of receivers to the assets of those Trusts of which various of the respondent companies are trustees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">The proposed receivers are also the proposed liquidators of the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">An important asset of each of the respondent trustees will no doubt be its right of indemnity out of the trust assets in respect of liabilities incurred in discharging its function as a trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">The enforcement of that indemnity, in the circumstances, may appropriately be joined with the discharge of the liquidator's function in winding up the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">70 The scope of the powers proposed for the liquidators in their capacity as receivers of trust assets is not limited to the enforcement of the trustees' indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">While, in an ideal world, it would be desirable to separate the function of the liquidators and receivers of the trust assets, in my opinion, in this case, that is likely to involve unnecessary expense and duplication of function.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">The position of the beneficiaries of the trusts will be protected by an order in each apposite case, that there be liberty to apply to the Court for directions as to the duties of the receivers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">The liquidators themselves, in their capacity as receivers, may also apply for such directions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">Conclusion 
 
71 For the preceding reasons I will make the orders sought by ASIC.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">I certify that the preceding seventy-one (71) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice French .</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">Associate:
Dated: 6 December 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr CM Slater 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Australian Investments and Securities Commission 
 
 
 Mr Norman Carey, the common director of each of the respondents, appeared on their behalf in person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">Date of Hearing: 20 November 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 December 2006 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1702.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>