<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZCBQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1538 (30 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1538.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">information provided by the appellant in his application for a protection visa was a part of the refugee review tribunal's reasons for affirming the minister's decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">appellant requested in his application to the tribunal that it refer to that information</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">information fell within s 424a(3)(b)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">appeal dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The appellant is an Indian citizen of Muslim belief who claims to have a well-founded fear of persecution for reason of his religious beliefs, political activities and associations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">His claims to the Refugee Review Tribunal may be summarised as follows: 
 
 &#8226; The appellant lived in Tamil Nadu in the South of India.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">He became a member of the Tamil Nadu Muslim Munnetra Kalagam party ('TMMK') in 1995 and was nominated acting secretary in 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">&#8226; The ruling Bharati Janatha Party ('BJP'), which is of Hindu belief, was opposed to Muslims including the TMMK and himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">&#8226; The police were Hindu, opposed to Muslims and favoured the ruling party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">In November 2000 they arrested and beat him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">&#8226; After his arrest in November 2000, he joined the Dravida Munetra Kalagam party and was pressured to join another party, the All India Anna Dravida Munetra Kalagam party ('AIADMK').</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Instead of joining the AIADMK, however, he publicly accused its leader of corruption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">&#8226; The AIADMK threatened to kill him and he fled to Rajasthan for nine months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">

2 The Tribunal's reasons record that the appellant, when questioned further about his arrest, said that he was arrested twice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">He also said that he was arrested "each year" right before the anniversary of the destruction of the Babri Masjid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Grounds of appeal 
 
3 The Tribunal affirmed the first respondent's decision not to grant a protection visa to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">He appears in person in this Court assisted by an interpreter to appeal a judgment of Lloyd-Jones FM dismissing his application for judicial review of the Tribunal's decision ( SZCBQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 735).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">4 The appellant filed a document titled "Applicant's Submissions" which sets out a number of matters in general terms in a form that this Court has seen before in relation to other appellants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The document bore little or no relation to the grounds in the notice of appeal which are also in general, non particularised terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">5 I asked the appellant whether he could add anything to the written submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">He referred to two factual matters: first, that if he returns to India his life will be in danger and secondly, if he were to relocate within India from Tamil Nadu he will have language problems and difficulties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">These matters are factual matters that do not assist the appellant in his appeal and are not directly relevant to the matters raised in his written submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">6 Mr Smith appears for the Minister and has assisted the Court by analysing the written submissions and isolating from them what might be called grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The appellant has confirmed that, in his analysis, Mr Smith did not leave out any grounds or, I infer, any detail in the submissions upon which the appellant wishes to rely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">7 The Minister takes no objection to the fact that the grounds of appeal now raised by the appellant were not raised in the notice of appeal nor, as to some, before the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Accordingly, I will deal with the six grounds of appeal as identified by Mr Smith and confirmed by the appellant as valid grounds of this appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">(1) The Application of Muin and Lie 
 
8 The appellant submits that he was misled and that the facts of Muin v Refugee Review Tribunal &amp; Lie v Refugee Review Tribunal [2002] HCA 30 ; (2002) 190 ALR 601 are the same as the facts in his case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">It is apparent that that is not so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The Tribunal in its decision specifically referred to the matters that were and were not before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The Tribunal observed ' for the avoidance of doubt ' that the departmental file did not contain the documents referred to in the decision under review under the heading "Part B: Evidence Before Me" but that documents specifically referred to in the decision were otherwise available and had been taken into account by the Tribunal in so far as they were considered to be relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Further, there is no evidence in the present case that the appellant was misled by anything said or done by the Tribunal in respect of those documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Accordingly, Muin has no application to the present case and the ground of appeal is rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">(2) Section 66 of the Migration Act 
 
9 The appellant alleges that '[t] he Tribunal does not have the power to take this decision in to effect ' because subsections 66(1) and (2) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ('the Act') were not observed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The Minister is required to notify the applicant for a protection visa of her decision to grant or refuse the visa in accordance with s 66 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">10 Mr Smith submits that s 66 has "no part to play" in this appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">I agree.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The decision under review by the Tribunal is dated 17 October 2002 and the application to the Tribunal for review was received by the Tribunal on 13 November 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The application includes an acknowledgment by the appellant of receipt of the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It follows that the application to the Tribunal was validly made within the relevant time limits (s 412(1)(b) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The Tribunal had jurisdiction to conduct its review and no relevant error is established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">11 In any event, a failure by the Minister to give notification of her decision does not affect the validity of that decision (s 66(4)) , nor the decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">(3) Section 424A of the Act 
 
12 Before the Federal Magistrate Counsel for the Minister raised as an issue whether there had been a failure by the Tribunal to comply with s 424A of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">It is accepted that the Tribunal referred to and relied upon information in the material in support of the appellant's application for a protection visa adversely to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Standing alone that would mean that there had been a contravention of s 424A(1) of the Act as no written notice of particulars of that information was given to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">However, the appellant, in his application to the Tribunal under the heading '[y] our Reasons for making this application ', stated ' Please Refer my Statement Claim of my Refugee Application '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">I am satisfied that in so doing he intended to and did refer to a document entitled ' Statement Claim of [the appellant]' which accompanied his protection visa application and is included in the Appeal Book.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">13 In those circumstances, for the reasons given in VUAV v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1271 at [10] to [13] and NBCM v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1150 at [13] , the "Statement Claim" and the information therein fell within s 424A(3)(b) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">I note that an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court in VUAV was refused on 12 April 2006 ( VUAV v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA Trans 183).</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Gummow J specifically said on that occasion that ' no error is apparent in Merkel J's decision upon the applicability of section 424A '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">On that basis special leave was refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">(4) Section 430 of the Act 
 
14 Section 430(1) of the Act provides that the Tribunal must, when making its decision on review, prepare a written statement in accordance with s 430(1) and, once that statement is prepared, give to the Secretary certain documents in accordance with s 430(3).</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The Tribunal's obligations pursuant to s 430(1) were considered by the High Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">No factual basis for any contravention of s 430 is made out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The ground of appeal has not been substantiated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">(5) The ignoring of relevant evidence 
 

 
15 The appellant's written submissions assert that he supplied additional evidence to the Tribunal to which it paid no attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The appellant also asserts generally and without particularisation that the Tribunal ignored relevant evidence including independent evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">When I asked the appellant what additional information he was referring to he said that he had given no additional information to the Tribunal by way of additional evidence or documentation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">16 It is clear that the claims made by the appellant to the Tribunal were based upon his religion and political beliefs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The Tribunal considered both those claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">It did not accept the appellant's claim as to his political beliefs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">It accepted that he was a Muslim but for the reasons which it gave and which were open to on the evidence before it, the Tribunal was not satisfied that that was sufficient to give rise to a well-founded fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">The Tribunal dealt with the appellant's claims, identified its findings on the questions of fact it considered to be material ( Yusuf at [69]) and was not obliged to refer to each and every aspect of the evidence before it in drawing its conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">No jurisdictional error is established on this basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">(6) Bad faith 
 

 
17 The appellant has not given any evidence or any particulars sufficient to ground an accusation of bad faith, which is a serious allegation that should not be raised without a proper basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Nor has the appellant pointed to any matter that would lead to any conclusion of bad faith, bias or apprehended bias or of a denial of procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">To the contrary, a reading of the Tribunal's decision makes it apparent that the Tribunal took detailed account of the evidence of the appellant and considered it before coming to its conclusions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Conclusion 
 
18 Neither the notice of appeal nor the applicant's submissions raise an arguable ground of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">It follows that the appeal should be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">I certify that the preceding eighteen (18) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Associate:

Dated: 17 November 2006


 The Appellant appeared in person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Counsel for the First Respondent: J Smith 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Sparke Helmore Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 30 October 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 October 2006 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1538.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>