<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Merck &amp; Co Inc v Genrx Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1407 (31 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1407.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interlocutory injunction</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application to restrain respondent from importing and supplying pharmaceutical products containing applicant's patented compound</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">claim that patent invalid for lack of novelty</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">considerations relevant to grant of injunction where respondent challenges validity of patent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether serious question to be tried on validity of patent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">patents</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 An international pharmaceutical company, Merck &amp; Co Inc, owns an Australian patent for a compound used therapeutically.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">It was granted the patent in 1992.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Another international pharmaceutical company, Apotex International Inc, is on the verge of supplying drugs for importation into Australia which contain that compound.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The generic drugs will be imported through GenRx Pty Ltd, a company ultimately owned by Apotex.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Arrangements are well advanced for the sale of the imported drugs in the Australian market which will commence after 1 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The drugs have been registered on the Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods and some are being included in the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Arrangements to import the drugs have been underway since at least November 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">There is little room to doubt that the importation of the drugs will involve an infringement of Merck's patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Merck has commenced infringement proceedings and seeks an interlocutory injunction to restrain the importation of the drugs until a final hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">GenRx resists the injunction and says, amongst other things, that there can be no infringement because the patent is not valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">That is because the invention was not novel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">2 The importation of the drugs is scheduled for 31 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The interlocutory application was heard on 26 and 27 October 2006 and, at the request of the parties, this judgment is being given before the scheduled date of importation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Given the limited time to prepare these reasons, they are intended convey the substance of my reasons for granting interlocutory injunctive relief but do not discuss some matters of detail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">3 The first applicant, Merck, is the registered owner of Australian Patent No 625704, entitled "Process for preparing 4-amino-1-hydroxybutylidene-1, 1-bisphosphonic acids or salts thereof".</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The shortened name of the compound 4-amino-1-hydroxybutylidene-1, 1-bisphosphonic acid is alendronic acid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The patent period is from 8 June 1990 to 8 June 2010.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">A claimed salt of alendronic acid in Merck's patent (claim 23) is 4-amino-1-hydroxybutylidene-1, 1-bisphosphonic acid monosodium salt trihydrate ("AMT").</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">AMT is an active ingredient in Merck products carrying the FOSAMAX label, prescribed for the treatment of various bone disorders such as osteoporosis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The second applicant, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme (Australia) Pty Ltd carries on in Australia the business of formulation, sale and distribution of pharmaceutical products.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">It is a subsidiary of the first applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">On 7 February 2001, MSDA obtained registration of "FOSAMAX Once Weekly" and "FOSAMAX Plus" on the Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The applicants commenced these proceedings on 25 September 2006 shortly after receiving correspondence suggesting one or number of the generic drugs to be imported by GenRx had been included in the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">They applied to this Court under s 120 of the Patents Act 1990 (Cth) that the respondent be restrained from infringing claims 16 to 27 of the patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">4 As interlocutory relief, the applicants seek orders that the respondent be restrained from infringing claims 16 to 27 of the patent by supplying, ordering to supply, importing or keeping for the purpose of doing any of those things the products branded Apo-Alendronate, GenRx Alendronate, Chemmart Alendronate, Terry White Chemists Alendronate and Aledronate-DP.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">This includes preventing the respondent from continuing to list or apply to list any one or more of those products for supply under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">A distributor of several of the imported products will be Symbion Health Ltd. 
 The case for infringement 
 
 5 Subject to a successful challenge to the validity of the patent, there is no basis for suggesting, on the cases presented in this interlocutory application, that the conduct of GenRx will not constitute infringement of Merck's patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">It will.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The drugs which GenRx proposes to import into Australia for sale contain AMT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">By s 13 of the Act, Merck has the exclusive rights to exploit the invention which includes an exclusive right to import and sell product which it covers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The conduct of GenRx will derogate from that right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">
 The case for invalidity 
 
 6 Central to GenRx's case in this interlocutory application that the patent was invalid, was a US patent dated 4 November 1986 concerning processes for preparing pharmacologically active biphosphonates and pharmaceutical compositions derived from them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">One of the inventors was Sergio Rosini.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The Rosini patent was published in the Australian Patent Office on 18 December 1986.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Merck has since acquired this patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">It contains one claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">It is "for a method of treatment of urolithiasis and inhibiting bone reabsorption which consists of administering to a patient in need thereof and effective amount of 4-amino-1-hydroxybutane-1, 1-bisphosphonic acid".</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Before considering what the patent discloses, it is convenient to discuss the principles concerning novelty of an invention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Lack of novelty is the only ground advanced by GenRx in the interlocutory hearing in support of the contention that the Merck's patent is invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">7 The principles to be applied in determining whether an invention was novel are comparatively settled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Courts both in Australia and the United Kingdom continue to view the principles as rooted in the decision of Lord Westbury in Hill v Evans (1862) 31 LJ Ch (NS) 457, 1A IPR 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">That decision has recently been described by Lord Hoffman as a judgment of unquestionable authority: Smithkline Beecham plc's (paroxetine methanesulfonate) patent [2006] RPC 10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Hill v Evans concerned disclosure and a patent for the purification of gas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Lord Westbury described the disclosure required in an earlier publication necessary to destroy a later patent for want of novelty, as involving a statement such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention could be made useful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">His Lordship continued by saying that if something remained to be ascertained which was necessary for the useful application of the discovery, that provided sufficient room for another valid patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">8 The other English authority described by Lord Hoffman in Smithkline Beecham plc's (paroxetine methanesulfonate) patent as of unquestionable authority was the judgment of the Court of Appeal in General Tyre and Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Co [1972] RPC 457, 1A IPR 121.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">In that case the prior publications and patent concerned processes (or aspects of processes) for making a compound suitable for tyre treads by mixing synthetic rubber with oil and carbon black.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The Court of Appeal indicated that if the prior inventor's publication contained a clear description of, or clear instructions to do or make, something that would infringe the patentee's claim if carried out after the grant of the patentee's patent, the patentee's claim would have been shown to lack the necessary novelty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">The prior inventor may have had a different starting point, but if the prior inventor's instructions were carried out and inevitably result in something being made or done which would constitute infringement of the patentee's claim, the patentee's claim would have been anticipated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">9 The case considered by the House of Lords in Smithkline Beecham plc's (paroxetine methanesulfonate) patent concerned a patent for a compound, a crystalline salt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Somewhat simply described, the earlier publication concerned the same compound (though with different characteristics) and contained examples which, if skilfully manipulated in a way not described in the earlier publication, created the compound with the characteristics described in the patent in suit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The trial judge concluded the patent was not valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">This judgment was reversed by the Court of Appeal but reinstated by the House of Lords.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Lord Hoffman gave the leading judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">As noted in the headnote, the following emerges from his Lordship's judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The infringement had to be not merely a possible or even likely consequence of performing the invention disclosed by the prior disclosure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">It had to be necessarily entailed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Anticipation necessary to defeat a patent for want of novelty required disclosure of subject-matter which, when performed, must necessarily infringe the patented invention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">It was the requirement that the performance of an invention disclosed in the prior art must necessarily infringe the patent which distinguished novelty from obviousness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The performance of an invention disclosed by the prior art would not infringe the patent but the prior art would make it obvious to a skilled person how he might make adaptations which resulted in an infringing invention, then the patent might be invalid for lack of inventive step but not for lack of novelty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">10 Australian authorities referred to by the parties, and judgments of Full Courts of this Court in particular, do not, in substance, suggest some other approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Senior counsel for GenRx referred to passages in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Lehane J in Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v F H Faulding and Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 in which their Honours spoke of it being sufficient that the prior publication gave a direction or made a recommendation or suggestion which could be followed by a skilled reader and that the direction, recommendation or suggestion might be implicit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">However, those observations were made in the context of quoting with approval the often cited and evocative observations of the Court of Appeal in General Tyre and Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Co that the prior publication must contain clear and unmistakable directions to what the patentee claims to have invented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">A signpost, however clear, upon the road to the patentee's invention was not sufficient.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The prior inventor must be clearly shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">The joint judgment of Black CJ and Lehane J has since been described in another recent Full Court judgment as deciding that the prior publication must contain "clear and unmistakable directions": Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 230 at [140].</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">To similar effect is the joint judgment of French and Lindgren JJ in another recent Full Court judgment Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly and Co (2005) 225 ALR 416 at [311]-[317].</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">11 In the present case, GenRx relies, in substance, on two aspects of the prior publication embodied in the Rosini patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">The first is that Rosini clearly directs the skilled reader to 4-amino (alendronic) acid and not 5-amino acid (I use the shorthand description used in GenRx's submissions which somewhat simplify what the patent says).</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">In a table, Table 6, the reader is referred to some typical pharmaceutical formulations containing amino-butan-bisphosphonic acid which included capsules containing 4-amino acid, sodium salt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">That is, a monosodium salt version of the acid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">One experiment in Rosini, experiment 5, instructs the reader to undertake an experiment commencing with a quality of 5-amino acid to which is added a solution of sodium hydroxide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">That is then decolourized, filtered and concentrated and kept in the cold for a period of three days under gentle stirring.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">This produces a crystalline solid which is washed with a small amount of cold water and then methanol.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">After this is dried at 100deg.C, a quantity of the monosodium salt of 5-amino acid is produced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">12 GenRx led evidence that experiment 5 provided an illustration of how a monosodium salt of 4-amino acid might be produced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">It also led evidence that if experiment 5 was followed but commencing with 4-amino acid rather than 5-amino acid as instructed, then AMT would be produced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">That would come about and the trihydrate (AMT being a trihydrated monosodium salt of alendronic acid) would be created if a drying process as contemplated in experiment 5 was carried out though, as Merck points out, at a different temperature in different conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Merck also responded by pointing out that experiment 5 commences with 5-amino-1-hydroxy pentan-1, 1-bisphosphonic acid which is not alendronic acid as that compound has an extra carbon atom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">13 The evidence of GenRx, at its highest, was the opinion of Dr McClelland, Professor Emeritus at the University of Toronto, that a person skilled in the art would follow the Rosini patent and be led directly and without difficulty to AMT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">In addition, as GenRx points out, Merck successfully prosecuted infringement proceedings in the United States in 2002 against a generic drug manufacturer which sought to sell and distribute a generic version of FOSOMAX containing, it appears, AMT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Merck did so relying on the Rosini patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Judge Farnam of the United States District Court of Delaware concluded (a conclusion upheld on appeal in the Court of Appeals in 2003) that the claim in the Rosini patent for 4-amino-1-hydroxybutane-1, 1-bisphosphonic acid included both its free acid and sodium salt forms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">His Honour's ultimate conclusion did not appear to depend on AMT being a monosodium trihydrate which, on evidence of the inventor of AMT (filed in a change of inventorship application in Australia in 1992), is of significance therapeutically.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">14 Having regard to the criticisms made by Merck of GenRx's evidence, I doubt that GenRx is, in relation to the contention advanced in this interlocutory hearing that the invention in the patent in suit is not novel, in the territory marked out by the authorities referred to at [7]-[10] above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">That is, GenRx's case of invalidity based on lack of novelty does not have strong prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Indeed it has, in my opinion, limited prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">However, I doubt that it is open to me to proceed on the basis that there is not a serious question to be tried on the alleged invalidity of the patent particularly having regard to the findings of the Federal District Court in the litigation in the United States.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">I accept there is a serious question to be tried.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">
 Adequacy of damages 
 
 15 There appeared to be no real issue about whether Merck would suffer damage as a result of GenRx importing into Australia the generic drugs containing AMT for distribution and sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">It appeared to be accepted, and probably necessarily so, that Merck would lose sales, possibly lose market share and other generics may quickly enter the market to compete with the FOSOMAX line of products.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The clear picture of Merck's present significant market share (though already adversely affected by one generic in the market, Alendro) is likely to be quickly and substantially muddied by the entry of not only the generics to be imported by GenRx, but other generics which might be encouraged to follow GenRx's example.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">It also appeared to not be seriously contested that Merck will lose the commercial advantages of being in the market with the patented products when the patent expires.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Changes may be made to the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme in the near future and how they might impact on any loss suffered by Merck would be difficult to gauge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Undertakings are offered by GenRx and Symbion that neither will request a reduction of the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme benchmark price until final judgment is given in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">
 Principles governing the grant of interlocutory relief 
 
 16 There was limited debate about what were the applicable principles governing the grant or refuse of interlocutory relief in proceedings such as the present.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The original submissions of the parties, as filed, appeared to accept that those principles were as discussed by Stone J in Hexal Australia Pty Ltd v Roche Therapeutics Inc (2005) 66 IPR 325, applied by Sundberg J in Pharmacia Italia SpA v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 387.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">That is, on the one hand, first the applicants must establish that there is a serious question to be tried on the alleged infringement, secondly unless the injunction sought is granted, they will suffer irreparable harm for which damages cannot adequately compensate and thirdly the balance of convenience favours the granting of the injunction sought, and on the other hand, the respondent must establish a serious question to be tried on the alleged invalidity of the patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">I accept these are the applicable principles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">17 During the course of the argument, counsel for GenRx referred to the decision of the High Court in Beecham Group Ltd v Bristol Laboratories Pty Ltd (1968) 119 CLR 618, the judgment of Stephen J in Firth Industries Ltd v Polyglas Engineering Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 25 ; (1975) 132 CLR 489 and observations in the fourth edition (2002) of Meagher, Gummow and Lehane's: Equity: Doctrines and Remedies at 782 (but, compare the commentary at 787) that "the old rule still obtains that only in the rarest of cases can a plaintiff obtain an interlocutory injunction against the infringement of the patent if the validity of the patent is put in issue".</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">However I think it is clear, particularly having regard to the analysis of Gummow J in Martin Engineering Co v Trison Holdings Pty Ltd (1988) 81 ALR 543, that Courts are now considerably less reticent about granting interlocutory injunctive relief in infringement proceedings, than may have been the case historically.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">
 Consideration 
 
 18 In my opinion, this is a case warranting the grant of interlocutory injunctive relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">The balance of convenience favours it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">Since at least November 2004, when the solicitors acting for GenRx in these proceedings sought in writing (by reference to the same file number that the firm is using for this matter) details of Merck's patent from IP Australia, GenRx has known of Merck's rights under the patent in relation to AMT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">A clear inference is available than since then, GenRx has set about making the commercial arrangements to import into Australia for sale and distribution drugs containing an active ingredient protected by Merck's patent in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">It has done so for the admitted purpose of gaining the commercial advantage of putting the second generic drug into the market.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">Those arrangements have included sponsoring the registration of the drugs on the Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods and sponsoring the inclusion of one of them in the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The other branded drugs to be imported have been or are likely to be listed in that scheme on the application of other sponsors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">19 There can be little doubt that GenRx has engaged in this conduct deliberately and with the knowledge that Merck's patent would be infringed unless it was able successfully to impeach its validity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">It could have done so by revocation proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">It has not and now calls in aid the consequences of not being able to give effect to the arrangements now in place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">That includes commercial loss to it and others and potentially, loss of reputation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">For my part I give little weight to these complaints or concerns.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">As just discussed, GenRx has placed itself in this position quite deliberately and knowingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">To use the language of some of the authorities, its "eyes were wide open".</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">20 While, if the infringement suit is successful, Merck's losses are ultimately only financial losses for which damages can be awarded, I accept that it will be difficult to assess with any real precision what those losses are so as compensate Merck for its actual loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">This is a relevant consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">Issues were raised by Merck about whether it would be able to recover damages from GenRx given that it is a company with only two issued dollar shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">I do not view this as a matter supporting the grant of interlocutory relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">If I had concluded that interlocutory relief should not be granted having regard to the matters already discussed, a regime could have been put in place to ensure that any order for damages ultimately made could be made efficacious and met by Apotex.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">21 The Act and the authorities to which I have referred create a statutory regime intended to afford patent owners a measure of protection subject, of course, to the rights of others to remove that protection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">For the reasons I have given, I consider that in the circumstances discussed, the protection the Act affords Merck should continue until this application has been heard and determined on a final basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">I proposed to grant interlocutory injunctive relief broadly in the term sought by Merck.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">GenRx should pay the applicants' costs of this interlocutory application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">


 I certify that the preceding twenty-one (21) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Moore J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Associate:

Dated: 31 October 2006

 Counsel for the Applicants: Ms K Howard SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Cropper Parkhill Solicitors 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms A N Bowne SC and Mr N R Murray 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Freehills 
 
 Date of Hearing: 26 and 27 October 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 31 October 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1407.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>