<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Servier Laboratories (Australia) Pty Ltd v GenRx Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1763 (30 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1763.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interlocutory injunction application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">respondent about to market the generic equivalent of applicant's product</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">respondent's product only registered by therapeutic goods administration for two of the three indications for which applicant's product registered</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">subsequent to filing of application tga registered third indication</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">costs</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The applicant is the owner of the therapeutic drug Coversyl (active ingredient - Perindopril) which has three registered indications for treatment: hypertension, chronic heart fatigue and coronary artery disease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The respondent is the producer of perindopril erbumine products are the generic version of Coversyl.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The applicant claims that the respondent circulated advertising material promoting its products as a "genuine alternative" to Coversyl Perindopril, thereby representing that the products were substitutable for each of the three registered indications outlined above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The Product Information for the Respondent's products indicates that it is not an authorised indication for coronary artery disease (the applicant's third registered indication).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The respondent obtained a listing from the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme effective from 1 December 2006, which required the respondent to be in an immediate position to supply the market from that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The applicant sought an interlocutory injunction preventing the respondent from representing that its products were substitutable with Coversyl to treat coronary artery disease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">4 Immediately prior to the scheduled commencement of the interlocutory hearing, the respondent had communication from the Therapeutic Goods Administration that its products had been registered for the third indication.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">As such, the applicant no longer has a claim against the respondents for misleading and deceptive conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Therefore, the only matter for me to decide is one of costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">5 The considerations which apply when a matter has otherwise been resolved but the parties seek an order for costs has recently been discussed by me in Oxford Funding Proprietary Limited v Oxford Asia Pacific Investments Proprietary Limited (No 2) [2006) FCA 1542 at par [5].</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">6 In the present case the dispute arose in circumstances of great urgency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The parties are fierce trade rivals, and understandably concerned to protect their commercial interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The Court should not be too ready to dictate in hindsight a particular course of conduct which the parties could or should have taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">7 I think the applicant acted reasonably in initiating proceedings to forestall what was arguably, in its view, misleading and deceptive conduct by the respondent which could be seriously damaging.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The respondent, on the other hand, proffered firm assurances which would meet the applicant's concerns.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">As events have turned out, those assurances have been substantiated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">It is possible that the respondent might have offered more corroborating detail in its letter of today's date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">However, that was a matter for judgment which had to be made quickly and under pressure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Given its legitimate concern about confidentiality of dealings with the Therapeutic Goods Administration, I do not think that the respondent acted unreasonably, although it might have acted differently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">8 In the circumstances, I do not propose to make any order as to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The substantive application will be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I certify that the preceding eight (8) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Associate:

Dated: 30 November 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: D Shavin QC and I Horak 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicant: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: S McVicar 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondent: Freehills 
 
 Date of Hearing: 30 November 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 November 2006 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1763.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>