<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXAI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1116 (22 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1116.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from federal magistrate</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">no question of principle</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">appeal dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 The appellant appeals from a judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court which dismissed his application for judicial review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The Tribunal had affirmed a decision of a delegate of the first respondent that the appellant was not entitled to a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The Tribunal found that the appellant did not have a well-founded fear of persecution if returned to India in the reasonably foreseeable future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">His Honour below rejected the following points raised on behalf of the appellant: 
 
 &#8226; the Tribunal's decision lacked logic;
 &#8226; the Tribunal failed to determine whether the appellant was a member of a particular social group;
 &#8226; the Tribunal erroneously rejected letters of support for the appellant; and
 &#8226; the Tribunal failed to consider the issue of relocation within India.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">
 
 3 His Honour in the Court below correctly dismissed each of the appellant's submissions on the above issues.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The Tribunal's reasons did not lack logic but disclosed a reasoning process and were not internally inconsistent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The Tribunal correctly assessed that the appellant was not a member of the social group constituted by members of the People's War Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">In any event, that was a question of fact for it to determine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">4 The Tribunal's rejection of the letters was a matter going to the merits of its decision and did not involve any judicially reviewable error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Further, the question of internal relocation did not arise on the basis of the reasoning of the Tribunal that the appellant was not at risk of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The Tribunal did not consider that the appellant was at risk of persecution from the People's War Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">That was a question of fact for it to determine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">It found that the People's War Group would not consider the appellant to be a police informer, as he claimed it would.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 The appellant's notice of appeal contends his Honour in the Court below erred in finding that the Tribunal's decision was not affected by a jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">He did not identify any such error in his oral submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">He failed to file any written submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Having read the decision of the Tribunal, and the analysis of it in the Court below, I do not consider that the Tribunal made a jurisdictional error in its consideration of the appellant's claim for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">6 The appeal is dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">


 I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Marshall.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Associate:


Dated: 23 August 2006



 The appellant represented himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Counsel for the Respondents: Mr E Heerey 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 22 August 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 August 2006 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1116.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>