<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cadbury Schweppes Plc v Effem Foods Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1267 (22 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1267.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal under s 60(4) of patents act 1990 (cth) by applicant for patent against decision of commissioner of patents upholding opposition to grant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">pursuant to leave, opponent withdrew its appearance on the appeal, did not appear on the hearing of the appeal, and submitted no evidence in support of the commissioner's decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">commissioner, joined as second respondent, appeared on hearing of appeal, but only to announce that she did not wish to participate actively on the hearing of the appeal or to oppose the allowing of the appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">procedure to be followed on the hearing of the appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">held : appeal could be allowed without applicant's adducing evidence to displace the opposition that had succeeded before the commissioner</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">patents</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 The following are my reasons for the orders made on 28 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The applicant ("Cadbury") appeals to the Court under s 60(4) of the Patents Act 1990 (Cth) ("the Act ") against a decision of a delegate of the second respondent ("the Delegate" and "the Commissioner" respectively) given on 30 September 2002 concerning an Australian Patent Application Number 706901 ("the Patent").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">By the decision, the Commissioner, by the Delegate, allowed the opposition of the respondent ("Effem") to the grant of the Patent, and awarded costs against Cadbury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 The Patent application was filed under the Patent Cooperation Treaty on 21 December 1995 under International Application Number PCT/GB95/03010.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The application claimed priority from British Application 9426078 dated 23 December 1994.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The publication date was 19 July 1996 and the publication journal date was 5 September 1996.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The application and complete specification were accepted on 6 May 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Notice of the acceptance was advertised on 1 July 1999 under serial number 706901.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Effem's notice of opposition was filed on 1 October 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">On the appeal, I had before me Effem's "statement of grounds and particulars of opposition" dated 4 January 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The opposition was heard on 19 February 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">4 The specification related to a "process for manufacture of reduced fat chocolate".</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">There are ten claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The process involves controlling the milling of the solid ingredients to produce particles of a specific "particle size distribution," in which the proportion of ultrafines is kept to such a level that the addition of water is not required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">5 Effem's grounds of opposition were:
 1. lack of novelty;
 2. obviousness;
 3. not a method of manufacture;
 4. non-compliance with s 40 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Before the Delegate, the opposition succeeded on obviousness alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">6 The closest art relied on by Effem was a PhD thesis entitled " Particle Size Distribution Effects in Chocolate Processing" by A D Darley, University of Bradford, 1987.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">This document was referred to as "D10" in the Delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">7 Cadbury challenged the admissibility of D10 before the Delegate on the ground that Effem had not provided an exact publication date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">However, the Delegate noted that the first page of D10 indicated that it was submitted in February 1987.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The Delegate stated, "A PhD thesis, once submitted, is published by the university within a few months at worst".</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">In addition, the Delegate noted that the cover sheet from the British Library Document Supply Centre carried a handwritten date of 1987.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">According to the Delegate, this suggested that the thesis was publicly available well before the priority date of Cadbury's application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 The Delegate found that, on the balance of probabilities, D10 was published before the earliest priority date of the claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On this basis the Delegate concluded that all ten claims were obvious and that there was no patentable subject matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">For this reason, dependent on D10 alone, the Delegate refused Cadbury's application for the Patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">9 On 7 August 2006, pursuant to O 22 r 1 of the Federal Court Rules , I granted Effem leave to withdraw its appearance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">On 14 August 2006, Effem filed a notice of withdrawal of appearance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">10 The Commissioner appeared on the hearing of the appeal, but did not wish to be heard in opposition to the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">With her consent, I ordered that she be added as second respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">11 In the light of the above developments, no evidence was adduced on the hearing of the appeal in support of any ground of opposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">12 An appeal under s 60(4) of the Act is a proceeding in the original jurisdiction of the Court, and is in the nature of a hearing de novo.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">None of the evidence in support of the opposition that was before the Delegate was before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">13 Cadbury submitted that the onus rested on Effem to establish that, if granted, the Patent would be clearly invalid: F Hoffman-La Roche AG v New England Biolabs Inc [2000] FCA 283 ; (2000) 99 FCR 56 at [48] - [67] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">14 Cadbury further submitted that in the circumstances, it was not required to adduce any evidence to counter the ground of opposition that succeeded before the Delegate or any other ground of opposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">15 Recently, in European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 , Young J dealt with a similar submission made in similar forensic circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Young J accepted the submission and held that the appeal should be allowed and that the application for the patent should proceed to grant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">His Honour referred to Caroma Sales Pty Ltd v Philmac Pty Ltd (1972) 46 ALJR 324 per Walsh J; Brickwood Holdings Pty Ltd v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [1983] 2 VR 587 at 588-589 per King J; and Titan Mining &amp; Engineering Pty Ltd v Arnall's Engineering Pty Ltd (1988) 12 NSWLR 73 at 75-76 per McLelland J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">16 I have read those authorities, but will not review them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">They support the following propositions: 
 
 &#8226; on the hearing of an appeal under s 60(4) of the Act (the precursor provision, with which the cases to which Young J referred were concerned, was s 60(5) of the Patents Act 1952 ), the only evidence to be taken into consideration is that adduced on that hearing; &#8226; the applicant is not obliged to put into evidence the evidentiary material that was before the Commissioner or other evidence, going to the merits of the appeal or going to actual or potential grounds of opposition; &#8226; where, as in the present case, the opponent has withdrawn and the Commissioner has indicated on the hearing of the appeal that she does not wish to take any active part in the proceeding, and there is no evidence before the Court capable of supporting any actual or potential ground of opposition, there is no basis on which the Court can uphold any ground of opposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">
 
 17 It is important to note that in the light of the history of the application, and, in particular, the Commissioner's acceptance of the application and the complete specification, s 61 of the Act would have obliged the Commissioner to grant the Patent if there had been no opposition to the grant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">In substance, that is now the position on the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">18 The appeal should be allowed, the Commissioner's decision allowing the opposition should be reversed, and the Patent application should proceed to grant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">19 Notwithstanding his submission that it was not incumbent on Cadbury to lead any evidence addressing any ground of opposition, in order to provide some "comfort" to the Court, Mr Burley, of counsel for Cadbury, did read an affidavit of Michael Kenneth Payne of the British Library Document Supply Centre, demonstrating that document D10 was in fact received by the British Library Document Supply Centre on 3 August 1998 --- well after the priority date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">20 The making of the orders foreshadowed above will not, of course, foreclose the question of the validity of the Patent in any future proceeding, such as a proceeding for revocation of the Patent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">


 

 I certify that the preceding twenty (20) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lindgren.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Associate:

Dated: 22 September 2006



 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr S C G Burley and Mr A Fox 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Griffith Hack 
 
 There was no appearance for the First Respondent 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: Ms L Inge of the Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 28 August 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 28 August 2006 
 
 Date of Publication of Reasons: 22 September 2006 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1267.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>