<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZDKI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 280 (22 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/280.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from federal magistrate's court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">earlier invalid invocation of jurisdiction of the refugee review tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">appeal dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 This is a purported appeal from the judgment and orders of Mowbray FM handed down on 28 October 2005, whereby his Honour dismissed an application for review of a decision adverse to the appellant given by the Refugee Review Tribunal earlier on 5 April 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The basis for the decision of his Honour was that the review application had been lodged 'well out of time', and that as a consequence there was no valid application for review placed by the appellant before the Tribunal, and accordingly the Tribunal's determination to that effect was not ' a decision on a review ' within s 430A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">As his Honour emphasised, the Tribunal's role is to review a valid application, and is only authorised by statute to review a matter and make a decision in response thereto when it has received a valid application to that end.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 Accordingly his Honour dismissed the application for review of the Tribunal's decision, for reasons similar to those framed by Driver FM in SZASD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FMCA 472 at [5] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">4 The matter came before me by way of a so-called amended notice of appeal (NSD 2193 of 2005), the purported grounds of appeal being as follows:
 
 
 '1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The Honourable court failed to determine whether there was any jurisdictional error in the purported decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The appellant seeks leave to amend his appeal to challenge the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The delegate of the Minister failed to have a regard to all of the information provided by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The delegate of the Minister breached procedural fairness and natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">' 
 
 

5 No particularity of those grounds was articulated by the appellant in the notice of appeal, nor in the course of his statements from the Bar Table.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Without at least particularity or other explanation, those grounds are meaningless.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">It appears that he had consulted with a migration agent named Mollah, who was identified in the reasons for judgment of Mowbray FM, and that those grounds were provided by that migration agent to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">6 It is readily apparent that the appeal has no viable foundation, in line with his unsuccessful application for review made to Mowbray FM, and his earlier application for review made to the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The appeal must be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Conti.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Associate:

Dated: 22 March 2006

 The Appellant was self-represented 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: A McInerney 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 21 March 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 March 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/280.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>