<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd v Finishing Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 219 (15 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/219.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">whether notice given by landlord containing new rental assessment valid</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether notice unequivocal and did not leave reasonable recipient in doubt as to meaning</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether reasonable recipient credited with knowledge of terms of lease</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether subjective reaction of recipient of notice relevant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether landlord's assessment required to be reasonable and not excessive</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether an implied duty of good faith</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">misleading or deceptive conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">provision of assessment of proper rent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether provision of assessment caused applicant's loss</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">unconscionable conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">whether individual under a "special disadvantage"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">amendment to pleadings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">whether claim adequately pleaded</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">whether amendment should be allowed after conclusion of evidence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">relevance of strength of case</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c15">contract</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c16">trade practices</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c17">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 INTRODUCTION 
 
 1 This is an application by Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd against Finishing Services Pty Ltd and Colliers International (Victoria) Pty Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">It arises out of the events surrounding the first respondent's attempt to increase the rent of a customised food processing and storage facility at 22-24 Glenvale Crescent, Mulgrave ("the Mulgrave premises"), that it owns and leases to the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 As against the first respondent, the applicant claims that the rental increase notice was invalid, that the first respondent breached an implied duty of good faith and fair dealing, and that the first respondent acted unconscionably, in breach of s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 The second respondent provided certain information to the first respondent as to the market rate of rental that, in its opinion, was applicable to the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">This information, in the form of a letter from the second respondent to the first respondent ("the Colliers letter"), was incorporated in the rental increase notice as an attachment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">As against the second respondent, the applicant claims that it engaged in misleading or deceptive conduct under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act , causing loss or damage to the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The claim against the second respondent is, in effect, pleaded as an alternative to the primary claim against the first respondent, that the rental increase notice was invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">If the challenge to the validity of that notice succeeds, the applicant does not press any claim against the second respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">BACKGROUND 
 
4 The first respondent leased the Mulgrave premises to the applicant in 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">At that time, the applicant was called Nobi Holdings Pty Ltd. Prior to this, the Mulgrave premises had been leased by the first respondent to New Zealand Milk (Ausapac) Pty Ltd ("New Zealand Milk"), a company associated with the New Zealand Government.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">5 The applicant's business involves the cutting and wrapping of cheese.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">This process is conducted out of the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The applicant's parent company is Lactos Pty Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">It conducts research and development, marketing and operations activities, and is based in Burnie, Tasmania.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Lactos Pty Ltd's parent company is a French company called Bongrain SA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Mr Claude Bertrand, a French national, is the General Manager of the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">6 The first respondent owns a number of industrial properties, including the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Its directors are John Allen, and his son Matthew.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">All references in these reasons for judgment to Mr Allen are to Mr John Allen, unless otherwise indicated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Mr Allen also is the principal of Allen &amp; Allen solicitors who operate out of Finishing Services' premises in Moorabbin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">It appears that Allen &amp; Allen only do work for companies associated with Mr Allen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">7 The lease for the Mulgrave premises is dated 1 September 1999, and is for a term of seven years, with the option of a further term ("the lease").</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The annual rental at the time of the signing of the lease was $244,152.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 Clause 3.2.2 of the lease provides for a "market rental review".</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The clause is prolix, to say the least.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">It relevantly provides as follows:
 
 "MARKET RENTAL REVIEW 
 
 Upon any day being not more than six months prior to 1 March 2003 and (if the Lessee exercises its option to renew) not more than 6 months prior to 1 September 2006 and 1 March 2010.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The Lessor or the Managing Agent may give written notice to the Lessee stating the sum which the Lessor assesses to be the proper rent for the premises for the ensuing period such rent being the market rental value for the premises on the assumption that the premises are tenanted and with all fixtures and fittings and partitions, plant machinery utensils shelving safes and other articles and materials as set out in schedule 2 installed by either the Lessor or the Lessee and having regard to the rents being obtained for comparable premises within the same municipality and the rent shall be varied accordingly, such variation to take effect on and from the day immediately following the date to which such notice shall relate and if the party receiving the notice does not object in writing to the proposed market rent within 30 days it becomes the rent for the review period PROVIDED that the Lessee may by notice in writing (delivered to the Lessor or the Managing Agent within 30 days following receipt of the Lessor's or the Managing Agent's notice of assessment) state that he disputes the Lessor's assessment in which case sub-clause (a) hereof will apply AND in all respects time shall be of the essence in the delivery of the said notice within the time so stipulated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">" (emphasis added)
 

9 Clause 3.2.2 goes on to provide a mechanism for determining the rent should the lessee dispute the lessor's assessment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">That mechanism involves having a member of the Australian Institute of Valuers determine the proper rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">10 The clause, as set out above, is ungrammatical at various points.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">For example, the first sentence is incomplete, and presumably ought to be linked to the second sentence with a comma.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">It also gives rise to difficult questions of interpretation because of the imprecise manner in which it was drafted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Nonetheless, it has been set out verbatim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">11 In practical terms, clause 3.2.2 provides that the lessor may serve written notice on the lessee specifying the lessor's assessment of the proper rent and, if the lessee does not object in writing within 30 days, the lessor's assessment will automatically become the new rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">12 Schedule 2, to which clause 3.2.2 refers, is in the following terms:
 
 "SCHEDULE 2 
 
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">75 millimetres thick insulated refrigeration wall panels 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Flex curtains, sliding doors, and concrete ramps to doorways and passageways 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Suspended insulated refrigeration ceiling panels 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Plumbing throughout including drains, sinks, grease pit and sewerage lines 
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Floor slabs, coverings and epoxy flooring 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Refrigeration plant including 3 head Copeland compressor and associated reticulation 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Electrical power, switchboards, reticulation and lighting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Security Systems 
 9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">All lighting including mercury vapour lighting 
 10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Fire extinguishers 
 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Hose Reels and Hoses 
 12.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Hydrants and Hoses 
 13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Carpets 
 14.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Office partitions 
 15.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Air conditioning units 
 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Hand basins 
 17.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Pans 
 18.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Kitchen equipment 
 19.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Boiler and Condensate System 
 20.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Air Compressors (1 Ecopack CA E30A and 1 Compair) 
 21.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">1 Hot Water Tank 
 22.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Wash stations and basins and sanitising stations 
 23.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">2 new fire hose reels 
 24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">5 new fire extinguishers 
 25.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Assorted pallet racking existing as at 1 September 1999 
 26.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">3 Hot Water Cylinders 
 27.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">High Pressure Grundfos Pump for hot water tank 
 28.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Steam Plant".</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">
 
 
 

13 Communications between the applicant and the first respondent in relation to an increase in rent commenced in late December 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">A letter dated 20 December 2002 was sent by Mr Allen, on behalf of the first respondent, to the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">It bore the heading "Notice of Rental Assessment commencing 1 March 2003 for 42-44 Glenvale Crescent, Mulgrave".</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">The letter was sent to the Mulgrave premises, addressed to "The Manager, Nobi Holdings Pty Ltd".</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">It was received, and stamped as such, by the applicant on 23 December 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The letter stated:
 
 "Under the terms of our lease a market review of the rent paid is to take effect from 1 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Please find enclosed the Managing Agent's letter in this regard which is self explanatory and will form the basis of the new rent starting 1 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">
 
 In due course we will correspond with you regarding the new monthly rental and the appropriate GST that will be payable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">" 
 

14 The "Managing Agent's letter" enclosed with the notice was a letter from Lynton Williams, an Associate at Colliers International (Victoria) Pty Limited (the second respondent), addressed to "John Allen, Finishing Services Pty Ltd" ("the Colliers letter").</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">It was dated 24 October 2002 and stated:
 
 "RE: 42 --- 44 GLENVALE CRESCENT, MULGRAVE 
 
 As your managing agent we draw your attention to the fact that a market value rental review is due in respect of this property on the 1 st of March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">
 
 We have investigated the current market rental levels for similar buildings that incorporate cool room and chiller facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">We report that in our opinion the market rates for the various areas are as follows: 
 
 Offices: 208 m2 x $155.00 p.sq.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">$ 32.240.00 p.a.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">
 Coolroom, etc: 2,768 m2 x $135,00 p.sq.m $373,680.00 p.a.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">
 Warehouse 400 m2 x $ 75.00 p.sq.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">$ 30,000.00 p.a.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">
 $435.920.00 p.a.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">
 
 Should you agree with the above we will notify the tenant accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">" 
 

15 It was accepted by the applicant, and by the first respondent, that the rental increase notice is constituted by the letter from Mr Allen and the Colliers letter attached to that letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Together I will refer to them as "the notice".</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">16 A relevant issue is whether the parties had any oral communication in late December.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">This goes to the applicant's claims in relation to good faith and unconscionable conduct, but also to the context in which the notice was served, and the factual matrix within which it should be construed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Mr Bertrand originally claimed that he had a telephone conversation with Mr Allen on 23 December 2002 (a Monday).</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Mr Allen denied absolutely that any such conversation had taken place on that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Indeed, he responded to Mr Bertrand's claim by pointing out that it was simply not possible for there to have been such a conversation on that date because the first respondent's factory and office had closed for the Christmas break on the afternoon of 20 December 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">Mr Bertrand then altered his position, and acknowledged that the conversation must have occurred on 20 December 2002, and not as he originally thought on 23 December 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">17 In any event, Mr Bertrand says that the purpose of the phone call was to arrange a meeting to discuss alterations to the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">He says that he and Mr Allen were unable to meet until 3 February 2003 because Mr Allen was unavailable over Christmas until 15 January, and Mr Bertrand was unavailable between 15 January 2003 and 30 January 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Mr Bertrand says he believes that the conversation would have taken place before he had read the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">During that telephone conversation, Mr Bertrand says that no mention was made of the rental increase.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">This claim by Mr Bertrand forms the core of the applicant's case on unconscionable conduct and good faith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">18 After receiving the notice, Mr Bertrand telephoned Mr Greg Finkemeyer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Mr Finkemeyer was in charge of a Lactos facility that was rented in Dingley, Victoria, and in that role, had a relationship with Jones Lang LaSalle, a large commercial real estate agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Mr Bertrand asked Mr Finkemeyer to provide him with an indication of what the current market rent would be on the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">19 In response to this request, Mr Finkemeyer sent Mr Bertrand an email on 17 January 2003, but which was not received by Mr Bertrand until after he returned from leave on 31 January 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Mr Finkemeyer stated:
 
 "I'm led to believe that the market price for Mulgrave is: 
 
 $120 per Square mt for Refrigerated/Plant space.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">
 $70 for office/dry store area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">" 
 

20 These figures would equate to an annual rental on the Mulgrave premises of $374,720, $61,200 less than the figure specified in Colliers letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">Both figures are exclusive of GST.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">21 The applicant provided the first respondent with a written response to the notice on 3 February 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">On that date, a meeting was held between the parties, primarily to discuss alterations that had taken place at the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">Mr Bertrand says the meeting was organised during the telephone conversation that he claims to have had with Mr Allen in late December.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">Mr Allen says that the meeting was organised on 3 February 2003, after Mr Bertrand called him to inform him that the applicant had made alterations at the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">At the meeting, Mr Bertrand gave Mr Allen a letter which stated:
 
 "We acknowledge receipt of your letter with the assessment by your agent of the market value for the property we rent from you in Mulgrave.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The amount of the increase you are asking for is very detrimental to our business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">Therefore we have requested an estimation from our own agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">
 
 His assessment turns out to be significantly different from your agent estimation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">His opinion on office/dry warehouse cost is $ 70 p.sq.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">and $ 120 p.sq.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">for refrigerated space.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">
 
 We would like to understand how these two numbers coming from professional agents can be so different and resolve this matter with you in due course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">" 
 

22 Both Mr Allen and Mr Bertrand agree that Mr Bertrand commented that the increase in rent would have a detrimental impact on the applicant's business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">Mr Allen says that he said words to the effect that it was "too late to complain" about the rent increase now, although Mr Bertrand says he does not have any recollection of Mr Allen's reaction to the letter he handed him at the 3 February 2003 meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">23 Following the meeting, Mr Allen sent a letter under cover of Allen &amp; Allen letterhead, dated 20 February 2003, to Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd c/o Lactos Pty Ltd in Burnie.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">It was marked to the attention of Alan Jarman, the company secretary of Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd. Mr Jarman was the person with whom Mr Allen usually corresponded in relation to matters involving the lease of the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">It relevantly stated:
 
 "Re: Lease from Finishing Services Pty Ltd 
 Premises: 42-44 Glenvale Crescent, Mulgrave 
 
 Please advise your bank to alter the telegraphic transfer commencing on 1 March 2003 in relation to the new rental for the current year at $39,959.33 per month of which $3,632.67 is the GST component.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">" 
 

24 The applicant submitted that it was of some relevance that Mr Allen had addressed the notice to the Mulgrave premises, rather than to Mr Jarman, which it contended would have been the usual course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">On the other hand, the lease itself provided for the service of a rent review notice at the demised premises, as well as the registered office of the lessee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">25 Mr Bertrand then sent a letter to Mr Allen, dated 7 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">After outlining some of the previous communications between the applicant and first respondent, it stated, amongst other things:
 
 "It is clear then that we do not have agreement as to the market rent for the premises and as such the provisions of clause 3.2.2(a) of the Lease are now operative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">
 
 We confirm our previous advices that we dispute that you have provided a proposed increase that is at market.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">We also note that you are estopped from relying on the time period set out in clause 3.2.2 due to your unavailability to meet during the relevant period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">" 
 

26 Mr Allen responded to this letter on 12 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">He stated that "[n]o written objection as required by clause 3.2.2 of the Lease was received during the 30 day period" and "[y]ou are therefore unable to dispute the rental as advised in our correspondence of 20 December 2002".</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Mr Allen indicated that Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd would be in breach of the lease if it did not pay the increased rental.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">27 On 17 March 2003, a meeting was held between Mr Bertrand and Mr Allen, at which the increase in rent was discussed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">Matthew Allen and Wayne Kelly, the plant manager for Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd, also attended the meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">Mr Bertrand offered to pay the increased rent up to a figure that it had been advised reflected market value (namely, the figure obtained by Mr Finkemeyer).</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">Mr Allen told Mr Bertrand that it was too late to object to the increase in rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">Mr Bertrand stated that Mr Allen should have told him about the 30 day deadline.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">Mr Allen rejected this suggestion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">28 Mr Bertrand deposes to a discussion at the 17 March 2003 meeting about the alleged conversation in late December, and the fact that the parties had not been able to meet all through January.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Mr Allen flatly denies that any such discussion took place during the course of the 17 March 2003 meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Both parties agree that the meeting ended with the parties deciding that the applicant should consider its position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">29 On 20 March 2003, Mr Bertrand sent a letter to Mr Allen stating "we confirm our position as set out in our letter to you of 7 March 2003".</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Mr Bertrand then stated:
 
 "Today, we have made an additional payment of $ 9,116.00.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">As such, we have now commenced paying rent at the amount set out in our letter to you of February 3, 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">This increased payment is being made as a sign of good faith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">It is, however, an interim measure pending the assessment of the correct amount.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">
 
 As such, we repeat our request that you implement the provisions of clause 3.2.2(a) of the Lease and request the Australian Institute of Valuers to nominate a member to determine the current fair market rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">" 
 

30 Mr Allen responded to this letter on 31 March 2003, stating, amongst other things:
 
 "It would appear that you totally ignored our correspondence of 12 March 2003 which was faxed to you and the original posted to you (a further copy is now enclosed).</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">
 
 As you can see from that letter we rely on the written Lease between our respective companies as one does when a dispute arises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">As you will note we rely on the Managing Agent's, Colliers International assessment of what the new rental should be --- you verbally told the writer that you were relying on a valuation from Jones Lang LaSalle and that was the basis of your letter of 3 February 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">
 
 Now in your correspondence of 20 March 2003 (even though you have adopted the new rent that you say should be payable by paying the balance into our bank account, pursuant to a Valuation from Jones Lang LaSalle) you are now out in the marketplace obtaining another assessment and I guess if that is not to your liking, you will then obtain another assessment and so on, until one is found that suits your company's needs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">
 
 Mr Bertrand, be advised that all this is what we say in the English language as "academic", that means that obtaining one assessment after another is a complete waste of your time and your company's money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">
 
 The new rent has been fixed according to the Lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Please have your company pay it without further procrastination which will stop further meetings and letter writing as my patience has nearly expired.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">" 
 

31 Mr Bertrand responded to this letter the following day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">He stated "[f]or the record, please note that we do not accept the matters put forward by you".</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">Mr Bertrand then stated that Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd would make the rental payments set out in the notice, back paid to 1 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">Mr Bertrand asserted that:
 
 "[w]e are paying these amounts under protest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">We shall now proceed to have an independent valuation obtained as set out in the lease between us.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">" 
 

32 Mr Bertrand also stated that a valuation had been requested by the applicant from Jones Lang LaSalle, however Jones Lang LaSalle had been unable to provide a valuation as they had previously done work for the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">33 Since 1 April 2003, the applicant has paid the increased rental, under protest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">It commenced proceedings in this Court on 17 December 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">THE CRITICAL ISSUES 
 
34 The critical issues to be determined in the proceeding against the first respondent are as follows:
 
 
 &#8226; was the rental increase notice vague and uncertain, and thereby invalid?</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">&#8226; was the rental increase notice invalid upon the basis that the rental assessment failed to take into account the particular assumptions that were stipulated in clause 3.2.2, as set out in [8] of these reasons for judgment?</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">&#8226; is a term of good faith to be implied into the lease and, if so, did the actions or omissions of Mr Allen surrounding the service of the notice constitute a breach of this obligation?</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">&#8226; does Mr Bertrand have some kind of "special disadvantage" by virtue of speaking English as a second language, which enlivens the principles of unconscionable conduct under s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act ?</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">
 

35 If the rental increase notice is invalid for whatever reason, the claim against the first respondent will succeed, and the claim against the second respondent goes nowhere.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">The same is true if the applicant succeeds against the first respondent on the basis of its claims of unconscionable conduct and breach of good faith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">However, if the notice is valid, and the applicant's other claims against the first respondent fail, the relevant issues to be determined with respect to the claim against the second respondent are:
 
 
 &#8226; was the Colliers letter misleading or deceptive?</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">&#8226; if so, did it cause, or contribute to, the applicant's loss?</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">
 
 THE APPLICANT'S CLAIMS 
 THE NOTICE WAS NOT A VALID NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 3.2.2 BECAUSE IT WAS VAGUE AND UNCERTAIN 
 
36 The applicant seeks a declaration that the notice was not a valid notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2 of the lease, and is of no effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">The first basis upon which the applicant claims the notice is invalid is that it was vague and uncertain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">37 The applicant relied upon a number of cases as authority for the proposition that a rental increase notice has to be clear and certain to be valid, and that such notices are construed strictly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">38 The first of these cases was Catley v Watson (1983) V ConvR |P54-003, which involved a notice of rescission served by a vendor upon a purchaser.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">In that case, "copyright condition 5" of the contract provided for the service of a notice of rescission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Brooking J stated, at 62,115:
 
 "In my opinion, a notice under copyright condition 5 is not valid unless it is, in relation to its essential features as required by that condition, clear and unambiguous.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">By this I mean, not that its import must be clear beyond the slightest peradventure, but that its terms must be such that a reasonable person, having given it fair and proper consideration, would be left in no doubt as to its meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">A notice is not unequivocal, in the sense in which such notices are required to be unequivocal in relation to their essential contents, if a reasonable person, having considered the notice as a whole, fairly and properly, might entertain a doubt as to its meaning in relation to some essential matter, even though he would form in his mind a preference for one view, rather than the other of what the notice was intended to convey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">It must be possible to say that, after the appropriate consideration, any doubts that may have arisen would have been quieted and the purchaser would not be left in any uncertainty as to the meaning of the notice...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">(emphasis added)
 

39 Plainly, Catley v Watson can be relied upon only by analogy as it concerns the requirements for a valid rescission notice and not the requirements for a valid rental review notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">40 The applicant also cited the case of Norwich Union Life Insurance Society v Tony Waller Ltd (1984) 270 EG 42.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">That case dealt with a rent review clause and a notice purportedly served pursuant to that clause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">The notice was not addressed to the tenant by its proper title and was flawed in other respects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">It was in the following terms:
 
 " Without Prejudice
 Dear Sir, 19 Fawkon Walk, Hoddesdon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">We have been instructed by your landlords, the Norwich Union Insurance Group to negotiate with you in connection with the rent review contained in your lease which becomes operative as at September 29 1982.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">
 
 It is out clients proposal to increase the rental to [sterling]11,500 per annum exclusive as from this date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">
 
 We trust that this increase is acceptable to you and would be obliged if when replying you would enclose the name and address of the solicitors who will be acting on your behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">
 
 Yours faithfully".</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">
 

41 In that case, Harman J stated, at 43:
 
 "I have been much impressed with Mr Pryor's argument that this document was in truth equivocal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">It is common ground between the parties that no specific form has to be adopted in order to constitute a trigger notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">Mr Wood's submission was that it should be a clear and unequivocal notice giving plain intimation to anyone receiving it of what it was.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Certainly, that is, in my view, the desirable state of all such notices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">But it being common ground that no special form of words is necessary --- no magic formula is involved --- the question is: trying to read it as a whole, looking at its confused terminology, its meaningless heading "Without prejudice" and its general ineptitude, is this a document which a tenant looking at it would think was a trigger notice?</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">" 
 

42 His Lordship concluded by finding, at 43, that:
 
 "although there are no magic words or magic formulae to be required before a rent review clause is invoked, ... the document does have to be clear and plain to any recipient.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">" 
 

43 The applicant also relied upon the decision of the English Court of Appeal in Shirlcar Properties Ltd v Heinitz (1983) 268 EG 362 (" Shirlcar Properties ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">That case also involved a rent review clause and "trigger" notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">The only matter at issue as to the validity of the notice was whether there was any doubt as to its meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">44 The body of the trigger notice was in the following form:
 
 "We act on behalf of your Landlords, Shirlcar Properties Ltd, and have been instructed to deal with the rent review on the above premises due as at the 29 th September 1981.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">The rent required as from the review date is [sterling]6,000 pa exclusive, and we look forward to receiving your agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">
 
 Yours faithfully".</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">
 

45 The agent's signature then followed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">However, as Lawton J explained at 363:
 
 "a difficulty has arisen because the letter did not end with the signature of the estate agents: under that signature in capital letters which were underlined came the words "subject to contract".</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Immediately below that, also in capital letters, were the words "recorded delivery".</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">" 
 

46 The tenant submitted that the words "subject to contract" meant that the notice could be read as the commencement of negotiations between the landlord and tenant, with the landlord putting forward a provisional figure which was merely a precursor to the rent review machinery under the lease being activated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">Otherwise, it was submitted, the reference to "subject to contract" did not make sense.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">47 The Court of Appeal (per Lawton, Kerr and Dillon LJJ) agreed and found the notice to be invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">The test propounded by their Lordships was whether the reasonable tenant in receipt of such a notice would be in doubt as to its meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">Lawton LJ, at 364, stated:
 
 "Since there is an argument both ways about this matter and as, in my judgment, it is an argument which is reasonable on both sides, it seems to me that it cannot be said that the tenants, on receiving this letter, would necessarily and reasonably have inferred that it was an effective trigger notice for the purpose of the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">There is doubt about its meaning and as there is doubt it seems to me that the letter was ineffective for the purposes of the rent review clause in the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">" 
 

48 Lastly, the applicant cited Central Pacific (Campus) Pty Ltd v Staged Developments Australia Pty Ltd (1998) V ConvR |P54-575 (" Central Pacific ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">That case, like Catley v Watson , involved a rescission notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">Callaway JA, with whom Buchanan JA agreed, stated at 66,909 that the relevant approach is to ask:
 
 "whether a reasonable person who had considered the notice as a whole and given it fair and proper consideration would be left in any doubt as to its meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">" 
 

49 In that case it was found that there was no ambiguity in the meaning of the notice, and therefore, the notice was valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">50 Turning to the application of these principles to this proceeding, the applicant contended that there were a number of features of the notice that would leave a reasonable person in receipt of it in doubt as to whether it was a notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2, or whether it merely conveyed to the reader that a rental review was contemplated, but would take place some time in the near future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">51 In particular, the applicant submitted that the notice would be likely to have conveyed to a reasonable person, reading it as a whole, that a rent review process was to commence on 1 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">That impression was bolstered by the reference in the heading in Mr Allen's letter to a "Rental Assessment " that would commence on that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">Indeed, it was further bolstered by the statement in Mr Allen's letter that "a market review of the rent paid is to take effect from 1 March 2003".</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">52 The applicant also relied upon the fact that Mr Allen concluded his letter by stating "[i]n due course we will correspond with you regarding the new monthly rental", thereby implying that there would be further discussions regarding the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">Finally, the applicant noted that the Colliers letter stated that "a market value rental review is due in respect of this property on the 1 st of March 2003", once again suggesting that there would be a " review " prior to any notice issuing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">Importantly, Mr Allen's letter referred to the Colliers letter, stating that it would " form the basis of" the new rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">That too was said to imply some further step having to be taken before the new rent was fixed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">53 The applicant contended that the impression that a rent review process would commence on 1 March 2003, rather than any actual requirement to pay increased rent, might have been dispelled had the notice referred specifically to clause 3.2.2, and identified itself as a notice issued under that clause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">However, nothing of that kind had been said.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">Rather, there had simply been a vague reference to a review "[u]nder the terms of our lease".</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">54 The applicant further submitted that another way in which the impression might have been dispelled was if the notice had specifically drawn the applicant's attention to its entitlement, as lessee, to dispute the new rental provided that it did so within 30 days, or alternatively, within the requisite period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">The failure to include in the notice any intimation of that type, which might have corrected an otherwise misleading impression, meant that the notice should be regarded as invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">55 The applicant acknowledged that there was no formal list of requirements that a notice must satisfy in order to be valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">Nor was there a template that a notice must fit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">Rather, each notice must be considered in the light of its own particular circumstances, and the language employed construed in a sensible and practical manner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">Nonetheless, it was submitted that where the notice was expressed in terms that were uncertain, it would require features of the kind identified above to counter that uncertainty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">56 In addition, the applicant submitted that the factual matrix within which the notice was sent should be taken into account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">This included the alleged telephone conversation on or about 20 December 2002 when, Mr Bertrand maintained, nothing was said by Mr Allen about any rental increase despite either having sent the notice on that very day, or having been about to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">The implication was that Mr Allen was acting in a manner that was less than forthright in his dealings with Mr Bertrand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">In particular, the implication was that Mr Allen hoped that the actual significance of the notice would escape Mr Bertrand's attention, and that he would not appreciate the need to object to the rental assessment figure within the requisite 30 day period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">That implication was said to be bolstered by the fact that the notice was sent on virtually the last working day before Christmas, and addressed to the applicant at the Mulgrave premises rather than to Mr Jarman, as would normally be the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">57 The applicant contended that given that the notice was itself at least ambiguous, the fact that a meeting had been arranged when the notice was sent for a date after the 30 day period (if I accept Mr Bertrand's evidence) lends further weight to the impression that the notice was not a notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">Rather, the applicant submitted, this supported its contention that the notice was merely an indication that some kind of review process would occur in the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">The applicant contended that a reasonable person in Mr Bertrand's position, reading the notice on 23 December 2002, would have in the back of his or her mind that there was to be a meeting with Mr Allen in early February, and construe the notice accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">58 In addition, the applicant contended that I should also take into account, in considering the factual matrix within which the notice was read, the fact that Mr Bertrand, although a professional and experienced businessman, spoke English as a second language and not entirely fluently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">THE NOTICE WAS NOT A VALID NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 3.2.2 BECAUSE IT DID NOT COMPLY WITH THE SUBSTANTIVE REQUIREMENTS OF CLAUSE 3.2.2 
 
59 The second basis upon which the applicant claimed that the notice was invalid was that it did not comply with the substantive requirements of clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">60 Clause 3.2.2 provides that the notice must state the sum which the lessor "assesses to be the proper rent for the premises for the ensuing period such rent being the market rental value for the premises on the assumption that the premises are tenanted and with all fixtures and fittings and partitions, plant machinery utensils shelving safes and other articles and materials as set out in schedule 2 installed by either the Lessor or the Lessee and having regard to the rents being obtained for comparable premises within the same municipality ...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">61 First, the applicant submitted that the notice did not contain a statement of the lessor's assessment of the proper rent because the rent stated in the notice was known by the first respondent to be clearly excessive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">62 Second, the applicant submitted that Mr Allen failed to assess the "proper rent" because he did not make the assumptions required by clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">The applicant placed particular emphasis upon the submission that the assessment had in fact included all fixtures and fittings within the Mulgrave premises, and not just those set out in schedule 2, as it claimed was specifically required by the terms of clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">Because there were additional fixtures and fittings, beyond those identified in that clause, that had been taken into account by Mr Allen, it was submitted that this had the effect of inflating the valuation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">63 The applicant contended that once it had established that the first respondent had not made the required assumptions, the onus was on the first respondent to demonstrate that these errors were immaterial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">In the applicant's submission, the first respondent had failed to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">64 I note at this stage that there is an issue between the parties as to whether the claim in relation to the fixtures and fittings was adequately pleaded by the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">I will deal with that question separately in these reasons for judgment at [106]-[124].</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">IMPLIED TERM OF GOOD FAITH 
 
65 The applicant referred to the numerous cases dealing with the implied contractual duty of good faith and fair dealing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">It submitted that where a clause gives a party more power than is legitimately needed to protect its interests, then, a duty of good faith should be implied into the exercise of that power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">It relied upon the decision of Sheller JA in Alcatel Australia Ltd v Scarcella (1998) 44 NSWLR 349 in support of this proposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">Like this proceeding, that case also involved a commercial lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">His Honour stated, at 368:
 
 "If a contract confers power on a contracting party in terms wider than necessary for the protection of the legitimate interests of that party, the courts may interpret the power as not extending to the action proposed by the party in whom the power is vested or, alternatively, conclude that the powers are being exercised in a capricious or arbitrary manner or for an extraneous purpose, which is another way of saying the same thing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">Thus, a vendor may not be allowed to exercise a contractual power where it would be unconscionable in the circumstances to do so...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">
 

66 The applicant's contentions in relation to good faith are only of relevance if the notice is found to be valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">The applicant noted that if the notice was found to be valid, the effect of clause 3.2.2 would be to give the landlord a wide power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">Therefore, so the applicant claimed, clause 3.2.2 is the type of clause in relation to which a duty of good faith should be implied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">67 The applicant submitted that the implied duty of good faith and fair dealing was breached by the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">It contended that the first respondent breached this duty through a combination of actions and omissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">First of these were the deficiencies in the notice, both in terms of its alleged vagueness and its substantive shortcomings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">This was combined with sending the letter just before Christmas where, so the applicant says, a meeting had been arranged between the parties after the expiration of the 30 day period, and when the applicant says, to the knowledge of the first respondent, the 30 day period would expire when Mr Bertrand was on leave.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">The applicant also adds to these circumstances the fact that the notice was sent to Mr Bertrand, who Mr Allen know did not speak English as his first language, instead of Mr Jarman, to whom notices and other correspondence relating to the Mulgrave premises had always previously been sent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">UNCONSCIONABLE CONDUCT 
 
68 This ground can be briefly summarised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">The applicant claimed that the first respondent had acted unconscionably in breach of s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">It claimed that the relevant "special disadvantage" in this case was that Mr Bertrand spoke English as a second language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">The applicant contended that the first respondent engaged in unconscionable conduct by sending the kind of letter it did, in the circumstances it did, to Mr Bertrand, who it knew did not speak English fluently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">MISLEADING OR DECEPTIVE CONDUCT BY THE SECOND RESPONDENT 
 
69 The applicant submitted that the second respondent did not honestly, and with proper foundation, hold the opinion that the market rent for the Mulgrave premises was $435,920, as was stated in the Colliers letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">In particular, the applicant contended that Mr Allen asked Mr Williams to provide a formal valuation of the market rent for the Mulgrave premises, and that Mr Williams made the same error as Mr Allen in assessing the rent by including all the fixtures and fittings, rather than those actually specified in schedule 2 to the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">The applicant claimed that the evidence given by Mr Williams in terms of the work he did in preparing the Colliers assessment supported its contention that he had not formed an honest and reasonable opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">70 The claim by the applicant is somewhat unorthodox in terms of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">The applicant did not claim that it was misled by the second respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">Rather, it claimed that it was the first respondent who was misled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">The applicant contended that it was sufficient for it to demonstrate that the first respondent relied upon the relevant conduct and that the applicant suffered loss and damage by reason of that reliance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">The applicant also submitted that it was not necessary for it to show that the misleading or deceptive conduct was the sole cause of the loss of damage suffered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">71 Alternatively, the applicant claimed that if the first respondent did not rely upon the opinion of the second respondent, the notice must therefore be invalid, as it could not constitute the first respondent's assessment of the proper rent for the Mulgrave premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">THE FIRST RESPONDENT'S SUBMISSIONS 
 
72 The first respondent submitted that this case could be viewed very simply.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">The first respondent sent the applicant a valid notice under clause 3.2.2 of the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">Under the lease the applicant had 30 days within which to object to this notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">The applicant failed to make such an objection and, as such, the rent proposed in the notice had automatically become the new rent payable under the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">73 I will address the first respondent's contentions in response to each of the applicant's claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">THE NOTICE WAS NOT A VALID NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 3.2.2 BECAUSE IT WAS VAGUE AND UNCERTAIN 
 
74 The first respondent submitted that the notice must be construed objectively and in context: Carradine Properties Ltd v Aslam [1976] 1 WLR 442 and Mannai Investment Co Ltd v Eagle Star Life Assurance Co Ltd [1997] UKHL 19 ; [1997] AC 749 at 767 (" Mannai ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">The first respondent also submitted that a reasonable recipient is to be credited with knowledge of the terms of the lease: Mannai .</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">See also MLW Technology Pty Ltd v May [2004] VSCA 29.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">75 Mannai involved two identical notices served in relation to two leases with provisions that were relevantly identical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">The notices were served by a tenant pursuant to a break clause in the leases which allowed the tenant to terminate the lease on six months notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">The notices erroneously specified that the lease was to be terminated on 12 January 1995.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">Under the leases, the tenant was only entitled to terminate on 13 January 1995 (the anniversary of the commencement of each lease).</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">The House of Lords, by a majority of three to two, expressly overruled a line of authority which held that even minor, technical shortcomings in a notice invalidated that notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">76 Their Lordships held that the reasonable recipient of the notice, who was apprised of the fact that the lease commenced upon 13 January and was determinable on that date, would have understood that the reference to 12 January in the notice was a "minor misdescription".</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">77 Lord Steyn stated the relevant test to be applied as follows at 767:
 
 "The question is not how the landlord understood the notices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">The construction of the notices must be approached objectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">The issue is how a reasonable recipient would have understood the notices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">And in considering this question the notices must be construed taking into account the relevant objective contextual scene.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">" 
 

78 Lord Hoffman said at 774-5:
 
 "The reasonable recipient will see that in purporting to terminate pursuant to clause 7(13) but naming 12 January 1995 as the day upon which he will do so, the tenant has made a mistake.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">He will reject as too improbable the possibility that the tenant meant that unless he could terminate on 12 January, he did not want to terminate at all.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">He will therefore understand the notice to mean that the tenant wants to terminate on the date on which, in accordance with clause 7(13), he may do so, i.e.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">13 January.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">" 
 

79 Against that background, the first respondent pointed to the following features of the notice in this proceeding:
 
 
 &#8226; it specified as its subject matter "Notice of Rental Assessment commencing 1 March 2003";
 &#8226; it directed the recipient's attention to the fact that "[u]nder the terms of our lease a market review of the rent paid is to take effect from 1 March 2003";
 &#8226; the Collier's letter (which forms part of the notice) stated that "a market value rental review is due in respect of this property on the 1 st of March 2003"; and
 &#8226; it "stated" the sum of $435,920.00 per annum "will form the basis of the new rent starting 1 March 2003".</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">
 

80 The first respondent submitted that a reasonable recipient, who had knowledge of the terms of the lease, would have regarded the notice as a "trigger notice" pursuant to clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">81 In support of this contention, the first respondent submitted that the notice closely resembled the rent review notice in Amalgamated Estates Ltd v Joystretch Manufacturing Ltd (1980) 257 EG 489 (" Amalgamated Estates ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">That notice was in the following terms:
 
 "Dear Sirs, Re: 14 Regent Street and 3 Bank Street, Rugby.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">Pursuant to the terms of your Lease of the above premises dated December 7 1973, we hereby give you notice that we require a review of the yearly rental payable thereunder as from December 10 1978.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">We specify that the new rent payable as from December 10 1978 will be [sterling]10,000 per annum exclusive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">This rent is proportionally in line with our recent lettings and reviews of other premises in the area with similar accommodation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">
 
 Please would you kindly acknowledge safe receipt of this notice by signing the enclosed copy notice and returning it in the stamped addressed envelope provided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">" 
 

82 The notice in Amalgamated Estates was upheld as being valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">I shall return to Amalgamated Estates , and whether the reasoning in that case is applicable to the present proceeding later in these reasons for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">THE NOTICE WAS NOT A VALID NOTICE UNDER CLAUSE 3.2.2 BECAUSE IT DID NOT COMPLY WITH THE SUBSTANTIVE REQUIREMENTS OF CLAUSE 3.2.2 
 
83 The first respondent contended that the only substantive requirement of clause 3.2.2 is that the lessor subjectively assess the "proper rent for the premises" as defined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">There is no requirement that this assessment be objectively "reasonable".</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">84 The first respondent relied upon a number of cases with comparable rent review clauses to support the proposition that all that the landlord must do is specify its subjective assessment of the rent --- it is up to the tenant to object.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">85 In GR Mailman &amp; Associates Pty Ltd v Wormald (Aust) Pty Ltd (1991) 24 NSWLR 80 (" Mailman "), the rent review clause, art 2.02(a), was in the following terms:
 
 "Within sixty days (60) prior to the expiration of each period specified ... the Lessor may give in writing, in the form set out hereunder, to the Lessee increasing the yearly rental to an amount which the Lessor considers will be the current market rent of the Demised Premises as at the Review Date and until the following Review Date or the expiration of the term as the case may be ... having regard to all matters then relevant to the determination of such rent including the terms and conditions of this Lease and in particular the fact that the Lessee is obliged to pay to the Lessor the Outgoings provided in Article 3 thereof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">" 
 

86 In that case, Gleeson CJ stated, at 89:
 
 "The lease also (in art 2.02(d)) states the consequences of the failure of the lessee to serve a counter-notice within the specified time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">The lessee is deemed to have agreed upon the current market rent for the next review period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">... 
 
 Moreover, the rent that is deemed to be the current market rent may be quite different from the actual market rent, at least so long as the lessor subjectively holds the belief referred to in art 2.02(a) .</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">" (emphasis added)
 

87 The first respondent also relied upon Amalgamated Estates in relation to the claim that the notice did not comply with the substantive requirements of clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">In Amalgamated Estates the obligation was to pay "open market rental".</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">The rent review clause (clause 3(a)) provided that "open market rental" was first to be determined in the following manner, namely:
 
 "specified in notice in writing signed by or on behalf of the Landlord and posted ... to the Tenant at the demised premises..." 
 

88 The lease then provided for the lessee to serve a "counter-notice" if it objected to the rent specified by the landlord in the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">In that case, Lawton LJ, with whom both Templeman LJ and O'Connor LJ agreed, stated at 491:
 
 "There are two questions, therefore, for decision in this case: (1) should there be implied into clause 3(a) of the proviso words to the effect set out in the defence, namely, that the sum specified by the landlords should be a bona fide and genuine pre-estimate of the open market rental value?</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">... 
 
 As to the first point, I have no doubt at all that the words which, it was submitted, should be read into clause 3(a) cannot be so read.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">The proviso deals with definitions and procedure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">Clause (1) of the proviso provides that the open market rental must be a rent which might reasonably be demanded by a willing landlord, etc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">Clause (3) sets out how that reasonable rent is to be fixed and it is to be done in three stages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">First, the landlord is to specify his figure; then there are to be negotiations for an agreement if his figure is not at once accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">That is clear from clause 3(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">If there is no agreement then there is to be arbitration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">It is after all those steps have been taken that a reasonable rent is to be ascertained; and I can see no room at all in this lease for implying that the figure specified by the landlord must start with a bona fide and genuine pre-estimate of the rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">" 
 

89 Similarly, Templeman LJ stated at 493:
 
 "The first point made by Mr de la Piquerie for the tenant is that there must be an implied term that the landlord will only specify a bona fide and genuine pre-estimate of the open market rental value.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">That appears to me to be an unnecessary and unworkable proposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">If a landlord puts forward a preposterous figure for rent, the tenant can always serve a counternotice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">It would be ludicrous if the court were obliged to decide whether the landlord's figure was a bona fide and genuine pre-estimate in order to decide whether the landlord's request for an increased rent was valid or wholly void.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">The court does not exist to punish a landlord for being greedy, especially as the definition of "greed" varies from Shylock to Portia and from landlord to tenant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">" 
 

90 The first respondent contended that challenges similar to that made by the applicant in the present proceeding had been unsuccessful in other cases, such as Fox &amp; Widley v Guran [1998] 3 EG 142 (a case where the submission that the landlord was required to estimate a "bona fide and genuine" assessment in a rent review notice was rejected) and Davstone (Holdings) Ltd v Al-Rifai (1976) 32 P&amp;CR 18 at 26 (a case which concerned whether there was an obligation upon a landlord to specify an objectively "reasonable" figure in a rent review notice).</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">91 In terms of the applicant's specific submission that the notice was invalid because the first respondent failed to have regard only to the fixtures and fittings outlined in schedule 2 of the lease, the respondents contended that this aspect of the applicant's case was not pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">Accordingly, they argued that the applicant required leave to amend its statement of claim if it wished to pursue this aspect of its application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">I deal with the question of whether amendment is required below.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">92 However, the first respondent submitted that even if this matter is adequately pleaded or, alternatively, if such leave is granted, the applicant's construction of clause 3.2.2 is flawed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">The first respondent contended that if clause 3.2.2 does objectively require the landlord to carry out the rental assessment on a certain basis, it is to take into account all "fixtures and fittings and partitions, plant machinery utensils shelving safes" and "other articles and materials as set out in schedule 2".</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">That is, the reference to schedule 2 only qualifies the reference to "other articles and materials".</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">The second respondent made substantially the same submission in relation to this construction of clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">IMPLIED TERM OF GOOD FAITH 
 
93 The first respondent contended that for a term to be implied, it must be "reasonable and necessary": Byrne v Australian Airlines Limited [1995] HCA 24 ; (1995) 185 CLR 410 at 450.</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">The first respondent submitted that an implied term of good faith was neither reasonable nor necessary in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">It submitted that the mechanism established by the lease, allowing the lessor to nominate the rental assessment and the lessee to object, contemplates that the rent specified in the lessor's rental assessment may not be reasonable, or otherwise acceptable to the lessee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">The first respondent submitted that the presence of the objection mechanism demonstrates that no such implied term is necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">94 The first respondent contended that the implication of such a term would alter the effect of the rent review mechanism agreed to, as it would enable a lessee to ignore a notice and "embark upon a curial challenge".</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">95 Even if such a term were to be implied, the first respondent submitted that the content of that term would require nothing more of the first respondent than that the rental assessment contained in the notice be an honestly held opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">The first respondent submitted that the evidence supports the contention that the assessment contained in the notice represented the honest opinion of Mr Allen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">UNCONSCIONABLE CONDUCT 
 
96 The first respondent challenged the unconscionable conduct claim on a number of bases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">First, it contended that the applicant was under no "special disadvantage" when it received the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">Second, as outlined above, the first respondent denied the applicant's assertions that there was any conversation to arrange a meeting on either 20 or 23 December 2002, one of the circumstances the applicant argued as going to Mr Allen acting unconscionably.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">Third, the first respondent contended that even if the applicant's factual submissions are accepted, the circumstances surrounding the sending of the notice did not constitute unconscionable conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">97 In addition, the first respondent submitted that the applicant had not established that the allegations of unconscionable conduct caused the applicant's loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">The first respondent contended that there is no evidence as to what Mr Jarman would have done if the notice had been sent to him, rather than Mr Bertrand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">Nor is there any evidence, the respondent submitted, that Mr Bertrand would have done anything differently had he received the notice earlier, or had the notice stated explicitly that it was a notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2 of the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">THE SECOND RESPONDENT'S SUBMISSIONS 
 
98 The second respondent submitted that the Colliers letter was not misleading, that it was not relied upon by the applicant, that the applicant cannot base its cause of action upon the first respondent's reliance on the Colliers letter, and that the relevant representations did not cause the applicant's loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">99 The second respondent argued that Mr Williams was asked by Mr Allen for a "ball park" figure only, and that Mr Williams relied upon information provided by Mr Allen to inform the opinion expressed in the letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">The second respondent contended that all that was required of Mr Williams was that the opinion he expressed was honestly held and had a proper foundation: Orion Pet Products Pty Ltd v Royal Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Vic) Inc [2002] FCA 860 ; (2002) 120 FCR 191 at 213.</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">The second respondent submitted that Mr Williams' opinion was honestly held, and that he had a proper foundation for the opinion, namely the regard he had to comparable developments at Caribbean Gardens and a development called the "Pellicano development".</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">It contended that Mr Williams was not required to undertake a detailed independent valuation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">The relevant "standard" in terms of a proper foundation for the opinion was that of a real estate agent, rather than that of an independent valuer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">Mr Williams is a real estate agent and could never provide a detailed, independent valuation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">100 In any event, the second respondent submitted that the figure provided by Mr Williams was within a permissible range of latitude that is appropriate for an "assessment" of this kind (14%), to that provided by Mr Finkemeyer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">As such, the Colliers letter cannot be considered misleading.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">101 Should the Colliers letter be found to be misleading or deceptive conduct under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act , the second respondent contended that it is not sufficient for the applicant to claim that the first respondent relied on the representation in order to make out a claim for damages under s 82 of the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">102 The second respondent submitted that relief for third party reliance on misleading or deceptive conduct is only available in the limited circumstance where the contravention was a "sine qua non" of the claimant entering into a transaction .</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">It relied upon the statement by Hill, Sackville and Katz JJ in McCarthy v McIntyre [1999] FCA 784 at [50] in support of this submission:
 
 "Where a claimant is able to show that, but for the misleading or deceptive conduct, he or she would not have entered into a transaction, then such loss as flows directly to the claimant from the transaction will satisfy the requirement of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">This is so where the claimant relies upon the misleading or deceptive conduct (the usual case).</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">It is also so where a third party whose action was a sina qua non of the entry by the claimant into the transaction (the present case as alleged) relies upon the misleading or deceptive conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">" 
 

103 No such transaction was entered into by the applicant, and nor, according to the second respondent, did the applicant itself rely upon the representation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">104 Further, the second respondent contended that if relief is more generally available for third party reliance in the circumstances of this case, the applicant's loss was not caused by the conduct of Colliers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">Rather, the second respondent submitted that the applicant's loss was caused by their own failure to object to the notice, and/or the unconscionable conduct of the first respondent or its breach of the implied term of good faith, if indeed these causes of action are established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">105 The second respondent acknowledged that negligence on behalf of the "victim" is not a "defence" to a s 52 contravention (although I note that the Act has now been amended such that "contributory negligence" can be taken into account so as to reduce damages under s 82).</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">However, the second respondent contended that this proposition does not apply where the conduct of the "victim" destroys the causal connection between the contravention of the Act, and the loss or damage suffered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">In other words, the second respondent submitted that the applicant's failure to respond to the notice constituted a novus actus interveniens that broke the chain of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">IS LEAVE TO AMEND REQUIRED FOR THE APPLICANT TO PLEAD ITS CASE IN RELATION TO THE SUBSTANTIVE REQUIREMENTS OF CLAUSE 3.2.2?</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">
 
106 As previously mentioned, the respondents submitted that the applicant did not adequately plead the claim that the notice is invalid because it failed to assess the rent on the assumption that only the fixtures and fittings in schedule 2 were to be taken into account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">Nor, according to the respondents, had the claim been opened, or supported by any evidence specifically adduced in relation to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">As such, the respondents contended that the applicant is required to seek leave to amend its statement of claim in order to pursue this claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">The respondents opposed any such leave being granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">107 The applicant argued that this claim was adequately pleaded, and therefore no amendment to its statement of claim was necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">Alternatively, should I consider that an amendment was necessary, the applicant submitted that a "minor amendment" should be permitted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">108 The applicant identified a number of aspects of its statement of claim which it said demonstrated that the claim was adequately pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">The statement of claim outlined certain terms of the lease, and in doing so, it reproduced the section of clause 3.2.2 that is set out above at [8] of these reasons for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">At [11] of the statement of claim, the applicant pleaded:
 
 "The Purported Notice did not state the proper rent for the Premises for the period from 1 March 2003 such rent being the market rental value for the Premises having regard to the rents being obtained for comparable premises within the same municipality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">" 
 

109 At [12] of the statement of claim, the applicant pleaded:
 
 "The sum stated in the Purported Notice did not constitute any assessment by the Lessor, alternatively the Lessor's reasonable assessment of the proper rent for the Premises for the period ensuing from 1 March 2003 such rent being the market rent or value for the premises having regard to the rents being obtained for comparable premises within the same municipality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">" 
 

110 The particulars to these claims make no reference to schedule 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">111 The applicant also pointed to [15] to [18] of the statement of claim which pleaded that the notice was not a valid notice by virtue of the matters alleged in a number of earlier paragraphs of the pleading, none of which mention schedule 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">112 The applicant acknowledged that its statement of claim focuses on the requirement that the rental assessment have regard to comparable premises, but contended that "that issue itself exposes the question of fixtures, fittings, plant and machinery".</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">It submitted that referring generally to clause 3.2.2, the validity of the notice, and the "excessive nature" of the increase in rent, sufficiently raises the issue of the nature and value of the fixtures, fittings, plant and machinery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">113 The applicant submitted that it was unable to plead this matter with more specificity because it was only at trial that the respondents asserted that the increase in rent was justified by the fact that the starting rental (in 1999) did not take into account the lessor's ownership of fixtures and fittings, whereas the rental specified in the notice did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">The applicant submitted that neither respondent pleaded this as a factor justifying the increase in rent, and it was a matter within the knowledge of the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">114 If leave to amend is required, the respondents oppose that application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">Curiously, the second respondent provided more detailed submissions as to why the application should be refused than did the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">I say "curiously" because, in one sense, it is to the second respondent's advantage if the applicant's case that the notice is invalid is strengthened by reliance upon the argument that Mr Allen had regard to the fixtures and fittings set out in schedule 2, but included in his thinking other fixtures and fittings that increased the overall valuation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">115 The second respondent gave numerous examples of cases where it said leave to amend in similar circumstances had been refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">See Lewis v Sydney Flour Pty Ltd (1956) 56 SR (NSW) 189, Burnham v City of Mordialloc [1956] VLR 239, Ralph v Strutton [1969] Qd R 348 and Mercantile Mutual Insurance (Australia) Ltd v Farrington (1996) 44 NSWLR 634.</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">116 The second respondent submitted that pleadings may be amended after the close of evidence provided that any new facts raised by the amendment were the subject of evidence and the other party had an opportunity to litigate them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">It contended that this case was not one where an amendment should be permitted so that the pleadings reflect the conduct of the trial and the issues litigated between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">Rather, the second respondent "cast its defence in a particular way on the basis of one case and is now faced with a different case that it may have fought differently".</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">See EFM Pty Ltd v New Zealand Steel (Aust) Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 290 at [24] per Warren J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">As such, the second respondent claimed that it would be prejudiced should an amendment be allowed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">It said that had this matter been pleaded, it could have cross-examined Mr Jarman or Mr Bertrand as to the value of the fixtures and fittings that are additional to those set out in schedule 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">117 The applicant submitted in closing that the onus lies upon the respondents to prove that the alleged misconstruction of clause 3.2.2 was not material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">Although the respondents both objected to this proposition, if it were held to be correct, the second respondent submitted that it has not had the opportunity to lead evidence as to the value of the "additional" fixtures and fittings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">118 The first respondent also submitted that it would have called additional evidence, and further cross-examined witnesses had this matter been pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">In particular, it said that it would have led additional evidence from Mr Allen in relation to his state of mind as to the inclusion of fixtures and fittings at the time he served the notice, would have cross-examined the applicant's witnesses as to the value of the fixtures and fittings falling outside of schedule 2, and would have considered calling further valuation evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">119 In response, the applicant submitted that from the time during the trial that Mr Allen gave evidence he was not required to ignore fixtures and fittings other than those identified in schedule 2, it was clear that the applicant contended that this was a basis for invalidity of the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">It relied upon the statement of the Stephen, Mason and Jacobs JJ in Leotta v Public Transport Commission (NSW) (1976) 9 ALR 437, at 446, where their Honours said:
 
 "If in the cause of action upon which the plaintiff sued there had emerged at the conclusion of the evidence facts which, if accepted, established that cause of action, then it was the duty of the trial judge to leave the issue of negligence to the jury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">The pleadings should have been amended in order to make the facts alleged and the particulars of negligence precisely conform to the evidence which had emerged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">... Now, and for many years past, a plaintiff does not fail by being refused leave to amend or through failure formally to apply for amendment, where the evidence has disclosed a case in the cause of action fit to be determined by the tribunal of fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">Particularly is this so when the action finally determines the rights of the parties in the cause of action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">" 
 

120 In my view, it is clear that the applicant's case that the notice is invalid because it included all the fixtures and fittings in the rental assessment, was not adequately pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">In the paragraphs of the pleading extracted above which claim the notice is invalid, there is no reference to fixtures and fittings or to schedule 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">Moreover, these paragraphs expressly focus upon another criterion upon which the proper rent is to be assessed, namely regard being had to comparable premises in the municipality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">As such, fixtures and fittings are expressly excluded from the question of whether the rent was invalidly assessed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">Accordingly, the applicant requires leave to amend its statement of claim to plead this aspect of its case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">121 Whether I should grant such leave after the conclusion of evidence is a thorny issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">The respondents have both claimed that to do so will prejudice their case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">They say, with some force, that they would have presented their case differently, including possibly leading new evidence, had the pleading been amended earlier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">However, the reasons the applicant gives for not pleading this claim earlier are persuasive as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">There is weight in the applicant's submission that these were matters within the knowledge of the first respondent, and that they only arose in the course of Mr Allen's cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">As such, the applicant was in no position to either plead, or open, in relation to this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">122 Amendments to pleadings should be allowed if it would not be unjust to do so: see National Australia Bank Ltd v Nobile (1988) 100 ALR 227 at 235-6 per Davies J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">In my view, that test cannot be satisfied in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">The fact is that the respondents have been denied the opportunity to put on further evidence as to the value of the additional fixtures and fittings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">They would be prejudiced if an amendment were allowed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">Accordingly, leave to amend the further amended statement of claim is denied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">123 The appropriate course for the applicant to have taken was for it to have sought leave to amend its statement of claim after the conclusion of Mr Allen's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">It was during that evidence that the applicant contended it became clear that it would rely upon this ground as a basis for invalidity of the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">By doing this, it may have avoided the prejudice it now claims it will suffer as a result of the pleadings not reflecting its claims in relation to the fixtures and fittings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">124 In any event, I would decline the application for leave to amend in part on the basis that the applicant's submission regarding the proper construction of clause 3.2.2 is by no means compelling (though it is plainly arguable).</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">It is clear that the strength of the applicant's case, in relation to the proposed amendment, is a relevant consideration when determining whether to grant leave to amend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">Had the applicant demonstrated a stronger case, regarding this issue, I may have been minded to allow the applicant to reopen its case, and the respondents to adduce further evidence in response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s430">When all that can be said is that there is an arguable case, the balance of convenience weighs against adopting that course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s431">THE CONTROVERSIAL EVIDENCE 
 
125 There are a number of issues where the evidence of the applicant and the respondents was in conflict.</sentence>
<sentence id="s432">They include whether Mr Bertrand and Mr Allen had a conversation on or about 20 December 2002, and if so, what the substance of that conversation was, and how to treat the expert valuation evidence given before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s433">These evidential issues go to the applicant's claims of unconscionable conduct, breach of good faith and whether the "proper rent" was stated in the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s434">126 Ultimately, as will become apparent in my conclusions, it is unnecessary to come to a final conclusion regarding these matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s435">It is sufficient, for present purposes, to say that had this case turned entirely upon whether Mr Bertrand's account of the alleged telephone conversation with Mr Allen, on or about 20 December 2002, should be accepted, or whether Mr Allen's firm denial of any such conversation should be preferred, I would not have found in favour of the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s436">In other words, I would not have found, on the balance of probabilities, that Mr Bertrand's evidence should be accepted in preference to that of Mr Allen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s437">127 That does not mean, of course, that I positively disbelieved Mr Bertrand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s438">It reflects nothing more than an inability to be satisfied, on the balance of probabilities, that his version was correct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s439">128 It is also unnecessary to resolve what fixtures and fittings Mr Allen took into account when making his rental assessment, given my ruling in relation to the amendment of the statement of claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s440">CONCLUSIONS 
 WAS THE FORM OF THE NOTICE VALID?</sentence>
<sentence id="s441">
 
129 The test to be applied to determine the validity of the notice is whether a reasonable recipient, who is credited with knowledge of the terms of the lease, and taking into account the surrounding circumstances, would have doubt as to the meaning of the notice or have regarded it as equivocal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s442">If so, the notice will be found to be invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s443">130 Since Mannai , that test has been repeatedly applied in English courts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s444">See, for example, the recent decision of the Court of Appeal in Lancecrest Limited v Asiwaju [2005] EWCA Civ 117 (" Lancecrest ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s445">The test has been applied in this Court in Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Metro on George Pty Ltd (2004) 210 ALR 244 per Bennett J (in the context of a notice of termination).</sentence>
<sentence id="s446">It has also been applied by the Victorian Court of Appeal in MLW Technology Pty Ltd v May [2005] VSCA 29 (in the context of a notice seeking enforcement of a term of a contract), by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Etlis v New Age Constructions (NSW) Pty Ltd [2005] NSWCA 165 (in the context of a notice triggering an extension of time in relation to building work), and in the Supreme Court of New South Wales in McIntyre v Marshall [2004] NSWSC 412 (a vendor's notice to complete), Gibbins Thomson Pty Ltd v Council of the City of Liverpool [2004] NSWSC 1172 (a notice of failure to meet obligations under the contract), and Heaps v Addison Wesley Longman [1999] NSWSC 1093 (a notice from a tenant requesting the appointment of a second valuer in relation to a rent review).</sentence>
<sentence id="s447">131 The authorities recognise that the application of this test can be a question of impression.</sentence>
<sentence id="s448">It can also turn upon the facts of the individual case and the terms of the specific clause under which the notice is issued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s449">132 The test laid down in Mannai is consistent with approaches taken to the validity of notices, or analogous documents, outside of contract law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s450">For instance, in Beneficial Finance Corporation v Commissioner of Australian Federal Police (1991) 31 FCR 523, Burchett J warned, at 533, against adopting an "overly technical view" in considering the validity of search warrants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s451">He stated, at 544, that in relation to the search warrants at issue in that case, "[t]he language may be infelicitous", however the nature of the offences specified in the search warrants was clear, and the search warrants were therefore valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s452">His Honour cited, at 543, New Zealand authority which adopted the test of what a "reasonable reader" would "gather" from the search warrants to determine whether they sufficiently indicated the offence involved: see Rural Timber Ltd v Hughes [1989] 3 NZLR 178.</sentence>
<sentence id="s453">133 I note that bankruptcy notices arguably constitute an exception to this approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s454">In Australian Steel Company (Operations) Pty Ltd v Lewis [2000] FCA 1915 ; (2001) 109 FCR 33, the majority in a specially constituted court of five (Black CJ, Heerey and Sundberg JJ, Lee and Gyles JJ dissenting) held that the misstatement in a bankruptcy notice of the statutory provision under which interest was being claimed served to invalidate the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s455">This was so even though the correct sum of interest was claimed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s456">The majority found that it was irrelevant whether a debtor might be misled or not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s457">Their Honours came to this view on the basis that the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth) made the requirement to specify the relevant legislative provision essential.</sentence>
<sentence id="s458">In my view, such an approach is not relevant to these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s459">In any event, it would only make it more difficult for the first respondent to establish the validity of the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s460">134 The applicant and first respondent both agree that the notice in this proceeding must be considered as a composite of the letter from Mr Allen addressed to the Manager of Nobi Holdings, and the Colliers letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s461">The applicant acknowledged, correctly in my view, that the notice did not need to refer to clause 3.2.2, and did not have to inform the recipient of the 30 day period within which to object to the increased rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s462">Nor did it have to adopt any particular form of words to be valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s463">135 Even taking this into account, I am unable to find that the notice satisfies the relevant test of validity, as outlined above at [129].</sentence>
<sentence id="s464">In my view, the notice is not expressed unequivocally and would leave a reasonable person in receipt thereof in doubt as to its effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s465">136 The letter refers to the market review, and then proceeds to refer to the Collier's letter "in this regard" which is said to be "self explanatory" and "will form the basis of the new rent".</sentence>
<sentence id="s466">It does not state a particular figure, nor does it say what the Lessor "specifies" or even "proposes" to be the new rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s467">The Colliers letter gives an opinion as to the market rates applicable to the Mulgrave premises, and then goes on to say "[s]hould you agree with the above we will notify the tenant accordingly".</sentence>
<sentence id="s468">Mr Allen's letter ends by stating "[i]n due course we will correspond with you regarding the new monthly rental".</sentence>
<sentence id="s469">137 In my view, reading the notice as a whole, but particularly the reference to the "self explanatory" Colliers letter (which itself refers to corresponding with the tenant in due course), would create sufficient doubt in the mind of a reasonable recipient as to make the notice invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s470">Any reasonable tenant apprised of the terms of the lease would, in reality, need to get some confirmation from the landlord as to whether this was, or was not, a notice under clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s471">It is quite possible, as the applicant submitted, that the notice could have been construed as constituting some sort of preliminary step prior to the activation of the formal rent review machinery under the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s472">138 I make these findings without coming to any conclusion as to whether Mr Bertrand and Mr Allen arranged the 3 February 2003 meeting at the end of December, which the applicant submitted went to the context within which the notice should be interpreted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s473">139 I accept that had Mr Bertrand been aware of the rent review clause in the lease (which he acknowledged he was not when he received the notice), it is probable that he would done something about it, rather than waiting until a meeting in early February to address the issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s474">Under cross-examination, Mr Bertrand acknowledged that the first time he looked at the lease was immediately prior to the 3 February meeting, and it was at this stage that he first realised that there was a 30 day time limit to object to rent review notices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s475">Mr Bertrand said that he did not look at the lease before this time because, in his mind, 1 March 2003 was the date by which he had to do something.</sentence>
<sentence id="s476">140 Also under cross-examination, it was suggested to Mr Bertrand that when he received the notice, he could have:
 
 "readily gone out and said, "Well, what does the lease say about market review?</sentence>
<sentence id="s477">" Couldn't you?</sentence>
<sentence id="s478">" 
 

141 Mr Bertrand replied that he wished he had done this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s479">However, it was not clear whether he was suggesting that if he had done so, he would have appreciated that the notice was a notice under clause 3.2.2, or whether he would have contacted Mr Allen to find out whether the notice was intended to be a notice under clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s480">142 In any event, the correct test to apply is not whether there is enough in a notice to put a reasonable tenant on inquiry to find out if a notice was indeed intended by the lessor to be a notice under 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s481">Nor is the subjective reaction of the recipient of the notice relevant: see Mannai at 767 per Lord Steyn and Lancecrest at [38]-[43] per Neuberger LJ and [88] per Brooke LJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s482">Either the notice is unequivocally a notice made pursuant to clause 3.2.2, or it is not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s483">If the meaning of the notice is in doubt, objectively viewed, the notice is invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s484">143 It is true that the notice is headed "Notice of Rental Assessment commencing 1 March 2003 for 42-44 Glenvale Crescent, Mulgrave".</sentence>
<sentence id="s485">However, the notice must be viewed as a whole and Shirlcar Properties makes it plain that what may otherwise be a valid notice can be invalidated by additional statements which affect the clarity, and import doubt, into the rest of the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s486">In my view, the characteristics of the notice, outlined above at [136], import uncertainty and ambiguity into the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s487">144 The cases relied upon by the first respondent as upholding notices in a similar form are, in my view, distinguishable from the notice in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s488">The first respondent placed particular reliance upon the notice that was upheld in Amalgamated Estates .</sentence>
<sentence id="s489">That notice was in a much clearer form than that in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s490">The relevant clause in the lease required the landlord to specify the open market rental by notice in writing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s491">The notice stated:
 
 "Pursuant to the terms of your Lease of the above premises dated December 7 1973, we hereby give you notice that we require a review of the yearly rental payable thereunder as from December 10 1978.</sentence>
<sentence id="s492">We specify that the new rent payable as from December 10 1978 will be [sterling]10,000 per annum exclusive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s493">" 
 

145 Moreover, the validity of the notice in Amalgamated Estates was not challenged on the basis of its form, but rather on the basis that the landlord had not specified a bona fide and genuine pre-estimate of the open market rental on the property in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s494">146 Fox &amp; Widley v Guran , another case cited by the first respondent, involved a typographical error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s495">The notice stated the rent review date as being 23 May 1989, rather than 25 May 1989.</sentence>
<sentence id="s496">Clarke J found that such an error could not mislead anyone, nor was there any evidence that the tenant had in fact been misled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s497">147 The closest the first respondent came to finding an analogous notice, the validity of which was upheld, was GHD Pty Ltd v Wayne [2001] QSC 73 (" GHD ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s498">In that case the lease was similar in substance to clause 3.2.2 and required the relevant amount to be specified by notice in writing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s499">The relevant notice stated:
 
 "As you will be aware your lease provides for a review of rental from 29 September 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s500">The Lessor proposes that there will be no change in the rental from the present level for the year commencing 29 September 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s501">" 
 

148 The notice then went on to deal with a proposal to renegotiate the terms of the lease to take account of the introduction of the goods and services tax legislation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s502">The lessee submitted that the use of the term "proposes" rather than "specifies", and the discussion of the GST proposal, rendered the notice equivocal, and therefore invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s503">The lessee also contended that the failure to specify an actual amount or refer to fair market rental suggested the notice represented a step in a preliminary negotiation before the rent review machinery was triggered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s504">149 Mackenzie J rejected these submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s505">His Honour noted that the matter was one of impression and that, in his view, the notice adequately conveyed the requisite meaning that the lease required to be conveyed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s506">150 GHD is distinguishable from the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s507">In GHD , Mackenzie J took the view that the GST discussion could be severed, or treated separately, from the rent review portion of the letter, and that the rent review portion of the letter was sufficiently clear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s508">If, in the notice at issue before me, the first respondent had simply referred to the lease and stated, as the lessor did in GHD , "the Lessor proposes that the rental commencing 1 March 2003 be $435,920 pa", and there was no ambiguous reference to the Colliers letter, the notice may well have been valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s509">However, the Colliers letter cannot be severed from this notice, and the reference to it in Mr Allen's letter, and the nature of the Colliers letter itself, import doubt into the meaning of the overall notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s510">151 Accordingly, I find that the notice was not sufficiently clear to be a valid notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2 of the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s511">152 I should note that in Central Pacific , it was suggested that the test expounded in Mannai was distinguishable from that in Catley v Watson : see Ormiston JA at 66,903 and Callaway JA at 66,909.</sentence>
<sentence id="s512">153 For my part, I cannot discern any difference in the effect of the tests in Mannai and Catley v Watson .</sentence>
<sentence id="s513">Nor could the Victorian Court of Appeal in MLW Technology Pty Ltd v May (see [82] per Gillard AJA (with whom Winneke P and Buchanan JA agreed)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s514">WAS THE NOTICE VALID IN SUBSTANCE?</sentence>
<sentence id="s515">
 
154 As the notice has been found to be invalid on the basis of form, it is strictly unnecessary to deal with this aspect of the applicant's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s516">I will, however, make some brief comments in relation to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s517">155 Because of my ruling in relation to the amendment of the applicant's statement of claim, the applicant is not able to pursue its claim that the notice is flawed because Mr Allen took into account fittings and fixtures additional to those in schedule 2 in assessing the proper rent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s518">Therefore, the applicant's only remaining contention under this ground is whether there was a failure to specify the "proper rent" because the rent specified was "excessive".</sentence>
<sentence id="s519">156 In my view, clause 3.2.2 did not require the lessor to stipulate a "reasonable" or "non-excessive" sum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s520">I reject the applicant's contention that the rent review clause in Mailman was not comparable to that at issue in this proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s521">Mailman required the lessor to give notice of what it considered was the "current market rent", having regard to certain matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s522">Clause 3.2.2 requires a statement of "the sum which the Lessor assesses to be the proper rent", taking into account certain assumptions and having regard to certain matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s523">Consistent with Gleeson CJ's statement in Mailman , as long as Mr Allen subjectively held the belief that this sum was the "proper rent", the requirements of clause 3.2.2 would have been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s524">I am not prepared, on the basis of the evidence before me, to infer that Mr Allen did not hold such a belief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s525">IMPLIED TERM OF GOOD FAITH 
 
157 The applicant's case in relation to breach of an implied term of good faith proceeded upon the assumption that the notice was found to be valid, and that therefore, clause 3.2.2 gave the first respondent the type of wide powers that would invoke the implication of the term.</sentence>
<sentence id="s526">As I have found that the notice was invalid, the issue does not strictly arise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s527">I do not propose therefore to say anything further about this aspect of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s528">UNCONSCIONABLE CONDUCT 
 
158 Much the same could be said about the applicant's claim under s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s529">However, I do wish to make some brief comments about one element of that claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s530">Section 51AA requires one party in a transaction to be under some sort of special disadvantage which the other party unconscientiously takes advantage of.</sentence>
<sentence id="s531">As previously indicated, the special disadvantage in this case was said to be the fact that Mr Bertrand spoke English as a second language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s532">159 Mr Bertrand was cross-examined in English and was able to communicate clearly and effectively during that process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s533">He was taken to various documents and had no trouble understanding them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s534">At the time of the events relevant to this application, Mr Bertrand was the General Manager of a sizeable commercial operation in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s535">Consequently, the applicant would have fallen well short of establishing that Mr Bertrand had a special disadvantage capable of invoking the operation of s 51AA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s536">MISLEADING OR DECEPTIVE CONDUCT CLAIM AGAINST THE SECOND RESPONDENT 
 
160 As I have found the notice to be invalid, the claim against the second respondent for misleading or deceptive conduct under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act is moot.</sentence>
<sentence id="s537">As the notice is invalid, the applicant cannot be said to have suffered loss or damage by virtue of the representations in the Colliers letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s538">Accordingly, the application against the second respondent is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s539">161 I wish, however, to make a number of comments in relation to this claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s540">162 Had the notice been found to be valid, and had the assessment in the notice been found to constitute a breach of s 52 , I would still have regarded the case against the second respondent as fundamentally flawed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s541">That is because, in my view, it would not be possible to conclude, on the evidence before me, that the applicant suffered loss or damage "by conduct" of the second respondent, as is required by s 82 of the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s542">163 In Wardley Australia Ltd v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514, the High Court held that s 82 plainly incorporates the concept of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s543">Mason CJ stated at 525:
 
 "The statutory cause of action arises when the plaintiff suffers loss or damage 
 "by" contravening conduct of another person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s544">"By" is a curious word to use.</sentence>
<sentence id="s545">One might have expected "by means of", "by reason of", "in consequence of" or "as a result of".</sentence>
<sentence id="s546">But the word clearly expresses the notion of causation without defining or elucidating it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s547">In this situation, s.82(1) should be understood as taking up the common law practical or common-sense concept of causation recently discussed by this Court in March v. Stramare (E. &amp; M. H.) Pty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s548">Ltd. , except in so far as that concept is modified or supplemented expressly or impliedly by the provisions of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s549">(footnote omitted) 
 

164 The authorities are clear that the applicant does not itself have to rely upon the misrepresentation in order to make a claim under s 82.</sentence>
<sentence id="s550">It may be sufficient for a third party to rely upon the misrepresentation, and for that third party reliance to cause the applicant's loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s551">See Janssen-Cilag Pty Limited v Pfizer Pty Limited (1992) 37 FCR 526 (" Janssen-Cilag "), Haynes v Top Slice Deli Pty Limited (1995) ATPR (Digest) |P46-147 (" Haynes "), and McCarthy v McIntyre [1999] FCA 784.</sentence>
<sentence id="s552">However, the authorities require a "sufficient and direct link", or a "requisite element of proximity" in order for s 82 to be satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s553">165 Janssen-Cilag involved a claim brought by a competitor of a company that had made misleading representations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s554">The applicant claimed damages for the loss of custom which resulted from customers buying more of the competitor's products as a result of the misleading conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s555">Lockhart J observed at 532:
 
 "Where a corporation engages in conduct which misleads consumers, the natural and direct result of which is to cause the public to buy more of that trader's product and less of a rival trader's product, the loss to the rival is direct and immediate; it is not remote or indirect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s556">The purpose of the conduct is to reduce the market share of the rival to the benefit of the trader engaging in the misleading conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s557">That benefit is achieved by misleading consumers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s558">This is a class of conduct to which s 82 is directed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s559">" 
 

166 In Haynes , the applicants purchased a franchise from Top Slice Deli.</sentence>
<sentence id="s560">Top Slice Deli's accountants had sent misleading financial information to the bank which approved the applicants' loan to purchase the franchise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s561">As against the accountants, Einfeld J found at 53,152:
 
 "Even if the bank's approval of the loan was an antecedent condition of entry into the agreements ...there was not an effective or true nexus between the approval and the entry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s562">To adopt the language of Justice Lockhart, any resulting loss from the failure of the business is both a remote and indirect, not the "natural and direct", result of the relevant conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s563">It therefore falls outside section 82..." 
 

167 In McCarthy v McIntyre , a bank relied upon a misleading valuation in making a loan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s564">The appellant suffered loss from the transaction entered into using the funds from the loan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s565">The issue in that case was whether, if the transaction would not have been entered into by the appellant had it not been for the making of the loan, was this sufficient to make a claim under s 82.</sentence>
<sentence id="s566">The Full Court (Hill, Sackville and Katz JJ) stated at [48]-[50]:
 
 "All that is necessary, in our opinion, is that there be a sufficient and direct link (ie, causation) between the loss or damage alleged to have been suffered by the claimant and the misleading or deceptive conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s567">
 
 It is well established that the misleading or deceptive conduct need not be the sole cause of the loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s568">...</sentence>
<sentence id="s569">Precisely what test should be used to judge what constitutes the sufficient causal connection required between the misleading conduct and the outcome is the subject of some difficulty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s570">Perhaps there is no simple test capable of formulation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s571">It is necessary that the issue of causation be approached in what the High Court in Wardley called a "practical or commonsense" way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s572">In many areas, the courts have applied a "but for" test of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s573">As McHugh, Hayne and Callinan JJ pointed out in Marks v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd at 346, the idea that a "but for" test is the exclusive test of causation has been found wanting in some contexts and it may yet be found to be wanting in the context of ss 82 and 87 of the Trade Practices Act (and their State equivalents).</sentence>
<sentence id="s574">Whether this be the case or not, the "but for" test, applied in a common sense and not a pedantic way, provides still a useful approach to the issue of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s575">
 
 Where a claimant is able to show that, but for the misleading or deceptive conduct, he or she would not have entered into a transaction, then such loss as flows directly to the claimant from the transaction will satisfy the requirement of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s576">This is so where the claimant relies upon the misleading or deceptive conduct (the usual case).</sentence>
<sentence id="s577">It is also so where a third party whose action was a sina qua non of the entry by the claimant into the transaction (the present case as alleged) relies upon the misleading or deceptive conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s578">" 
 

168 The matter was then remitted to the primary judge to make factual findings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s579">The remittal judgment was also appealed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s580">In that appeal ( McCarthy v McIntyre [2000] FCA 1250) , Whitlam, Emmett and Hely JJ found, at [53]:
 
 "there is no basis for concluding that, if the valuation of the Tropicana Hotel had been in the order of $2,100,000, Westpac would not have advanced the same proportion of the valuation, namely, $1,071,000 rather than $1,622,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s581">That, of course, would have given rise to the need to borrow additional funds elsewhere.</sentence>
<sentence id="s582">There is no evidence to support a conclusion that it would not have been possible to borrow the additional funds from another source.</sentence>
<sentence id="s583">" 
 

169 The reasoning of their Honours is relevant to this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s584">It cannot be said that "but for" the Collier's assessment, Mr Allen would have sent the applicant a notice for less than the sum actually specified in the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s585">It is quite possible that a higher figure may have been specified, given that Mr Allen gave evidence that he believed Mr Williams' figure was "a bit low", and actually thought that the Mulgrave premises were worth more.</sentence>
<sentence id="s586">Mr Allen would have been well within his rights to serve a notice which specified a higher amount, if he believed that this reflected the proper rent, taking into account the relevant criteria outlined in clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s587">The applicant's case would require me to make findings about "what would have happened" but for the alleged misleading conduct in a way that would border upon pure speculation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s588">170 Not being able to satisfy the "but for" test would have been a serious problem for the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s589">There is, however, a further insurmountable hurdle in relation to the applicant's case in relation to causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s590">171 In my view, the applicant's failure to object to the notice, if it were found to be valid, would constitute a break in the chain of causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s591">Put another way, at its highest, what the second respondent would have "caused" was a rental assessment notice to be sent which specified an annual rental which did not reflect the "proper rent" as defined in clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s592">While negligence on the part of a "victim" of a contravention is not a defence to a claim for damages under s 82, this does not apply where the victim's conduct operates so as to destroy the causal connection between the contravention and the loss or damage: Henville v Walker [2001] HCA 52 ; (2001) 206 CLR 459 at 468 per Gleeson CJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s593">172 Accordingly, had the notice been valid, and had the other claims against the first respondent failed, I would not have found the second respondent liable to pay damages under s 82 even if it had, by preparing the letter, contravened s 52, because the second respondent, by its conduct, would not have caused the applicant's loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s594">ORDERS 
 
173 It is clear from what I have already stated that the applicant is entitled to a declaration that the notice upon which the first respondent relied for increasing the rent was not a valid notice pursuant to clause 3.2.2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s595">It follows that the notice was of no effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s596">174 As previously indicated, the applicant has paid the rent demanded pursuant to the notice under protest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s597">The question of what relief, if any, the applicant may be entitled to, arising out of these payments, will need to be addressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s598">So too will the question of costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s599">175 These questions are complicated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s600">The relief sought by the applicant against the first respondent in its amended application filed on 10 November 2004 included some nineteen separate claims, many of them in the alternative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s601">For example, the applicant postulated a number of possibilities, including declarations as to the current applicable rent for the premises ranging from the current figure of $275,279 to a significantly higher figure, depending upon how that rental is calculated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s602">In the alternative, the applicant sought an order compelling the first respondent to request the president or other senior officer of the Australian Property Institute (being the successor to the Australian Institute of Valuers) to determine a proper rent for the premises in the manner set out in clause 3.2.2(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s603">There are other permutations of these claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s604">176 My finding that the notice was invalid leaves the question of any relief regarding the payments made under protest to be determined in accordance with general principles of common law, equity and restitution, and not pursuant to either s 87 or s 82 of the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s605">Because there was evidence led as to what the proper rent determined in accordance with clause 3.2.2 should be, there may have to be a finding made regarding that matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s606">177 The figures that are suggested in the evidence range from Mr Ned Walsh (the expert called on behalf of the applicant) who fixed upon a figure of approximately $330,000 per annum including GST, Mr Finkemeyer whose original estimate was approximately $370,000 per annum without GST, Mr Brian Dudakov (the expert called on behalf of the second respondent) who valued the proper rent at approximately $440,000 per annum including GST, and the "ballpark figure" arrived at by Mr Williams of around $470,000 per annum including GST.</sentence>
<sentence id="s607">The evidence of Mr Walsh and Mr Dudakov was directed primarily towards the liability of the second respondent, but can, of course, be utilised in determining what amount, if any, the first respondent should be required to repay to the applicant, having regard to my finding that the notice was invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s608">I have reached no conclusion regarding that matter as it is necessary firstly to establish the basis upon which the applicant is entitled to any such repayment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s609">178 Alternatively, the parties may be able to agree, between themselves, as to what form any such relief should take.</sentence>
<sentence id="s610">That would obviate the need for further lengthy and expensive submissions to be made regarding this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s611">179 In determining what orders may be appropriate, the parties may wish to consider the applicability of the principles laid down in United Scientific Holdings Ltd v Burnley Borough Council [1978] AC 904 (" United Scientific Holdings ") in relation to the retrospective application of rent reviews completed outside the period provided for under the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s612">180 In United Scientific Holdings , the House of Lords held that there was nothing in that case that displaced the presumption that strict adherence to the timetables specified in the relevant rent review clauses was not of the essence of the contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s613">181 There were in fact two separate cases decided in United Scientific Holdings .</sentence>
<sentence id="s614">The first involved a rent review on a 99 year lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s615">The review was to occur each ten years after the commencement of the lease, with the new rent to commence on 31 August of that year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s616">The rent review mechanisms provided that the revised rent was to be determined by agreement, or failing agreement, by arbitration "during the year immediately preceding" the 10 year period to which that rent would relate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s617">By the end of the first 10 year period, such agreement had not been reached, and nor had the matter been referred to arbitration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s618">182 The second case involved a 21 year lease, commencing upon 8 April 1968.</sentence>
<sentence id="s619">The rent was to be reviewed every seven years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s620">The relevant machinery provided for the lessor to serve a notice on the lessee, and the lessee to serve a counter-notice accepting the proposal or making a counter-offer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s621">The parties were then to negotiate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s622">If agreement had not been reached after a certain time, the lessor was required to appoint an independent valuer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s623">In this case, the lessor's notice was served within time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s624">However, no agreement had been reached by the parties, and the lessor failed to appoint an independent valuer within the time provided for under the lease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s625">183 In both cases the House of Lords held that time was not of the essence in relation to the clauses in the leases which the lessors had not complied with.</sentence>
<sentence id="s626">The lessors had not lost the opportunity to have the rent for the next rental period reviewed by virtue of not complying with the time periods set down in the rent review machinery clauses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s627">184 The potential significance of the case for this proceeding in terms of any final orders that may be made is as follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s628">The House of Lords held that once the relevant terms were complied with (namely an arbitration concluded in the first case and independent valuation conducted in the second case), the new rent would be payable from the date that the lease provided that the new rental period was to commence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s629">That is, despite the lessors' tardiness, not only did they maintain their rights to rent reviews, but once the rent reviews were completed, the revised rent applied retrospectively as if those reviews had been completed on time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s630">185 Whether the parties wish to consider or rely upon United Scientific Holdings in putting forward orders to reflect my reasons for judgement is, however, a matter for them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s631">186 There is also potentially a difficult question to be resolved regarding costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s632">The applicant has succeeded against the first respondent in relation to its claim that the notice was invalid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s633">However, there were a number of other issues raised in relation to which it either did not succeed, or would not have succeeded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s634">That is a matter that may have to be taken into account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s635">187 With regard to the second respondent, it is sufficient to note, for present purposes, that the applicant's claim against it must be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s636">It is clear that the second respondent will be entitled to its costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s637">Beyond these findings, it may be necessary to hear the parties further.</sentence>
<sentence id="s638">188 I will direct that each party bring in proposed minutes of orders that reflect the findings made in these reasons for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s639">That should be done within 21 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s640">If agreement can be reached regarding the form of such orders, so much the better.</sentence>
<sentence id="s641">If not, I will make available a date upon which there can be further argument as to the form that any final orders should take.</sentence>
<sentence id="s642">I certify that the preceding one hundred and eighty-eight (188) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Weinberg.</sentence>
<sentence id="s643">Associate:

Dated: 15 March 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr J.J. Gleeson 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicant: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr P.J. O'Callaghan QC with Mr M.S.</sentence>
<sentence id="s644">Osborne 
 
 Solicitors for the First Respondent: Allen &amp; Allen 
 
 Counsel for the Second Respondent: Mr P.J. Cawthorn 
 
 Solicitors for the Second Respondent: Phillips Fox 
 
 Dates of Hearing: 11, 12, 13, 14 and 15 July 2005 and 4, 11 and 12 August 2005 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 March 2006 




 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/219.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>