<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Shahid v The Australasian College of Dermatologists [2006] FCA 414 (13 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/414.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application by respondent for costs of interlocutory applications to be payable forthwith</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">applicant's filing amended statement of claim significantly changing nature of application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">costs on interlocutory matters awarded with liberty to apply</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">lapse of application lodged over two years previously</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">proceeding to be heard shortly</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">possibility of further delay in time when costs payable due to preparation of reasons and possibility of appeals</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">circumstances justified departure from ordinary rule that costs paid after completion of proceeding</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">costs</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The respondent brings a notice of motion seeking taxation of costs of interlocutory proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 On 28 April 2005, orders were made that the respondent's notice of motion filed on 20 August 2004 and the applicant's notice of motion filed on 14 June 2004 be dismissed by consent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">In each case it was further ordered that the respondent's costs thrown away by the notice of motion be paid by the applicant to be taxed with liberty to apply in relation to the time of taxation in the event the proceeding is not resolved within six months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">That period expired on 28 October 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The motion is brought in reliance on the liberty thus granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 The hearing of this proceeding is listed for the week of 1 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The consequence is that the notice of motion comes before the Court, as it were, on the eve of the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The applicant says that it is brought to 'punish' the applicant as a person of limited resources.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">However, the notice of motion was filed on 1 March 2006 and has only now been brought on.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">4 The evidence of the solicitor whose affidavit supports the notice of motion on behalf of the respondent is that, notwithstanding that the taxation process may overlap the trial dates, it is her belief that the process will be completed well before judgment is handed down, as there is normally a gap between trial and the handing down of judgment and of course there is the possibility of appeal against any judgment in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">5 The respondent relies on the reasoning in McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Ltd [1999] FCA 1639 and Sereika v Cardinal Financial Securities Ltd (formerly Inteq Custodians Ltd) [2001] FCA 687.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">6 In McKellar , Weinberg J followed the approach taken by Branson J in Life Airbag Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Life Airbag Co (New Zealand) Ltd [1998] FCA 545 and Kiefel J in Harris v Cigna Insurance Australia Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-445.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">In Harris , Kiefel J accepted that an order that certain costs be taxed and paid forthwith was justified in circumstances where there had been a long delay in the course of the proceeding by the pursuit of an ill-considered and unnecessary claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">It is common ground that the making of the order sought by the notice of motion is a matter in the discretion of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">7 The applicant's notice of motion of 14 June 2004 moved for an injunction restraining the respondent from having any communication with the Appeals Committee of the respondent in relation to the applicant's appeal unless the applicant was informed in advance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Further it sought for the respondent to supply copies of all material relating to the short listing of the applicant in the years 2000 --- 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Further, that the respondent supply copies of all files and documents relating to the application in 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">8 The respondent's notice of motion of 20 August 2004 sought to dismiss the proceeding as it was then constituted and contained a notice of objection to jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">9 As a consequence of the filing of an amended statement of claim each of these notices of motions became redundant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">That is, the nature of the action was fundamentally changed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">No longer was the Court sought to intervene in ongoing proceedings before the Appeals Committee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The amended statement of claim brought a Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) series of claims based on past behaviour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">10 Consequently, the effect of the filing of the amended statement of claim was to see the action commenced afresh.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">That was after the application had been on foot since 9 March 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">In other words, when the orders of 28 April 2005 were made, the original application had been on foot for over 12 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">11 Although the proceeding is due to be heard in the first week of May, time will be required for preparation and publication of reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Additionally, time may be taken by any appeals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">In my view, in those circumstances, this motion raises issues which fall within the principles identified in the cases referred to in McKellar .</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">That is, I consider that there are circumstances in the time which has elapsed and the significant nature of the change to the pleadings which warrants a departure from the ordinary rule that costs are to be paid after the completion of proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">12 Accordingly, I consider that the discretion should be exercised in favour of the grant of the notice of motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">I certify that the preceding twelve (12) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Nicholson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Associate:

Dated: 13 April 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: S Bhojani 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: David Rawlinson 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: I Freeman 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 12 April 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 April 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/414.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>