<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lord v Agreserves Australia Limited ACN 080 646 251 [2006] FCA 598 (11 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/598.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">joinder of claims</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application by liquidator</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">claim against defendants for unfair preferences</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 Edited from Transcript 
 
 1 The plaintiff, liquidator for Parle Foods Pty Limited ACN 050 213 468 (in Liquidation) (Receivers and Managers Appointed) ("the company"), has commenced proceedings in the present matter and in 38 other proceedings, claiming that the various defendants received amounts as "unfair preferences" as defined by section 588FA of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth)
 
2 The plaintiff seeks leave under Order 6 Rule 2(b) of the Federal Court Rules to join the various defendants as defendants in matter NSD 439 of 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Background 
 
3 The defendants are in some cases national corporations but others are smaller firms or companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The defendants include the Commonwealth of Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">4 The company carried on business mainly in Griffith and many of the defendants are located in the Griffith area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">A number of defendants are from interstate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The claims when grouped for each defendant range from just under $10,000 to, in one case, over $3 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">5 The plaintiff filed an interlocutory originating process in matter NSD439 of 2006 on 6 March 2006, seeking an order under Order 6 Rule 2, that the plaintiff have leave to join in the proceedings all of the 38 defendants listed in the schedule to the originating process which was filed on the same day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">6 The plaintiff accepts that Order 6 Rule 2(a)(ii) has not been met because the claims do not arise out of the same transaction or series of transactions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Leave is therefore required under order 6 rule 2(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">7 Since the proceedings have already been commenced, leave is required nunc pro tunc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">8 Mr Taylor SC appears for the first defendant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr J.T.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Johnson appears for 13 of the defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">They oppose leave.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">9 The plaintiff relies on the test stated by Austin J in Dean-Willcocks v Air Transit International Pty Limited [2002] NSWSC 525 ; (2002) 55 NSWLR 64 (" Dean-Willcocks") , in particular, at [34].</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Mr Taylor and Mr Johnson accept that this is the correct approach although they say that the case is distinguishable from the present proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">10 Austin J said at [34] in Dean-Willcocks that the court's task is to identify and weigh the advantages and disadvantages to the plaintiff and the defendants as a whole, and in terms of the efficient use of the court's resources, having regard to the commonality of issues raised by each claim and the court's ability to case manage the proceedings so as to minimise disadvantages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">11 His Honour said at [35] that there are some special features of unfair preference proceedings which may justify the grant of leave even though leave would not be granted in similarly constituted proceedings which have a different subject matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">It is unnecessary to repeat the three considerations to which his Honour referred at [35].</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">12 The approach adopted by Austin J was followed by Young CJ in Eq in Gloria Marshall Australia Pty Limited (in liq) v Bell Press Pty Limited [2002] NSWSC 1191.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">His Honour considered that the best way of dealing with the matter was to apply a common sense approach to the issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I respectfully follow what was said by Austin J and by the Chief Judge in Equity as guiding the exercise of my discretion in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Discussion 
 
13 The present proceedings are at a very early stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The "consolidated" proceeding and the 38 separate proceedings were commenced close to the expiration of the limitation period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The plaintiff proposes to discontinue against seven of the defendants, leaving 31 in the consolidated proceeding or 31 separate actions if I refuse leave in matter NSD439 of 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">14 The submissions of Mr Taylor and Mr Johnson are that there ought to be 31 separate proceedings rather than one consolidated action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">They submit that many of the factors which were present in Dean-Willcocks are not applicable to the present proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The principle matters to which they point are fourfold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">15 Firstly, they say that separate proceedings have already been commenced in this court and that those proceedings can be case managed, so it is submitted, just as efficiently as one consolidated action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">16 Secondly, they submit that the question of insolvency can be determined in the separate proceedings in a way which will bind all of the defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">17 Third, they point out that there is no evidence of the plaintiff's prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">18 Fourth, counsel submit that the evidence suggests that there will be no dividend for the unsecured creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">They say that such funds as are recovered will be subject to the liquidator's lien and therefore go towards payment of his fees rather than for the benefit of the unsecured creditors as a whole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">19 I do not consider that any of the factors to which counsel for the various defendants pointed, displace the considerations to which Austin J referred at [35].</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It seems to me that those considerations apply equally here notwithstanding the fact that there may be no recovery for the benefit of the body of unsecured creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">20 As to that issue the proceedings are at an early stage and it would not seem possible to predict what the outcome may be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">I am concerned that there is no evidence as to prospects of success but the short answer to all of the submissions of counsel for the defendants lies in the fact that there are separate proceedings already on foot.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Mr Mathas, for the plaintiff, accepts that if leave is given in matter NSD439 of 2006, the separate proceedings must be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">21 Thus the question may be reduced to a very simple one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Is it more advantageous and efficient to have 31 separate cases or one consolidated action?</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">In my opinion it is plainly more efficient to have one proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The most important factor is the solvency issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">That is to say, was the company insolvent at the time of the relevant transaction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">That issue is common to all cases although it is not yet known whether all of the defendants propose to put that issue in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">22 The plaintiff proposes to file a solvency report dealing with that issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">By following the course proposed by the plaintiff I can case manage the proceedings to a point where the solvency issue has been determined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">I have been told today that at least two of the defendants propose to put solvency in issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Either the others do or they do not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Once the question has been determined and once it emerges which defendants seek to put it in issue I can then decide to in effect deconsolidate the hearing by appropriate orders and directions for the hearing of the remaining issues, either in separate cases or in groups of cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">23 I have considered all of the other objections raised by Mr Taylor and Mr Johnson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">In my view none of the objections lead to a different result in weighing the advantages and disadvantages of proceeding in the manner which I propose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">24 To the extent that any difficulties may arise in relation to the interlocutory stages of the proceedings such as discovery, if the parties cannot agree on the course I can deal with them by appropriate directions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">25 In Dean-Willcocks, Austin J pointed out that one of the factors which justify the joinder of a number of defendants is the fact that the case management of the proceedings is allocated in the Supreme Court of New South Wales to the Corporations List.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">That is a regular weekly list within which issues of this type are dealt with and their progress is monitored and dealt with expeditiously.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">26 There is a separate Corporations List in the Federal Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">A Corporations Duty Judge sits on Fridays at 9.30am to hear matters referred from a registrar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Urgent applications may be made directly, on any day of the week, to the rostered Corporations Duty Judge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">At present the Corporations Duty Judges are by rotation, Justices Emmett, Gyles, and Lindgren, although other members of the Court's Corporations Panel fill that role if one or other of those judges is not available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Details of the Court's administrative arrangements for dealing with Corporations matters are contained in a notice to practitioners issued by the NSW District Registrar on 6 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">27 I will myself case manage the present proceedings but in the event that something may arise at a time when I am not available, the matter could be dealt with by the Corporations Duty Judge who is sitting at that time to deal with urgent applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The matter can therefore be dealt with and managed in much the same way as matters are managed in the corporations list of the Supreme Court of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">28 It follows, as I have said, that if there are any real difficulties and the parties cannot agree, I will be able to deal with them by appropriate directions, or if for some reason I am not available, the issues can be dealt with promptly by the Corporations Duty Judge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">29 I have considered the written submission of Mr Johnson that if the proceedings were to be dealt with by way of separate actions, Rule 2.13 of the Federal Court Corporations Rules could be utilised to enable interested persons to appear so as to enable relevant common issues such as the solvency issue to be determined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">However, it does seem to me that the better course is the course which I propose to adopt, namely, that I will give leave as sought by the plaintiff, thereby enabling me to deal, hopefully efficiently and promptly, with all of the issues in the way that I have indicated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">30 I therefore propose to make orders in terms of those proposed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">31 Mr Johnson appeared for 13 defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">He undertook to ensure appearances are filed for all of them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">As at the date of publication of this judgment, appearances have not be filed for these defendants, other than the 18 th defendant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">I certify that the preceding thirty-one (31) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Associate:

Dated: 23 May 2006


 Solicitor for the Plaintiff Deacons (Mr Mathas) 
 
 Counsel for the 1 st Defendant Mr Taylor SC 
 
 Solicitor for the 1 st Defendant: Dibbs Abbott Stillman 
 
 Solicitor for the 2 nd Defendant: Minter Ellison 
 Solicitor for the 3 rd Defendant: Henry Davis York 
 
 Solicitor for the 12 th Defendant: Dibbs Abbott Stillman 
 
 Solicitor for the 15 th Defendant: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the 6 th , 11 th , 14 th , 16 th , 18 th , 20 th , 22 nd , 26 th , 29 th , 30 th , 32 nd , 33 rd , and 35 th Defendants Mr J Johnson 
 
 Solicitor for the 18 th Defendant: Coadys 
 
 Date of Hearing: 11 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 May 2006 

 IN THE FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 
 
 NEW SOUTH WALES DISTRICT REGISTRY 
 No: (P)NSD439/2006 
 
 SCHEDULE OF DEFENDANTS 
 (as at 11 May 2006) 


 AEP INDUSTRIES AUSTRALIA PTY LTD ACN 075 939 614 
 SECOND DEFENDANT 

 AMCOR PACKAGING AUSTRALIA PTY LIMITED ABN 55 004 275 165 TRADING AS ''AMCOR FIBRE PACKAGING'' 
 THIRD DEFENDANT 

 PILMARK PTY LTD ABN 43 563 811 054 TRADING AS '' AREA WHOLESALE FOODS '' 
 FOURTH DEFENDANT 

 FERNTIN PTY LIMITED ACN 057 652 598 TRADING '' BELFORD PETROLEUM '' 
 FIFTH DEFENDANT 

 THE BUILDING SUPPLY COMPANY PTY LIMITED ACN 003 362 490 
 SIXTH DEFENDANT 

 LAWRENCE CAPELLO AND ANOTHER TRADING AS '' CAPELLO &amp; DE LUCA '' 
 SEVENTH DEFENDANT 

 CHEETHAM SALT LIMITED ACN 006 926 487 
 EIGHTH DEFENDANT 

 BRAMBLES AUSTRALIA LIMITED ACN 000 164 938 TRADING AS ''CHEP AUSTRALIA'' 
 NINTH DEFENDANT 

 COATES HIRE OPERATIONS PTY LIMITED ACN 99 074 126 971 
 TENTH DEFENDANT 

 COLLIER &amp; MILLER PTY LIMITED ACN 000 521 344 
 ELEVENTH DEFENDANT 

 COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA 
 TWELFTH DEFENDANT 

 DRAGON PRINTING PTY LIMITED ACN 099 774 893 
 THIRTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 ELIAS GAMBA PARTNERS PTY LIMITED ABN 78 747 231 364 
 FOURTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 REXEL AUSTRALIA LIMITED ACN 000 437 758 TRADING AS ''FOY ELECTRICAL WHOLESALE'' 
 FIFTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 F &amp; N TREFILLO PTY LIMITED ACN 003 968 054 TRADING AS ''FRANKS SERVICE CENTRE'' 
 SIXTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 FAIRFERN PTY LTD ACN 002 225 390 TRADING AS ''GEORGE DUNCAN ELECTRICS'' 
 SEVENTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 GORDON BROTHERS INDUSTRIES PTY LTD ACN 005 888 175 
 EIGHTEENTH DEFENDANT 

 GREENS GENERAL FOODS PTY LIMITED ACN 001 553 564 
 NINETEENTH DEFENDANT MAX RENNIE, GARY EDWARD RENNIE, KATHRYN ANN RENNIE, ANNETTE LAWRENCE, SHANE LAWRENCE AND SHIRLEY ELIZABETH RENNIE TRADING AS ''GRIFFITH CITY HIRE'' 
 TWENTIETH DEFENDANT 

 DENIS VINCENT COUCH &amp; MARGARET ANNE COUCH TRADING AS ''GRIFFITH ELECTRONIC SERVICES'' 
 TWENTY FIRST DEFENDANT 

 KAY OLIVER PTY LTD ACN 079 276 565 
 TWENTY SECOND DEFENDANT 

 EBONY BAY PTY LTD ACN 055 460 449 TRADING AS ''LEFROY VALLEY'' 
 TWENTY THIRD DEFENDANT 

 ROGER ALLEN VARDANEGA AND GEORGE RIGON T/AS MACKENZIE AND VARDANEGA 
 TWENTY FOURTH DEFENDANT 

 MAXITHERM BOILERS PTY LIMITED ACN 000 054 375 
 TWENTY FIFTH DEFENDANT 

 MAZZON SYSTEMS ENGINEERING AUSTRALIA PTY LTD ACN 070 025 384 
 TWENTY SIXTH DEFENDANT 

 WELLS, MICHAEL 
 TWENTY SEVENTH DEFENDANT 

 MINNOW INVESTMENTS PTY LTD ACN 078 715 929 
 TWENTY EIGHTH DEFENDANT 

 TREVOR LEONARD O'BRIEN TRADING AS '' O'BRIENS TRANSPORT'' 
 TWENTY NINTH DEFENDANT 

 PHOENIX FOODS PTY LTD ACN 064 565 724 
 THIRTIETH DEFENDANT 

 PRESTIGE PACKAGING AUSTRALIA PTY LTD ACN 057 341 330 
 THIRTY FIRST DEFENDANT 

 PRESTONS LEETON PTY LTD ACN 058 201 755 
 THIRTY SECOND DEFENDANT 

 SOUTH PACIFIC SEEDS PTY LTD ACN 002 887 256 
 THIRTY THIRD DEFENDANT 

 SUGAR AUSTRALIA PTY LTD ACN 812 451 169 
 THIRTY FOURTH DEFENDANT 

 TRIMGOOD PTY LTD ACN 050 104 893 
 THIRTY FIFTH DEFENDANT 

 UPPER MURRAY CASE SUPPLIES PTY LTD ACN 085 511 799 
 THIRTY SIXTH DEFENDANT 

 VISY PACKAGING PTY LTD ACN 095 313 723 
 THIRTY EIGHTH DEFENDANT 

 JOEL SIMFORD WELDINGS SERVICES ABN 52 097 563 338 
 FORTIETH DEFENDANT 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/598.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>