<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Restom v Battenberg, in the matter of Battenberg (with Corrigendum dated 22 May 2006) [2006] FCA 524 (4 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/524.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interim application to dismiss creditors petition and alternatively set aside subpoenas</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether debtor ordinarily resident or had a dwelling house in australia at the date of the act of bankruptcy</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">found to be arguable basis for allegation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">application successful in part</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">bankruptcy</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 (REVISED FROM THE TRANSCRIPT) 
 
 1 This is an interim application by the debtor to dismiss the creditors petition that was filed on 21 October 2005 and alternatively to set aside subpoenas to the Union Club, the Australia Club Incorporated and the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The petition alleged in paragraph 3 that at the time at which the act of bankruptcy was committed, being 6 June 2005, the debtor was carrying on business in Australia, was personally present in Australia, was ordinarily resident in Australia and had a dwelling house in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">That was supported by an affidavit verifying the petition sworn by Brian Stewart Olliver on 20 October 2005 in which he asserted that those allegations were 'within my own knowledge true'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 Mr Johnson of counsel who appears for the petitioning creditors today withdrew the allegation that the debtor was personally present in Australia on the date of the act of bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 During February and March this year, the debtor has been seeking and ultimately, the petitioning creditor has provided, particulars of the allegations to found jurisdiction under section 43 of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The particulars to support the allegation that the debtor was carrying on business in Australia were as follows:
 
 '1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">
 
 a) Investor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">
 b) In Australia and in particular in Melbourne and in Sydney.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">
 c) The debtor travels to and from Australia to consider and oversee investments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">
 d) The evidence is included in documents produced on subpoena by the Department of Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">' 

4 The material upon which paragraph 1(d) was based is said to be contained in exhibit 2, which consists of the Department of Immigration's incoming and outgoing passenger card records.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">There is nothing in exhibit 2 to indicate anything more than that the debtor described his occupation in passenger cards both outgoing and incoming as an investor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">There is no material in those documents to show where the place of the investments was and in particular that there was any connection whatsoever to his occupation as an investor and Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The petitioning creditors were not able to advance any other basis upon which it was alleged that there was any business being carried on in Australia by the debtor at the time of the act of bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">5 In my opinion, having regard to the fact that her Honour, Stone J, ordered that these particulars be answered on 9 March 2006 and that the allegations were made and verified in the creditors petition, I am able to infer and I do infer that at the time this allegation was made there was no basis for the allegation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In my opinion, the particulars are inadequate to support the allegation and it is therefore one that, as particularised, should not be allowed to stand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Accordingly, I strike out the allegation that the debtor was carrying on business in Australia in paragraph 3 of the creditors petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">6 I also strike out, because of its abandonment in court today, the allegation that the debtor was personally present in Australia on that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">7 The claims as to the debtor's ordinary residence in having a dwelling house in Australia as at the date of the act of bankruptcy are, in my opinion, sufficiently particularised so as to permit them to remain in the creditors petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">During the course of the hearing, exhibit 1 was tendered which was a document that appears to have been prepared by the debtor on 3 May 2005 and used in the Employment Appeal Tribunal of either Scotland or the United Kingdom in support of an appeal by him from the decision of the Employment Tribunal relating to his employment of a chauffeur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">8 In that notice of appeal, the appellant describes his address as being at Ethersey House, Illawarra Highway, Sutton Forrest, New South Wales 2576, Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">He gave as a ground of his appeal the following: 
 
 'The named Respondent (Lord Battenberg) although this has been disputed, is not domiciled in Scotland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">' 


 
9 The grounds which were then elaborated included the following: 
 
 'F) That the Tribunal erred in determining that it had jurisdiction to hear the matter, the Appellant having Australian domicile at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">(The letter of 3 March 2005 from Messrs Russo, the Appellant's Australian solicitors, to Russel &amp; Aitkin refers).</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">
 ... 
 
 K) That no (no) attempt was made to inform the respondent that the employment Tribunal was about to reconvene.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">As a result he was again unrepresented at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">This was despite the fact that his London and Australian contact details had been supplied to the Tribunal and had been quoted in correspondence from the Tribunal' (emphasis in original) 


 
10 The letter of 3 March 2005 from the appellant's solicitor which appears to have been used in the decision, the subject of the Employment Appeal Tribunal proceedings, was not tendered or produced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">I recognise that there is a distinction in law between a person having an Australian or other domicile at a particular time and that person's residence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The notice of appeal, indeed, suggests that one place of residence at the time at which it was filed may have been an address in London, although it may also have been a place of work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">11 In my opinion, the fact that the debtor always, on the outgoing and incoming passenger cards in evidence, gave his intended address in Australia as Ethersey House, which is his mother's residence, suggests that there is an available argument that he is able regularly to resort to that place as a residence within the meaning of the authorities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Of course, I can make no decision about the likelihood of the success of such an argument.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Simply, having regard to the way the matter has been particularised, it seems to me that there is at least an arguable basis, and I put it no higher than that, that depending on the evidence ultimately advanced at the trial in support of and in answer to the particulars, the trial judge could find that the debtor either was ordinarily resident in Australia or had a dwelling house in Australia within the meaning of the authorities discussed by Graham J in Mathai v Kwee [2005] FCA 932 at [111] to [126].</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">12 For those reasons, I do not consider that there is any abuse of process or other basis upon which I should strike out the remaining allegations in paragraph 3 of the creditors petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">13 The next issue is whether the subpoenas to the two clubs should be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Each subpoena seeks in par 1 'application for membership with' the respective club.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">No name of any person is set out as to whose application it is, nor is there any relevant time period as to which such an application was to be made referrable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">In my opinion, there is no legitimate basis for requiring that paragraph to be answered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">14 The second and third paragraphs of the respective subpoenas seek copies of personal details provided in writing or orally by the debtor to the respective club: 'at times he has stayed at the club during the period 1 March 2005 to 1 March 2006'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">And correspondence with the debtor, including accounts sent and paid by him during that period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">15 The act of bankruptcy was committed on 6 June 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The period for which these details are sought extends for almost nine months after that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">These paragraphs seek a wide range of details as to any correspondence including accounts, which do not appear to be relevant for the current purpose and they do not appear to be supported as to relevance by the petitioning creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The only relevance for which the argument that the petitioning creditors sought to make those paragraphs apposite was to prove the elements of par 3 of the creditor's petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">No allegation in par 3 in relation to ordinary residence or dwelling house was directed to the debtors use of or staying at either club.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">16 In my opinion, the paragraphs have no relevance to the proceedings and are therefore an abuse of process and should not be required to be answered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Paragraph 4 of the subpoena to the Union Club seeks copies of court process and affidavits issued by the debtor to the club disclosing his address for service during the period 1 March 2005 to 1 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">There was no attempt to support why an address for service was relevant to the issues of the place of ordinary residence or the debtor's dwelling house as at the date of bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">I regard the paragraph as an abuse of process and it ought to be struck out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">It follows that there is no part of the schedule to either subpoena to the clubs that survives.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Therefore the subpoenas should be set aside and to the extent that any documents may have been produced in answer to the subpoenas by the clubs, the documents should be returned without being inspected by any party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">17 Lastly, the application seeks that the subpoena issued to the debtor on 13 December 2005 be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">That subpoena seeks documents that relate to the Scottish Employment Tribunal proceedings and the appeal from it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Inter alia, it specifically seeks in paragraph 4 the letter dated 3 March 2005 from the debtor's solicitors to Russel &amp; Aitken referred to in the ground of appeal F in the Employment Appeals Tribunal proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">For the reasons that I have already given, it seems to me that the material sought in this subpoena has relevance and, subject to any proper objections as to production, ought be answered as Stone J has already directed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">I refuse to set that subpoena aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">18 The debtor seeks the costs of this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">I certify that the preceding eighteen (18) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Associate:

Dated: 9 May 2006


 Counsel for the Applicants: J Johnson 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Sally Nash &amp; Co 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: MR Aldridge SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Russo &amp; Partners 
 
 Date of Hearing: 4 April 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 4 April 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/524.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>