<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Seymour v Migration Agents Registration Authority [2006] FCA 649 (31 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/649.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for review of a decision of the administrative appeals tribunal ("aat")</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">aat decision to refuse application for stay of decision of migration agents registration authority to refuse migration registration application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">effect of s 300(7) of migration act 1958 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether stay would be effective</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 Introduction 
 
1 This is an application for review of a decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ("AAT"), dated 27 April 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application is made under s 13 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) (" ADJR Act ") and s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) (" Judiciary Act ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The AAT refused to grant a stay under s 41(2) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) (" AAT Act ") against the operation of a decision of the first respondent, the Migration Agents Registration Authority ("the MARA") made on 20 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">On that date the MARA refused an application made by the applicant for registration as a migration agent for the 12 month period from 24 May 2005 to 23 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ("the Act "), both in its previous form, and in the terms as amended by the Migration Legislation Amendment (Migration Agents Integrity Measures) Act 2004 (Cth) ("the Amending Act "), provided for migration agents to be registered and that the registration lasts for a period of 12 months after registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Application for registration must then be made annually.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">4 Section 300 of the Act provides for automatic continuation of a registered migration agent's registration in certain circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The provisions for automatic continuation were amended by the terms of the new s 300 introduced by the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">5 The AAT refused to grant the applicant a stay because it considered that the terms of the new s 300 prevented the AAT from granting a stay order which would be effective.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">6 The essential question which arises on this application is the proper construction of 
s 300, as introduced by the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">In particular, the application turns upon the construction of s 300(7) which provides that "for the purposes of this section", the MARA is taken to have made a decision, even if the decision is later stayed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The Relevant Legislation 
 
7 Prior to 1 July 2004, s 300 of the Act provided that:-
 
 "300 Automatic continuation of registration 
 
 (1) If: 
 
 (a) before the end of the last day (the expiry day) of the period of registration of a registered agent, the agent has made a registration application; and 
 
 (b) the agent has paid the registration application fee (if any) in respect of the application; and 
 
 (c) the Migration Agents Registration Authority has not decided the application before the end of the expiry day; 
 
 the agent's registration is taken to continue until the Authority decides the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">
 
 (2) Application granted if no decision within a certain period 
 However, if the Authority has not decided the registration application before the end of the period of 10 months beginning on the day after the expiry day, the application is taken to have been granted at the end of that period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">
 
 (3) When registration takes effect 
 If the Authority grants the registration application, or the registration application is taken to have been granted under subsection (2), the registration is treated as having taken effect at the end of the expiry day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">" 
 
8 In Shi v Migration Institute of Australia [2003] FCA 1304 ; (2003) 134 FCR 326 (" Shi") , Tamberlin J considered this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">His Honour described the repeat registration system as a 'continuum' and found that s 300 operated as a deeming provision so that an agent is treated as if s/he were registered and has the same rights as if s/he were registered up to the time of the making of the decision not to renew.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">He concluded that a decision by the MARA not to renew has an operation capable of being stayed, pursuant to s 41(2) of the AAT Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">9 However, on 1 July 2004, amendments contained in the Amending Act came into effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">By Item 63 in Schedule 1 of the Amending Act , s 300 was repealed and substituted with the following:
 
 "300 Automatic continuation of registration 
 
 When agent's registration is automatically continued 

 (1) Subsection (4) applies to continue a registered migration agent's registration beyond the last day (the expiry day) of the agent's registration if, before the end of the expiry day: 
 
 (a) the agent made a registration application; and 
 
 (b) the agent paid the registration application fee (if any) in respect of the application; and 
 
 (c) the Migration Agents Registration Authority had not decided the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">
 
 Exception--suspension 

 (2) However, subsection (4) does not apply to continue the agent's registration if, before the end of the expiry day, the Authority made a decision to suspend the agent's registration, unless: 
 
 (a) the suspension had been completed before the end of the expiry day; or 
 
 (b) there was a decision (other than a stay order) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal or a court in force, immediately before the end of the expiry day, to the effect that the agent's registration is not suspended or cancelled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">
 
 Exception--cancellation 

 (3) Subsection (4) also does not apply to continue the agent's registration if, before the end of the expiry day, the Authority made a decision to cancel the agent's registration, unless: 
 
 (a) there was a decision (other than a stay order) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal or a court in force, immediately before the end of the expiry day, to the effect that the agent's registration is not suspended or cancelled; or 
 
 (b) there was a decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal or a court in force to the effect that the agent's registration is suspended, and the suspension had been completed before the end of the expiry day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">
 
 Period of continuation of registration 

 (4) The agent's registration is taken to continue after the expiry day until the earliest of the following: 
 
 (a) the Authority decides the application; 
 
 (b) the Authority decides to suspend the agent's registration; 
 
 (c) the Authority decides to cancel the agent's registration; 
 
 (d) the end of the period of 10 months beginning on the day after the expiry day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">
 
 Application granted if no decision within a certain period 

 (5) If, before the end of the period of 10 months beginning on the day after the expiry day, the Authority has not: 
 
 (a) decided the registration application; and 
 
 (b) decided to suspend the agent's registration; and 
 
 (c) decided to cancel the agent's registration; 
 
 then the application is taken to have been granted at the end of that period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">
 
 When registration takes effect 

 (6) If the Authority grants the registration application, or the registration application is taken to have been granted under subsection (5), the registration is treated as having taken effect at the end of the expiry day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">
 
 When Authority makes decision 
 
 (7) For the purposes of this section, the Authority is taken to have made a decision even if the decision is later stayed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">" 
 Background 
 
10 The applicant was first registered as a migration agent on 15 April 1994.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">For reasons which are not clear, the applicant's registration came to expire on 23 May each year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">11 In May 2004, the applicant applied for registration for the year from 24 May 2004 to 23 May 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The application was refused by the MARA in February 2005 but the AAT subsequently granted a stay of the decision under the terms of the Act as in force prior to the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The MARA's decision was affirmed by the AAT in January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Judicial review of that decision has been sought from another judge of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">That matter is quite separate from the present proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">12 On 5 May 2005, the applicant lodged his application for registration for 24 May 2005 to 23 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The parties agree that the amended s 300 was in force at the time of the application, by virtue of the transitional provisions in Item 179A in Schedule 1 to the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">13 On 20 February 2006, the MARA rejected the application for the period 24 May 2005 to 23 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The Decision of the AAT 
 
14 The applicant sought a stay of the decision of the MARA in the AAT, arguing that a stay would have the effect of prolonging registration under s 300 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">15 The learned Deputy President referred to the decision of Tamberlin J in Shi .</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">However, he observed that Shi was decided on the Act as it stood before the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The question for the Deputy President was therefore whether there was power to grant a stay under the new s 300 introduced by the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">16 The AAT referred to the amendments to s 300 and the supplementary explanatory memorandum to the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">It noted that the effect of s 300(4)(a) was that the Applicant's registration as a migration agent ceased on 20 February 2006 when the MARA made its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">17 The AAT then considered s 300(7), stating at [17](d)] that:-
 
 "The clear import of section 300(7) is that a decision once made (and the term decision must include a decision under subsection 4(a)) stands notwithstanding that it might be the subject of a stay order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">" 
 

18 The AAT concluded at [21] that:-
 
 "To grant a stay order in these circumstances would be entirely without purpose, and simply because it would not be effective.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The registration of the Applicant ceased on 20 February 2006 and without registration he cannot act as a migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">To grant a stay order might have the effect that the public is misled and moreover would expose the Applicant to prosecution under a number of sections of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">I appreciate that the effect of this decision might appear to be harsh; however, the legislation is cast in terms which in my view, prevents me from granting a stay order which is effective.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">" 
 The Proper Approach to Statutory Construction 
 
19 The modern approach to statutory construction is to construe the relevant provision in its context so that it is consistent with the language and purpose of all the provisions of the statute; see CIC Insurance Limited v Bankstown Football Club Limited [1997] HCA 2 ; (1997) 187 CLR 384 at 408 (Brennan CJ, Dawson, Toohey and Gummow JJ); Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at [69] (McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Recourse to extrinsic material, including the legislative history and explanatory material such as a Second Reading Speech is permitted; see Newcastle City Council v GIO General Limited [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85 at 99 (Toohey, Gaudron and Gummow JJ) and at 112 (McHugh J); Isherwood v Butler Pollnow Pty Limited (1986) 6 NSWLR 363 at 387-388 (McHugh JA).</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Part 3 of the Act , as amended by the Amending Act 
 
20 Section 300 is located within Part 3 of the Act ; this part deals with the provision of assistance to persons in connection with applications for migration visas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Persons must be registered as migration agents in order to give, and charge a fee for, migration assistance; see ss 280 and 281 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Severe penalties are imposed for the breach of these provisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">21 Division 3 of Part 3 concerns the registration of persons as migration agents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Central to these provisions are the duties and powers of the MARA to determine applications for registration, cancel or suspend a migration agent's registration, or caution a migration agent; see s 303.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">22 The provisions setting out the requirements for registration are highly prescriptive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">When applying for registration, different criteria apply to those who have, in the 12 months prior to making an application, been a registered migration agent, and those who have not; see ss 288(2) and 288A .</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The criteria in relation to the latter group is more onerous, and includes completion of a prescribed course, within a prescribed period, and passing a prescribed exam or having prescribed qualifications; see s 289A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">23 In addition, every applicant must satisfy certain character requirements; s 290 provides as follows:-
 
 "290 Applicant must not be registered if not a person of integrity or not fit and proper 
 (1) An applicant must not be registered if the Migration Agents Registration Authority is satisfied that: 
 (a) the applicant is not a fit and proper person to give immigration assistance; or 
 (b) the applicant is not a person of integrity; or 
 (c) the applicant is related by employment to an individual who is not a person of integrity and the applicant should not be registered because of that relationship.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">
 (2) In considering whether it is satisfied that the applicant is not fit and proper or not a person of integrity, the Migration Agents Registration Authority must take into account: 
 (a) the extent of the applicant's knowledge of migration procedure; and 
 (c) any conviction of the applicant of a criminal offence relevant to the question whether the applicant is not: 
 (i) a fit and proper person to give immigration assistance; or 
 (ii) a person of integrity; 
 (except a conviction that is spent under Part VIIC of the Crimes Act 1914 ); and 
 (d) any criminal proceedings that the applicant is the subject of and that the Authority considers relevant to the application; and 
 (e) any inquiry or investigation that the applicant is or has been the subject of and that the Authority considers relevant to the application; and 
 (f) any disciplinary action that is being taken, or has been taken, against the applicant that the Authority considers relevant to the application; and 
 (g) any bankruptcy (present or past) of the applicant; and 
 (h) any other matter relevant to the applicant's fitness to give immigration assistance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">
 (3) In considering whether it is satisfied that an individual to whom the applicant is related by employment is not a person of integrity, the Migration Agents Registration Authority must take into account each of the following matters, so far as the Authority considers it relevant to the question whether the individual is not a person of integrity: 
 (a) any conviction of the individual of a criminal offence (except a conviction that is spent under Part VIIC of the Crimes Act 1914); 
 (b) any criminal proceedings that the individual is the subject of; 
 (c) any inquiry or investigation that the individual is or has been the subject of; 
 (d) any disciplinary action that is being taken, or has been taken, against the individual; 
 (e) any bankruptcy (present or past) of the individual.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">
 (4) To avoid doubt, this section applies to all applicants (not just first time applicants).</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">" 
 
 

24 Furthermore, an applicant will not be registered if they have been refused registration as a migration agent within 12 months prior to making the application; see s 291.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">25 There are further requirements relating to professional development, professional indemnity insurance, age, citizenship, and residency; see ss 290A, 292B, 293 and 294.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">26 As noted earlier, registration lasts for 12 months (see s 299), though this period is subject to a number of other provisions, including s 300, which has been reproduced above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">27 Section 303 gives the MARA power to discipline registered migration agents, and in particular to cancel or suspend an agent's registration or caution that agent if satisfied that:-
 
 "(d) the agent's application for registration was known by the agent to be false or misleading in a material particular; or 
 
 (e) the agent becomes bankrupt; or 
 
 (f) the agent is not a person of integrity or is otherwise not a fit and proper person to give immigration assistance; or 
 
 (g) an individual related by employment to the agent is not a person of integrity; or 
 
 (h) the agent has not complied with the Code of Conduct prescribed under section 314.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">" 
 

 
28 Provision is also made in ss 305 and 305A for the publication of disciplinary decisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">29 An application may be made to the AAT for review of a decision by the MARA: s 306.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Section 306AA states that:-
 
 "If the Administrative Appeals Tribunal or a court orders a stay of a decision under section 303 to cancel or suspend a registered migration agent's registration, it is taken to be a condition of the order that the prescribed supervisory requirements apply in relation to the agent during the period of the order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">" 
 

30 Division 3 of Part 3 of the Act constitutes a highly regulated system of registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">It reveals an intention to ensure, so far as possible, that registered migration agents have and maintain sufficient training and good character so that they provide appropriate immigration assistance to visa applicants and persons seeking advice on migration questions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">31 Tamberlin J observed in Shi at [14] that Part 3 of the Act was introduced in 1992 with the purpose of establishing a comprehensive scheme for registration and control of migration agents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Prior to its introduction, there was no regulation of migration agents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The emphasis in Division 3, Part 3 on migration agents having sufficient training and good character, and the provisions relating to publication of disciplinary proceedings indicates a concern that the integrity of the visa scheme governed by the Act is maintained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Proper Construction of s 300 
 
32 Section s 300 is to be construed in its context in light of the statutory scheme to which I have referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">It is to be borne in mind that a registered agent does not have a right to be re-registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Applications must be made each year and the criteria for registration must be satisfied on each application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">33 It is true that s 300(1) operates so as to extend the period of registration of a registered migration agent beyond the expiry date of the agent's registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The combined effect of ss 300(1) and (4) is that a registered agent's registration is taken to continue after the expiry date, provided that the requirements of s 300(1) (a) to (c) are satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">34 However, s 300(4) makes it plain that the registration is taken to continue only until the earliest of the decisions of the MARA specified in s 300(4) (a) to (c), or the date specified in s 300(4)(d).</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">35 The effect of s 300(4) is that although the usual period of registration is for 12 months, it may be extended for a period of up to 10 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">36 But it is plain from s 300(4)(a) that the statutory extension of an agent's registration ceases when the MARA decides the application in respect of the current year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">If the decision is favourable to the agent, he or she is registered for the full 12 month period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">37 However, if the MARA's decision is to refuse registration, then the applicant ceases to be a registered migration agent, so long as that decision is made before the end of the 10 month extension provided for in s 300(4)(d).</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">38 The same consequence applies if the MARA's decision is to suspend or cancel the agent's registration; see s 300(4)(b) and (c).</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">39 If the MARA's decision is to refuse registration, an applicant may seek review of the decision of the AAT; see s 306.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">An appeal on a question of law lies to the Court from the decision of the AAT; see s 44(1) of the AAT Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Alternatively, the decision of the AAT is amenable to judicial review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">40 It is in those circumstances that the effect of s 300(7) falls for consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">41 The ordinary meaning of s 300(7) follows from the opening words.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">It is plain that the words "(f)or the purposes of this section" apply to each type of decision referred to in 
s 300(1) to (6).</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">42 Thus, upon the proper construction of ss 300(4)(a) and (7), the statutory extension of an agent's registration ceases when the MARA decides to refuse the application for registration, even if that decision is later stayed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">43 This is the ordinary meaning of s 300(4)(a) and s 300(7).</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">It is consistent with the scheme of Division 3 of Part 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">It is consistent, in particular, with the central role of the MARA in regulating the scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">It achieves the dual aim of the provisions of Division 3 of Part 3 , being the protection of visa applicants and maintaining the integrity of the visa scheme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">44 It may also be thought that this meaning is consistent with the title of the Amending Act , that is to say the Migration Legislation Amendment (Migration Agents Integrity Measures) Act 2004 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The Extrinsic Material 
 
45 The relevant extrinsic material gives unqualified support to the view I have expressed as to the proper construction of ss 300(4)(a) and (7).</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">46 The learned Deputy President set out in full at [14] of the decision of the AAT the content of the relevant paragraphs of the Supplementary Explanatory Memorandum to the Amending Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Those paragraphs explain the provisions of s 300 and I do not propose to repeat them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">47 However, I should observe that [30], [31] and [36] of the Supplementary Explanatory Memorandum state in the plainest terms that the statutory extension continues only until the decision of the MARA, or until the other events stated in s 300(4).</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">48 Moreover, [41] of the Supplementary Explanatory Memorandum states that 
s 300(7) "makes it clear that for the purposes of s 300, the MARA is taken to have made a decision, even if it is later stayed".</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Reference is made, by way of example, to orders staying the operation of a suspension or cancellation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">49 Although this paragraph of the Supplementary Explanatory Memorandum refers to only two of the three types of decision referred to in s 300(4), these words can only be used as a guide to the meaning of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">They do not replace the statutory language; see Re Bolton; Ex parte Beane [1987] HCA 12 ; (1987) 162 CLR 514 at 518 (Mason CJ, Wilson and Dawson JJ); see also R v Young [1999] NSWCCA 166 ; (1999) 46 NSWLR 681 at [35] (Spigelman CJ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">50 In my opinion it is clear that the Supplementary Explanatory Memorandum referred to a cancellation and suspension only by way of example.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">It is clear that the draftsman of the document was pointing to the effect of s 300(7) in relation to all types of decisions contemplated by the section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">51 If further support be needed, it may be found in the Second Reading Speech made by Mr Gary Hargrave, the Minister for Citizenship and Multicultural Affairs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">52 The Minister said, on 24 March 2004, at Hansard p 27110, that the Amending Act , dealt inter alia , with concerns about sanctioned agents no longer being able to practice once their registration year expires.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">He said that such an agent will no longer be able to practice after the expiry date by making an application for review and obtaining a stay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">53 These comments, on their face, seem to be directed at agents whose registration is suspended or cancelled but the overall thrust of the speech supports the construction which I have adopted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">The applicant's submissions 
 
54 The essence of the applicant's submission is that the opening words of s 300(7) are limited to decisions of the MARA to suspend or cancel the agent's registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">55 However, there is simply no warrant for this approach in the plain meaning of 
s 300(4) or the plain words of s 300(7).</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">The words "for the purposes of this section" mean what they say.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">There is nothing to suggest that they should be read down in the manner urged by the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">56 The applicant submits that the AAT's decision ignores the power given to the AAT to stay decisions of the MARA pursuant to s 306AA and Regulation 7B of the Migration Agents Regulations 1998 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">
 
57 However, s306AA is not concerned with a stay of a decision refusing an application for registration which was deemed continuing by force of s 300(1) and (4).</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">Rather, s 306AA deals with orders staying a decision under s 303 to cancel or suspend the registration of an agent who has already been registered for the current year; that is, prior to the cancellation or suspension.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">This was illustrated in Tanari v Migration Agents Registration Authority [2005] AATA 419 (" Tanari ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">58 Section 300 lays down a different regime for deemed registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">Quite plainly, a migration agent whose application for registration in the current year is granted, is no longer deemed registered; s/he is actually registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">But the registration is treated as having taken effect at the end of the expiry date; ie from the commencement of the current year; see s 300(6).</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">59 Section 300(4)(b) and (c) therefore deal with the situation where the MARA decides, during the period of deemed continuation of registration (but before the grant of any application for registration), to suspend or cancel the agent's registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">The relevant regime is explained by reference to s 300(2) and (3) when read with s 300(4).</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">60 Section 300(2) and (3) deal with the situation where an application for registration is made before the end of the expiry day and, between the date of the application and the end of the expiry day suspension or cancellation proceedings are brought against the agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">If, between those dates the MARA makes a decision to suspend or cancel the registration, then s 300(4) does not apply to continue the agent's registration unless the conditions stated in s 300(2)(a) or (b) or s 300(a) or (b) are satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">61 Section 300(4)(b) and (c) must therefore address the situation where suspension or cancellation proceedings are on foot between the date of application and the expiry day but the MARA has not made a decision on those proceedings until after the expiry day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">The effect of ss 300(4)(b) and (c) is that, if the MARA then decides to suspend or cancel the registration, the deemed continuation ceases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">62 Such a decision, as with a decision taken during the deeming period to refuse an application for registration, is not amenable to an effective stay by virtue of the provisions in s 300(7).</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">63 This approach to the proper construction is supported by the Minister's Second Reading speech to which I referred in [51] --- [52].</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">64 The applicant submits that the interpretation of s 300(7) which I have adopted produces an "absurd result".</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">Mr Hurley argues that Part 3 creates a scheme where registration is paramount, is to be obtained over short periods, and decisions refusing registration are subject to merits review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">The applicant submits that without the possibility of staying a decision of the MARA, the merits review system is 'useless' unless concluded within one registration year, for otherwise, an agent would not be eligible for re-registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">65 The applicant also points to the serious consequences of the AAT's decision for the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The practical effect of the decision is that he can no longer practice as a migration agent and so is deprived of the opportunity to pursue his livelihood, at least until he obtains successful merits review or successfully applies afresh for registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">66 I do not think these consequences can be described as "absurd".</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">It seems to me that the construction given to s 300(7) by the AAT is consistent with the purpose of the provisions and the clear wording of the section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">Upon a decision to refuse registration, s 300(4)(a) is enlivened and the deeming provision in s 300(1) ceases to have the effect of continuing an agent's registration; section 300(7) evinces a clear legislative intention that even a stay cannot operate to defeat the effect of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Conclusion and Orders 
 
67 The AAT has made no error of law, and the application must be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">
 
 
I certify that the preceding sixty-seven (67) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">Associate:

Date: 31 May 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr T Hurley 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr J Smith 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 10 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 31 May 2006 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/649.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>