<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>S307/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multiculturaland Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 650 (30 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/650.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for review of decision of refugee review tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">doctrine of res judicata</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 BACKGROUND 
 
1 The two applicants, a mother ("the applicant") and her son, are citizens of India.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">They arrived in Australia on 18 July 1997 and lodged a combined application for protection visas with the Department of Immigration and Multicultural Affairs on 24 December 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">On 8 April 1998, the applications were refused by a delegate of the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The applicants sought review of that decision before the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the Tribunal") on 4 May 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">On 27 March 2000, the Tribunal affirmed the decision of the delegate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">2 The applicant then applied to the Federal Court for judicial review of the decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">That application was heard by Moore J on 7 September 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Both the applicant and the respondent were represented by counsel at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On 5 October 2000, Moore J dismissed the application and ordered the applicant to pay the costs of the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">3 On 17 June 2003, the applicant filed an application in the High Court of Australia for an order nisi requiring the respondents to show cause why constitutional writs should not be issued in respect of the decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The applicant supported her application for an order nisi by an affidavit sworn by her on 16 June 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">4 The application was remitted to this Court pursuant to orders made by Gaudron J following the delivery of judgment in Muin v Refugee Review Tribunal [2002] HCA 30 ; (2002) 190 ALR 601.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 By letter dated 12 November 2004, the District Registrar of this Court notified the applicant that the Court proposed to consider whether there was an arguable case on the basis of the written material that the applicant had given to the Court and without any oral hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The applicant was invited to file written submissions on the question of whether the Court should make an order nisi .</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Written submissions were filed by the applicant on 10 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">6 I propose to deal with this application on the papers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">DISCUSSION 
 
 7 Res judicata arises where a cause of action relied on in proceedings has, in former proceedings, passed into judgment so that it has merged and has no longer an independent existence: see Blair v Curren [1939] HCA 23 ; (1939) 62 CLR 464 at 532 per Dixon J; Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589 at 597 per Gibbs CJ, Mason and Aickin JJ ( Anshun ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The doctrine of res judicata represents a complete bar to a new application because the cause of action is extinguished by the judgment: see Anshun at 612-3 per Brennan J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">8 The question to be determined on a plea of res judicata is whether the cause of action relied upon in the proceedings in which the plea is raised is the same cause of action which has been determined in the earlier proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">In determining that question, the Court will have regard to the substance rather than the form of the proceedings: Trawl Industries of Australia Pty Ltd v Effem Foods Pty Ltd (1992) 36 FCR 406 (affirmed (1993) 43 FCR 510).</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">9 In the draft order nisi , the applicants claim that the Tribunal failed to afford them natural justice because they had not been given an opportunity (or at least an adequate opportunity) to prepare and present favourable material at the hearing or an adequate opportunity to respond to unfavourable material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">In her supporting affidavit, the applicant does not give any particulars of the material that she wished to present to the Tribunal or the unfavourable material that she did not have an opportunity to respond to.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">There is no evidence before me that would support the applicant's claim that she was denied natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">10 The submissions filed by the applicant on 10 December 2004 raise a number of grounds of review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">First, the applicant submits that the Tribunal erred in failing to determine whether, on the totality of the facts found, she had a well-founded fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Secondly, it is argued that the Tribunal misunderstood the elements of the definition of a refugee under the Convention which were supported by the facts of the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Thirdly, the applicant says that the Tribunal erred in finding that women in India and/or Sikh women did not constitute a social group for Convention purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Fourthly, the applicant claims that she was denied procedural fairness as the Tribunal forced her to attend the hearing despite the fact that she had informed it of her psychological condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Finally, the applicant made a number of claims regarding the merits of the decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">In particular, the applicant says that the Tribunal did not realise that she suffered because of her husband's involvement in the Sikh movements and that she has a fear of harm by the Indian police authorities, who have provided her with no protection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">11 The grounds of review before Moore J were, in substance, the same as the first and third grounds outlined in the applicant's written submissions in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">These grounds are set out in the judgment of Moore J at [10]: 
 
 "In the proceedings in this Court, counsel for the applicant pressed two grounds of review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">First, it was argued that the Tribunal failed to determine whether, on the totality of the facts as found, the applicant had a well-founded fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Second, it was said that the Tribunal erred in finding that women in India, or Sikh women, did not constitute a particular social group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Each of these errors was said to constitute an error involving an incorrect interpretation of the applicable law or an incorrect application of the law to the facts, and thus to amount to errors of law pursuant to s 476(1)(e) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">" 

12 The judgment and orders of Moore J were final and resolved a controversy between the applicant and the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Accordingly, the doctrine of res judicata applies to the present application because, in substance, it seeks review of the same Tribunal decision that was the subject of the applicant's previous judicial review application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The facts giving rise to the right to review are the same and the grounds of review are the same.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The right to relief in each case is informed by the same principles of substantive law and the proceedings do not differ in any material respect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">13 I have considered the reasons for decision of the Tribunal and can see no reviewable error of principle or law which would warrant further consideration of the applicants' case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">14 The application for an order nisi should therefore be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">I certify that the preceding fourteen (14) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tamberlin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Associate:

Dated: 30 May 2006


 The Applicant is self-represented 
 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 May 2006 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/650.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>