<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited; Pendant Software Pty Limited v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 (6 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/717.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interlocutory application to restrain defendant from taking any further step in a proceeding/application in the takeovers panel</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">interlocutory application for orders to dismiss or stay court proceeding</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">pre-emptive rights regime under company constitution</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">takeover offer</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether it is within discretion of directors to refuse to register acceptance of shares for reason that may prevent a higher bid</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">where application made to takeovers panel</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">whether same substratum of facts before takeovers panel and the court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">whether declaration by the takeovers panel would render proceeding in court nugatory</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">role of the takeovers panel under the corporations act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 There are two interlocutory applications before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">An interlocutory application on behalf of the plaintiff, Pendant Software Pty Limited ("Pendant Software") for an order that the second defendant, Mr Berend Hoff, be restrained from taking any further step directly or indirectly in a proceeding/application commenced by him in the Takeovers Panel pursuant to the application made by him dated 25 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 There is also a notice of motion filed on behalf of the first, fourth and fifth defendants, that the proceeding be dismissed generally, or as against them with no order as to costs and in the alternative, an order that the proceeding be stayed generally or against them, until further order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">3 The background to the applications is set against a takeover offer by Pendant Software for all of the shares in the capital of Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited ("Tower").</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Tower has an issued capital of 31,176,500 shares held by approximately 124 shareholders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">It carries on the business of the supply of software for document management in large organisations, primarily to government and large bureaucratic institutions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Pendant Properties Pty Limited, a company associated with Pendant Software, holds 9,521,000 shares in the capital of Tower representing approximately 30.54 per cent of its issued capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 The second defendant, Mr Hoff, a director of Tower, owns 9,432,464 shares in the capital of Tower representing approximately 30.26 per cent of its issued capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Tower's Constitution has pre-emptive rights for existing shareholders which restrict the opportunity for shareholders to transfer shares in Tower without first offering them to existing shareholders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">These pre-emptive rights are found in rule 120 of the Constitution of Tower.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Rule 120.1 provides that:
 
 "Subject to rule 120.8, no shares may be transferred to a person who is not a member so long as any member or members are willing to purchase them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">" 

Thereafter follow provisions to determine whether or not there are any such members who are willing to purchase any shares which a member wishes to transfer or offer for sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 Rule 121 which is headed, "Registration of Transfers --- Directors' discretion", provides that subject to rule 120.8 the directors may in their discretion refuse to register a transfer of shares from a member to a non member without assigning any reason for refusal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Rule 120.8 is not relevant for present purposes but it provides for the transfer of shares to family members or related entities of a member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">6 On 9 January 2006, Tower sent to shareholders a transfer notice received from a shareholder, Equity Partners One Pty Limited ("Equity Partners"), which was seeking to sell 4,500,000 shares in Tower for $1.45 per share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Tower's notice to shareholders offered these shares to existing members in accordance with the pre-emptive rights provision contained in rule 120.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">No shareholders wanted to purchase any of the shares offered for sale by Equity Partners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">On 2 February 2006, Tower notified Equity Partners of this fact and stated in a letter:
 
 "I wish to formally confirm that pursuant to the Notice and subsequent offer for sale of shares held by Equity Partners One Pty Limited (EP) that TOWER Software Engineering, acting as agent on behalf of EP has not found any member or members willing to purchase any of the shares offered for sale by EP.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">
 
 Accordingly, EP is at liberty, subject to rule 121 to sell or transfer the shares (or any of them) to any eligible person at a price not less than the price placed on the shares in the Notice at any time before 2 nd May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">" 


 
7 On 18 April 2006, Pendant Software announced a takeover offer for all the shares in Tower and served a bidder's statement and offer on Tower on that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The offer price was $1.45 per share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The takeover announcement and offer also noted that rule 120 of Tower's Constitution applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The conditions of the offer also included a condition numbered 10.8, headed "Registration of Transfers" which provided:
 
 "This Offer and any contract that results from your acceptance of it are subject to the further condition that: 
 
 the directors of Tower Software agree to register all acceptances and transfers received by Pendant under the Offer no later than 10 days after acceptances become unconditional or 10 days from the end of the Offer Period (unless extended under the Corporations Act ) whichever is the earlier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">If this condition is not fulfilled, all contracts resulting from the acceptance of the Offer will be automatically void.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">This condition cannot be waived by Pendant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">" 

8 On 18 April 2006 the directors of Tower agreed, with Mr Hoff dissenting, to the following resolution: 
 
 "The Board resolved, Brand [sic] Hoff dissenting, to acknowledge receipt of the Bidder's Statement and further resolved, without Bill Frost participating in the vote, to consent to the Bidder's Statement being sent by Pendant Software Pty Ltd to all Company shareholders and option holders as soon as Pendant Software Pty Ltd chooses, noting that this may be earlier than otherwise provided in the Corporations Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The majority of the Directors were of the opinion that it was in the interests of Tower Software to consent to early distribution so that shareholders, and staff in particular, were as fully informed as practicable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Mr Frost declared his interest as a Director and shareholder in the Bidder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">" 
 

On 20 April 2006, Pendant Software received an acceptance and transfer dated 19 April 2006 from Equity Partners in respect of its 4,500,000 shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The acceptance and transfer form was signed by Pendant Software and dated 20 April 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">9 On 1 May 2006 Pendant Software declared its offer unconditional pursuant to s 650F of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) ("the Act ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">It served a notice on Tower which stated:
 
 "Pendant Software Pty Limited ( Pendant ) gives notice under Section 650F of the Corporations Act and Section 10.11 of Pendant's Offer dated 18 April 2006 ( Offer) made pursuant to the Bidder's Statement dated 18 th April 2006 ( Bidder's Statement ) and Supplementary Statement dated 19 April 2006, in relation to its takeover bid for all of the issued ordinary shares and to any person who becomes registered or entitled to be registered as the holder of shares in Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited ( Tower Software ) that: 
 
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">It declares each Offer and any contract resulting from acceptance of such Offer free from all the conditions set out in Section 10.7 of the Bidder's Statement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">
 
 
 
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">As at 9.00 am on the date of this Notice, Pendant has received acceptances under the Offer for 4,500,000 shares in Tower Software, being 14.43% of all shares in Tower Software on issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Pendant therefore has voting power in these shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">
 
 
 
 
 
 It is noted that while Pendant is not the registered holder of any shares in Tower Software that Pendant Properties Pty Ltd, which is associated with Pendant, holds 9,521,000 shares in Tower Software comprising a further 30.54% of Tower Software's shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Pendant also has or is deemed to have voting power in those shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">
 
 Accordingly, as at 9.00 am on the date of this Notice, Pendant has voting power in a total of 14,021,000 Tower Software shares, being 44.97% of all Tower Software shares on issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">" 
 

10 On 1 May 2006, Mr Frost, a director of Pendant Software, and also a director of Tower, wrote to the Chairman of Tower, Mr Service, in the following terms:
 
 "A Section 650F Notice was given to Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited ( Tower Software ), effective today (copy attached).</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">As Pendant Software Pty Ltd ( Pendant ) has a legally binding unconditional acceptance and transfer from Equity Partners One Pty Ltd ( Equity Partners ) for 4,500,000 shares (14.43%) I formally request a meeting of Tower Software directors to be held at the soonest possible date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">
 
 At that meeting I will request that the directors resolve to agree to register all acceptances and transfers received by Pendant under the Offer to acquire all the shares in Tower Software as per Condition 10.8 of the Bidder's Statement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 
 Also Pendant will require a separate resolution agreeing to register the aforementioned transfer of 4,500,000 shares in Tower Software from Equity Partners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">
 
 I draw your attention to the 10 day time frame under Condition 10.8 of the Bidder's Statement and request a meeting of directors be held in sufficient time to give Pendant Software (if the directors so resolve to register all the acceptances and transfers) 3 working days to have the Equity Partners transfers stamped under ACT law and then registered in Pendant Software's name.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">" 

11 A directors' meeting was called for 4 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Prior to the meeting the Chairman of Tower, the fifth defendant, obtained a memorandum of advice from Tower's solicitors, Mallesons Stephen Jaques.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">In this memorandum of advice the solicitors summarised the background to the takeover offer and the transfer from Equity Partners, gave advice in relation to the exercise of directors' discretion and as to the legality of the agreement in relation to the transfer of Equity Partners' shares to Pendant Software.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">In particular section 4.7 of the advice which was headed, "Can directors take a further possible bid into account?</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">" stated:
 
 "In exercising their discretion to refuse to register a transfer, the Directors must have regard to what they consider is in the best interests of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">In our view, where registration of a transfer might prevent or discourage a new bid at a higher price and there is a real prospect of such a bid, that is a factor to which the Directors could properly have regard in exercising their discretion to refuse registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">" 
 

A copy of that advice was given to Mr Frost who sought counsel's advice in response to it and obtained that counsel's advice on 2 May.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Counsel's advice joined issue with the advice of Mallesons Stephen Jaques and in substance argued that it was improper for the directors to take into account the possibility of another bid at a higher price as being a reason for justifying the refusal to register the shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">This particular matter was dealt with in paragraphs 41, 48 and 49 of counsel's advice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">12 The directors' meeting was held on 4 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The chairman tabled a letter from Quadrant Private Equity Pty Limited which stated that Quadrant submitted a confidential, non binding proposal on behalf of funds advised by it to acquire on a friendly basis Tower, and set out in summary the proposal with an indicative price of $1.55 per share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The proposal was noted to be incomplete, confidential and non binding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">13 Item 5 on the agenda before the Board was the transfer by Equity Partners to Pendant Software.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">According to Mr Frost he tabled the acceptance and transfer form executed by Equity Partners in respect of the 4,500,000 shares held by it and moved two resolutions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The first was that the directors of Tower agree to register the acceptance and transfer received by Pendant Software under its offer dated 18 April 2006 from Equity Partners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The second resolution was that the directors of Tower agree to register all acceptances and transfers received by Pendant Software under the offer no later than 10 days after acceptances became unconditional or 10 days from the end of the offer period, unless extended under the Act , whichever was the earlier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">14 According to the Chairman, Mr Service, and the company secretary, the resolution which was put was that the transfer tabled by Mr Frost in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the company from Equity Partners to Pendant Software, for a total consideration of $6,525,000 be registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">For present purposes nothing turns on the difference in the versions of the resolution which were put.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">In the events which occurred the resolution in relation to the transfer was put, and was defeated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Mr Frost abstained from voting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The second resolution was put and that was defeated as well and again Mr Frost abstained from voting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">15 What then occurred was that after discussion by the Board a further resolution was proposed in the following terms:
 
 "The Directors of Tower agree to register all acceptances and transfers received by Pendant Software Pty Limited under the Offer, such registration to occur after the Offer Period, provided that: 


 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">The transfers: 


 
 
 &#8226; have been properly stamped; 
 &#8226; are signed by a member of Tower as transferor and Pendant Software as transferee; 
 &#8226; are in respect of shares in Tower of which the transferring member is registered as the holder; and 
 &#8226; relate to shares in respect of which rule 120 of Tower's Constitution either does not apply or has been satisfied; 
 


 
 
 2. to do so would not involve a breach of duty on the part of Directors and it is not otherwise unlawful; and 
 


 
 
 3. no higher offer is made for Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited's shares during the Offer Period (as extended under the Corporations Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">" 
 


That resolution was passed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">16 Mr Frost in his capacity as a director of Pendant Software, was concerned that;
 
 (a) this last resolution did not constitute a consent or approval to registration within s 1071F(1)(a) of the Act; (b) condition 10.8 of the offer remained unsatisfied and would remain so on 12 May 2006 so that the offer automatically terminated on that date; (c) the directors may have acted unlawfully in refusing to agree to register the transfer from Equity Partners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">

17 As a result, the proceeding in this Court was instituted against the directors of Tower on 9 May with a claim for interlocutory relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The relief sought in the initiating process was:
 
 
 "1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">A declaration that the second and third provisos set out in the resolution of the directors of the company passed on 4 May 2006 (as set out in the affidavit of Frederick John Frost affirmed in this proceeding on 9 May 2006) are void and of no effect and that the said resolution is and was from 4 May 2006 otherwise valid according to its terms and constitutes and constituted a consent or approval to registration within the meaning of s 1071F(1)(a) of the Corporations Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">
 
 
 
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">An order nunc pro tunc (with effect from 4 May 2006) under section 1071F(2) of the Corporations Act that the instrument of transfer dated 19 April 2006 between Equity Partners One Pty Limited as transferor and the Plaintiff as transferee in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the capital of the First Defendant be registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">
 
 
 
 
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Further or alternatively, an order nunc pro tunc (with effect from 4 May 2006) under section 175 of the Corporations Act that the plaintiff be entered on the first defendant's register of members as the holder of the shares referred to in Order 2 of these orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">" 
 


 
18 The interlocutory relief was sought in the following terms:
 
 
 "1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Subject to final hearing and determination of the proceeding or further order, an interlocutory order requiring the defendants (as the "relevant authority" as that term is defined in s 1071F of the Corporations Act ), by no later than 5pm on 11 May 2006, to consent to or approve (subject only to payment of stamp duty) the registration of all instruments of transfer delivered to the company for registration by the plaintiff in respect of acceptances received by the plaintiff under the takeover offer made by the plaintiff for shares in the company dated 18 April 2006 including the instrument of transfer dated 19 April 2006 between Equity Partners One Pty Limited as transferor and the Plaintiff as transferee in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the capital of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">Further or alternatively and subject to final hearing and determination of the proceeding or further order, an interlocutory order requiring the defendants (as the "relevant authority" as that term is defined in s 1071F of the Corporations Act ), by no later than 5 pm on 11 May 2006, to consent to or approve (subject only to payment of stamp duty) the registration of the instrument of transfer dated 19 April 2006 between Equity Partners One Pty Limited as transferor and the Plaintiff as transferee in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the capital of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">
 
 
 
 
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Further or alternatively and subject to final hearing and determination of the proceeding, a condition set out below or further order, that the instrument of transfer dated 19 April 2006 between Equity Partners One Pty Limited as transferor and the Plaintiff as transferee in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the capital of the company (subject only to payment of stamp duty) be registered by no later than 5pm on 11 May 2006 and that the plaintiff be entered on the first defendant's register of members as the holder of said shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">
 
 
 
 CONDITION 
 
 
 The plaintiff consenting to its removal from the first defendant's register of members as the holder of said shares (and with effect as if the plaintiff had never been so registered) if the court discharges this injunction or determines, as a matter of final determination, that this order ought not to have been made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">
 
 
 
 
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">Directions for an urgent trial as may be appropriate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">" 
 
 
 
 

19 The cause of action was based substantially on s 1071F of the Act which provides: 
 
 "(1) If a relevant authority in relation to a company: 
 (a) refuses or fails to register; or 
 
 
 
 (b) refuses or fails to give its consent or approval to the registration of; 
 
 
 
 
 a transfer or transmission of securities of the company, the transferee or transmittee may apply to the Court for an order under this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">
 
 
 
 
 
 (2) If the Court is satisfied on the application that the refusal or failure was without just cause, the Court may: 
 (a) order that the transfer or transmission be registered; or 
 
 
 
 
 (b) make such other order as it thinks just and reasonable, including: 
 
 
 
 (i) in the case of a transfer or transmission of shares --- an order providing for the purchase of the shares by a specified member of the company or by the company; and 
 (ii) in the case of a purchase by the company --- an order providing for the reduction accordingly of the capital of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">
 
 
 (3) In this section: 
 relevant authority , in relation to a company, means: 
 
 
 
 (a) a person who has, 2 or more persons who together have, or a body that has, authority to register a transfer or transmission of securities of the company; or 
 (b) a person, 2 or more persons, or a body, whose consent or approval is required before a transfer or transmission of securities of the company is registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">" 
 
 

20 The application for interlocutory relief was heard on 11 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">It was opposed by the directors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">It was argued, in substance, that the third proviso to the resolution of 4 May 2006 disclosed a refusal to register the shares for an improper purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">21 In the course of the hearing s 659B of the Act was raised in relation to the Court's jurisdiction to hear the interlocutory application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Section 659B provides:
 
 
 "(1) Only the following may commence court proceedings in relation to a takeover bid, or proposed takeover bid, before the end of the bid period: 
 
 
 (a) ASIC; 
 (b) a Minister of the Commonwealth; 
 (c) a Minister of a State or Territory in this jurisdiction; 
 (d) the holder of an office established by a law of: 
 
 
 (i) the Commonwealth; or 
 (ii) a State or Territory in this jurisdiction; 
 
 
 
 
 (e) a body corporate incorporated for a public purpose by a law of: 
 
 
 
 
 (i) the Commonwealth; or 
 (ii) a State or Territory in this jurisdiction; 
 to the extent to which it is exercising a power conferred by a law of the Commonwealth or a State or Territory in this jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">
 
 
 
 (2) A court may stay: 
 
 
 
 (a) court proceedings in relation to a takeover bid or proposed takeover bid; or 
 (b) court proceedings that would have a significant effect on the progress of a takeover bid; 
 
 
 
 
 until the end of the bid period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 
 (3) In deciding whether to exercise its powers under subsection (2), the court is to have regard to: 
 (a) the purposes of this Chapter; and 
 (b) the availability of review by the Panel under Division 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">
 
 
 
 (4) For the purposes of this section: 
 
 
 court proceedings in relation to a takeover bid or proposed takeover bid : 
 (a) means any proceedings before a court in relation to: 
 
 
 (i) an action taken or to be taken as part of, or for the purposes of, the bid or the target's response to the bid; or 
 (ii) a document prepared or to be prepared, or a notice given or to be given, under this Chapter; and 
 
 
 (b) includes: 
 
 
 (i) proceedings to enforce an obligation imposed by this Chapter; or 
 (ii) proceedings for the review of a decision, or the exercise of a power or discretion, under this Chapter; or 
 (iii) proceedings for the review of a decision, or the exercise of a power or discretion, under Chapter 6C in relation to securities of the target of a takeover bid during the bid period; and 
 (iv) proceedings under Part 2F.1A for leave to bring, or to intervene in, proceedings referred to in paragraph (a) or subparagraph (b)(i), (ii) or (iii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">
 
 
 
 This is not limited to proceedings brought under this Chapter or this Act but includes proceedings under other Commonwealth and State or Territory laws (including the general law).</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">
 
 
 
 
 
 (5) Nothing in this section is intended to affect the jurisdiction of the High Court under section 75 of the Constitution .</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">" 
 

22 In the reasons I handed down on 11 May 2006 for granting the interlocutory relief, I found there was a serious question to be tried whether the relevant directors of Tower were under an obligation to agree to register the acceptances and transfers which were in issue in the proceeding and whether there may be a breach of duty in the steps taken already by the directors in relation to resolutions for the acceptance and consent to those transfers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">I also found that the balance of convenience was in favour of the grant of interlocutory relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">In relation to s 659B I found that although it might be put that the action before the Court was taken for the purpose of the bid an issue of characterisation of the relief arose because the substantive and ultimate relief which the plaintiff was seeking was a remedy for refusal of ultimate registration and an acceptance for registration of the transfers under s 1071F of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">I held that s 659B was a general provision and s 1071 was a specific provision in relation to a specific remedy and I considered that there was a serious question to be tried as to whether the Court had jurisdiction in relation to granting interlocutory relief where the ultimate relief sought was in respect of relief under s 1071F of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">23 I made a limited order on that day for the purpose of keeping the takeover offer alive having regard to the self executing nature of condition 10.8 of the offer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The order I made on that day subject to the usual undertaking as to damages which was given was in the following terms:
 
 
 "1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Subject to the final hearing and determination of the proceeding, the conditions set out below or further order, the defendants/respondents (as the "relevant authority" as that term is defined in s 1071F of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) ("the Act ") by no later than midnight on 11 May 2006, consent to or approve (subject only to payment of stamp duty) the registration of all instruments of transfer delivered to Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited ("the company") for registration by the plaintiff/applicant in respect of acceptances received by it under the takeover offer made by it for shares in the company dated 18 April 2006 including the instrument of transfer dated 19 April 2006 between Equity Partners One Pty Limited as transferor and the plaintiff/applicant as transferee in respect of 4,500,000 shares in the capital of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">
 
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The conditions referred to in par 1 of this order are as follows: 
 
 
 
 
 A This order shall be treated, as between the parties, as if never made if it is discharged or not continued at the final hearing and determination of this proceeding or by further order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 B This order shall be without prejudice to each of the defendants/respondents being at liberty to contend at any further hearing of this proceeding (including the final hearing and determination of this proceeding) that: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) this order ought not have been made 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) that they are not required to register acceptances and transfers received by the plaintiff/applicant under the Offer on the basis that: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) to do so would involve a breach of duty on their part and is otherwise lawful 
 (b) a higher offer is made for the company's shares during the Offer Period (as extended under the Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">
 
 
 
 
 C The plaintiff/applicant will not, by virtue of the making of this order, contend that the making of this order constitutes an admission by the defendants/respondents or any of them that they were not entitled to pass the resolution in the form of Resolution 3 (as referred to in par 61 of the affidavit of Frederick John Frost affirmed in this proceeding on 9 May 2006) or that such resolution did not constitute an agreement or consent for the purposes of s 1071F of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">
 
 
 
 
 
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Liberty is reserved to all parties to apply on one day's written notice to each other party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">
 
 
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Costs reserved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">" 


 
24 I then adjourned the further directions hearing in the matter to 22 May 2006 which was extended by consent to 24 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">At the directions hearing on 24 May 2006 I was told that the resolution contemplated by my order of 11 May had been passed and that the only issue left in the proceeding was the issue of registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">25 I was also informed that Mr Hoff, as a shareholder in Tower, was proposing to issue an application before the Takeovers Panel the next day and wanted to adjourn the further directions hearing for the time being.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">Pendant Software's takeover offer was open until 18 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">26 The issue which was before the Court at this stage was put rather succinctly by Mr Glick S.C. for Pendant Software, in the following terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">
 "The single point in our application is this, there being no attack on the offer or anything like that from the target.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">The single point is this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">It is a single point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">It is almost like a case stated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Is it within the discretion of the directors under these articles to refuse to register an acceptance of shares for the reason that registration of those shares may, may prevent, another person bidding a higher price for the shares?</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Now, I may not have put that elegantly but that is a single point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">Is that a proper or improper purpose?</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">" 


In the course of argument, Mr Glick acknowledged that Mr Hoff had the opportunity to go to the Takeovers Panel and seek relief if he was so disposed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Directions were then given on the basis of a Panel hearing and determination probably occurring thereafter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">27 On the following day, 25 May 2006, Mr Hoff filed an application with the Takeovers Panel seeking declarations pursuant to s 657A of the Act of unacceptable circumstances in relation to Tower in respect of:
 
 (a) the Board resolution of 18 April 2006; 


 
 
 (b) Pendant Software's acceptance of the notice of acceptance and transfer by Equity Partners of its shares in Tower.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">
 

28 The parties to the application before the Takeovers Panel were Mr Hoff as the applicant, Pendant Software, Equity Partners and Tower.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">Mr Hoff sought a number of orders from the Takeovers Panel in the following terms:
 
 
 "(a) the resolution of the Board of Directors of Tower on 18 April, 2006 [the terms of which were set out] be declared to be unacceptable circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">
 
 (b) the distribution of the Bidder's Statement to shareholders prior to 3 May, 2006 be declared to be unacceptable circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">
 
 (c) the acceptance by Pendant Software of the Notice of Acceptance and Transfer dated 19 April, 2006 from Equity Partners be declared to be unacceptable circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">
 
 
 
 
 
 (d) the acceptance by Pendant Software of the Notice of Acceptance and Transfer from Equity Partners dated 19 April, 2006 is void.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">
 
 
 
 
 
 (e) no shareholder be able to accept the bid, or submit to Pendant Software in response to the bid a valid Notice of Acceptance and Transfer, prior to the date of the Panel's determination, alternatively, prior to the date of the Target's Statement (17 May, 2006).</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">
 
 
 
 
 
 (f) Pendant Software pay the costs of the Applicant of the proceedings before the Panel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">" 
 

29 On 29 May 2006 Pendant Software filed a submission with the Takeovers Panel submitting that it should decline to hear the application because the substantive disputes between the parties were already the subject of the proceeding in this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">It should be noted that there were different parties in each proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Although Mr Hoff was a party to both of them he was a party in a different capacity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">As a defendant in this Court his capacity was that of director; in the Takeovers Panel application he was proceeding as a shareholder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">30 The validity of the Equity Partners acceptance and transfer is in issue in both proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">Pendant Software contends that the issues raised by Mr Hoff before the Panel substantially overlap issues raised in the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">However, the Panel brief raises many issues which will not be before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">For example, there are the issues raised under the heading, "Disclosure" in paragraphs 10 and following of the annexure of issues for consideration annexed to the Panel brief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">There are the issues under the heading, "Early dispatch of the bidder's statement", in paragraphs 23 and following.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">It is also fair to say that the Panel brief does raise one of the issues which is before the Court in paragraph 39 which asks, "How does the Applicant's submission that Equity Partners' acceptance ought to be declared void fit with the current Federal Court proceedings?</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">" 
 
31 On 2 June 2006 the Panel said it would abide any order of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">It is not a party to the interlocutory application to restrain the continuation of the proceeding before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">The restraint which is sought is against Mr Hoff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">32 There was a meeting of the Board of Tower on 1 June 2006 at which Mr Frost said he was not seeking registration of the transfer from Equity Partners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">The Chairman said that he and the first and fourth defendants had no objection to the transfer being registered immediately on it being presented to Tower in registrable form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">It is in those circumstances that the first, fourth and fifth defendants filed their motion to seek dismissal or stay of the proceeding as they contend that the point is now moot.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">33 Pendant Software seeks in substance an anti-suit injunction against Mr Hoff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">The principles of anti-suit injunctions are well established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">Mr Ehrlich who appeared on the interlocutory application for Pendant Software referred to two well known authorities in this area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">In CSR Limited v Cigna Insurance Australia Ltd [1997] HCA 33 ; (1997) 189 CLR 345, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Kirby JJ, said at 391: 
 
 "The counterpart of a court's power to prevent its processes being abused [by granting a stay] is its power to protect the integrity of those processes once set in motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">And in some cases, it is that counterpart power of protection that authorises the grant of anti-suit injunctions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Thus, for example, if "an estate is being administered ... or a petition in bankruptcy has been presented ... or winding up proceedings have been commenced ... an injunction [may be] granted to restrain a person from seeking, by foreign proceedings, to obtain the sole benefit of certain foreign assets".</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">Similarly, as Gummow J pointed out in National Mutual Holdings Pty Ltd v The Sentry Corporation , a court may grant an injunction to restrain a person from commencing or continuing foreign proceedings if they, the foreign proceedings, interfere with or have a tendency to interfere with proceedings pending in that court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">
 
 The inherent power to grant anti-suit injunctions is not confined to the examples just given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">As with other aspects of that power, it is not to be restricted to defined and closed categories.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">Rather, it is to be exercised when the administration of justice so demands or, in the context of anti-suit injunctions, when necessary for the protection of the court's own proceedings or processes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">" (footnotes omitted)
 

34 In National Mutual Holdings Pty Limited v Sentry Corporation (1989) 22 FCR 209 Gummow J said at 232:
 
 "In Australia, there is the further consideration that where a court has begun to exercise the judicial power of the Commonwealth in relation to a particular matter, it has the exclusive right to exercise or control the exercise of the functions which form part of that power or are incidental to it: cf Pioneer Concrete (Vic) Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1982] HCA 65 ; (1982) 152 CLR 460 at 471---3, 474.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">" 
 

35 Mr Dixon, who appeared on behalf of Mr Hoff, submitted that a more appropriate approach was to consider the principles involved with potential commissions of contempt of Court in relation to an administrative proceeding which might impinge upon a Court proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">He referred to Sage v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2005] FCA 1043 , and to Hammond v Commonwealth of Australia [1982] HCA 42 ; (1982) 152 CLR 188, where Gibbs CJ, with whom Mason and Murphy JJ agreed, said at 196:
 
 "The ground of the application for the injunction is that the further examination of the plaintiff, and the making of the report, would constitute a contempt of the County Court before which the criminal proceedings against the plaintiff are pending.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">To succeed in obtaining an injunction on that ground, the plaintiff must establish that there is a real risk, as opposed to a remote possibility, that justice will be interfered with if the Commission proceeds in accordance with its present intention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">The tendency of the proposed actions to interfere with the course of justice must be a practical reality - a theoretical tendency is not enough.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">So much is recognized by the Builders Labourers' Case .</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">
 
 The first question that arises is whether it would be an interference with the due administration of justice if the examination of the plaintiff were to proceed before the Commission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">A witness appearing before the Commission is subject to the obligations imposed by s. 6 of the Royal Commissions Act 1902 (Cth) and s. 16 of the Evidence Act 1958 (Vict.).</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">" 
 

36 A particularly relevant question to ask is what is the matter which is before the Court?</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">I consider that the matter is not the integrity of the takeover offer as a whole; that is a matter for the Panel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">The primacy of the Panel's jurisdiction in relation to takeover offers is found in ss 659AA and 659B of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Section 659AA provides:
 
 "The object of sections 659B and 659C is to make the Panel the main forum for resolving disputes about a takeover bid until the bid period has ended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">" 
 

37 It is important to note that the Panel does not adjudicate on disputed rights, nor does it exercise judicial power to resolve disputes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">The distinction between the task of the Panel and the task of a Court such as the Federal Court, was clearly identified by Emmett J in Glencore International AG v Takeovers Panel (2005) 220 ALR 495, where his Honour said at [55] and [56]:
 
 "The making of binding declarations of right, by way of adjudication of disputes about rights and obligations that arise from the operation of the law upon past events or conduct, is a classical instance of the exercise of judicial power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">However, the declarations for which s 657A provides are not binding declarations of right, in the sense in which that term is used in the context of the exercise of judicial power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">The adjudication made by the review panel in the present case was not an adjudication of a dispute about rights and obligations of the parties that had arisen from the operation of the law on past events or conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">The object of the review panel's declaration and orders was not to resolve a dispute about existing rights and obligations, by determining what those rights and obligations were, but to determine what legal rights and obligations should be created .</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">
 
 
 
 
 
 The orders made under s 657D created rights and obligations that, prior to the making of the orders, did not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">In that sense, the decisions of the review panel did not involve any adjudication of a dispute about existing rights and obligations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">In applying for a declaration and orders, Centennial was not seeking the vindication of any right or obligation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">The declaration made by the review panel did not resolve any actual or potential controversy as to existing rights: see, generally, Precision Data Holdings Ltd v Wills [1991] HCA 58 ; (1991) 173 CLR 167 at 188-190; 104 ALR 317 at 325; 6 ACSR 269 at 277.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">" 
 

38 Mr Ehrlich emphasised that the orders which Mr Hoff was seeking before the Panel included a declaration of the acceptance by Pendant Software of the notice of acceptance and transfer from Equity Partners dated 19 April 2006 to be unacceptable circumstances and that such acceptance be declared void.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">He submitted that if the Panel made a declaration that the transfer, which is the subject of this proceeding, was declared void then a declaration sought in this proceeding would be rendered nugatory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">However, it is open to the Panel to make such a declaration for reasons unrelated to the reasons which might move the Court to grant the relief that is open to it in this proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">39 The Panel, pursuant to s 657A of the Act , can declare circumstances in relation to the affairs of a company to be unacceptable circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">That opportunity or option is not available to the Federal Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">The Panel can make a declaration of unacceptable circumstances for a reason that it is not open to the Federal Court in respect of a matter on which the Federal Court cannot adjudicate upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Although the directors reserve the right in this proceeding to allege that they are entitled to refuse registration of the transfer for just cause because of unlawful conduct on the part of Pendant Software the Federal Court cannot approach that matter on the basis of determining whether any conduct of Pendant Software constituted unacceptable circumstances as contemplated by s 657A of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">40 The Federal Court does not have available to it the framework within which the Panel may declare circumstances to be unacceptable circumstances, although of course the Court can determine whether breaches of the Act have occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">It may well be that the opportunity for the directors to argue that they were not obliged to agree or consent to registration of the transfer from Equity Partners to Pendant Software will raise for consideration whether there has been a breach of s 606 of the Act , so that for the purposes of s 1071F of the Act , the directors were entitled to refuse to give their consent or approval to the registration of the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">41 As Mr Ehrlich put it, whether there was a breach of s 606 and a pre-bid understanding may well form part of the substratum of facts that go to the question whether the directors had just cause to refuse to agree or consent to registration of the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">Nevertheless the determination of whether such an issue gives rise to unacceptable circumstances is a matter committed to the Panel under the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">There is a statutory scheme, the object of which is enshrined in s 659AA , namely that the Panel is the main forum for resolving disputes about takeover bids until the bid period has ended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">42 As counsel for Pendant Software acknowledged earlier, it is no part of Pendant Software's application to this Court to exclude the operation of the Panel in relation to the takeover offer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">What Pendant Software does seek is to challenge what it called a self-evident attempt to render nugatory the Federal Court proceeding and destroy the subject matter of it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">However, if the Panel makes a declaration which has a consequential effect upon the transfer from Equity Partners to Pendant Software, it will do so not because it has assumed the role of the Federal Court, but rather for a reason, namely the existence of unacceptable circumstances, with which the Court cannot deal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">That matter is committed to the Panel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">43 The Federal Court is not seized of the determination of all the issues raised by Mr Hoff before the Panel; it is seized of the issue whether the directors have acted in a way which invokes s 1071F of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Although the Court has to determine whether the directors were, on 11 May 2006 and prior thereto on 4 May 2006, entitled to refuse to agree or consent to the registration of the transfer from Equity Partners, the Court is not set at large upon the sea of the takeover offer, although it can determine whether the directors had just cause to refuse to agree or consent to the registration of the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">If there be any unacceptable circumstances found in the lead up to an implementation of Pendant Software's takeover offer then it is for the Panel to tease those out and make declarations in relation to them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">That is not a task committed to the Federal Court under the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">
 

44 If there be such unacceptable circumstances found which the Panel determines have an effect or consequence upon the transfer from Equity Partners to Pendant Software then that decision or declaration is not impinging upon the jurisdictional turf of the Federal Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">It is a consequence of the Panel undertaking the task identified by Emmett J in par [56] of his judgment in Glencore (supra).</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">It is not the Panel making a decision on, or a declaration in relation to, the issue of the obligation of the directors on 4 or 11 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">The consequence of the Panel's determination may be to remove the substratum of the basis for the registration of the transfer sought by Pendant Software, but that is not because of the Panel assuming the task of the Court or destroying the substratum of the matter before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">It is because there is a separate and independent basis for a challenge to the consequences of the carrying out and implementation of Pendant Software's takeover offer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">45 Mr Ehrlich submitted that what was left alive by the interlocutory order I made on 11 May 2006 was the lawfulness of the directors' conduct in relation to the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">Assuming for the moment that that submission is correct, it does not follow that the Panel cannot reach a conclusion in relation to the takeover which may equate with the unlawfulness of directors' conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">It will not be a finding of unlawful conduct such as a Court might make, rather it is as a result of a finding of unacceptable circumstances within a framework of the takeover offer and the Panel provisions of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">46 Accordingly I am not disposed to restrain Mr Hoff from continuing with his application to the Panel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">I am also not disposed to dismiss the proceeding as against the first, fourth and fifth defendants or stay the proceeding against them as sought in their motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Their counsel in argument did not press for dismissal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">Mr Hoff and the third defendant are not parties to that motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">The terms of my order on 11 May 2006 leave it open for them to argue that they did not have to agree or consent to the registration of the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">Whilst that reservation is still alive it is premature to deal with that motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">Although the first, fourth and fifth defendants are prepared to register the transfer they are not prepared, or it was not clear whether they were prepared, to consent to judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">There is also the issue of costs and whether Pendant Software was entitled to commence the proceeding having regard to the qualified resolution on 4 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">
 

47 Subject to anything counsel may say I would propose an order that each of the interlocutory applications or motions brought before me yesterday be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">I certify that the preceding forty-seven (47) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Goldberg.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">Associate:

Dated: 7 June 2006


 Counsel for the plaintiff: P Ehrlich 
 
 Solicitor for the plaintiff: Septimus Lee Jones 
 
 Counsel for the 1 st , 4 th &amp; 5 th defendants: R Strong 
 
 Solicitor for the 1 st , 4 th &amp; 5 th defendants: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the 2 nd defendant: J Dixon 
 
 Solicitor for the 2 nd defendant: Macpherson + Kelley 
 
 Date of Hearing: 5 June 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 June 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/717.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>