<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHAL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 701 (25 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/701.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for extension of time to file and serve notice of appeal dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application for an extension of time to file and serve a notice of appeal against a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court dismissing an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal confirming the refusal of a protection visa ( SZHAL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FMCA 22).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 In order to obtain such an extension there is the necessity to show at least some available argument in favour of an appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I think I can say that this matter is probably as bereft of such an argument as any I have ever seen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">That is saying something.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The applicant arrived in Australia in 2002 and did not seek a protection visa until 2005 in circumstances where he had been apprehended by the authorities, having overstayed his visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">4 He has made it clear in what he has said to me today that his grievance lies in what occurred to him at the time of his being taken into detention and in particular the loss of his belongings, including, so he says, a substantial sum of cash.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">5 I have read the decision of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">I have read the decision of the learned Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">There is no breath of a chance of any appeal succeeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">There is no arguable basis upon which a protection visa could have been allowed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">6 The application for extension of time is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">I order that the applicant pay the costs of the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">7 I should make clear that whatever grievances the applicant has in relation to matters other than the grant of a protection visa are not before this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">I certify that the preceding seven (7) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Associate:

Dated: 6 June 2006


 
 The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Susan Goodman of Blake Dawson Waldron 
 
 Date of Hearing: 25 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 25 May 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/701.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>