<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>CZAH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 86 (13 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/86.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">no point of principle</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 This is an application for an extension of time in which to seek leave to appeal from a judgment of a Federal Magistrate of 9 August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">That judgment concerned an application for judicial review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal of 17 June 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The application was dismissed by the Federal Magistrate as incompetent, because the Federal Magistrate concluded that the Tribunal's decision was a privative clause decision and in relation to such a decision applications had to be made within specified times.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The Federal Magistrate was, in my view, correct in reaching the conclusion he did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">It was against a background in which the applicant had litigated both in the Federal Court and the Full Court of the Federal Court and the High Court the question of whether or not the Tribunal's decision was attended by jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">2 In my opinion, the prospects of the applicant succeeding in any appeal, were time to be extended and leave given, are remote in the extreme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Accordingly, the application for an extension of time in which to seek leave to appeal is refused with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">I certify that the preceding two (2) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Moore.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Associate:

Dated: 20 February 2006


 The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: A Chand 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 13 February 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 February 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/86.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>