<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>NAZW v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 96 (10 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/96.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appellant failed to attend rrt hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">signed acceptance of hearing invitation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">suggestion of default by migration agent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether effective invitation sent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether rrt authorised to proceed to decide review</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">ss422b , s 424a , 425 , 426a ,</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">migration</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">migration act 1958 (cth)</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 Introduction 
 

 
1 This is an appeal from a decision of Federal Magistrate Driver given on 13 September 2005 dismissing an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the RRT") handed down on 23 December 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The RRT affirmed a decision of a delegate of the Minister not to grant the appellant a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The appellant is a citizen of the Peoples Republic of China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">He claimed to have a well-founded fear of persecution in China on the ground that he was a practitioner of Falun Gung.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The appellant's application for review of the decision of the delegate was filed on 8 May 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">It gave as the address to which correspondence was to be sent as "Jack Meng Immigration Pty Limited" and it gave the appellant's home address as his residential address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">In answer to a question "Please tell us why you consider yourself to be a refugee" the appellant stated in the application for review "Please see my file at DIMIA".</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 On 15 October 2003, the RRT wrote to the appellant at his authorised address, namely that of the migration agent, stating that the Tribunal had considered the material before it but was unable to make a decision in his favour on the information alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The appellant was invited to attend a hearing listed for Tuesday, 25 November 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">A copy of this invitation to attend the hearing was also sent to the appellant at his home address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">5 On 18 October 2003, the RRT received a response to the hearing invitation, apparently signed by the appellant stating that he wanted to attend the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">On 20 October 2003 the letter addressed to the appellant at his home address was returned to the RRT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">A box marked "insufficiently addressed" was ticked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6 The appellant did not attend the hearing and the RRT proceeded to make a decision on the review under section 426A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ("the Act ") without taking any further action to enable the appellant to appear before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">7 The RRT was not satisfied on the evidence before it that the appellant had a well-founded fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">It found that the claims were unclear and lacking in detail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">8 Federal Magistrate Driver observed at [2] that the only jurisdictional error apparent on the face of the application for review was an assertion that the RRT had overlooked some of the appellant's claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">His Honour considered that there was no substance in this submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">9 The learned Federal Magistrate then went on to consider whether there was an arguable case of jurisdictional error arising from the failure of the RRT to take any steps to contact the applicant's migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">He referred to a decision of a Full Court in NAJT v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 (" NAJT ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">10 Federal Magistrate Driver found at [6] that the RRT had met its statutory obligation under s 425 of the Act to invite the applicant to a hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The learned Magistrate observed at [7] that the RRT believed the appellant had accepted the hearing invitation and that the form of acceptance of the invitation was potent evidence of that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">11 His Honour went on to say that whilst he did not exclude the possibility that the signature on the form of acceptance was not the appellant's signature, any default or misbehaviour on the part of the migration agent could not invalidate the decision of the RRT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">12 His Honour found that there was nothing before the RRT to indicate that the appellant did not want to attend the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">His Honour found that the RRT had invited the appellant to attend in accordance with its statutory obligation and that it was entitled pursuant to s 426A to proceed in his absence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">13 The learned Magistrate went on at [9] to say that there may be circumstances where it is desirable for the RRT to attempt to contact a migration agent but he said that whether there was a breach of a general law fair hearing rule in the present case was not a question which it was necessary to decide because of the provisions of s 422B of the Migration Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">14 His Honour said that the only remaining issue was whether there was a possible breach of s 424A of the Act in not notifying the appellant of the information contained in the protection visa application upon which the RRT relied in coming to its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">15 However, his Honour found at [11] that the information was adopted by the appellant in his application for review and accordingly the information fell within the exception contained in s 424A(3)(b) of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Discussion 
 
16 The notice of appeal raises the same grounds as were put before the learned Federal Magistrate, with one exception.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The additional ground is that the Minister asserted before the Federal Magistrate that the appellant entered Australia in 1997 whereas in fact he arrived in 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">17 There is no error in the Federal Magistrate's finding that the appellant's claims were not overlooked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">His Honour was correct in adopting the Minister's submissions set out at [2] of the judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">18 The appellant is correct in asserting that the Minister's submissions before the Federal Magistrate mistakenly referred to the applicant's date of arrival in Australia as 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">However, that was of no relevance to the decision; indeed the RRTs decision specifically refers to the fact that the appellant arrived in Australia in March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The learned Magistrate was correct in finding that the RRT was entitled to proceed under s 426A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">19 The exercise of the power under s 426A(1) is predicated upon the satisfaction of two conditions, these are: first, an invitation under s 425 , and second, a failure to appear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Both of those conditions were satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">20 Even if the appellant's failure to attend involved no fault on his part, the RRT was authorised to proceed to decide the review in the appellant's absence: see VNAA v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 134 ; (2004) 136 FCR 407 at [16] ; NADK of 2002 v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 184 at [16] ; SZBCS v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1457 ; B41 of 2003, in the matter of an application for a Writ of Mandamus, Prohibition and Certiorari against Refugee Review Tribunal [2004] FCA 30 at [23] to [35].</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">21 Whether or not the decision in NAJT might be thought to have been decided on analogous provisions of the Act , namely ss 57 , 494A , 494B and 494C , it is clear that the case turns on its own facts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">22 Madgwick J, with whom Conti J agreed, said at [189] that on the evidence in that case it was known to the delegate before he proceeded to make his decision that an effective invitation had not been sent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">That was not the position here.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">23 As the learned Federal Magistrate held, the RRT believed that the invitation had been received and accepted, indeed it was entitled to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The return of the form of invitation sent to the appellant's residential address was not to the point because the RRT had received a form of acceptance apparently signed by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">It was entitled to proceed on the basis that the form had been sent to and received by the appellant's authorised agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">24 The application for review by the RRT was filed after the provisions of s 422B came into force in July 2002; that section was therefore applicable: see SZBJW v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1356 at [4] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">There may be some doubt as to the construction and effect of s 422B: see WAJR v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 106 at [57] ; see also Moradian v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1590 at [29] to [36].</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">25 However, even if s 422B was not effective to exclude any operation of the common law fair hearing rule, on the facts of the present case there was nothing to give rise to an obligation of procedural fairness to contact the appellant's migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">26 The appellant's adoption of the contents of his migration file in his application for review had the effect that the appellant gave that information for the purpose of his review application: see s 424A(3)(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">The RRT was therefore not required to provide particulars of information under section 424A(1): see SZBNK v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">27 For the reasons that I have given the appeal must be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">I certify that the preceding twenty seven (27) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Associate:

Dated: 17 February 2006


 
 The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 10 February 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 10 February 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/96.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>