<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited (ACN 102 907 184) v Bose [2006] FCA 94 (8 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/94.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for default judgment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether failure of respondents to defend the proceedings with due diligence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">

 
 Introduction 
 
1 This is an application for default judgment pursuant to Order 35A of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The applicant seeks default judgment by reason of the failure of the respondents to defend the proceedings with due diligence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The notice of motion seeking default judgment was filed in court today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">It was served on Friday, 3 February 2006, which is less than the three days clear notice prescribed by the rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">I will refer to this later.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 The proceedings relate to the planned performance of a performer known as "Busta Rhymes" at Luna Park Sydney.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The applicants claim that they entered into a contract with Mr Bose of Drop Dead Promotion New Zealand, as agent for Busta Rhymes, for the performance of Busta Rhymes at Luna Park on 29 September 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Mr Rhymes did not ultimately perform.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The orders sought include claims for damages for breach of contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Background 
 
4 On 2 June 2005, I gave leave to the applicant to serve an amended statement of claim outside the Commonwealth in accordance with Division 2 of Order 8 of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">5 On 30 June 2005 at a directions hearing before me there was no appearance by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">I stood the matter over to 4 August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">6 On 4 August 2005 there was still no appearance from the respondents and the applicant indicated that it wished to file an application for default judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">7 On 24 August 2005, the matter was listed for hearing of the application for default judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">However, at the hearing the respondents appeared by solicitors Messrs Gray and Perkins who filed a notice of appearance on that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">8 Orders were made for the filing of a defence and a defence was filed on 29 September 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">9 At a directions hearing on 29 September 2005 I referred the matter to mediation and listed it for further directions on 24 November 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">I subsequently vacated the directions hearing and relisted it for directions on 15 December 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">10 On 7 December 2005, Messrs Gray and Perkins filed a notice of ceasing to act supported by an affidavit of a partner of that firm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">11 At the directions hearing on 15 December 2005 there was no appearance by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The solicitor for the applicant indicated on that date that the applicant would be seeking an order for default judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I stood the matter over to today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">12 On 6 January 2006, the solicitors for the applicant wrote to each of the respondents informing them that the application for default judgment would be listed for hearing before me this morning as a consequence of the failure of the respondents to appear at the directions hearing on 15 December 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">There has been no reply to those letters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">13 Both firms of solicitors retained by the respondents have ceased to act and it appears that monies are owing to them for legal fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">In those circumstances it seems to me that the respondents are not defending the proceeding and the court's powers to make orders on default are enlivened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">14 It seems to me to be appropriate to proceed today on the notice of motion notwithstanding that it was served less than three clear days before the date fixed for the hearing of the notice of motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">15 A copy of the form of the proposed notice of motion was sent by the solicitors for the applicant to the respondents' by facsimile on 3 February 2006 and by regular post on 6 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Discussions 
 
16 It was until recently well settled that there was no presumption upon default of the respondent of the correctness of the applicant's claims: see Commissioner of Taxation v Finn [1960] HCA 69 ; (1960) 103 CLR 165.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">17 It was not open to the court to make an order for default judgment except on the bringing of a motion supported by evidence as to the merits of the application: see Australian Securities Commission v McLeod (1994) 54 FCR 309 per Drummond J; see also for example Grey v Mango Prepaid Calling Cards Pty Limited [2004] FCA 1664 per Nicholson J, and Zomba Production Music v. Roadhouse Productions (2001) 190 ALR 288 per Stone J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">18 However, recent authorities indicate that the introduction of Order 35A provides the foundation for a finding that in the absence of a defence where there is a pleading by way of a statement of claim then the facts in the statement of claim are admitted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">19 Here there is a defence, but the respondents are not pursuing it with due diligence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">20 Recent authorities support the proposition that Order 35 does not require proof by way of evidence of the claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It requires that on the face of the statement of claim there is a claim for relief sought and that the court has jurisdiction to grant that relief: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 1Cellnet LLC [2005] FCA 856 per Nicholson J at [14] and Arthur v Vaupotic Investments Pty Limited [2005] FCA 433 ; cf Wu v Avin Operations Pty Limited (ACN 076 956 913) [2006] FCA 36 at [49] , [57] --- [58].</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">21 I am satisfied that the respondents are aware of the proceeding and that they were aware of today's application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">I am also satisfied that they are in default for the reasons previously mentioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">22 The power to enter default judgment is enlivened for the reasons given above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The structure of the statement of claim is straight forward.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Damages are calculated in an affidavit of Peter Warren Hearne sworn 17 August 2005 and filed on 18 August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The amount claimed is $125,193.95.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">23 There was an error in the application as originally filed and the amount claimed is slightly less than the claim in its original form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">I am satisfied that the calculation is a calculation of the loss and damage suffered by the applicant as a result of the failure of Busta Rhymes to perform at Luna Park on 29 September 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">24 I note that on 25 November 2005, the applicant by consent discontinued the proceedings against the Third Respondent (Drop Dead Entertainment Ltd (NZ) NZCN 14 98 190) with no order as to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">25 Accordingly I will make orders in terms of [1] and [2] of the short minutes of order and I will order the respondents to pay the applicant's costs on a party/party basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">I note that the interest rate referred to in [2] of the short minutes of order is the rate currently prescribed by the Federal Court rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">I certify that the preceding twenty five (25) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Associate:

Dated: 16 February 2006


 Solicitor for the Applicant: Esplins Solicitors 
 
 
 No appearance for the respondent 
 
 Date of Hearing: 8 February 2005 
 
 Date of Judgment: 8 February 2005 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/94.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>