<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>McIlwain v Ramsey Food Packaging Pty Ltd (No. 3) [2006] FCA 994 (3 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/994.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for a stay pending an application for leave to appeal.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 I have before me an application by notice of motion by each of the four respondents (applicants on the motion) filed on 20 July 2006 for an order that until an application for leave to appeal and any appeal arising from the grant of such leave is finally determined, further proceedings in the disposition in this matter (QUD66 of 2003) be stayed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The application for the stay was heard on Thursday, 27 July 2006 at 10.15am.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">At the conclusion of argument, I reserved the matter with a view to advising the parties that judgment on the matter would be delivered later that morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The parties, by consent, requested that the matter be listed at 3.30pm in order to allow discussions to take place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">I was then asked to adjourn the application for the stay generally subject to further notification from the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">On Tuesday, 1 August 2006, I was advised that no resolution had been reached and accordingly I advised the parties that I would give judgment on the application for the stay at 9.45am today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">3 On 20 January 2006, I published reasons in relation to particular matters arising out of a consideration of the factual and legal issues in the matter consequent upon a trial of the action in which extensive argument occurred in relation to a 'no case' to answer submission made by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">That submission was made on the footing that the respondents were put to an election not to call evidence in the proceeding as a condition of making the 'no case' submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">In dealing with the matter, I reviewed all of the evidence and the issues with a view to ultimately making final dispositive orders subject to further submissions on particular matters before making any orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">See generally McIlwain v Ramsey Food Packaging Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 828 at [82] --- [92] and [370] --- [382].</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">4 The respondents have filed an application for leave to appeal from the judgment and leave is sought pursuant to s 24(1A) of the Federal Court Act 1976.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">A date for the hearing of the application will shortly be allocated by the Registry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Although an engaged consideration of the merits of that application is not part of this application for a stay, one aspect of the orthodoxy of the approach to considering the treatment of appeals is the recognition that an appeal does not lie either with or without leave from reasons for judgment but only from judgments, decrees and orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">As the authorities observe, the word 'judgment' in this context refers to operative judicial acts and is not used as a convenient shorthand description of reasons for judgment: see Driclad Pty Ltd v FCT [1966] HCA 59 ; (1968) 121 CLR 45; Ah Toy v Registrar of Companies (1985) 10 FCR 280 at 28586; Hannpost Pty Ltd v Mita Copiers Australia Pty Ltd (1996) 137 ALR 701 at 711 and Gribbles Pathology (Vic) Pty Ltd v Minister for Human Services and Health (1996) 67 FCR 327.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">In publishing the reasons on 30 June 2006, directions orders were made for the making of further written and oral submissions on particular matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In order to accommodate counsels' availability, the applicant was required to make submissions on the relevant matters by Friday, 14 July 2006 and the respondents by Friday, 21 July 2006 with a view to the matter being listed for further argument at 10.15am on 27 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">On that day, the application for the stay was argued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">5 The further matters which are to occur in the proceeding (QUD66 of 2003) involve a number of things.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">In publishing the reasons, I gave directions for the further conduct of the trial with a view to resolving matters which would, upon resolution, lead to the making of dispositive orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The matters that remain to be dealt are these.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">First, the applicant was requested to formulate draft declarations reflecting the findings of contravention of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) ('the Act').</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Those proposed declarations are to be the subject of submissions and further consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Mr Hatcher SC characterises the request made of the applicant to submit draft forms of declaration as a delegation to the applicant of the judicial task.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">However, those formulations are to be considered and will be the subject of further oral submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Secondly, aspects of the claim for lost earnings concerning Mr Blackadder is to be the subject of further submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Thirdly, written submissions were sought from the applicant and the respondents concerning the principles governing the assessment of a compensation component described as general damages in the applicants' Further, Further Amended Statement of Claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Fourthly, written submissions were to be provided on the question of whether a penalty ought to be imposed upon any of the respondents pursuant to s 298U(a) of the Act and if so, the principles guiding the determining of such a penalty in all the circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Fifthly, the principles guiding the circumstances in which an order ought to be made under s 356 of the Act that any penalty imposed upon the respondents be paid to the Employment Advocate, is the subject of further argument.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">6 Counsel for the respondents say that the respondents have been substantially prejudiced because they have not been given an opportunity to be heard on the unchallenged evidence of lost earnings and whether the accepted evidence supports the loss claimed and its calculation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">That lack of opportunity to be heard is said to be compounded by a further hearing of the matter and thus the proceeding should be stayed pending the application for leave and the resolution of any appeal, should leave be given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">7 Counsel for the respondents will seek to establish the merits of the primary position in arguing the application for leave.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">It seems to me, however, that the appellate process of the Court is greatly aided by ensuring that all matters that remain to be dealt with are dealt with so that dispositive orders might be made which can then be the subject of appeal and thus bring the entire controversy before the Court in its appellate jurisdiction subject to the scope of the grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Such an appeal might be heard together with any appeal from the 'Reasons for Judgment' should leave be given pursuant to the existing application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">8 Accordingly I propose to take the following course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">I propose to make further directions in the conduct of the trial and they are that the respondents file in the Court and serve upon the applicant any further affidavit material upon which any of them intend to rely in relation to the determination of the question of whether a penalty ought to be imposed upon any of the respondents pursuant to s 298U(a) of the Act, by 4.00pm on Thursday, 17 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The applicant is to file affidavits in reply (if any) by Thursday, 24 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The matter will be re-listed for the hearing of oral submissions in relation to that matter, to the form of any declaration that ought to be made, the question going to Mr Blackadder, the question of the principles and material going to whether an award of damages ought be made in respect of any one of the individuals and submissions as to whether an order ought to be made pursuant to s 356 of the Act, at 10.15am on Monday, 28 August 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">9 I will then determine each of those matters and make a series of orders which will be dispositive of the matters in issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">I do not propose to make orders piecemeal but will make all final orders upon the hearing of oral submissions and the consideration of all oral and written submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">10 I will dismiss the application for the stay and reserve the question of the costs of the stay to be dealt with at the time of determining the costs of the action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">

I certify that the preceding ten [10]
numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the 
Reasons for Judgment herein of the 
Honourable Justice Greenwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Associate:

Dated: 3 August 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr Martin SC and Mr S Horneman-Wren 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent:: Mr G Hatcher SC, Mr A C Barlow 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Hannigans Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 27 July 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment 3 August 2006 
 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/994.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>