<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEMJ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1848 (30 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1848.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">judicial review</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">protection visa</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">application for judicial review of tribunal decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">first application dismissed in federal court on remitter from high court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">second application for judicial review commenced in federal magistrates court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">application dismissed on non-appearance at summary disposition hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">application to reinstate proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">delays</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">seven month delay from dismissal of remitted proceedings to institution of proceedings in federal magistrates court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">two year delay from dismissal of proceedings in federal magistrates court to reinstatement application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">application for leave to appeal from dismissal of reinstatement application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">no merit in application for leave</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">no prospect of success on appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">application for leave dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 Introduction 
 
1 The applicant for leave to appeal is a citizen of Fiji.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">She was born on 29 August 1972.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">She is married, but separated from her husband.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">She arrived in Australia on 30 June 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">On 31 July 2000 she lodged an application with the Department of Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (the Department) for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That application was refused by a delegate of the Minister on 12 October 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On 22 October 2000 she applied to the Refugee Review Tribunal (the Tribunal) for a review of the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The matter did not go to a hearing until 1 June 2001 and on 22 June 2001 the Tribunal affirmed the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">2 The applicant joined representative proceedings in the High Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Her application was eventually remitted to the Federal Court and was dismissed on 20 February 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">She made a new application to the Federal Magistrates Court in September 2004 for review of the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">That application was summarily dismissed on 4 February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">She made unsuccessful applications to the Minister in 2005, 2006 and 2007 for the grant of a visa under s 417 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">All were declined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">She then applied to the Federal Magistrates Court on 2 March 2007 for an order setting aside the dismissal of her application in February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">That application was dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The applicant now seeks leave to appeal against the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">When the matter came on for hearing on 30 October 2007 and, after having given the applicant an opportunity to be heard, I dismissed her application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">I now publish my full reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Factual and procedural background 
 
3 The applicant's claims were summarised in the Tribunal's reasons for decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">It described her at the time as a 28 year old Indian woman from Nadi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">In a statement which accompanied her application for a protection visa she said that she had arrived in Australia on a three month visitor visa and had intended to return to Fiji upon its expiry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The elected government of Fiji was overthrown by an armed rebellion on 19 May 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The applicant claimed, in her statement, that hostages who had been taken at the time of her application were still in custody of the terrorists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">She claimed that the leader of the rebels had declared that his intention was to change the Constitution to ensure that ethnic Indians were permanently disenfranchised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">A large number of Indian businesses had been burned and looted with a damage figure estimated at $30 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The police and army who were mainly indigenous Fijians, were said to have been unwilling and unable to protect people of Indian origin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The applicant claimed that the homes of Indian Fijians had been broken into and families assaulted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">She said there had been reports of Indian females being raped.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">She also claimed that the Great Council of Chiefs of Fiji had met and endorsed the anti-Indian demands of the terrorists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Subsequently, however, the Fiji military took over the administration and imposed martial law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">She said that the Indian population particularly in the urban areas and Suva were fleeing their homes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">4 In a submission dated 25 May 2001 the applicant's advisors stated that she was a machinist and a supporter of the Fiji Labour Party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">She claimed that on 20 May 2000 some indigenous Fijians came to her house and asked her to vacate it so they could live there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">When she and her husband refused, they beat him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The following day she and her husband went to the police who told them to return home and they would come and take a statement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">However this never eventuated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">A few days later their house was stoned again.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Again they reported it to the police but nothing happened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">On 1 June 2000, according to the applicant, some Fijians started to break into their house and told them if they did not vacate it they would both be killed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">They again reported the matter to the police, but again nothing happened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">They then went and stayed at a friend's place until they left Fiji.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">5 The claims that the house had been attacked had not been mentioned in the applicant's initial statement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">She said that she had told her previous advisor of these things but he did not write them down.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">6 The Tribunal was not satisfied about the applicant's claims that her house had been invaded on two occasions, that her husband had been beaten and that her house had been stoned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Had such frightening events really occurred, the Tribunal considered that the applicant would have insisted they be recorded in her initial application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Instead the statement with her application referred generally to events in Fiji.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The Tribunal was confirmed in its view by the applicant's indication that she had intended to return to Fiji once things had settled down.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">7 The Tribunal was satisfied that the situation in Fiji had settled down.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The law and order situation had been secured following the arrest of George Speight who was the leader of the rebellion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">The country information to which the Tribunal referred indicated that the risk to Indian Fijians was low and that it had mainly taken the form of threats and low level theft.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The authorities had promised safety for all citizens and had sent extra troops and police to troubled areas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The Tribunal did accept that, particularly during the time of the coup, there was harassment of Indian Fijians in various areas as the information provided by the applicant's advisor had indicated and as was confirmed by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">The Tribunal concluded that there was no real chance that the applicant would face persecution because of her ethnicity should she return to Fiji.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">8 On 17 August 2001 the applicant joined the Lie class action in the High Court which involved a challenge to various decisions of the Tribunal based upon a failure of procedural fairness relating to the failure of the Department to transfer certain documents to the Tribunal which were relevant to the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">On 25 November 2002, Gaudron J ordered that the application be remitted to the Federal Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Ultimately, the remitted application was dismissed by Emmett J on 20 February 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">9 Some seven months later, on 29 September 2004, the applicant filed an application in the Federal Magistrates Court under s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) seeking writs of prohibition, certiorari and mandamus in relation to the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The grounds of the application were uninformatively framed to include breach of the rules of natural justice and procedural fairness, error of law, failure to have regard to relevant material, failure to observe procedures required to be observed, improper exercise of power and want of evidence or other material to justify the making of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">10 The Minister filed a notice of objection to competency on 7 October 2004 on the basis that subs 477(1A) of the Act provided that an application to the Federal Magistrates Court under s 39B of the Judiciary Act and s 483 of the Act must be made within 28 days of the notification of the Tribunal decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">An amended application was filed on 3 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">The grounds were materially changed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">In the amended application it was claimed that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error when, having found that there was selective harassment of Indian Fijians at the hands of ethnic Fijians, he did not find that this constituted persecution for a Convention reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">It was also alleged that the applicant was denied the opportunity to explain why she believed that the harm which she apprehended arose as a result of her ethnicity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The Tribunal was also said to have failed to have had regard to a relevant consideration, namely constant and selective harassment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Further, the Tribunal was said to have used critical adverse information obtained after the delegate's decision which was neither provided to the applicant before the hearing nor put to the applicant during the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Generalised grounds of misapplication of the relevant test and irrational or illogical reasoning and failure to give proper and adequate reasons were also raised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">The Tribunal was also said to have erred in failing to consider all the claims and issues put forward by the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">11 On 11 October 2004 consent orders were made in the Federal Magistrates Court requiring the Minister to file and serve a bundle of relevant documents (ie the Green Book) by 25 October 2004 and the applicant to file and serve any affidavit containing additional evidence relied upon by 15 November 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The Minister's application for summary dismissal was listed for hearing on 4 February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Notice of that listing was sent by the Minister's solicitors to the applicant's solicitors on 15 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">According to an affidavit sworn by the Minister's solicitor on 1 February 2005 the applicant's solicitors had not replied to their letter of 15 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The letter had not been returned as undeliverable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">12 On 4 February 2005 the application for summary dismissal, apparently pursuant to the objection to competency, came on for hearing before Nicholls FM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">There was no appearance for the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">The application was dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">13 On 2 March 2007 the applicant filed an order seeking to set aside the orders which had been made on 4 February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">She supported that application with an affidavit sworn the same date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">She said in that affidavit, inter alia (at [4]): 
 
 Previously I have in Federal Magistrate Court, but my solicitor withdraws that application and appeal to Minister Under S417.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">We were not aware of any judicial procedure; I believe that we had been denied natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">I also believe that there is lack of procedural fairness in my case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">The procedure that was required to be observed under the Migration Act 1958 , in connection with the making of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">[sic]
 

14 On 13 April 2007 Nicholls FM made orders in the following terms: 
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Leave is granted to the respondent to file by 20 April 2007 any further submissions on the issue of the credibility of the applicant's evidence and whether a request pursuant to s 417 of the Migration Act is a sufficient explanation for delay in the exercise of the Court's discretion pursuant to Rule 16.05 of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Leave is granted to the applicant to file and serve in response any written submissions on these issues by 27 April 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">
 

Written submissions were filed by the Minister on 20 April 2007 together with a chronology.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">15 At the hearing before the learned magistrate a number of exhibits were received relating to the applicant's unsuccessful approaches to the Minister for the grant of a visa pursuant to s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">These comprised: 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">A letter dated 5 August 2005 from the applicant's solicitors to the Minister requesting intervention pursuant to s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">A reply from the Minister's department dated 12 October 2006 advising that the Minister decided not to consider exercising the power under s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">A letter from the applicant dated 31 October 2006 to the Minister again seeking the Minister's intervention pursuant to s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">A response from the Minister's department which was undated but advised that the information provided did not come within ministerial guidelines for referral to the Minister for consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">A request by the applicant dated 10 January 2007 seeking intervention yet again pursuant to s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">A response by the Minister's department dated 28 March 2007, again advising the unsuccessful outcome of the request.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">

16 The learned magistrate identified as the issues for consideration: 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">The circumstances which led to the applicant's non appearance at the hearing on 4 February 2005 and any explanation for that non appearance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The utility of reinstating the original application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">Whether the relief sought should, in any event, be refused given the unexplained delay by the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">

17 The applicant gave evidence at the hearing, part of which related to the current political situation in Fiji.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The learned magistrate referred to evidence in which the applicant explained that she had been assisted in making the application of 2 March 2007 by her uncle who wrote it out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">There were certain matters contained in her own affidavit which she apparently could not understand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">She told the Court that she had pursued judicial review of the Tribunal decision soon after the decision was given by commencing proceedings in the High Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Following the ultimate dismissal of those proceedings in February 2004, on remitter to the Federal Court, she engaged another solicitor to make an application to the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">She and her husband were assisted by her uncle in paying that solicitor to assist them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">They maintained monthly contact with the solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">She then said that her solicitor had withdrawn her application to the Court and she knew "somewhere about" 4 February 2005 that she had missed the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">When she asked the solicitor about it he told her that her application had been withdrawn from the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">She claimed that following this she and her uncle had taken all her papers and things and had gone to see another solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">18 The learned Federal Magistrate noted that the applicant had confirmed that she took no action whatever in relation to the solicitor who had withdrawn her application without her authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">She was unable to explain the seven month delay between the dismissal in February 2004 of proceedings commenced in the High Court and the commencement of proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court on 29 September 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">19 The applicant confirmed that the solicitor who acted for her in the Federal Magistrates Court did not tell her to seek ministerial intervention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">However this was in conflict with what appeared in her affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">When this was pointed out she confirmed that the withdrawal of her case, which was action taken by her then solicitor, was distinct from the subsequent action taken to seek the Minister's intervention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">20 The learned magistrate did not accept the applicant's explanation for her failure to attend Court on 4 February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Her evidence was that other than for a "monthly" inquiry she had left matters in the hands of her solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Soon after the date of the dismissal she was told by her solicitor that her case had been "withdrawn".</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">The learned magistrate noted that there was nothing on the Court file to show any withdrawal of her application by way of notice of discontinuance or other communication as required by the Rules of the Federal Magistrates Court .</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">What was left was that neither the applicant nor her then solicitor appeared at the relevant hearing with the result that the application was dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Despite her solicitor allegedly acting without her instruction and authority she made no complaint either to the Court or to the relevant authorities concerned with the conduct of solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">She appeared at the time to acquiesce with whatever action or inaction had been taken by the solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">She consulted other solicitors and sought to pursue ministerial intervention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">She did not employ the services of those other solicitors to have her matter reinstated before the Federal Magistrates Court in a timely fashion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">21 The learned magistrate agreed with the submission of counsel for the Minister that the applicant's evidence that she did not know anything about the dismissal of the application or what to do to remedy her situation in February 2005 should not be accepted in the face of very clear evidence from her concerning her ability to both actively and repeatedly pursue previous court action and subsequently to pursue intervention by the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">He did not accept that the applicant had provided a satisfactory explanation for her failure to attend Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">22 The learned magistrate then went into the basis upon which the applicant sought review of the Tribunal decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">This was done under the heading "Utility of Reinstatement".</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">This section of his reasons for judgment was in substance a review of the merits of her judicial review application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">The applicant had not been able to show any basis upon which the Tribunal's decision could be said to be affected by jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">23 Further, the learned magistrate said that even if he were to accept the applicant's explanation for her absence from Court on 4 February 2005, and even if he were able to discern on the material before the Court, some basis for her claim to the relief sought in the original application, he would still refuse to grant it having regard to her "unwarrantable and unexplained delay" in seeking judicial review in relation to the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Her explanation for the two year delay from the time of the dismissal of the application to seeking its reinstatement was that she had been pursuing repeated requests to the Minister to intervene pursuant to s 417 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">She sought to reopen her case because she understood that there might have been changes in the law that would lead to her application being successful and that she would have a better chance of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">The learned magistrate treated two periods of delay as relevant to his discretion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">The first was the initial seven month period between the cessation of the High Court proceedings and the commencement of the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">The second was the two year delay between the cessation of proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court and her attempt to revive those proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">Merits of the application for leave to appeal 
 
24 Where an application is made for leave to appeal against an interlocutory decision which has the effect of a final disposition of the proceedings, the threshold for securing such leave may be low.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">In this case, however, I am satisfied that there is no merit at all in the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">The applicant has had the benefit of a careful consideration by the learned magistrate of the merits of her judicial review application in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">The substantial delays involved in relation to the commencement of the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court and the institution of the reinstatement application were, as the learned magistrate found, not satisfactorily explained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">25 The applicant was unable to say anything at the hearing of the application for leave that would indicate any basis upon which leave should be granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">The application will therefore be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Conclusion 
 
26 The application is dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">I certify that the preceding twenty-six (26) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice French.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Associate:
Dated: 27 November 2007


 
 The applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr R White 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 30 October 2007 
 
 Date of Order:
Date of Publication of Reasons: 30 October 2007

27 November 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1848.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>