<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZFNX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1980 (13 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1980.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from decision of federal magistrate</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">where delegate of first respondent refused application for protection visa</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">where second respondent invited appellant to hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">where appellant failed to attend hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">where second respondent under s 426a migration act 1958 (cth) affirmed decision of first respondent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">where appellant on application for constitutional writs in federal magistrates court alleged fraud by agent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">where federal magistrate made no factual findings as to fraud because third party fraud immaterial to judicial review</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">where subsequent high court decision that fraudulent conduct of migration agent relevant to judicial review of tribunal decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether fraud unarguable on evidence before federal magistrate.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an appeal from orders made by a Federal Magistrate on 29 January 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The principal order made by the Federal Magistrate was an order dismissing the appellant's application for constitutional writs directed to the Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs, now the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship ("the Minister"), and the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the Tribunal").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The appellant is a citizen of the People's Republic of China and he was born in Tianjin on 10 April 1953.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">He arrived in Australia on 30 August 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">On 24 September 2004 he applied for a Protection (class XA) visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">On 29 September 2004 a delegate of the Minister refused to grant his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On 1 November 2004 the appellant lodged an application for review with the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">On 22 December 2004 the Tribunal handed down a decision affirming the delegate's decision not to grant a protection visa to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 On 20 January 2005 the appellant lodged an application in the Federal Magistrates Court of Australia under the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) and the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ("the Act ") seeking constitutional writs directed to the Minister and the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The appellant's application was amended on 7 June 2006 and it was the amended application which was considered by the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">There was one ground in the amended application and it was in the following terms:
 
 The applicant was deprived of the opportunity of attending a hearing in this matter in the Refugee Review Tribunal as a result of the wrongful conduct of his migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The details of this claim are set out in my affidavit dated 3 May 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">In the circumstances, there was a denial of procedural fairness and jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">

4 The appellant was represented by counsel before the Federal Magistrate but appeared in person before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The facts 
 
5 The appellant's application for a protection visa contained statements to the effect that the appellant's "current residential address" was 160/422 Pitt Street, Sydney, New South Wales, 2000 ("the Pitt Street address") and that his "current postal address" was the same as his residential address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">6 In the application the appellant said that he was a Falun Gong practitioner and one of the leaders of the Falun Gong movement in Hedong District, Tianjin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">He described the nature of the Falun Gong movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">He said that he was detained by the police for almost one month in a detention centre in Tianjin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">He said that he was tortured by the police and forced to declare not to practise Falun Gong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">He said:
 
 After I was released, I was informed that my company were noticed by the authority to reduce my salary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I suffered spiritually and economically.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">

7 The appellant said that he decided to leave China and with the help of some of his friends he was able to obtain a passport.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">He entered Australia under a business visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 The Department of Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs wrote to the appellant at the Pitt Street address by letter dated 29 September 2004 advising him that his application for a protection visa had been refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">9 The appellant's application for review by the Tribunal was dated 1 November 2004 and in it he gave the Pitt Street address as his residential address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">In the statement attached to the application for review the appellant repeated the claims that he made in his application for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">10 The Tribunal wrote to the appellant at the Pitt Street address by letter dated 2 November 2004 and provided details of how the appellant's application for review would proceed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The Tribunal wrote again to the appellant at the Pitt Street address by letter dated 8 November 2004 advising him that it was unable to make a decision in his favour on the information alone and inviting him to a hearing of the Tribunal to be held on 2 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">11 In its reasons, the Tribunal described what happened from that point:
 
 The letter was sent by registered mail to the applicant at the residential address listed in his application for review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">No authorised recipient or separate mailing address are listed in the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">No response was received and the letter was not returned unclaimed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">On 24 November 2004 the Tribunal checked its file and the departmental file for a more recent address and telephone number for the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">No telephone number is listed in the application for review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">On the same day the Tribunal checked the departmental movements database to confirm that the applicant is still in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">


 
12 The appellant did not appear before the Tribunal on 2 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The Tribunal decided to exercise the power in s 426A of the Act to make a decision on the review without taking any further action to allow or enable the applicant to appear before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">13 The Tribunal wrote to the appellant at the Pitt Street address by letter dated 3 December 2004 advising him that the decision of the Tribunal would be handed down on 22 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">14 The Tribunal affirmed the decision under review and it expressed its conclusions in the following terms:
 
 The Applicant's claim that he will face persecution if he returns to China rests on his claim to have been a Falun Gong practitioner and leader and he does not claim to have suffered any harm for any other Convention-related reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">His claims concerning his Falun Gong involvement, unsubstantiated and lacking in detail on important points as they are, do not provide sufficient grounds for the Tribunal to have confidence in the claimed basis for his professed fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Nor, given the unsubstantiated and vague nature of his claims to have been harmed because of his Falun Gong involvement, is the Tribunal satisfied that he has ever suffered harm in China for this reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">In the light of all the evidence available to it, the Tribunal is not satisfied that the Applicant faces a real chance of harm amounting to persecution from the Chinese authorities because of any involvement with the Falun Gong faith, either now or in the reasonably foreseeable future should he return to China, and is not satisfied that he has a well founded fear of persecution for this or any other Convention-related reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The Tribunal is not satisfied that the Applicant is a refugee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">

15 In his affidavit sworn in support of his application in the Federal Magistrates Court the appellant said that he did not speak, understand or read English.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">He said that a short time after he arrived in Australia he was introduced to a person called Songtao Lue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">He explained to Mr Lue that he was a Falun Gong practitioner in China and that he feared returning to China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Mr Lue told the appellant that he would help him apply for a "refugee visa".</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The appellant paid Mr Lue two sums of money, $400 on or about 18 September 2004 and $350 on or about 30 September 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The appellant attached to his affidavit two receipts recording these payments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">16 In his affidavit the appellant acknowledged that he had signed Parts B and C of the application for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">However, in his evidence before the Federal Magistrate he denied that the signature appearing in Part C was his signature.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">17 The appellant said that he did not recognise the address of 160/422 Pitt Street, Sydney, New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">He said that when he arrived in Sydney he spent a few weeks living in an apartment in the city and that he lived in the apartment with Mr Lue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">He said that he did not know the address of the apartment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">He then moved to Auburn and lived in Auburn for about one year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">In about June 2005 he moved to Cabramatta where he continued to live until this year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">18 The appellant said that some of the information contained in the statement which accompanied his application for a protection visa was incorrect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">He said that the statement, 
 
 I was detained by the police for almost one month in a Tianjin detention centre, tortured by the police and forced to declare not to practise Falun Gong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">


was incorrect and was not information that he gave to Mr Lue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">He said that he did not know that this information was in his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">19 The appellant said that after lodging his application for a protection visa and over the following few months, Mr Lue contacted him by telephone occasionally and asked him to come into his office to sign documents in relation to his visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">He went to Mr Lue's office and signed documents but Mr Lue did not tell him how his refugee application was proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">20 The appellant said that he signed the application for review which was lodged with the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The address in the application for review, that is to say the Pitt Street address, was not his address in November 2004 and he said that he never told Mr Lue that he lived at that address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">21 As to the proposed hearing before the Tribunal the appellant said:
 
 I am now aware that in December 2004 there was a hearing for my matter in the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the Tribunal").</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">At the time, I was unaware there was a hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">I never received a letter from the Tribunal telling me about the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Mr Lue never told me about the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">If I'd been aware of the hearing, I would have attended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">I would have told the Tribunal that I was a Falun Gong practitioner in China and I feared persecution if I am forced to return to China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">

22 The Magistrate heard the appellant's application for constitutional writs on 20 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The appellant's affidavit was received in evidence and the appellant was cross-examined by counsel for the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">On 29 January 2007, the Magistrate delivered his reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Magistrate's reasons 
 
23 The Magistrate summarised the appellant's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">He found that it was apparent from the sequence of events that letters sent by the Department and the Tribunal to the Pitt Street address came to the attention of the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">The Magistrate noted that the appellant did not allege any fault on the part of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">24 The Magistrate said that the appellant's claim was that he was unaware of the proposed Tribunal hearing on 2 December 2004 because his agent did not tell him about it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">He noted that the appellant described the agent's conduct as "wrongful" and that the written submissions filed by counsel for the appellant sought to separate the issue of wrongful conduct into fraudulent and non-fraudulent conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The Magistrate said that while some authorities suggested that such a dichotomy might have been a useful one in proceedings, recent decisions binding on him led to a different conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The Magistrate referred to various sections in the Migration Act and decisions of this Court, including the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365 (" SZFDE ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The Magistrate took the view that an agent's wrongful conduct, whether fraudulent or not, in failing to inform an applicant of a hearing of the Tribunal of which notification had been given did not give rise to jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">The Federal Magistrate did not make an express finding to the effect that the appellant's agent did not advise him of the proposed hearing before the Tribunal because he said that even if that were so it did not affect the result.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">He said that the outcome of the application for constitutional writs in relation to the decision of the Tribunal did not turn on whether or not the agent's conduct in not informing the appellant of the proposed Tribunal hearing was fraudulent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">The Magistrate said:
 
 Therefore, the Tribunal was entitled under the Act to proceed to a determination notwithstanding that the applicant may not have been informed by his agent of the Tribunal's proposed hearing, with the result that the Tribunal's decision is not affected by jurisdictional error on this account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">


 
25 As I have said, the Federal Magistrate did not find it necessary to make findings as to whether the appellant was aware of the proposed hearing of the Tribunal or whether, assuming he was not aware, that came about as a result of fraud or negligence or mistake on the part of Mr Lue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">26 On the authorities as they stood at the time of the Federal Magistrate's decision, his decision was correct: SZFDE ; SZGQL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1420.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">27 The respondent in SZFDE sought and obtained from the High Court of Australia special leave to appeal against the decision of the Full Court of this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">The appeal was heard on 24 May 2007 and, on 2 August 2007, the High Court handed down its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">The Court reversed the decision of the Full Court of this Court: SZFDE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2007) 81 ALJR 1401.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Issue on the appeal 
 
28 The appellant submitted that the Federal Magistrate erred in concluding that the Tribunal was entitled to proceed to determine the application for review even though he (the appellant) had not been informed of the proposed hearing of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">29 For his part, the Minister sought an extension of the time within which to file and serve a notice of contention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">On 6 June 2007 I granted that extension of time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The notice of contention is in the following terms:
 
 The first respondent contends that the judgment of Federal Magistrate Cameron should be affirmed on the following grounds (not being grounds relied upon by the court below):
 
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">There was no evidence before Federal Magistrate Cameron upon which the Court could have found that the applicant's adviser had fraudulently failed to inform the applicant of the hearing before the Tribunal; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Federal Magistrate Cameron should have rejected the applicant's contention that his adviser had fraudulently failed to inform the applicant of the hearing before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 


 
30 The notice of contention was filed so that the Minister could submit that even if fraud by an agent, leading to an applicant not attending a hearing of the Tribunal, could amount to jurisdictional error, nevertheless, in this case, fraud could not be established and the appeal should be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">31 In SZFDE the High Court held that fraud by an applicant's agent causing the applicant not to attend a hearing of the Tribunal could constitute jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The Court said (at 1412 [51] and [52]):
 
 No doubt Mr Hussain was fraudulent in his dealings with the appellants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">But the concomitant was the stultification of the operation of the critically important natural justice provisions made in Div 4 Pt 7 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">In short, while the Tribunal undoubtedly acted on an assumption of regularity, in truth, by reason of the fraud of Mr Hussain, it was disabled from the due discharge of its imperative statutory functions with respect to the conduct of the review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">That state of affairs merits the description of the practice of fraud "on" the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">The consequence is that the decision made by the Tribunal is properly regarded, in law, as no decision at all.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">This is because, in the sense of the authorities, the jurisdiction remains constructively unexercised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">The authorities were collected in Bhardwaj .</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">

32 The effect of the decision of the High Court in SZFDE is that if an agent is fraudulent in his or her dealings with an applicant for review and that results in the applicant not being heard by the Tribunal then the Tribunal's decision may be void, the Tribunal's jurisdiction being "constructively unexercised".</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">33 Although it is not entirely clear, I think it is correct to say that it is not enough that the agent acts negligently or incorrectly; he or she must act fraudulently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">In SZFDE the High Court said (at 1412-13 [53]) (footnotes omitted):
 
 The significance of the outcome in this appeal should not be misunderstood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The appeal has turned upon the particular importance of the provisions of Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Act for the conduct by the tribunal of reviews and the place therein of the ss 425 and 426A .</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">In the Full Court, French J correctly emphasised that there are sound reasons of policy why a person whose conduct before an administrative tribunal has been affected, to the detriment of that person, by bad or negligent advice or some other mishap should not be heard to complain that the detriment vitiates the decision made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The outcome in the present appeal stands apart from and above such considerations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">

Whilst it might be possible to construe the above passage as limited to bad or negligent advice provided to an applicant who actually appears before the Tribunal, I think there is sufficient indication in the decision of the Full Court of this Court in SZFDE that an applicant's failure to appear before the Tribunal by reason of the bad or negligent advice of his or her agent, as distinct from fraudulent advice or conduct, is not without more sufficient to constitute jurisdictional error: French J at 391-392 [101]-[103]; Allsop J at 401-402 [138]-[139].</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">34 Furthermore, the fraud must affect the process prescribed by the Act , in particular, whether the applicant has had the opportunity to appear before the Tribunal to give evidence and present arguments relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">35 The Minister submitted that there was simply no evidence of fraud before the Federal Magistrate and that in those circumstances it was appropriate to dismiss the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">36 The Federal Magistrate did not make any findings as to whether Mr Lue had been fraudulent in his dealings with the appellant and whether that had affected the process prescribed in the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">That was understandable on the authorities as they stood at the time of his decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">However, the effect of the decision of the High Court in SZFDE is that the question of fraud and its effect on the process must be considered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">37 In my opinion, the question of whether there was even an arguable case of fraud raised before the Federal Magistrate is finely balanced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">Counsel for the Minister referred to the transcript of the hearing before the Federal Magistrate and reminded me of the fact that strong evidence is usually required to establish fraud.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">He referred to Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">There is considerable force in the Minister's submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">The appellant appears to have changed his story on whether his signature appears on one of the documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">More importantly perhaps is that, on the face of it, it is difficult to discern a motive for any fraudulent dealing on the part of Mr Lue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">Despite these considerations, I do not think I should go so far as to conclude that on no possible view of the evidence before the Federal Magistrate could fraud be established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">If the appellant's signature was falsely placed on a relevant document and part of a statement "made up", then that may go some way towards establishing fraud, although it will still be necessary for the appellant to show that the fraud (if there be fraud) has affected the process prescribed by the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">I am not to be taken as saying that it is likely that fraud will be made out, but simply that I cannot be certain that it cannot be made out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">It seems to me that the application for constitutional writs must be remitted to the Federal Magistrates Court for rehearing in accordance with these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">I am satisfied that the circumstances are such that a rehearing of the application is necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Conclusions 
 
38 The appeal must be allowed and the orders made by the Federal Magistrate on 29 January 2007 must be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">The application is remitted to the Federal Magistrates Court of Australia for rehearing in accordance with these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">I will hear the parties on the question of costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">I certify that the preceding thirty-eight (38) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">Associate:

Dated: 13 December 2007


 The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr P S Braham 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Blake Dawson Waldron 
 
 Date of Hearing: 2 May, 6 and 27 June 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 December 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1980.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>