<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Walters v Commissioner of Taxation (No. 2) [2007] FCA 1403 (7 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1403.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">resolution of the question of costs arising out of walters v commissioner of taxation [2007] fca 1270</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">taxation and revenue</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 On 20 August 2007, the Court delivered judgment in Walters v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 1270 in which the Court dismissed the Application by David Walters and Rhondda Walters (QUD8 of 2006) and upheld the Application by the Commissioner of Taxation (QUD10 of 2006).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Because the parties had not made submissions in relation to costs, the question of costs was reserved to be determined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">David Walters and Rhondda Walters provided short submissions on 27 August 2007 and the Commissioner of Taxation provided short written submissions on 3 September 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 David Walters and Rhondda Walters accept that there are no special circumstances which would alter the burden of the usual order for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Since the Commissioner of Taxation has been successful in both Applications, the Order of the Court will be that David James Walters and Rhondda Isobel Walters are to pay the costs of the Commissioner of Taxation of and incidental to each Application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">I certify that the preceding two (2) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Associate:

Dated: 7 September 2007

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr D Russell QC and Mr P G Bickford 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Cleary Hoare Solicitors 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr G J Davies QC and Mr D Harding 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Ms Lynch, Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Submissions by David Walters and Rhondda Walters: 27 August 2007 
 
 Date of Submissions by the Commissioner of Taxation: 3 September 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 September 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1403.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>