<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Labocus Precious Metals Pty Ltd v Thomas [2007] FCA 1072 (19 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1072.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">expert evidence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">enquiry under s 178 of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">evidence</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 

 
1 In this matter the applicants sought to read two affidavits of a well-known chartered accountant and trustee, William James Hamilton, the two affidavits being sworn on 17 July and 18 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">I propose to reject the totality of both affidavits in their current form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I have had argument before me as to the admissibility of expert evidence in professional cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">That may not be the correct focus of debate for the admissibility of this evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">I say that because although there is an explicit, or implicit, assertion in the pleadings by the applicants that the first respondent has failed to take into account properly the interests of creditors at the time of the composition meetings, and although that matter can be seen as a question of professional standards, the structure of the claim and of the proceeding is founded significantly, though not wholly, on the operation of s 178 of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">2 Section 178 of the Bankruptcy Act is in wide terms giving power to the court to make such order as it thinks just and equitable, in effect in review of decisions by the trustee in the course of the administration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">That undertaking and that inquiry may be quite a wide one and the boundary of what is evidence of relevance to that inquiry and the making of orders, consequent upon such inquiry, can be seen to be much wider than the admissibility of evidence as probative and in conformity with the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) in a professional negligence case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Nevertheless, the debate that took place before me was of assistance in reaching my conclusion on either basis; that is, the basis of a professional negligence action and a wider s 178 action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 Without going through the affidavits in detail, they contain evidence which can be summarised as evidence in which Mr Hamilton says what a prudent trustee would have done and evidence as to what he would have done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">There is a body of authority, best illustrated by the judgment of Austin J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Vines (2006) 58 ACSR 298 which rejects evidence in professional negligence cases where the expert evidence does not direct itself to the developed practice amongst competent professionals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">His Honour referred to Permanent Trustee v Boulton (1994) 33 NSWLR 735, and also the well-known case of Midland Bank v Hett Stubbs and Kemp [1978] 3 All ER 571.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">4 The evidence in the two affidavits is sufficiently muddled, if I may say so, without disrespect to Mr Hamilton, not to be of real utility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">If what Mr Hamilton is seeking to say is that in his view no competent professional could ever have taken the steps that were taken by Mr Thomas, the evidence may not be admissible on those authorities by reference to the test of admissibility in a professional negligence case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">I reserve the question as to whether that evidence would be admissible in a s 178 inquiry, such as the present.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">It may be that what he is saying, however, is that he would have done it in a particular manner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">If that is all he is saying, that does not mean that no prudent trustee would have undertaken the steps that Mr Thomas did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">5 Taken from a professional negligence case standpoint, that evidence is irrelevant if the issue is the standard of care of the professional in question, because all that has been proved is what one person in the profession would have done, not what no one, properly informed, could have done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">That said, again, I would reserve the position as to whether that evidence was admissible for an inquiry under s 178 of the Bankruptcy Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">I would also reserve the question of the operation of the discretionary exclusionary provision being s 135 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">If other evidence is to be brought forward in proper form, I will deal with that at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">For now I simply reject the affidavits of William James Hamilton of 17 and 18 July 2007 and they will be marked for identification, MFI 1 and MFI 2 accordingly, in case there is any debate about this issue on another occasion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Allsop.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Associate:

Dated: 2 August 2007


 Counsel for the Applicants: Mr CR Newlinds SC and Mr JT Svehla 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Wordsworth Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr A Spencer 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Home Wilkinson Lowry Lawyers 
 
 Solicitor for the Second and Third Respondents: McMahons National Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 19 July 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 July 2007 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1072.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>