<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Unsworth v Tristar Steering and Suspension Australia Limited [2007] FCA 1434 (12 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1434.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">whether evidence improperly obtained</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">investigative powers of workplace inspector are not spent by a decision to commence court proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">investigative powers of workplace inspector are not spent by a decision to commence court proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">evidence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">workplace relations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The applicant seeks to read and rely upon an affidavit of Ms Elizabeth Anne Goodall affirmed on 19 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Objection is taken on behalf of the respondent on a number of grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">As the decision is an interlocutory ruling in the course of the hearing I will not deliver extensive reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">I will assume a knowledge of the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 On 17 July 2007 an exhibit to the first affidavit of the deponent was rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">It purported to set out the contents of interviews between the deponent, then a workplace inspector, and certain employees of the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Leave was granted to adduce oral evidence on the topic.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">It was then decided that an affidavit would be prepared which would deal with the matters in relation to which leave had been granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">This is the affidavit in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">3 The affidavit deals with interviews occurring during a visit to the factory premises of the respondent on 5 February 2007, during which Inspector Goodall conducted an interview with a person now known to be Mr Huuson Nguyen; a visit to Brownbuilt's factory on 7 February 2007 where there was an interview of each of Mr George Koorey, the Finance and Administration Manager of the respondent, and Ms Yvonne Arnold, the Human Resources Administrator of the respondent; and a visit to the factory on 12 February 2007 where there was an interview of Mr Amit Misra, the Operations Manager of the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">4 I have ruled earlier that s 87(1)(b) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) has the effect that an employee is able to make an ex post facto admission binding the employer provided that it relates to a matter within the scope of the person's employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">5 The first basis of objection was that the evidence was improperly obtained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">A voir dire was held in relation to that question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6 The starting point is Pt 6 of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) (the Act) dealing with workplace inspectors, as the deponent was an inspector at all times material to this issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">It is submitted for the respondent that it is apparent that Inspector Goodall entered the premises that she did in order to interview the individuals pursuant to s 169(2)(b)(iii) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The powers of a workplace inspector under that section may only be exercised: 
 
 
 
 "169(1) (a) for the purpose of determining whether any of the following are being, or have been, observed: 
 (i) workplace agreements; 
 (ii) awards; 
 ..." 
 
 
 
 

7 It is submitted that, at least by 2 February 2007, a decision had been made to commence the current proceedings alleging contravention of the terms of the relevant certified (workplace) agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">It follows, so it is said, that the only conclusion available is that the purpose was not to investigate whether there was, or had been, a contravention but to obtain evidence in relation to the contravention that had already been the subject of a decision to prosecute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">It was submitted that such a purpose was beyond the scope of s 169(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Put another way, the power was spent once the decision to proceed had been taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The evidence was, therefore, obtained illegally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">8 The first answer by counsel for the applicant is that there is no evidence that the deponent was exercising the compulsory statutory powers in conducting the interviews in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">It is submitted that she was simply asking questions of persons willing to answer without compulsion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">There is no express reference to the use or existence of the statutory powers in relation to the relevant interviews.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">It is, at least, doubtful whether the statutory preconditions for the operation of s 169(2)(a) existed in relation to the Brownbuilt premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On the other hand, Inspector Goodall was no doubt presenting as an authorised inspector and it may not be necessary to wave a badge to assert the statutory powers to gain entry and conduct the interviews.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">9 It is not necessary to resolve that issue as, in my opinion, the objection cannot succeed in the face of the decision of the Full Court in Laing v Carroll [2005] FCAFC 202 ; (2005) 146 FCR 511 which concerned the operation of the predecessors to s 169 of the Act, namely, s 83BH and s 86 of the Act as it stood in 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The sections cannot be distinguished in substance and the reasoning in Laing [2005] FCAFC 202 ; 146 FCR 511 is directly applicable to the present circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Lander J gave the leading judgment on this point (at [246]---[286]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Kenny J agreed (at [82]) but added some observations of her own on this point ([90]---[93]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">On this reasoning, the powers in question are not spent, even by the institution of civil penalty proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">It seems that Spender J would agree ([76]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">There is no need for me to repeat the analysis of the authorities to be found in those judgments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">I would only add a reference to the judgment of Merkel J in Health Insurance Commission v Freeman (1998) 88 FCR 544 at 558---560 (agreed with by Von Doussa J and Carr J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The argument is weaker in this case than in Laing [2005] FCAFC 202 ; 146 FCR 511 as the proceeding had not been commenced at the time of the interviews.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It can be concluded that a decision in principle to commence the proceeding had been taken by 2 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">That is not incompatible with the necessity for completion of the investigation prior to actual commencement of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">I should add that there is no basis here for an argument that the interviews constituted a contempt of court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The evidence was not illegally obtained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">10 Separate objection is taken to para 4 of the affidavit, referring to a conversation with a Mr Huuson Nguyen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">I agree with the submission for the respondent that this evidence is not admissible, even with the assistance of s 87 of the Evidence Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">There is no evidence that the scope of his employment is such as to make the statements admissible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Paragraphs 3 and 5 fall with para 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">11 Objection is taken to paras 18---23 of the affidavit on the basis that they go beyond the leave which was granted to lead further evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">A conscious decision was made by the deponent to omit the content of these paragraphs from the statement which had previously been tendered and rejected as the interviewee had requested that the comments be kept strictly confidential and not on the record.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">I can see no good reason for granting leave to permit that decision to be reversed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It is clear enough that the statements would not have been made for the record.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Even if admissible pursuant to s 87 of the Evidence Act , there would be arguments for excluding the evidence pursuant to either s 135 or s 138 of that Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Leave is refused and the paragraphs will be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">I certify that the preceding eleven (11) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Associate:

Dated: 12 September 2007

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr IM Neil SC, Mr T Saunders 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr A Moses, Mr A Short 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Minter Ellison 
 
 Date of Argument: 20 July 2007 
 
 Date of Ruling: 12 September 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1434.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>