<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIHX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1295 (20 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1295.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from a decision of a federal magistrate</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">malaysian citizen of chinese ethnicity</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">non-attendance at hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">federal magistrate correct in concluding no breach of s 425(1)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">new grounds raised on appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">appeal dismissed.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an appeal against an order of a Federal Magistrate made on 29 May 2007 dismissing an application for judicial review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal (the Tribunal) made on 8 December 2005 and handed down on 3 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The Tribunal had affirmed a decision of a delegate of the Minister to refuse to grant a protection visa to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The appellant was born on 31 March 1963 and is a citizen of Malaysia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">He arrived in Australia on 12 June 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">On 25 July 2005 he applied for a Protection (Class XA) visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">A delegate of the first respondent refused his application on 24 August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On 28 September 2005 the appellant lodged an application for review to the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The Tribunal affirmed the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 In a statement attached to his protection visa application, the appellant claimed that he was persecuted in Malaysia on the Convention ground of race, namely, his Chinese ethnicity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">He claimed the Chinese minority were subject to racial discrimination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">He stated that Chinese people in Malaysia were not afforded the same opportunities as the Malaysian majority and that if returned to Malaysia he would become a target of "gangsters".</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">He would receive no help from the Government.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">4 The appellant did not supplement those claims in respect of his review application to the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 On his application to the Tribunal for review, the appellant did not nominate an agent or authorised recipient to receive correspondence, instead electing that it be sent to him at "34 Parkside Drive, Kogarah Bay, NSW, 2217" (the Kogarah Bay address).</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">6 On 27 October 2005 the Tribunal sent the appellant an "invitation to hearing" by way of registered letter to this address inviting him to a hearing on 30 November 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">This letter was "returned to sender" with the box marked "refused" ticked and was received by the Tribunal on 2 November 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">7 On 18 November 2005 the Tribunal sent a letter to the appellant at 36/460 Pitt Street, Sydney, NSW, 2000 (the Pitt Street address), which was the postal address recorded on the appellant's initial protection visa application, seeking confirmation of the appellant's address and enclosing a change of contact details form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The Tribunal warned the appellant (in bold text) that if it had not heard from him by 6 December 2005 it would assume "that [his] addresses have not changed from the ones shown in the box above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">" No reply was received from the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">He did not attend the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">8 The Tribunal proceeded to make a decision pursuant to s 426A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">9 The Tribunal set out the appellant's claims as stated in his protection visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In its finding and reasons, the Tribunal stated that the appellant's claims were "vague and lacking in detail" and that he had "provided little evidence of any persecution or discrimination he may have suffered or that he fears that he may suffer from gangs in Malaysia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">" The Tribunal noted that the claims were mere assertions and that the Tribunal had not had the opportunity to test those claims at a hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Due to the lack of detail as to how the appellant was adversely affected, the Tribunal said that it could not be satisfied that the appellant had suffered serious harm in the past or would do so in the reasonably foreseeable future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The Tribunal concluded that it was not satisfied that the appellant had a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">10 On 9 December 2005 the Tribunal wrote to the appellant at the Kogarah Bay address advising that a decision had been made and would be handed down on 3 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The decision was then sent to the appellant at the Kogarah Bay address on 3 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">11 On 9 February 2006 the appellant applied to the Federal Magistrates Court for a review of the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">He claimed that the Tribunal failed to invite him to a hearing and therefore breached s 425(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The particulars stated that the appellant assumed that as the Tribunal had sent the letter dated 6 December 2005 to the Pitt Street address, that by stating it would assume "that [his] addresses have not changed from the ones shown in the box above", it was referring to his Pitt Street address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">He asserted that he was not notified by the Tribunal regarding the hearing or any other matters in relation to his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">12 In the application to the Federal Magistrates Court, he stated that he received notification of the decision of the Tribunal on 12 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It is to be remembered that the Tribunal's decision was sent to the same address as the invitation to hearing letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">In his affidavit filed with his application he stated that he "recently became aware that [the] RRT has refused [his] application and the decision was sent to [his] previous address at Kogarah Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">"
 
13 The Federal Magistrate examined the procedures prescribed by the Act in order for the Tribunal to validly effect notice of an invitation to hearing and concluded that the Tribunal invited the appellant to attend a hearing in accordance with the prescribed time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The Federal Magistrate concluded that the Tribunal had complied with its obligations pursuant to s 425(1) in inviting the appellant to a hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The Federal Magistrate further concluded that the Tribunal was entitled to make a decision under s 426A of the Act without inviting the appellant to a further hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The ground identified by the appellant in his application to the Federal Magistrates Court was therefore not made out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">14 The Federal Magistrate also considered the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">She concluded that the Tribunal was within jurisdiction to dismiss the application on the material before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">15 On 18 June 2007 the appellant filed a notice of appeal to this court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Two grounds are raised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">First, that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error in relying upon historical country information rather than up-to-date information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Secondly, that the Tribunal breached its obligations under s 424A of the Act by not putting the country information on which it relied to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">16 The notice of appeal raises two grounds not in issue before the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">In WAJR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 624, new appeal grounds were substituted at the last minute when the appellant had been assigned pro bono counsel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">French J noted at [18]:
 
 It is ordinarily regarded as exceptional to allow a point to be raised on appeal that was not raised at first instance --- University of Wollongong v Metwally (No 2) [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68; 59 ALJR 481; Crampton v R [2000] HCA 60 ; (2000) 206 CLR 161; 176 ALR 369.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">But as Branson and Katz JJ said in H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2000) 63 ALD 43 at [3]:
 
 
 "This does not mean that an issue can never be argued on appeal that was not argued at the hearing at first instance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">" 
 

17 His Honour continued at [19]:
 
 To allow too readily the running of new points, or indeed a whole new case, on appeal is to undermine the appellate process by rendering the trial process almost irrelevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">

18 There appear to be no "exceptional" circumstances in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The appellant sought to impugn the Tribunal's decision under s 425(1) of the Act before the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">That point has now been abandoned in favour of two quite different grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">To allow the appellant to agitate those grounds would be to render the process before the Federal Magistrate irrelevant and indeed contrary to the policy in the Act, as this Court would be made the Court of first instance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The appellant, who was unrepresented on appeal, could not explain why the present course had been adopted and why the matters sought to be agitated could not have been raised before the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">For those reasons, in my opinion, it would have been inappropriate to have allowed the appellant to argue those matters on this appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">However, there is a more compelling reason for reaching that conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Both new grounds would fail for the simple reason that the Tribunal did not rely on any country information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The grounds of appeal are therefore irrelevant to the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">19 The appeal must be dismissed and the appellant must pay the first respondent's costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">I certify that the preceding nineteen (19) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lander J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Associate:

Dated: 21 August 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: N Johnson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 20 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 August 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1295.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>