<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Reidy v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation, in the matter of Forseasons Pty Limited [2007] FCA 1330 (21 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1330.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">failure by administrator to serve and publish notices of a second creditors' meeting within statutory time limit</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">query whether a prospective declaration of validity may be made under s 1322(4)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">time limits extended</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application by Geoffrey Philip Reidy, the administrator of the second plaintiff Forseasons Pty Limited ACN 107 517 993 (the Administrator), for relief under s 1322 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Act) to deal with some irregularities which have occurred in relation to the calling of a second meeting by the Administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">There are two irregularities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The first relates to service of a notice of the meeting upon creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">That was a day late, assuming the mail was delivered the following day, informal service having taken place on the correct day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The second is that notice of the meeting was not published in the newspapers until a day after it should have been.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The meeting is fixed for tomorrow.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The evidence is that the only creditors of which there is any evidence have both acknowledged receipt of the notice of meeting and consent to and approve the regularisation of the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">I am quite satisfied that the irregularities arose due to inadvertence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">2 The irregularities are essentially of a procedural nature, bearing in mind the relevant definitions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">There is no doubt that the persons concerned in the contravention acted honestly and, in my opinion, no substantial injustice has been, or is likely to be, caused to any person by making the order sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Indeed, a failure to regularise the matter would lead to delay and further cost to the creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Therefore, everything points to making the appropriate order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">I might say that I am satisfied that s 1322 applies, notwithstanding the existence of s 447A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">3 The initial application was for a declaration of validity of the meeting which is to take place tomorrow.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I rather doubt whether that declaration can be made in advance, having in mind the wording of s 1322(4)(a) notwithstanding some commentary to which I have been referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In any event, the application is now for orders extending the two relevant periods concerned to 16 August 2007, the effect of which will be that there will be no breach and there should, therefore, be no doubt about the validity of the meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">If any residual difficulty is felt, then an application can be made at that stage to have the appropriate declaration made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">I am not suggesting that would be necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">4 I am also satisfied that notice has been given to the appropriate persons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">5 It will be a condition of the grant of relief that the costs and expenses associated with this application should be borne by the Administrator personally and not the creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Associate:

Dated: 17 September 2007


 Solicitor for the Plaintiffs: Mr MJ Fitzgerald 
 
 Date of Hearing: 21 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 August 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1330.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>