<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Get Motor Cycles Pty Ltd(Formerly Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd) (3) [2007] FCA 1078 (27 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1078.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">security for costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">where respondents seek security for costs against applicant company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">where significant and avoidable delay in bringing application for security</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">where trial imminent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether delay in bringing application will prejudice applicant if security is ordered</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">where applicant is impecunious company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">where no evidence put forward about assets or liabilities of persons standing behind applicant company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">where cross-claim on foot</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">where respondents indicate that if security is ordered cross-claim will be abandoned</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">whether estimate by respondents' solicitor of respondents' future costs admissible</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">relevant principles on application for security for costs.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application by the respondents by notice of motion for an order for security for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application is brought pursuant to s 1335 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) or s 56 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), or both.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">There is no dispute that it appears by credible testimony that there is reason to believe that Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd, the applicant in the proceedings, will be unable to pay the respondents' costs if they are successful in their defence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">In those circumstances, similar factors are relevant to whether an order for security for costs should be made whether the application be considered under s 1335 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) or s 56 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth): Jodast Pty Ltd v A &amp; J Blattner Pty Ltd (1991) 104 ALR 248 per Hill J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 The respondents seek an order that the applicant provide security for their costs by way of a bank guarantee in the sum of $250,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">They seek an order that if the security is not provided, the applicant's proceeding should be stayed or dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The respondents have brought a cross-claim against the applicant but, on the hearing of their notice of motion, they have indicated that if security is granted they will not pursue the cross-claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3 
 
On 16 July 2007 I made the following order:
 
 "Nicholas Jules Stuart [sic] on or before 23 July 2007 provide a personal guarantee to the respondents whereby he guarantees the payment of any costs the applicant is ordered to pay the respondents and incurred by the respondents on or after 5 July 2007 up to a sum of $200,000.00.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">"
 

My reasons for making that order follow.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The facts 
 
4 The applicant company was incorporated on 13 July 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Its directors are Julius John Abrahams and Nicholas Jules Stewart.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr Stewart is Mr Abrahams' son and it seems that he changed his name from Abrahams to Stewart.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Mr Stewart holds 23 of the applicant' s 24 issued ordinary shares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Mr Abrahams owns the other share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The applicant changed its name from Victorian Tree Services Pty Ltd to Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd in early November 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The commercial relationship between the applicant and the first respondent appears to have commenced in about September 2004 and it concluded in about August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">5 The financial statements of the applicant for the financial years ended 30 June 2005 and 30 June 2006 were put before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The former also contain the figures for the financial year ended 30 June 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Nothing has been put before me as to the financial position of the applicant after 30 June 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">6 The financial statements show that the applicant previously conducted a business referred to as VTS, which presumably is Victorian Tree Services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">That business was sold at some time during the financial year ended 30 June 2005 for the sum of $89,859.64.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">In its statement of claim, the applicant claims that it sold its arboricultural business at an undervalue because there was pressure for it to enter into the agreement with the respondents quickly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">7 The financial statements show that for the financial year ended 30 June 2006 the retained losses of the applicant were $521,050.48, comprising an operating loss of $247,317.63 and retained losses from the beginning of the financial year of $273,732.85.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The net liabilities of the applicant as at 30 June 2006 were $456,297.48.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">8 
 
Counsel for the respondents referred me to matters in the financial statements which, he submitted, showed that the applicant was never profitable, even when conducting its arboricultural business, and that the present parlous position of the applicant was due to the way in which the company was managed rather than any conduct by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">I will need to return to consider those submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">For present purposes, it is sufficient to note that it is clear the applicant will not be able to meet any costs orders made against it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">9 The respondents submit that the directors and shareholders, or at least Mr Stewart, are paying the applicant's legal costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">That is something which would have to be inferred from the financial statements, for there is no express evidence in support of the assertion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">On the other hand, there is no evidence of a major creditor or group of creditors funding the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">In my opinion, it is appropriate on the balance of probabilities to infer that Mr Stewart is funding the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">It is also appropriate to infer that Mr Stewart will be a major beneficiary if the proceedings are successful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">No evidence was put forward as to the capacity of Mr Stewart to meet an order for costs if an order was made in favour of the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">In other words, no information as to his assets or liabilities was put before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">10 It is convenient at this point to briefly outline the nature of the applicant's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">11 A company called Jianshe or Jianshe Industries Co Ltd manufactured motorcycles and all-terrain vehicles in China under the name, logo or style of "Jianshe".</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">In September 2004 the applicant and the first respondent entered into a distribution agreement in relation to Jianshe motorcycles and other related products and parts ("the products") from China, whereby the applicant became the first respondent's distributor of Jianshe products in the States of Victoria, South Australia and Tasmania.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The relationship did not last and it came to an end, in circumstances which are in dispute, in about August 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The applicant claims to have suffered loss and damage as a result of the respondents' conduct and it claims that the first respondent was in breach of contract and that it wrongfully repudiated the contract, that it engaged in unconscionable conduct under Part IVA s 51AC of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ("TPA"), that it contravened an applicable industry code and, in particular, the Franchising Code of Conduct in the Trade Practices (Industry Codes-Franchising) Regulations 1998 under Part IVB s 51AD of the TPA, that it engaged in misleading or deceptive conduct under Part V s 52 of the TPA, that it breached implied warranties imposed on an importer under Part V Division 2A ss 74B, C, D and F and that the second respondent was liable under the accessorial liability provisions in the TPA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Various forms of relief are claimed, including damages at common law and compensation under s 82 of the TPA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Orders under s 87 of the TPA are also claimed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">12 The applicant pleads that it still has in its possession Jianshe products for which it paid the first respondent the sum of about $94,019.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The respondents claim that these products have depreciated in value.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">13 The proceedings were instituted by the applicant on 6 February 2006 and a defence and cross-claim were filed by the respondents on 5 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">On 15 December 2006 a series of orders were made, including an order listing the matter for trial on 2 June 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">That date was subsequently vacated and a new trial date of 16 July 2007 was fixed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Subsequently, I vacated that date and the trial will now commence on 13 August 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">In large measure, the need to vacate that date was brought about by an application by the applicant to amend its statement of claim and the late delivery by the applicant of an outline of a witness statement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">14 I will not recite the details of all the interlocutory steps taken in the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">However, two should be mentioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">On 4 April 2007 I refused an application by the applicant for summary judgment on part of its claim: Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 489.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In May 2007 I dealt with an application by the respondents for a stay or dismissal of the proceedings by reason of non-compliance by the applicant with various orders of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The details of the application are set out in my reasons on a question of costs: Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 903.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">15 The respondents' notice of motion seeking security for costs was filed and served on 5 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">On the face of it, the application has not been brought promptly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The respondents sought to explain the delay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">They put forward evidence establishing that on 25 October 2006 their solicitors wrote to the applicant's solicitors seeking details of assets held by the applicant and expressing the respondents' concern about their ability to recover their costs if successful in their defence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">An application for security for costs was foreshadowed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The respondents put forward evidence establishing that on 22 February 2007 their solicitors wrote to the applicant's solicitors requesting, among other things, copies of the applicant's accounts and that they received a copy of the accounts on 14 June 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">16 The applicant put forward evidence establishing that there were a number of other events relevant to the question of delay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">It seems that the respondents' solicitors raised with the applicant's former solicitor the respondents' concern about recovering their costs from the applicant in the event they were successful in their defence as early as March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">That was shortly after the proceedings were commenced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The respondents' solicitors had conducted searches of real property owned by the applicant and they requested details of the applicant's assets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">On 15 March 2006, the applicant's former solicitor wrote to the respondents' solicitors in the following terms:
 
 " Security for costs 
 
 The Respondents by their own admission and without prejudice to the Applicant's Application and Statement of Claim does [sic] have an asset --- the Stock which for this issue you will no doubt accept is valued at about $100K.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">Therefore the Respondent can look to that for security for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">"
 

17 On 15 March 2006, the respondents' solicitors responded to that letter by saying they would seek their clients' instruction and advise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">18 It seems that the respondents' solicitors followed up their letter to the applicant's solicitors dated 25 October 2006 (see [15]) when on 13 November 2006 they wrote to the applicant's solicitors in the following terms:
 
 " Security for costs 
 
 As outlined in our letter of 25 October 2006, our clients are concerned that if they successfully defend your client's claim, any costs order made in our clients' favour may not be enforceable against your client.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">If your client cannot (or does not) satisfy us by no later than 17 November 2006 that any costs order made in our clients' favour can be enforced, we shall apply for an order for security for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">As previously outlined, if an application for security for costs is necessary, we will be seeking security for costs in or about the sum of $50,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">"
 

19 The evidence establishes that the respondents could have obtained copies of the applicant's financial statements at any time from October 2006 onwards but they did not do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">20 The applicant's managing director, Mr Stewart, states that past costs and expenses "have been incurred by the applicant in reliance on the assumption induced by the conduct of the Respondents that no security for costs would be sought in the proceeding by the Respondent".</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">Mr Stewart also states:
 
 "That had the Applicant been required to give security for costs when this matter commenced, or in March 2006, or in October 2006, or in December 2006 when it was set down for hearing or at the time of the two interlocutory decisions of the court the Applicant may well have decided to reconsider continuing this litigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Applicant has incurred costs over eighteen months on the basis that there was no order for security for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">" 
 

21 I accept that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">22 In my opinion, the delay by the respondents in applying for security for costs is significant and it is not explained by the respondents in a way which diminishes its significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">23 Before turning to consider the matters relevant to the exercise of the discretion, it is necessary to consider the quantum of costs sought by the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The respondents' solicitor estimates their future costs from 5 July 2007 (that is, the date of the notice of motion) at around $300,000 comprising:
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Preparation for trial of 10 days at $10,670 per day for senior and junior counsel and instructing solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">A 15-day trial at $10,670 per day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Disbursements by way of witness fees and travelling expenses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">

24 The applicant challenged the estimates on the ground that the respondents' solicitors did not have the necessary qualifications to make them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">I think they were qualified to make the estimates and I reject the challenge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">It seems to me that the estimates are within an appropriate range.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">25 Had this been a case in which it was appropriate to order security by way of cash deposit or bank guarantee, it would be necessary to consider the extent to which the figure of $300,000 should be discounted to reflect various contingencies, including the possibility that the proceedings may settle (GE Dal Pont, Law of Costs (LexisNexis Butterworths) at [28.29]-[28.39]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">However, it is not necessary to do that because I do not think that an order of that nature should be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Exercise of the discretion 
 
26 The discretion to order security for costs is a very broad one: Lucas v Yorke (1983) 50 ALR 228.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The authorities have identified a number of factors relevant to the exercise of the discretion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I refer, by way of example, to the discussion by Beazley J in KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 56 FCR 189 at 196-198, French J in Carey-Hazell v Getz Bros &amp; Co (Aust) Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1334 at [28] , Hill J in Equity Access Ltd v Westpac Banking Corporation (1989) ATPR 40-972 and Jessup J in Acohs Pty Ltd v Ucorp Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1279 ; (2006) 155 FCR 181 at 183-186 [7] - [12] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">27 The factors which have been identified in the authorities are as follows:
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">Whether the application for security is brought promptly;
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">The strength and bone fides of the applicant's case; 
 
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Whether the applicant's impecuniosity was caused by the respondent's conduct the subject of the claim;
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Whether the respondent's application for security is oppressive in the sense that it is being used merely to deny an impecunious applicant a right to litigate;
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">Whether there are any persons standing behind the applicant who are likely to benefit from the litigation and who are willing to provide the necessary security;
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Whether the persons standing behind the applicant have offered any personal undertaking to be liable for the costs and, if so, the form of any such undertaking;
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Whether the applicant is in substance a plaintiff or the proceedings are defensive in the sense of directly resisting proceedings already brought or seeking to halt the respondent's self-help procedures;
 8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">Whether there are aspects of public interest which weigh in the balance against making an order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Whether there are any particular discretionary matters peculiar to the circumstances of the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">
 

28 Not all of these factors are necessarily relevant in every case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">Furthermore, one may be decisive or of very great weight in the circumstances of a particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">29 In this case the first matter, namely, the delay in bringing the application is a very significant matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">There is no doubt the respondents were aware of the Court's power to make an order for security for costs and, indeed, they raised the issue with the applicant's former solicitor in March 2006 and with the applicant's present solicitor in October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">The applicant's financial statements could have been obtained by the respondents from October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The application for security was not brought until less than two weeks before the first adjusted trial date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The fact that that trial date has now been changed to 13 August 2007 is relevant but, in the end, I do not think that it detracts in any significant way from the importance to be attached to the respondents' delay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The respondents submit that any delay on their part cannot be decisive of their application and, in fact, in the absence of prejudice, is of minimal significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">They referred to Hughes Bros Pty Ltd v Trustees of the Roman Catholic Church for the Archdiocese of Sydney (Unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Hunter J, 7 November 1995); Clarence Street v ISIS Projects Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 380.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">In Clarence St , McDougall J said (at [22]):
 
 "The authorities, I think, on a proper analysis also make it plain that delay is not to be looked at in the abstract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">What is important is whether, assuming that delay has been shown, such delay causes actual prejudice to the party against whom the order is sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Even if prejudice is shown, the application need not fail; but unless it is shown, the significance of delay as a countervailing factor disappears.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">See the decision of Hunter J in Hughes Bros Pty Limited v Trustees of the Roman Catholic Church for the Archdiocese of Sydney (7 November 1995, unreported; BC 95079079).</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">"
 

30 There are other authorities which suggest that the weight to be attached to delay by an applicant for security will depend on whether there is any prejudice to the party against whom security is sought (see the authorities referred to in GE Dal Pont, Law of Costs (LexisNexis Butterworths) at [29.129]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">For present purposes, I will assume that delay is only of significance if prejudice to the applicant is shown.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">I am satisfied that the applicant will suffer prejudice if an order for security is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">It is plain from its financial statements that it cannot provide security by way of a cash deposit or bank guarantee and it has expended what are presumably substantial costs in preparing its case for trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">It is clear from Mr Stewart's evidence that the applicant may not have proceeded this far had an application for security for costs been made earlier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">31 In my opinion, it would cause prejudice to the applicant and be quite unfair to it to make an order for security for costs by way of a cash deposit or bank guarantee at this late stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">To my mind, that is a sufficient reason to refuse the application insofar as it seeks security of that nature.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">However, having regard to the matters outlined below, it does not stand in the way of an order that the party who will benefit from the proceeding if it is successful, Nicholas Jules Stewart, be required to provide a personal guarantee whereby he guarantees the payment of any costs the applicant is ordered to pay the respondents and incurred by the respondents on or after 5 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">I realise that I have conducted no inquiry into Mr Stewart's financial position and his ability to meet a costs order, but I do not think that that means that such a guarantee cannot constitute a form of security: Clyde Industries Ltd v Ryad Engineering Pty Ltd (1993) 11 ACLC 325 at 328 per Rowland J (see also the discussion in Dal Pont at 964-965 [29.28]-[29.29]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">In any event, if such a guarantee is worthless, that would be a reason to refuse an order for security for costs because the proceedings would otherwise be stifled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">32 My conclusions have been reached not only in the context of the delay, but also having regard to the other factors which I turn now to address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">33 As to the second matter referred to in [27], I am satisfied that the applicant's claim is bona fide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">However, I am not prepared to go any further than that because there are a number of contested issues and, in those circumstances, it would be inappropriate for me to comment on the merits of the applicant's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">34 As to the third matter, there is no doubt that the applicant is impecunious.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">However, the respondents contend that the applicant was impecunious before it entered into a commercial relationship with the respondents or that its present parlous position is due to the applicant's poor financial management or both.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">As to the respondents' first submission, it is not easy without more information to determine how the applicant was performing before it entered into a commercial relationship with the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">On the one hand, the VTS business was sold for $89,859.64 suggesting that it was a profitable business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">On the other hand, for the financial year ended 30 June 2004, the applicant earned income of around $7,000 but had retained losses of about $62,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The balance sheet of the applicant as at 30 June 2004 indicates net liabilities of about $37,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">As I have said, at some stage in the financial year ended 30 June 2005 the applicant sold the VTS business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">A profit and loss statement by segment for the financial year ended 30 June 2005 suggests that the VTS business was profitable until it was sold although the statement was subject to various criticisms by counsel for the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">It is not possible for me to resolve those issues on this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">As to the respondents' second submission, there is simply no evidence which would enable me, assuming it was otherwise appropriate for me to do so, to draw any conclusions as to causation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">I think that all that I can say in fairness to both parties is that, if liability and causation are made out it would seem that the respondents' conduct has contributed to a fairly significant decline in the applicant's business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">35 As to the fourth matter, the applicant has not established that the litigation will be stifled if an order for security for costs is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">The onus is on it to do so: Bell Wholesale Co Ltd v Gates Export Corporation (1984) 2 FCR 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">While it has been established that it will not be able to pay the respondents' costs if they are successful in their defence it has not been established that those who stand behind the applicant cannot provide security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">As I have said, no evidence as to the financial position of Mr Stewart has been put before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">36 As to the fifth and sixth matters, in view of the order which I have made, it is not necessary for me to say anything more about those factors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">37 As to the seventh matter, it is not relevant here.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">38 As to the eighth matter, this provides some moderate support for refusing an order for security for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">The applicant points to its claim in relation to the Franchising Code of Conduct and submits that there is a public interest in allowing a claim to proceed which involves what the applicant submits is a blatant breach of what are consumer protection provisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">I have accorded this matter some weight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">39 As to the ninth matter, there are no particular discretionary matters in this case other than those which I have identified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Conclusion 
 
40 It was for these reasons that I made the order I did on 16 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">I certify that the preceding forty (40) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Associate:

Dated: 27 July 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr Ian Jones SC with Mr T Hurley 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Francis V Gallichio 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr D H Denton SC with Ms M A Tran 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Williams Graham Carman 
 
 Dates of Hearing: 12, 16 July 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 July 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1078.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>