<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZILF v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship (Corrigendum 9 November 2007) [2007] FCA 1702 (7 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1702.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">consideration of an appeal from the federal magistrates court raising questions going to s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth) and whether the refugee review tribunal was required to make particular findings of fact</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">no appearance by the appellant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">motion for dismissal pursuant to s 25(2b) of the federal court of australia act 1976</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This matter is listed for hearing today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The appellant in the proceedings has failed to appear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">3 The matter was listed for hearing at 2.15pm today and it is now 2.32pm and the appellant, although called, has failed to appear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The Federal Court Registry sent a letter to the appellant on 20 September 2007 advising the appellant of the place, date and time for the hearing of the appeal and that letter was sent to the address for service nominated by the appellant in the notice of appeal filed on 2 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">4 In addition to that letter, the solicitors for the respondents, Blake Dawson Waldron, wrote a letter to the appellant at the same address enclosing a copy of the first respondent's outline of submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That letter is dated 2 November 2007 and those letters have been marked Exhibits 1 and 2 in the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">5 By reason of the failure of the appellant to appear, the first respondent moves for an order pursuant to s 25(2B)(bb) for an order of the Court dismissing the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">6 In view of the failure to appear, I order that the appeal is dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Associate:

Dated: 7 November 2007

 Solicitor for the Appellant Self Represented 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: J Mitchell 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 7 November 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 November 2007 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1702.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>