<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 (19 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2028.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">error of law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whole body impairment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">use of tables in comcare guide</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">injury</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">assessment of permanent impairment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">requirement to isolate compensable effects from effects of underlying condition where it is possible</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">failure to give adequate reasons</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 BUCHANAN J: 
 
1 Mrs Maree Jordan commenced employment with the Australian Postal Corporation ('Australia Post') in 1993.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">She remained in that employment, as a postal delivery officer, until 3 January 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">During the course of her employment she made two claims for compensation with respect to injuries to her right arm or shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">On 22 August 1994 she strained a muscle in her right arm after reaching up while sorting mail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">On 19 July 1996 she suffered a partial tear to a tendon in her right shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The claims were accepted by Australia Post.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">2 On 4 May 2004, more than three years after leaving her employment, Mrs Jordan had surgery on her right shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Shortly before the surgery Dr David Maxwell, on 12 February 2004, provided the following observations:
 
 'Mrs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Maree Jordan still has some symptoms and signs suggestive of right calcific tendonitis involving the supraspinatus tendon causing some impingement of the right shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">
 
 I consider that is probable that the nature and conditions of her work, specifically repetitive use of her right arm, has led to attrition of the right supraspinatus tendon, leading to calcification within the tendon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">This has caused an impingement syndrome.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">' 
 

3 Dr Maxwell therefore, in early 2004, attributed Ms Jordon's difficulties to work related injury or aggravation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">As will be seen, two years later, after surgery, he had a different opinion about the source of her ongoing difficulties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">4 Dr Jerome Goldberg, who performed the surgery made the following statement of his operative findings in a report dated 4 May 2004:
 
 ' OPERATIVE FINDINGS: The patient had a stable shoulder with full movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">There was a 1cm area of calcification about the supraspinatus adjacent to the greater tuberosity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The rotator cuff around the calcific deposit was inflamed and there was a large amount of fatty infiltration consistent with a chronic condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">' 
 

5 Dr Goldberg removed the calcification.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">In a report dated 5 August 2004 Dr Goldberg said:
 
 'She is three months following shoulder surgery and her shoulder is progressing very well, though she still has some discomfort with heavy lifting and overhead work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Her movements today are extremely good and are near full, which is far better than pre-operatively .</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">
 
 Mrs Jordan has ongoing pain and parasthesia in her forearm and hand and this is unrelated to any problem with her shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I believe she requires some EMG studies and perhaps referral to a neurologist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">As ethics demand, I leave this in your hands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

6 Later that year Dr Goldberg said, on 2 December 2004:
 
 'She is six months following her arthroscopic excision of calcium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">She is still complaining of pain about her shoulder, despite having excellent movement .</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">
 
 X-rays confirm that the calcium has essentially been completely removed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">There is a small fleck of calcium about the soft tissues, but this is normal following removal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">
 
 I believe the patient's residual problem relates to tendonitis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">' 
 (emphasis added) 


 
7 On 2 May 2005 Dr Goldberg provided a further report.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">It said, in part:
 
 ' Although her movements have returned to normal, which is far better than her pre-operative level, she is still troubled by pain with activity and when over-using her arm .</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">You will recall that x-rays confirm she has had a good subacromial decompression and the calcium has been completely removed from the cuff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">
 
 Unfortunately I believe this is the best Marie [sic] is going to get.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Although she has done reasonably well from surgery from the point of view of improvement in range of motion, she still has ongoing pain which is likely to be permanent .</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">She is able to cope with this at present and I have advised her to use her arm within the limits of her discomfort.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

8 Mrs Jordan made a claim for compensation on 2 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The claim for compensation was required to be addressed in accordance with s 24 of the Safety, Rehabilitation and Compensation Act 1988 (Cth) ('the Act').</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Section 24 provides relevantly as follows:
 
 
 '(1) Where an injury to an employee results in a permanent impairment , Comcare is liable to pay compensation to the employee in respect of the injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">
 
 ... 
 
 
 (5) Comcare shall determine the degree of permanent impairment of the employee resulting from an injury under the provisions of the approved Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">
 
 (6) The degree of permanent impairment shall be expressed as a percentage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">
 
 (7) Subject to section 25 , if: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) the employee has a permanent impairment other than a hearing loss; and 
 (b) Comcare determines that the degree of permanent impairment is less than 10%; 
 
 
 
 
 an amount of compensation is not payable to the employee under this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">' 
 (emphasis added) 
 

9 'Injury' is defined by s 5A of the Act relevantly as follows:
 
 ' injury means: 
 (a) a disease suffered by an employee; or 
 
 
 (b) an injury (other than a disease) suffered by an employee , that is a physical or mental injury arising out of, or in the course of, the employee's employment ; or 
 (c) an aggravation of a physical or mental injury (other than a disease) suffered by an employee (whether or not that injury arose out of, or in the course of, the employee's employment), that is an aggravation that arose out of, or in the course of that employment ; 
 
 
 but does not include a disease, injury or aggravation suffered as a result of reasonable administrative action taken in a reasonable manner in respect of the employee's employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

10 Section 28 of the Act provides for the preparation of a 'Guide to the Assessment of the Degree of Permanent Impairment' ('the Guide') which is the Guide referred to in s 24(5).</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Section 28(1) and (4) provide:
 
 
 '(1) Comcare may, from time to time, prepare a written document, to be called the "Guide to the Assessment of the Degree of Permanent Impairment", setting out: 
 

 (a) criteria by reference to which the degree of the permanent impairment of an employee resulting from an injury shall be determined ; 
 
 (b) criteria by reference to which the degree of non-economic loss suffered by an employee as a result of an injury or impairment shall be determined; and 
 
 (c) methods by which the degree of permanent impairment and the degree of non-economic loss, as determined under those criteria, shall be expressed as a percentage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 

 
 ... 
 

 
 
 (4) Where Comcare, a licensee or the Administrative Appeals Tribunal is required to assess or re-assess, or review the assessment or re-assessment of, the degree of permanent impairment of an employee resulting from an injury, or the degree of non-economic loss suffered by an employee, the provisions of the approved Guide are binding on Comcare, the licensee or the Administrative Appeals Tribunal, as the case may be, in the carrying out of that assessment, re-assessment or review, and the assessment, re-assessment or review shall be made under the relevant provisions of the approved Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">' 
 

(emphasis added)
 

 
11 Accordingly, the Guide was binding in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">There is now a second edition of the Guide in operation but it was the first edition which was relevant to an assessment of Mrs Jordan's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">In accordance with s 28 , the criteria set out in the Guide related only to impairment resulting from work related injury or aggravation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">12 In the Guide, under the heading 'Principles of Assessment' the following provisions appeared:
 
 ' Gradations of Impairment 
 
 Each table contains impairment values at gradations of 5% or multiples of five percent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Where it is not clear which of two impairment values is more appropriate, Comcare has the discretion to determine which value properly reflects the degree of impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">
 
 There is no discretion to choose an impairment value not specified in the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">For example, where 10% and 20% are specified values there is no discretion to determine impairment as 15%.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">' 
 
 
 
 ... 
 
 Aggravation 
 
 
 
 An assessment should not be made unless the effects of an aggravation are considered permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">If the employee's impairment is entirely attributable to a pre-existing or underlying condition, or to the natural progression of such a condition the assessment for permanent impairment should be nil.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">
 
 Where it is possible to isolate the compensable effects of an injury upon a pre-existing or underlying condition the assessment of the degree of permanent impairment should reflect only the impairment due to those compensable effects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">' 
 
 
 
 

13 The specification of gradations of impairment 'values' is important.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">These values were assigned by various tables which the Guide contained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Each value covered a range.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The ultimate choice of the appropriate value was entrusted to the determining authorities (note also s 24(5)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">14 The principles concerning aggravation are also very important in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">They directed that, where possible, only compensable injury should be assigned a value.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">That is consistent with s 24 which directs a determination of the degree of impairment resulting from an 'injury' (as defined in s 5A).</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Neither s 24 nor the Guide contemplate unnecessary assessment of, or the assignment of a percentage value of impairment to, non-compensable injury or underlying conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">It follows from this statement of principles, and from authority which will be referred to in due course, that if it was not possible to isolate the compensable effects of a work related injury from those of an underlying condition the assessment was to be made by reference to the totality of effects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">15 'Whole person impairment' was defined by the Guide in the following way:
 
 ' Whole Person Impairment means the medical effects of an injury or a disease and is drawn from the American Medical Association Guides where it is there referred to as "whole man" impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Evaluation of whole person impairment is a medical appraisal of the nature and extent of the effect of an injury or disease on a person's functional capacity and on the activities of daily living.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The Guides are structured by assembling detailed descriptions of impairments into groups according to body system and expressing the extent of each impairment as a percentage value of of [sic] the functional capacity of a normal healthy person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Thus a percentage value can be assigned to an employee's impairment by reference to the relevant description in this Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">' 
 
(emphasis added)
 

 
16 'Injury' was defined in the Guide in relevantly the same terms as in the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">It follows that, for the purpose of the present case, whole person impairment referred only to the medical effects of an injury or aggravation arising out of or in the course of employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">17 The table for the assessment of Mrs Jordan's claim was Table 9.1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">It provided (relevantly) as follows:
 'TABLE 9.1 
 
 Upper Extremity 
 (Percentage Whole Person Impairment) 
 
 Introduction --- These tables are intended to be used to assess impairment arising from specific joint lesions or amputations ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">These tables can be used to assess the impairment of overall limb function from any cause ... 
 
 Assessment is in accordance with the range of joint movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">X-rays should not be taken solely for assessment purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">
 
 ... 
 
 
 
 
 
 ______________________________________________________________ 
 
 % DESCRIPTION OF LEVEL OF IMPAIRMENT 
 
 0 X-ray changes but no loss of function of shoulder, elbow or wrist 
 
 
 
 5 Any ONE of the following: 
 
 
 
 
 &#8226; x-ray changes with minimal loss of function of shoulder , elbow or wrist 
 
 
 
 &#8226; ankylosis of any joint of fingers 4 and/or 5 
 
 10 Any ONE of the following: 
 
 
 
 &#8226; loss of less than half normal range of movement of shoulder or elbow 
 &#8226; loss of half normal range of movement of wrist 
 &#8226; ankylosis of any joints of fingers 2 and/or 3 
 
 
 
 
 15 Any ONE of the following: 
 
 
 
 &#8226; loss of more than half normal range of movement of wrist 
 &#8226; ankylosis of any joints of thumb 
 
 
 
 
 
 20 Any ONE of the following: 
 
 
 
 
 &#8226; loss of half normal range of movement of shoulder or elbow 
 &#8226; ankylosis of wrist 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 30 Loss of more than half normal range of movement of shoulder or elbow 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 40 Ankylosis of shoulder or elbow.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

18 A value of 10% level of whole person impairment was thus assigned by Table 9.1 in the event of 'loss of less than half normal range of movement of shoulder or elbow'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">It may be accepted, having regard to the conditions for assigning a value of 5%, that the resulting loss of function needed to be more than minimal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">In accordance with Table 9.1, therefore, a value of 10% whole person impairment would be assigned in the event of more than minimal loss of function up to at least loss of 49% of normal range of movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The accommodation of such a large range within the value of 10% whole person impairment is potentially significant for the disposition of the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">19 An officer of Australia Post rejected Mrs Jordan's claim on 9 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">In a letter to Mrs Jordan's solicitors, after reference was made to Dr Goldberg's reports, including matters which I have extracted above, it was said:
 
 'All of the above confirm that while Mrs Jordan reported a level of pain symptoms post surgery her range of movement of the right shoulder is clearly at a normal level.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">Against the appropriate Table of the Comcare Guide, Table 9.1, there is clearly no evidence to suggest that your client's level of impairment reaches the required threshold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">
 
 It is certainly unclear how your client's shoulder condition has altered from one of having normal movements in Dr Goldberg's report of 2/5/05 to one of limited range as at 2/2/06.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">This is against all the evidence of the reports post surgery and is contradictory to the opinion expressed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">' 
 

20 Mrs Jordan sought a review of the decision of 9 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">In a letter dated 27 February 2006 the original decision was affirmed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">The Reconsideration Officer said in her letter:
 
 'The Compensation Claim for permanent Injury was submitted under cover of your letter dated 6 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Other than the Part C certificate, no further medical opinion was provided in support of the claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">
 
 The Part C certificate was completed by Dr Goldberg.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">He does not provide an assessment of impairment in percentage terms nor does he apparently make an assessment in accordance with the Guide to the Assessment of the Degree of Permanent Impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">He indicates, as best I can interpret, that the extent of the impairment is pain and a reduced range of movement, but provides no description of any decrease in range of movement of the right shoulder such as to meet the requirement in section 24(7)(b) of 10 per cent whole person impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">
 
 In the absence of any such evidence, I am of the opinion that Ms Jordan has not discharged the evidentiary onus to establish an entitlement to the payment of compensation pursuant to sections 24 and 27 of the Safety, Rehabilitation and Compensation Act 1988 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">' 
 

21 Mrs Jordan made an application to the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ('the AAT') for a review of the decision to refuse her claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">Her claim was put squarely on the basis that her impairment arose from the fact that pain caused by a work related injury restricted the normal range of movement of her right shoulder to an extent representing 10% whole person impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">It is not suggested that such a circumstance would not qualify for compensation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">22 The AAT had a series of medical reports before it, including those to which I have referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">It took oral evidence from Mrs Jordan and two medical practitioners on 31 January 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">One of the medical practitioners was Dr Maxwell who had made a further report dated 20 April 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The other was Dr Richard Evans who provided a report dated 14 February 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Dr Evans' report contained the following:
 
 'The exact cause of the persisting shoulder pain is uncertain, but it is not surprising.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">It could arise from the damaged rotator cuff, from associated synovitis, from subacromial/subdeltoid bursitis, or from the damage to the glenoid labrum (the cartilaginous rim of the socket of the "ball and socket" shoulder joint).</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">
 
 ... 
 
 PROGNOSIS: She is likely to continue to experience pain and impaired movement in the right shoulder .</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">
 
 DISABILITY: The permanent whole person impairment of Mrs Jordan's right upper extremity is 10% (Table 9.1: "loss of less than half of normal range of movement of shoulder or elbow").</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">It has occurred as a result of the nature and conditions of her work with Australia Post between 1997 and 2001 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">
 
 I confirm that maximum medical improvement has occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">I also confirm that the above disability is substantially a result of Mrs Jordan's employment with Australia Post .</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

23 It appeared during Dr Evans' evidence that his opinion was in part confirmed by ultrasounds taken on 19 September 1996, 14 October 1998 and 10 May 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">He did not have the benefit of any ultrasounds taken after the operation performed in May 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">He did not have a copy of the operation report nor any other reports by Dr Goldberg.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">He was asked:
 
 'So you had no information about the results that the surgeon recorded post-operatively?---That's right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">' 
 

24 Dr Maxwell's written report included the following:
 
 ' Mrs Maree Jordan continues to complain of pain in her right shoulder .</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">Since I last saw her she has had surgery in the form of an excision of chronic calcification of the rotator cuff which she states has had no effect on her symptoms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">When I saw her prior to this surgery on the 12/2/2004 she only had 10deg.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">of loss of abduction and flexion and other movements were within normal range.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">After the operation on the 2/12/2004 Dr Goldberg states that she had excellent movement in her shoulder despite complaining of pain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">When he examined her on the 2/5/2005 he stated in the 2 nd paragraph of his letter that "her movements had returned to normal which was far better than the pre-operative period".</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">When I tested her range of movements there was virtually no scapulothoracic movement on abduction and flexion indicating that her movement was all glenhumeral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">This is unusual in patients with rotator cuff pathology as normally the glenhumeral movement is the most affected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">I therefore consider it is doubtful that she was exerting maximum voluntary effort during my physical examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">She also seemed emotionally labile and had a hyperactive pain response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">
 
 ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">In accordance with Table 9.1 she has 10% WPI as she has loss of less than half the normal range of movement of her shoulder ... 
 
 The WPI does relate to her right shoulder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">As previously outlined I do not consider she has suffered a specific work related injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">I consider that she has a degenerative condition of calcification of the rotator cuff which may have been aggravated in the course of her work but her symptoms are now due to the underlying condition as she has not worked since 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Any impairment is also related to the underlying condition .</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

25 In his oral evidence Dr Maxwell said:
 
 ' You still accept that she satisfies something more than an insignificant range of movement related to her work condition, that's right, isn't it?---Yes 
 
 I don't know that there's anything else I need to ask?--- I'd actually changed my opinion and I felt that the calcification was a degenerative condition and I wasn't conceding that it was actually related to her work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">I felt that it was aggravated by her work, but not caused by her work and therefore if she hadn't worked for four years that it was no longer aggravated by her work .</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">It was due [to] the underlying calcification.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

26 According, therefore, to Dr Maxwell's assessment the impairment which he identified was not, to any extent, the result of compensable injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">When he assigned a value of 10% WPI Dr Maxwell made no distinction between compensable and non-compensable injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">The Act and the Guide only contemplate and direct that a value will be assigned to the degree of permanent impairment arising from an 'injury'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">In accordance with the view expressed by Dr Maxwell, that Mrs Jordan's impairment was due to an underlying condition and did not arise out of her employment, the percentage value which he should have assigned, in accordance with the principles in the Guide, was nil.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">27 As will be seen, the AAT preferred Dr Maxwell's assessment to that of Dr Evans, although it did not adopt the whole of his conclusions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">28 Counsel for Mrs Jordan submitted that in light of Dr Maxwell's earlier conclusion, that the restriction on movement experienced by Mrs Jordan before her operation was attributable to 'the nature and conditions of her work' (see Dr Maxwell's report of 12 February 2004), it was not open as a matter of law for the AAT to accept any change of opinion by Dr Maxwell to the effect that Mrs Jordan's impairment in 2006 was now due only to an underlying condition and not to a work related 'injury'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">He relied upon the judgments of Jenkinson J in Comcare v Amorebieta (1996) 66 FCR 83 ( 'Amorebieta' ) and Burchett J in Martin v Australian Postal Corporation [1999] FCA 655 ; 29 AAR 420 (' Martin' ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">However in my view neither of those decisions supports the proposition which was advanced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">Showing that a work related aggravation of a pre-existing condition is a continuing aggravation is a necessary condition for a conclusion that it represents a work related compensable injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">As well as continuing, the effects of aggravation must also be permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">29 While Dr Maxwell did not appear to doubt that Mrs Jordon's ongoing pain resulted in loss of a significant range of movement, on his assessment any aggravation of Mrs Jordan's underlying condition, which resulted from the nature and conditions of her work, had been completely resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">With the passage of time it was clear, in his view, that her symptoms were due entirely to the underlying condition and in no part to aggravation caused by her work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">That was a question for medical assessment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Dr Maxwell certainly did not commit any error of law, nor did the AAT in relying upon his opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">30 Counsel for Australia Post contended, in opposing the appeal, that a relevant injury, to be compensable, must be wholly related to work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">To the extent that the submission invokes the definition of 'injury' earlier set out and its associated effect on s 24 and the Guide, it is clearly correct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">However, neither the Act nor the Guide exclude the possibility that some impairment might result from the combined effect of an underlying condition and a work related aggravation of that condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">In those circumstances it is, strictly speaking, only the work related aggravation which is compensable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">The Guide directs that, 'where it is possible', the compensable effects of any work related aggravation should be isolated from the effects of the underlying condition for the purpose of assessing the degree of permanent impairment due to compensable effects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">That may be easier said than done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">If it is not possible the assessment made should operate beneficially to the claimant (see Martin at [29] to [30]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">31 In the critical passages in the AAT decision it said the following:
 
 
 '55.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">On balance, we prefer the assessment of Dr Maxwell that Mrs Jordan does experience 10% impairment, but that this is not simply attributable to a work related injury .</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">She had full movement restored to the shoulder by the surgery in 2004 but has not maintained any improvement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">As she has not worked since 2001, we favour Dr Maxwell's assessment that this suggests a degenerative condition rather than a continuing effect from the work injury or aggravation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">We find further reassurance in taking this view from Dr Evans's oral evidence that the surgery he understood to have been performed normally would provide relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Dr Evans's opinion was coloured by his knowledge being confined to what he told us at the hearing, that is, he knew the applicant had arthroscopic surgery and he had the information from her that it didn't help and that she had injections.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">He thought the injections from Dr Goldberg after the operation implied that the result wasn't a very good one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">By comparison, this was not what Dr Goldberg believed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">Dr Goldberg was pleased with the result of the surgery and observed improved range of movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Unfortunately, Dr Evans did not have the benefit of Dr Goldberg's reports when forming his own opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">
 
 
 
 
 
 56.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">We find that Mrs Jordan's injury did benefit from the surgery in 2004 and that her impairment , while possibly being in the order of 10%, must be discounted when assessing the degree of impairment for compensation because it is partly attributable to a degenerative condition of calcification .</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">It is necessary for the injury to result in 10% impairment before compensation is payable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">See s 24(7).</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">
 
 
 
 57.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">It follows that we will affirm the decision under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

32 In my view this approach reveals a misunderstanding of the statutory scheme and the legal effect of the direction contained in the Guide, by which the AAT was bound.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">It does not appear that the AAT embraced Dr Maxwell's final conclusion, although preferring his opinion to Dr Evans'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">Had it done so it would have concluded there was nil impairment under Table 9.1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">Rather, the AAT appeared to proceed by deduction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">It concluded that Mrs Jordan's loss of range of movement was partly attributable to an underlying condition and that any attribution at all of Mrs Jordan's injury to a degenerative condition of calcification necessarily resulted in the extent of impairment dropping below 10%.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">However, it is not permissible to proceed upon any assumption that 'discounting' for the presence or contribution of an underlying condition necessarily resulted in whole person impairment of less than 10%.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">There are three reasons for that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">The first is that any assigned value represents a final conclusion about whole person impairment arising from employment injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">It is not a starting point for further calculations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Secondly, the assigned value (in this case 10%) accommodates a wide range of loss of range of movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">Attribution of some loss to an underlying condition, unless it entirely explains the loss of range of movement, will in many cases not make the final assignment of a value any less valid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">For example, if a 45% loss of range of shoulder movement was due, as to 20%, to an underlying condition, the remaining 25% attributable to work injury or aggravation would still represent, in accordance with Table 9.1 of the Guide, a 10% whole person impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">The third reason is related to the last mentioned circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">The Guide directs that compensable effects be isolated 'where it is possible'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">As already observed, where that is not possible no discount, to the disadvantage of a claimant, of the effects of a work related injury will be permissible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">33 The AAT accepted Dr Maxwell's assessment that Mrs Jordan had lost a significant range of movement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">Unless it concluded that the loss of range was entirely due to an underlying condition in my view it was obliged to consider whether the effects of any work related injury could be isolated from the effects of the underlying condition so that an impairment value could be assigned directly to, and only to, the effects of the work related injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">34 The approach taken by the AAT overlooks the necessity for appropriate isolating of compensable effects (where it is possible) before a value is assigned to the impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">It is inconsistent with the legislative arrangements to discount after a value is assigned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">The error is compounded when, as in the present case, a false starting point is chosen for the deduction process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">The process adopted by the AAT could only result in rejection of the claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">That approach represented a failure to address the question for its attention --- namely, what level of impairment was due to a work related injury?</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">35 The view which I take of the necessity to evaluate only compensable effects, and attribute a value for whole person impairment to them, appears to me to be consistent with observations made by Jenkinson J in Amorebieta where his Honour said (at 96):
 
 
 'The inclusion of the phrase in s.24(5) ["resulting from an injury"] is explicable as a means of making clear that only impairment which results from harm suffered in compensable circumstances is to be the subject of determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">"Injury" is so defined as to require contribution to the harm by the employment or, in the case of an injury other than a disease or the aggravation of such an injury, to require that it arise "in the course of" the employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">' 
 (emphasis added)
 

36 It is relevant to note also that Jenkinson J rejected the proposition (although in a different context) that the assignment of percentage values in tables in the Guide allowed some mathematically derived result rather than a direct assignation of value based upon a medical evaluation of the effects of compensable injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">His Honour said (at 99):
 
 'It was a ground of appeal that the Tribunal had failed to recognise that on its proper construction Table 9.6 required that the loss of less than half normal range of movement of the thoraco-lumbar spine which would justify assessment of "whole person impairment" as 10 per cent was a loss of at least one third of the normal range of movement of the thoraco-lumbar spine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">That construction was proposed because 10 per cent whole person impairment was one third of the 30 per cent whole person impairment shown by the Table to be appropriate in respect of complete loss of movement of the thoraco-lumbar spine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">
 
 The explanation of the expression "whole person impairment" in the Guide Glossary (set out above at p 92) shows it to signify a "medical appraisal".</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">Without expert medical evidence that the mathematical relationship suggested in submission accords with the processes of medical appraisal of whole person impairment the Tribunal would not in my opinion be free to accept the submission ...' 
 (emphasis added)
 

37 It follows from what I have said that, in my view, the AAT made errors of law in its assessment of Mrs Jordan's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">38 Counsel for Mrs Jordan also contended that the AAT had made an error of law by not providing sufficient reasons for its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Section 43(2) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) ('the AAT Act') requires the AAT to give reasons for its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">Section 43(2B) of the AAT Act provides:
 
 
 '(2B) Where the Tribunal gives in writing the reasons for its decision, those reasons shall include its findings on material questions of fact and a reference to the evidence or other material on which those findings were based.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">' 
 
 
 

These requirements were referred to and explained by Burchett J in Martin at [18] and [19].</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">39 Although it is clear that the reasons for decision of the AAT were based upon a preference for Dr Maxwell's opinion to that of Dr Evans, what is omitted from the AAT decision is any finding on the factual question concerning the assessment of the degree of permanent impairment suffered by Mrs Jordan as assigned by the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">As already discussed, the assumption that partial attribution of her loss of range of movement to a degenerative condition of calcification necessarily resulted in her failure to establish a 10% whole person impairment is unsound and not in accordance with the Act or the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">In circumstances where Dr Maxwell's assessment was not wholly embraced it was necessary for the AAT to make sufficient findings of fact to reach its own objectively sustainable conclusion as to what percentage degree of whole person impairment should be assigned in accordance with the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">A final result was not to be reached by a process of simple deduction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">40 Counsel for Australia Post sought to support the form of reasoning used by the AAT by reference to a decision of a Full Court in Carson v Comcare [2004] FCAFC 204 ( 'Carson' ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">In Carson the Full Court said at [55] and [56]:
 
 
 '55.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">Neither before the primary judge, nor on this appeal, did the appellant identify, let alone establish, any error of law in respect of the central findings by the second AAT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">As the primary judge noted: 
 
 
 'The second AAT accepted that Dr Carson had a permanent impairment of 10 per cent, and that Dr Carson had some permanent impairment related to his workplace.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">The Tribunal regarded it as possible to "isolate the compensable effects" of the work-related injury on a pre-existing condition in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">The tribunal was ultimately "satisfied that the applicant had a permanent impairment of 5 per cent prior to suffering his compensable injury at the DSTO.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">The Tribunal is thus bound to find that the permanent impairment suffered by the applicant is only 5%".</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">' 
 
 56.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">As earlier indicated, the primary judge noted that 
 
 "On appeal, the appellant did not seek to argue that the compensable effects could not be isolated and that his injury should be treated as an aggravation that was wholly compensable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">" ' 
 
 
 
 

41 In Carson the Full Court approved the findings of the primary judge that no error of law had been demonstrated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">It is important to note, however, that the argument for the appellant in that case was that there was no pre-existing disorder/impairment, with the result that there was no foundation for suggesting that Dr Carson suffered less than 10% whole person impairment as a result of a work injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">That contention was not accepted as raising any question of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">No occasion arose, as I read the judgment, to analyse the approach taken by the AAT of deducting from a 10% whole person impairment, assigned by the Guide, an amount of 5% whole person impairment found to be due to a pre-existing condition, with the result that less than 10% remained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">42 Such an approach does not, with respect, appear to me, in any event, to have been in accordance with the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">Table 5.1 of the Guide (which was relevant to Dr Carson) provided the following indicia for the assessment of psychiatric conditions:
 
 
 '5 Despite the presence of ONE of the following is capable of performing activities of daily living without supervision or assistance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">
 

 &#8226; reactions to stressors of daily living with minor loss of personal or social efficiency 
 
 &#8226; lack of conscience directed behaviour without harm to community or self 
 
 &#8226; minor distortions of thinking 
 
 
 
 
 10 Despite the presence of MORE THAN ONE of the following is capable of performing activities of daily living without supervision or assistance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">
 

 &#8226; reactions to stressors of daily living with minor loss of personal or social efficiency 
 
 &#8226; lack of conscience directed behaviour without harm to community or self 
 
 &#8226; minor distortions of thinking.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">' 
 
 

43 It certainly seems possible that two of the three indicia of impairment might be found to be present as a result of employment injury notwithstanding that the third indicia was already present as a result of a pre-existing condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">As I read the Guide an assessment of 10% whole person impairment should still be made in such a case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">44 What is required is the assignment of a value in accordance with the Guide as a response to the assessment of work related injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">It is an error to approach the matter by attempting to assign an overall level of impairment regardless of its cause and then deduct some amount for pre-existing injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">If a value is attributed in accordance with the Guide having regard, only (as the Guide itself suggests) to work related injury no occasion will arise to embark upon the discounting exercise which was employed in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">45 In my view the AAT failed, as directed by s 43(2B) of the AAT Act to make material findings of fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">It failed to identify whether it was possible to isolate to what extent Mrs Jordan's loss of range of movement was attributable to a work related injury rather than a degenerative process of calcification and, were it possible to do so, to assess those effects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">It failed to assign a percentage value for whole person impairment in accordance with the Guide and as required by s 24(5) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">46 In my view, therefore, the AAT committed a number of errors of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">It did not, as required by s 24(5) of the Act, determine the degree of Mrs Jordan's impairment resulting from work related injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">It did not approach its task in accordance with the Guide.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">It did not give adequate reasons for its decision that Mrs Jordan's claims for compensation should be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">47 The Court is not in a position where it could substitute any view of its own for assessments which are entrusted under the Act and under the Guide to the relevant authorities and to the AAT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">48 The appropriate course is to set aside the decision of the AAT and remit the matter to the AAT for further consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">49 The whole of the matter will be remitted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">It will be within the discretion of the AAT whether further evidence is taken (see s 44(5)) of the AAT Act and Peacock v Repatriation Commission (2007) 161 FCR 256 at [24]-[26]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">I was asked by the appellant to direct that the AAT be reconstituted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">I will not do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">I see no reason to intrude upon the discretion of the President of the AAT (see s 20B of the AAT Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">50 The appellant sought her costs if successful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">No submissions to the contrary were advanced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">I can see no reason why costs should not follow the result of the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">I certify that the preceding fifty (50) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Buchanan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">Associate:

Dated: 19 December 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: D Richards 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Slater &amp; Gordon 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: R Henderson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Graham Jones Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 4 December 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 December 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2028.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>