<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gaunt v Hille [2007] FCA 2017 (18 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2017.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from local court of western australia</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">project home builder</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">collusion between builder's client and competitor builder to copy home plans</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">issue not pleaded but raised by counsel in opening and closing submissions at trial without objection</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">local court of western australia not a court of pleadings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether issue before the local court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">whether principal liable for the acts of an agent who authorised the competitor builder to copy house plans</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">whether damages for loss of profits on building contract payable in respect of breach of copyright.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">copyright</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 In 2000, the first appellant, Mr Roger Gaunt, was resident in Wales, but he wanted to move to Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">His two brothers, Mr Richard Gaunt and Mr Barry Gaunt were then resident in Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Mr Roger Gaunt purchased a block of land at The Vines, a suburb of Perth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">In December 2000, whilst visiting his brothers, he inspected a display home of the second respondent, a house builder, which trades under the name of "Atrium Homes" (Atrium).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">This display home was built in accordance with plans, drawn up by the first respondent (Mr Hille), and known as the "Lakeview" design.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Mr Roger Gaunt thought that the rooms in the display home were too small and wanted the design of the Lakeview home modified to accommodate his special requirements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Atrium entered into an agreement for the preparation of the plans with Mr Roger Gaunt pursuant to which he paid Atrium $5,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The agreement provided that Atrium retained copyright in the new plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Mr Roger Gaunt returned to Wales leaving his brother, Mr Richard Gaunt, with a power of attorney authorising Richard to contract on his behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">In accordance with the preparation of plans agreement, Atrium drew up a new set of plans, known in the proceeding below, as the "Atrium Gaunt" plans, or the "modified Lakeview design" plans, and forwarded them to Mr Richard Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">2 The Gaunts fell out with Atrium over the site costs quoted for the building of the Atrium Gaunt house.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr Roger Gaunt authorised his brother, Mr Richard Gaunt to engage a different builder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Mr Richard Gaunt approached the second appellant (Beaumonde), a competitor of Atrium, with whom he had prior dealings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Mr Richard Gaunt handed the Atrium Gaunt plans to Mr Richard Marzec, an employee of Beaumonde; and on behalf of his brother, Roger, he engaged Beaumonde to draw up plans and build the house on the site at The Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Beaumonde then copied the Atrium Gaunt plans and built the house at The Vines using those plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">3 After a trial in the Local Court of Western Australia which lasted 13 days, the Magistrate found that Mr Richard Gaunt had colluded with Mr Marzec on behalf of Beaumonde, in the copying of the plans and found that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for infringement of the copyright in the original Lakeview design and the modified Lakeview or Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The Magistrate awarded damages of $15,450 to Atrium and $1,500 to Mr Hille.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">He also awarded the respondents costs and ordered that the costs be taxed on a "non- routine" basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The Magistrate also ordered that Beaumonde, which had been joined as a third party, indemnify Mr Roger Gaunt in respect of 50% of the damages and costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">4 Mr Roger Gaunt and Beaumonde appeal against the Magistrate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The following issues arise:
 
 1 Whether the Magistrate erred in finding that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for infringement of copyright in the plans, notwithstanding that he did not copy the plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">2 Whether the Magistrate erred in finding that Atrium had copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">
 
 
 
 3 Whether the Magistrate erred in awarding damages to Atrium on the basis of the net profit it would have made had it been engaged to build the Atrium Gaunt home.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">
 
 
 
 4 Whether the Magistrate erred in making a special costs order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">
 
 
 
 5 Whether the Magistrate erred in awarding Mr Hille damages for infringement of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">
 
 

5 Mr Roger Gaunt also alleged that the Magistrate erred in ordering that Beaumonde indemnify Mr Roger Gaunt in respect of 50% of his liability for damages and costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It was contended that the Magistrate should have found that there was a separate contractual undertaking, comprised or evidenced by a letter of 25 March 2002 from Beaumonde, to indemnify Mr Roger Gaunt completely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">6 Atrium cross-appealed against the decision of the Magistrate to award Atrium damages in the sum of $15,450.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">In the alternative, Atrium said, in a notice of contention, that the Magistrate's award of damages in the sum of $15,450 should be upheld on the grounds that it reflected a loss of opportunity by Atrium to make a profit from the construction of a house at The Vines in accordance with the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">
 The basis for the liability of Mr Roger Gaunt 

7 I deal, first, with the issue of whether the Magistrate erred in finding Mr Roger Gaunt liable for infringement of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">This issue emerges from grounds 1, 2 and 3 of Mr Roger Gaunt's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">8 As previously stated, the Magistrate found that Beaumonde copied the Atrium Gaunt plans and built the house in accordance with the copied plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The Magistrate also found that there was collusion between Mr Richard Gaunt and Mr Marzec to breach copyright by Beaumonde copying the Atrium Gaunt plans and building the house in accordance with the copied plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The Magistrate found that in dealing with Mr Marzec of Beaumonde, and in handing the Atrium Gaunt plans to him, Mr Richard Gaunt acted as agent for Mr Roger Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">9 At 622 of the appeal book the Magistrate observed:
 
 I am wholly satisfied that Mr Richard Gaunt, as agent for Roger Gaunt the defendant, gave the plans as created by the second plaintiff [Atrium] to Mr Marzec, who then transferred them to the third party's [Beaumonde's] offices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">It may be true that a number of developments were made by Marzec and/or the draftsman in the office of the third party to change the plans but the evidence in the form of collusion between Richard Gaunt and Mr Marzec is overwhelming.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">This conclusion, in my view, caused the breach of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">

10 It appears that the word "conclusion" in the final sentence of the Magistrate's observations should read "collusion".</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">11 Further, at 625 of the appeal book the Magistrate observed:
 
 In this particular case I am satisfied that a substantial part of the Atrium Gaunt building has been copied by the defendant [Mr Roger Gaunt] and by the third party [Beaumonde].</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">I am further satisfied that both the defendant and third party acted in conjunction with each other given what I have said above as being the conversation between Mr Richard Gaunt and Mr Richard Marzec for the defendant and third party respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">

12 Mr Roger Gaunt contended that he was not personally involved in the dealings that took place between Mr Marzec, on behalf of Beaumonde, and Mr Richard Gaunt and, accordingly, should not have been found liable for the infringement of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Further, Mr Roger Gaunt contended the Magistrate should have found that he did not authorise the infringement of Mr Hille's or Atrium's copyright, and that he did not appoint either of his brothers as his agent with authority for either of them to sub-authorise Beaumonde to copy the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">13 Therefore, said Mr Roger Gaunt, there was no basis upon which the Magistrate could find that he had authorised the infringement of copyright under s 36(1A) of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) (the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">14 It was further submitted that a principal would only be liable for the torts of a person who was the servant or employee of the principal acting within the scope of the servant's or employee's employment; or if the principal had actually authorised the tortious conduct of the agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">It was said that Mr Roger Gaunt could not be liable because Mr Richard Gaunt was not the servant or employee of Mr Roger Gaunt, nor had Mr Roger Gaunt ever authorised his brother, Richard, to copy or to authorise the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">15 Counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt accepted that Mr Gaunt had on a number of occasions in cross-examination accepted that his brothers had authority to act, and had acted on his behalf, in dealing with Beaumonde.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">However, counsel said this did not have the consequence that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for any tort that may have been committed by his brother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Specifically counsel said:
 
 Again, that's where we say that the magistrate fell into error, with respect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">He's taken the proposition that Roger is the brother of Richard and Barry and just assumed that Roger must be responsible for whatever they did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">But Moon v Towers makes it absolutely clear that even in a father/son relationship you can't just make the leap.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">

16 Counsel referred to the following observations by Willies J in the case of Moon v Towers (1860) 8 CB(NS) 611 (141 ER 1306) ( Moon v Towers ):
 
 I am not aware of any such relation between a father and son...as will make the acts of the son more binding upon the father than the acts of anybody else...No man ought, as a general rule, to be responsible for acts not his own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In the present case, it is clear that the young man had no prior authority from his father to take the steps he did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">And it is equally clear to mind that the father, when informed of what his son had done, did not intend to make the acts of his son his own by any ratification.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">

17 In any event, said Mr Roger Gaunt, it was not open to the Magistrate to find that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for any torts committed by Mr Richard Gaunt as agent for Mr Roger Gaunt, because no case to that effect had been pleaded, nor was the case conducted on that basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Mr Roger Gaunt said that the case which had been run at trial was confined to a claim that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable because he had authorised the infringing conduct within the meaning s 36(1A) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">18 Beaumonde supported these submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">19 In my view, the Magistrate's judgment is to be read as a finding that Mr Richard Gaunt authorised Mr Marzec, on behalf of Beaumonde, to copy the Atrium Gaunt plans, and that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for the infringement of copyright because Mr Richard Gaunt was acting within the scope of his authority in committing the tort of authorising the infringement of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">It was, in my view, open to the Magistrate to come to the view that he did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">20 First, for liability to attach to Mr Roger Gaunt, it was not necessary for the Magistrate to find that Mr Roger Gaunt had authorised Mr Richard Gaunt to authorise the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">It is sufficient to find that the tortious acts were committed in the course of Mr Richard Gaunt executing the agency granted him by his brother, Mr Roger Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">In the case of Sweeney v Boylan Nominees Pty Limited [2006] HCA 19 ; (2006) 226 CLR 161, the High Court in the joint judgment made the following observations regarding the case of Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 170, at [22]:
 
 Colonial Mutual Life establishes that if an independent contractor is engaged to solicit the bringing about of legal relations between the principal who engages the contractor and third parties, the principal will be held liable for slanders uttered to persuade the third party to make an agreement with the principal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">It is a conclusion that depends directly upon the identification of the independent contractor as the principal's agent (properly so called) and the recognition that the conduct of which complaint is made was conduct undertaken in the course of, and for the purpose of, executing that agency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">

21 In my view, these comments are apposite to the relationship of Mr Richard Gaunt as agent, and Mr Roger Gaunt as principal, in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">22 It was not in dispute at trial that Mr Roger Gaunt had authorised Mr Richard Gaunt to enter into legal relations, namely to contract, on his behalf, with Beaumonde to construct a house on the site at The Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">In para 17 of their particulars of claim, Mr Hille and Atrium pleaded:
 
 At a time unknown to the Plaintiffs, the Defendant [Mr Roger Gaunt] authorised the construction of a two storey brick and tile house on the Site by a different builder ("the House").</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">

23 This allegation was admitted in Mr Roger Gaunt's particulars of defence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Further, in para 6 of Mr Roger Gaunt's amended particulars of claim against Beaumonde, as third party, Mr Gaunt pleaded that:
 
 In or around June 2001 the Defendant [Mr Roger Gaunt], through his agents, engaged the Third Party [Beaumonde] to construct on the site a house on a modified version of the San Marino design ("the House").</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">

24 
 
Further, the evidence was that Mr Roger Gaunt had signed a power of attorney in favour of his brother Richard, that authorised Mr Richard Gaunt to contract with third parties on his behalf; and that Richard, in reliance on that power of attorney had, on behalf of his brother, entered into the preparation of plans agreement with Beaumonde dated 9 May 2001, and the undated construction agreement with Beaumonde.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">25 Also, in his evidence-in-chief Mr Roger Gaunt said that he had a conversation with Mr Bill Marcolina, the Managing Director of Atrium, during which he told Mr Marcolina that he intended to terminate his relationship with Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">He then said at 282 of the appeal book:
 
 So, I rang my brother Richard and I said to him, "Right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">We're finished with Bill.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">We are not going to do any more work with Bill.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Sign on another builder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">" So then Beaumonde came into it then.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">

26 Further, in re-examination Mr Roger Gaunt said at 345 of the appeal book:
 
 So would your brothers have your authority to commence arrangements with another builder without speaking to you?---Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">They was acting on my behalf, they were.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Whatever they did I accept.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">

27 In cross-examination of Mr Roger Gaunt by counsel for Beaumonde, Mr Gaunt said at 347 of the appeal book:
 
 Just to clarify that last answer, you were referring to Richard Gaunt - - ?---Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">- - not Richard Marzec?---Doing - - but Richard Gaunt was acting on my behalf talking to Richard Marzec.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">That's right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">Yes?---Yeah.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">And you were saying you accept the consequences of your brother acting on your authority?---Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">

28 In my view, the position of Mr Richard Gaunt was one of an agent, "properly so called" - in the sense that he was a person who was authorised by Mr Roger Gaunt to enter into contractual relations, on Mr Roger Gaunt's behalf, with a third party builder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">The scope of the authority was to engage a builder to prepare plans and construct a residence at the site at The Vines in accordance with those plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">It was in the course of executing that agency that Mr Richard Gaunt colluded with Beaumonde in the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">29 In my view, the observations referred to by counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt from the case of Moon v Towers , have no application to the facts in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">The Magistrate's decision was not based on the fact that there was a close family relationship between Mr Roger Gaunt and Mr Richard Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The decision was based on the fact that Mr Richard Gaunt was the agent "properly so called" to contract with, on behalf of his brother, a third party builder to prepare plans, and construct a residence at the site at The Vines in accordance with those plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">30 I now deal with the submission that it was not open to the Magistrate to reach the decision he did, because the "agency" case (referred to during argument as the "vicarious liability" case) was not before the court below.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">31 In my view, by reason of the matters referred to at [22] to [23] above, it was open on the pleadings alone for the Magistrate to find that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for the tort of Mr Richard Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">However, even if that was not the case, it is apparent that the case was conducted on the basis that it was not in dispute that Mr Roger Gaunt had authorised Mr Richard Gaunt to negotiate and contract with Beaumonde in relation to the construction of the house at The Vines and that he was responsible for Mr Richard Gaunt's actions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">The Local Court of Western Australia is not a court of pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">However, even if it was, by reason of the parties having conducted the case on the basis that Mr Richard Gaunt was authorised by Mr Roger Gaunt to find and contract with a third party builder on his behalf, it was open to the Magistrate to find that Mr Roger Gaunt was liable for the conduct of Mr Richard Gaunt in relation to the infringement of the copyright in respect of the Atrium Gaunt plans ( Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658).</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">However, even if I was wrong in this respect, the factual foundation on which the trial was conducted, would permit the Court on appeal to uphold the Magistrate's decision ( Ravinder Rohini Pty Ltd v Krizaic (1991) 30 FCR 300 at 314-315).</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">32 Because of these findings, it is not necessary for me to decide whether leave should be given to Atrium and Mr Hille to amend their notice of contention to contend that the Magistrate's decision should be upheld on the alternative basis that Mr Roger Gaunt had ratified the tortious conduct of Mr Richard Gaunt and Beaumonde.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Had it been necessary to do so, I would have allowed the amendment to the notice of contention, and upheld the contention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">
 The basis of Atrium's claim to copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans 

33 The next issue arises from grounds 4 to 8 of Mr Roger Gaunt's grounds of appeal, and grounds 1 to 5 of Beaumonde's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">34 Atrium and Mr Hille pleaded that Mr Hille had granted Atrium an exclusive licence in the modified Lakeview design pursuant to a written agreement dated 10 June 1996.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">There was no alternative claim pleaded that Atrium was the owner of copyright in the modified Lakeview design or Atrium Gaunt plans, in its own right by reason of the scope of the modifications that it made to the original Lakeview design.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">35 The Magistrate found that Atrium had carried out a "significant amount of work" in relation to the drafting of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">The Magistrate referred to the case of Ladbroke (Football) v William Hill (Football) Ltd [1964] 1 WLR 273 at 289 and concluded that, by reason of the original work undertaken by Atrium in relation to the Atrium Gaunt plans, it had copyright in those plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">The Magistrate also found that the Atrium Gaunt plans were derived from the Lakeview design plans, in which Mr Hille owned the copyright, and that the copyright of Mr Hille in the Lakeview design plans had also been infringed by the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">36 The appellants contended that because Atrium did not plead that it had copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans by reason of the original work that it had undertaken, it was not open to the Magistrate to come to that finding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">It was said that the Magistrate's finding was "manifestly unfair" because it was not the case run by Atrium and Mr Hille at the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">Beaumonde contended that it was denied procedural fairness because the basis upon which the Magistrate found that Atrium owned the copyright was not "fully ventilated and tested" at trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">Beaumonde submitted that it was prejudiced because it did not cross-examine Mr Marcolina as to the substantiality of the modification in the Atrium Gaunt plans, it did not explore the question of the employment status of the draftsman of the modifications and it did not make a Jones v Dunkel submission at trial in relation to the failure to call the draftsman of the modifications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">Mr Roger Gaunt supported Beaumonde's submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">37 In support of its submissions Beaumonde relied, in particular, upon the case of Garden City Wallpaper and Curtain Centre Pty Ltd v Barenfar Pty Ltd (unreported, Full Court, Supreme Court of Western Australia, Kennedy, Franklyn and Walsh JJ, 18 September 1998) ( Garden City ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">38 At trial, in his written opening submissions, counsel for Atrium and Mr Hille, referred to the "original work" contention in respect of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Paragraph 6 of the relevant submissions which were submitted at the commencement of the trial in September 2004 was to the following effect:
 
 The fact that the Atrium Gaunt derives in part from earlier drawings does not prevent the Atrium Gaunt being a separate original artistic work attracting copyright protection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">Sufficient labour, skill and expertise was expended in the production of the Atrium Gaunt and accordingly it is afforded its own copyright protection: LB (Plastics) Ltd v Swish Products Ltd [1979] RPC 551 at 569.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">

39 During closing submissions counsel for Atrium and Mr Hille said:
 
 Your worship pleases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">Let me firstly deal with the law, then I'll move to the evidence and the facts and then address you on damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">Your Worship has submissions by the plaintiffs that were submitted in September 2004 at the commencement of the trial, and in particular I draw your attention to paragraph 6, where we say the fact that Atrium/Gaunt derives in part from earlier drawings does not prevent the Atrium/Gaunt being a separate original artistic work attracting copyright protection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">Sufficient labour, skill and expertise was extended in the production of the Atrium/Gaunt and, accordingly, it's afforded its own copyright protection .</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">And we quote the case of LD Plastics v Swish Products as our authority for that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">In response to the proposition that the plaintiffs do not have a claim, the claim of the first plaintiff cannot be denied under any circumstances because in his own right, Mr Greg Hille has a right to claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">He has also said that he was the author of the Vanessa and the Lakeview, and that's not been contradicted, and we've heard evidence that the Atrium/Gaunt was a derivative of the Lakeview.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">So there's no question about Greg Hille having a pathway to his claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">The pathway of Atrium via exhibit 16, which your Worship has had attention drawn to, and also, as I have just indicated, via its own independent claim to the original artistic work that occurs in the Atrium/Gaunt which is the Exhibit 17.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">

40 At the trial of the matter before the Magistrate, each party was represented by counsel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Neither counsel for Beaumonde, nor counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt objected, at the commencement of the trial that the written opening submissions of counsel for Atrium and Mr Hille were beyond the scope of the pleaded case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Nor did either counsel seek an adjournment to permit such arrangements to be made as may be necessary to meet the case referred to in the written opening submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">41 Further, neither counsel for Beaumonde, nor counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt objected, when counsel for Atrium and Mr Hille made the closing submissions referred to in [39] above, that he or she was taken by surprise or that the case being advanced was beyond the scope of the pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Nor did either counsel apply for leave to re-open their respective cases, or for any witnesses to be recalled, or to call other witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">42 As previously mentioned, the Local Court was not a court of pleadings (s 41 of the Local Court Act 1904 (WA)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">However, ordinary principles of procedural fairness required that each of the parties be aware of the case that it had to meet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">In the case of Re R H Burton; Ex parte Steven Burns t/as Burns Corporation , (unreported, Full Court, Supreme Court of Western Australia, Malcolm CJ, Pidgeon and Steytler JJ, 6 February 1998), Malcolm CJ (Pidgeon and Steytler JJ agreeing) referred to the requirement to advise the other party of the case to be met, in circumstances where pleadings were not required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">Malcolm CJ observed at 18-19:
 
 The requirement that a respondent be given notice of the case against him or her does not need to be satisfied by way of pleadings or where there is a hearing, by way of an opening of the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">The necessary notice of the case may be given by the application itself, by the written material submitted in support of the application or orally at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">

43 In my view, the appellants were sufficiently advised by the opening submissions and the closing submissions of the case being advanced to satisfy the requirements of natural justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">Each of the appellants was legally represented and it was open to each of the appellants to make an application for an adjournment in the event that they were unable to meet the case referred to in the opening and closing submissions, or were otherwise taken by surprise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">44 
 
In any event, even if the Local Court was a court of pleadings, it would not now be open to the appellants to complain that the case advanced by Atrium was outside the scope of the pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">This is because the case was conducted, without objection by the appellants, on the basis advanced by counsel for Atrium and Mr Hille in his opening and closing submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">45 In my view, the following observations of the High Court in the case of Laws Holdings Pty Ltd v Short (1972) 46 ALJR 563 at 572 ( Laws ) are apposite to this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">In that case, the question of estoppel was first raised by the trial judge during the closing address of counsel for the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Counsel for the appellant did not raise any objection that the respondents' pleading might not be adequate to raise a plea of estoppel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">Nor did counsel seek an adjournment or seek to re-open the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">On appeal, it was contended that the trial judge should not have given effect to a finding of estoppel because the question of estoppel was not raised by the pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">At 572 Gibbs J observed:
 
 However, when the question of estoppel was raised counsel for the appellant made no effort to re-open the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">In my opinion the appellant cannot now complain that the facts were not fully explored when, knowing that estoppel was in issue, it's counsel made no attempt at the trial to obtain further evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">If the appellant's counsel had then requested an opportunity to recall any of the witnesses, or to call further witnesses, I would have viewed the matter in a different light.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">However, in the circumstances, it seems to me that the appellant ought not now be allowed to complain of the defect in the pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">

46 In this case, there were two opportunities for counsel for each of the appellants to complain or object to the case being put in opening and closing on a basis which was not pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">However, counsel did not avail themselves of that opportunity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">As Gibbs J said in Laws , the circumstances may have been different had counsel made a complaint at the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">47 The Garden City case relied upon by the appellants is distinguishable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">48 First, the Garden City case involved a trial in the Supreme Court of Western Australia deciding a case alleging a contravention of s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) on the basis of misleading or deceptive conduct which had not been pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">The Supreme Court of Western Australia is a court of pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">49 Secondly, in Garden City the trial judge decided the case on a basis which had not been advanced by either party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">50 At 10, Franklyn J observed:
 
 As I understand it, neither party was alerted to His Honour's decision to rely upon the unpleaded case, that becoming apparent only when his reasons for decision were published.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">

51 At 15, Franklyn J, after having referred to a passage in the judgement of the trial judge, said:
 
 In my view the quoted passage again demonstrates that the unpleaded case was not clearly before the court and specifically not apparent to the parties during the course of the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">

52 Further, Franklyn J said at 17 that:
 
 The case identified by His Honour, either as the "unpleaded case" or the alternative to which I have referred, was not so identified by respondent's counsel at trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">

53 In this case, in contrast to Garden City , both in opening and closing submissions, counsel for Atrium identified a claim to copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans, based on original work by modification made to the original Lakeview design plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">54 Further, there are contentions in the grounds of appeal that Mr Hille had not granted an exclusive licence to Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">It was said that the agreement relied upon by Atrium and Mr Hille fell short of being an exclusive licence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">It was, so the appellants said, no more than an "unexercised option".</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">Submissions in support of, and opposing, these contentions were also made by counsel for the appellants and the respondents respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">However, I accept counsel for Beaumonde's submission that the Magistrate did not base his decision on any findings in relation to the claim founded on the grant of an exclusive licence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">Accordingly, in my view, the contentions in the grounds of appeal and the submissions addressing these contentions were misdirected, and irrelevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">55 For the reasons set out above, I dismiss grounds 1 to 5 of Beaumonde's grounds of appeal and grounds 4 to 8 of Mr Roger Gaunt's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">56 In ground 6 of Beaumonde's grounds of appeal, Beaumonde contended that the Magistrate erred in fact and in law in finding that Atrium was the owner of the copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans when there was no evidence that the draftsman of the plans was an employee of Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">57 In my view, it was open to the Magistrate to conclude that Atrium was the owner of the copyright by reason of the original work undertaken by Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">58 First, there was no issue on the pleadings that the Atrium Gaunt plans had been prepared by anyone other than Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">Thus, para 13 of Atrium's particulars of claim pleaded that, pursuant to the terms of the preparation of plans agreement and in consideration of the $5,000, Atrium "prepared drawings specifications plans and estimates".</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">By para 2 of the particulars of amended defence, Mr Roger Gaunt admitted that plea.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">In my view, this was a sufficient basis for the Magistrate, once he determined that the modifications to the Lakeview design plans entailed original work, to decide that Atrium was the owner of the copyright in the modified plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">59 Secondly, and in any event, in evidence Mr Bill Marcolina, the Managing Director of Atrium, drew a distinction between the position of Mr Hille as an external contractor, and his "in-house drafting department" which comprised Mr Oliver Standing as the senior draftsperson and, at the relevant time, two or three other draftspersons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">Mr Marcolina also deposed that he believed the modifications had been done "in-house".</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">As previously stated, there was no cross-examination directed towards contesting the status of the "in-house" draftpersons as employees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">60 Accordingly, I dismiss ground 6 of Beaumonde's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Atrium's damages 
 
61 Each of Mr Roger Gaunt (ground of appeal 12) and Beaumonde (ground of appeal 7) complained that the Magistrate erred in awarding damages to Atrium on the basis of a loss of net profit that Atrium would have made from building the house in accordance with the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">62 The Magistrate said that, in awarding damages, he would follow the reasoning of her Honour Judge Kennedy in Delstrat Pty Ltd v Bond [2004] WADC 55 ( Delstrat ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">The Magistrate observed as follows:
 
 In that case Her Honour ordered damages based on the assessment of the builder's loss of profit flowing from the owner's failure to engage the builder to construct the infringing dwelling.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">Her Honour considered:
 
 
 1) The flagrancy of the infringement; 
 
 
 
 2) The plaintiff's artistic skills, work and expenses in preparing the initial design;
 
 3) That the plaintiff was a builder and experienced high levels of overhead costs;
 
 4) That by not constructing the infringing dwelling the plaintiff had lost exposure in the marketplace due to the history of featuring his work in advertising;
 
 5) That the artistic work infringed by the defendants in that case included fully developed plans according to the contour and position of the particular block and including the elevations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">
 
 In this case it is clear that the defendant gave the full working drawings of the modified Lakeview house to the third party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">The third party in my view used those plans to develop the Beaumonde Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">The Beaumonde Gaunt was built in exactly the same situation as the plaintiff's site plan showed and a substantial part of the Atrium Gaunt was in fact reproduced by both the defendant and the third party acting in conjunction with each other.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">

63 The Magistrate went on to say:
 
 In terms of damages which flows from that breach I am satisfied that amounts should be fixed at 25% of $225,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">To that sum there should be a further reduction of 10% of that sum for the overheads such as advertising costs, schedules etc. Those losses fixed at 25% of $225,000 less the overheads is said to be $25,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">In respect of the damages I am of the view that they should be fixed at 15% which is the net profit obtainable by the second plaintiff according to Mr Hans Jorgen Sphan which I estimate as 15% of $225,000 that sum being $15,450.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">Accordingly I make that award.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">I do not make any award in relation to damages for flagrancy of the breach of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">In respect of the claim therefore, I am satisfied that the defendant is liable for the breach of copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">I am further satisfied that the defendant was well aware through his agents of the dangers of using plans as supplied by the second plaintiff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">I am further satisfied that the defendant and third party were well aware of the dangers of breach of copyright, they having discussed it very early on in their negotiations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">The plaintiff's case is therefore made out against the defendant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">In respect of the indemnity sought by the defendant against the third party I am satisfied that such an indemnity should extend as to 50% of the defendant's liability.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">Both the defendant and third party should be liable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">The third party should pay an indemnity of 50% of the damages to the second plaintiff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">In regards to the first plaintiff's claim I am satisfied that he should be paid damages in the sum of $1500 for breach of copyright of his original plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">

64 Mr Roger Gaunt and Beaumonde contended that the Magistrate erred in awarding damages on the basis of a net profit that Atrium would have made had Mr Roger Gaunt engaged Atrium to construct the residence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">This was because on the evidence, Mr Roger Gaunt would not have contracted with Atrium for the construction of the house at The Vines, because he had fallen out with Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">It followed, said the appellants, that Atrium did not lose any profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">It also followed that, insofar as damages may be awarded on the basis of the loss of opportunity to build the house and obtain exposure in the market place, the loss of opportunity ought to be assessed as very small.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">65 It was also contended that the Magistrate erred in failing to take into account when awarding damages, that Mr Roger Gaunt had paid a fee of $5,000 to Atrium under the preparation of plans agreement, that Atrium would have been liable to pay Mr Hille a fee in respect of the use of Mr Hille's copyright in the plans which were modified by Atrium, and that Atrium's copyright arose from copying and modifying the Lakeview design plans in respect of which Mr Hille held the copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">66 The respondent, Atrium, cross-appealed, contending that in awarding damages to Atrium in the sum of $15,450, the Magistrate had made an arithmetical error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">It was contended by Atrium that the Magistrate intended to award Atrium damages comprising 15% of $222,500.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">This would amount to the sum of $33,750 - which would exceed the $25,000 jurisdictional limit of the Local Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">Accordingly, Atrium claims $25,000 by way of damages by way of its cross-appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">67 Atrium has also filed a notice of contention, contending, as an alternative, that the actual award of $15,450 should be affirmed on the basis that the infringement by Mr Roger Gaunt caused Atrium to lose the opportunity of being engaged by Mr Roger Gaunt to construct the dwelling and earn profits there from.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">68 Clause 2(a) of the preparation of plans agreement with Atrium provided that no transfer of ownership of the copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans to Mr Roger Gaunt occurred by reason of payment of $5,000 under that agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">69 Further, the agreement also had provision for the parties to agree a fee which would be payable as a licence fee in the event that Mr Roger Gaunt decided not to use Atrium for the construction of the residence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">However, the space for the inclusion of such a fee was left blank by the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">70 The agreement also provided, in effect, that if Mr Roger Gaunt proceeded to engage Atrium to construct the dwelling, then the (unspecified) copyright licence fee otherwise payable by Mr Roger Gaunt to Atrium for the use of the Atrium Gaunt plans, was deemed to be incorporated in the building contract price.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">71 In Sutherland Publishing Co Ltd v Caxton Publishing Co Ltd [1936] 1 Ch 323 at 336, Lord Wright MR said that the measure of damages in a copyright case is "the depreciation caused by the infringement to the value of the copyright as a chose in action".</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">72 In Autodesk Australia Pty Ltd v Cheung (1990) 94 ALR 472 at 475 ( Autodesk ), Wilcox J observed that Lord Wright's formulation had to be -
 
 "applied with caution because it is potentially misleading.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">It will usually be difficult, often impossible, for a copyright owner to establish that a particular unauthorised reproduction has caused a diminution in the capital value of a copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">

73 He went on to say:
 
 No doubt, it is because of these matters that judicial warnings have sometimes been given against applying Lord Wright's test too literally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">Thus in Interfirm Comparison (Australia) Pty Ltd v Law Society of New South Wales (1975) 6 ALR 445 Bowen CJ in Eq commented at 446 that it would be wrong to treat the measure of damages stated by Lord Wright as "having, in effect, the force and rigidity of statutory provision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">The purpose of damages is to compensate the plaintiff for the loss which he has suffered as a result of the defendant's breach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">It would, in my opinion, be wrong to regard it as the exclusive measure of damages for breach of copyright appropriate to all circumstances".</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">

74 In my view, the Magistrate erred in his approach to the awarding of compensatory damages on the basis of the loss of profit that Atrium would have earned had it been awarded the contract by Mr Roger Gaunt to build the residence at The Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">75 That measure of damages failed to take account of the fact that Mr Roger Gaunt was under no obligation to engage Atrium for the construction of the house.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">In my view, this is a case where damages should be assessed as being at large and I should award the "amount I think right as if I were a jury".</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">76 In the case of Autodesk , the respondent, Mr Cheung, imported and distributed "pirate" copies of computer programs free of charge to purchasers of computer hardware sold by the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">The court had to determine the quantum of damages which should be awarded to the applicant copyright owners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">Counsel for the respondent contended that there was no reason to believe that Mr Cheung would have acquired all of the infringing computer programs from the applicants had he been required to do so at normal cost.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">Accordingly, so it was contended, it could not be said that the applicants had been deprived of sales of this number of programs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">Wilcox J referred to the "licence fee" approach to the assessment of damages and at 476-477, he observed:
 
 The approach has the attraction of precision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">In a case where the court may infer that, presented with a choice of paying the licence fee and not using the work, the infringer would have paid the licence fee, the approach is also a logical one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">Ex hypothesi the copyright owner has been deprived of a licence fee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">But, where this inference cannot be drawn, it is much more difficult to say that the damage sustained by the copyright owner is equal to a licence fee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">No assumption can be made that, if forced to obtain a licence, the defendant would have copied the work or copied it to the same extent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">

77 Wilcox J went on to say at 477:
 
 I am not convinced that the activities of Mr Cheung, in relation to the programs found in his possession at the time of search, had the effect of depriving the applicants of the particular sums of money which they claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">It is probable that his activities cost them some sales, because some customers he supplied with AutoCAD programs would otherwise have purchased programs from the applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">But that loss relates to the supply of programs before the date of the search.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">It has nothing to do with the number of programs which happened to be in Mr Cheung's premises at the time of the search.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">Under the circumstances, it is not logical to apply the "licence fee" approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">However unsatisfactory that course may seem, the court must treat the damages as being "at large", in the words of Horridge J in Fenning Film Service Ltd v Wolverhampton, Walsall &amp; District Cinemas Ltd [1914] 3 KB 1171 at 1174, giving "what amount I think right as if I were a jury".</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">So approaching the matter, and bearing in mind that Autodesk Australia would have suffered a greater financial loss from foregone sales than Autodesk Inc, I allow compensatory damages of $15,000, comprising $10,000 to Autodesk Australia and $5000 to Autodesk Inc.
 

78 The case of Chabot v Davies [1936] 3 All ER 221, has some similarities to this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">In that case, at the request of the defendants the plaintiff, a designer and fitter of shopfronts, submitted plans to the defendants for the renovation of the front of their shop in Camden High Street.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">Along with the plans, the plaintiff submitted a quotation of &#8356;406 7s for undertaking the renovation work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">However, the defendants did not engage the plaintiff to carry out the renovation work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">Instead, the defendants engaged a different builder and provided him with the plaintiff's plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">The second builder renovated the shopfront in accordance with traced copies of the plans drawn up by the plaintiff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">The trial judge found that there had been an infringement of the plaintiff's copyright in the plans and said that damages were at large.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">The trial judge came to the view that, in the circumstances, the amount that would have been payable as a licence fee under the scale of the Royal Institute of British Architects, being &#8356;52, was inadequate to compensate the plaintiff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">The trial judge awarded damages in the sum of 100 guineas as being reasonable remuneration for the work of the plaintiff.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">This amount was about 25% of the quoted price for carrying out the work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">79 In the case of Meikle v Maufe [1941] 3 All ER 144 ( Meikle ), the defendant architect was engaged by a building owner to design renovations to its building which had originally been designed by the plaintiff architect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">The defendant's design incorporated some features of the original building design.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">The court held that the defendant architect infringed the plaintiff architect's copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">Prior to awarding the contract for the design of the extensions, the owner of the building had decided against engaging the plaintiff architect in favour of engaging the defendant architect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">However, the fact that the owner had deliberately decided not to award the contract to the plaintiff architect, did not preclude the court from awarding the plaintiff architect damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">The court applied the observations of Horridge J in Fenning Film Service Ltd v Wolverhampton, Walsall &amp; District Cinemas Ltd [1914] 3 KB 1171 at 1174 (referred to by Wilcox J in Autodesk at [77] above) and found that damages were at large.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">However, the court rejected an argument that it should award the plaintiff architect the profits it would have earned had it been appointed as architect for the carrying out of extensions to the existing building.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">The court said that in assessing damages, it was entitled "to take into account all the surrounding circumstances in exactly the same way as one is entitled to do in the case of the invasion of a common law right of property".</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">80 Like the court in Meikle and in Delstrat , I am of the view that, the fact that there was evidence that Mr Roger Gaunt would not have contracted with Atrium, does not preclude me from awarding damages at large.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">In assessing damages at large as a jury, I take into account the following surrounding circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">81 First, the preparation of plans agreement did not provide that the Atrium Gaunt plans would be available to be used by another builder on the instruction of Mr Roger Gaunt, on the payment of a licence fee to Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">This is to be inferred from the fact that the parties left that part of the standard form of agreement blank.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">82 Secondly, Atrium was not in the same position as an independent draftsman whose business is comprised primarily of the drawing up of plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">Instead, Atrium, like other project home builders, provided an integrated service of both drawing up plans and building houses in accordance with standard plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">The price of the house reflects this standardised approach to house design and construction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">To that end, Atrium and other project home builders incur costs including the building and marketing of display homes which would not be incurred by a business comprising only a drawing office.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">83 Thirdly, Mr Roger Gaunt elected to approach a project builder to build his residence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">The Atrium Gaunt plans were created and transferred into the possession of Mr Richard Gaunt as agent for Mr Roger Gaunt, pursuant to a business model founded on an expectation that, the plans would be used by Mr Roger Gaunt as part of a further contractual arrangement, which would include the consideration for the use of the plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">By authorising breach of Atrium's copyright, Mr Richard Gaunt, on behalf of his brother, defeated the expectation that underlay the production and the delivery to him of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">This was conduct which undermined the business model on which Atrium's business was based, and thereby, caused harm to Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">84 Fourthly, I take into account the fact that Mr Roger Gaunt paid $5,000 under the preparation for plans agreement, but place little weight on this fact, because it was not intended to comprise consideration for the right to use Atrium's copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">There were a number of other services which Atrium had provided in the course of producing plans specifically designed for Mr Roger Gaunt's site at The Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">85 Fifthly, Mr Roger Gaunt was under a time constraint within which to commence building his house.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">Also, Mr Roger Gaunt preferred the Atrium Gaunt design to that of the San Marino design, which was the competitive design offered by Beaumonde.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">There was therefore, in my view, a chance that had Beaumonde not agreed to collude in the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans, Mr Roger Gaunt would have been required to, and would have, reconsidered his decision not to proceed with Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">However, Atrium was deprived of this chance by the infringing conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">86 Sixthly, the anticipated profit of $33,370 would serve as a limit on the amount that may be awarded by way of damages at large.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">This is because $33,370 reflects the profit likely to be obtained on completion of the total project, with the attendant work and risk.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">Therefore, the amount payable by way of damages at large would be substantially less than $33,370.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">87 In my view, $9,500 is an appropriate award of damages at large taking into account the surrounding circumstances referred to above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">88 Accordingly, I uphold in part the appellants' appeal on this ground.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">I also dismiss Atrium's cross-appeal and contention, although in respect of the contention I have accepted that Atrium's loss of a chance is a relevant surrounding circumstance in assessing damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">
 The costs order 

89 The Magistrate made an order that the costs of the "matter be taxed on the non-routine scale".</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">90 Each of Mr Roger Gaunt (ground of appeal 13) and Beaumonde (grounds of appeal 9 and 10) complained that the Magistrate erred in making this special costs order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">At the hearing, however, Beaumonde abandoned its grounds of appeal on this issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">91 Mr Roger Gaunt submitted in support of his ground of appeal, that the trial was not sufficiently complex to warrant the making of a special costs order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">The making of a special costs order was a matter within the discretion of the presiding Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">In this case, the trial lasted for 13 days, each of the parties was represented by counsel and there was complex legal argument in respect of a matter, namely breach of copyright, which is not a routine matter in the Local Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">On the basis of these matters, it was open to the Magistrate, in the exercise of his discretion, to make an order that the costs be taxed on a non-routine basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">92 I, accordingly, dismiss Mr Roger Gaunt's ground of appeal 13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">
 Whether Mr Hille was a copyright owner 

93 Mr Roger Gaunt, in grounds 9 and 10 of his notice of appeal, contended that the Magistrate erred in determining that there had been an infringement of Mr Hille's copyright by the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans because Mr Hille was not the author of the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">It was contended that it was not possible for both Atrium and Mr Hille to be owners of copyright in the Atrium Gaunt plans.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">94 In my view, these grounds of appeal should be dismissed because they misread the finding of the Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">The Magistrate has found that Mr Hille was the copyright owner of the earlier Lakeview design which was modified to produce the Atrium Gaunt plans, and that it was Mr Hille's copyright in the earlier Lakeview plans which was indirectly infringed by the copying of the Atrium Gaunt plans by Beaumonde.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">Whilst there is no direct composite statement by the Magistrate in these terms in the judgment, this conclusion is obvious from a number of separate findings made at different places in the judgment and by his award of damages to Mr Hille.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">That was a finding which was open to the Magistrate to make.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">He had the Lakeview plans and the Atrium Gaunt plans before him, and was able to assess the extent to which the Atrium Gaunt plans reproduced Mr Hille's Lakeview design.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">(See Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd v Henley Arch Pty Ltd (1998) 46 IPR 309 at 312-313.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">)
 
95 I dismiss grounds 9 and 10 of Mr Roger Gaunt's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">96 Further, Beaumonde, in its ground of appeal 8, contended that the Magistrate erred in awarding any damages to Mr Hille as there was no finding of infringement of Mr Hille's copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">I reject this ground for the reasons set out in [94] above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">
 Beaumonde's letter of 25 March 2002 

97 The Magistrate made orders, in the third party proceedings, that Beaumonde pay 50% of the damages and costs awarded against Mr Roger Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">98 In ground 11 of his notice of appeal, Mr Roger Gaunt contended that the Magistrate failed to consider properly his "claim against Beaumonde, in particular, the letter dated 25 March 2002 from Beaumonde to Atrium".</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">99 Although it is not expressly stated in the ground of appeal, I understand Mr Roger Gaunt's contention to be that the Magistrate should have found that there was a contract of indemnity between Mr Roger Gaunt, through his brother Richard, and Beaumonde, which was comprised or evidenced by a letter dated 25 March 2002 from Beaumonde to Atrium.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">100 The letter dated 25 March 2002, written by Mr Greg Cowie of Beaumonde to Atrium, reads as follows:
 
 It is disappointing that you still wish to pursue the matter concerning the copyright issue against our client, Mr Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">We believe Mr Gaunt had no intention of copying your display home when he approached Beaumonde Homes to design his home at No 431 Barbera Lanes, The Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">Mr Gaunt had no definite ideas on his requirements for his new home for which Atrium Homes converted one of your display homes to suit his needs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">For one reason or another, he did not proceed to build with Atrium Homes and engaged Beaumonde Homes to change one of our display homes to suit his specific needs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">As this home in question was a Beaumonde Homes display with changes and thus Beaumonde Homes copyright, we have no choice but to defend the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">If you still wish to proceed with Court action, we request that all correspondence be directed to Elio Galante, C/O Beaumonde Homes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">

101 The face of the letter records that a copy was sent to "Mr Gaunt".</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">102 Counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt said that this claim of a contractual indemnity by Beaumonde was not pleaded but was alleged in his counsel's opening at the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">103 In my view, the Magistrate did not err in failing to consider a claim associated with the letter of 25 March 2002, in determining the extent to which Beaumonde should indemnify Mr Roger Gaunt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">This is because there was no case run at trial based upon a separate contractual indemnity comprised by, or evidenced by, the letter of 25 March 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">104 First, counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt was correct in conceding that a claim based on a separate indemnity undertaking comprised by, or evidenced by, the letter of 25 March 2002 was not pleaded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">However, counsel's submission that such a claim was identified in the opening of Mr Roger Gaunt's case against Beaumonde at trial cannot be accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">In my view, counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt did not open Mr Gaunt's claim against Beaumonde on any basis which went beyond that of the pleaded case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">This is apparent from the following extract of the trial transcript which records the opening of the third party case by counsel for Mr Roger Gaunt (who was not counsel in the appeal):
 
 Your Worship, the defendant's position is as stated in his amended defence and the amended statement of claim against the third parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">...
 
 [H]e claims that if he is by any chance liable to the plaintiffs then the loss and damage that has been caused to him, he claims that infringement was because of the third party and that the third party should indemnify him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">

105 Secondly, although Mr Roger Gaunt and Mr Richard Gaunt gave evidence that Beaumonde had said that it would "take care of" Atrium's allegation as to copying the Atrium Gaunt plans, and that this was recorded in a letter from Beaumonde, they did not regard the letter of 25 March 2002 as containing that assurance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">Rather, they referred to and relied upon a letter of 15 June 2002 which was addressed directly to Mr Richard Gaunt by Beaumonde (exhibit 44 at the trial).</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">106 
 
Thirdly, and in any event, there was no consideration identified to support the contractual indemnity relied upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">107 Accordingly, I would dismiss ground 11 of Mr Roger Gaunt's grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">108 I will hear the parties on costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">I certify that the preceding one hundred and eight (108) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Siopis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">Associate:

Dated: 18 December 2007


 Counsel for the First Appellant: 
 K G Robson 
 
 Solicitor for the First Appellant: 
 Pinnington and Associates 
 
 Counsel for the Second Appellant: 
M D Cuerden 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Appellant 
Griffiths &amp; Godecke 
 
 Counsel for the First and Second Respondents: 
 J T Schoombee 
 
 Solicitor for the First and Second Respondents: 
 G V Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 22 and 23 March 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 December 2007 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2017.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>