<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wotton v Queensland [2007] FCA 280 (2 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/280.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">ex parte application for interim injunction under s 46pp of the human rights and equal opportunity act 1986 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">where complaint lodged with human rights and equal opportunity commission day before application to federal court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">where complaint to commission concerned criminal charges laid against applicant in context of palm island "riots" of 2004</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">where applicant seeks to restrain respondents from taking further steps in prosecution and trial pending finalisation of complaint by commission</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">human rights</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an ex parte application for an interim injunction under s 46PP of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act 1986 (Cth) ("the Act ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application was filed in Court today by Lex Patrick Wotton ("the applicant").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Also filed was a statement in support of the application which states that the application is brought by the applicant as a representative party and that the group members to whom this proceeding relates are "the residents of Palm Island of aboriginal descent who were residents between 18 and 28 November 2004, including the applicant".</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 In terms, the application seeks to restrain the respondents from taking any further step in the prosecution or trial of the applicant pending the determination of the applicant's complaint with the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission ("the Commission") lodged on 1 March 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Alternatively, the applicant seeks an injunction in the general jurisdiction of the Court in aid of the proceedings in the Commission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The trial of the applicant and four co-accused is scheduled to commence on 5 March 2007 in the District Court in Queensland, which is in three days' time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Counsel for Mr Wotton indicated, orally, that the injunction might appropriately be made to operate only for a few days until the respondents appeared and an application heard for a further interim injunction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3 The background, in summary form, is that in November 2004 there was civil unrest on Palm Island arising from the death of a member of the local Aboriginal community while in police custody.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The applicant was arrested on Palm Island on 27 November 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Charges against the applicant were then laid under s 65 of the Queensland Criminal Code 1899 in relation to his alleged involvement in that unrest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Those charges attract a maximum sentence of life imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">There have been several applications in the District Court of Queensland incidental to the criminal proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">An application was made to have the matter transferred from Townsville to Brisbane, which was successful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">More recently, there has been an application for a permanent or temporary stay of the indictment which was unsuccessful and in respect of which judgment was given on 28 February 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">4 The complaint lodged yesterday with the Commission alleges, at least principally, that in the circumstances, the arrest, charging, prosecuting and trial of the applicant contravened or would contravene the Racial Discrimination Act 1975 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">It is against this background that an order is now sought under s 46PP of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">There has been considerable delay in lodging the complaint with the Commission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The complaint could have been lodged any time after the charges were laid, having regard to at least some of the grounds in the complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">As a consequence of the delay, this application is being made on the eve of a trial in circumstances where the application could have been made and considered by the Court much earlier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">It is true that, in form, this application is being made immediately after the complaint was lodged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">It is the lodging of such complaint which enlivens the jurisdiction of this Court under s 46PP of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">However, in substance, the application is being made many months after such a complaint could have been made and the jurisdiction of the Court invoked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">5 In those circumstances, it is inappropriate to grant an ex parte interim injunction the effect of which would probably be to stop a criminal trial which is scheduled to commence in three days' time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Whilst there is no direct evidence about this, it is highly likely that witnesses have been marshalled for the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">To make the order sought would be disruptive to the ordinary processes and procedures of the criminal justice system in Queensland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">6 It may ultimately be that the issues raised by the applicant in the complaint to the Commission prove to be of substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It may ultimately be that the Court should act under s 46PP of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">However, that is said in circumstances where there has not been a contested hearing and in circumstances where the reach of s 46PP , in the context of the criminal justice system, has not been explored.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">7 I should note that the application purports to be a representative proceeding under Pt IVA of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">I express no view about whether such a proceeding can be brought in relation to a matter of this type, and if so, whether the proceedings have been regularly instituted having regard to the procedural constraints attending the operation of Pt IVA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">8 I propose to dismiss the ex parte application for an interim injunction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">If the applicant is minded to do so the application for an interim injunction can be renewed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">9 The facts and circumstances giving rise to this application singularly relate to events in Queensland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The respondents are Queensland entities and the applicant is a Queensland resident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">I further order that the matter be transferred to the Registry of this Court in Queensland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Moore.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Associate:

Dated: 9 March 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr P King 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Levitt Robinson Solicitors 
 
 Date of Hearing: 2 March 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 2 March 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/280.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>