<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Ho v Professional Services Review Committee No 295 [2007] FCA 388 (26 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/388.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">health insurance</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">investigation by professional services review committee as to whether a medical practitioner has engaged in inappropriate practice in relation to the number of services rendered or initiated by him</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether exceptional circumstances existed that excused the conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">operation of s 106ka(2) of the health insurance act 1973 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">relation to reg 11(a) of the health insurance (professional services review) regulations 1999 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">meaning of 'exceptional circumstances'</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">meaning of 'unusual occurrence'</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">circumstances under which committee must consider reg 11(a)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether practice management considerations are relevant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">'exceptional circumstances'</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">'unusual occurrence'</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">administrative law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">words and phrases</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 Dr Ho and Dr Do practice in partnership at Merrylands in New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">On 13 December 2001 the Health Insurance Commission made separate investigative referrals expressing concern that each of the doctors, who were general practitioners, had engaged in inappropriate practice in connection with rendering certain referred services during 2000, within the meaning of s 106KA of the Health Insurance Act 1973 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The referrals under s 86 of the Act expressed concern that Dr Ho had engaged in inappropriate practice on 24 occasions between 1 January 2000 and 6 November 2000 and that Dr Do had done so on 56 occasions in the period between 1 January 2000 and 23 June 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 Separate professional services review committees were established with different members to consider each referral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Each committee had a hearing, prepared a separate draft report, received further submissions and then prepared a separate final report in respect of each doctor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The conclusion of each final report was a finding under s 106L of the Act that the conduct of the doctor in relation to the rendering of professional attendances on the days identified constituted a prescribed pattern of services within the referral period and that he had thus engaged in inappropriate practice for the purposes of s 106KA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">3 In 1999 each of the doctors had been in partnership with a third doctor, Dr Bao-Quy Nguyen-Phuoc, who was Dr Ho's brother-in-law at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Earlier, when they had established that partnership, the three of them had been involved in another medical practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Dr Nguyen-Phuoc claimed he had been entitled to take that practice's database which was then used in the new practice of the three.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The previous practice's principal contested the ownership of the database.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">That dispute involved the practice of the three doctors in litigation that was finally settled in June 1999 with a payment of a substantial sum to the previous practice's principal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">4 In late 1998 and early 1999 relations between Dr Nguyen-Phuoc on the one hand and Drs Ho and Do on the other began to deteriorate severely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The partnership finally dissolved at the end of December 1999 when Dr Nguyen-Phuoc left taking 909 patient files out of a total of 11,258.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Drs Ho and Do then began a new partnership retaining the balance of the patient files.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">They initially practised from the partnership's old rooms, but in late March 2000 moved to new premises in Merrylands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">5 Dr Ho challenges the final report of Professional Services Review Committee No 295.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">They found that Dr Ho had engaged in inappropriate practice by rendering 80 or more professional attendances on 24 days during the referral period (1 January 2000 to 6 November 2000) which constituted a prescribed pattern of services under s 106KA(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">6 Dr Do challenges the final report of Professional Services Review Committee No 293.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">They found that Dr Do had engaged in inappropriate practice by rendering 80 or more professional attendances on 56 days during the referral period (1 January 2000 to 23 June 2000) which constituted a prescribed pattern of services under s 106KA(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">7 The committees also found that they did not consider that exceptional circumstances existed that affected the rendering of services by Dr Ho or Dr Do on any of the 24 or 56 days in question for the purposes of s 106KA(2) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">8 In essence, each of Dr Ho and Dr Do asserts that the findings in each final report resulted from each committee committing jurisdictional errors, constructively failing to exercise its jurisdiction, denying procedural fairness, making errors of law or improperly exercising a power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">This was alleged to arise from the following:
 
 
 (a) the committee failing to consider or apply reg 11(a) of the Health Insurance (Professional Services Review) Regulations 1999 (Cth) first, at all or, secondly, in respect of any or all of the 24 or 56 days in the referral period and, thirdly, if they did apply reg 11(a), the committee misconstrued it;
 (b) the committee taking into account practice management considerations for the purposes of reg 11(a) or incorrectly using practice management as a test for rejecting the doctor's claim that exceptional circumstances existed for the purpose of s 106KA(2) on one or more of the relevant days;
 (c) the committee failing to apply the statutory test, namely whether the doctor's circumstances were truly exceptional having regard to the unusual operation of his medical practice and bearing in mind the circumstances ordinarily faced by general practitioners;
 (d) each final report was an improper exercise of the power conferred on the committee because they applied a policy of practice management firmly instead of having regard to the merits of the case;
 (e) each final report involved a denial of natural justice because the committee was affected by apprehended bias in light of the overwhelming and impermissible emphasis and effect it gave to the policy of practice management.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">
 

9 On 13 July 2006, I made an order pursuant to O 29 r 2 that these questions be decided separately from an argument that the provisions of the Act are not valid laws because the Parliament had no power to enact them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">This constitutional question has been raised in separate and related litigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">10 Dr Ho and Dr Do, respectively, conducted their proceedings before each committee on the admitted basis that each had had more than 80 patient consultations on each of the 24 and 56 respective separate days referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Regulation 10 of the Health Insurance (Professional Services Review) Regulations 1999 (Cth) provided that professional attendances constituted a prescribed pattern of services in the circumstance that 80 or more such services were rendered on each of 20 or more days in a 12 month period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The question in these proceedings is essentially whether or not each committee had before it, and if so, properly considered the nature of each doctors' claim that exceptional circumstances existed on all or some of the referred days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">No point was taken that the period in each of the referrals was of less than 12 months, for they were fairly based on respective periods which could have been used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The regulations commenced only on 1 November 1999 (reg 2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">11 Critical for present purposes are the provisions of s 106KA and reg 11 at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Relevantly s 106KA was in the following terms:
 
 '106KA Patterns of services 
 
 
 
 (1) Subject to subsections (2) and (2A), if, during a particular period (the relevant period ), the circumstances in which some or all of the referred services were rendered or initiated constituted a prescribed pattern of services, the conduct of the person under review in connection with rendering or initiating services during that period in those circumstances is taken, for the purposes of this Part, to have constituted engaging in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">
 
 (2) If the person under review satisfies the Committee that, on a particular day or particular days during the relevant period, exceptional circumstances existed that affected the rendering or initiating of services by the person, the person's conduct in connection with rendering or initiating services on that day or those days is not taken by subsection (1) to have constituted engaging in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">
 
 (2A) However, subsection (2) does not affect the operation of subsection (1) in respect of the remaining day or days during the relevant period on which the person rendered or initiated referred services even if the circumstances in which the referred services were rendered or initiated on that day or those days would not, if considered alone, have constituted a prescribed pattern of services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">
 
 (3) The regulations may prescribe, in relation to: 
 
 (a) a particular profession; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) an identified group or groups of practitioners in a particular profession; 
 
 
 
 
 
 circumstances in which services of a particular kind or description that are rendered or initiated constitute, or do not constitute, a prescribed pattern of services for the purposes of subsection (1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">
 
 (4) The circumstances that may be prescribed under subsection (3) as circumstances in which services that are rendered or initiated constitute a prescribed pattern of services include, but are not limited to, the rendering or initiation of more than a specified number of services, or more than a specified number of services of a particular kind, on each of more than a specified number of days during a period of a specified duration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">
 
 (5) The circumstances that constitute exceptional circumstances for the purposes of subsection (2) include, but are not limited to, circumstances that are declared by the regulations to be exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">
 
 (6) This section only applies to services rendered or initiated after the commencement of this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">
 
 (7) This section does not preclude the Committee from making a finding under this Subdivision (other than section 106KB) in relation to conduct during a particular period in connection with rendering or initiating services without considering whether or not the circumstances in which the services were rendered or initiated constituted a prescribed pattern of services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">' 
 
 

12 Reg 11 was in these terms:
 
 ' 11 Exceptional circumstances 
 
 
 
 For subsection 106KA(5) of the Act, the following circumstances are declared as constituting exceptional circumstances: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) an unusual occurrence causing an unusual level of need for professional attendances; 
 
 (b) an absence of other medical services, for patients of the person under review during the relevant period, having regard to: 
 
 (i) the location of the practice of the person under review; and 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) characteristics of the patients of the person under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">' 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 EXCEPTIONAL CIRCUMSTANCES 
 
13 In Oreb v Willcock [2005] FCAFC 196 ; (2005) 146 FCR 237 the Full Court held that there were two ways of establishing exceptional circumstances for the purposes of s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">First, the doctor concerned could show that on the particular day or days during the relevant period 'exceptional circumstances', within the ordinary English meaning of the words, existed which affected the rendering or initiating of services by the doctor so as to take him or her outside the deeming pursuant to s 106KA(1) of engagement in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Secondly, the doctor could rely upon 'exceptional circumstances' as prescribed in regulations made pursuant to s 106KA(5), being those set out in reg 11 ( Oreb 146 FCR at 240 [6] per Black CJ and Wilcox J; see also per Lander J at 265 [169], 268 [191]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">14 Although Oreb [2005] FCAFC 196 ; 146 FCR 237 concerned the construction of s 106KA and reg 11(b) the Court also made observations as to how reg 11(a) might be engaged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The Court held that once the practitioner had established that exceptional circumstances existed in either sense the practitioner had also to show a causal connection between those established circumstances and the provision of the relevant services if he or she were to get the benefit of s 106KA(2) ( Oreb 146 FCR at 240-241 [7]-[10], 266 [178]-[181]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">15 And, in a decision handed down on the same day, Cohn v Hatcher [2005] FCAFC 199 ; (2005) 146 FCR 275 the same Full Court looked again at the operation of 'exceptional circumstances' within s 106KA and reg 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Lander J said that reg 11(a) provided for certain circumstances which are like, but not the same as, circumstances which might be 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(2) ( Cohn 146 FCR at 288 [67]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">He held that, first, the medical practitioner had to establish that an unusual occurrence had occurred which caused an unusual level of need for professional attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Next, the practitioner must establish that that occurrence affected the rendering or initiating of services by him or her ( Cohn 146 FCR at 288 [70]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">In this way each of reg 11(a) and s 106KA(2) were held to interact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">And, once the medical practitioner establishes both that exceptional circumstances existed and they affected the rendering or initiating of services by him or her, the day or days on which that is established are not taken by s 106KA(1) to have constituted engaging in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">The Full Court did not deal with the operation of s 106KA(2A).</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">16 At the outset it is important to understand how s 106KA operates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">First, s 106KA(1) is expressly made subject to subsections (2) and (2A).</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Each of the latter subsections identifies an exception to s 106KA(1) although the exceptions work in different ways.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">How they work bears on what s 106KA(1) itself does in deeming a certain state of affairs to amount to a practitioner engaging in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">17 Because s 106KA(1) creates a statutory fiction, by the deeming it prescribes, ss 106KA(2) and (2A) recognise that the person under review is entitled, to a point, to negate that fiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Critically, s 106KA(1) refers to '... the circumstances in which some or all of the referred services were rendered ... constituted a prescribed pattern of services'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Thus while not all of the referred services may remain a part of a pattern after the committee examines them, it is essential that what remains is a pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">A pattern, by regulation 10 , must have the characteristic that 80 or more professional attendances within the meaning of reg 7 ' ... are rendered on each of 20 or more days in a 12 month period'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">Thus, conduct cannot satisfy reg 10 so as to constitute a prescribed pattern of services unless it occurs 'on each of 20 or more days'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">18 Next, s 106KA(2) affords the practitioner a means of negating that he or she engaged in inappropriate practice on or more or each of the days in the relevant period which has been referred to the committee for examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">The effect of s 106KA(2A) will need to be considered if for one or more, but not all, of the days referred, the practitioner satisfies the committee under s 106KA(2) that the services were rendered when exceptional circumstances existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Now, s 106KA(2A) provides, first, that s 106KA(2) '... does not affect the operation of subsection (1) in respect of the remaining day or days during the relevant period during which the person rendered ... referred services'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">At first blush, 'the operation of' s 106KA(1) to which s 106KA(2A) refers must be in respect of the remaining day or days --- that is, s 106KA(1) remains engaged despite one or more of the days in the pattern originally alleged being shown not to be part of any prescribed pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">But, critically, s 106KA(2A) goes on to provide that the remaining day or days do not, even if considered alone, cease to constitute a prescribed pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">19 The doctors argued that because reg 10 prescribed only one circumstance, namely a pattern extending over 20 or more days, if the practitioner showed that exceptional circumstances existed on enough of the days on which referred services were rendered to leave only 19 or less days, s 106KA(1) could have no operation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">They said the consequence was that s 106KA(2A) did not expose the practitioner to a finding that he or she engaged in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">20 It is, of course, significant that the Act does not prescribe any period or pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Rather ss 106KA(3) and (4) authorise the making of regulations for those purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The fact that regulations may operate in a way which produces a particular result is irrelevant in construing the meaning of the statute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The last clause of s 106KA(2A) is, however, arcane and obscure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">It provides that even if the operation of s 106KA(2) has removed one or more days from the pattern, that removal does not affect the operation of s 106KA(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">So, the circumstances in which the referred services were rendered on the day or days left in the original period (after any day has been removed by the operation of s 106KA(2)) can still be found to be inappropriate practice even though what remains '... would not, if considered alone, have constituted a prescribed pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">' The committee contended that this meant that even though the 20 days which reg 10 set as the minimum period for a prescribed pattern cannot be established after days are removed by force of s 106KA(2), the remaining 19 or less days, even if only 1, can amount to a pattern of 20 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">21 The words of s 106KA(2A) suggest that 1 day can constitute a pattern even though the definition of the pattern applied in s 106KA(1) would not otherwise have been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">That is an odd result, but no sensible alternative construction of s 106KA(2A) appears to be open which gives effect to the words of the last clause: cp ASIC v DB Management Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 7 ; (2000) 199 CLR 321 at 338 [34] - [35] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">22 If one construes s 106KA(2) using the prescription in reg 11(a), the section then provides that if the medical practitioner satisfies the committee that on a particular day or particular days during the relevant period an unusual occurrence causing an unusual level of need for professional attendances existed that affected the rendering or initiating of services by the medical practitioner, his or her conduct in connection with rendering or initiating those services on that day or those days is not taken by s 106KA(1) to have constituted engaging in inappropriate practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">23 I am of opinion that the expression 'exceptional circumstances' requires consideration of all the circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">In Griffiths v The Queen [1989] HCA 39 ; (1989) 167 CLR 372 at 379 Brennan and Dawson JJ considered a statutory provision which entitled either a parole board or a court to specify a shorter non-parole period than that required under another section only if it determined that the circumstances justified that course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">They said of the appellant's circumstances:
 
 'Although no one of these factors was exceptional, in combination they may reasonably be regarded as amounting to exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">' 
 

24 Brennan and Dawson JJ held that the failure in that case to evaluate the relevant circumstances in combination was a failure to consider matters which were relevant to the exercise of the discretion under the section (167 CLR at 379).</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Deane J, (with whom Gaudron and McHugh JJ expressed their concurrence on this point, albeit that they were dissenting) explained that the power under consideration allowed departure from the norm only in the exceptional or special case where the circumstances justified it (167 CLR at 383, 397).</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">25 And, in Baker v The Queen [2004] HCA 45 ; (2004) 223 CLR 513 at 573 [173] Callinan J referred with approval to what Lord Bingham of Cornhill CJ had said in R v Kelly (Edward) [2000] QB 198 at 208, namely:
 
 'We must construe "exceptional" as an ordinary, familiar English adjective, and not as a term of art.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">It describes a circumstance which is such as to form an exception, which is out of the ordinary course, or unusual, or special, or uncommon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">To be exceptional a circumstance need not be unique, or unprecedented, or very rare; but it cannot be one that is regularly, or routinely, or normally encountered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">' 
 

26 Exceptional circumstances within the meaning of s 106KA(2) can include a single exceptional matter, a combination of exceptional factors or a combination of ordinary factors which, although individually of no particular significance, when taken together are seen as exceptional.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Thus, the sun and moon appear in the sky everyday and there is nothing exceptional about seeing them both simultaneously during day time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">But an eclipse, whether lunar or solar, is exceptional, even though it can be predicted, because it is outside the usual course of events.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">27 It is not correct to construe 'exceptional circumstances' as being only some unexpected occurrence, although frequently it will be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">Nor is it correct to construe the plural 'circumstances' as if it were only a singular occurrence, even though it can be a one off situation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">The ordinary and natural meaning of 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(2) includes a combination of factors which, when viewed together, may reasonably be seen as producing a situation which is out of the ordinary course, unusual, special or uncommon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">And, the section is directed to the circumstances of the actual practitioner, not a hypothetical being, when he or she initiates or renders the services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">THE COMMITTEES' INTERPRETATION OF 'EXCEPTIONAL CIRCUMSTANCES' 
 
28 Each committee used a set of standard paragraphs under the heading 'Prescribed Pattern of Services --- Legal Considerations'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">In these paragraphs they had regard to the fact that s 106KA had been introduced into the Act by the Health Insurance Amendment (Professional Services Review) Act 1999 (Cth) to implement the recommendations of the Review Committee of the Professional Services Review Scheme which had reported to the government the same year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">That report had stated that the medical profession generally accepted that high volume provision of services by a practitioner prohibited adequate clinical input.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">29 The Review Report recommended, following wide consultations with relevant medical organisations, that the threshold for deeming practice to be inappropriate in the case of a general practitioner should be 80 or more services on 20 or more days in a year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Each committee noted that the Review Report also had recommended that a practitioner should be able to demonstrate to the satisfaction of a committee that exceptional circumstances occurred which allowed him or her to practice appropriately while rendering such a high number of services (see: recommendation 3 in the Review Report and its attendant reasoning).</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Each committee went on to refer to the Review Report's use of examples of exceptional circumstances such as an exceptional event or a very extreme geographic occurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">The Review Report also indicated that regard should be had to the availability of alternative medical services or unusual occurrences causing unusual levels of need for medical services and said that it was expected 'that argument [sic] that a practitioner's ability or organisation provides an exceptional circumstance is unlikely to be sustained'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">30 Each committee considered that those examples and comments confirmed their view that 'exceptional circumstances were seen as being generally intermittent or episodic situations beyond the practitioner's control but necessitating the provision of medical services as well as practicable'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">They also referred to the explanatory memorandum issued by the Minister when he introduced the Bill which became the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">Each committee then said this (using the paragraph numbering in Committee 295's Report):
 
 
 '52.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">This Committee considers that this confirms that " exceptional circumstances " were seen as most likely to be of an intermittent or episodic nature, rather than a predictable on-going situation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The Committee does not see that some extreme on-going circumstance is totally ruled out (if " particular days " can be " many days ") --- although the general body of general practitioners would ordinarily expect a practitioner to manage their practice to promptly bring patient attendance rates down to acceptable levels such that proper clinical care can be provided to all patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">
 
 53.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">In summary, it appears to the Committee that subsection 106KA(1) and the Regulations implement a view of the legislature that it is most unlikely that 80 or more professional attendances can be rendered satisfactorily within one day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The " 20 or more days " proviso acknowledges that the exigencies of normal practice may occasionally require a doctor to provide more attendances in a day than would otherwise be considered satisfactory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">But by subsection 106KA(2) of the Act, exceptional circumstances will be required to justify 20 or more such days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">Thus, the exception may be read as excusing lower standard services on particular days because of exceptional circumstances --- and it will be difficult to justify this on an on-going basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">' 
 
 

31 These two paragraphs appear to be part of a standard form explanation used by other committees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">The same words appear in Dr Oreb's committee's report: see: Oreb 146 FCR at 262 [156].</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">Immediately after quoting these words, Lander J said that the committee there fell into error in its construction of s 106KA(2) and reg 11, by failing to have regard to the terms of reg 11 itself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Likewise, I am of opinion that the committees here fell into error, by putting a gloss on the meaning of s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">They asserted that the expression 'exceptional circumstances' was to be seen 'as most likely to be of an intermittent or episodic nature, rather than a predictable on-going situation'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">32 As McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ pointed out in Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 384 [78] , the duty of a court is to give the words of a statutory provision the meaning that the legislature is taken to have intended it to have.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">They said:
 
 'Ordinarily, that meaning (the legal meaning) will correspond with the grammatical meaning of the provision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">But not always.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">The context of the words, the consequences of a literal or grammatical construction, the purpose of the statute or the canons of construction (for example, the presumption that, in the absence of unmistakable and unambiguous language, the legislature has not intended to interfere with basic rights, freedoms or immunities: Coco v The Queen [1994] HCA 15 ; (1994) 179 CLR 427 at 437) may require the words of a legislative provision to be read in a way that does not correspond with the literal or grammatical meaning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">' (See also DB Management 199 CLR at 338 [34].</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">)
 

33 Indeed, the provisions of reg 11 prescribed some of the matters which the Review Report regarded as exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">But reg 11 could not supplant the natural and ordinary meaning of 'exceptional circumstances' as used in s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">Rather the purpose of the regulation-making power granted by the Parliament in s 106KA(5) was to set out a free-standing set of circumstances which may or may not be within the ordinary and natural meaning of 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">34 However, in their approach the committees have made the tail of the regulation wag the dog of the statute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">This eschewed the ordinary principles of statutory construction and the application of the salutary and broad discretion which the Parliament, by its words, conferred on the committees in s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">While reg 11 gave effect to intentions expressed in the Review Report and in the Parliament, it did not restrict the circumstances which a committee must take into account in forming a view for the purposes of the application of s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Those intentions are matters to which the Court may have regard as part of the historical context in which s 106KA was enacted so that a purposive meaning can be given to the legislation: Network Ten Pty Ltd v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 14 ; (2004) 218 CLR 273 at 280-281 [10] - [11] per McHugh ACJ, Gummow and Hayne JJ; Sydney Airport Corporation Ltd v Australian Competition Tribunal [2006] FCAFC 146 ; (2006) 155 FCR 124 at 125 [2] per French, Finn and Allsop JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">The literal construction of s 106KA(2) and reg 11 will not defeat the intention of the Parliament (or the Executive in making the regulation).</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">35 As Mason CJ, Wilson and Dawson JJ said in Re Bolton; ex Parte Beane [1987] HCA 12 ; (1987) 162 CLR 514 at 518:
 
 'The function of the court is to give effect to the will of Parliament as expressed in the law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">' 
 

In effect, the view which each committee took as to the management of the respective doctors' practice and its concentration on the episodic construction they had placed on 'exceptional circumstances' resulted in them failing to consider the combination of circumstances relied on by each doctor either in the context of s 106KA(2) or reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">36 The committees focused on the examples given in the Review Report, which were codified in reg 11, as identifying what s 106KA(2) meant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">That is how they discerned a test that the words 'exceptional circumstances' do not convey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">Their test of an 'intermittent or episodic' situation, rather than a predictable on-going one, is narrower than the natural and ordinary meaning of 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The real question was whether the circumstances relied on were individually or in combination such as formed an exception to the ordinary course of practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">The circumstances necessarily included the actual situation of the practitioner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">Of course, a practitioner who habitually saw more than 80 patients a day may not be able to show 'exceptional circumstances', if he or she were located in a city.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">But, what of the one doctor in a country town?</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Is such a doctor's position affected if he or she has been looking for, but cannot find, any other practitioner to join his or her practice?</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Or consider a specialist in a country centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">The statute did not condemn dedicated professionals; rather it sought to protect the public from unsatisfactory methods of practice and inappropriate derivation of income from the medical benefits system while providing that some exceptions must be given recognition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">37 This is not to say that had the committees approached the task confided to them under s 106KA and reg 11(a) in accordance with law they could not have come to the same conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">The provisions of s 106KA are intended to be protective of the public.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">The section seeks to create presumptions as to the circumstances in which particular numbers of professional services may be initiated or rendered by practitioners over a given period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">This is intended to ensure that the standard of care provided by practitioners to patients is maintained at an appropriately high standard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">38 What s 106KA(2) does is to give effect to fictions, first, the fiction of the deeming worked by force of s 106KA(1) and, secondly, the fiction that where exceptional circumstances are established that deeming is negated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">That does not affect the other provisions of the Act dealing with inappropriate conduct notwithstanding the failure of the deeming provisions to catch the conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">Thus, the exception in s 106KA(2) does not require examination of the individual services or attendances rendered by the doctor any more than the deeming in s 106KA(1) does.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">Each subsection looks at a particular factual situation and its operation is engaged or not depending on those facts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">DR HO'S CLAIM OF EXCEPTIONAL CIRCUMSTANCES 
 
39 Dr Ho said that because of the nature of the partnership before Dr Nguyen-Phuoc left, and the circumstances in which he did leave, when he and Dr Do had to deal with over 10,000 patients of the practice, it was sometimes necessary to see more than 80 a day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">This was because, although they were making efforts to do so, they had been unable to locate a suitable replacement for Dr Nguyen-Phuoc who could work in the practice on a full time basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">This was made more difficult than usual because at this time medical practices were being corporatised which affected the market and availability of practitioners who might be suitable recruits to work in the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Moreover, the first day on which the new practice operated was 4 January 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">A large number of patients needed to be seen following the Christmas break and the re-organisation of the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">When the practice closed for two days so they could move to new rooms in late March 2000, Dr Ho saw more than 80 patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">A number of the other days on which over 80 patients were seen were Mondays during winter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">Dr Ho said that his practice was a family practice, rather than a medical centre type practice, in which individuals were important and wished to see the doctor of their nomination or choice, rather than being referred to whoever was available at the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">40 In addition, in the relevant period there were two days on which Dr Do went home sick and another on which he was not present at the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">41 In essence, the committee rejected all of these explanations finding that for each of them, proper practice management would have enabled Dr Ho to see less than 80 patients on any of the days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">THE WAY DR HO PUT HIS POSITION BEFORE THE COMMITTEE 
 
42 At the conclusion of Dr Ho's hearing the chairman expressed the preliminary view of the committee which he said was to be spelled out in detail in their draft report to similar effect, namely that the practice appeared to be a high volume one and that there were no particular distinguishing features shown in the adjudicative referral material for any of the 24 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">The chairman then summarised the committee's understanding of the claim for exceptional circumstances made by Dr Ho as follows:
 
 
 &#8226; his lack of awareness of the 80/20 rule during the referral period;
 &#8226; the serious conflict in his earlier practice;
 &#8226; the departure of Dr Nguyen-Phuoc from that practice;
 &#8226; the current practice's inability to employ another doctor;
 &#8226; the high numbers of patients in the practice's books;
 &#8226; busy Mondays, days after long weekends and wintertime; and
 &#8226; two days when his partner suffered a sudden illness and was unable to work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">
 

43 Dr Ho asserted that there had been exceptional circumstances on each of the 24 days on which he rendered 80 or more professional attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">The committee recorded in its draft, and then final, reports that three issues principally affected the practice:
 
 
 (1) The two court cases in 1999 and 2000 involving aspects of partnership disputes, including the extra stress on Dr Ho resulting from the fact that Dr Nguyen-Phuoc was his brother-in-law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">(2) The attempts of the new practice to recruit a third doctor from late March to late November 2000, when one was successfully recruited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">(3) The need to give special consideration to particular days within the 24 day period (such as when Dr Do went home sick).</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">
 

44 The committee reports noted that Dr Ho said he had worked long hours, often in excess of the opening hours of 8.30a.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">to 8.00p.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">and he had provided a calendar showing the hours which he had worked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">He had said that 15 of the 24 days in question were Mondays, which tended to be the busiest in general practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">On 4 of the days, when over 80 patients were seen, the surgery had been closed for a number of the preceding days, namely:
 
 
 &#8226; 4 January 2000: the surgery had been closed for 3 days over the preceding New Year period;
 &#8226; 27 March 2000: the surgery opened in new premises after a 2 day closure in which it was moved;
 &#8226; 26 April 2000: the surgery had been closed for 6 days over Easter (and, presumably, Anzac Day) break;
 &#8226; 13 June 2000: the surgery had been closed for 3 days over the Queen's Birthday holiday.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">
 

45 In addition, the committee reports noted the claim concerning the two days on which Dr Do had gone home sick and left Dr Ho on his own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">However, the committee reports did not refer to Dr Ho's claim that Dr Do had been away on one further day, 25 June 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">46 The committee reports also noted that Dr Ho said that he had been unaware of the 80/20 rule during the relevant period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">47 In its draft report, in a passage which remained unchanged in the final report, the committee concluded that in the context of Report 4 which was part of the referral, the 24 days when Dr Ho rendered 80 or more professional attendances showed no particular distinguishing features.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Report 4 set out in tabular form the number of services per day rendered by Dr Ho during the referral period by calendar month with monthly totals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">This suggested to the committee that his practice was 'a high volume practice'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">And they concluded:
 
 'Having weighed all the evidence, the committee did not accept that Dr Ho's claims as stated [in the earlier part of the draft report] ... constituted exceptional circumstances on any of the 24 days when 80 or more services were rendered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">' 
 

48 That statement of non-acceptance was the whole of the reasoning to that point in the committee's reports justifying rejection of Dr Ho's explanation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">DR HO --- THE FINAL REPORT 
 
49 After the draft report had been served on Dr Ho in accordance with s 106KD(3) he made submissions upon the findings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">In its final report the committee set out, in tabular form, a summary of the thrust of Dr Ho's submissions and their response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">The committee noted in response to the argument that s 106KA(2) should be interpreted literally, that a purposive approach should be taken referring to Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1988) 194 CLR 355.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">50 The committee's final report noted that Dr Ho's lawyers had raised legal issues in his post hearing submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">The submissions claimed that the chairman's summary given at the conclusion of the hearing had understated the difficulties encountered by Dr Ho.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">The submissions provided further material concerning, among other things, the difficulties encountered by Dr Ho as a result of the former partnership litigation disputes, the problems of locating and engaging a suitable new doctor and the difficulties caused by the corporatisation of medical practices which was then occurring.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">Corporatisation was said to make it even more difficult than normal to recruit a suitable practitioner to the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">51 The committee noted that most of Dr Ho's claimed stressful circumstances were outside the referral period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">It went on to say:
 
 
 '[70] In relation to his practice, Dr Ho did not present any additional evidence to the committee on how he might have alternatively managed his patients, for instance, by limiting hours and initiating an appointment system, or by referring patients to other practitioners or hospitals in the area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">Dr Ho told the committee that in retrospect he could have handled the situation thus: "I could say no and refuse to see them because my volume was so high.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">I just did not" because he felt it was more an ethical issue that he see his regular patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">The committee considers the opening hours of the Familyland Medical Practice during the referral period to be both business and lifestyle decisions made by the partners in the practice and, thus, this does not constitute exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">' 
 
 

52 The committee found that such matters did not constitute exceptional circumstances on particular days within the meaning of s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">It said that, '[r]ather, the circumstances described were part of a long-term and on-going practice'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">The committee noted that Dr Ho had told them that he and his partner knew that it was a problem that they were seeing a lot of patients and at the end of the day were very tired and run down.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">It referred to his evidence that:
 
 'I mean, the way ... that I run the practice when it is busy, you become a casualty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">' 
 

53 The post hearing submission challenged the committee's preliminary conclusion that the practice was a high volume one and that the 24 days were not significantly different from other days, suggesting that the committee was making an adverse inference relating to Dr Ho's conduct on the other days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">54 The committee responded in the final report that they recognised that the factors to which Dr Ho had drawn attention might be relevant to the task of the Determining Authority, but that they did not constitute exceptional circumstances 'such as to excuse inappropriate practice by way of a prescribed pattern of services'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">The committee said that they had not made any finding about Dr Ho's services in general but had noted his general pattern when assessing his claim that there were exceptional circumstances on the 24 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">55 The final report noted Dr Ho's concession that most of the stressful circumstances had occurred outside the referral period but rejected his submission that more weight should be given to the difficulty in attracting another doctor to the practice before November 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">They said that all practices had to cope on occasion with ongoing resource limitations '... and must adjust their patient load accordingly to maintain the quality of services'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">The committee said they had amended their draft report accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">56 In answer to Dr Ho's post hearing submission that the 3 days when he was alone at the surgery were circumstances which he could not reasonably have foreseen and were of an intermittent or episodic nature, the committee responded, again, that their '...view is that all practices must cope on occasion with ongoing resource limitations and must adjust their patient load accordingly to maintain the quality of services'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">The committee referred to its earlier finding that Dr Ho had not presented any additional evidence on how he might have managed his patients in an alternative way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">(The reference in the report to paragraph 69 was agreed to be a typographical error for paragraph 70 of the same report.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">)
 
57 The final report then said that in reaching their findings the committee had applied their combined professional expertise and had had regard to all of the evidence before them concerning Dr Ho's conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">Finally, the committee made findings that:
 
 
 &#8226; Dr Ho engaged in inappropriate practice by rendering 80 or more professional attendances on 24 days during the referral period which constituted a prescribed pattern of services under s 106KA(1) of the Act;
 &#8226; for the purposes of s 106KA(2) the committee did not consider that exceptional circumstances existed that affected the rendering of services by Dr Ho on any of the 24 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">
 

58 Both the committee in their reports and Dr Ho in his submissions had set out the express terms of reg 11(a) but neither discussed in terms how reg 11(a) related to consideration of Dr Ho's position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">DR DO'S CLAIM OF EXCEPTIONAL CIRCUMSTANCES 
 
59 In his initial statement to Committee 293 Dr Do referred to the circumstances in which he, Dr Ho and Dr Nguyen-Phuoc had left a practice run by another doctor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">Dr Nguyen-Phuoc took the old practice's patient data base representing that he was entitled to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">The former practice's principal disputed that and commenced litigation against the three partners which was settled towards the end of 1999 on the basis that they paid the other doctor a significant sum of money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">60 Dr Do noted that when Dr Nguyen-Phuoc left in December 1999 and they dissolved their partnership the latter took with him only about 1,000 of the 11,000 patient files.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">He said that a significant area of the dispute between Dr Nguyen-Phuoc and Dr Ho and himself had been the former's growing interest in alternative health therapies at the expense of traditional medicine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">The ongoing dispute with the former practice's principal and this developing tension within the new partnership made the doctors feel that they could not recruit any further practitioners until the uncertainty generated by the litigation was finalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">Soon after the litigation was settled the partnership was dissolved and for most of the year 2000 only two practitioners serviced a patient population which was almost the same size as that that had been served by three.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">He noted that the first person whom they recruited to take on some of the burden during the earlier part of the year 2000 only worked about 20 days between March and September 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Dr Do said that he was not aware of the 80/20 rule until he received notification from the Health Insurance Commission in 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">THE WAY DR DO PUT HIS POSITION BEFORE THE COMMITTEE 
 
61 The chairman advised Dr Do at the hearing that although exceptional circumstances were declared in reg 11, the legislation did not prevent the committee from considering circumstances other than those declared.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">At one point during the course of the hearing before the committee the solicitor for Dr Do said that the overall thrust of his case was that the difficulties created by Dr Nguyen-Phuoc's conduct when a member of the partnership, the disenchantment with him of a significant number of his patients and his ultimate leaving the practice, combined with litigation with the former practice (over the patient list), led Dr Do to feel uncomfortable and uncertain about where his practice was going so that he did not want to take on another doctor while in partnership with Dr Nguyen-Phuoc to deal with what was said to be a fairly heavy patient load and that caused him to render as many services as he did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">The chairman acknowledged that the submission accorded with what the committee had understood from Dr Do's written submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">62 At the conclusion of the hearing the chairman informed Dr Do of the committee's preliminary views in relation to the evidence of exceptional circumstances he had presented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">He summarised the claims saying that the committee understood that the reasons advanced by Dr Do were the limited availability of medical practitioners in the practice due to a doctor leaving in late 1999 and said that the committee had difficulty in accepting that that constituted exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">The chairman said that the referral extended over a six month period in the first half of the year 2000 and that Dr Do had the opportunity to employ another doctor at his practice following the departure of Dr Nguyen-Phuoc or to make other arrangements for his patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">He said that the committee believed that there were about 50 medical providers in the area at the time and wondered whether there was any reason why overflow patients could not have gone to those other general practitioners in an emergency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">The committee observed that one other surgery advertised being open 24 hours a day, seven days a week, and another had opening hours between 8.00a.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">and 10.00p.m.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">seven day a week during 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">63 The committee said that it appeared that Dr Do's practice generally provided high numbers of services and that the days with 80 or more were simply a part of that pattern, observing that there seemed to be nothing particular about those days, other than the number of professional attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">The chairman noted that Dr Do had provided some additional explanations for 5 particular days in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">64 The chairman said that the committee had reached the preliminary finding that Dr Do had engaged in inappropriate practice by rendering 80 or more personal attendances on 20 or more days during the referral period and that that constituted a prescribed pattern of services under s 106KA of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">65 Once again, Dr Do did not challenge Report 4 in the investigative referral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">It set out the number of services per day rendered by him during the referral period by calendar month.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">On 17 days Dr Do rendered over 100 services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">Like Dr Ho, Dr Do referred to the circumstances surrounding the partnership with Dr Nguyen-Phuoc and its subsequent dissolution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">Dr Do submitted that there were exceptional circumstances in respect of 5 of the 56 days in the referral, namely 4 January (105 services), 27 January (105 services), 27 March (112 services), 20 April (124 services) and 26 April 2000 (126 services).</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">66 He submitted that on 4 January 2000 the practice reopened following the departure of Dr Nguyen-Phuoc and that there was a large number of patients who required attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">He said that he and Dr Ho had attempted to advertise for another doctor to join the practice but advertisements could not be placed until February 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">The committee found that exceptional circumstances did not exist on that particular occasion and that those circumstances were foreseeable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">They said that 'some effort could have been made to limit the number of patients seen by Dr Do on that day', and they suggested that a triage system could have been established to ensure that the patients with an immediate healthcare need were attended to but others could have been directed to another healthcare provider or scheduled to present to Dr Do at another time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">They noted that Dr Do had not presented any evidence that he had developed or put in place an action plan to manage the increased patient demand on this day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">67 Dr Do submitted that the practice had been closed for the Australia Day public holiday on 26 January and the practice reopened on the next day when a large number of patients requested attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">Again, the committee found that exceptional circumstances did not exist on that particular day noting that a public holiday was a foreseeable event and that it was reasonable to expect Dr Do to implement a plan, such as a triage system, to limit the number of patients seen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">Again, the committee noted that he had not presented any evidence about developing or putting in place an action plan to manage the increased patient demand on that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">68 Dr Do said that on 24 March he had verbally advised patients that he did not intend to work on the next two days and that subsequently a large number of patients requested attention when he returned to work on 27 March 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">Again, the committee rejected the contention that this constituted exceptional circumstances for that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">They considered that Dr Do should have foreseen that his intention not to work on 25 and 26 March would increase patient demand on his next day of work and he should have implemented a plan to limit the number of patients seen, such as by engaging a locum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">They again referred to the absence of any evidence from Dr Do of developing or putting in place any action plan to manage increased patient demand on the day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">69 Dr Do submitted that Dr Ho was absent from the practice in the period between 20-25 April for the Easter and Anzac Day break and that therefore he was the only doctor present to attend to a large number of patients seeking attention on 20 April 2000, the day before Good Friday.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">The committee found that Dr Do had continued to see patients over this period and that the only day on which he did not work was Easter Sunday, 23 April.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">They found that exceptional circumstances did not exist on 20 April and that Dr Do should have foreseen that his practice partner's intention not to work over the Easter/Anzac period would increase patient demand on his own services at that time and that he should have implemented a plan to limit the number of patients seen, such as by engaging a locum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">Once again, the committee noted that Dr Do had not presented evidence of developing or putting in place an action plan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">As to Wednesday 26 April, the committee came to a similar conclusion in relation to the increased demand on the practice when the holiday break concluded and Dr Ho had returned to work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">70 The committee then went on to make findings that Dr Do had not been able to demonstrate to their satisfaction that exceptional circumstances had existed on the 5 days in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">They said that they did not believe that the limited availability of medical practitioners in the practice constituted exceptional circumstances when the partnership had reduced to two.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">They pointed out that there were approximately 50 medical providers in the immediate area at the time and that patients unable to be seen by Dr Do would have been able to access other practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">The committee pointed to the fact that Dr Do had illustrated his ability to limit the number of patients seen by giving them advance notice on 24 March that he would not be available on the succeeding two days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">71 Critically, the committee noted that Dr Do had not submitted that there were particular exceptional circumstances on the 51 other days in the subject of the referral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">However, he had submitted that throughout the referral period there were circumstances which, coupled with patient demand, constituted exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">Those circumstances were the litigation, partnership difficulties with Dr Nguyen-Phuoc, the difficulties in engaging another doctor and corporatisation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">The committee considered that those circumstances could and should have been managed so as to limit patient numbers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">They did not consider that these constituted exceptional circumstances on a particular day or days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">The committee said that it appeared that Dr Do generally provided high numbers of services and that the days of 80 or more were simply part of that pattern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">They considered that Dr Do did not appear to understand the need to manage the number of consultations that he undertook regardless of demands from patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">They did say that:
 
 '[o]n his own evidence, Dr Do seems to feel a high sense of responsibility to see all patients that come to see him, but fails to recognise that he cannot take responsibility for all patients, no matter how caring and diligent he is.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">' 
 

72 The committee pointed out that the principle inherent in the legislation and their own view was that regularly seeing a high number of patients inevitably compromises both patient care and the doctor's ability to manage other aspects of his or her own life including personal health and family needs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">They identified the introduction of an appointment system to the Familyland Medical Practice after February 2001 as reinforcing their view that the management of patients was possible in a busy family medical practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">73 The committee considered a post hearing submission by Dr Do but came to the conclusion that it did not provide any additional relevant information which he had not already provided to the committee in relation to the claim of exceptional circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">They noted that Dr Do had claimed to have been unaware of the introduction of the deeming provisions but they referred to a circular sent out by the Health Insurance Commission in September 1999 and the Medicare Benefits Schedule Book which had been issued on 1 November 1999, each of which publicised these matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">74 The committee said that in reaching their findings they had applied their combined professional expertise and had regard to all of the evidence before them including the conduct of Dr Do, and his written and oral answers to the committee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">They made findings as follows:
 
 
 &#8226; Dr Do engaged in inappropriate practice by rendering 80 or more professional attendances on each of the 56 days, and that this constituted a prescribed pattern of services under s 106KA(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">&#8226; The committee did not consider that exceptional circumstances existed that affected the rendering of services by Dr Do on any of the 56 days in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">
 
 DR DO --- THE FINAL REPORT 
 
75 After they had provided Dr Do with a copy of their draft report, he responded with submissions on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">The committee then prepared a final set of responses which were incorporated into the form of the report which I have set out above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">The committee made a number of alterations to the form of the draft report as a result of Dr Do's comments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">The committee identified Dr Do's claim of the combination of factors which he said amounted to exceptional circumstances but said:
 
 'The committee considers that these circumstances could and should have been managed so as to limit the patient numbers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">It does not consider that they constituted exceptional circumstances on a particular day or days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">' 
 
 

The committee said that the legislation made no provision for proving that services were acceptable notwithstanding high numbers on a day and adhered to its interpretation set out above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">DID THE COMMITTEES FAIL TO CONSIDER OR APPLY REG 11(A)?</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">
 
76 The process of judicial review is to do with procedures and observance by those charged with carrying out the procedures required by law, rather than with the substantive outcome: SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592 at 598 [25] per Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">77 As Lander J pointed out in Oreb (146 FCR at 268 [193]) there is always a two step inquiry as to whether exceptional circumstances are made out in accordance with s 106KA(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">The first step is to inquire whether the circumstances relied upon, whether under the ordinary English meaning or one or more of the meanings declared in reg 11, amounted to 'exceptional circumstances'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">If so, the second step is to consider the effect of the circumstances so found on the rendering and initiating of services by the practitioner on the day or days in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">78 It is common ground that there was no express consideration of reg 11(a) by either committee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">At the forefront of the doctors' argument was the fact that the committees failed to conduct any analysis in the terms of, or having regard expressly to, reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">In Lee v Kelly [2005] FCAFC 197 , another decision of Black CJ, Wilcox and Lander JJ decided at the same time as Oreb [2005] FCAFC 196 ; 146 FCR 237 and Hatcher [2005] FCAFC 199 ; 146 FCR 275, Lander J, with whom the Chief Justice and Wilcox J agreed, said at [2005] FCAFC 197 [24] that if a medical practitioner relied on the provisions of s 106KA(2), the committee must satisfy themselves as to whether in doing so the medical practitioner was relying upon 'exceptional circumstances' in its ordinary English meaning or upon either of the sub-paragraphs in reg 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">He pointed out that a medical practitioner could rely on all three, but that would be unlikely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">Lander J observed that it was more likely that the practitioner would rely on only one of the three matters to discharge the onus in s 106KA(2) and continued:
 
 'If, however, the medical practitioner is not able to articulate which of the three separate legislative provisions are relied upon, then the committee must inquire as to whether the factual circumstances advanced by the medical practitioner come within any of the exceptional circumstances in s 106KA(2), or the circumstances in reg 11(a) or reg 11(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">' 
 

79 Lander J held that the general practitioner does not need to establish that the circumstances were the dominant circumstances affecting the rendering or initiating of the services, only that the 'exceptional circumstances' acted upon or influenced the initiation or rendering of the services (see Oreb 146 FCR at 266 [178]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">That was the relevant degree of relationship between the exceptional circumstances and the rendering or initiating of the services which the committees here had to consider.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">Each committee relied on standard paragraphs which explained its view of 'exceptional circumstances'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">But in each of the present cases the committees did not apply that test, because they recited the same paragraphs used by the committee in Oreb [2005] FCAFC 196 ; 146 FCR 237 as the appropriate legal standard by which to assess the conduct of each of Drs Ho and Do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">80 The doctors submit that each of the factors on which they relied before the committees should have been considered individually by them as an occurrence on which reg 11(a) operated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">Thus, for example, the doctors say that their inability to find a suitable replacement doctor was capable of being seen as an unusual occurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">The nature of their practice was, in effect, one in which the remaining two doctors were treating a population of patients which belonged to a practice of three doctors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">That created, so they said, an unusual level of need for professional attendances, in that practice of two.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">81 The committees reasoned that the unusual level of need could have been met by referring the patients elsewhere or somehow through practice management.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">That is true, but the argument does not address the terms of reg 11(a) which refer to the cause of an unusual level of need, not to how the unusual level of need can or should be addressed once it exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">82 Here, each committee began its consideration of what confronted Dr Ho and Dr Do on 4 January 2000 as if they were able to apply practice management techniques so as to render no more than 80 services each on that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">That approach ignored the actual circumstances which existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">It is not usual to begin a new practice after a difficult partnership dissolution in which the two remaining partners must service, from the first day, over 90% of the patients of the practice three partners had previously serviced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">Again, that first day followed the New Year's holiday weekend closure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">Less doctors were then available to deal with patients who presented as patients of their continuing practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">Nor is it in the ordinary course, or regular, that a replacement doctor was not then available, or that market conditions were, at the time, such that replacements were harder than usual to find.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">If it were reasonable to seek to maintain the goodwill and professional approach of the practice while a bona fide search continued for a replacement or extra doctor, there would quite possibly be a higher demand on those practitioners by patients who had confidence in the then members of the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">83 These combined factors were capable of being 'exceptional circumstances' even though they had at the time of the hearing the additional characteristics of being, as Dr Ho's committee said, long term and on-going.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">The 'long term' conclusion was made with hindsight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">It was not so on 4 January 2000, although the earlier history of the practice had begun to skew the workload towards Dr Ho and Dr Do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">And, one reason why the doctors said it occurred, which can be seen with hindsight to have made this 'long term', was their subsequent difficulty in finding a suitable replacement for Dr Nguyen-Phuoc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">Once the replacement was found, a 'normal', not exceptional, situation could be seen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">84 Management of the number of services initiated or rendered by a practitioner is obviously relevant to the assessment of 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(2), but it is not an absolute concept applicable regardless of the other operative circumstances affecting the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">85 The committees argued that they were not required to consider reg 11(a) unless a doctor raised matters that might arguably support the inference.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">But I am of opinion that the doctors did raise circumstances which were capable of being considered as falling within reg 11(a) and the committees failed to undertake their statutory function by not considering them: Lee [2005] FCAFC 197 [24].</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">The doctors raised matters which might arguably have supported the possible application of reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">The committees needed to address the applicability of reg 11(a) in terms if they were to discharge their functions according to law ( Oreb 146 FCR at 242 [15]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">Neither committee did so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">86 To take again the simple example of when Dr Do went home sick on two occasions, leaving Dr Ho as the only doctor at the surgery, it was an unusual occurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">That was capable of being viewed as an unusual occurrence, because it was quite out of the ordinary in the practice, even though from time to time, one of the doctors would be expected to fall sick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">That does not mean that the occurrence is usual.</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">It is in the ordinary experience of life unusual for people to fall sick and be required to go home from work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">Of course it happens, but, when it does, it is a disruption to the routine not only of the person concerned but of those with whom the person works.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">And, when a shortage of personnel occurs in the work place through such an occurrence, the fact of the person going home sick increases the burden on that person's colleagues in the work place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">The fact that practice management or other methods may have been used to address it does not rob the occurrence of its characteristic of being out of the ordinary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">On those days patients presented for medical attention and only one doctor, not two, was available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">87 In the case of a medical practice, the increase in the burden is reflected in the remaining practitioner or practitioners being the only persons available to offer medical services to patients who are presenting on that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">Therefore, by going home sick, Dr Do could have created an unusual level of need for professional attendances from Dr Ho as the remaining medical practitioner in the practice available to see the practice's patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">88 Each of the circumstances relied on by the doctors could have amounted to an unusual circumstance within the meaning of reg 11(a) in itself, or in one or more combinations, and each could have been seen as causing an unusual level of need for professional attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">The cause which reg 11(a) required to be considered was the effect of the relevant occurrence on the ability of each of the two doctors to deal with the practice's workload.</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">Because the committees did not address the application of reg 11(a) at all, they failed to have regard to a relevant consideration or constructively failed to exercise their jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">89 For these reasons, I am of opinion the committee committed a jurisdictional error in this respect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">DID THE COMMITTEES APPLY A POLICY THAT PRACTICE MANAGEMENT OUGHT TO HAVE MET THE CIRCUMSTANCES CLAIMED TO BE EXCEPTIONAL?</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">
 
90 The doctors argued that the committees, in effect, posited that practice management was a panacea to each suggestion of exceptional circumstances which the doctors put forward.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">In Oreb 146 FCR at 240 [6] Black CJ and Wilcox J said that it was for a committee to determine whether the relevant circumstances were truly exceptional, having regard to the usual operation of a practice of a kind conducted by the person under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">They said that in the case of a general medical practitioner the touchstone would be the circumstances ordinarily faced by general practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">They later explained that the committee in that case had expressed a qualified view that 'exceptional circumstances' were seen as most likely to be of an intermittent or episodic nature and did accept 'some extreme on-going circumstance' may be an exceptional circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">Their Honours said that it was for a committee to determine the facts of the case, including whether circumstances advanced by the doctor should be regarded as exceptional, having regard to the usual operation of a general practitioner's practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">In making that determination, they said, a committee might be required to consider whether particular circumstances were foreseeable or avoidable and in relation to that type of situation, there was room for consideration of the way in which a particular practice was managed (146 FCR at 241-242 [13]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">91 Dr Do's case illustrates that considerations of practice management were relevant considerations for assessing the question under s 106KA(2) as to whether exceptional circumstances existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">In the period of nearly six months, almost one-third of the period (56 days) involved Dr Do providing more than 80 services per day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">That was capable of giving rise to an inference that he found himself in a 'usual', rather than 'exceptional', situation (leaving aside the circumstances of the 5 particular days he raised separately).</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">His answer was, however, that the combination of circumstances which were protracted, but essentially temporary, amounted to 'exceptional circumstances'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">92 I am of opinion that each committee did not look at the combination of factors having regard to the statutory test in s 106KA(2) and that they committed an error of law in failing to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">If a three person practice is, for a temporary period, reduced to a lesser number of practitioners, that in itself is capable of being an exceptional circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">It is not the point to say that practice management could change the situation, except if a third doctor were able to be introduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">That was the very difficulty facing Drs Ho and Do in their practices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">They claimed that no third doctor was available for the referral periods, although their case was that they were seeking to recruit one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">So while each committee was entitled to consider how the situation could be managed, it was with respect to the actual practice of the doctors that they needed to address themselves.</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">93 The question of whether or not the committees correctly concluded that the doctors had not satisfied them that exceptional circumstances existed that affected the rendering or initiating of services by the doctors on any one or more of the 24 or 56 days involved a question of mixed fact and law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">Provided that the committee applied the appropriate legal test, ordinarily they would be free to determine the facts for themselves (cp: Oreb 146 FCR at 265 [171]-[173]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">94 The doctors argued that each committee incorrectly applied the test of 'exceptional circumstances' in s 106KA(5) by which I understand them to mean that subs (5) extends the ordinary English meaning of the expression 'exceptional circumstances' to include those declared in reg 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">95 The doctors said that the committees could not take into account questions of practice management in considering reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">They rely on remarks made by Black CJ and Wilcox J in Oreb 146 FCR at 242 [15] when they said:
 
 'That being so, the possible application of reg 11(b) needed to have been addressed by the committee in terms, and in reasoning that was free of consideration (irrelevant in the context of reg 11) of patient management measures that might have been available and desirable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">' 
 

96 Their Honours continued that other matters including patient demand, special needs of the patients of the practice, inability of the practice to obtain or retain additional resources and the individual practitioner's work pattern were relevant to reg 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">They said whether or not the practitioner '... could have better organised his practice was irrelevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">The focus of reg 11 is the need of the patients, not the management skills of practitioners' ( Oreb 146 FCR at 242 [16]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">97 While their Honours were expressing a view on proper construction of reg 11(b) in particular, their observations are of assistance in the construction of reg 11(a) and its operation in the present cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">However, there is one significant textual difference between reg 11(a) and reg 11(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">That is the use of the word 'unusual' in two places in reg 11(a) in contradistinction to the use of the concept of 'absence' in reg 11(b) as the determining factor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">Because 'unusual' is an ordinary English word which involves the making of a value judgment as to departure from a norm, the committees argued that an example given by Kiefel J in Hatcher v Cohn [2004] FCA 1548 ; (2004) 139 FCR 425 at 440 [56] of an epidemic or tragedy involving injury to many people exemplified the correct approach to the construction of an 'unusual occurrence' in reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">But on appeal, Lander J (with whom Black CJ agreed: 146 FCR at 276 [1]) said at 288 [67]-[68]:
 
 
 '[67] Again, it would not be appropriate to attempt to categorise what might be an unusual occurrence or what might be an unusual level of need.</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">The occurrence must be unusual and the level of need must be unusual and be caused by the unusual occurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">Regulation 11(a) provides for circumstances which are like, but not the same as, circumstances which might be "exceptional circumstances" in s 106KA(2) ... 
 
 [68] Again, no more need be said about the paragraph other than because the occurrence must be unusual it must be not usual or out of the ordinary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">Again, because the level of need for professional services which must be caused must be unusual, that level of professional services must be not usual or must be out of the ordinary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">' 
 
 

98 The level of need to which reg 11(a) refers cannot be connected to the way in which the individual practitioner manages his or her practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">The need is that of the patient or patients caused by the unusual occurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">The need in reg 11(a) is 'for professional attendances', that is for services provided by a doctor to more than one patient (see reg 7 which defines 'professional attendance' as meaning a particular service).</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">Patients need services or professional attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">Unless patients present for or request the doctor to see them, no need for professional services could arise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">If, as appears to be accepted in the construction placed on s 106KA(2) by the Full Court in Oreb 146 FCR at 241-242 [13], questions of practice management are relevant, there is a reasonable basis for construing reg 11(a) as not taking such considerations into account, in the same way as the Full Courts approached this matter in relation to reg 11(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">99 I am of opinion that it is not appropriate to put a gloss on the words of reg 11(a) so as to confine the expression 'an unusual occurrence' to the example used by Kiefel J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">Rather, the words are of general application and must be considered for the purpose of reg 11(a) in respect of each situation which a practitioner asserts is an exceptional circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">And just as the ordinary English meaning of the words 'exceptional circumstances' can apply to a combination of circumstances, I am of opinion that the expression 'an unusual occurrence' in reg 11(a) is not to be confined to a singular event, such as an epidemic or an accident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">In legislation, the singular includes the plural in the absence of a contrary intention (see s 23(b) of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">As in many areas of ordinary experience, an occurrence can be the product of a combination of causes and forces.</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">100 The doctors argued before the committee that on Mondays in winter a large number of patients presented for services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">One might infer that they were suffering from normal winter maladies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">But there is a question of judgment involved as to whether such an occurrence is 'unusual'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">By itself it may not be and a properly managed practice may be able to cope with such a demand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">But a practice that is one doctor short in its desired or 'ordinary' manning levels may, again, be faced with 'an unusual occurrence' formed from a combination of 'usual' and predictable circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">It is predictable that if a practice is short one practitioner, it may not be able to comply with the 80/20 rule if a larger number of patients present on particular days (whereas if the extra doctor were present, the practice would comply).</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">The situation in which the practitioners would then find themselves would be unusual (because of the absence of one doctor) and temporary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">And that is so even though the situation drags on because one of its characteristics is the difficulty in locating a suitable recruit to the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">It is not usual for a three practitioner practice to have to service its patients with two practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">101 Another consideration in this regard must be the nature of the practice, its client base, the need to maintain and build the goodwill of patients and the likelihood or not that the situation, involving short staffing, is to continue indefinitely as a 'usual' feature of the practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">A practice which was not short staffed ordinarily would be able to cope with the increased demand on a Monday in winter which the practices of Drs Ho and Do experienced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">The same practice which temporarily lacked one doctor (but was expecting to fill the vacancy and was making bona fide efforts to do so but was frustrated genuinely by the then constraints of the market) is capable of being considered as being subject to 'an unusual occurrence' within the meaning of reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">However, the committees never considered the matter from this perspective.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">And, if either committee were to find that this was 'an unusual occurrence' there was a basis for them also finding that this caused an unusual level of need for professional services from the respective doctor, because of the unusual absence of another doctor in the practice to treat those patients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">102 For these reasons I am of opinion that each committee failed to address the matters they were required to address under reg 11(a) in accordance with law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">SHOULD RELIEF BE GRANTED 
 
103 The committees argued that any error in their application of s 106KA(2) and reg 11 would not have made any difference to the outcome.</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">They asserted that, for example, even if an error had been made in relation to the 3 days that Dr Do was not present at the practice, Dr Ho would still have to establish 'exceptional circumstances' for each of the remaining 21 days in the referral period in respect of him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">104 However, I am of opinion that the way in which the committees approached the application of the tests 'exceptional circumstances' was erroneous and that on any further hearing, a committee will be able to reconsider the whole of the evidence and take further evidence, if so advised, having regard to the proper legal standards to be applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">Each committee followed an incorrect procedure and their decisions were affected by jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">There is no reason why the doctors should not be granted the relief they seek: SZBEL 231 ALR at 598 [25] where Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ said:
 
 'It is, therefore, not to the point to ask whether the tribunal's factual conclusions were right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">The relevant question is about the tribunal's processes, not its actual decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">' 
 

See also Tran v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1229 ; (2006) 154 FCR 536 at 548-553 [56] - [81] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">WAS THERE AN IMPROPER EXERCISE OF POWER BASED ON RIGID APPLICATION OF PRACTICE MANAGEMENT?</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">
 
105 I am opinion, for the reasons that I have given, that each committee misconstrued or failed to apply the tests for 'exceptional circumstances' under s 106KA(2) and reg 11(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">For those reasons I do not consider that this ground arises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">APPARENT BIAS 
 
106 The doctors argued that because the committees focused on practice management as a substantive answer to the doctors' reliance on 'exceptional circumstances', this demonstrated that each committee had an inflexibility of approach which would entitle a hypothetical fair-minded lay person, properly informed as to the nature of the proceedings or process, reasonably to apprehend that each committee might not have brought an impartial mind to making the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">In deciding that question, the Court determines the issue objectively: Hot Holdings Pty Ltd v Creasy [2002] HCA 51 ; (2002) 210 CLR 438 at 459 [68] per McHugh J citing Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex Parte H [2001] HCA 28 ; (2001) 75 ALJR 982 at 990 [28] ; [2001] HCA 28 ; 179 ALR 425 at 434-435 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">107 Because I am of opinion that each committee made an error of law in their approach, as explained above, I am not satisfied that an apprehension of bias would be perceived by the hypothetical fair-minded lay person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">Rather that person would consider that the committee was applying a wrong view of the law to its task and there is no reason to think that if properly instructed as to the law to be applied, the committee would not reapply itself appropriately to the issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">108 However, I am more troubled about the question raised late in the argument that each of the committees has been the active respondent in the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">Each of the committees submitted that there was no other respondent who had a right of appearance and that the committees were the only proper respondents in proceedings brought for judicial review of their decisions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">109 I do not consider this to be a correct view.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">There is no doubt each of the committees is a proper and necessary party to such proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">After all, it is their decision which is challenged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">If the Court were to make an order, it must make one in favour of or against the members of the committee whose decision is the subject of the proceedings for judicial review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">110 The members of the tribunal are the relevant officers of the Commonwealth for the purposes of the proceedings and it is necessary that they be joined as parties to the proceedings: SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 at 173 [43] per McHugh J, 185-186 [91] per Gummow J, 199 [153] per Kirby J, 204 [180] per Hayne J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">Here, the tribunal took what the High Court said in The Queen v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal; Ex Parte Hardiman [1980] HCA 13 ; (1980) 144 CLR 13 at 35-36 was an unusual course of contesting the doctors' case for relief by presenting a substantive argument.</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">Gibbs, Stephen, Mason, Aickin and Wilson JJ said:
 
 'In cases of this kind the usual course is for a tribunal to submit to such order as the court may make.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">The course which was adopted by the Tribunal in this Court is not one which we would wish to encourage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">If a tribunal becomes a protagonist in this Court there is the risk that by so doing it endangers the impartiality which it is expected to maintain in subsequent proceedings which may take place if and when relief is granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">The presentation of a case in this Court by a tribunal should be regarded as exceptional and, where it occurs should, in general, be limited to submissions going to the powers and procedures of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">' 
 

111 The third respondent, now known as the Medicare Australia CEO, in a case like the present has an interest in defending the conduct of proceedings by a committee established under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">Such proceedings are initiated by a reference from the Medicare Australia CEO under s 86(1) and a final determination made by the determining authority is conveyed to the Medicare Australia CEO pursuant to s 106W.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">If for some reason in proceedings it is not appropriate to join the Medicare Australia CEO as the intended active respondent, the proper respondent must be the Minister administering the Health Insurance Act 1973 (Cth) for the time being.</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">He or she is the officer of the Commonwealth who has the immediate interest in ensuring the due administration of legislation for which he or she is responsible under administrative arrangements and s 64 of the Constitution of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">112 It is not satisfactory that the decision of a committee can be challenged, including on the basis that there is an apprehension of bias alleged against them, and have to defend themselves actively in proceedings of this kind, for the reasons given in Hardiman 144 CLR at 35-36.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">Moreover, the fact that each committee has defended its own interpretation of the legislation and their dismissal of the doctors' cases would suggest to a fair-minded lay person that they will find it difficult entirely to put out of their mind the approach which the Court in proceedings such as this finds to be erroneous if they were to come to reapply themselves to the task.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">Not everyone, especially a body which has actively defended themselves in contested litigation, would be able to approach the task anew, unaffected by the forensic demonstration of their previous error of approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">Moreover, there is no reason here not to order them to pay the doctors' costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">A fair-minded lay person would be entitled to think that the committees here would not have the equanimity of Sir Winston Churchill, who said:
 
 'In the course of my life, I have often had to eat my own words, and I must confess that I have always found it a wholesome diet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">' 
 

113 That is not to suggest any adverse view about the members of either of the two committees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">There is no reason to doubt that they would try to apply the law as the Court has declared it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">But it is unsatisfactory that having actively sought to uphold a view of the law and their conclusions adverse to the doctors, the same committees should then be called upon to reconsider the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">114 The second aspect of procedural fairness or natural justice is that a person should not be a judge in his or her own cause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">Here, each committee has acted as a protagonist in this Court in their own cause and they now suggest they should be returned to the position of being a judge, in the sense of a lay tribunal charged with functions of administrative decision-making, in the same cause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">That is an unsatisfactory outcome which should not occur unless it is necessary under the legislation: see Laws v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal [1990] HCA 31 ; (1990) 170 CLR 70 at 81-82 per Mason CJ and Brennan J, 96 per Deane J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">I am of the preliminary opinion that it is not necessary, but I will hear the parties, if they desire, on whether I should make orders of the following nature:
 
 
 (a) An order in the nature of a writ of prohibition in the first instance issue prohibiting each of the first respondents from further constituting Professional Services Review Committee No 295 [293].</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">(b) An order in the nature of a writ of mandamus issue requiring the fourth respondent to reconstitute Professional Services Review Committee No 295 [293] to further consider the referral made on 13 December 2001 under s 86 of the Health Insurance Act 1973 (Cth) in accordance with law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">
 

115 For the reasons I have given, each committee made a jurisdictional error and the doctors are entitled to relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">I certify that the preceding one hundred and fifteen (115) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares.</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">Associate:
Dated: 26 March 2007

 Counsel for the Applicants: MA Robinson 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Tress Cox 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: RM Henderson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Minter Ellison 
 
 Date of Hearing: 21, 22 September 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 26 March 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/388.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>