<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIMO v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 515 (20 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/515.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">protection visa</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">no jurisdictional error</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 BUCHANAN J: 
 
1 The appellant is a citizen of the People's Republic of China who arrived in Australia on 18 September 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The next day he applied for a protection (class XA) visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">His application was refused by a delegate of the first respondent on 20 October 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 On 14 November 2005 he applied for a review of the delegate's decision by the Refugee Review Tribunal ('the RRT').</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The RRT handed down a decision on 14 February 2006 affirming the decision of the delegate not to grant a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 On 13 March 2006 the appellant made an application for judicial review to the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">That application was dismissed by Emmett FM on 4 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">By a Notice of Appeal filed on 19 December 2006 the appellant appeals to this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">4 The application for judicial review - as filed in the Federal Magistrates Court - had four grounds:
 
 '1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">RRT failed to carry out its statutory duty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 
 
 RRT failed to consider my application according to Section s.424A of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">RRT failed to notify me in writing about the reasons RRT may affirm the decision from DIMIA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">RRT had bias against me when considering my my [sic] application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">RRT refused my application without giving rasonable [sic] foundation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">RRT failed to refer to sufficient independent information for the consideration of my application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">' 
 
 

5 In an amended application filed on 4 July 2006 a single ground was advanced --- namely: 'The Tribunal failed to carry out its statutory duty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">' 
 
6 A number of particulars were provided which may be reduced to the proposition that the Tribunal failed to comply with s 424A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) because it must have used information contained in the appellant's visa application as part of the reason to dismiss his application for review and had failed in its duty to bring the information to his attention and invite his comments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">7 Section 424A provides:
 
 '(1) Subject to subsection (3), the Tribunal must: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) give to the applicant, in the way that the Tribunal considers appropriate in the circumstances, particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the decision that is under review; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) ensure, as far as is reasonably practicable, that the applicant understands why it is relevant to the review; and 
 
 


 
 
 
 (c) invite the applicant to comment on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">
 
 
 
 
 (2) The information and invitation must be given to the applicant: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) except where paragraph (b) applies --- by one of the methods specified in section 441A ; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) if the applicant is in immigration detention --- by a method prescribed for the purposes of giving documents to such a person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">
 
 
 
 
 (3) This section does not apply to information: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) that is not specifically about the applicant or another person and is just about a class of persons of which the applicant or other person is a member; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) that is non-disclosable information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">' 
 
 
 
 

8 To examine the allegation made in the amended application for judicial review some discussion of the decision of the RRT is necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The appellant gave oral evidence to the RRT on 12 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The RRT decision records that, at the hearing, he 'essentially repeated his claims' made in his visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It then recorded further information obtained from the appellant at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">9 The appellant's claims were that in April 2005 he was arrested, detained and then tortured whilst in detention because he was found in possession of documents left with him by a business acquaintance, Mr Chen, which documents related to an unregistered religious group in China known as the 'Shouters'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">These claims were accepted by the RRT, they were not used to decide any matter adversely to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">10 The RRT also referred to some independent country information to the effect that the authorities in China were intolerant of unregistered religious groups, the Shouters was regarded as a cult by the Chinese authorities and was banned and religious activities were 'targeted' but:
 
 '... those reports indicated that it was only active religious activists who attracted the adverse interest of the authorities in China and the information did not support his claim that persons such as himself, that is persons who were not actively involved in religious activities, risked the adverse interest from the authorities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">' 
 

11 Independent country information was not required by s 424A to be disclosed to the appellant because it was not specifically about the appellant or another person (see s 424A(3)(a)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">12 The basis of the RRT's decision adversely to the appellant was that, despite his two week detention in April 2005, there was no indication the appellant had been of any interest to the Chinese authorities either before or after that period and as the appellant 'stated that he has no interest in religious activities' the RRT was 'satisfied that he is not involved or implicated in any activity which will attract the adverse interest of the PRC authorities in the reasonably foreseeable future'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">13 On these grounds the RRT was not satisfied the appellant had a well-founded fear of persecution in China for reason of religion or any other Convention reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">14 The information upon which these findings were made was provided by the appellant at the hearing and was not required to be given back to him in writing for his comment (see s 424A(3)(b)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">15 The matters I have referred to are, in substance, the reasons given by Emmett FM at paras 24 and 25 of her judgment for rejecting the sole ground in the appellant's amended application for judicial review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">No error has been, or could be, shown in that conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">16 Despite the limited ground of challenge in his amended application for judicial review, and the fact that, by that amended application, he had effectively abandoned any allegation of bias, at the hearing before Emmett FM the appellant gave voice to such an allegation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">He also suggested that the RRT made its decision 'on suspicion and a guess', that the RRT had wrongly assessed he was not a member of the Shouters group (but he had never said he was --- he said he was not interested in religion or religious activities) and that the RRT had misunderstood the risk from the Chinese authorities' perception that he was close to Mr Chen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">17 Emmett FM rejected all these allegations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">She was correct to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">None had any apparent substance and some were contradicted by evidence the appellant himself gave to the RRT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">18 The appeal to this Court advances three grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">They are:
 
 
 '2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The Tribunal failed to consider my application according to S424A of the Migration Act 1958 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The Tribunal did not notify me the reason or part of the reason for affirming the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">
 
 
 
 
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The Tribunal failed to consider my claims for my application for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The Tribunal failed to consider my application according to S91R of the Migration Act 1958 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">
 
 
 
 
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The Tribunal failed to refer to independent information for the consideration of my application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">' 
 
 

19 The first ground was correctly rejected by Emmett FM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">20 The second ground contains two allegations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The first is without any merit and obviously wrong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">The second limb is, as the first respondent's counsel submits, misconceived.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Disposition of the appellant's claims did not raise an issue requiring consideration of s 91R of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">This appears to be a currently fashionable ground of appeal but it has no application to the present matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">21 The third ground has no basis in fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">The RRT did refer to independent country information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Some supported the appellant's claims, some did not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The RRT explained the use which was made of the information.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">As earlier discussed, it was not required to be put to the appellant for his comment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">22 At the hearing of the appeal the appellant, through an interpreter, in effect, repeated the matters set out in the Notice of Appeal but added as well that the RRT was biased.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Mr Frew, who appeared for the first respondent relied on the written submissions he had filed and added, as to the allegation of bias, a reference to para 29 of the judgment of Emmett FM where her Honour said:
 
 'The applicant also contended this morning that the Tribunal was biased, however, no particulars were provided and there was no evidence to support such a contention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">' 
 

23 The same may be said for the allegation made to me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">24 When he was invited to add anything further the appellant indicated he had not seen a copy of the written submissions for the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">He was shown a copy of a letter addressed to him dated 28 February 2007 from solicitors for the first respondent telling him of the time and place of the hearing of the appeal and stating that a copy of the written submissions were attached thereto.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">He accepted seeing the letter but not any attachment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">25 A copy of the written submissions for the first respondent was then provided to him and the matter was stood down so that they could be read to him as translated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">26 When the hearing resumed the appellant did not specifically address the first respondent's written submissions but added to his earlier remarks, that the RRT had wrongly assumed he would not be persecuted if he returned to China where he had in fact been earlier persecuted for religious activities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">I understood these remarks to relate to the matters he had relied on before the RRT and to suggest the RRT had reached a wrong conclusion about them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">For the reasons I have already given I am not satisfied that any relevant error has been established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">27 I am satisfied the appellant was not denied a fair opportunity to advance any argument he wished in support of his appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">28 The challenges to both the decision of the RRT and the judgment of Emmett FM are without substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">No jurisdictional error has been shown in the work of the RRT.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">No error has been shown in the judgment of Emmett FM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">29 I will dismiss the appeal with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">I certify that the preceding twenty-nine (29) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Buchanan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Associate:

Dated: 20 April 2007 


 The Appellant is self represented 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr Stephen Free 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Ms Zoe McDonald of DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 5 March 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 April 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/515.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>