<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Lee [2007] FCA 508 (11 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/508.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">investigation by asic</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application for orders under s 1323 of the corporations act 2001</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">principles to be applied</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 Australian Securities and Investments Commission is conducting an investigation to discover who is behind a fraudulent trading scheme that has come to its attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">It appears that Australian investors have been induced into purchasing non-existent "heating oil options", "gasoline options" and "gold bullion options" on non-existent foreign commodities exchanges.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">All in all, investors have been cheated into paying around $8 million dollars for these bogus investments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The money investors have paid was transferred into three foreign bank accounts, one in the name of Capital Marketing Services, another in the name of Universal Trading, both with the Hong Kong branch of the Bank of China, and a third in the name of AM Global Management with the Kuala Lumpur branch of the AmBank (M) Berhad.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">A small portion of the money found its way (by transfer) into Australian bank accounts maintained by each defendant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">On 17 November 2006, on the ex parte application of ASIC, I made orders freezing the Australian bank accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Four days later the orders were continued and an additional order was made freezing other accounts and restraining any dealing with an asset one defendant had purchased with the money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The orders were again extended on 19 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Following a hearing on 29 January 2007, the orders were continued pending trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">What follows are my reasons for making the last order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">2 First, the factual background.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Not much is known about the defendants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The first defendant, Mr Lee, lives in Malaysia, at least according to the records of his Australian bankers, Westpac and ANZ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">He may have travelled to Australia on one or two occasions in the past.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Mr Lee maintains several accounts with ANZ and Westpac.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In the period February to September 2006, over $2 million was transferred into his Westpac accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The money came in by electronic funds transfer of amounts not exceeding $100,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Most transfers were effected by a "cash dealer located in Singapore known as the Colombo Exchange".</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">A small sum, $48,964.94, has been traced back to the Universal account with the Bank of China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Over a similar period (March to November 2006) around $1.6 million was transferred into Mr Lee's accounts with the ANZ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">This amount was also paid by regular deposits of less than $100,000 in most instances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">An amount of approximately $90,000 came from the Capital Marketing Services account with the Bank of China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">3 Following the ex parte orders, the court papers were sent by ASIC to Mr Lee at his address in Malaysia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">A few days later Mr Lee (or someone who purported to be Mr Lee) responded to ASIC by email.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The person said that the information in the papers was "totally new and shocking to me".</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">He said that ASIC "can be assured that I will contact you within the next 24 hours after I have go [sic] through all the attachments and probably seek a legal representative in Australia to represent my interest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">" This was followed up a few days later by a second email in which Mr Lee (or the person purporting to be Mr Lee) said that he was in the process "of engaging a top firm in Melbourne to represent [him] in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">" He went on to say: "Also I asked you to properly investigate this case especially in Malaysia, Hong Kong and Australia (cold calling as mentioned in those attachments).</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Please do not simply jump to conclusion about myself / 1 st defendant in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">Myself runs an IT company in Malaysia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">"
 
4 In due course Mr Lee retained Melbourne solicitors, Baker &amp; McKenzie, to act on his behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The solicitors took up with ASIC its investigation into Mr Lee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">In a letter dated 20 December 2006 the solicitors informed ASIC that they would not advise their client "to participate in [ASIC's] investigations in any way unless ASIC [could] confirm in writing that [Mr Lee was] not and [would] not be a subject in any criminal or civil penalty investigation and unless and until [ASIC gave] undertakings to that effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">" ASIC was not willing to give the undertaking.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Accordingly, Mr Lee has not provided ASIC with any information concerning the money in his accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">5 Mr Lee took much the same attitude on the interlocutory application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">That is, he elected to remain silent, filing no affidavit or other material explaining how he came to have in his accounts funds some of which it would seem had been stolen from Australian investors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">6 ASIC is continuing its investigation into Mr Lee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The investigation has disclosed that Mr Lee has several foreign bank accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The accounts that have been tracked down so far are in Vietnam, Hong Kong and the United States of America.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Large sums of money (in the millions of dollars) have been deposited into the accounts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">In all more than $A7.5 million has been deposited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">ASIC's inquiries suggest that the source of the funds is the same Singaporean cash dealer who deposited money into Mr Lee's accounts with Westpac and ANZ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">More information is likely to be discovered about Mr Lee as the investigation progresses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">7 The second defendant, Mr Jugraj, lives in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">He came here as a student.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Mr Jugraj has an account with the Commonwealth Bank.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Between 23 October and 1 November 2006, three deposits, totalling approximately $90,000, were made into the account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">The source of the funds was the Bank of China account maintained by Capital Marketing Services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Mr Jugraj informed ASIC that the deposits were arranged by his father, an Indian citizen who lives in Chennai.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">He told ASIC that the purpose of the funds was to support his application for permanent residence in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">He said that he believes his father used the services of a finance broker in Chennai to arrange for the funds to be deposited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The money has been used by Mr Jugraj to purchase Northern Territory Treasury Corporation bonds in the amount of $100,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">The bonds are still in his name and the orders I made on 21 November 2006 included an order that Mr Jugraj not deal with the bonds pending the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">8 The source of the power to make the restraining orders sought by ASIC is s 1323(1) of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) which, relevantly, provides that where an investigation is being carried out either under the Australian Securities and Investments Commission Act 2001 (Cth) or the Corporations Act in relation to an act or omission by a person (referred to as the "relevant person") that constitutes or may constitute a contravention of the Corporations Act and the court "considers it necessary or desirable to do so for the purpose of protecting the interests of a person (... called an aggrieved person) to whom [the relevant person] is liable, or may be or become liable, to pay money ... the Court may ... make one or more of the following orders:
 
 
 
 
 (d) an order prohibiting a person who is indebted to the relevant person... from making a payment in total or partial discharge of the debt to... [the relevant person]; 
 (e) an order prohibiting a person holding money... on behalf of the relevant person... from paying all or any of the money, or transferring, or otherwise parting with possession of the financial products or other property, to... the person on whose behalf the money... is... held; 
 (f) an order prohibiting the taking or sending out of [the] jurisdiction... by a person of money of the relevant person...
 
 

9 It is also necessary to mention s 1323(3).</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">By that subsection the court is given power to make an interim order under s 1323(1) if "in the opinion of the court it is desirable to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">" The orders I made, for which these are the reasons, were interim orders made under s 1323(3).</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">10 Before explaining the reasons for making the orders, I will make some preliminary observations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">First, the evidence, which is unlikely to be contradicted when this case comes on for final hearing, is that there have been serious breaches of the Corporations Act , the ASIC Act and both Commonwealth and State Crimes Acts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">This is not surprising given the nature of the fraud that has been perpetrated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The principal (although, I accept, not the only) purpose for the investigation is to identify the perpetrators so that they may be prosecuted and track down the money that investors have been cheated into parting with so that it may be returned to them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">11 Second, one of the several objects of s 1323 is to assist people who have lost money, as a result of breaches of the Corporations Act or ASIC Act, to recover what they have lost either in specie (which will often be impossible) or by way of damages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The section achieves this object by permitting, by way of injunction or the appointment of a receiver, the preservation of property against which the person who has lost money (the aggrieved person) can have recourse if he has a good personal or proprietary claim against the person who has taken his money (the relevant person).</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">12 Nevertheless, and this is the third observation, the remedies available under s 1323 are dramatic and the court should exercise care before making any order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">While it is not necessary to show that the aggrieved person in fact has a case against the relevant person in order to obtain an interim injunction, the strength of the case is important.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">If the investigation is in its early stages it may be enough to show a possible case against the relevant person or the person on whose behalf the relevant person holds property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">If the investigation is in late stages, or has been completed, probably no order should be made (or continued) unless the evidence suggests a prime facie case of liability: see generally Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Walker (1987) 11 ACLR 884; Corporate Affairs Commission (SA) v Lone Star Exploration NL (No 2) (1988) 14 ACLR 499; Australian Securities Commission v A S Nominees Ltd (1995) 18 ACSR 459, 511-512.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">13 The final observation concerns the "jurisdictional pre-conditions" that are imposed by s 1323.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Here I am not referring simply to the three conditions referred to in s 1323(1) that were commented upon in Corporate Affairs Commission v United International Technologies Pty Ltd (1987) 6 ACLC 637, 642.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">I have in mind what might also be described as a "jurisdictional pre-condition" namely the requirements in paras (d) (e) and (f) that a protective order can only be made in respect of "[indebtedness]... to the relevant person or [his] associate" (para (d)), "[any] money, financial or products or other property [held] on behalf of the relevant person or [his] associate" (para (e)) and "money of the relevant person [or his associate]" (para (f)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">At a final hearing of an application under s 1323 it will be necessary for ASIC to prove on the civil standard that one of these conditions exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">When an interim order is sought this is not a requirement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">All the court need do is decide whether it is "desirable" that an interim order be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">And it may be desirable even if ASIC is not able to tender proof that will establish the existence of any one of the conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">By analogy with cases on interlocutory injunctions, if ASIC can show something like a possible or prima facie case that will usually be enough.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">14 Returning to the case at hand, the interim orders were made for the following reasons: As I have said, it appears not to be in dispute that some of the money paid by investors has found its way into each defendant's account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">I infer from this that each defendant was either involved in the fraud or holds money on behalf of a person who was involved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The inference is more readily drawn by the fact that neither defendant has gone into evidence to explain how he came by money from the Universal or Capital Marketing Services accounts in Hong Kong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">In these circumstances the investors might have good claims against each defendant, or in respect of the funds in each defendant's possession, and are entitled to a protective order to preserve those funds until the matter is more fully investigated at the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">
 
 I certify that the preceding fourteen (14) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Finkelstein.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">Associate: 


Dated: 11 April 2007


 Counsel for the Plaintiff: M Sifris SC
J Moore 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Australian Securities and Investments Commission 
 
 Counsel for the First Defendant: J Delany SC
A Hanak 
 
 Solicitor for the First Defendant: Baker &amp; McKenzie 
 
 Appearing for the Second Defendant: Praveen Kumar Jugraj (in person) 
 
 Date of Hearing: 9 February 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 April 2007 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/508.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>