<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rana v University of South Australia [2007] FCA 816 (31 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/816.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">advertisement</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">where respondent advertised event to public</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether advertisement amounted to offer</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether any payment made to respondent by applicant in relation to event</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether contract arose</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether any loss or damage established.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">misleading and deceptive conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">claim that respondent breached s 52 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">applicant refused entry to event</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether advertisement of event to public amounted to misleading or deceptive conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">whether statements made by employee of respondent to applicant amounted to misleading or deceptive conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">claim for damages under s 82 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth).</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">injunctive relief</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">injunction sought in relation to claims in contract and under trade practices act .</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">contract</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c15">trade practices</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c16">remedies</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is a proceeding in the original jurisdiction of this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 Mr Ranjit Rana claims damages against the University of South Australia ("the University") and he relies on two causes of action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">First, he claims that the University contravened s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ("the Act ") and that he is entitled to damages under s 82 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Secondly, he claims that he entered into a contract with the University, which it breached, and that, as a result, he is entitled to damages from the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">In addition to his claim for damages, Mr Rana claims an injunction against the University, restraining it from banning him from attending any public functions held by it in the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 Mr Rana appeared in person and he gave evidence in support of his case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">He did not call any witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The University was represented and it called a number of witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">All witnesses swore affidavits, and the affidavit or affidavits of each witness, for the most part, constituted the evidence in chief of that witness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Each witness was cross-examined by the opposing party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">4 For reasons which I will give, I find that Mr Rana was a most unsatisfactory witness and I do not accept his evidence except where it accords with other evidence which I accept.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">It is sufficient to say at this point that Mr Rana's evidence as to important events changed during the course of the proceedings, some of his evidence was highly improbable and a good deal of his evidence was inconsistent with evidence which I accept.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 I find that each of the witnesses called by the University was honest and straightforward, and I accept each witness as a witness of truth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6 It is convenient, before dealing with any other matters, to summarise Mr Rana's case against the University as set out in his statement of claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">In doing that, I will also set out those matters which are common ground between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Mr Rana's case as set out in the statement of claim 
 
7 Mr Rana's claim arises out of events which allegedly took place on Monday 27 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">8 It is common ground that on that day the University held an event at the Adelaide Convention Centre ("the Convention Centre").</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The event was what the University called a "hypothetical" and it involved a discussion about the prospects of Australian businesses exporting wine to the Asian market.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The hypothetical involved seven panellists each with differing areas of either interest or expertise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The hypothetical was conducted from 6.30 pm to 8.30 pm or thereabouts and, as advertised, there were "drinks and nibbles" from 5.30 pm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The ticket price was $45, with University alumni, staff and students entitled to a discount.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">A person who purchased nine tickets received an additional ticket free of charge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">9 An advertisement for the hypothetical appeared in The Australian newspaper on 27 March 2006 and it stated that if a person wanted to "book" for the hypothetical he or she could contact Ms Melissa Ellmers on a telephone number provided, or visit the University's website.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The evidence of Ms Ellmers suggests that to "book" in the context of the advertisement and the hypothetical meant to purchase tickets by credit card or cheque.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">10 It is common ground that Mr Rana saw the advertisement to which I have referred and that he contacted Ms Ellmers, who was an employee of the University, by telephone and discussed attendance at the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">He went to the Convention Centre in the early evening of Monday 27 March 2006, but he was refused entry to the hypothetical by another employee of the University, Ms Helen McIver.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">11 Mr Rana's case (as pleaded in his statement of claim) is that when he spoke to Ms Ellmers, she promised to provide him with ten tickets and he said that he would pay $35 for each ticket "as a member of the University of South Australia's alumni".</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">His case is that he went to the Convention Centre and that at about 5.20 pm he gave Ms McIver the sum of $350.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Ms McIver did not give Mr Rana the tickets "as promised by Melissa Ellmers".</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">Mr Rana's case is that Ms McIver called security guards and "SA Police" and told them that Mr Rana had been banned from all University functions for being a troublemaker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">12 Mr Rana's case is that the University was involved in trade or commerce as it had promoted the hypothetical by the advertisement in The Australian newspaper on 27 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">His case is that the University's conduct was misleading or deceptive in that he was not allowed to attend the hypothetical "for the public as advertised in the national newspaper".</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Not only was he misled, but his case is that the security guards and police officers were also misled because of what Ms McIver said to them about him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">In addition, Mr Rana's family and friends were also misled or deceived.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Mr Rana alleges that he was induced to buy the tickets by the University's conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Mr Rana's plea of loss and damage is in the following terms:
 
 "The applicant has suffered loss or damage by the respondent's conduct, in that he suffered humiliation, embarrassment, loss of reputation and face and aggravation of paranoid schizophrenia by the ban placed in that function as described above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The total amount for the loss and damage is A$1000000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">"
 

13 In addition, Mr Rana alleges in his statement of claim that the events described above gave rise to a contract between him and the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">He alleges that Ms Ellmers agreed that he would be provided with ten tickets for $35 each.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">He claims that under the contract he would attend the Convention Centre, pay the money and receive the tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The contract was an "oral and implied contract".</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">14 Mr Rana's case is that the contract was breached by the University when it banned him from attending the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">He paid for the tickets, but the money was not returned to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">He claims that he was disparaged in front of his guests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Mr Rana claims the same loss and damage for the alleged breach of contract as he claims for the alleged contravention of s 52 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">15 In his statement of claim, Mr Rana also alleges that the University breached a deed of settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Mr Rana tendered a deed of settlement and a release between himself and the University dated 2 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">It appears from the deed that Mr Rana had two proceedings in this Court against the University and that under the deed he agreed to discontinue the proceedings and in return the University agreed to pay Mr Rana a sum of money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">There is an allegation in the statement of claim that, by its conduct on 27 March 2006, the University breached a term of the deed, although it was unclear by the end of the case whether this allegation was still being pursued by Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">In any event, I have read the deed of settlement and release and, having regard to my findings of fact, it does not appear to me that any conduct of the University on 27 March 2006 constituted a breach of a term of the deed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">An aspect of the University's case 
 
16 It is convenient at this stage to note one important point about the University's case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In its defence, the University alleged that Ms McIver believed that Mr Rana was not permitted to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">In her affidavit filed and served pursuant to orders of the Court made before the trial, Ms McIver referred to previous dealings she had had with Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">On an interlocutory hearing, Mr Rana sought from the University further and better discovery of documents relating to his previous dealings with the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">After an adjournment to consider its attitude to the application, the University decided that it would not lead any evidence of its previous dealings with Mr Rana, or evidence from Ms McIver as to the effect those dealings had on her decision to exclude Mr Rana from the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">In those circumstances, I refused the application for further and better discovery of documents relating to Mr Rana's previous dealings with the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Although Mr Rana cross-examined Ms McIver as to some aspects of his previous dealings with the University, by and large, the trial proceeded without evidence from Ms McIver as to the precise reason or reasons she refused to allow Mr Rana entry to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Findings of fact 
 
17 It is convenient to start by mentioning the evidence of Ms Annabel Jane Mansfield who was a witness called by the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Ms Mansfield was employed by the University and she held the position of Coordinator of Marketing and Alumni in the Business Division Office.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">She was responsible for the promotion and marketing of the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">She understood that the hypothetical was open to anyone who wished to attend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">She understood that it was to be a public event held on private property and open to any fee-paying member of the public who was interested in attending.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">She approved the final form and content of the advertisement for the hypothetical which appeared in The Australian newspaper on 27 March 2006 and which Mr Rana said he read.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">18 As I have said, it is common ground that there was a telephone conversation between Mr Rana and Ms Ellmers on 27 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">I accept Ms Ellmers' account of that conversation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">I will now summarise that account and, at the same time, it is convenient to summarise her evidence of later events which I also accept.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">19 Ms Ellmers was employed by the University and she held the position of Resource Administrator for the School of Management.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">She was responsible for obtaining registrations for the hypothetical and that included answering telephone inquiries about the event and taking credit card bookings in advance of the event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Ms Ellmers was doing those things on the basis, as she understood it, that the hypothetical was open to the public.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">20 Ms Ellmers was subject to direction by Ms McIver.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">21 Ms Ellmers was contacted by Mr Rana by telephone at between 3.30 pm and 4.00 pm on 27 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">She did not know Mr Rana and had not spoken to him before.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">22 Mr Rana asked about the price for attendance at the hypothetical and Ms Ellmers told him that the full price was $45 per person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">There was then a discussion about the discount available to alumni members of the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Ms Ellmers obtained details of Mr Rana's name and telephone number.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Ms Ellmers told Mr Rana that he could pay by credit card by providing his details to her, or by cash.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Mr Rana did not wish to pay by credit card and he said that he would pay by cash.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Ms Ellmers said that she would see Mr Rana at the registration desk at the Convention Centre where he could pay cash for his ticket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">There was never any mention by Mr Rana of a desire or wish to purchase ten tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">Ms Ellmers did not at any time refer to Ms Kellie Willason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">23 
 
Some time after Ms Ellmers had finished her telephone conversation with Mr Rana, Ms McIver came into her office and saw that she had noted Mr Rana's details.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">She told Ms Ellmers that she was concerned about Mr Rana attending the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">At some point, she told Ms Ellmers that she would be denying Mr Rana entry to the event and that if he approached Ms Ellmers she should refer him to her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">24 Ms Ellmers left her place of work and arrived at the Convention Centre at about 5.00 pm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">She went and sat at the registration desk at the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">She saw a person, who Ms McIver later told her was Mr Rana, enter the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">She saw Ms McIver have a conversation with Mr Rana and she was later told by Ms McIver that during the conversation she had told Mr Rana that he was not permitted to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Ms Ellmers said that the conversation was brief and not heated and that there were very few other people in the foyer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Mr Rana was alone and he left the Convention Centre alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">He was not escorted out by any other person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">25 Ms Ellmers was the only person who dealt with cash payments and the issuing of receipts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">Mr Rana did not pay her any money and the receipt which he produced to the Court (discussed in [26] and [27] below) was not the type of receipt used for cash purchases of tickets for the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">26 I have already summarised Mr Rana's case (as set out in the statement of claim) in relation to his telephone conversation with Ms Ellmers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">In his affidavit sworn on 28 March 2006 (Exhibit A1) he repeats those allegations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">In his affidavit sworn on 10 April 2006 he states that he sent the sum of $350 for the tickets to Ms Ellmers and that a receipt was given to "us" by her representative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">He exhibits a copy receipt to his affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The copy receipt is undated and is numbered 151719.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">It shows the purported payment of the sum of $350.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">I will refer to this document as the "copy receipt".</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">27 The University conducted a search in relation to a receipt numbered 151719.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">It called evidence, which I accept, of a search of the University records conducted by Ms Rachel Watherston, and the discovery of a carbon copy receipt numbered 151719 and dated 15 August 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">That receipt relates to the payment by Mr Rana of the sum of $50 in relation to an "MBA Application 05888756741".</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">I am satisfied on the evidence in this case that Mr Rana never paid any amount to the University in relation to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The copy receipt exhibited to Mr Rana's affidavit sworn on 10 April 2006 was, according to the evidence of Ms Ellmers, which I accept, not the type of receipt used by the University in relation to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Having regard to all the evidence in this case, I am satisfied that the copy receipt is a document Mr Rana prepared by making certain additions and deletions to the receipt dated 15 August 2002 or another copy thereof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">Of course, that conclusion reflects very badly on his credit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">28 Mr Rana claims that after his telephone conversation with Ms Ellmers he sent an electronic message or email to Ms Ellmers and received a response and that he later (at about 3.00 pm) received a voice message on his message bank from Ms Ellmers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">I do not accept that evidence because it is inconsistent with the evidence of Ms Ellmers as to what occurred on 27 March 2006 and her movements on that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">29 In his affidavit sworn on 17 July 2006, Mr Rana refers to paying for the tickets at the "student admission office" and that Ms Ellmers had told him that he was to tell the cashier at the office that the payment was to be directed to Ms Kellie Willason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">I reject that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">I accept the evidence of Ms Ellmers that she had only one telephone conversation with Mr Rana on 27 March 2006, and that she made no reference to Ms Willason or to payment at a place other than the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">I also accept the evidence of Ms Kellie Willason that she was in no way involved with the hypothetical held on 27 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">30 There is more to be said about the topics of Mr Rana's allegations that he paid for tickets and of the events at the Convention Centre, but it is convenient to do that in the context of discussing the evidence of Ms McIver.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">I accept Ms McIver's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">31 Ms McIver was employed by the University and she held the position of School Executive Officer in the School of Management.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">The School of Management was responsible for organising the registration and payment in relation to the hypothetical and Ms McIver was responsible for supervising this process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">As she understood it, the hypothetical was open to members of the public who paid the required fee and it was a marketing exercise on the part of the University and its Division of Business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">She was aware that Ms Ellmers was answering inquiries and taking registrations for the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">She went into Ms Ellmers' office at about 4.30 pm on 27 March 2006 and saw that Mr Rana had expressed interest in attending the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">A short time afterwards, Ms McIver went to the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">At the Convention Centre she decided that she would not allow Mr Rana to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">Mr Rana arrived at the Convention Centre at 5.00 pm.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">He was alone and there were very few people at the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">There were no security guards or police officers present.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">32 Ms McIver had a conversation with Mr Rana which lasted for only a minute or two.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Mr Rana identified himself and said that he had come to register for the event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">He did not mention anything about registering for other people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">Ms McIver said words to the effect of:
 
 "I'm sorry but I can't allow you to the event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">"
 

Mr Rana asked Ms McIver to explain why and, in response to this question, Ms McIver said:
 
 "I think you know why.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">"
 

Mr Rana repeated his question and Ms McIver said words to the effect of:
 
 "I won't let you in given your past history with the Division.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">"
 

33 Mr Rana said that he would sue the University and then left.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">Neither party raised their voice during the conversation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">Ms McIver could smell alcohol on Mr Rana's breath.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">34 Mr Rana did not give any cash to Ms McIver and she did not see him give cash to anyone else.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">35 Mr Rana left the building alone and although Ms McIver tried to contact the security office she could not get through.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">She did not call the police.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">36 It will be recalled that in his statement of claim, Mr Rana alleged that he gave Ms McIver the sum of $350 for tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">He repeated this assertion in his affidavit sworn on 28 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">As I have said, in later affidavits his story changed and Mr Rana said that he paid the sum of $350 to the cashier at the "student admission office".</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">In cross-examination, Mr Rana was asked to explain this apparent change in his evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">His answer was incredible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">He said that both accounts were true and that what he had paid to Ms McIver was a further sum of money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">His evidence is not clear as to the quantum of the further amount he says he paid to Ms McIver.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">His version of events is incredible and I do not believe it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">It is difficult to believe that Mr Rana would in effect pay twice, and very difficult to believe that Ms McIver would accept money from Mr Rana and then refuse him entry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">As I have said, Ms McIver was an honest and straightforward witness and she said, and I accept, that she did not receive any money from Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">37 It will also be recalled that in his statement of claim, Mr Rana said that he mentioned to Ms Ellmers that he wished to purchase ten tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">For the reasons I have given, I do not accept that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Nor do I accept Mr Rana's assertion (in his statement of claim) that he went to the Convention Centre with a party consisting of his family and friends.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">His evidence as to where his party of family and friends was at the time of his conversation with Ms McIver is unclear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">I am satisfied that Mr Rana went to the Convention Centre alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">That was the evidence of Ms Ellmers and Ms McIver, and his evidence, when asked in cross-examination about the number and composition of his party, was most unsatisfactory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">38 The tenor of Mr Rana's evidence was that a number of security guards and police officers were involved in the events surrounding his departure from the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">In addition to the evidence of Ms McIver that no security guards or police officers were involved, the University called Mr Richard Trevor Pieper, who was employed by the Adelaide Convention Centre as Security Manager.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">I accept Mr Pieper's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">Mr Pieper had dealings with the University's employees in relation to the hypothetical, although he said he is unable to remember their names.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">He spoke to an employee, probably Ms McIver, who told him she did not want Mr Rana to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">He advised Ms McIver that as the individual had not yet paid for his ticket, she could refuse him entry to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">Mr Pieper was not able to leave a member of his security staff at the hypothetical and he left Ms McIver with two numbers to telephone if there was any trouble.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">Neither his staff nor the external security service provider was contacted in relation to the hypothetical and neither was required to take any action in relation to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">39 I find that neither security guards nor police officers were involved in Mr Rana's departure from the Convention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">40 As part of his case, Mr Rana tendered in evidence email messages which he asserts were sent to him after the hypothetical by employees of the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">The email messages are said by Mr Rana to contain admissions by the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">The relevant email messages are as follows:
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">An email message from Ms McIver to Mr Rana, allegedly sent on 29 March 2006, which suggests that the University received the sum of $350 from Mr Rana in relation to the hypothetical (exhibit "D" to Mr Rana's affidavit sworn on 10 April 2006).</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">An email message from Ms Kellie Willason to Mr Rana, allegedly sent on 24 April 2006, which suggests that the University received the sum of $350 from Mr Rana in relation to the hypothetical and wished to return it (exhibit "A" to Mr Rana's affidavit sworn on 1 May 2006).</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">An email message from Ms McIver to "Sapol.enquiries@police.sa.gov.au", allegedly sent on 14 July 2006, making very serious allegations against Mr Rana (exhibit "Rana 4" to Mr Rana's affidavit sworn on 17 July 2006).</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">

41 I am satisfied from the evidence of Ms McIver, Ms Willason and Mr Kevin Roger Dronfield that none of these email messages were sent by the persons alleged to have sent them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">Ms McIver and Ms Willason each denied sending the email said to have come from them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">Mr Dronfield is employed by the University in the position of Information Technology Security Specialist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Although he has no formal qualifications in information technology, he has a good deal of practical experience.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">He has worked in the University's Information Technology department since 1978 and he has worked exclusively in the information technology field for more than 28 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">He states, and I accept, that the email messages referred to in 1 and 2 above were not sent from the University's email system, that they appear to have been sent from an email address which he identified and which suggests a link with Mr Rana, and that the face of the email message has been altered at the time of sending to make it appear that it originated from the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">He expressed the same conclusions in relation to the email message referred to in 3 above, save that he could not identify the source of the message.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">I accept Mr Dronfield's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">In my opinion, he had sufficient knowledge and experience gained from his employment in the field of information technology for approximately 28 years to conduct the investigations and express the views which he did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">42 Mr Rana sought to counter Mr Dronfield's evidence by giving evidence that he had closed his email account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">Furthermore, he gave evidence that police officers had seized his computer and, when it was returned, the hard drive did not work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">Mr Rana's evidence on these topics was very confusing and there is nothing in it to suggest that my conclusions as to the email messages are incorrect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">I should say that I am satisfied from Mr Rana's cross-examination that he had not closed his email account at the relevant time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">43 The University employees previously referred to did not send the email messages and Mr Rana was the only person who had an interest in making it appear that they had done so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">In light of the evidence which I have accepted, I find on the balance of probabilities that Mr Rana sent the three email messages referred to above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">44 My findings of fact reflect the evidence put forward by the University and I have rejected many of the factual assertions made by Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">Nevertheless, it remains necessary for me to consider whether the claims made by Mr Rana are made out having regard to the findings of fact which I have made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">It is convenient to start with Mr Rana's claim based on an alleged breach of contract.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">The alleged breach of contract 
 
45 Mr Rana did not purchase a ticket or tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">He did not pay any money to the University in relation to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">Ms Ellmers did not promise Mr Rana ten tickets or, indeed, any tickets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">My findings as to the content of the conversation between Ms Ellmers and Mr Rana are set out in [22] above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">In my opinion, Ms Ellmers did no more than provide information to Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">Those conclusions mean that Mr Rana's case in contract as pleaded must fail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">46 Nevertheless, it is appropriate that I consider whether it is possible to characterise the advertisement which appeared in The Australian newspaper on 27 March 2006 as one of those offers made to the public at large and capable of acceptance by the performance of an act which also constitutes the performance of the relevant contractual obligation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">In this case, can it be said that there was such an offer, reinforced perhaps by the statements made by Ms Ellmers during her telephone conversation with Mr Rana, that Mr Rana accepted and performed by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket?</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">In my opinion, the advertisement and the statements made by Ms Ellmers would not be understood by a member of the public as an offer which was to be acted upon and a reasonable reader of the advertisement would have understood that a member of the public would have no right of entry until a booking was made, or a person presented himself at the Convention Centre and actually purchased a ticket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">Of course, even with a ticket, there may be terms, express or implied, enabling the University to deny entry to the ticketholder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">47 This case is distinguishable from Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256 and the reward cases such as Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101; see also R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">In this case, having regard to the form and content of the advertisement, the reference to booking and the nature of the event, it cannot be said that there was an offer capable of acceptance merely by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">In my opinion, the decision in Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701 is distinguishable on the ground that the nature of a railway timetable is quite different from the advertisement in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">Furthermore, it is commonly understood that the circumstances in which a train cannot carry a passenger are far more limited than the circumstances in which a member of the public is denied entry to an event such as that involved in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">In any event, I prefer the reasoning of Crompton J in Denton v Great Northern Railway (supra) who doubted that the defendant was answerable in contract (5 E and B 867-870; ER 704-705).</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">48 Even if (contrary to my finding) there was a contract and a breach of contract, Mr Rana has failed to prove any loss or damage flowing from the breach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">The failure to prove any loss or damage means that I do not need to consider whether the types of loss claimed by Mr Rana are, in law, recoverable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">49 As far as what might be called reliance loss is concerned, as I have said, I am satisfied that Mr Rana did not pay any money to the University in relation to the hypothetical and there can be no recovery on that ground.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">Furthermore, Mr Rana did not seek to establish any loss or damage suffered as a result of travelling to the Convention Centre in the expectation of being admitted to the event and there can be no recovery on that ground.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">50 Mr Rana's claim for loss or damage by way of psychiatric injury fails because there is simply no proof of psychiatric injury.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">Mr Rana gave no evidence as to his psychiatric condition and he called no medical evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">51 Mr Rana's claim for loss of reputation and face, including humiliation and embarrassment, fails because, as I have said, I am satisfied that the conversation between Mr Rana and Ms McIver was a measured and relatively quiet one; that no one else was present during the conversation and certainly not any family or friends of Mr Rana, and that Mr Rana left the Convention Centre quietly and without an escort.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">He was not escorted out of the Convention Centre by security guards or police officers or, indeed, by anyone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">Furthermore, Mr Rana was not emotionally distressed or, at least, not openly so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">In fact, he had the presence of mind to calmly tell Ms McIver during his conversation with her that he would be suing the University.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Mr Rana referred to the decision in Baltic Shipping Co v Dillon [1993] HCA 4 ; (1993) 176 CLR 344, but there is no evidence of disappointment or emotional distress, even if it was otherwise an appropriate case for such an award.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">The alleged contravention of s 52 of the Act 
 
52 The University admits that it is a corporation within s 52 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">Furthermore, the University did not argue that its conduct on 27 March 2006 was not in trade or commerce.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">53 The first question is whether any conduct of the University on 27 March 2006 was misleading or deceptive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">As I understood Mr Rana's case, the conduct which he alleged was misleading or deceptive was the insertion of the advertisement in The Australian newspaper and the statements made by Ms Ellmers during her conversation with Mr Rana on the telephone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">The contents of the advertisement are clear, and I have accepted Ms Ellmers' account of her conversation with Mr Rana as the correct one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">54 Mr Rana was denied entry to the hypothetical and it was this that led him to assert that the University's earlier conduct was misleading or deceptive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">55 Mr Rana's case was that the advertisement contained an implied statement or representation about entry to the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">In my opinion, the statements made by Ms Ellmers add nothing to the impression created by the advertisement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">As I have said, Ms Ellmers did little more than provide information about the hypothetical to Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">56 The University submits that any implied statement or representation in the advertisement was as to a future matter (ie entry to the hypothetical) and that there was no evidence that the University made any such statement or representation knowing it was untrue, or reckless as to whether it was true or false.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">It submits that, insofar as Mr Rana relies on s 51A of the Act to establish that such representation as was made was misleading, it has established that Ms Mansfield, who approved the final form and content of the advertisement, and Ms Ellmers, who made the statements she did, had reasonable grounds for making the implied statement or representation in that both had a genuine belief that the hypothetical was open to any member of the public who paid for a ticket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">The University submits that it was another of its employees, Ms McIver, who made the decision to deny Mr Rana entry to the hypothetical and that this decision was made after Ms Ellmers' conversation with Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">It seems to me that this submission may raise some complex issues.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">Bearing in mind that Mr Rana was not represented and, therefore, I did not have the benefit of full submissions on both sides of the issue, and as I am able to decide the claim under s 52 on another ground, I prefer not to express an opinion on this submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">57 In my opinion, neither the advertisement nor Ms Ellmers' statements during her telephone conversation with Mr Rana contained or gave rise to an implied statement or representation as to the right of a member of the public to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">In saying that, I am directing my attention to the period prior to the purchase of a ticket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">On purchase of a ticket there will be contractual rights and obligations between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">It is well established that even when a ticket is purchased, the right of a ticketholder, should there be a breach, is reflected in a claim for damages rather than a right to enter or stay on land ( Cowell v Rosehill Racecourse Co Ltd [1937] HCA 17 ; (1937) 56 CLR 605).</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">In any event, in relation to the period prior to the purchase of a ticket, the advertisement or statements of Ms Ellmers do not contain or give rise to an implied statement or representation as to the right of a member of the public to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">Clearly, there cannot be any implied statement or representation that there is an unqualified right because there might be any number of reasons why the organiser of an event might justifiably deny a person a ticket or entry to the event, ranging from the cancellation of the event or a full auditorium on the one hand, to disruptive conduct or inappropriate dress by the proposed attendee on the other.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">No reasonable reader of the advertisement or party to the conversation with Ms Ellmers would understand that, prior to the purchase of a ticket, any member of the public had an unqualified right to attend the hypothetical.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">To my mind, it is not possible to conclude that there is an implied statement or representation as to a right of a more limited nature, for example, a right to enter subject to a good reason to exclude, because there would simply be no unanimity, or even a majority view, as to the particular circumstances which would justify the exclusion of a member of the public.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">58 Even if I am wrong in reaching the conclusions set out above and the University has contravened s 52 of the Act , Mr Rana's claim for damages under s 82 must fail because he has not proved any loss or damage within the provisions of that section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">I need do no more than refer to my conclusions as to loss and damage in the context of Mr Rana's claim for breach of contract ([46]-[50]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">59 Mr Rana's claim for damages for an alleged contravention of s 52 of the Act fails.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">The claim for an injunction 
 
60 On my findings and conclusions, Mr Rana has not established a breach of contract or a contravention of s 52 of the Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">For this reason, his claim for an injunction should be refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">There are probably a number of other reasons why it would not be appropriate to grant the injunction sought by Mr Rana but, in the circumstances, it is not necessary to discuss those other reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">Conclusion 
 
61 The proceeding must be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">I will hear the parties as to costs and any other orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">I certify that the preceding sixty-one (61) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">Associate:

Dated: 31 May 2007
 The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr M Douglas with Mr T Martin 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Minter Ellison 
 
 Date of Hearing: 6 October 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 31 May 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/816.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>