<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Intertax Property Investments Pty Ltd v Karger [2007] FCA 928 (15 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/928.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">consideration of an application by liquidators of the applicant for leave to discontinue the proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">corporations law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 By this application, the liquidators of the applicant seek leave to discontinue proceedings pursuant to O 22, r 2(1)(d) of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The brief background facts are that on 25 August 2006, the Supreme Court of Queensland ordered that the applicant in the proceedings be wound up and that Matthew Leslie Joiner and Gerald Thomas Collins be appointed as liquidators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The liquidators have considered the proceedings before this Court and have formed the view that it is not in the best interests of the creditors of the applicant company that the proceedings be pursued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Accordingly, the liquidators seek leave to discontinue the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The proceedings are made up of a large number of parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">2 The background to the various orders made in the proceedings to date is briefly this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On 14 April 2005, the application was filed naming the first eight respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">On 15 April 2005, the ninth to 12 th respondents were joined by order of Kiefel J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On 27 May 2005, judgment was entered for the applicant against the fifth respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">On 30 August 2005, the applicant discontinued the proceedings against the fourth, eighth, 10 th and 11 th respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">On 6 September 2005, the applicant filed a statement of claim against the first, second, third, ninth and 12 th respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">3 On 13 April 2006, the applicant discontinued the proceedings against the first, third and ninth respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Although named in the proceedings, the proceedings do not appear to have been pursued against the 6 th and 7 th respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Consequently, the proceedings remain on foot only in respect of the second and 12 th respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The application is supported by an affidavit of Damien Roger Butler filed 3 May 2007 and an affidavit of Meredith Bennett deposing to service of the application on the second and 12 th respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">At to the 12 th respondent, the position is that on 27 April 2007, the 12 th respondent was deregistered by the Australian Securities and Investment Commission ('ASIC').</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">In response to being served with the current application, ASIC indicated that it does not oppose the application nor the orders sought by the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">4 The applicant has not received any response from the second respondent and the second respondent has not appeared before the Court this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The second and 12 th respondents filed a defence in the proceeding on 30 September 2005 and an amended defence on 1 November 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">I am satisfied, for the purposes of the rule that leave ought to be given to discontinue the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I am also satisfied that the appropriate order in the circumstances is that there ought to be no order as to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The discontinuance of the proceedings by the liquidators is due to their objective assessment of the merits of the proceeding and the step to be taken to best serve the interests of the creditors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Accordingly, 
 
5 I will make no order as to costs and grant leave to discontinue the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Associate:

Dated: 15 June 2007
 Counsel for the Applicant: Applicant - not represented by counsel 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Ms M Bennett, Deacons Solicitors 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: No appearance 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: No appearance 
 
 Date of Hearing: 15 June 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 June 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/928.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>