<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kennedy v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 932 (15 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/932.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for leave pursuant to s 14zzo of the taxation administration act 1953 (cth) to amend an objection in relation to an appealable objection decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">taxation</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 I have before me six applications by each applicant in the following proceedings, namely, QUD61/2007 Jennifer Maree Kennedy v Commissioner of Taxation ; QUD62/2007 Jennifer Maree Kennedy v Commissioner of Taxation ; QUD63/2007 Rodney John Kennedy v Commissioner of Taxation ; QUD64/2007 Rodney John Kennedy v Commissioner of Taxation ; QUD65/2007 Kennedy Haulage (Qld) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation ; and QUD66/2007 Kennedy Haulage (Qld) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation , for the exercise of the Court's discretion under s 14ZZO of the Taxation Administration Act 1953 (Cth) ('TAA') for leave to amend the grounds of objection made by each applicant in a taxation objection in relation to an appealable objection decision to an assessment issued by the Commissioner of Taxation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 Leave is sought to introduce the following further ground:
 
 'The decision to assess penalty made under Div 298 in schedule 1 to the Taxation Administration Act 1953 (TAA) was not duly made in accordance with law, is thereby a nullity, and is thereby excessive within s 14ZZO TAA in that no debt is owed to the Commonwealth under it: McAndrew v FC of T [1956] HCA 62 ; (1956) 98 CLR 263'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">
 
 

3 The respondent does not oppose the making of the order in each application although the respondent makes it plain that the proposed ground is contested and will in part constitute the controversy between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">4 Accordingly, I propose to grant leave to amend the ground of objection in each application in the above terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">5 I propose to make the following further directions:
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The applicant has leave pursuant to O 16 of the Federal Court Rules to deliver interrogatories to the respondent in relation to the assessment to penalty
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The applicant has leave to deliver any interrogatories upon which the applicant proposes to rely on or before 28 June 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The respondent shall answer the applicant's interrogatories (subject to proper objections) by 20 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The respondent shall file and serve any Amended Statement of Facts, Issues and Contentions on or before 20 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The applicant shall file and serve a Notice to Admit Facts and Documents on or before 3 August 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The respondents shall file and serve a response to the Notice to Admit Facts and Documents on or before 17 August 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The applicant shall file and serve a Statement of Facts, Issues and Contentions and any Affidavits upon which the applicant intends to rely at the hearing of the appeal in relation to the appealable objection decision on or before 31 August 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The matter shall be re-listed for review at 9.30am on 10 September 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The costs of the application and directions hearing are to be reserved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The parties have liberty to apply to the Court on two days notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">
 


 I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Associate:

Dated: 15 June 2007

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr M Robertson 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Hartnett Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Respondent represented by Solicitors 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Ms K Lynch, Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 15 June 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 June 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/932.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>