<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZCBT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCA 9 (12 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/9.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">relocation principle</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether tribunal applied the correct test in finding that the applicant did not have a well-founded fear of persecution for a convention reason</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">relocation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether tribunal considered the possibility of future persecution</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">ambit of the tribunal's obligations to consider future persecution upon relocation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The appellant is a Coptic Christian lawyer, who is a citizen of Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">He claims that he was persecuted in Egypt because of his religion, because he was a member of a particular social group (namely Christian lawyers) and because he was a member of the liberal political opposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">His application for a protection visa was rejected by a delegate of the respondent and by the Refugee Review Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">His application for review of this decision to the Federal Magistrates Court was dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 In his evidence given to the Refugee Review Tribunal, the appellant made graphic claims of persecution in the form of beatings and threatened torture as well as more generally discriminatory conduct from both the community and police officers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The appellant claimed that he was the deacon of his Coptic church and, in late 2000, was also acting as its legal adviser in relation to the proposed purchase of adjoining property that the church wished to acquire for expansion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">He claimed that in December 2000 he was beaten by a group of men who were attempting to prevent the sale of the adjoining land to the church.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">He suspected that they were motivated by Muslim fanaticism.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 The appellant claimed that shortly after this incident, the local mosque began broadcasting sermons and prayers as well as a Muslim radio station at very high volume from a loud speaker only four metres from his balcony .</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">At the same time, his Muslim neighbours also began tuning in to the same Muslim radio station and loudly playing its broadcasts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The noise was so loud that the house shook and he could not hear his phone calls.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">He claims that this behaviour was directed at him and that his Christian neighbours knew this and declined to get involved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">4 In 2001, the appellant became active in an opposition political party and began to complain publicly, including by writing numerous letters of complaint about the inequality between Christians and Muslims in Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">He also lodged a complaint with the Minister for Religious Houses about the loudspeaker outside his home.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">In June 2001, the appellant claims he was detained by Egyptian police for three days without food or water and that he was periodically beaten in this period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The appellant claimed that following his complaint about this conduct to the Egyptian authorities a police officer called him and told him that the problems he was experiencing would stop if he would convert to Islam.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The appellant claims that in July 2001 police took him from his home to a police station where they held him for some days and attempted unsuccessfully to torture him by electrocution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">He said that he was released after he paid a bribe of five hundred Egyptian pounds and told the officer that he wanted to convert to Islam but needed some time so that he could persuade his parents to convert as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The Tribunal's decision 
 
5 The Tribunal accepted that the appellant is an Egyptian national and is a Coptic Christian.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The Tribunal expressly noted that it considered the appellant's application on the basis of the oral testimony he gave at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The Tribunal regarded the appellant as having given this evidence, 'fully, frankly and coherently'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The Tribunal noted that the appellant did not mention at the hearing some matters referred to in his visa application however, because that application had been prepared with the assistance of a lawyer who no longer acted for the appellant, the Tribunal disregarded those claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">6 It is clear that the Tribunal had significant misgivings about some aspects of the appellant's account of his experiences in Egypt, describing some aspects as 'implausible' and others as 'quite incredible'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The Tribunal rejected the appellant's claim that Coptic Christian lawyers were a particular social group in Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The Tribunal also did not accept that the appellant faced persecution because of his membership of the liberal political party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">From the appellant's account of his experiences the Tribunal found that his political activities were generally directed towards religious issues and concluded that any persecution that the appellant may have suffered would have been because of his religion rather than his political affiliation or profession.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">For that reason the Tribunal stated that it would deal with the application on the basis that the appellant claimed to fear persecution based on his religion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">7 The Tribunal accepted that the appellant had been assaulted in the street and that this incident could have been associated with the proposed purchase of land for the Church but was satisfied that this was an isolated incident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The Tribunal said:
 
 'In the circumstances, I am not satisfied that this incident, of itself, constitutes Convention persecution, or demonstrates a failure on the part of the authorities to provide protection to the applicant, or gives rise to a well founded fear of persecution in the foreseeable future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">' 

8 The Tribunal did not attach any significance to the failure of the police to apprehend the perpetrators as, on the appellant's own account, the information he gave to the police was incomplete.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The Tribunal also rejected the appellant's account of the incident involving the connection of a loudspeaker just outside his home:
 
 'I must say that I find the applicant's account of these events quite extraordinary and far-fetched.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">While he may genuinely believe that he was a victim of a conspiracy involving the mosque ... and all the Muslim residents of the street, I cannot accept that the events occurred as the applicant described them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">It is simply implausible that anyone in the street could bear the noise created if these events had in fact occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">' 

9 On other issues it is not entirely clear whether the Tribunal accepted the appellant's account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It said, for instance, that it accepted that the appellant 'may have' embarked on a campaign of letter writing and that it 'is possible' that this led to his unlawful detention in June 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The Tribunal also accepted that he 'may have' been beaten as claimed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Perhaps the Tribunal did not feel it needed to make a firm finding on these claims because it was of the opinion that 'the police were acting as rogue individuals, and not in a manner sanctioned by the state'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The Tribunal's explanation for why the 'rogue' police acted as they did was similarly tentative:
 
 'I consider it plausible that someone in one of the government agencies which was the subject of a complaint by the applicant may have organised this incident in order to teach this perceived troublemaker a lesson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">' 

10 The Tribunal rejected the appellant's evidence about the police officers' attempt to torture him and about his negotiating his release on the promise of converting to Islam.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">In particular the Tribunal found the notion that he was able to stall the police for four months on the pretext of attempting to convert his parents 'inherently implausible' and did not accept that these events 'happened as he claims'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">It is not clear from this statement whether the Tribunal rejected the whole of this account or only some of the details.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">11 Ultimately the Tribunal did not accept very much of the appellant's account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Moreover it clearly regarded those experiences that it did accept had occurred as the actions of some rogue police and as a very local problem:
 
 'At the highest, I accept that the applicant was the victim of some police harassment in his place of residence .</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">I accept that his religion may have been an element in this victimisation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">' 
 (emphasis added) 
 
 

12 While it is difficult to assess the degree of importance the Tribunal attached to these incidents in terms of their predictive capacity for future persecution should the appellant be returned to Egypt, it was sufficient for the Tribunal to be moved to consider the possibility of relocation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">This gives the question of relocation greater significance than it would otherwise have had.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">In any event, the Tribunal was satisfied that the appellant could avoid these local problems by relocating within Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">
 'When I asked the applicant if there was any reason why he would not be able to relocate to avoid his local problems, he identified no reason why he would [sic] unable to do so, except to say that the law is the same everywhere and that the police would get him wherever he went.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">He did not suggest that he would attract new harassment by continuing to engage in the same kinds of activity as he had in the past.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">On the applicant's own evidence, he has not broken any law, so no question arises of him facing any legal sanction applicable anywhere in Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Given that the applicant is well educated, a lawyer, and a male with family support, and in the absence of any information put forward by the applicant as to why he would be unable to relocate within Egypt, I am satisfied that it would be reasonable for him to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">I am also satisfied that he would thereby be able to avoid any problems he has faced in Giza, which I am satisfied are locally based and confined to local individuals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">I do not consider that the applicant has established for himself a national profile as a political or religious activist by his work in Giza, his membership of the Liberal Party, or his letter writing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">I find that he obtained a reputation, locally, as a troublemaker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">I do not consider that the local police or authorities would pursue the applicant to another city, or inform the authorities there of his presence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">' 
 The Federal Magistrate's decision 
 
13 The appellant sought review of the Tribunal's decision in the Federal Magistrates Court, relying on two grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">First, it was submitted, the Tribunal erred in failing to address the appellant's claims, in particular of persecution for his membership of the Liberal Party, for his membership of the particular social group made up of Coptic Christian lawyers and for his alleged apostasy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Secondly, it was submitted that the Tribunal erred in misapplying the test for relocation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">14 The Federal Magistrate rejected the appellant's first submission, noting that the Tribunal did not regard Coptic Christian lawyers as a particular social group and referring to the Tribunal's finding that the appellant's problems emerged as a result of the religious focus of his political activities and its findings about the circumstances surrounding the appellant's detention and alleged attempted torture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">15 In respect of the second ground of appeal, the appellant submitted that the Tribunal merely asked whether the applicant might be able to relocate, rather than whether he could or whether it would be reasonable to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The Federal Magistrate summarised the Tribunal's approach to this issue as follows:
 
 'The Tribunal's reasons disclose that it: 
 
 a) understood that the basis for the principal [sic] of relocation is that a refugee is somebody who has a well founded fear of persecution in his/her country rather than in any particular area of the country; 
 b) noted the applicant could relocate to another area of Egypt, for example Cairo or Alexandria; 
 c) considered the reasons for which relocation might not be reasonable including asking the applicant why relocation [sic] why he could not relocate; 
 d) weighed the issues as to whether relocation was reasonable --- including that the applicant was well educated and a male with family support; and 
 
 e) concluded that it was reasonable for the applicant to relocate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">' 

16 The Federal Magistrate found that the Tribunal's conclusion as to relocation was open to it, and that in reaching this conclusion the Tribunal correctly applied the test for relocation: Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">This appeal 
 
17 Before discussing the submissions made on appeal, I should mention one puzzling aspect of the Tribunal's reasons, namely the inconsistency between dates of various incidents described by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">The Tribunal records that the appellant gave evidence that he was arrested twice in 2001 (in June and July) and that he left Egypt some four months after the second arrest, that is in late October 2001; however the material in the appeal book shows, and the Tribunal's opening paragraph records, that the appellant arrived in Australia on 25 October 2002 and that his application for a protection visa was lodged on 9 January 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">There is no suggestion that the appellant came other than directly to Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Although the Tribunal mentioned that a psychologist who examined the appellant referred to the appellant's account as being one of detention and torture in 2002 the Tribunal did not dwell on this point and, as mentioned above, the Tribunal specifically stated that it was relying only on the account that the appellant gave at the hearing; see [5] above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">18 The appellant's primary submission in this Court is that the Federal Magistrate erred in failing to find that the Tribunal misapplied the test for relocation, and in doing so made a jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">I agree with this submission and, in general, with the submissions made by counsel for the appellant, Mr O'Donnell.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">19 The Tribunal's assessment that the appellant's problems were localised coupled with his level of education and family support led the Tribunal to conclude that it would be reasonable for the appellant to relocate to another part of Egypt; see [12] above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The Tribunal thought it likely that the appellant had been perceived locally as a trouble maker and, in the passage quoted at [12], above the Tribunal made the important finding that 'the local police or authorities would [not] pursue the applicant to another city, or inform the authorities there of his presence'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">20 In the appellant's submission, this approach demonstrated that the Tribunal was distracted from the question that is at the heart of any enquiry as to whether a person is a refugee, namely does the person have a well-founded fear of future persecution should that person be returned to their own country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">This is the crucial issue and, as Gummow and Hayne JJ have noted, persecution in the past is neither necessary nor sufficient for an affirmative answer to that question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">A person could have a well-founded fear of persecution even if there is no likelihood that those responsible for past persecution would be able to mete out similar treatment in the future or even if there had been no persecution in the past; Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473 at [72] - [74] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">21 It must be emphasised here that it is the prospect of return to the applicant's own country not to a particular part or parts of that country that must be considered; Randhawa at 440.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Provided that it is reasonably practicable for the person claiming refugee status to relocate with safety to another part of that country then it cannot be said that the person has a well-founded fear of persecution in that country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">In such a case a finding that relocation meets these criteria will be a (or the) critical element in the determination of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Irrespective of the Tribunal's scepticism about aspects of the appellant's claims, is clear that the Tribunal's view as to the appellant's ability to relocate within Egypt with comparative ease was a critical element in its decision that the appellant did not have a well-founded fear of persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">22 The Tribunal's consideration of the relocation issue logically raised three separate questions:
 
 (a) If the appellant relocated elsewhere in Egypt, would he face persecution from those who had targeted him previously?</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">(b) Had the appellant's persistent campaigning against religious inequalities given him a national profile, such that others in Egypt would persecute him even if he relocated ?</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">(c) If the appellant relocated elsewhere in Egypt, would he continue to engage in campaigns against religious inequality?</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">If so, would this conduct lead others in Egypt (or even just in the area to which he relocated) to persecute him?</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">

23 The Tribunal clearly addressed questions 1 and 2 above and answered them adversely to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Counsel for the Minister submitted that the third question was effectively answered by the Tribunal's statement: 
 
 'He did not suggest that he would attract new harassment by continuing to engage in the same kinds of activity as he had in the past.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">' 

24 This comment must be considered in the context of the exchange that the Tribunal had with the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">The Tribunal reported the exchange thus:
 
 'I asked the applicant whether he thought that he might be able to relocate to another area of Egypt, and avoid any problems with the local police in Giza.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">He replied that the police and the law about conversion is the same all over Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">I suggested that this assumed that the police in Giza would find out where he was and notify the local police.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">He said that wherever he goes they will get him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">' 

25 It is clear from this exchange that the Tribunal's questions were specifically directed to the local problems and whether the appellant could escape those local problems by relocating.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">They were focused on the consequences of past conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">As reported by the Tribunal there was nothing in the exchange that would have directed the appellant's mind to his future activities and their consequences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">26 The Minister urged a 'beneficial' construction of the Tribunal's reasons and referred to comments made in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259, in particular at 271-272.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">The phrase 'beneficial construction', as used in Wu Shan Liang has a specific meaning, and was certainly not intended to mean that any ambiguity in the Tribunal's reasons be resolved in the Tribunal's favour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Rather, the construction of the Tribunal's reasons should be beneficial in the sense that the Tribunal's reasons would not be over-zealously scrutinised, with an eye attuned to error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">In this sense a 'beneficial' approach to the Tribunal's reasons does not require this Court to assume that a vital issue was addressed when there is no evidence of this and, indeed, the general thrust of the Tribunal's comments suggest that the issue was overlooked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">27 The Minister did not accept that the Tribunal had overlooked an essential issue and submitted that the scope of the Tribunal's obligation to consider future persecution of an applicant if relocated is determined by the appellant's claims and the material before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The Minister relied upon the judgment of Black CJ in Randhawa at 443:
 
 'I agree that it would ordinarily be quite wrong for a decision-maker faced with a relocation possibility to take the general approach that there must be a safe haven somewhere without giving the issue more specific attention, but the extent of the decision-maker's task will be largely determined by the case sought to be made out by an applicant .</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">' 
 
 (emphasis added) 

28 In the Minister's submissions much was made of the fact that the relevant conduct of the appellant consisted of letter writing and the Tribunal could not be expected to investigate the possibility of the appellant facing persecution for his letter writing, which is not an activity that one would expect to provoke persecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">This is, with respect, a somewhat disingenuous submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">The appellant was not engaged in writing social letters; the Tribunal described him as embarking on 'a campaign of letter writing' which included letters of complaint to government departments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">29 Here, the questions of whether the appellant would continue his campaign of letter-writing in the future, and whether this conduct would lead to persecution elsewhere in Egypt, necessarily arose on the material before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">It was the appellant's letter writing that the Tribunal accepted may have led to his unlawful detention by Giza police for three days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">The Tribunal accepted that the appellant may have been beaten during this detention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">It is no answer to say that letter writing per se is not an activity that tends to provoke violence --- the Tribunal had accepted that this was a possibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">30 The Tribunal found that the appellant had a reputation as a troublemaker and that it was likely that this was at the root of his past treatment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">That being so it was not sufficient to find that those responsible for that treatment would not seek him out in other parts of Egypt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">It was necessary for the Tribunal to ask if the appellant is likely to continue with the conduct that marked him as a troublemaker in the past and, if so, whether that conduct would, in the future, evoke a similar response from others.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The Tribunal is not entitled to base its prediction on an expectation that the appellant will modify his behaviour on his return to Egypt; Appellant S395/2002 at [40] per McHugh and Kirby JJ and at [80]-[82] per Gummow and Hayne JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">31 The appeal must be allowed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">I certify that the preceding thirty-one (31) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Stone .</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Associate:
Dated: 12 January 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: B O'Donnell 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: R Francois 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 11 December 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 12 January 2007 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/9.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>