<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cram v Registrar, Administrative Appeals Tribunal [2007] FCA 965 (19 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/965.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application purportedly for an order of review against administrative appeals tribunal for failure to return documents</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">motion to dismiss proceeding on basis no reasonable prospect of success</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">held: proceeding dismissed as no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">practice &amp; procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application purportedly for an order of review against the Administrative Appeals Tribunal for failure of the Registrar of that Tribunal to return all documents tendered by Mr Cram in a matter heard and determined by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The respondent filed a notice of appearance and by that notice submitted to any order of the Court save as to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Notwithstanding that, and at my request, the Australian Government Solicitor has taken some trouble in this matter to assist Mr Cram in seeking to recover from the Tribunal the documents which he believes ought to have been returned to him and has attended before this Court on at least three occasions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">I have sought to explain to Mr Cram on more than one of those occasions that his application does not appear to disclose a reasonable cause of action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Notwithstanding that, Mr Cram has not been willing to bring this proceeding to an end.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 A notice of motion has now been filed by the respondent for the proceeding to be dismissed pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) on the basis that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The motion is listed for hearing today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 Mr Cram has today objected to my sitting and has suggested that his application should be heard by the Full Court because of the position of Downes J who both holds a commission on this Court and is the President of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">As no decision of Downes J is the subject matter of the application, I do not accept that the Court is not properly constituted to exercise the original jurisdiction of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">5 Mr Cram has also sought to file in Court a notice of objection to competency, in which objection is taken to my personal competency, and a notice of appeal against decisions made by me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">No final orders have, at this stage, been made by me in this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">I advised Mr Cram that he would need to take these notices to the Registry if he wished to take any further steps in respect of them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Further, Mr Cram has made allegations of abuse of power by me and suggested that I am acting in collusion with the respondent to damage his position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">I do not accept the validity of the accusations made by Mr Cram.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I am not willing for those or any reasons to disqualify myself from further dealing with this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">6 The above matters raised by Mr Cram are no answer to the respondent's motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Mr Cram has advanced no other arguments in opposition to the order sought on the respondent's motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">7 I am satisfied that the application in this matter does not disclose a reasonable cause of action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Moreover the documents that Mr Cram wished to recover from the Tribunal have now, as I am satisfied, been returned to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The proceeding is therefore dismissed pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act on the basis that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I certify that the preceding seven (7) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Branson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Associate:

Dated: 27 June 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: The applicant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 19 June 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 June 2007 


 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/965.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>