<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Duncan v National Australia Bank [2007] FCA 95 (8 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/95.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for damages for undertaking given by counsel</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application dismissed.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">interlocutory application</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application by the first cross-respondent, Andrew Morton Garrett, as trustee of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3, for an order that the applicant, Mr Duncan, and the third respondent, Mr Macks, pay damages pursuant to an undertaking given by them by counsel on 1 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">This matter has a long history.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Mr Macks is the trustee of the bankrupt estate of Andrew Morton Garrett and Mr Duncan, the trustee of the bankrupt estate of Averil Garrett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Mr Garrett was made bankrupt on 24 September 2004 and Ms Garrett on 22 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">There has been a multitude of actions brought by Mr Garrett in relation to the events leading up to his bankruptcy and events since his bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">2 In 2005, the trustees of the two estates sought to recover the assets of the estate and the assets of trusts of which Mr and Ms Garrett were trustees prior to their bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Following their bankruptcy, Evajade Proprietary Limited, a company apparently controlled by Mr Garrett, became the trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">3 Evidence disclosed that during 2005, assets were transferred from one trust to another ahead of the efforts of the two trustees to recover the assets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On 31 January 2006, Mr Garrett gave two undertakings to the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The first was that no further charges would be created affecting the assets of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The second undertaking was that no further charges would be created affecting the assets of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 1 or No 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">4 A number of directions hearing were heard in early 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">On 1 March 2006, Mr Sandow, who was then the director of Evajade Proprietary Limited, purported to resign and Mr Garrett asserted that by virtue of a power of attorney over Evajade, he had appointed a new director to Evajade, a Mr Tsouvelis, who was not then present in Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 Later in the course of that hearing, Mr Garrett asserted that on 9 February 2006 a person named Mr Joseph Nicolazzo had been appointed joint trustee of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The addition of the joint trustee to the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3 had the inevitable consequence of causing the matter to be adjourned to enable Mr Nicolazzo to be joined as a party and to afford the cross-claimants an opportunity to re-amend their statement of claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In addition, Mr Garrett asserted on that day that he had been appointed as joint trustee of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 1 and No 2 on 27 January 2006, which also had the inevitable consequence of delaying the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">6 Towards the end of the hearing on 1 March 2006, I asked Mr Garrett to give undertakings to the Court that he would not appoint any new trustees for any of the Andrew Garrett Family Trusts and he would not dispose of any assets of any of the three Andrew Garrett Family Trusts without the leave of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Mr Garrett indicated that he could give the first undertaking but could not give the second.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">He referred to an unexecuted assignment of debt which purported to assign the Berringer Blass royalty stream to Zoltan Varveghy and Antoine Jacques Alcides for consideration of $1 plus, (1) assignment of international bill of exchange with serial number 12123353, and ASIN:CB!79472537 to the account of Andrew Morton Garrett and Joseph Nicolazzo as trustees of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3; (2) execution of irrevocable direction and authority to Berringer Blass Wine Estates in favour of Andrew Morton Garrett as trustee of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3 for $100,000 per annum; (3) a fee of $US25 million payable pro rata on success judgement of the damages of $US50 million in an action to be brought against the defendant, to be named in a Court action brought in the name of Zolton Zarszeghy (sic), Antoine Jacques Alcides and Credit Net Bank International (plaintiffs).</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">7 The assignment of debt had been executed by Mr Garrett but not by Mr Nicolazzo, Mr Varveghy or Mr Alcides.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I put it to Mr Garrett during the hearing that if his execution of the assignment of debt had the effect of devaluing the asset of the Berringer Blass royalty stream, that he might be in breach of the undertaking he made to the Court on 31 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">If executed, the effect of the assignment of debt was to effectively replace an asset of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3 with a chose in action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">8 I adjourned the matter to enable Mr Varveghy, Mr Alcides and Mr Nicolazzo to be joined as parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">I also made orders in the nature of injunctions so as to protect the position pending their being joined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On the undertaking given by Miss Maharaj QC on behalf of the cross-claimant, Mr Macks, the orders I made were:
 
 
 'Until Further orders: 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The seventh and eighth cross-respondents are restrained from executing a document, being an assignment of debt, between Andrew Morton Garrett and Joseph Nicolazzo as trustees of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust (No 3), and Zoltan Varveghy and Antoine Jacques Alcides, and described as Exhibit MM in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The first cross-respondent, Joseph Nicolazzo is restrained from executing the document referred to in paragraph 5(i) hereof and described as Exhibit MM in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The trustees of the Andrew Garrett Family Trust (No 1) and the Andrew Garrett Family Trust (No 2) and the Andrew Garrett Family Trust (No 3), are restrained from disposing of, or dealing in any way with any of the assets of those trusts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The seventh and eighth cross-respondents, Zoltan Varveghy and Antoine Jacques Alcides are restrained from disposing of, or dealing in any way with any assets acquired by them pursuant to the terms of the document described in 5(i) hereof and described as Exhibit MM in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">' 
 
 

9 On 31 March 2006, because events had changed, I discharged that order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Mr Garrett now seeks damages which he says the Andrew Garrett Family Trust No 3 has suffered as a result of the making of those orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">In my opinion, the application fails in its premise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">I am not satisfied on any of the evidence which has been put to me that the orders made were inappropriate, having regard to the circumstances which then existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">10 There was a history leading up to 1 March 2006 which disclosed that Mr Garrett was taking steps to put assets beyond the reach of the trustees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The trustees had been given no notice prior to the hearing that it was intended that the transaction which was contemplated in exhibit MM would occur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">They were entitled, in my opinion, to seek to restrain the execution of the document pending their investigations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">11 
 
For those reasons, the application for damages on the undertaking as to damages is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">I certify that the preceding eleven (11) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lander.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Associate:

Dated: 8 February 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr M Hayes 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Cosoff Cudmore Knox 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: The First Respondent did not apear 
 
 Counsel for the Second Respondent: Mr J Wilkinson 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: Cowell Clarke 
 
 Counsel for the Third Respondent: Ms E Trebilcock 
 
 Solicitor for the Third Respondent: Lipman Karas 
 
 Counsel for the First Cross-Respondent: Mr Garrett appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Second to Eighth Cross-Respondents: The Second to Eights Cross-Respondents did not appear 
 
 Date of Hearing: 8 February 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 8 February 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/95.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>