<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 5) [2008] FCA 1700 (14 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1700.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">discharge of mortgage prior to the tender of the principal amount</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">amount due retained in a separate bank account</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">right to interest following the discharge of mortgage</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether interest should be calculated at the rate actually accrued on the deposit or the rate specified in the mortgage</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">mortgage</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 Receivers were appointed under s 601EE of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) to wind up an unregistered managed investment scheme known as the Mews Retirement Village: Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (2006) 236 ALR 699.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The receivers were directed to sell the principal asset of the scheme, a parcel of land at Lot 4, Railway Parade, Upper Swan, a semi-rural area on the outskirts of Perth (Mews land).</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The receivers found a purchaser and with court approval entered into a contract to sell the land for $24 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">To enable completion of the sale the mortgagees, National Australia Bank Ltd as first mortgagee and Rental Fleets Australia Pty Ltd and AVS Property Pty Ltd as second mortgagees, were ordered to deliver up duly executed discharges of mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Out of the proceeds of sale the NAB was paid the amount due under its mortgage, being the sum of $9,647,925.35.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The balance (after deducting the costs and expenses of sale) was about $13 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">This was less than the amount claimed by AVS to be secured by the second mortgage: it claimed it was owed in excess of $14 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">In those circumstances it was ordered that the balance be paid into an interest bearing account in the name of the receivers pending the determination of what was due to AVS: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 3) (2008) 246 ALR 580 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On the taking of accounts it was established that the principal due to AVS was $4,100,282.64 and that interest calculated to 17 March 2008 (the day the money was paid into the receivers' account) was $1,573,613.32: Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 1071 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Those amounts were paid to AVS on 22 September 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The question in issue is whether AVS is also entitled to interest on its debt from 17 March 2008 to 22 September 2008 either at the rate specified in the mortgage (14.71 per cent per annum) or at the rate accruing on the deposit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">2 To resolve the issue raised it is necessary to deal with two questions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The first is whether the interest due under the mortgage ceased to run when the second mortgagees discharged their mortgage and the proceeds of sale were paid into the receivers' account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">If the answer to that question is 'yes', the second question is who is entitled to the interest that has accrued on the debt, being a portion of the money in the receivers' account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">3 On the first question, the general rule is that until a mortgage is discharged by the actual payment and acceptance of the amount due, the rights and obligations imposed by the mortgage remain in force: Samuel Keller (Holdings) Ltd v Martins Bank Ltd [1971] 1 WLR 43, Megarry J and CA; Inglis v Commonwealth Trading Bank of Australia [1972] HCA 74 ; (1972) 126 CLR 161 , 164-165.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">One result of this rule is that interest continues to run until the principal is paid out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">4 But the requirement to pay interest until the mortgage is discharged can be displaced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">For instance, if the mortgagor tenders the amount due under the mortgage in return for a discharge and the tender is refused, interest will cease to run: Bank of New South Wales v O'Connor (1889) 14 App Cas 273, 284; Rourke v Robinson [1911] 1 Ch 480.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">There is authority which holds that even if there has been a tender of the amount due the tender does not stop interest running unless the sum has been set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">There is a conflict whether the money tendered should be paid into court ( Kinnard v Trollope (1889) 42 Ch D 610 , 615-616) or kept in a separate account ( Barratt v Gough-Thomas [1951] 2 All ER 48, 49).</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">In Graham v Seal (1919) LJ Ch 31 , 36 the Court of Appeal said that the tender need not be such that would afford a defence to an action in law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I take this to be authority for the proposition that the money need only be put aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">5 Another instance where interest will cease to run before discharge is where the mortgagee wrongfully states or indicates that it will not discharge the mortgage on the due date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The old cases suggest that even in that circumstance a tender is an essential pre-requisite to stop interest from running: Bishop v Church [1751] EngR 97 ; (1751) 2 Ves Sen 371 , 372 ("if a strict tender is not made, the court cannot stop the interest: though cases may be, where the court would wish to do it"); Garforth v Bradley [1755] EngR 138 ; (1755) 2 Ves Sen 675 , 678 ("the rule is so strict, that, where a certain security is taken by the mortgagees, their interest shall not stop but upon a proper tender and notice" --- the reference to notice is to the rule of equity which required six months notice to be given of the mortgagor's intention to pay the mortgage debt).</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">6 It is clear, however, that tender of the amount due is not always required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">That was settled in Scarfe v Morgan [1838] EngR 253 ; (1838) 4 M&amp;W 270.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">There Parke B said (at 279) that a mortgagee could agree to waive the necessity of a tender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">In Kerford v Mondel (1859) 28 LJ Ex 303 , after referring to Scarfe v Morgan , Bramwell B said (at 306) that if a mortgagee "goes on, and so conducts himself as to indicate that a tender of the one amount had been nugatory, he dispenses with the tender".</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">This is consistent with modern authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">For example in Mahoney v Lindsey (1980) 55 ALJR 118 the High Court considered the need for a purchaser to tender the purchase price in order to obtain an order for the specific performance of a contract for the sale of land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Gibbs J (with whom the other judges agreed) said (at 603): "But a plaintiff may be dispensed from performing a condition by the defendant expressly or impliedly intimating that it is useless for him to perform it and requesting him not to do so", citing Dixon CJ in Turnbull (Peter) &amp; Co v Mundus Trading Co (Australasia) Pty Ltd [1954] HCA 25 ; (1954) 90 CLR 235 , 246-247.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">7 In the case at bar the second mortgagees made it clear that they would not discharge the second mortgage at the settlement unless AVS received the whole of the proceeds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">It was for this reason that the vendor, Western Retirement Village Management Pty Ltd (in liq), took proceedings to obtain the discharge of the second mortgage and to have determined what was due under that mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The money was paid into the receivers' account to protect AVS in the event it could establish a claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It was placed into an interest bearing account rather than being paid into court as this would result in a better return.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">In substance, if it matters, the payment into the receivers' account was the equivalent of a payment into court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">At that point, the obligation to continue paying interest under the mortgage was discharged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">8 This brings me to the second question which is whether AVS is entitled to the interest which has accrued on amount found to be due.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The answer depends, in the first place, upon the right to trace.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">AVS had a proprietary interest in the Mews land by way of security for the payment of the mortgage debt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">It is entitled to trace its interest into the money for which the land was exchanged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">It did not lose that right when the money was paid into the receivers' account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">In other words, it retained its security interest over the substituted asset.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">9 The reason is this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The right to trace is not a claim or a remedy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It is the process by which a person discovers what has happened to his property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">It enables the person tracing to substitute the traceable proceeds for the original asset: see generally Foskett v McKeowan [2001] 1 AC 102; Buhr v Barclays Bank Pty Ltd [2001] EWCA Civ 1223.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">In AVCO Financial Services Ltd v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [1989] 17 NSWLR 679, 682 Young J said: "[I]t is clear that if a person has an equitable charge over land and that land is sold by a mortgagee, that the equitable charge attaches to the fund that is produced as a result of there being a surplus on the sale".</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">In Dick v Harper [2006] BPIR 20 an equitable chargee who had a proprietary interest over certain property was entitled to trace his interest into several bank accounts where the proceeds of the sale of the property were held.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">10 As AVS is entitled to trace its security interest into the proceeds, it is also entitled to the interest derived from its share of the proceeds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">According to Roman law the owner of a thing (res) was entitled to each thing (res) which was produced by the first thing: res accessoria cedit principali (accessio).</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Some of the rules of accessio have found their way into the common law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">For example, in Swain v Law Society [1982] 1 WLR 17, 36 Oliver LJ said: "[T]hat which is the fruit of trust property or of the trusteeship is itself trust property".</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Interest is the fruit of capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Generally speaking, therefore, the owner of the capital is entitled to the interest which it produces: Dick v Harpour at [55].</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">11 In light of the forgoing there will be an order that AVS be paid the interest which has in fact accrued on the principal debt together with any interest that has accrued on interest, if that is what happened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The costs of the parties should be paid out of the balance held in the receivers' account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">I certify that the preceding eleven (11) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Finkelstein.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Associate:

Dated: 14 November 2008


 Solicitor for the Mews Receivers: Blake Dawson 
 
 Solicitor for the 7 th Defendant: Arnold Bloch Leibler 
 
 Solicitor for AVS Property Pty Ltd Deacons 
 
 

 Written Submissions filed by the Mews Receivers: 31 October 2008 
 
 Written Submissions filed by the 7 th Defendant: 2 &amp; 20 October 2008 
 
 Written Submissions filed by AVS Property Pty Ltd: 9 &amp; 20 October 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 14 November 2008 

 
 
 
 
 SCHEDULE OF PARTIES 

 
 AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION 
 Plaintiff
 

 GDK FINANCIAL SOLUTIONS PTY LTD (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 First Defendant
 


 WINDSOR VILLAGE MANGEMENT PTY LTD (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 Second Defendant
 

 WESTERN RETIREMENT VILLAGE MANAGEMENT PTY LTD 
 (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 Third Defendant
 

 THE MEWS VILLAGE NOMINEES PTY LIMITED (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 Fourth Defendant
 

 PERIDON MANGEMENT PTY LTD (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 Fifth Defendant
 

 ROSEDALE VILLAGE NOMINEES PTY LTD (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 Sixth Defendant
 

 PETER HASTINGS WARNE 
 Seventh Defendant
 

 RENTAL FLEETS AUSTRALIA PTY LTD 
 Eight Defendant
 

 JOHN MONTGOMERIE 
 Ninth Defendant
 

 ANDREW REGINALD YEO 
 Tenth Defendant
 

 GUISEPPE DE SIMONE 
 Eleventh Defendant
 

 SEACHANGE MANAGEMENT PTY LTD 
 Twelfth Defendant
 

 ZMB AUSTRALIA 
 Thirteenth Defendant
 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1700.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>