<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lee v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 1023 (27 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1023.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for issue of a criminal justice stay warrant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">applicant an unlawful non-citizen who is to be, or is likely to be, removed or deported</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">applicant wishing to stay in australia to prosecute appeal against a criminal conviction. held : (1) s 151 of migration act 1958 (cth) does not empower court to issue criminal justice stay warrant but assumes that a court, commonwealth or state, is given that power otherwise; (2) perspective of provisions dealing with criminal justice stay warrants and certificates is that of the administrators of criminal justice system, not the individual the subject of investigation, prosecution or punishment; (3) applicant therefore lacked standing to apply for criminal justice stay warrant; (4) applicant could not show a claim for relief under s 39b of judiciary act 1903 (cth) having regard to mandatory terms of s 198 of migration act 1958 (cth) requiring officer to remove applicant from australia.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 In this proceeding which came before me yesterday the applicant, by his second amended application then filed, claims the following:
 
 
 (1) A Declaration pursuant to s 151 Migration Act 1958 that the applicant is entitled to a warrant staying his removal from Australia for the purposes of the administration of criminal justice in relation to an offence against a law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">
 
 
 
 (2) An Order that a warrant be issued staying the removal of the applicant from Australia pending hearing of the Applicant's appeal in the District Court on 22 July 2008, plus 28 days, being an appeal from the Applicant's conviction in the Burwood Local Court on 22 October 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">
 

2 Section 151 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act) provides:
 
 
 (1) If an unlawful non-citizen is to be, or is likely to be, removed or deported, this Act does not prevent a court issuing for the purposes of the administration of criminal justice in relation to an offence against a law a warrant to stay the removal or deportation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">(2) If a criminal justice stay warrant about a non-citizen is in force, the non-citizen is not to be removed or deported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">(3) If a court issues a criminal justice stay warrant about a non-citizen, the applicant for the warrant is responsible for the costs of any maintenance, accommodation or immigration detention of the non-citizen while the warrant is in force.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">
 

A warrant described in s 151 is called a criminal justice stay warrant: s 142 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">
 
 
 

3 It is common ground that the applicant is an unlawful non-citizen who is to be, or is likely to be, removed or deported within s 151(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The notions of removal and deportation refer to removal or deportation from Australia: see the definitions of "remove" and "deportation" in s 5 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">4 It is not necessary for me to outline the history of the applicant's period of residence in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">What is immediately relevant is that on 22 October 2007 he was convicted in the Burwood Local Court of assault occasioning actual bodily harm (see s 59(1) of the Crimes Act 1900 (NSW)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">He has appealed against that conviction and the appeal is currently for hearing in the District Court of New South Wales at Campbelltown on 22 July 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The applicant wishes to prosecute that appeal and to tender on the hearing of the appeal expert evidence from a psychologist and from a forensic psychiatrist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 It will be noted at once that s 151(1) of the Act does not purport to confer power to issue a criminal justice stay warrant or to make a declaration that a person is entitled to have one issued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The question of this Court's power to issue such a warrant occupied debate yesterday.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I am of the view that s 151 does not give the Court power to grant the applicant the relief he seeks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">6 Consistently with this view, it will be noted that s 151 refers to "a court".</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The section assumes the existence of courts that are otherwise invested with power to issue criminal justice warrants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">7 In written submissions handed up in Court a short while ago it is stated that the applicant now resiles from an argument he advanced yesterday that the necessary power is to be found in s 151 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Nonetheless, I will address s 151 because in the course of argument today counsel for the applicant has returned to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">8 Section 151 occurs in Div 4 of Pt 2 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Division 4 is headed "Criminal justice visitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">" Section 141 states that Div 4:
 ... is enacted so that, if the administration of criminal justice requires the presence in Australia of a non-citizen, that non-citizen may be brought to, or allowed to stay in, Australia for the purposes of that administration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">9 The expression "administration of criminal justice" is defined in s 142 of the Act as follows:
 administration of criminal justice means: (a) an investigation to find out whether an offence has been committed; or (b) the prosecution of a person for an offence; or 
 
 (c) the punishment by way of imprisonment of a person for the commission of an offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">
 

The references to investigation, prosecution and punishment in the definition make it clear that the relevant perspective is that of the administrators of the criminal justice system, not that of a person who may be suspected of having committed a criminal offence, or who is being or has been prosecuted for an offence, or who has been or may be punished by way of imprisonment for the commission of an offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Indeed, the bare expression "administration of criminal justice", even independently of the definition, would, to my mind, indicate the perspective mentioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">10 The views expressed above are supported by the scheme of the provisions in Div 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">11 Subdivision B of Div 4 provides for the issue of criminal justice entry certificates and Subdiv C provides for the issue of criminal justice stay certificates, or, of present relevance, criminal justice stay warrants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">12 Subdivision C is concerned with unlawful non-citizens who are to be or who are likely to be removed or deported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Section 147 provides that in such a case if, inter alia, the Attorney-General considers that the non-citizen should remain in Australia temporarily for the purposes of the administration of criminal justice in relation to an offence against a law of the Commonwealth, the Attorney-General may give a certificate that the stay of the non-citizen's removal or deportation is required for the administration of criminal justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">13 Just as s 147 provides for the issue of Commonwealth criminal justice stay certificates, s 148 provides for the issue of State criminal justice stay certificates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Predictably, whereas s 147 relates to offences against the law of the Commonwealth, s 148 relates to offences against the law of a State.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Section 148 empowers an authorised official for a State, in certain circumstances, to give a certificate that the stay of a non-citizen's removal or deportation is required for the administration of criminal justice by the State.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">14 Section 150 provides that if a criminal justice stay certificate (defined in s 142 as a certificate given under s 147 or s 148) about a non-citizen is in force, the non-citizen is not to be removed or deported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">15 Sections 147 and 148 are "enacted in the public interest in the administration of justice" and "are, on the face of it, not intended to create any rights or privileges on the part of the unlawful non-citizen": Goldie v Commonwealth of Australia [2002] FCA 261 at [36] per French J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Similar observations are applicable to s 151 in my view, and see, to a similar effect, In the matter of an application by Solomon Barudea for a warrant under s 151(1) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) [1995] VSC 55 at [22] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">16 I return now to the terms of s 151.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The reference to a "court" in that section has an ambulatory operation and refers to any court otherwise seized of power to issue a warrant to stay a removal or deportation for the purposes of the administration of criminal justice in the particular jurisdiction, Commonwealth or State as the case may be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">17 The picture that emerges from the above provisions is that they are concerned with investigation, enforcement and punishment within the criminal justice system of the Commonwealth or of a State respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Although I was not directed to any other provision of Commonwealth or State legislation, it seems reasonable to expect that it will be a court invested with jurisdiction in respect of Commonwealth or State investigation, prosecution or punishment that will have power to issue a criminal justice stay warrant in relation to it --- in the present case a court of the State of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">18 There are at least two other considerations suggesting that s 151 does not give this Court the power to issue a criminal justice warrant on the present application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The first is found in definitions contained in s 142.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">A "criminal justice entry certificate" is a certificate "given under" one or other of various specified sections, and a "criminal justice stay certificate" is a certificate "given under" s 147 or s 148.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">In contrast a "criminal justice stay warrant" is simply a warrant "described in" section 151.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">That is to say, the words "given under" are absent in the latter case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The reason is that a criminal justice stay warrant is not "given under" s 151.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">19 The second consideration depends on the legislative history of s 151.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Section 151 was originally s 54G of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Section 54G formed part of Div 3 of Pt 2 and was inserted in the Act by the Migration Reform Act 1992 (Cth) (No 184 of 1992).</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Division 3 of Pt 2 became Div 4 of Pt 2 , and s 54G became s 151, following the renumbering effected by the Migration Legislation Amendment Act 1994 (Cth) (No 60 of 1994).</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">20 In the Explanatory Memorandum for the Migration Reform Bill 1992 , para 182 stated of the then proposed s 54G (see now s 151) that the purpose of the section was to ensure that the powers created by Div 3 (see now Div 4) did not interfere with the power of a court to issue a warrant requiring that a non-citizen not be removed or deported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That paragraph of the Explanatory Memorandum also stated:
 The section [s 54G] also makes it clear that the applicant to the court for the warrant (ie the relevant law enforcement agency) is responsible for any accommodation, maintenance, or migration detention costs associated with requiring that non-citizen to remain in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">[my emphasis] 
This statement is consistent with my statement earlier that the perspective that permeates Div 4 is that of the administrators of the criminal justice system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">In sum, the applicant does not have standing to apply for a criminal justice stay warrant under s 151.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">21 It appears that the purpose of s 151 is to carve out an exception to s 153.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Section 153 provides:
 (1) Subject to subsection (2), if: 
 
 
 (a) this Act requires the removal or deportation of a non citizen; and
 (b) there is no criminal justice stay certificate or criminal justice stay warrant about the non-citizen; 
 
 
 
 
 any other law, or anything done under any other law, of the Commonwealth or a State (whether passed or made before or after the commencement of this section), not being an Act passed after that commencement expressed to be exempt from this section, does not prevent the removal or deportation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">
 
 
 
 (2) Subsection (1) does not permit the removal or deportation of a non-citizen if that removal or deportation would be in breach of an order of the High Court, the Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">
 

22 Section 198(6) of the Act would have the effect in the present case of requiring an officer to remove or deport the applicant from Australia "as soon as reasonably practicable".</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Accordingly, paras (a) and (b) of s 153(1) are satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Subsection (2) of s 153 limits the operation of the concluding words of subs (1) of that section, but one must look elsewhere to find a power in this Court to make an order of the kind referred to in subs (2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">23 Today counsel for the applicant seeks to rely on s 39B(1) or s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth), which provide, relevantly, as follows:
 
 
 (1) ... the original jurisdiction of the Federal Court of Australia includes jurisdiction with respect to any matter in which a writ of mandamus or prohibition or an injunction is sought against an officer or officers of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">
 
 
 
 (1A) The original jurisdiction of the Federal Court of Australia also includes jurisdiction in any matter: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) in which the Commonwealth is seeking an injunction or a declaration; or 
 
 
 
 
 (b) arising under the Constitution , or involving its interpretation; or 
 
 
 
 
 (c) arising under any laws made by the Parliament, other than a matter in respect of which a criminal prosecution is instituted or any other criminal matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">
 
 

 In relation to s 39B(1) it is put that this Court has jurisdiction because an injunction is sought against an officer of the Commonwealth, namely, the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">In relation to s 39B(1A) it is put that this Court has jurisdiction because the "matter" in question arises under a law made by the Commonwealth Parliament, namely, the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Counsel has made it clear that the relief that he seeks is final relief rather than interlocutory relief, although I do not think that the distinction is critical here.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">24 In his submissions, counsel for the applicant says that the criminal justice stay warrant referred to in s 151 is, in substance, an "injunction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">" I need not discuss this submission and am content to approach the matter on the assumption that the applicant seeks an injunction against the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">25 Ultimately, the problem which the applicant still has is to demonstrate a case for the granting of injunctive relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">26 Section 198(6) of the Act is mandatory in its terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">It has the effect that an "officer" (defined in s 5 of the Act) must remove the applicant from Australia "as soon as reasonably practicable".</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The fact that the applicant desires to prosecute his appeal on 22 July 2008 does not render it not "reasonably practicable" for an officer to remove him from Australia prior to that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">This Court does not have a general jurisdiction to relieve from the effect of s 198(6).</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">27 For the above reasons, the Court will order that the application be dismissed and that the applicant pay the respondent's costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">I certify that the preceding twenty-seven (27) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lindgren.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">Associate:

Dated: 7 July 2008



 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr R Killalea with Mr C Bolger 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr JAC Potts 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 26, 27 June 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 June 2008 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1023.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>