<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Mitchell v Bailey (No 3) (includes corrigendum dated 11 July 2008) [2008] FCA 1029 (11 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1029.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">court of disputed returns</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">appropriate orders</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">where parties agreed the commonwealth should pay the costs of the petitioner and of the first respondent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">where the commonwealth was not a party to the petition</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">where the commonwealth did not object to the orders sought</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">where the proceeding raised novel issues that were in the public interest to resolve</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">where the court corrected errors made during the scrutiny of the reserved ballot-papers</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">parliamentary elections</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 On 2 July 2008 I handed down judgment in Mitchell v Bailey (No 2) [2008] FCA 692.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Having considered a petition which had been filed in the High Court and referred for trial in this Court I concluded that the Australian Electoral Officer ("AEO") for Victoria had erred in ruling that nine ballot-papers, cast in the election for a Member of the House of Representatives for the Division of McEwen, held on 24 November 2007, were formal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I found that a further 142 votes, which the AEO had determined were informal were formal and should have been counted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">As a result of these decisions I determined that the first respondent had been certified correctly as the candidate who had been elected for the Division.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">She had been so elected by a margin of 27 votes after the preferences of other candidates had been distributed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The parties sought an opportunity to consider my reasons before making submissions as to what orders should be made by the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The parties agreed on the orders which they wished the Court to make.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Pursuant to O 35 rule 10 of the Federal Court Rules , they submitted minutes of consent orders on 4 July 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The agreed orders were: 
 "1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The petition is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">

 The Commonwealth pay the Petitioner his costs of and incidental to the petition, including costs reserved by Crennan J on 21 February 2008 and any other reserved costs, on a party/party basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The Commonwealth pay the First Respondent her costs of and incidental to the petition, including costs reserved by Crennan J on 21 February 2008 and any other reserved costs, on a party/party basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">"
 
Written submissions were filed by all parties supporting the making of these orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">At no stage was the Commonwealth a party to the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The second respondent expressly disavowed any right to speak on behalf of the Commonwealth in relation to costs issues.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">For this reason I listed the matter for hearing on the question of whether a costs order could be made against the Commonwealth without the Commonwealth being afforded the opportunity to be heard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">At the hearing senior counsel for the second respondent advised the Court that an appropriate officer within the Department of Finance and Deregulation had been advised of the proposed orders and would write to the Court advising that the Commonwealth did not oppose the making of such orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">By letter dated 7 July 2008 Mr Marc Mowbray-d'Arbela, the Assistant Secretary, Legislative Review Branch, Financial Management Group of the Department of Finance and Deregulation advised the Court that he was authorised "to convey the position of the Commonwealth in relation to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">" That position was that the Commonwealth did not object to the Court making the orders which were sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The Court has a discretionary power, under ss 360(1)(ix) and (4) of the Commonwealth Electoral Act 1918 (Cth) ("the Act") to make orders of the kind sought in paragraphs two and three of the minutes submitted to the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Orders of this kind may be made "where the Court considers it appropriate to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">" In Nile v Wood [1988] HCA 30 ; (1988) 167 CLR 133 at 142, Brennan J said that the discretion to make a costs order against the Commonwealth under s 360(4): 
 "... may properly be exercised when the proceedings have arisen because an officer of the Commonwealth has failed properly to perform his function or when the proceedings have resulted in some public benefit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In such cases it may be appropriate that the public purse ought bear the costs or some of them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">I do not suggest that these categories are exhaustive, but it would not be appropriate to exercise the discretion whenever a litigant chooses to put the validity of an election to the test.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Some warrant for imposing a liability on the funds of the Commonwealth must appear before it is appropriate to make an order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">" 
 Deane and Toohey JJ, in a passage which was subsequently said by Gaudron J, in Hudson v Lee [1993] HCA 58 ; (1993) 177 CLR 627 at 633, to be cast in "wider" terms, said (at 143) that: 
 "This power to order costs against the Commonwealth, which is unlikely in the ordinary case to be a party to proceedings before the Court of Disputed Returns, is not constricted by reference to the principles controlling the making of an order for costs inter partes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It is a general power conferred upon the Court of Disputed Returns, in the exercise of its special jurisdiction, to order that the Commonwealth pay the costs of a party whenever the Court considers it appropriate so to do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">We would not attempt to confine it by definition beyond saying that it should be exercised when considerations of what is fair and just support, on balance, an order indemnifying a party against costs which the party may have incurred in connexion with an electoral petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">" 
 In my view it is appropriate that the orders sought by the parties in relation to costs should be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The proceeding raised issues which were novel and which it was in the public interest to resolve.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The Court found that a significant number of inadvertent errors had been made during the scrutiny of reserved ballot-papers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The petitioner had been prejudiced by an even greater number of errors than had been alleged in the petition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">These errors would have affected the outcome of the election had it not been that an even greater number of errors were made which prejudiced the successful candidate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The fact that these errors had occurred and required correction by the Court is probably a sufficient reason, standing alone, to make the orders sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">There were, however, a series of novel issues which it was necessary to resolve in the course of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Those issues included: Whether the parties, or their legal advisors, could be provided with access to the reserved ballot-papers consistently with the provisions of s 360(1)(iii) of the Act and, if so, on what conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Whether the Act imposed any statutory obligations on an Australian Electoral Officer which, if not complied with, could give rise to a contravention of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">What processes should be adopted by the Court in order to deal with a petition which alleged that errors had been made by an Australian Electoral Officer in determining the formality of reserved ballot-papers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Whether the Court should engage in merits review or judicial review of decisions made by an Australian Electoral Officer under s 281 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">
It was, in my opinion, necessary and desirable, in the public interest, that these issues should be resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The orders sought should, therefore, be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">There should also be a direction, pursuant to the requirements of s 369 of the Act, that the Registrar provide a copy of my orders to the Governor-General and to the Clerk of the House of Representatives.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">I certify that the preceding ten (10) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 11 July 2008
 
 Counsel for the Petitioner: Mr P Hanks QC 
 
 Solicitor for the Petitioner: Holding Redlich 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr D Bennett 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Gadens Lawyers 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: Mr P Santamaria SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 7 July 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 July 2008 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1029.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>