<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cruse v Construction, Forestry, Mining &amp; Energy Union (No 2) [2008] FCA 1637 (5 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1637.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">breach of ss 170nc and 298sc of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) by union shop steward and union</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">union vicariously liable for breaches by shop steward</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether penalties appropriate</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">level of penalties</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">industrial law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 On 22 August 2008, the Court published its reasons for judgment in Cruse v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2008] FCA 1267 ("the substantive judgment").</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">In the substantive judgment, the Court held that Mr Fry, a delegate of the respondent Union, breached ss 298SC and 170NC of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) ("the WR Act ").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">It also found the Union vicariously liable for Mr Fry's breaches.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">This judgment should be read together with the substantive judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">It deals with the issue of what penalties, if any, should be imposed on Mr Fry and the Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Section 298SC 
 
2 Mr Fry was employed at the Hamilton site referred to in the substantive judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">He was engaged on the construction side of the project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">He was also a CFMEU shop steward.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">It was custom and practice on the construction side of the site for employees to be members of the CFMEU.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The position of Mr Anton was unusual because he was a self-employed building contractor engaged to perform odd jobs around the Hamilton site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Mr Fry's role as shop steward included the enrolment of non-members on the construction side of the site into the CFMEU.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">He enrolled Mr Anton but 'gilded the lily' in encouraging him to do so by saying that he had an obligation to join the CFMEU.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">No doubt, as a CFMEU shop steward, and with everyone else on the construction side of the site almost certainly being in the CFMEU, Mr Fry considered that Mr Anton should be in the CFMEU.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">That does not excuse the breach of s 298SC of the WR Act committed by Mr Fry, but it does explain it and put it in context.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">3 Mr Fry is fifty-nine years old.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">He has no history of prior contravention of any provision of the WR Act or the more onerous Building and Construction Industry Improvement Act 2005 (Cth) ("the BCII Act "), which places special obligations and requirements on building and construction workers which do not apply to other sections of the workforce.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Mr Fry lives in Hamilton in rural Victoria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">He is employed as a scaffolder doing work around the Western District of Victoria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">He is not a wealthy man.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">He has given evidence that he "will not at any time in the future make a false statement to anyone regarding their obligation to be a member of the CFMEU".</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">4 In the circumstances, I see no point in imposing any penalty on Mr Fry for his breach of s 298SC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I am confident Mr Fry will be true to his word and not commit any further breach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">This proceeding has, no doubt, been of educative value for him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">However, in the circumstances, it is appropriate to record by declaration that he breached s 298SC of the WR Act as found in the substantive judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">5 The CFMEU has vicarious liability for Mr Fry's breach of s 298SC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The extent of the penalty to be imposed on the CFMEU is informed by the following relevant considerations:
 
&#8226; the only two alleged prior contraventions of the provision did not involve the Victorian branch of the CFMEU;
 
&#8226; the only two alleged prior contraventions involved vicarious liability;
 
&#8226; vicarious liability has resulted from the acts of a rank and file member/worker at a rural site as distinct from a paid officer of the CFMEU;
 
&#8226; the CFMEU is not established as a profit making body but exists for the benefit of its members;
 
&#8226; on being misled as to his liability to join the CFMEU, Mr Anton was content to renew his membership after the events the subject of the substantive judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">6 Having regard to all the above circumstances, as well as the importance of complying with the Act, I consider that it is sufficient to record by way of declaration that the CFMEU has breached s 298SC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">This order will act as an encouragement for the CFMEU to educate its shop stewards so that they do not involve it in further vicarious breaches of this provision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Also given the unusual circumstances in which the breach occurred, I consider that no useful purpose would be gained by imposing a monetary penalty on the CFMEU for this breach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">Section 170NC 
 
7 In the substantive judgment Mr Fry was found to have breached s 170NC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The breach arose because Mr Fry told Mr Anton that he had to have an enterprise bargaining agreement to work on the construction side of the site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">By Mr Anton entering into an enterprise bargaining agreement he was able to charge out his services on site at a higher rate than he previously did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">By strange coincidence Mr Anton benefited from the unlawful behaviour directed at him by Mr Fry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Mr Anton did not want an enterprise agreement but faced the prospect of not being able to work on the construction side of the site without one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The negation of his choice was unlawful and deserves admonition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">However, Mr Anton was 'a strange beast' on the site, being a self-employed contractor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">It appears to me that Mr Fry did not quite know how Mr Anton fitted into the industrial regulation of the site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">8 I see no point in imposing a penalty on Mr Fry for his breach of s 170NC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">He clearly misunderstood Mr Anton's status.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">He did not have the industrial skills to discern that Mr Anton was not an employer and/or that he did not require an enterprise bargaining agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">He has given evidence that he will not repeat this breach by "coerc[ing] any person to make agreement with the CFMEU".</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">However, a declaration should be made recording Mr Fry's breach of s 170NC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">9 The CFMEU is vicariously liable for Mr Fry's breach of s 170NC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">It has previously contravened that provision through vicarious liability for a breach by an officer in a branch other than Victoria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">It is significant, in this matter, that when senior officers of the CFMEU came to the Hamilton site they sought to ensure that the issues between Mr Anton and other workers on the site were resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">However, on the issue of general deterrence, it is important that the Court recognises that a fundamental aspect of the right to engage in bargaining free from coercion has been breached.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">It is therefore appropriate in this case that the Court impose a monetary penalty, albeit on the lower side of the scale of that available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">A penalty on the low side is deserved in this case because:
 
&#8226; the liability arose from the actions of a rural shop steward at a comparatively isolated site as distinct from that of a paid officer;
 
&#8226; Mr Anton's position was unusual and must have been very difficult for Mr Fry to understand;
 
&#8226; the CFMEU sought to resolve issues with Mr Anton as soon as senior officers became aware of them;
 
&#8226; no financial harm resulted from the breach but, fortuitously, Mr Anton benefited from it;
 
&#8226; CFMEU will be encouraged by the proceeding to educate its shop stewards about the position of self-employed contractors on building sites vis-&agrave;-vis enterprise bargaining agreements, in the knowledge that further breaches will lead to harsher penalties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">10 In the circumstances the Court will impose a penalty of $4,000 on the CFMEU for its vicarious breach of s 170NC of the WR Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">In fixing that penalty I have also had regard to the fact that the CFMEU breached the freedom of association provisions of the WR Act on a number of occasions prior to events which led to the current breach of s 170NC of the WR Act , an allied provision to the freedom of association provisions in the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">I certify that the preceding ten (10) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Marshall .</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Associate:

Dated: 6 November 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr P O'Grady 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr E White 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union 

 Date of Hearing: 5 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 5 November 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1637.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>