<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tervonen v Finland [2008] FCA 1539 (16 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1539.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">leave to appeal against dismissal of application challenging an extradition request</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether applicant's arguments necessarily determined in other proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">failure to put argument in earlier appeal proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether anshun estoppel</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether an abuse of process to attempt to put argument again</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">leave to appeal granted .</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">whether applicant an extraditable person</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">whether applicant accused of relevant offences</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether argument available in the particular proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether anshun estoppel.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">extradition</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 BUCHANAN J: 
 History 
 
1 This matter has a complex history.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Mr Tervonen is resisting extradition to Finland to face numerous allegations of fraud, forgery and related offences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The extradition process, which is conventionally regarded as proceeding in four stages (see Harris v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 386 ( 'Harris' ) at 389; Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 ( 'Kainhofer' ) at 547; Vasiljkovic v Commonwealth [2006] HCA 40 ; (2006) 227 CLR 614 at [55] and Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 ; (2008) 166 FCR 91 at [9] ) commenced when the Australian government, on 27 July 2006, received a request from Finland for the extradition of Mr Tervonen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">2 The extradition process includes the issue of a provisional arrest warrant under s 12 of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) ('the Act') by a magistrate upon application on behalf of an extradition country, the issue of a notice under s 16 of the Act by the Attorney-General (or other responsible Minister), upon receipt of an extradition request from an extradition country, stating to a magistrate that the request has been received and the conduct of proceedings under s 19 of the Act by a magistrate to determine whether a person whose extradition is sought is eligible for surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The High Court pointed out in Kainhofer that these three steps (which occur within the first three stages identified in Harris ) are 'administrative in nature' and are 'exercisable by different repositories in sequence' but that 'none of them authorises the repository of a power to review the exercise of a power by another repository earlier in the sequence' (185 CLR 528 at 538).</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That is an important consideration to be borne in mind with respect to the procedural history which follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">3 On 18 August 2006 the then Minister for Justice and Customs, Senator Ellison, issued a Notice of Receipt of Extradition Request under s 16(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">On 30 April 2007 Senator Johnston, who was then the Minister for Justice and Customs, issued an amended notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">4 On 6 June 2007 a magistrate determined pursuant to s 19 of the Act that Mr Tervonen was eligible for surrender for offences itemised in the amended notice issued on 30 April 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">However, on 6 November 2007 Rares J decided that each of the first two notices was invalid ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684).</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">As a result, on 20 December 2007 Gyles J ordered that the magistrate's order made on 6 June 2007 be quashed ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067).</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">5 A Full Court which considered an appeal against the judgment of Rares J decided on 6 March 2008 that the amended notice of 30 April 2007 was substantially valid ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24) and also, as a consequence, upheld the appeal against the judgment of Gyles J ( The Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">That matter was remitted to Gyles J for further consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Gyles J subsequently confirmed the magistrate's order of 6 June 2007 save in respect of certain offences omitted from the amended notice under s 16 as a result of the order of the Full Court which found that notice substantially, but not entirely, valid ( Tervonen v Finland [2008] FCA 781).</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The latest decision of Gyles J is subject to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The appeal is listed for hearing in November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">6 Meanwhile, on 21 December 2007 Mr Tervonen commenced the further proceedings which led to the judgment in respect of which he has sought leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">On this occasion he filed an application relying on s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) seeking a determination that the extradition request made by Finland on 27 July 2006 was 'invalid'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Those proceedings were dismissed by Flick J on 6 August 2008 ( Tervonen v Finland [2008] FCA 1133).</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">It is against that judgment of Flick J that Mr Tervonen has sought leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The argument 
 
7 The foundation for the fresh proceedings instituted by Mr Tervonen was the proposition that some of the warrants relied upon by Finland were warrants for the arrest of Mr Tervonen for pre-trial investigation purposes rather than to stand trial 'accused' of relevant 'offences' , which are essential ingredients in the statutory meaning given by s 6 of the Act to the term 'extraditable person' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">8 The question whether a person is an 'extraditable person' is one of the matters which lies at the heart of the determination of a magistrate under s 12 of the Act and the formation of the opinion of a Minister under s 16 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Flick J acknowledged that failure by an extradition request to identify an extraditable person would open the way to a challenge to the validity of a notice issued under s 16 of the Act even though, as his Honour pointed out in the judgment against which leave to appeal has been sought, there does not appear to be any basis upon which an extradition request might be directly challenged as 'invalid'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">9 Flick J dismissed the proceedings because he concluded that the arguments upon which Mr Tervonen wished to rely had already been decided against him, that Mr Tervonen was estopped from raising the arguments again and that the proceedings were an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The test for leave to appeal 
 
10 The test to be applied in determining whether leave to appeal should be granted is set out in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397 ( 'D&eacute;cor' ), namely, 'whether the decision at first instance was attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered and whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused, supposing the decision at first instance was wrong' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The earlier attempts to put the argument 
 
11 At this point it is necessary to distinguish between the proceedings before Rares J and the appeal from Rares J to the Full Court (on the one hand), which were each concerned with s 16 of the Act, and the proceedings before Gyles J (on the other hand) which were concerned with s 19 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">As I pointed out earlier, an appeal has been filed against the latest judgment of Gyles J and the appeal is listed for hearing in November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Before the magistrate who determined that Mr Tervonen was eligible for surrender, and before Gyles J, Mr Tervonen relied on the arguments he wished to advance in the proceedings before Flick J. Gyles J felt constrained by the judgment of the High Court in Kainhofer to conclude that the argument was unavailable in proceedings concerned with s 19 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Whether that was a correct view or not may be examined on the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">If it was correct then the arguments are not available to Mr Tervonen in connection with s 19 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">If Gyles J was incorrect the arguments remain available in that context, although it does not appear that they relate to all the warrants outstanding against Mr Tervonen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">12 Gyles J, however, did not think that Mr Tervonen's contentions were unworthy of consideration or necessarily wrong so far as they concerned fundamental aspects of the extradition arrangements between Australia and Finland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">His Honour said:
 
 
 '8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Tervonen puts authentication of the warrants in issue but also takes a point of substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">He contends (and contended before the Magistrate) that five of the eight warrants are for his arrest for pre-trial investigation purposes rather than for trial for the offences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">He submits that there is a clear distinction in Finnish law between the two purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">He submits that only a public prosecutor can bring a prosecution, the police powers being limited to the investigation stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">These submissions are not evidence, but have clearly flagged an issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">
 
 ...' 
 
 
and:
 
 
 '20.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">It appears that Tervonen put a similar argument to Rares J in the proceeding challenging the validity of the s 16 notice --- see Tervonen [2007] FCA 1684 ; 98 ALD 589 at [33] ---[44].</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Rares J decided that it was open to the Minister to form the relevant opinion but did not consider the correctness or otherwise of that opinion, the proceeding before him being a challenge on administrative law grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">
 
 21.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">In my opinion, it is tolerably clear in the present case that only the first three warrants would normally be regarded as being "for the arrest of the person for the offence", the other warrants being connected with coercive investigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">To borrow from Art 1 of the Treaty, it was only those warrants by which Tervonen had been charged by a competent authority with the relevant offences against the law of Finland, bearing in mind that an extradition treaty must be a treaty relating to the surrender of persons accused or convicted of offences (s 5).</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">That conclusion is assisted by the failure of Finland to produce material to the Magistrate explaining the system as it applied to the issues in the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">
 
 
 
 22.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">However, counsel for Finland submits that this argument is effectively foreclosed to Tervonen by the decision of the High Court in Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">
 
 ...' 
 
 

and:
 
 
 '24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">...</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">I can see no escape from the conclusion that the decision of the High Court in Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 does have the effect as submitted on behalf of Finland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">
 
 25.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">On the merits of the issue, if it were open to be considered, in Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 , Gummow J said (at 564): 
 
 
 
 "The fundamental question is whether the person whose extradition is sought under Pt II is one in respect of whom there has been taken by the competent authorities in the extradition country a decision to invoke the operation of the criminal law by the taking of whatever steps are necessary to initiate what might fairly be described as a prosecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">" 
 
 
 
 The fact that his Honour did not agree with the conclusion of the Full Court in that case on that issue would not be of any significance here, as the facts here are considerably stronger than the facts in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">There is nothing in the majority judgment in the High Court to indicate that they would have taken a different view in principle from Gummow J if the question had fallen for determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">' 
 


 
13 In his judgment concerning s 16 of the Act Rares J also addressed the question whether it was open to the Minister to find that the Finnish warrants satisfied the criteria established by s 6(a)(i) of the Act, namely, whether they were warrants in force for the arrest of Mr Tervonen in relation to offences which he was accused of having committed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Mr Tervonen had argued before Rares J that the warrants referred to him 'being suspected on probable cause' of identified conduct and that such a formulation fell short of an accusation that he had committed a relevant offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Rares J rejected the argument.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">He referred to the following passage in Kainhofer at 540:
 'It is sufficient to say that, in considering whether a person is an extraditable person under s 6(a)(i) of the Act, it is necessary to bear in mind the statutory object of enabling Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties with countries that adopt a variety of criminal procedures different from our own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">' 
14 Rares J said (at [37] and [42]):
 
 
 '37 Mr Tervonen argued that on their face none of the 8 warrants amounted to an accusation that Mr Tervonen had actually committed an offence or that he was 'accused' of having done so within the meaning of s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">He said that a mere statement in the warrants that his arrest was claimed and that he was 'suspected with probable cause of the following criminal acts' which were then set out was insufficient to satisfy s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">
 
 ... 
 
 42 Each warrant, on its face, was termed a 'warrant'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">It was issued by a Finnish court for the arrest of Mr Tervonen who was stated to have been suspected on probable cause of having committed an offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The Minister could reasonably form the opinion that each document was a warrant, issued by a Finnish Court, in force, for the arrest of Mr Tervonen in relation to an offence against the law of Finland that he was accused of having committed within the meaning of s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">While other persons may not have formed the same view, having regard to the significant differences between the laws of other countries and Australia, to which Mason CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ referred to in Kainhofer 185 CLR at 540, I am of opinion that it was open to Senator Ellison to form the view that each of the warrants was one which met the description in s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">' 
 
 
15 As earlier noted Rares J, however, decided that each of the two notices under s 16 which were before him for examination was invalidly issued and he made orders quashing them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">When those orders were appealed it would usually be, and was, the case that the appeal would be decided without disturbing the conclusion which Rares J had reached that it was open to Senator Ellison to conclude that Mr Tervonen was an extraditable person within the meaning of s 6(a)(i) of the Act unless Mr Tervonen put that conclusion in issue by filing a notice of contention in the appeal seeking to support the conclusion of invalidity of the notices upon this ground, if necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">He did not do that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">As Flick J pointed out in the judgment in respect of which leave to appeal is sought (at [16]):
 'No argument as to the meaning of the words "accused" or "offence" occurred in the Full Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">No notice of contention was filed on behalf of Mr Tervonen seeking to raise any such argument before the Full Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">' Another consideration 
 
16 There is a further matter which is worth mentioning before I deal more directly with whether the tests in D&eacute;cor have been made out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Flick J dismissed Mr Tervonen's application in response to a notice of motion filed by the Minister which sought dismissal of the proceeding under O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules on the basis it was frivolous or vexatious or an abuse of process or, alternatively, under s 31A(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) on the basis it had no reasonable prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">Flick J dismissed the application pursuant to O 20 r 5 although it was clear that his Honour also formed the view that it had no reasonable prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">He could, as a result, have relied instead, or in addition, upon s 31A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">17 It is well established that an order for summary dismissal of an application under a rule such as O 20 r 5 is an interlocutory order (see the cases discussed in Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Company of Australia Limited [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 ( 'Jefferson Ford' ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">That is why leave to appeal is required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">However, on the majority view in Jefferson Ford Mr Tervonen would have been entitled, as of right, to appeal against an order dismissing his application under s 31A had that procedural foundation been selected instead of O 20 r 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">I need say nothing about whether a challenge to an order under s 31A would have enjoyed reasonable prospects of success but I would be reluctant to unduly curtail Mr Tervonen's opportunity to challenge the decision, when in other circumstances he might have done so as of right, unless it is clear that there is a legal bar to any possibility of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The first limb in D&eacute;cor 
 
18 Flick J decided that Mr Tervonen's argument had no prospects of success for the reasons given by Gyles J, that it should have been raised in the appeal proceeding against the orders of Rares J and that it was an abuse of process to raise the matter now.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Those matters require separate attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The decision of Gyles J 
 
19 In Kainhofer (a case which concerned extradition sought by Austria, a civil law country like Finland) a Full Court of this Court upheld the same sort of argument that Mr Tervonen wishes to rely upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">The proceedings were concerned with the operation of s 19 , rather than s 16 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">The Full Court said (at 358-359):
 'The Act clearly provides for the surrender of a person to a requesting State only if the person is accused, or has been convicted, of an extradition offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">We are of opinion that the Treaty is to the same effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">' ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">Neither the Act nor the Treaty, however, defines the circumstances in which a person is to be regarded as being "accused" of the offence or offences in respect of which surrender is sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">In the jurisprudence of this country, one would not normally speak of a person as a person who is "accused" of a criminal offence in the sense in which that expression is used in the Act unless legal proceedings for the imposition of a penalty in respect of the offence have been commenced by the laying before a magistrate or other appropriate official of an information or complaint alleging the commission of the offence or by the presentation to a court of an indictment alleging such commission or unless the person has been formally charged with the offence before an appropriate official following upon his arrest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">That statement may not be exhaustive but, in any event, it would not be sufficient to establish that a person was "accused" of an offence to show only that a complaint had been made to the police alleging the commission of the offence or that the police, or other investigating body, were conducting inquiries to determine whether there was evidence of the commission of the offence sufficient to warrant the person being "accused" of the offence in the sense mentioned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">That the warrant of arrest provides for the appellant to be taken into custody "on the strong suspicion" of having committed the specified offences clearly suggests that her presence in the Republic of Austria is required in furtherance of the investigations being conducted by the appropriate authorities in that country rather than to answer criminal charges of which she is presently "accused" in the sense to which we have referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">' (Emphasis added) 
20 However, in the High Court that approach was not regarded as sufficiently focussed upon the particular requirements of s 19 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">The majority judgment held (185 CLR at 540):
 'In the present case, the only issue for determination under s 19(2)(a) was whether the document produced was a duly authenticated warrant or copy warrant issued by the Republic of Austria for the arrest of the respondent for an extradition offence for which the surrender of the respondent was sought by the Republic of Austria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">That issue did not require a finding as to whether the respondent was a person "accused".</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">It follows that the Federal Court was in error in considering whether the s 19 magistrate could properly have found that the respondent had been "accused" of any of the four offences in relation to which the magistrate held the respondent to be eligible for surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">It is unnecessary to decide whether the Federal Court was itself in error in the meaning which it attributed to "accused" or in the effect which it attributed to the warrant for the arrest of the respondent issued by the Salzburg State Court in the Republic of Austria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">' (Emphasis added) 
21 The High Court's approach was based upon the fact that s 19 does not require a magistrate to enquire into whether a person against whom extradition is brought is an 'extraditable person' within the meaning of s 6 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Further, although whether a person is an extraditable person is a matter about which the Minister must form an opinion (s 16(2)(a)(i)), a magistrate is not entitled to review that opinion ( Kainhofer at 538).</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">It was for those reasons that Gyles J also concluded that Mr Tervonen's argument could not be sustained in relation to proceedings under s 19.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">As indicated, that decision is subject to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Mr Tervonen's interests in relation to his present application are best served by assuming the correctness of Gyles J's decision for present purposes because it strengthens the proposition that he should have been allowed to argue the matter in connection with s 16 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">22 Having regard to the judgment of the High Court in Kainhofer, it is at least arguable that Flick J was incorrect to conclude that there was no possibility of a different result, in proceedings concerning s 16 of the Act, than that reached by Gyles J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Anshun estoppel 
 
23 Flick J's decision was also based upon the decision of the High Court in Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Proprietary Limited [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">His Honour said, in the judgment in respect of which leave is sought, (at [24]):
 
 
 '24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">Any argument that a person is not an "extraditable person" , because there is no warrant for his arrest for an "offence" , is an argument which should have been raised --- if it was to be raised at all --- when the Minister's decisions under s 16 were under scrutiny by this Court either at first instance or on appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">It is an argument which should have been advanced as a reason why the Minister could not have lawfully reached the "opinion" required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">' 
 
 

24 Anshun estoppel, as the principle distilled by that decision is now known in Australia, is not an absolute bar as the following passages in the majority judgment (at 602-604) illustrate:
 '[W]e would prefer to say that there will be no estoppel unless it appears that the matter relied upon as a defence in the second action was so relevant to the subject matter of the first action that it would have been unreasonable not to rely on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Generally speaking, it would be unreasonable not to plead a defence if, having regard to the nature of the plaintiff's claim, and its subject matter it would be expected that the defendant would raise the defence and thereby enable the relevant issues to be determined in the one proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">In this respect, we need to recall that there are a variety of circumstances, some referred to in the earlier case, why a party may justifiably refrain from litigating an issue in one proceeding yet wish to litigate the issue in other proceedings e.g.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">expense, importance of the particular issue, motives extraneous to the actual litigation, to mention but a few ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">It has generally been accepted that a party will be estopped from bringing an action which, if it succeeds, will result in a judgment which conflicts with an earlier judgment ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The likelihood that the omission to plead a defence will contribute to the existence of conflicting judgments is obviously an important factor to be taken into account in deciding whether the omission to plead can found an estoppel against the assertion of the same matter as a foundation for a cause of action in a second proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">By "conflicting" judgments we include judgments which are contradictory, thought they may not be pronounced on the same cause of action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">It is enough that they appear to declare rights which are inconsistent in respect of the same transaction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">' 
25 Invocation of the principle of Anshun estoppel calls for the exercise of a judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">In the present case it required an assessment of whether it was 'unreasonable' for Mr Tervonen not to have raised his present contentions on the appeal against Rares J and whether there is a risk of 'conflicting judgments' if he is allowed to argue the matter now.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">26 Because the application of the doctrine of Anshun estoppel calls for the exercise of a judgment I am prepared to accept that there is room for argument about Flick J's conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">Abuse of process 
 
27 Finally, Flick J decided that it would be an abuse of process, and vexatious and oppressive, to put the Minister to the task of meeting another challenge to Mr Tervonen's extradition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">In part the conclusion was based upon the decision of Gyles J. Flick J said (at [28]):
 'The decision of Gyles J correctly, with respect, concluded that the argument sought to be pursued was foreclosed by the decision in Kainhofer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">To now permit the same argument to be advanced, albeit against a different respondent, would be an abuse of process as it would be the pursuit of litigation already resolved against a party and litigation having no prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">' 
28 I have already expressed my view that there is scope for debate about whether Gyles J's conclusion, that Mr Tervonen's argument was not available in relation to s 19 of the Act, foreclosed it also in relation to s 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">29 The other basis upon which Flick J concluded that Mr Tervonen's application was an abuse of process appeared to be (at [32]-[33]) that the time had arrived to put a stop to Mr Tervonen's continuing attempts to challenge decisions which must be taken to have been 'fully reviewed', or an 'ample opportunity' extended for such review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">His Honour also expressed the view (at [39]-[40]) that it was 'too late' to allow the application to proceed and to do so would be an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">30 Those conclusions were expressed somewhat generally, although his Honour did refer to his judgment in Brock v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 2091 ; (2007) 243 ALR 315 ( 'Brock' ) at [72]-[74].</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">His Honour's judgment in Brock was affirmed on appeal on 17 September 2008 ( Brock v Minister for Home Affairs [2008] FCAFC 165 ( 'Brock Appeal' ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Importantly, for present purposes, Lindgren and Tracey JJ said (at [77]):
 
 
 '77 We would also uphold the second ground advanced by Ms Gleeson of counsel for the Minister, for resisting the granting of leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">This is that according to the scheme of the provisions to which we have referred, the work to be done by the issue of a Notice of Receipt of Extradition Request under s 16 is spent once the s 19 stage in the process is reached .</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">The presence of para (c) in s 19(2) demonstrates an intention that any challenge to the satisfaction of the dual criminality provision is to take place within the framework of an application under s 21 for review of the Magistrate's order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">The Magistrate was required to satisfy herself independently that the dual criminality requirement was met, and was not required to review the Minister's having been previously satisfied that it was met for s 16 purposes: see Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 at 538-539.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">' 
 (Emphasis added) 
 
 
31 On one view, the passage I have emphasised may apply to the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">It marks an important point of departure from the views expressed in the Brock Appeal by Gray J (see at [8]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">The conclusion is binding upon me so far as it applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">32 However, their Honours were not addressing the question of whether Mr Brock was an extraditable person within the meaning of s 6 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">They were dealing with the 'dual criminality' requirement about which the Minister must form an opinion (s 16(2)(a)(ii)) and the magistrate must be satisfied (s 19(2)(c)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">The magistrate is required to form an independent view about that issue which is neither a review of the Minister's opinion nor dependent upon it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">However, whether a person is 'an extraditable person' is not a matter about which a magistrate must be satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">For present purposes (although a Full Court may in due course take a different view) I do not read the passage from the Brock Appeal which I have extracted above as eliminating the possibility of a challenge to the formation of an opinion by a Minister that a person is an extraditable person simply because the s 19 stage has been reached.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">The second limb in D&eacute;cor 
 
33 As I have concluded that there is room for legitimate argument to the effect that Flick J was incorrect in the view to which he came on each of the aspects which moved him to dismiss Mr Tervonen's latest application, it is necessary to deal with whether substantial injustice would be caused by refusing leave to appeal, supposing the decision at first instance to be wrong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">34 Although Mr Tervonen's argument, and Gyles J's tentative view about its attractions, did not extend to all the warrants upon which Finland relied when it sought his extradition, Mr Tervonen has a real and direct interest in limiting, so far as he can, the offences for which he may, in due course, be surrendered for extradition, even if he cannot avoid extradition altogether.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">That is because he must not, under the Act, be surrendered unless Finland has given a 'specialty assurance' to the effect that he will only be tried for offences for which he is surrendered (see s 22(3) and (4) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">35 In my view, therefore, there is a possibility of substantial injustice to Mr Tervonen unless it is clear that an appeal against the judgment of Flick J would have no prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">I am satisfied that this favours a grant of leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">36 I am reinforced in that approach by the fact that where a decision finally disposes of an application that is a circumstance which generally operates in favour of a grant of leave unless it may nevertheless be concluded that there are such insufficient prospects of success that the grant of leave to appeal would be of no real utility (see Ex parte Bucknell [1936] HCA 67 ; (1936) 56 CLR 221 at 225-6; see also Yap v Granich and Associates [2001] FCA 1735).</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">Conclusion 
 
37 In all the circumstances, I think there remains open to Mr Tervonen the possibility that a Full Court might conclude that he should not be prevented from putting his argument that the Minister should not have formed the opinion that he was an extraditable person with respect to some, at least, of the eight warrants relied upon by Finland.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">In the context of s 16 of the Act, even if not under s 19, such an argument gains support from the observations of the Full Court in Kainhofer and from the remarks of Gyles J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">I am also satisfied that the interests of justice require that the opportunity to argue an appeal should not be denied to Mr Tervonen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">38 Naturally, Mr Tervonen's failure to press the argument on the appeal from Rares J remains a formidable obstacle to his prospects on appeal but it is not my task to decide whether Flick J was correct or incorrect in his approach to that issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">If there is a sufficient case for the attention of a Full Court Mr Tervonen is entitled to a grant of leave to appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">39 I emphasise that my decision that Mr Tervonen should have leave to appeal against the summary dismissal of his application provides no forecast of the result of the appeal, much less of the outcome of the application if the appeal is upheld.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">As Flick J, with respect, correctly observed, the application is largely misconceived in its focus and with respect to the precise relief which was sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">Those problems remain, even if an appeal succeeds, but they are not at the centre of matters for present attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">40 I will order that leave is granted to appeal against the judgment of Flick J in Tervonen v Finland [2008] FCA 1133.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">Costs will be reserved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">41 In my view this is a suitable matter for use of the arrangements set out in O 80 of the Federal Court Rules to provide Mr Tervonen with pro bono legal representation should he wish to avail himself of it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">I will give the necessary directions to make that facility available to Mr Tervonen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">I certify that the preceding forty-one (41) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Buchanan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">Associate:

Dated: 16 October 2008

 The Applicant appeared in person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">Solicitor for the Third Respondent: Blake Dawson 

 Date of Hearing: 16 September 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 16 October 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1539.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>