<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pascoe v Ambernap Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1975 (19 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1975.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">winding up application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">sole member, sole director company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">member bankrupt</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">order that company be wound up and trustee in bankruptcy be appointed as liquidator</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application for an order pursuant to s 461(1)(a) of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) that the defendant company, Ambernap Pty Ltd, be wound up and that Mr Scott Darren Pascoe be appointed as the official liquidator of that company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 Critical to the application is the fact that Ambernap is a sole member, sole director company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The sole member and director is Mr Jon McArthur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Mr McArthur was made bankrupt by a sequestration order made in the Federal Magistrates Court on 26 March 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Mr Pascoe was appointed as Mr McArthur's trustee in bankruptcy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 It appears that the sole asset of Ambernap is shares in a company called Pendarves Estate Pty Limited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Pendarves has been in members' voluntary liquidation since January 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The liquidator of that company is Mr Manfred Holzman.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Ambernap owns approximately 34 per cent of the issued share capital in Pendarves.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">4 On 3 December 2004, Mr Holzman wrote to the solicitors for Mr Pascoe stating that Mr Holzman expected to pay a dividend of approximately $95,000 as soon as Mr Holzman received confirmation of Mr Pascoe's appointment as official liquidator of Ambernap.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">On 8 December 2008, Ambernap passed a resolution in accordance with s 249B of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) that Ambernap be wound up in accordance with s 461(1)(a) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The resolution was signed as a true record by Mr Pascoe in his capacity as the trustee of the property of Mr McArthur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Mr Pascoe was not registered as the holder of the shares in Ambernap Pty Limited held by Mr McArthur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 In those circumstances, two issues arise on the present application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The first is whether it was open to Mr Pascoe to rely upon the provisions of s 1072C of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">I have been taken this afternoon to a number of authorities which deal with the effect of that section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The decision of Campbell J in the Official Trustee in Bankruptcy v Buffier (2005) ACSR 839 seems to me plainly to support the applicability of s 1072C to authorise Mr Pascoe to pass the resolution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Other authorities to the same effect include the decision of Sackville J in Prentice v Cummins [2002] FCA 1165 at [7] ; the decision of Hasluck J in Nilant v RL &amp; KW Nominees Pty Ltd [2007] WASC 105 ; and the decision of Heerey J in Rambaldi; in the matter of Weeden, a bankrupt v Weeden [2008] FCA 1597 at [40] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">6 The second issue which arises is whether it is appropriate to appoint Mr Pascoe as the liquidator of Ambernap.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">In theory, it might be thought that there may be a conflict arising from Mr Pascoe's position as the trustee in bankruptcy of Mr McArthur and his position as the liquidator of Ambernap.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">However, it seems to me that in the present case, where Ambernap is a sole member, sole director company, there is no real difference between the interests of the bankrupt and the interests of the member of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">7 Of course, the interests of creditors need to be considered, and I have been taken to evidence of the somewhat scanty records of Ambernap, which include a balance sheet as at 30 June 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The effect of the balance sheet, after adjustment for the fact that the receivables of the company now appear to be a maximum of $97,000 is that the sole asset of the administration will be the dividend from Pendarves in that amount, whereas the liabilities of the company comprising borrowings set forth in the balance sheet are in excess of $3.7 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">8 It seems to me that, whether or not there is any real conflict of interest, I ought to accept the submission of Mr Baird, who appears for the plaintiff, that the practical and sensible approach in the present case is to appoint Mr Pascoe as the liquidator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">This is because, as I have said, the sole asset would appear to be the dividend of approximately $97,000 that will come into the administration, and there is a plain need to avoid incurring duplicated costs and expenses arising from the appointment of a different person as the liquidator of Ambernap.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">9 It seems to me, therefore, that I should make an order for the winding up of Ambernap and the appointment of Mr Pascoe as the official liquidator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">I propose to make orders and declarations in terms of [1], [2], [4], [5] and [6] of the short minutes of order, which I have signed and dated and placed with the Court papers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Associate:
Dated: 20 January 2009

 Counsel for the Plaintiff: J Baird 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Henry Davis York 

 Date of Hearing: 19 December 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 December 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1975.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>