<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLSI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 1052 (15 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1052.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interlocutory decision of federal magistrates court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application filed out of time</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">no explanation for delay</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">extension of time refused</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">leave to appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">substantially new arguments sought to be raised</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">draft grounds without substance</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an Application for Leave to Appeal from a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court: SZLSI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FMCA 418.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The Applicants, who are husband and wife, arrived from India in May 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">They applied to the Department of Immigration and Citizenship for Protection (Class XA) Visas in June 2007 and those applications were refused in July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The Refugee Review Tribunal affirmed the decision to refuse the visas by its decision in October 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The First Applicant appeared before the Court this morning unrepresented, although he did have the benefit of an interpreter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">He also appeared on behalf of his wife.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">4 In its reasons for decision published on 26 March 2008, the Federal Magistrates Court dismissed the application made to that Court pursuant to r 44.12(1)(a) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">That Rule relevantly provides as follows: 
 Show cause hearing (1) At a hearing of an application for an order to show cause, the Court may: (a) if it is not satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed -- dismiss the application... ... (2) To avoid doubt, a dismissal under paragraph (1) (a) is interlocutory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">5 The Application for Leave to Appeal was filed in this Court on 28 April 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">That Application also sought an order dispensing with compliance with O 52, r 5(2) of the Federal Court Rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 
6 Leave to appeal is required because the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court is interlocutory: Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), s 24(1A).</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">An extension of time is also required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Although there is no rule providing for the time within which an appeal is to be brought in respect to an interlocutory decision of the Federal Magistrates Court, there is an implied time limit of 21 days: SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543 at [9] per Lindgren J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">See also: Applicant M171/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 220 at [32] per Moore J; SZLRL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 716 at [6] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The Application as filed in this Court was outside the period of 21 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">7 It is not considered that any extension of time should be granted and, even if an extension of time were to be granted, leave to appeal would have been refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">8 An order extending time is " not automatic " and a " discretion to extend time is given for the sole purpose of enabling the court or justice to do justice between the parties ": Gallo v Dawson [1990] HCA 30 ; (1990) 64 ALJR 458 , 93 ALR 479 at 480 per McHugh J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">It has further been said that "[s] ome good reason should ... be shown to dispense with the requirement to file an application for leave to appeal within 21 days ": Nguyen v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCAFC 38 at [23] per Moore, Bennett and Buchanan JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">9 In the present proceeding no explanation was provided as to why there was non-compliance with the required 21 day period, other than the statement this morning by the First Applicant that he was not aware that there was any time limit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">In such circumstances, no extension of time is warranted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The discretion to extend time within which to appeal from an interlocutory decision is that conferred by O 52, r 15(2) of the Federal Court Rules and not O 52, r 5(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">And that discretion, as r 15(2) expressly provides, may be exercised " for special reasons ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 at 195, 70 ALR 185 at 193, Lockhart, Sheppard and Burchett JJ helpfully observed in respect to this provision:
 What is needed to justify an extension of time is indicated in r 15(2) by the words "for special reasons".</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">It is that there be shown a special reason why the appeal should be permitted to proceed, though filed after the expiry of twenty-one days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">In that context, the expression "special reasons" is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is twenty-one days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will, for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in the particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">We do not think the use of the expression "for special reasons" implies something narrower than this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">...</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">It should not be overlooked that r 15(2) enables leave to be given "at any time"; the "special reasons" relevant to such a power cannot but describe an elastic test, suitable for application across a range of situations, from an oversight of a day to a neglect persisted in during a prolonged period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">It would require something very persuasive indeed to justify a grant of leave after, for example, a year; equally, it may be said, something much less significant might justify leave where a party is a few days late.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">"Special reasons" must be understood in a sense capable of accommodating both types of situation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">It is an expression describing a flexible discretionary power, but one requiring a case to be made upon grounds sufficient to justify a departure, in the particular circumstances, from the ordinary rule prescribing a period within which an appeal must be filed and served.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">See also: SZLAF v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 219 at [11] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">10 In the present proceeding, the extension of time which is sought may be for a limited period of time, but there is no " special reason " to justify an extension being granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Irrespective of the absence of any explanation for non-compliance, it is further considered that the Draft Notice of Appeal raises no issue which should now be entertained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Indeed, the attempt being made in the Draft Notice of Appeal to raise issues substantially different to those resolved by the Federal Magistrates Court only provides a reason to refuse an extension of time rather than granting one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">11 Even had an extension of time been granted, leave to appeal would have been refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">12 Section 24(1A) of the 1976 Act confers on the Court " an unfettered discretion " in " unqualified terms ": Decor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 399; [1991] FCA 655 ; 104 ALR 621 at 622 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The requirement for leave to appeal is thus not a requirement that a particular test be satisfied: Lomas v Winton Shire Council [2002] FCAFC 413 at [15] per Cooper, Kiefel and Emmett JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Relevant to the exercise of the discretion, however, is a consideration of:
 
(a) whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary judge is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered; and
 
(b) whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused, supposing that decision were wrong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">See: Harrington v Rich [2008] FCAFC 61 at [25] per Sackville, Emmett and Jacobson JJ; Telstra Corporation Ltd v AAPT Ltd (1997) 38 IPR 539 at 542 per Lockhart, Beaumont and Hill JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">No question sought to be raised in the present appeal would raise any question of importance beyond the concerns of the parties to the present proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Contrast: Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission v P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 123 at [10] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">13 In the present proceeding it is not considered that the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">The Refugee Review Tribunal concluded that the factual account given by the Applicants was " lacking in detail and implausible ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Before the Federal Magistrates Court two principal arguments were advanced, namely:
 
(a) that there had been a denial of natural justice; and 
 
(b) that there had been non-compliance with s 425 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">It would also appear that the Applicants contended:
 
(c) that "[t] he Tribunal erred in law amounting to jurisdictional error in determining that relocation is a reasonable and feasible option for the applicant "; and 
 
(d) that there had been a "[c] onstructive failure of jurisdiction ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">All arguments were rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">14 The Draft Notice of Appeal as filed in this Court set forth as proposed Grounds of Appeal :
 
1. a failure " to consider political opinion of the applicant as per Article 1 (a) of the Refugees Convention "; 
 
2. a failure " to assess the claims of the applicant based on Particular social groups pursuant to Art1 of the Convention ";
 
3. the making of findings by the Tribunal " in the complete absence of evidence ";
 
4. the failure of the Tribunal to " apply 'reasonable internal relocation test' in accordance of the law " when finding that " the applicant could relocate in other places in India "; and 
 
5. that the " Federal Magistrate erred in law as he did not go into the merit of the case ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">15 If the final proposed Ground is presently left to one side, other than the fourth proposed Ground, these were not arguments advanced before the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">As was concluded in Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71 per Gibbs CJ, Mason, Wilson, Brennan, Deane and Dawson JJ:
 It is elementary that a party is bound by the conduct of his case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Except in the most exceptional circumstances, it would be contrary to all principle to allow a party, after a case had been decided against him, to raise a new argument which, whether deliberately or by inadvertence, he failed to put during the hearing when he had an opportunity to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">No explanation was forthcoming as to why those arguments were not advanced before the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">16 The course apparently now being pursued by the Applicants in seeking leave to appeal is the course of substantially abandoning the arguments that they unsuccessfully advanced before the Federal Magistrates Court and, without explanation, to now seek to advance completely new arguments on appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The discretion conferred by s 24(1A) to grant leave to appeal may be accepted as being conferred in " unqualified terms ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">But however wide that discretion may be, it would be a surprising exercise of that discretion should leave be granted in such circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">17 The arguments sought to be raised by the Draft Notice of Appeal are, in any event, each without substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">There is no reason why leave to appeal could not be confined to a particular proposed ground -- as opposed to leave being granted in respect to the Draft Notice of Appeal in its entirety.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">But none of the grounds in the Draft Notice of Appeal warrant leave being granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">18 The " Particulars " provided in relation to the first proposed Ground are but an impermissible invitation to revisit the merits of the decision as made by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Those " Particulars " thus state that "[t] he Tribunal failed to appreciate " the matters thereafter set forth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The reliance sought to be placed by the Applicants upon V v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 428 , 92 FCR 355 is misplaced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Views were there expressed as to what constituted " political opinion " for the purposes of art 1A(2) of the Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees done at Geneva on 28 July 1951.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">And the obligation of the Tribunal to make findings on material questions of fact imposed by s 430(1) of the 1958 Act was also recounted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">But, in the present proceeding, there could not be said to be any non-compliance by the Tribunal with s 430(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">It made its findings on those matters material to its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">19 Parts of the first proposed Ground of Appeal are, in any event, in direct conflict with the manner in which the claim was advanced before the Refugee Review Tribunal and the evidence then given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">The first proposed Ground thus states in part as follows:
 ... During the hearing the applicant stated that when his former business partner wanted to overtake his business from him as he was a Hindu, he complained to the police and the police did not protect him and asked for bribes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">But, before the Tribunal, his evidence was that he did not complain to the police.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The Tribunal thus recounted as follows the evidence then given:
 ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">Asked why he didn't report the threats and beating to the police, the applicant claimed that the police wouldn't do anything unless they were bribed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Tribunal put to the applicant that it was not possible to know for sure that the police would not act on his behalf without a bribe unless he actually reported the incidents to them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">The applicant claimed that he had experience with the traffic police and knows that they ask for money for any reason and will beat you if you do not pay them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Not only is there a divergence between the manner in which the proceeding was conducted before the Federal Magistrates Court and this Court, there is also a divergence between the factual account now sought to be advanced for determination by this Court and the factual account advanced before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">In the absence of an explanation, leave to appeal to raise such a ground should not be granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">20 The same conclusion may be expressed in respect to the second proposed Ground of Appeal .</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The reliance in that ground upon Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 , 197 ALR 389 and C v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 1430 , 94 FCR 366 is again equally misplaced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">This proposed Ground also suffers from a further difficulty -- it purports to set forth as " Particulars " matters of evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">It is thus stated that (without alteration):
 ... it is beyond any doubt that the authority knew about the applicant's complains.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">They knew that he was being targeted for money in his business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">But it was submitted on behalf of the Respondent Minister that there was no such evidence before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">The Tribunal's exposition in its reasons for decision of the " Claims and Evidence " does not refer to any such evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">This would be a further reason for not granting leave to appeal -- at least in respect to this proposed Ground.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">
 
21 The third proposed Ground of Appeal is also without substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">The findings as made by the Tribunal were all open to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">22 The proposed fourth Ground is again without substance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Relocation within India was not a basis upon which the Tribunal proceeded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">And, as noted by the Federal Magistrates Court:
 [14] The particulars set out under ground 2 are taken from a precedent with no clear application to the present case, and they also garble several contentions which are difficult to understand as a coherent argument.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">The Tribunal, in fact, did not address issues of relocation in the present case, and was not required to do so on the path of reasoning it followed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">23 The final proposed Ground proceeds from a misconception as to the role of the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The task of that Court was to determine if the Tribunal had committed jurisdictional error ( Migration Act 1958 (Cth), s 474 ; Plaintiff S 157/2002 v Commonwealth [2003] HCA 2 , 211 CLR 476).</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Its task was not to " go into the merit of the case ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">See: O'Donnell B, ' Jurisdictional Error, Invalidity and the Role of Injunction in s 75(v) of the Australian Constitution ' (2007) 28 Aust Bar Rev 291; Beaton-Wells C, ' Judicial Review of Migration Decisions: Life After S157' (2005) 33 FL Rev 141.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">24 It is thus considered that an extension of time should be refused and the proceeding should be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The Applicants should pay the costs of the First Respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">ORDERS 
 
25 The orders of the Court are:
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">The application to extend time within which to seek leave to appeal is refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">The proceeding is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">The Applicants are to pay the costs of the First Respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">I certify that the preceding twenty-five (25) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">Associate:

Dated: 15 July 2008

 The First Applicant: The First Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: DLA Phillips Fox 

 Date of Hearing: 15 July 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 July 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1052.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>