<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Southern Equity Pty Ltd v Timevale Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1395 (3 September 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1395.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">jurisdiction</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">cross-vesting</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether in interests of justice to transfer proceeding by consent to state court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">doubt about whether judicial power of the commonwealth could be exercised</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">proceeding may have been a nullity</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">proposed amendment to remove federal element from proceeding</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">thrown away by reason of amendment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">proceeding transferred to state court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether court should order that costs be taxed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">file to be forwarded to state court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">courts and judges</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 

 
1 This unfortunate proceeding was commenced on 30 March 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">For some time, it has been the oldest proceeding in my docket and, on occasions, I have described it publicly as the most delinquent proceeding in my docket.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">It has proved extraordinarily difficult, over almost two and a half years, to produce a situation in which the parties would be ready to go to trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">In recent months, I have taken to making somewhat stringent timetabling orders, in an effort to persuade the parties to focus on the case, and to prepare it adequately for trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Much time and effort has been wasted on both sides over that time, and there have been long periods of delay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The Court file is replete with notes of telephone conversations by my associates with the solicitors for the parties, seeking information as to why timetabling orders have not been complied with.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The picture is, indeed, a very sorry one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">2 The matter was listed for the trial to begin this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">This has caused a change of counsel on both sides in fairly recent times, and that, in turn, has caused a flurry of activity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">On 19 August 2008, the respondent forwarded to the Court a further amended defence and cross-claim, apparently in the hope of seeking leave to file it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">I had intended to deal with any leave issue this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The further amended defence and cross-claim raised for the first time, so far as the pleadings were concerned, a constitutional issue concerned with the nature of the judicial power of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">At a previous directions hearing, I had asked the question whether some of the relief sought by the applicant really amounted to seeking the advisory opinion of the Court on what might be the situation if certain events were to occur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The respondent finally sought to take that up in the amended defence and cross-claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">3 Subsequently, on 28 and 29 August, ie Thursday and Friday of last week, and after prompting by my associate, the solicitors for the respondent began sending the requisite notices, pursuant to s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth), to the Attorneys-General for the Commonwealth, the states and the relevant territories.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">I am advised that responses have been received from all but the Attorney-General for Western Australia by this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">There is a question, however, as to whether a reasonable time has elapsed, so as to permit the proceeding to go ahead this morning in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">4 At 9.29 am today, there arrived on the facsimile machine in my chambers minutes of order proposed by consent of the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Those orders involve the vacation of the trial date, leave to the applicant to file a further amended application and further amended statement of claim, an order pursuant to s 5(4) of the Jurisdiction of Courts (Cross-vesting) Act 1987 (Cth) transferring the proceeding to the Supreme Court of New South Wales, and some consequential orders as to costs in relation to the costs thrown away by the amendments sought, and by the vacation of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">5 I was mystified by receiving these orders at such a late stage and in that form, but counsel for both parties have enlightened me substantially this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The effect of the further amendments proposed by the applicant is to eliminate, perhaps altogether, the federal elements of the claim, and to focus, largely, on points of construction in relation to the licence agreement that is the subject of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The applicant's representatives have a concern that, if it turns out that the Court does not have jurisdiction because relief sought originally was not within the exercise of the judicial power of the Commonwealth, then it might turn out that the entire proceeding was a nullity, and that the other matters that had been raised in it were not capable of determination in this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">6 It is essentially for that reason that it seems to me that it might be in the interests of justice to accede to the request that I transfer the matter to a State Supreme Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">While the question whether the relief sought, some of which remains in the proposed further amended application, is truly relief that can be granted by a court would still have to be determined, it would not have to be determined in the context of the exercise of the judicial power of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">If there were doubt about the jurisdiction of this Court from the outset, then it would be better that the parties not be required to have that doubt resolved to the disadvantage of one or other of them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">7 I confess reluctance to order the transfer at the present time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The amounts of money spent in the preparation of this proceeding for trial have far exceeded what ought to have been spent, and the transfer of the matter to another court, effectively with a new start in relation to pleadings, is something that I am very reluctant to do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Having regard to the difficulties caused by the possible constitutional issue, and by the abandonment of what might be called the elements of federal jurisdiction in the proceeding, however, I am prepared to accede to what the parties desire me to do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">8 The transfer that is sought is to the Supreme Court of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The facility to which the licence agreement relates is in Queensland, and the respondent is a Queensland corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">On the other hand, the respondent is represented by lawyers from Sydney.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The governing law of the licence agreement is stated to be the law of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">In pleadings to date, the respondent has relied on a New South Wales statute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Accordingly, the dispute is not entirely divorced from New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">In the circumstances, I think I should accede to the parties' agreed desire that the transfer should be to the Supreme Court of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">9 On looking closely at the terms of the orders sought, I have some difficulty with those relating to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Having heard counsel in relation to the orders for costs, I have decided that I am willing to make the order that the applicant pay the respondent's costs thrown away by the amendment, and by the vacation of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">I am not, however, prepared to make the order proposed that those costs be taxed and payable forthwith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The practicalities of such an order seem to me to defeat it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Once the proceeding is transferred to the Supreme Court of New South Wales, the file must be sent immediately by the registry of this Court to the registry of that court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The absence of the file would, effectively, defeat any attempt by a registrar of this Court to tax costs pursuant to such an order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">10 The parties have discussed the matter between themselves, and resolved it by counsel for the applicant offering an undertaking to consent to an order in the Supreme Court of New South Wales that the costs the subject of that order be assessed and paid forthwith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">11 The orders I make, then, are as follows:
 
The Court notes that the applicant by its counsel undertakes to consent to an order in the Supreme Court of New South Wales that the costs the subject of para 4 of the orders be assessed and payable forthwith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">By consent, the Court orders:
1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">That the date fixed for the trial of this proceeding, 3 September 2008, be vacated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">That the applicant have leave to file a further amended application and further
 amended statement of claim in the form tendered to the Court this day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Pursuant to s 5(4) of the Jurisdiction of Courts (Cross-vesting) Act 1987 (Cth), that
 the proceeding be transferred to the Supreme Court of New South Wales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That the applicant pay the respondent's costs thrown away by:

 (a) the filing of the further amended application and further amended statement of
 claim; and

 
(b) the vacation of the trial date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">I certify that the preceding eleven (11) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gray.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Associate:

Dated: 11 September 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr R Garratt QC, with Ms M Schilling 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Maddocks 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr C Harris SC, with Mr M O'Connor 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Matthews Folbigg Pty Ltd 

 Date of Hearing: 3 September 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 September 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1395.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>