<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Worimi Local Aboriginal Land Council v Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales (No 2) (Corrigendum dated 19 January 2009) [2008] FCA 1929 (18 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1929.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">non-claimant application under native title act 1993 (cth) seeking determination that no native title exists over land</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">previous claimant applications for determination that native title exists struck out for not meeting requirements of act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">previous claimant joined as third respondent under s 84(5) of the act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">third respondent opposes non-claimant application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">role of minister in proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">minister has not abandoned right to participate</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">minister not required to establish interest to remain a party</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">burden of proof</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">evidentiary burden</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">requirement to prove negative proposition on balance of probabilities</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">no presumption of native title</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">third respondent is not required to establish native title but is required to adduce evidence once applicant has adduced sufficient evidence from which the negative proposition may be inferred</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">third respondent has not adduced sufficient evidence to cast doubt on applicant's case</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">no sufficient evidence that asserted rights and interests arise under normative system of traditional laws acknowledged and traditional customs observed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">applicant entitled to determination that there is no native title over the land</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c15">native title</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 INTRODUCTION 
 
1 The applicant ('the Land Council') seeks a declaration that no native title exists in land at Boat Harbour in the Local Government Area of Port Stephens, Parish of Tomaree, County of Gloucester, State of New South Wales, being Lot 576 in Deposited Plan 48823 ('the Land' or 'Lot 576').</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">This is a non-claimant application, commenced on 31 December 2004, for an approved determination of native title pursuant to s 13 of the Native Title Act 1993 (Cth) ('the Act').</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">An application may be made to the Court under Part 3 of the Act for a determination of native title in relation to an area for which there is no approved determination of native title (s 13(1)(a) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">A determination made on such an application will constitute an ' approved determination of native title ' (s 13(3)(a)) unless varied or revoked (s 13(4)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">2 The Land Council is a body corporate established under s 50 of the Aboriginal Land Rights Act 1983 (NSW) ('the NSW Act') for an area delineated under s 49 of the NSW Act and known as the Worimi Local Aboriginal Land Council Area, which includes the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Membership of the Land Council is not confined by statute to persons with a traditional association with the area but, by s 54(2A) of the NSW Act, is open to adult Aboriginal persons who either reside within the Land Council's area or have a sufficient association with that area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Membership is also open to Aboriginal owners in relation to land in that area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Formal requirements 
 
3 The Land Council's non-native title rights and interests arose from the grant and transfer of the Land to the Land Council by the Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales ('the Minister') pursuant to s 36 of the NSW Act on 16 March 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Following the transfer of the area that includes Lot 576, the Land Council holds a non-native title interest ' in relation to the whole of the area in relation to which the determination is sought '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">It is the holder of an ' an estate in fee simple ... subject to any native title rights and interests existing in relation to the land immediately before the transfer ' (s 36(9) of the NSW Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">As the holder of such an interest, the Land Council is entitled under s 61(1) (Table, clause 2) of the Act to make the present application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Section 40AA of the NSW Act prevents the Land Council from selling, exchanging, leasing, disposing of, mortgaging or otherwise dealing with the Land unless the Land is the subject of an approved determination of native title within the meaning of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">4 On 11 October 2004, the Land Council resolved, pursuant to s 40D of the NSW Act, that Lot 576 was not of cultural significance to Aborigines of the area and to dispose of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The non-claimant application was lodged on 31 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">5 The proceedings were commenced by Peter Hillig in his capacity as administrator of the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Following the cessation of his appointment, an order was made on 29 June 2007 substituting the Land Council as the applicant in these proceedings pursuant to O 6 r 11 of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The Minister was automatically joined pursuant to s 84(4) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">6 The non-claimant application was notified in accordance with s 66 of the Act:
 
a. in the Sydney Morning Herald on 23 February 2005;
 
b. in the Koori Mail on 23 February 2005; and
 
c. in the Port Stephens Examiner on 24 February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">7 The notification period for the application (s 66 of the Act) was from 9 March to 8 June 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">There is no dispute that the application was appropriately published and notified and that the requirements of s 66 of the Act have been complied with.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">8 A notice of intention to become a party to these proceedings was filed within the three month time period provided for in the s 66 notice by New South Wales Native Title Services Limited ('Native Title Services') and by Mr and Mrs Parkinson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The application by Mr and Mrs Parkinson to be joined to the proceedings was dismissed ( Peter Hillig as Administrator of Worimi Local Aboriginal Land Council v Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales, State Minister under the Native Title Act 1993 (Cth) [2006] FCA 61).</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Native Title Services was joined as a party on 5 July 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">On 11 March 2008, an order was made granting leave to that party (whose name had been amended to NTS Corp Limited) to withdraw as a party to the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">9 I have recorded the history of this matter in Worimi Local Aboriginal Land Council v Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales [2007] FCA 1357 (' Worimi 2007 ').</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">That history includes the striking out of two claimant applications filed by the third respondent, Mr Gary Dates, who prefers to be called Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">I will refer to him as Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Each application was struck out pursuant to s 84C of the Act for failure to comply with s 61 ( Hillig as Administrator of Worimi Local Aboriginal Land Council v Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales (No 2) [2006] FCA 1115 ; Worimi v Minister for Lands for the State of New South Wales [2006] FCA 1770 (' Worimi 2006 ')).</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Worimi did not give notice within the notification period that he wanted to be a party to the non-claimant application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">On 30 March 2007, Worimi filed an amended notice of motion to be joined as a party to the non-claimant application pursuant to s 84(5) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">For the reasons set out in Worimi 2007 , I made an order that he be joined as a respondent to these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">10 No other person asserting the existence of native title in Lot 576 gave notice under s 84(3) of the Act within the notification period of a desire to be a party to the non-claimant application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">11 The hearing commenced over three years after lodgement of the non-claimant application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The delay resulted from the numerous applications in this matter, from the application for joinder by Mr and Mrs Parkinson to repeated applications for adjournment by Worimi to enable him to prepare claimant applications, seek legal advice and file evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">In the time between the filing of the application and the hearing, no Aboriginal person other than Worimi has come forward seeking to become a party to the non-claimant application pursuant to s 84(5) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">No Aboriginal person other than Worimi has come forward to resist the declaration sought by the Land Council on the basis of a positive assertion of the existence of native title in relation to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The only Aboriginal people other than Worimi to come forward and to give evidence in these proceedings have done so as witnesses for the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">No claimant applications other than those filed by Worimi have been made asserting the existence of native title in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">12 The Land has been described as "Worimi country" by Worimi and by other Worimi witnesses called by the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Worimi places reliance on the evidence of these witnesses, Worimi people who were born and raised in the Port Stephens area and who have been claimants in previous native title applications over areas held by the Land Council close to Lot 576, and on their evidence that Lot 576 was part of "our traditional land" and that it falls within the boundaries of the Worimi nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">13 During the course of the proceedings, there was a view of the Land and the place adjacent to the Land, described by Worimi as "the baptism place" on Kingsley Beach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Only women inspected the beach site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">14 Section 61 of the Act identifies applications that may be made under Division 1 of Part 3 of the Act and identifies the persons who have standing to invoke the Court's jurisdiction by making such an application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">It is not in issue that the non-claimant application properly invokes the Court's jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The issues 
 
15 A number of questions arise:
 
&#8226; What is the role of the Minister in these proceedings?</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">&#8226; What is the burden of proof on the Land Council and on Worimi?</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">&#8226; Is there a presumption that native title exists over the Land?</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">&#8226; Does the description of the Land as part of "traditional Worimi country" establish a presumption of native title?</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">&#8226; Must the Land Council provide evidence to negative the existence of native title over Lot 576 to the extent of negativing each of the elements of native title under the Act?</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">&#8226; In order to defeat a prima facie case of no native title, must Worimi adduce evidence of each of the elements of native title under the Act?</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">&#8226; What is the relevance of the fact that some of the witnesses called by the Land Council have made claimant applications seeking determinations of native title over land within Worimi traditional land in the Port Stephens area?</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">&#8226; What is the Land Council evidence?</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">&#8226; What is Worimi's evidence?</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">&#8226; What does the evidence as a whole establish?</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">THE ROLE OF THE MINISTER 
 
16 As noted in [5], the Minister was automatically joined as a party to the proceedings under s 84(4) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Section 84(4) provides that the relevant State Minister is a party to proceedings, without any expressed limitation, where the area covered by the application is within the jurisdictional limits of the State.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The Minister did not exercise his entitlement under s 84(4) to give notice to the Court that he does not want to be a party to the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Worimi did not apply to have him removed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">He remains a party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">17 Worimi says that, because the Land was transferred to the Land Council in fee simple, the Minister has no interest in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">He submits that, as there can be no positive determination of native title in these proceedings, no compensation obligation can accrue to the Minister as a result of these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">He submits that the Minister has no interest that could be affected by these proceedings: no interest to protect, no interest which may be affected by a determination that native title does not exist in the Land and no obligation of fairness to be accorded by permitting cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">18 Worimi submits that the Minister has no right to cross-examine witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">He also appears to submit that the Minister has no right to make submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">He relies in part on the fact that, although the Minister had been represented at all directions hearings, the Minister had not actively participated in the proceedings until the business day before the trial and had not filed evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">19 Worimi submits that no party has an automatic right to cross-examine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">However, as the Minister points out, s 27 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) ('the Evidence Act ') provides that a party may question any witness, except as provided by that Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Section 28 provides for cross-examination by more than one party, subject to an order of the Court directing otherwise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">The Court may restrict cross-examination, but that has not occurred in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">No such order was sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Worimi raised the role of the Minister at a late stage of the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The Minister was not on notice that Worimi sought to limit his participation until the proceedings were well advanced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">No good reason was given for such a course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">20 The Minister did not file evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">His participation was in the form of limited cross-examination and making submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">I do not see how his participation inappropriately prejudiced Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The case advanced by the Minister did not raise matters that were new in the proceedings and were, other than as to his participation, the subject of submissions from the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">21 The Minister's stated concern is to ensure that, if the Court is not satisfied that there are no native title rights and interests in the Land, the Court does not make findings in relation to matters which, by operation of s 225 of the Act, would need to be addressed if the Court were to make a positive determination of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The Minister submits that, if the Land Council fails to discharge the burden of proof, the application should simply be dismissed without making any findings resulting from Worimi's assertions as to the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">In other words, acceptance of Worimi's assertions might throw sufficient doubt upon the absence of native title without the necessary result being that native title, under the Act, exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">22 There is no basis for Worimi's suggestion that the Minister has abandoned the right to participate in the proceedings or that he is bound to take a submitting role.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">I see no basis for Worimi's submission that the Minister's role is somehow constrained and that his counsel has no right to cross-examine witnesses in the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">I do not accept that the Minister's interests are not affected by a determination in the proceedings simply because the Land is owned by the Land Council and not by the Crown.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">I accept the Minister's submission that, as the Crown in right of the State holds the radical title to the Land, it has an interest in knowing whether or not, and in what way, its radical title is burdened by native title rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">He also has an interest in the operation of the NSW Act, including the operation of s 36(9) and s 40AA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">23 In any event, the Act does not require the Minister to establish an interest in order to be a party to the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">I will not disregard the cross-examination by counsel for the Minister or the submissions made on his behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">THE BURDEN OF PROOF 
 The legal burden 
 
24 It is common ground that the Land Council may not deal with the Land if it is subject to native title rights and interests existing in relation to the Land (ss 36(9) and 40AA of the NSW Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Where there is no approved determination of native title, an application may be made to the Court under the Act for a determination of native title in relation to the Land (s 13(1) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">The Land Council, as a party holding a non-native title interest in relation to the Land, may make an application for a native title determination as mentioned in s 13(1) (s 61(1) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">25 All parties accept that the Land Council bears the burden of proof to satisfy the Court that no native title exists in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">All parties agree that the onus is on the Land Council to establish that there is no native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">26 The Land Council and the Minister accept that the applicable standard of proof is the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">While there was some suggestion from Worimi that the standard of proof may be higher in the present case, he ultimately accepted that the Land Council must prove its case on the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Worimi's written submissions state that it ' is common ground that the standard of proof is the balance of probabilities '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">27 There can be no doubt that the Land Council's case was and is clear: it seeks a determination that there is no native title in relation to Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The onus of establishing that fact is an onus borne by the Land Council on the civil standard, the balance of probabilities, taking account of the whole of the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">28 All parties accept that, in a non-claimant application for a determination that native title does not exist, the Court is not required to and cannot make a determination that native title does exist under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">29 There is no dispute that the Court may only grant the declaratory relief sought by the Land Council if satisfied that the Land is not subject to native title rights and interests existing in relation to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">30 Worimi's submissions regarding the matters that he says the Land Council must prove in order to discharge its legal burden of proof are put in various ways which are not of identical effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">He says that the Land Council must establish that native title existed at sovereignty, importing a requirement to establish the laws and customs observed in respect of the Land and then show that the observation of those laws and customs has ceased and that any connection which Aboriginal people may have had with the Land under traditional law and custom has not been maintained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">He also asserts that there is a presumption that native title exists over the Land which must be disproved by the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">31 I will address the issue of the evidentiary burden on the parties separately from the issue of whether or not there is a presumption of native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">However, because of the link between these issues, this approach necessarily involves some repetition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">The evidentiary burden 
 
32 Worimi says that, because the Land Council asserts that native title does not exist, it is required to prove the absence of each of the elements necessary to establish native title under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">On 19 December 2007, after Worimi had been joined and a hearing date allocated, I directed the filing of Statements of Contentions by the Land Council and by Worimi, better to understand the case being made by each of these parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">While the document that the parties were directed to file was called a Statement of Contentions, it was clearly not a pleading in the sense used in Jango v Northern Territory [2006] FCA 318 ; (2006) 152 FCR 150.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">In that case, the "Points of Claim" filed by the applicant was considered to define the nature of the applicant's claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">33 Worimi says that the material facts in respect of each of the facts and contentions and in respect of each of the elements necessary to establish native title have not been articulated in the Land Council's Statement of Facts and Contentions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">He treats them as equivalent to pleadings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">They are not and were not intended by me to be so, nor were they understood by the Land Council as such.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">Submissions on the evidentiary burden 
 
34 Submissions have been made concerning what has been called ' the evidential onus ' of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">The Land Council contends that, on establishing the matters necessary to demonstrate that the appropriate notification procedures have occurred and in the absence of a claimant application, the Court should infer that no native title exists over the Land and ' the evidential onus ' shifts to Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">The Land Council and the Minister both say that Worimi has ' an onus ' regarding his assertion that native title exists over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">35 Worimi submits that the applicant in a non-claimant application under s 61(1) of the Act for a determination of the absence of native title has the same onus of proof as an applicant in a claimant application under s 61(1) for a determination of the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">That is, Worimi submits that the proof of no native title equates to the proof required for a determination of the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">By that, he says, all of the matters that would need to be proved to establish native title must be proved in the negative for a declaration of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">It follows, he says, that the applicant for a determination of the absence of native title would need to adduce evidence as to the historical, archaeological, linguistic and anthropological matters in the light of direct testimony of Aboriginal witnesses to establish the status of traditional laws and customs pre-sovereignty and since 1788.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">36 Worimi's basic contention is that all questions of proof, both "legal" and "evidential", are borne by the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">Worimi contends that the Land Council must clearly and unequivocally prove an absence of native title, adducing evidence including expert evidence covering the time from pre-sovereignty through to the present day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">Worimi relies on the beneficial nature of the Act and the objects of the Act to provide for the recognition and protection of native title, to establish ways in which future dealings affecting native title may proceed and to set standards for those dealings (ss 3(a) and 3(b) of the Act respectively).</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">37 While he denies that native title does not exist over the Land, Worimi has previously asserted that there is no burden upon him either to disprove the Land Council's case or to prove that native title exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">However, in written submissions, Worimi accepted that if the Land Council establishes a prima facie case that native title does not exist over the Land, that is, if there is sufficient evidence from which the negative proposition may be inferred, the evidential burden shifts to Worimi to adduce evidence to raise a doubt as to the existence of a fact in issue, being the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">He is then obliged to advance evidence which, he says, the Land Council would have to rebut in the discharge of its legal burden of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">38 Worimi's submissions can be summarised as follows: 
 
&#8226; Prior to amendments to the Act in 1998, the applicant in the case of a non-claimant application bore an onus under s 70(1)(a) of ' having to make out a prima facie case for a determination that native title had been extinguished ', either in the sense that there had been technical extinguishment by inconsistent government dealing, or in the sense that any pre-sovereignty connection to that Land under traditional laws and customs had been lost.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">&#8226; No change was effected by the 1998 amendments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Specifically, there is no suggestion of an intention to reverse the onus of proof on non-claimant applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">&#8226; It is the Land Council that is seeking a determination by virtue of s 61(1) (clause (2)) of the Act and, accordingly, the Land Council bears the onus of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">&#8226; The legal burden of proving the necessary elements entitling the Land Council to a declaration is on the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">&#8226; The evidence required to satisfy the onus of proof to obtain a declaration of no native title is not to be satisfied without strict proof of historical and anthropological facts through the use of widely accepted authoritative writings and expert evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">&#8226; This expert evidence is necessary before a prima facie case is established and before there is any consideration of the evidence adduced by Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">&#8226; In weighing the evidence, it is necessary to take account of the ability of the party bearing the onus of proof to adduce evidence on a particular fact in issue and the extent to which it has done so or could do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">&#8226; The evidential burden does not shift to Worimi until the Land Council has proven a prima facie case which would negative the proposition that the Land is subject to native title rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">39 Worimi equates the legal burden of proving the absence of native title with an obligation to prove that each of the necessary elements to establish the existence of native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">Worimi emphasises that the following factual matters must be established by an applicant to prove the existence of native title:
 A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">That in 1788 there was a society of Aboriginal people who were unified by a normative system or 'body of norms' of traditional laws acknowledged, and customs observed, in an Area being claimed; B.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">The nature of the traditional laws and customs of the society in 1788; C. That the traditional laws and customs that form the normative system of the society give rise to native title rights and interests in land and water in an Area being claimed; D. The rights and interests that are possessed under the traditional laws and customs of the society; E. The traditional laws and customs of the society have been passed from generation to generation and had a continuous existence and vitality without substantial interruption since 1788 to the present time; F. The traditional laws and customs provide a "connection" between the Aboriginal people and the Area being claimed that has been maintained by the continued acknowledgement of traditional laws, and observance of traditional customs to the present day; G. Whether the current laws and customs have changed and adapted so not to sustain the same rights and interests that existed at sovereignty and, as such, have not remained traditional or have been lost or abandoned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">40 Worimi accepts that Aboriginal evidence provides the foundation for evidence of the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">The Land Council has called Worimi people to give evidence of laws and customs and of the connection with land in the area of Port Stephens.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Worimi says that the Land Council cannot start to prove that the Land is not subject to native title rights and interests in relation to it until it has first proven what the nature and content of those native title rights and interests were at, or around, the time of sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">He says that, once this is done, the Land Council can ' start to deconstruct this conclusion ' to prove that any connection has not been maintained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">He contends that the calling of seven Aboriginal persons to say that they have no specific knowledge about the Land falls short of the proof required to demonstrate that the Land is not subject to native title rights and interests in relation to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">Worimi seems to base his submissions on an inference arising from the pre-sovereignty presence of Aboriginal people on and around the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">He says that it is necessary to show, as a minimum, that the Worimi people as a whole ' no longer observe and acknowledge traditional laws and customs in relation to the Port Stephens area where the Land is located '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">Worimi says that the Land Council must prove that the existence and observance of those laws and customs has been substantially interrupted from sovereignty or that they no longer exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">41 The Land Council says that the standard of proof does not change or become more onerous than the civil standard because these proceedings concern native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">It acknowledges that, in considering whether that standard has been satisfied, the Court will have regard to the objects and purposes of the Act ( Munn for and on behalf of the Gunggari People v State of Queensland [2001] FCA 1229 ; (2001) 115 FCR 109 at [28] ) and acknowledges that it is required to prove the negative proposition: that there is no native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">The Land Council does contend, however, that once it adduces evidence which, if accepted, establishes the negative proposition, the evidential onus to adduce evidence to show that the negative proposition is incorrect shifts to Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">The Land Council does not accept that it is required to establish the negative proposition by establishing the absence of each of the elements necessary to prove the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">42 The Land Council and Worimi appear to agree that the evidential burden shifts to Worimi if the Land Council establishes sufficient evidence from which the negative proposition of no native title may be inferred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">The real difference between the parties relates to their submissions regarding what evidence is sufficient to establish the negative proposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Consideration 
 
43 A native title determination application may only be made in accordance with the Act ( Commonwealth v Clifton (2007) 164 FCR 355 at [40]---[57]) and in accordance with the procedures set out in the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">As the Full Court noted in Clifton , stringent requirements are placed upon an applicant seeking a determination of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">If I am not satisfied that native title does not exist, the application should be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">44 The Act does not provide for a procedure that enables a respondent to obtain a determination of native title which that party could not obtain as an applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">The Act requires a native title claimant application to be authorised by the relevant native title claim group ( Clifton at [48]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Worimi has failed to maintain his filed claimant applications as they were not authorised by his asserted claim group, as described in each claimant application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">45 The beneficial nature of the Act does not mean that a different standard applies to the evidentiary burden and the onus of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">Worimi has not advanced sufficient reason why the Land Council's application should not be determined on the civil standard of the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">In any event, Worimi appears to have accepted that the applicable standard of proof is the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">46 In the absence of a claimant application following the giving of notice of the making of the non-claimant application in respect of the Land, the Court is entitled to be satisfied that no other claim group or groups assert a claim to hold native title to the Land ( Clifton at [59]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">At the very least, this supports an inference of an absence of native title over the Land, subject to the matters to be raised by Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">47 It does not follow that the absence of a native title claim means that, without more, there is a declaration of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">As was recognised in the joinder of Worimi to these proceedings, Worimi's assertion of native title rights and interests may lead to a more informed decision in the non-claimant application ( Worimi 2007 at [30]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">Worimi may not be able to establish that native title does exist but his evidence, if accepted, may cast doubt on the Land Council's case ( Worimi 2007 at [36]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">48 It does not follow, as Worimi has previously asserted, that his inability to secure a positive native title determination means that there is no evidentiary burden on him to support his contention that there is native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">As in other proceedings, in proceedings seeking a judgment in rem that no native title exists and in proceedings arising under beneficial legislation, the Court will assess the whole of the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">49 The onus of proof is on the Land Council, which must satisfy the legal burden on the balance of probabilities, but there is no reason to conclude that if the Land Council establishes a prima facie case of no native title, there is no onus on Worimi to adduce any evidence in support of his assertion of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">In dealing with the defensive use of native title in Kokatha People v State of South Australia [2007] FCA 1057 , Finn J observed at [52] that a non-applicant native title claimant who is unable to obtain authorisation to make a s 61 claim stands in no different position than any person who claims native title but is unable to institute proceedings to have that claim established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">50 The evidentiary burden on a party in Worimi's position in circumstances where the moving party must prove a negative proposition has been described in Apollo Shower Screens Pty Ltd v Building and Construction Industry Long Service Payments Corporation (1985) 1 NSWLR 561 (at 565) as similar to ' the evidential burden placed upon an accused in a criminal trial who seeks to raise the issue of self-defence which the Crown must disprove '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">51 Derschaw v Sutton (1996) 17 WAR 419 was a case of defensive native title to a criminal prosecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">That is, the defendants sought to establish the existence of native title as a defence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Justice Franklyn (with whom Murray J agreed) held at 431 that the defendants had to adduce or direct the Court's attention to evidence of each of the material matters necessary to establish the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">Despite Worimi's submission that the case has no precedent value, it should, as a decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia, be followed unless it is plainly wrong ( Farah Constructions Pty Ltd v Say-Dee Pty Ltd (2007) 230 CLR 89 at [135]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">Similar reasoning has been followed in other cases (see, for example, Mason v Tritton (1994) 34 NSWLR 572; Dillon v Davies (1998) 156 ALR 142 ; Lewis v Wanganeen [2005] SASC 36).</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">Special leave to appeal Derschaw to the High Court was refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">In my respectful opinion, it is not plainly wrong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">Justice Franklyn , drawing from Mabo v The State of Queensland (No 2) [1992] HCA 23 ; (1992) 175 CLR 1 , pointed out that, in the absence of evidence going to each element of native title, there is insufficient foundation for the claim to have legal justification.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">I agree, with respect, with that analysis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">To establish the existence of native title under the Act, the same elements of native title apply whether native title is asserted by an applicant or by a respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">52 If the elements of native title are established by a non-applicant claimant, it can prevent a determination that native title does not exist, although it cannot secure a positive determination of native title under s 225 of the Act ( Kokatha at [50] per Finn J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">However, Worimi's evidence may be sufficient to raise a doubt as to the non-existence of native title without amounting to proof necessary for a claimant application or for a finding that native title exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">53 The Minister submits that a party seeking to resist the making of the orders sought in a non-claimant application must adduce or identify at least some credible evidence addressing the following matters as identified in Members of the Yorta Yorta Aboriginal Community v State of Victoria [2002] HCA 58 ; (2002) 214 CLR 422 , De Rose v State of South Australia [2003] FCAFC 286 ; (2003) 133 FCR 325 and De Rose v South Australia (No 2) [2005] FCAFC 110 ; (2005) 145 FCR 290: 
 
 
 a that at the time of sovereignty there was "a body of persons united in and by its acknowledgement and observance of a body of laws and customs" (the "pre-sovereignty society"); 
 
 b the nature and content of a normative body of laws and customs (the "traditional laws and customs") pursuant to which rights and interests were held at the time of sovereignty; 
 
 c the nature and content of the rights and interests held at the time of sovereignty pursuant to the traditional laws and customs (the "traditional rights and interests"); 
 
 d that the pre-sovereignty society has substantially maintained its identity and existence from generation to generation in accordance with the traditional laws and customs through to the present time; 
 
 e that the traditional laws and customs have been acknowledged and observed by the pre-sovereignty society and their successors, and that such acknowledgement and observance has continued substantially uninterrupted since sovereignty; 
 
 f that since sovereignty the pre-sovereignty society and their successors have maintained a connection with the application area and have transmitted rights and interests in relation to the application area by and in accordance with the traditional laws and customs; 
 
 g that they, the native title claim group (as a whole), acknowledge and observe the traditional laws and customs; 
 
 h the nature and content of the traditional laws and customs observed by members of the native title claim group; 
 
 i that, by the traditional laws and customs that are still observed by them, the native title claim group has a connection with the application area; 
 
 j that, by the traditional laws and customs that are still observed by them, the native title claim group has rights and interests in the application area; 
 
 k the nature and extent of the extant rights and interests; and, 
 
 l that such rights and interests have not been extinguished, (or if extinguishment has occurred, it is to be disregarded); and are not "antithetical to the fundamental tenets of the common law".</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">
 
 

54 The Minister contends that it is not necessary for Worimi to prove or even adduce evidence touching all of the matters necessary to obtain a positive determination of native title, for example, evidence of all pre-sovereignty rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">He says that a respondent seeking to avoid a finding of no native title must at least present evidence of some such rights and interests which disclose that there is a native title claim group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">This may create a heavy burden for such a respondent but that is, he submits, inherent in the nature of the case to be made that native title exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">55 Worimi does not need to establish that native title exists on the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">It is for the Court to assess the totality of the evidence to determine whether the Land Council has established, on the balance of probabilities, that native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Worimi has identified a number of different groups, at various stages of these proceedings, that he says hold native title in the Land, including himself and his immediate family, and all Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">He must also provide evidence that addresses, at the least, the Land Council's evidence that there is no native title within the principles set down in Yorta Yorta ; that there is no normative body of laws and customs in connection with the Land, the observance of which has been substantially maintained from the time of sovereignty to the present day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">Worimi does not need to prove each element of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">He is not obliged to establish native title as if it were a positive defence being asserted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">He does, however, need to address native title under the Act by reference to those material matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">He must address the necessary elements sufficiently to cast doubt on the Land Council's assertion of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">He needs to show that there have existed traditional laws and customs in relation to the Land, the continued observance of those laws and customs and the maintenance of a connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">If he does not lead evidence as to each of those matters, elements of native title, he will need to adduce evidence, sufficient in scope and weight, as to one or more of those elements to cast doubt on the proposition that native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">56 Worimi contends that the evidence required to discharge the Land Council's onus of proof ' may not be achieved without strict proof of historical and anthropological facts through use of widely accepted authoritative writings and expert evidence ' and ' involves consideration of the historical, archaeological, linguistic and anthropological evidence in the light of the direct testimony of Aboriginal witnesses '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">Worimi says that, in determining the question of the existence or non-existence of native title on the balance of probabilities, regard should be had to the ability of the parties to adduce evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">By this, he seems to be saying that the Court should give more weight to his evidence and discount the evidence of the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">If he is, I do not accept it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">57 All of the evidence is to be weighed according to the proof which it was in the power of one side to produce and in the power of the other to have contradicted ( Apollo Shower Screens at 565).</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">Once the Land Council has established sufficient evidence from which the negative proposition, an absence of native title, may be inferred, Worimi carries an evidential burden to advance evidence of any particular matters going to the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">It is then for the Land Council to deal with the evidence in the discharge of its overall burden of proof ( Apollo Shower Screens at 565).</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">58 Worimi submits that the Land Council is in a position to call all of the customary expert evidence and has not done so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">The Land Council submits that Worimi is in the position to adduce evidence from other Worimi persons in support of his claim and has not done so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">Each party asserts that he or it is under no obligation to provide further evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">59 Worimi asserts that he and his immediate family may be the only Worimi people who were given native title rights and interests in the Land and, he adds, in the area from Birubi Beach to Boat Harbour, under traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">It follows that Worimi has the means of bringing forward evidence to establish the existence of the native title rights and interests he asserts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">It is not for the Court to conduct a roving enquiry as to whether anybody, and if so who, might hold native title over the Land ( Jango v Northern Territory (2007) 159 FCR 531 (' Jango ') at [84]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">In considering the evidence adduced by Worimi, it is relevant that he is the person who is able to adduce evidence of the laws and customs that he asserts he and his family practise and observe.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">On the other hand, he has insufficient resources to present the expert historical and anthropological evidence to substantiate his claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">60 The power of a party to adduce evidence may be relevant to the weight to be accorded to the evidence presented ( Apollo Shower Screens at 565; Blatch v Archer [1774] EngR 2 ; (1774) 1 Cowp 63 at 65; Ho v Powell (2001) 51 NSWLR 572 at [15]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">It may also be relevant to the standard of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">There is, however, a distinction between the probabilities on limited material available and whether limited material provides an appropriate basis on which to reach a reasonable decision ( Ho at [14]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">61 I accept that Worimi is not in a position to be able to adduce the historical and anthropological evidence to establish the existence of the Garuahgal clan of which he claims to be a member and the existence of traditional laws and customs over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">I do not, however, accept Worimi's submission that the Land Council is obliged to provide proof of historical and anthropological facts through the use of ' widely accepted authoritative writings and expert evidence ' in order to satisfy the burden of establishing the absence of native title on the balance of probabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">The Land Council is not required first to establish each of the elements of native title and then to rebut them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">The requirement to prove the negative does not equate to the requirement to prove the positive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">62 I am conscious of the absence of the kind of detailed expert evidence that is frequently adduced in determinations of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">I am also conscious of the consequences of a determination of the absence of native title and the Land Council's stated wish to sell Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">The Court must consider such evidence as has been adduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">The Land Council's evidence supports a case of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">Worimi has adduced evidence in support of his assertion of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">The possibility of native title over the Land can only be assessed on the available evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">I do not accept that the Land Council is obliged to prove that native title does not exist in the way advanced by Worimi, by establishing the nature and content of any native title rights and interests at the time of sovereignty and then "deconstructing" this through admissible evidence to show that any connection which Aboriginal people may have had with the Land no longer exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">The Land Council must establish, on the balance of probabilities, that native title under the Act does not exist over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">Is there a presumption that native title exists over the Land?</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">
 Worimi's submissions 
 
63 Worimi says that it follows from the fact that the burden of proof is on the Land Council that ' as a matter of common sense and logic there is a presumption to the effect that the Land is subject to native title rights and interests until the contrary is proven '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">Worimi says that there is a presumption, which the Land Council must negate, that there is native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">64 Based on the presumption that native title exists over the Land, Worimi contends that:
 
&#8226; It is common ground that Lot 576 falls within traditional Worimi country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">&#8226; The Land Council must prove that any connection which Aboriginal people may have had with the Land under traditional laws and customs has not been maintained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">&#8226; In order to succeed, the Land Council must establish that traditional law and custom has ceased to be observed anywhere in "Worimi country".</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">&#8226; It is incumbent upon the Land Council to adduce evidence from Worimi people positively to assert that no laws and customs have been passed down to them by their forebears and, additionally, there needs to be expert evidence that there were a set of normative rules traditionally adopted and followed and observed by the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">&#8226; Following Yorta Yorta , the Land Council must prove that pre-existing laws and customs have been substantially interrupted from what they were at sovereignty or no longer exist at all.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">&#8226; There must be evidence of the cessation of the acknowledgement of laws and observance of customs sufficient to show that those laws and customs have been abandoned by the whole of Worimi society.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">65 Worimi submits that the evidence supports the inference that there was a group of Worimi people and a society of Aboriginal people who inhabited the area around Port Stephens at the time of sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">For the purposes of this application, I accept that to be the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">66 Worimi submits that, once this is accepted, it follows that this group had some form of normative rules which regulated their society and that, once this is accepted, it follows ' as a matter of logic and reason ' that, bearing in mind the burden of proof, the Land Council is required to lead sufficient evidence:
 
(i) of the nature and existence of pre-sovereign native title rights and interests; and
 
(ii) to the effect that these pre-sovereign rights and interests are no longer observed before the Court may infer the non-existence of native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">67 It then follows, in Worimi's submission, that the Land Council must lead extensive expert evidence of the Aboriginal laws and customs before the Court is able to assess the evidence of the Land Council's contemporary Aboriginal witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">Consideration 
 
68 Worimi's submissions assume that a presumption of native title applies, that nothing short of evidence in respect of the whole area that could be associated with the Worimi people suffices and that the Land Council must prove an absence of native title by reference to each element necessary to prove the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">69 There is no presumption of the existence of native title under the Act, either for a claimant seeking a determination of the existence of native title or for a non-claimant seeking a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">70 The Land Council acknowledges that it bears the legal onus of proof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">However, it denies the existence of a presumption that native title exists either under the Act or at common law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">It contends that the evidentiary starting point as to whether native title does or does not exist is neutral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">71 As the Minister points out, Worimi seems to suggest that it is incumbent on the Land Council to demonstrate that no possible combination of known or unknown past or present actions, beliefs or patterns of behaviour could amount to the acknowledgment of laws or observance of customs capable of sustaining any possible rights or interests in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">The burden of proving the absence of native title does not rise so high and is not envisaged by provision in the Act for a determination that no native title exists in respect of certain land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">72 In Mason v Tritton (1994) 34 NSWLR 572, Kirby P pointed to the difficulty for Aboriginal people to provide recorded details of, for example, genealogy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">At 586---589, his Honour discussed the inferences that can be drawn to overcome the absence of evidence for the period from 1788 to a later time, in that case to the 1880s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">Referring to the analysis in Wigmore on Evidence, vol 2, 3 rd edition at 437, his Honour said that it is not appropriate to apply a "presumption of continuance" but a process of inference.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">His Honour was prepared to draw an inference from proved use of land in the 1880s back to the time before 1788.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">As he noted, it is more easily drawn in more traditional Aboriginal communities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">However, in Mason , there were other aspects of the claim to native title which were not proved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">Further, it is hard to see from Yorta Yorta how a presumption of native title can be said to apply.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">73 I do not accept Worimi's submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">They assume that, in order to establish that there is no native title, the Land Council must first prove the nature of the pre-sovereign native title rights and interests which are presumed to exist, assume that the relevant laws and customs have continued to be observed since sovereignty and then disprove the present existence of native title by reference to each of the elements necessary to establish it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">If it is necessary to prove each of a number of elements to establish native title and it can be shown that one of those elements is missing, that is sufficient to demonstrate that there is presently no native title over particular land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">74 Worimi points to Gale v Minister for Land &amp; Water Conservation for the State of New South Wales [2004] FCA 374 where it was accepted that at the time of sovereignty, the lands were inhabited by organised communities of Aboriginal people who had rights and interests in the subject lands, sourced in traditional laws and customs (at [34]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">The parties accepted the ' tenacious persistence of native title ' and of traditional Aboriginal culture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">Justice Madgwick took account of extensive expert reports of anthropologists and historians, as well as other evidence that had been filed, to conclude that there was no native title over the lands in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">That expert evidence was available in Gale .</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">The fact that no such evidence is available in these proceedings does not prevent a decision being reached as to whether the Land Council has satisfied the burden of establishing the absence of native title, on the basis of the evidence adduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">75 The Land Council is not required to overcome and negative a presumption that native title exists over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">The description of the Land as part of "traditional Worimi country" 
 
76 Worimi points to the description of all of the land around Port Stephens as "traditional Worimi country" or in similar terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">The Minister accepts that ' it is common ground that the Land falls within traditional Worimi country '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">However, the Minister does not agree that the use of such an expression or such informal identification of a region with a people, the Worimi nation, entails acceptance that there is and has at all times since 1788 been a native title holding group that is part of a society which has all the attributes that are necessary to sustain native title rights and interests in the Land under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">77 Lot 576 is part of the land held by the Land Council in fee simple by reason of the transfer of the land under the NSW Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">It, together with the surrounding land, including Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach, have been described by the witnesses as "traditional Worimi country".</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">78 The use of the expression "traditional Worimi country" with respect to the Land does not create a presumption, without more, of the existence of native title for the purposes of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">Traditional land, or land that is regarded as traditional land and associated with a particular identified group, may or may not be subject to native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">There are requirements associated with the concept of native title under the Act that go beyond identification of land as "traditional land" or as land associated with the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">79 The description of the Land as part of "traditional Worimi country" does not establish a presumption of native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">THE NSW ACT 
 
80 It is apparent from the Second Reading Speech for the NSW Act that s 36(9) and s 40AA were intended to ' compensate Aboriginal people for dispossession from their traditional lands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">If that traditional connection has been maintained in a way which would sustain a claim for native title, then it is that claim which should have precedence '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">81 The transfer of land to the Land Council was not a recognition that there had been a traditional connection with that land sufficient to constitute native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">The relevant sections were introduced into the NSW Act to ensure that grants made under the NSW Act would not extinguish native title and would not be inconsistent either with the Racial Discrimination Act 1975 (Cth) or the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">82 Land may not be transferred by the Land Council until a determination is made as to the existence or absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">If native title is shown to exist, the rights of traditional owners take precedence over the right of the Land Council to sell the land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">83 Worimi maintains that the inquiry for the purposes of these proceedings is not limited to the existence of native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">He contends that the inquiry extends to a determination of whether or not traditional laws and customs continue to be acknowledged and observed not only over Lot 576 but also over the surrounding country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">He relies on the proviso in s 36(9) of the NSW Act, which relevantly provides:
 
 
 ... any transfer of lands to an Aboriginal Land Council under this section shall be for an estate in fee simple but shall be subject to any native title rights and interests existing in relation to the lands immediately before the transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">
 
 
84 Worimi's submission, in summary, is as follows:
 
&#8226; "In relation to" is a phrase of wide import, satisfied by a connection or association between the two things ( Law Society of New South Wales v Bruce (1996) 40 NSWLR 77).</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">&#8226; Native title rights and interests under the Act cannot be divorced from the territory claimed to constitute the traditional country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">&#8226; As the Land falls within traditional Worimi country, the consideration of whether or not there is native title over Lot 576 requires a consideration of native title rights and interests over the whole of traditional Worimi country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">85 There is no dispute that the Act, having as one of the main objects to provide for the recognition and protection of native title, is remedial in nature and to be construed beneficially.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">86 Section 36(9) equates the lands the subject of the transfer to the relevant Aboriginal Land Council with the lands the subject of native title rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">The word "lands" has the same meaning in each use in subsection (9).</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">The subsection recognises that native title rights and interests may not amount to a right or interest "in" the subject land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">The acknowledgment or observation of a law or custom does not necessarily amount to a right or interest "in" the land itself but may give rise to a native title right or interest "in relation to" the land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">This is recognised in, for example, ss 211(1) and (3) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">87 Section 36(9) of the NSW Act addresses native title rights and interests over land that has been transferred to an Aboriginal Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">In the present case, the Land Council only wants to sell a part of that land, namely, Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">It wishes to establish that there are no native title rights and interests over the land it wishes to sell.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">The existence of native title over other land held by the Land Council may or may not be relevant but it is not determinative of native title over or in relation to Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">There is no obligation arising from the wording of s 36(9) of the NSW Act to inquire into the existence of native title over all Worimi traditional land or over all of the land held by the Land Council for the purposes of these proceedings, which only concern Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">CONCLUSION ON PRELIMINARY MATTERS 
 
88 In relation to the non-claimant application for a determination that no native title exists over the Land, the following seems to me to apply:
 
&#8226; The Act permits the making of non-claimant applications for determinations that no native title exists over land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">&#8226; This allows people with interests in land to ascertain whether native title exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">The Act envisages that determinations of the absence of native title may be made and provides a statutory guarantee of validity to future acts (s 24FA).</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">Section 61(1) provides for non-claimant applications for native title determinations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">There is no indication in the Act that there is a presumption that native title exists that must be displaced by an applicant seeking a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">&#8226; The Minister has not abandoned his right to participate in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">The Minister has an interest in these proceedings, namely, to ensure that if the Court is not satisfied that there is no native title over the Land, that the Court does not make findings in relation to matters which would need to be addressed in making a positive determination of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">The Minister also has an interest in knowing whether or not, and in what way, the Crown's radical title is burdened by native title rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">In any event, the Act does not require the Minister to establish an interest in order to be party to these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">&#8226; These proceedings do not enable Worimi to obtain a declaration that native title exists.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">In order to establish that native title exists, it is necessary to make an application under the Act and to comply with the Act and the requirements for the establishment of native title ( Kokatha ; Clifton ; Worimi 2007 ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">&#8226; An applicant for a determination of the absence of native title has an onus to establish that there is no native title over the land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">That onus applies to a civil standard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">The applicant must demonstrate on the balance of probabilities that native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">&#8226; There is no indication in the NSW Act or the Act to indicate that the standard to be applied is other than the ordinary civil standard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">&#8226; A respondent to the application may adduce evidence to cast doubt on the applicant's case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">As I said in Worimi 2007 at [35], Worimi would need to advance a case that establishes that native title does exist or to cast doubt on the Land Council's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">Worimi's assertion of his native title rights and interests may lead to a more informed decision in the non-claimant application ( Worimi 2007 at [30]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">&#8226; The decision is based upon the whole of the evidence before the Court including evidence adduced by Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">&#8226; The evidence adduced by Worimi should be assessed to determine whether it is sufficient to cast doubt on the Land Council's case such that the Land Council does not satisfy the Court that, on the balance of probabilities, no native title exists over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">&#8226; Accordingly, the onus is not on the Land Council to satisfy the Court as to the absence of each element required to prove the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">The Land Council is not required positively to establish the situation pre-sovereignty and from sovereignty to the present time with expert evidence of laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">It is contrary to logic to say that a person who wishes to establish that there is no native title must first positively prove that there were laws and customs at any stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">&#8226; Worimi is the person who asserts the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">That necessarily means native title under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">The evidence must address the elements of such a claim, in particular the laws and customs and rights and interests from pre-sovereignty or the time of sovereignty to the present.</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">It is not necessary to prove each element of native title but the evidence should be sufficiently cogent with respect to those elements it does address to cast doubt on the assertion that native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">If the evidence establishes the absence of a necessary element of native title, such as continuous connection with the Land, this would provide support for a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">&#8226; The Land Council may call evidence as to the existence or non-existence of laws and customs at each of those stages and as to the existence of a class or persons claiming the communal, group or individual rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">The Land Council may establish that only one necessary element is missing, such as continuous connection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">That would be sufficient to establish an absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">&#8226; The subject matter of this application is the land constituted by a single lot, Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">Worimi contends that it is impossible to deal with Lot 576 without also considering the surrounding land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">The Land Council has no obligation to demonstrate an absence of native title throughout the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">The evidence needs to concern the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">However, evidence that relates to an area that goes beyond a recently subdivided lot is likely to be relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">The question remains, however, whether there are native title rights and interests over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">&#8226; It is not in dispute that all formal requirements for a non-claimant application for a determination of the absence of native title have been met.</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">In the absence of any evidence as to the existence of native title over the Land, the Land Council would be entitled to the determination it seeks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">Both the Land Council and Worimi have adduced evidence addressing the existence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">It is necessary to consider the whole of that evidence to ascertain whether the Land Council has established, on the balance of probabilities, that there is no native title or whether sufficient doubt has been cast on the Land Council's case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">THE EVIDENCE 
 
89 Apart from the formal matters, the Land Council filed a number of affidavits of people who asserted that they were of the Worimi tribe or nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">This evidence addressed matters raised in Worimi's various affidavits filed in support of his native title claimant applications and in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">In order better to understand the Land Council's evidence, I will first consider Worimi's evidence as filed in his first affidavit for this hearing and as clarified in cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">Worimi's affidavit of 18 December 2007 
 
90 In his affidavit affirmed after his joinder as a respondent in these proceedings (the 18 December 2007 affidavit), Worimi sets out a number of matters to which objection is taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">Many of those matters are in the form of assertion, including assertions as to matters not within Worimi's knowledge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">Worimi's evidence is, by its nature, personal and historical and referable to his father and father's mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">I accept that those matters are stated as to his own belief of the facts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">The matters dealt with in the 18 December 2007 affidavit are as follows:
 
&#8226; He is a Worimi man and he says he was given the responsibility for the custodianship of the Land and for the whole of the Garuahgal area which he describes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">Worimi grew up in Raymond Terrace ' which is part of Worimi Country '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">His father was Leonard Dates, son of Ellen Dates (nee Russell) and Freddie Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">Ellen and Freddie Dates lived at Raymond Terrace.</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">He says that Freddie Dates was the son of Mary Mahr and that Mary Mahr was born on the Burral River.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">&#8226; Worimi grew up in Raymond Terrace and attended school there until about the age of 13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">He was raised by Ellen Dates in Raymond Terrance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">When he was young his family and friends used to gather in a clearing behind the Raymond Terrace house which he says was ' our ceremonial ground ', where the family would eat oysters and pippis and the initiated elders would dance and sing and tell stories.</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">The elders included Worimi's father, his father's brother, Arnold, and others from the Karuah Mission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">&#8226; Worimi currently resides within the area that he describes as the Garuahgal area and has been there all of his life except for approximately three years when he was in Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">&#8226; He has always considered the Garuahgal area to be his and his family's country and he has camped all over that country, including on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">&#8226; In about 1977 he and his family lived on the land between Stockton and Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">They lived a traditional lifestyle in that they camped and obtained food in the ways he had been taught by his father, his father's brothers and Ellen Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">After a conversation with police officers they stopped living there but continued to camp in the area whenever they could in the same manner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">&#8226; Ellen Dates told him that the area between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour was a special place for Garuahgal women, as the women used the strip of beach and the freshwater spring that runs along the Land to wash their babies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">His father showed him the rocks that form the boundaries of the area that was special to women and told him to avoid the area and not to go beyond the rock boundaries.</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">&#8226; Worimi accepts that as a Worimi man he is not allowed to know ' most of the Worimi law and custom regarding the womans' site '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">He is entitled to know some things about the site, including its location, so he can ensure that it is protected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">He was told of those matters by Ellen Dates and by his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">&#8226; Ellen Dates told him about the women's site when he was a young boy so that he knew it was an important place and a place that he should avoid because he is a man.</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">&#8226; He explains what happened at that site but does not say from whom he obtained that information, nor how he knew of the detail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">He says that he knew the following: 
 
 
 Pregnant Worimi women, including women from the Guruahgal clan, used to travel to the Land from the surrounding area to have their babies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">
 
 After they had their babies, the women take the babies down to the place where the sea meets the sand on an area of Kingsley Beach near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">The Worimi word for the place where the sea meets the sand is ' Poona '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">On this part of the Poona , the women bathe the babies in the sea water and give them their tribal totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">
 
 

&#8226; Worimi says that he continues to obey the prohibition on men going to the Poona but has encouraged his daughters to go there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">&#8226; The women's site at the Poona was not on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">That is, it was not on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">Worimi says that there was a billabong (also described by Worimi as a waterhole or freshwater stream) on or near Lot 576 and that there was no restriction on men going to the billabong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">He also says that men were allowed to go and camp on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">He has visited and camped on Lot 576 many times since the age of 13 and continued to do so, that is, to camp on and visit the Land on a regular basis and to take his children to the Land, until about two years ago.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">They caught and ate fish and shellfish at the beach and from the rocks near the Land and Worimi says that he always believed that he had the right to do these things on the Land because it was part of ' my Guruahgal country '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">&#8226; He has also taken wood and other natural materials from the Land for sculptures and other artworks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">Worimi says that when his daughter, Beryl Dates, had a son in December 2006, his wife and daughter took the baby to the Poona and flushed the afterbirth in the sea and then wiped the afterbirth on the baby's head and gave him his tribal totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">The afterbirth was then wrapped in bark and the two women buried the afterbirth on the Land after Worimi's wife, Cynthia, placed sand in the hole it was buried in.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">Worimi says that his daughter is now the keeper of the site and he is not allowed to know where she buried the afterbirth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">&#8226; Worimi says that he is the custodian of the Land which means that he is required to undertake cultural and heritage protection activities in relation to the Land and to care for and conserve the natural resources of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">91 Worimi says:
 
 
 I now believe that me and my family may be the only Worimi people who were given the native title rights and interests in the Land, and the area from Birubi Beach to Boat Harbour, under traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">
 
 

92 Worimi also described ' the traditional laws and customs of my Worimi family group '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">He says that his knowledge of those laws and customs was taught to him by his father, Leonard, his father's mother, Ellen Dates, his father's brother, Arnold, and other elders on the Karuah Reserve including Big Bill Ridgeway who, he said, taught all the young kids at Karuah Reserve.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">Worimi says that his father had responsibility for protecting culturally significant places, including the Land, the coastal areas nearby and the women's sites.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">As the eldest male in his family, he was a custodian and a keeper of customary law for Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">Worimi's father shared that responsibility with other Worimi men who were responsible for other families and other areas in Worimi country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">He says that, in relation to the Land and the surrounding area, his father's mother, Ellen Dates, had an overlapping role as custodian/protector of the women's business at that place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">Worimi says that on his father's death, as the eldest son, the position of custodian passed to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">93 Worimi describes what he says are other significant sites in ' my country ' including mountains and the ' Guardian Tree ' on Bulahdelah Mountain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">He describes the way in which the Guardian Tree is the guardian of all men and women in the Worimi area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">94 Worimi also describes the giving of totems.</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">He says that Worimi tribal totems are animals with whom the child will grow to have a particular affinity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">His tribal totem is the river goanna which was given to him as a boy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">Worimi people are, he says, all spirits of their totem but take on human form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">He learnt this from his father and his father's mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">95 Worimi describes marriage law under Worimi law and says that when a woman marries into another tribe or clan she takes the law and custom of her husband's country and that marriage gives a connection to land under Worimi law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">His present wife, Cynthia, was born in the Dunghutti area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">96 Worimi describes Worimi death and burial law, including the law that a Worimi person must try to come home to the territory of his or her particular clan to die and be buried and that burial should be near the mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">He also says that the dead were placed in the forks of trees and then wrapped in bark and placed in a hollow log.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">He says he has taught these laws to his children.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">97 Worimi says that both his father and Uncle Arnold were initiated and that his father taught him words and sentences in the Worimi language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">He says that he used to speak a lot of Worimi language with his father and his father's brothers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">Worimi is trying to pass the language on to his children.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">Worimi also records being taught to burn patches of bush in the country and to hunt, gather and fish.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">He describes in some detail what he used to catch and eat.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">He says that he was taught these methods by his father and his father's brother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">98 Worimi says that his father and his father's brother taught him that the Hunter River was created by a rainbow serpent whose belly now forms Kooragang Island.</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">99 Worimi says that he took his children to the Land, including his daughter Priscilla Dates when she was small.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">He says that he took Priscilla to Boat Harbour and to Kingsley Beach, that he told his children the stories of the Dreamtime and the creation of the land and that Kingsley Beach was where baptisms took place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">He says that he told them about the totems.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">100 Worimi says that his grandmother told him that women would wash the afterbirth in the sea and give a sea totem to the baby.</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">The afterbirth would be wrapped and the woman would pick out a place which would then become special to that woman.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">She also told him that the waterhole (the billabong on or near the Land) was important as a way to purify and wash the saltwater off the babies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">He said he was told this by his father's mother when he was about 10 years old.</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">The Land Council's evidence 
 
101 It is convenient to deal next with the Land Council's evidence, which responded in part to Worimi's 18 December 2007 affidavit, and then deal further with Worimi's evidence in cross-examination, which followed the Land Council's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">102 The Land Council relies on evidence from indigenous people to the effect that the Land is not considered to be subject to native title rights and interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">The Land Council witnesses gave evidence of the observation of traditional law and custom over Worimi land, the fact that many of the families had lived on Karuah Mission and that their way of living did not encompass traditional use of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">They cannot say that there is no native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">They can, however, speak of their own knowledge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">Worimi submits that an inference should be drawn from the failure to call more of the 300 members of the Land Council ( Jones v Dunkel (1959) 101 CLR 298).</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">This ignores the fact that the Land Council duly resolved to dispose of the Land in accordance with s 40D of the NSW Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">The Land Council has established that 83% of the voting members present at a properly constituted extraordinary meeting on 11 October 2004 voted in favour of selling Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">103 The Land Council's witnesses referred to Worimi as Gary and I shall do so in the summary of their evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">Valerie Rose Merrick 
 
104 Valerie Rose Merrick says that she is an Aboriginal elder and traditional owner from the Worimi tribe.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">Ms Merrick was born in Karuah at the Mission and has lived the whole of her life in the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">She has been involved in the Worimi community for her whole life and with the Land Council since it was established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">Ms Merrick is related to Worimi in that his grandmother, Ellen Dates (nee Russell) was her great-aunt, being her grandfather's sister on her mother's side.</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">105 Ms Merrick is a traditional owner in the sense that she is referred to as one of the persons listed on the Register under the NSW Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">106 Ms Merrick's evidence answering and disputing a number of Worimi's assertions is of her own knowledge and her belief, based upon information received from others:
 
&#8226; Ms Merrick's mother, Drusilla, was a Worimi person and her father's mother was either Worimi or Biripi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">&#8226; Ellen Dates (Worimi's father's mother) and her husband were very religious Christian people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">&#8226; Ms Merrick has never heard any stories to say that Ellen Dates was recognised as a traditional custodian or protector of Boat Harbour or of any other land in the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s430">&#8226; From stories that she was told, Ellen Dates dived for lobsters in the area near Shoal Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s431">She heard no stories connecting Ellen Dates with Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s432">&#8226; Ms Merrick has not had any stories passed down to her to say that land at Boat Harbour was a sacred women's place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s433">She denies that it was a special, sacred place for women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s434">&#8226; When she was young she would go to Boat Harbour with her mother and father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s435">She was never told that there was a place either there or near there where men were not allowed to go.</sentence>
<sentence id="s436">&#8226; Ms Merrick is aware of a sacred site for Worimi women in the Port Stephens area, around Salamander Bay, but says there is no place near Boat Harbour or between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour that is sacred to women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s437">If there were such a place, men and children would not be permitted to go there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s438">&#8226; A person does not become a traditional elder because he is the eldest son.</sentence>
<sentence id="s439">&#8226; It is contrary to law and custom, as Ms Merrick knows it, to enable Leonard Dates, Gary's father, to give him Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s440">All of the people are traditional owners and it is not for one person to give away land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s441">&#8226; Ms Merrick is not aware of members of the Worimi community using Boat Harbour for camping or any other traditional Aboriginal purposes other than fishing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s442">She herself has not observed Worimi living in Boat Harbour or in the Port Stephens area in the traditional Aboriginal way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s443">&#8226; Ms Merrick was a member of a claim group with respect to a claimant application over Bagnalls Beach filed in 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s444">Ms Merrick said that she was authorised on behalf of the claim group in relation to their native title rights and interests as Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s445">Forster is, she says, part of Worimi country down to Stockton and all the land was marked out by rivers and mountains and the coastline of the bays.</sentence>
<sentence id="s446">&#8226; Ms Merrick believes that she and her family have native title rights and interests over Bagnalls Beach, which is about 3 to 4 kilometres from Nelson Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s447">She says that they had a connection with most of the land around that area and that she is a custodian and a traditional owner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s448">&#8226; Ms Merrick accepted that Lot 576 is ' within Worimi Country '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s449">&#8226; Ms Merrick acknowledges that the Land Council wishes to sell the Land to pay its debts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s450">She accepts that the Land should be sold in order for the Land Council to be able to provide housing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s451">Viola Louise Brown 
 
107 Viola Louise Brown is an Aboriginal knowledge holder of the Maaiangal clan of the Worimi nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s452">A knowledge holder or elder is a person who knows about the land, plants and animals, the ceremonies of their clan and where the women's sites and men's sites are.</sentence>
<sentence id="s453">&#8226; Ms Brown was born near Port Stephens.</sentence>
<sentence id="s454">&#8226; She is also a registered Aboriginal owner under the NSW Act and was a native title claimant for Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s455">&#8226; Ms Brown was brought up as an Aboriginal and recognises the laws and the need to keep them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s456">She says that Worimi people wandered all over the lands.</sentence>
<sentence id="s457">She has written a book on Worimi laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s458">She lives by the laws herself in the same way as her forebears lived.</sentence>
<sentence id="s459">&#8226; Ms Brown has pursued an interest in the genealogy of the Worimi people and Aboriginal cultural mapping for approximately 20 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s460">She has been involved in projects to protect Worimi customs, flora and fauna and to raise awareness of the Worimi way of life in the community.</sentence>
<sentence id="s461">&#8226; Ms Brown supports the Land Council's application for an order that there is no native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s462">&#8226; The Worimi tribe or nation is made up of a number of clans or "nguras", including the Maaiangal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s463">The territory of the Maaiangal clan includes Lot 576 and there cannot be two clans in the one area of land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s464">A clan is made up of generations of one family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s465">&#8226; Ms Brown denies that the Land is Garuahgal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s466">&#8226; Ms Brown has always lived in the Port Stephens area except for about 12 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s467">Her family has always lived in the Port Stephens area, particular at Soldiers Point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s468">&#8226; Ms Brown's father, George Ridgeway, was part of the Maaiangal clan and her mother was of the Yorta Yorta people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s469">Ms Brown's father's father was James Ridgeway.</sentence>
<sentence id="s470">&#8226; Ms Brown knew of Gary's father, Leonard Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s471">She says that he was not recognised as an elder within the Worimi nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s472">He was not of the Maaiangal clan and, she says, neither is Gary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s473">Ms Brown also knew of Gary's mother who was from the Yorta Yorta people and Gary's grandmother, Ellen Dates, who was her mother's father's sister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s474">To her memory, Ellen Dates lived in Karuah, not at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s475">&#8226; She asserts that a lot of the information in Gary's application of 9 February 2006 and his affidavits of 20 January 2006 and 18 December 2007 is untrue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s476">&#8226; As to Gary's claim that he is representing the Garuahgal clan of the Worimi nation, Ms Brown says that there is no Worimi clan called Garuahgal and she does not know where that information came from.</sentence>
<sentence id="s477">The only clan that Ms Brown knows of by that name is near Glenbrook, which is not part of Worimi territory and it is spelt Garaugal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s478">&#8226; Ms Brown says that the Worimi women's waterhole which was a birthing site was at Salamander Bay and not at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s479">She points out that a stream of water, as described as existing on Lot 576, would not be deep enough to immerse oneself in, which is what a woman did when she wanted a baby; she immersed herself in the waterhole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s480">If possible, the woman would return to the same waterhole when she had her child, to clean the child in the waterhole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s481">She also says that the area at Boat Harbour is not suitable for a birthing site because there is no protection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s482">&#8226; Ms Brown repeated in cross-examination that, so far as she knew, there was no waterhole or women's site at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s483">She rejected the suggestion that, if a billabong had been present at Boat Harbour, it might have been a women's birthing site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s484">She says that neither she nor anyone she has talked to had ever heard of it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s485">She emphasised the need for there to be deep water for the birthing site, which would not exist where Gary's suggested billabong was.</sentence>
<sentence id="s486">However, she did accept that Worimi people lived all over the Maaiangal land and that some may not have been able to get to Salamander Bay to give birth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s487">&#8226; Ms Brown was told many things as she was growing up but she was never told of a women's site at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s488">She believes she would have been told about it had it existed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s489">She says that, having gone near the Land, she did not get any sense of it being a sacred women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s490">Further, if it was a women's site then Gary could not go onto the Land himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s491">In the past he would have been killed for going onto a sacred women's site, because men just did not go on to a women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s492">&#8226; Ms Brown considers it unlikely that Gary would have had all the knowledge passed on to him by the time he was about 12 years old when his grandmother passed on.</sentence>
<sentence id="s493">Usually knowledge is passed on gradually as one gets older and more respected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s494">It is usually passed on after the person has been initiated, which occurs when a person reaches puberty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s495">&#8226; Ms Brown says that land does not pass to a particular person as a custodian; it belongs to the community and therefore there are a number of custodians and knowledge holders of the land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s496">&#8226; Ms Brown remembers going with her family, including men, to the area around the Land and Fisherman's Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s497">&#8226; Ms Brown disputes a number of specific matters in Gary's affidavit including his reference to "billabong" which is not, she says, a term used by Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s498">She also disputes his claim that a number of specific sites (not on the Land) are sacred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s499">She rejects his claim that there were other specific sacred sites in the area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s500">In particular, she says there was no special "Guardian Tree", nor a rock formation which is a goanna on top of a mountain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s501">&#8226; She also disputes Gary's description of the position of a totem for Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s502">She says that Worimi people are not spirits of their totem which have taken on a human form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s503">She says that when you are born, you get a personal totem from something that is nearby at the time that you were born and also a tribal totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s504">The totem for Worimi is lightning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s505">There is also a clan totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s506">The Maaiangal totem is the shark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s507">There is also a women's totem, a white-throated tree creeper, and a men's totem, the little bat.</sentence>
<sentence id="s508">&#8226; Ms Brown also says that it is not true that when a woman marries into another clan she takes the law and custom of her husband's clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s509">A woman keeps her own clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s510">Ms Brown also disputes a number of Gary's specific claims of customs including methods of hunting and fishing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s511">She says that Gary's descriptions are simply not true.</sentence>
<sentence id="s512">She also disputes some of the stories that Gary said applied as beliefs of the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s513">&#8226; Ms Brown went to the Land with other Worimi women after Gary said that his wife and daughter had buried the afterbirth of his daughter's child.</sentence>
<sentence id="s514">They could find no indication that the afterbirth had been buried on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s515">&#8226; Ms Brown accepts that oystering was a traditional pursuit of Worimi people and had been pre-sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s516">Her father, grandfather and great grandfather were all fisherman.</sentence>
<sentence id="s517">They built boats from tea tree.</sentence>
<sentence id="s518">She has passed information on bush foods to her children because it is part of Worimi culture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s519">&#8226; Ms Brown had been part of a claim group over Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s520">She still believes that native title exists in that area but says it was just on the Stockton Bight area and does not take in Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s521">The claim over Stockton Bight did not extend to Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s522">Stockton Bight is, she says, part of the land of the Maaiangal clan, who owned it before the white people came.</sentence>
<sentence id="s523">It was important because burials and ceremonies were held there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s524">&#8226; Ms Brown emphasises that Gary is not a Maaiangal person and that Boat Harbour is Maaiangal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s525">Gwen Joyce Russell 
 
&#8226; Ms Russell is an Aboriginal elder from the Worimi tribe who learnt about the traditions and stories that are part of her culture from her great aunt, Loui Ridgeway.</sentence>
<sentence id="s526">Loui Ridgeway would speak about different parts of the culture and what they used to do but never mentioned going to Boat Harbour or about it being a sacred place for women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s527">Ms Russell also learnt about Worimi culture from her husband's mother and father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s528">Her husband's father, Archie Russell, was a brother of Ellen Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s529">&#8226; Ms Russell says that only women would talk about women's sites.</sentence>
<sentence id="s530">Men would know where women's sites were but they wouldn't know what happened there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s531">&#8226; Ms Russell used to go to Boat Harbour with her own family and other families.</sentence>
<sentence id="s532">&#8226; Ms Russell, like the other witnesses from the Worimi people called by the Land Council, refers to Worimi as Gary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s533">She says that he started calling himself Worimi but that others of the Worimi people do not call him Worimi, but Gary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s534">&#8226; Ms Russell has never heard of Gary or anyone else living at Boat Harbour in a traditional Aboriginal way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s535">To her knowledge, Gary's father, Leonard Dates, did not use the Land for camping and Gary's grandmother, Ellen Dates, did not swim off any rocks on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s536">Ms Russell is not aware of anyone using the Land for camping or any other traditional Aboriginal purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s537">&#8226; She says that Gary made his native title applications without talking to her about it as a female elder of the Worimi tribe.</sentence>
<sentence id="s538">He did not ask her whether she would support his native title application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s539">&#8226; Ms Russell has no knowledge of the connection that Gary says that he and his family have with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s540">She says that she would have known about it if he and his family had been visiting the Land over the years, because of the connections with their two families.</sentence>
<sentence id="s541">She has no such knowledge or recollection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s542">&#8226; Ms Russell was one of the women who went to the Land after hearing that Gary had buried the afterbirth of his grandson on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s543">She could not see any sign of the ground being freshly dug up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s544">&#8226; Ms Russell also disputes Gary's description of other nearby areas, such as Kooragang Island, being a sacred site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s545">As far as she knows it was ' a bit of an island and then was built up from rubbish dumped from ships, years ago '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s546">She also disputes Gary's description of the Hunter River being made by a rainbow serpent and his description of the methods of getting pippis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s547">&#8226; Ms Russell disputes that it is Worimi law that you should be buried near your mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s548">She had never heard of the Guardian Tree or the rock formations described by Gary on Bulahdelah Mountain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s549">&#8226; Ms Russell joined the claim over Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s550">She believes that that land was not just Maaiangal land but was Worimi land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s551">Carol Dawn Ridgeway-Bissett 
 
&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett is an elder of the Maaiangal clan of the Worimi nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s552">Her family is of the Maaiangal clan of the Worimi tribe or nation and she confirms that the Maaiangal land includes Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s553">&#8226; She has lived in the Port Stephens and Newcastle area for her whole life and has been involved with Worimi Aboriginal community in a number of projects to protect customs, flora and fauna and to raise awareness of Worimi life.</sentence>
<sentence id="s554">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett was born at Soldiers Point and her family has always lived in the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s555">She says that the only Aboriginal families that lived on the Soldiers Point peninsula were related to her family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s556">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett was an Associate Lecturer in Aboriginal Studies at the University of Newcastle for a number of years and has been involved, as has her sister Ms Brown, in a number of consulting organisations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s557">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett did not vote for the sale of the Boat Harbour land because ' it is our traditional land '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s558">She says that it is important to her family and it is important to the rest of the Aboriginal community ' in that it is Aboriginal owned land '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s559">She does say, however, that Gary's native title application ' was nonsense and should not have been made '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s560">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that she conducts welcomes to country and has done so for some years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s561">Such welcomes were commenced in the late 1990s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s562">The only other ceremonies conducted on Worimi land by her family were initiations by her grandfather up to 1922.</sentence>
<sentence id="s563">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that there is no Worimi clan called Garuahgal and that the Land is not Garuahgal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s564">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett disputes Gary's claim to be part of the Worimi tribe.</sentence>
<sentence id="s565">She says that he claims to be a descendant of Mary Mahr.</sentence>
<sentence id="s566">According to Gary, Mary Mahr was born at "Burral River".</sentence>
<sentence id="s567">Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that if this refers to Burrell Creek, that area is part of the Biripi nation's territory, so that Mary Mahr would have been part of the Biripi nation and not the Worimi nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s568">Worimi's mother is of the Yorta Yorta nation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s569">&#8226; Some of the intricacies of identity are apparent from Ms Ridgeway-Bissett's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s570">She says that, in the Worimi nation, you are Worimi through the male line.</sentence>
<sentence id="s571">On that basis, Ms Russell is not Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s572">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says there were no clans other than Maaiangal at Soldiers Point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s573">The Ridgeways are Maaiangal clan and the Land is part of Maaiangal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s574">&#8226; Further, Ellen Dates, Gary's grandmother, is not, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says, of the Maaiangal clan and could not have been made a custodian and protector of Boat Harbour, as the land around Boat Harbour is land of the Maaiangal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s575">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says she was told many things about what happened in the area and believes that she would have been told if there was a women's site there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s576">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that Boat Harbour is not a sacred place for women or a waterhole for giving birth and the land between Biripi Beach and Boat Harbour is not a sacred women's place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s577">She confirms that, under traditional law and custom, men are not allowed to know about women's sites and were not told any details about what women did on the sites.</sentence>
<sentence id="s578">She says that Gary could not be a protector of a women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s579">&#8226; The sacred site for Worimi women in the Port Stephen's area is at Salamander Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s580">The site at Salamander Bay is sheltered, in contrast to the alleged women's site at Boat Harbour, which is rocky and exposed and not near any of the camping areas.</sentence>
<sentence id="s581">&#8226; Having examined the area around the Land, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett could not find anything to show that it was a sacred women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s582">Prior to that visit she had not specifically gone to the land at Boat Harbour although she used to visit there as a child, but to her it was just part of the bush.</sentence>
<sentence id="s583">She says that, had it been a sacred site, she would have been told not to go there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s584">She says that the land at Boat Harbour isn't sheltered enough for camping.</sentence>
<sentence id="s585">It was a community area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s586">&#8226; As to Gary's affidavit of 18 December 2007, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that "billabong" is a Northern Territory word.</sentence>
<sentence id="s587">She denies that there is a billabong (the Worimi word is "namby") on or joining or next to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s588">She also says that babies were not bathed in sea water after they were born.</sentence>
<sentence id="s589">&#8226; She disputes the "Guardian Tree" and says that there is no such thing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s590">She supports Ms Brown's description of the link between an Aboriginal person and a totem and does not agree that it is Worimi law that you must come home to be buried in your clan territory or near your mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s591">She says that Worimi people did not adopt the burial practice of placing bodies in trees and says that it is not part of Worimi law to visit graves.</sentence>
<sentence id="s592">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett disputes that the Hunter River was made by a rainbow serpent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s593">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett says that there is an island called Ash Island upon which there are some middens but confirms that Kooragang Island is made up of a number of different islands and was built up from ballast, dredging and other waste to form one big island in the 1960s and 1970s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s594">She also disputes Gary's description of traditional methods of hunting and fishing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s595">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett was part of the group that inspected the Land after they heard that Gary's grandson's afterbirth was buried there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s596">She says that she could not find anything to suggest that afterbirth had been buried on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s597">&#8226; She confirms a native title claim over Stockton Bight land which was part of a land created at the time of the Dreaming and contains many sites used for camping and burying.</sentence>
<sentence id="s598">Ms Ridgeway-Bissett believes that there is a duty to protect and preserve all the Maaiangal land for future generations including the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s599">She believes that it should be held in trust for the Aboriginal peoples.</sentence>
<sentence id="s600">&#8226; Ms Ridgeway-Bissett was also part of the claim group for Bagnalls Beach which, she says, was also a part of her family's traditional country and used for fishing and gathering plants for food and medicine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s601">She believes that there are native title rights and interests over Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s602">The claim of the area of Stockton Bight did not include the area around Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s603">A claim has not been made over Boat Harbour and Ms Ridgeway-Bissett does not propose to make one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s604">Noel John Ridgeway 
 
&#8226; Noel John Ridgeway is an elder of the Worimi tribe.</sentence>
<sentence id="s605">He grew up in the Karuah Mission and his father was Big Bill Ridgeway.</sentence>
<sentence id="s606">&#8226; Mr Ridgeway says that Gary should not be called Worimi and no-one calls him that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s607">He remembers Gary from the Karuah Reserve or Mission when he was young.</sentence>
<sentence id="s608">He also remembers Gary's parents and Leonard Dates' parents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s609">At the Karuah Mission everyone was a churchgoer and no-one learnt the Aboriginal language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s610">English was spoken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s611">&#8226; Mr Ridgeway says that he can remember Gary coming to visit the Karuah Mission when he was about 7 or 8 years old.</sentence>
<sentence id="s612">He cannot recall going to visit the Dates family after they left the Mission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s613">&#8226; Mr Ridgeway has been to the Land but does not remember going there as a child.</sentence>
<sentence id="s614">He does not think that the Land has any particular significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s615">&#8226; Mr Ridgeway disputes Gary's assertion that Big Bill Ridgeway told Gary about Aboriginal ways.</sentence>
<sentence id="s616">He says that his parents did talk about old times but did not talk about tribal ways ' because we more or less lived in a white society '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s617">&#8226; Mr Ridgeway says that he wasn't taught about women's sites and men's sites in the early days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s618">He only learnt about that after the Land Council was formed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s619">&#8226; When asked whether the Land was inside Worimi country, Mr Ridgeway said that it was given to the Worimi people by the government and inside the boundary of the land so transferred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s620">Jaye Ellen Quinlan 
 
&#8226; Jaye Ellen Quinlan is Gary Dates' sister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s621">She says that she does not know why Gary says that he has a claim on the Land and that she does not believe that to be the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s622">&#8226; Ms Quinlan's memory is that her father Leonard Dates never spoke an Aboriginal language and did not do anything to show his Aboriginal culture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s623">&#8226; Ms Quinlan lived with Ellen Dates for a number of years when she was young and Ellen Dates was in her 80s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s624">She says that Ellen Dates did not speak an Aboriginal language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s625">Ellen Dates died when Ms Quinlan was about 11 years old.</sentence>
<sentence id="s626">She never saw Ellen Dates having ' any corroborees or anything like that ' and didn't see her carrying out any traditional Aboriginal activity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s627">Ms Quinlan confirms that Ellen Dates was very religious and that she took Ms Quinlan to church.</sentence>
<sentence id="s628">&#8226; Ms Quinlan has never been to the Land and says that her family did not go there when they were children.</sentence>
<sentence id="s629">They did not have a car and Leonard Dates did not drive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s630">She does not know what the Garuahgal clan is and only heard about it through Worimi's claim on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s631">&#8226; She never went camping with her father and had never known him to go camping although she could not say that he didn't do so, especially at the time when she was with her grandmother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s632">&#8226; She says that Gary spent a lot of time away from home when he was young and that when he was about 16 years old he left home.</sentence>
<sentence id="s633">She understands that he went to live in Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s634">Priscilla Anne Dates 
 
&#8226; Priscilla Anne Dates is Worimi's daughter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s635">She is also a member of the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s636">&#8226; Ms Dates lived with Worimi's mother and father, Beryl and Leonard Dates, the latter until he died, until she was 16 or 17 years of age and then lived with her mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s637">She is the daughter of Worimi and Alana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s638">&#8226; Ms Dates has been through the area where the Land is situated but has never been on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s639">She says that she did not go there when she was young.</sentence>
<sentence id="s640">She has no special feelings for the Land and does not know anything about it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s641">Ms Dates was adamant that she did not, when she was growing up, learn about Aboriginal tribes or Aboriginal clans or Aboriginal culture and first heard her father speak of it in the last couple of years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s642">She says that she never heard her father speaking an Aboriginal language.</sentence>
<sentence id="s643">&#8226; Ms Dates says that Worimi told her a couple of years ago that women had their babies on the Land but that was the first time she had heard anything about it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s644">She says that she did not learn anything about Aboriginal culture when she was growing up from Beryl Dates, Leonard Dates or Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s645">&#8226; Ms Dates accepted that she had affirmed two previous affidavits supporting Worimi's claims but says that she was drunk on both occasions and that she only signed them out of love for her father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s646">She had given inconsistent evidence in previous affidavits in support of her father's claimant applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s647">She accepted that she had not been coerced into signing those previous affidavits but said that she had been drunk on both occasions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s648">&#8226; While Ms Dates has given conflicting evidence, her recollection was not perfect and she readily agreed with many of the propositions put to her in cross-examination, she was adamant about a number of things: she was not approached to give evidence in support of the Land Council; she was not offered any compensation or inducement to do so; she is not scared of her father or of any family members; she has not been threatened with any violence in relation to her evidence; no pressure has been placed on her to give evidence --- she has done it of her own volition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s649">Kelvin Andrew Dates 
 
108 There is, in addition, an affidavit by Kelvin Andrew Dates, Worimi's younger brother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s650">Kelvin Dates was required for cross-examination but was unable to attend because of illness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s651">Kelvin Dates' inability to attend was accepted by all parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s652">That inability and the absence of cross-examination does, however, affect the weight to be given to the matters to which he deposes which are in dispute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s653">Kelvin Dates says:
 
&#8226; That he is an Aboriginal from the Worimi tribe; a son of Leonard and Beryl Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s654">His father was a Worimi person and his mother a Yorta Yorta person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s655">&#8226; Kelvin Dates has been recognised as a traditional owner among the Worimi Aboriginal community.</sentence>
<sentence id="s656">He has been nominated as a traditional owner by his family and accepted by the community as a traditional owner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s657">He says that he does not believe that Worimi has been recognised as a traditional owner among the Worimi Aboriginal community.</sentence>
<sentence id="s658">&#8226; Beryl Dates was born in Victoria and, to Kelvin Dates' knowledge, has never been to Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s659">Kelvin Dates is not aware of any cultural significance at Boat Harbour or that there has been any fishing at or storytelling about Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s660">He himself had not been to Boat Harbour until early 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s661">&#8226; He was not aware of his father passing Boat Harbour to Gary or telling any stories to him, or camping or fishing with him at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s662">&#8226; Kelvin Dates never heard his father speak of Aboriginal culture or about Aboriginal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s663">Kelvin Dates believes that Gary left the Port Stephens area in the late 1960s and returned around 1976.</sentence>
<sentence id="s664">He confirmed that the family did not have a car when he was growing up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s665">He said his father had a motorbike but he had never seen either of his parents drive a motor vehicle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s666">&#8226; To his knowledge, his grandparents never lived at Boat Harbour and did not have any connection to Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s667">His father and grandfather were born in Karuah and his grandmother in Forster.</sentence>
<sentence id="s668">&#8226; He is not aware of Gary living a traditional lifestyle at Boat Harbour or anywhere else and is not aware of his brother having a connection to Boat Harbour prior to his native title application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s669">&#8226; He says that his family did not have a special connection to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s670">He was not taught about fishing and hunting when he was growing up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s671">He has never heard of the Guardian Tree or rock formations on Bulahdelah Mountain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s672">He does not agree that it is Worimi law that you should be buried near your mother or that you should return to your territory when you die.</sentence>
<sentence id="s673">He had not heard the story of the creation of the Hunter River as described by Gary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s674">Worimi's affidavit of 1 May 2008 
 
109 Worimi responded to the evidence of the Land Council's witnesses in a further affidavit filed in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s675">He reiterated that the Land was important to all Worimi people, in particular to women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s676">He explained that he restricted his claim as being on behalf of the women in his immediate family because other Worimi women affirmed affidavits that they did not know about the women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s677">He says that he understands that all Worimi people hold native title in the Land, not just himself or his immediate family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s678">110 Worimi answered specific assertions in the Land Council's evidence and said, for example, that Leonard Dates and his grandmother did speak 'Worimi Lingo' and that his father had shared his knowledge and culture with Ms Quinlan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s679">Further, he said that his father had initiation scars on his chest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s680">111 Worimi reiterated his claims concerning the knowledge passed to him and explained why Ms Quinlan and Kelvin Dates may not have been aware of that knowledge or the fact that it was passed to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s681">He also reiterated how he was told by his father and his father's mother of the matters about which he had given evidence and which were disputed by the Land Council's witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s682">Further, he says that he was told that when babies are born of the Saltwater people (Maaiangal, Garuahgal, Tobwabba and Gamapingal clans), the baby's head is splashed with saltwater and they are given their totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s683">112 Worimi says that he was told that Mary Mahr was born at Burral River, 60 kilometres from Karuah.</sentence>
<sentence id="s684">The tender bundle and the relevance of the fact that some of the witnesses called by the Land Council have made claimant applications seeking determinations of the existence of native title over land within Worimi traditional land in the Port Stephens area 
 
113 Applications for determinations of the existence of native title have been filed, but not determined, in respect of areas within the lands held by the Land Council, which have also been described as "Worimi land".</sentence>
<sentence id="s685">Named applicants in those applications included Ms Brown, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett and Kelvin Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s686">Those applications cover Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach but do not include Lot 576 or land within the immediate vicinity of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s687">114 Worimi sought to tender material in respect of those applications made on behalf of the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s688">The claims over Bagnalls Beach and Stockton Bight were the subject of cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s689">Both involved areas within what has been described as Worimi country and, Worimi says, in close proximity to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s690">In those applications, assertions were made as to membership of the Worimi people and membership of a native title claim group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s691">Evidence in support of the applications was directed to the cultural heritage significance of the areas to the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s692">Affidavits contained material concerning customs of the area and of the Aboriginal people who lived there, including descriptions of fishing and the passing of knowledge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s693">115 There is a reference in some of those documents to Maaiangal people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s694">One reference links the Maaiangal clan with Kelvin Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s695">116 Worimi contends that the documents evidencing previous native title applications in relation to land in the Port Stephens area by Worimi people are admissible and relevant to the issue of whether those witnesses believe that native title exists in the Port Stephens area and whether there are other Worimi persons who may hold native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s696">The claimants included witnesses in these proceedings, who were cross-examined on the fact that they had filed and supported native title applications in the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s697">The fact of those applications and the fact that assertions were made in those applications is relevant and admissible in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s698">However, I do not accept Worimi's submission that the fact of the earlier native title applications leads to the conclusion that the witnesses were untruthful in their evidence in these proceedings or that they tailored their evidence to suit the present wish to sell Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s699">117 The Land Council and the Minister objected to the tender of the material on the basis of relevance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s700">The Land Council submitted that the cross-examination of the witnesses on this subject matter went to credit and that the documentary material was not admissible because of s 106 of the Evidence Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s701">The Minister and Worimi finally submitted that, if admitted into evidence, the evidence should be received as evidence of statements or assertions made by the author of the document, not evidence of the truth of those statements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s702">118 I do not consider that the applications and the fact that some of the witnesses were claimants for native title over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach impeaches their credit in these proceedings even if the documents in the tender bundle were admissible for that purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s703">The witnesses were cross-examined about those applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s704">Generally speaking, they do not want to see any of the land held by the Land Council sold but accept that it is necessary for the Land Council to sell Lot 576 to pay debts and provide housing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s705">They do not object to that sale as Lot 576 does not have significance to them in terms of law or custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s706">119 I accept the tender of those documents as going to the fact that the applications were made and the fact that the assertions therein were made by the witnesses concerned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s707">Worimi also tendered, and I accepted, the tender of his grandparents' marriage certificate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s708">120 Part of the bundle contained the judgment and the reasons for a decision of a judge of the Court, that did not require tender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s709">121 Also included was a decision of the National Native Title Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s710">It is admitted as a decision of the National Native Title Tribunal of 24 September 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s711">122 Also included was what seemed to be genealogical material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s712">No evidence was adduced as to the basis of that material or as to its status, nor were the authors offered for cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s713">To the extent that that material states conclusions, the basis for the conclusions is not sufficiently included.</sentence>
<sentence id="s714">I reject the documents entitled "Colbran Genealogy" and an extract from Norman Tindale "Aboriginal Tribes of Australia" (not strictly included in the bundle).</sentence>
<sentence id="s715">123 It follows that Worimi's tender bundle shows that applications for native title determinations were made in 1998 and 2000 over land in the Port Stephens area in proximity to Lot 576, being Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach, but not including the Land the subject of this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s716">The applications were made and/or supported by certain witnesses in these proceedings, including Kevin Dates, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett, Ms Brown, Ms Merrick and Ms Russell, as well as by the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s717">124 Worimi contends that the assertions of native title over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach are inconsistent with the denial of native title over the Land and the area adjacent to the Land at Kingsley Beach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s718">The inconsistency that Worimi relies on relates to his assertion that the phrase "in relation to" in s 36(9) of the NSW Act necessitates a consideration of native title rights and interests over the whole of the land held by the Land Council pursuant to the transfer under the NSW Act and includes other land in the Port Stephens area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s719">I have not accepted that such an inconsistency arises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s720">Worimi says that it is highly relevant that there have been assertions of native title over land located on the coast in "close proximity" to Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s721">I accept that the existence of native title over land in close proximity to Lot 576 may be relevant to the existence of native title over the Land to the extent that if casts light on one or more of the elements of the asserted native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s722">125 Worimi accepts that the mere assertions in those claims do not prove that native title exists but submits that it is relevant that the witnesses assert that they are descendants of people from Port Stephens whom they considered were native title holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s723">126 The issue is native title under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s724">The evidence must be looked at as a whole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s725">An assertion of native title is not sufficient.</sentence>
<sentence id="s726">It is necessary to provide some evidence of connection with the Land and the laws acknowledged and customs observed in connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s727">There is no inconsistency with the fact of the assertions of native title over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach and the denial of the existence of native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s728">The fact that evidence could show a connection with Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach does not mean that it could also be shown for Lot 576 or Kingsley's Beach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s729">The witnesses who were part of the claim group over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach maintain the existence of laws and customs in connection with that land but positively assert that they have no knowledge of any continuing laws acknowledged or customs observed in connection with Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s730">To the contrary, they deny the existence of such laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s731">Worimi's evidence in cross-examination 
 
127 It was apparent from Worimi's evidence in cross-examination that he is of the view that he has been badly treated by the Maaiangal people, who say that they own the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s732">Worimi says that he was and is upset that the Land Council wishes to sell the Land to pay debts and buy housing, without considering the cultural significance of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s733">There appears to be no dispute that the Land Council wishes to sell the Land to pay off its debts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s734">It is apparent that the witnesses called by the Land Council support the sale of the Land for that purpose and accept that that was the reason for the Land Council's application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s735">Worimi says that, despite the fact that he knows of the need for housing, he does not wish to have sacred land sold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s736">Worimi asserts that the provision of housing is the government's responsibility and not that of the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s737">128 In answer to some of the matters that are the subject of the Land Council's evidence:
 
&#8226; Worimi accepts that before the meeting of the Land Council that he attended on 6 December 2004, he had never asserted that native title existed in Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s738">That was, he says, because the map provided with the resolution at the meeting on that occasion reminded him of the fact that it was a women's business place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s739">&#8226; Worimi was not a member of the claim group over Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s740">He says that it was part of Garuahgal land before it was Maaiangal land but he cannot remember if he complained of that fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s741">He did not seek to become part of that claim nor did he make a native title claim otherwise over Stockton Bight.</sentence>
<sentence id="s742">He did not seek to participate as a claimant over Bagnalls Beach although Bagnalls Beach is, according to Worimi, part of Garuahgal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s743">Worimi has not made a native title claim over any land in what he says is Garuahgal country or any other part of Boat Harbour other than Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s744">&#8226; Worimi says that the claim to native title over Lot 576 can only be made through him because of his knowledge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s745">&#8226; Worimi says that Ellen Dates had great faith both in God and in her ancestors and that she was not strictly Christian.</sentence>
<sentence id="s746">&#8226; He maintains that his grandmother told him about the baptism place, the Poona on the beach and the waterhole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s747">She used her own word ' Poona '; she did not use the word "billabong" but freshwater spring.</sentence>
<sentence id="s748">She described a stream running through Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s749">&#8226; He says that his sisters, other than Ms Quinlan, did not know of the matters that he was told by his grandmother and that the other Worimi women have no knowledge of traditional law and custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s750">&#8226; Women came from other areas to the Poona; they were Garuahgal women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s751">He does not know why they are not supporting his assertion of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s752">&#8226; Worimi says that there were three phases of use of the Land and the nearby area of Kingsley Beach: a baptism where the ocean meets the beach (the Poona); there was then washing in the waterhole (located on or near the Land); and then the afterbirth was buried somewhere on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s753">&#8226; He also said that as a child his father taught him the Worimi language which he used to speak with his father and father's brothers and is trying to pass on to his children.</sentence>
<sentence id="s754">&#8226; Worimi maintains that his father did follow Aboriginal law and custom and that he often went to Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s755">His father told him that he was the custodian and protector of all of the Worimi land, not of all the Worimi women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s756">&#8226; Worimi said that Big Bill Ridgeway did not teach the children about Aboriginal law and custom, just about throwing boomerangs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s757">&#8226; Worimi does not recall saying that he was an elder of the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s758">He accepts that he cannot be so because he is not yet 60.</sentence>
<sentence id="s759">He says he is a custodian but not an elder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s760">He became a custodian at age 27.</sentence>
<sentence id="s761">He says that the age of 51 has no significance at all.</sentence>
<sentence id="s762">However, Worimi has previously stated that he became an elder at 51 years of age.</sentence>
<sentence id="s763">&#8226; Worimi asserts that his daughter Priscilla Dates is lying.</sentence>
<sentence id="s764">He says that the daughters who affirmed affidavits in support of his claimant applications did so because they knew he was telling the truth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s765">&#8226; Importantly, Worimi says that to his knowledge, Ellen Dates did not pass on any information about the Boat Harbour land and the practices of the women's site to any of his sisters except Ms Quinlan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s766">129 Worimi described the actions of his daughter Beryl in performing a baptism ceremony for his grandson which involved baptising the child in saltwater at Kingsley Beach, the giving of his totem and then burying the afterbirth somewhere on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s767">Worimi said that this represented a culture, ' a tribal custom that has been taken away from my people and this may be the first [time] that it's happened [in] over the last probably 150 years '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s768">He also accepted in cross-examination that the Worimi no longer carry out these practices but that the Dunghutti continue to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s769">Worimi's wife, Cynthia, is Dunghutti and he said that the steps his daughter Beryl and his wife Cynthia took to baptise his grandson were not Worimi practices but Dunghutti practices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s770">130 When asked whether he asserts that he personally has native title over Lot 576, Worimi reiterated that he makes the assertion ' on behalf of all my people, of the 11 clans ... of the Worimi nation '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s771">Insofar as his claim extends to being on behalf of his wife, daughters and mother, he says that it is only for permission to go onto the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s772">He says that if the contrary was asserted in an affidavit or in a claimant application he did not understand it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s773">131 Worimi accepts that his mother does not have native title over the Land and that she lost her tribal right once his father died because she is Yorta Yorta.</sentence>
<sentence id="s774">According to Worimi, she has had no rights to make a native title application over Lot 576 since 1981.</sentence>
<sentence id="s775">I note that he did not rely on that fact when I found that his mother was, on his case, included in his asserted claim group but had not authorised his claimant application ( Worimi 2006 and Hillig (No 2) ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s776">To the contrary, he obtained her authorisation subsequently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s777">This is only necessary if, contrary to his evidence in cross-examination, she is part of the Worimi claim group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s778">Worimi's previous affidavits 
 
132 Previous affidavits sworn by Worimi in respect of his claimant applications and his application for joinder explained his claim for native title over the Land and the reasons for it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s779">I will not summarise all of those affidavits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s780">Some are evidence in these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s781">Many of the matters contained in Worimi's previous affidavits were referred to in Worimi 2007 , Worimi 2006 and Hillig (No 2) .</sentence>
<sentence id="s782">However, some matters, as found in those cases, bear repeating.</sentence>
<sentence id="s783">They are either matters that Worimi says are part of his own knowledge or represent his understanding, based on stories told to him by his father and grandmother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s784">Although some of the affidavits were not read or tendered as evidence in these proceedings, they formed an acknowledged background to the evidence and submissions:
 The affidavit of 19 August 2005 ( Worimi 2006 )
 
&#8226; In the affidavit of 19 August 2005, Worimi asserted that he held native title in the Land, as did the Garuahgal people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s785">He said that part of the Land was a sacred and secret place for women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s786">The affidavit of 20 January 2006 
 
&#8226; In the affidavit of 20 January 2006, which was filed in support of Worimi's first claimant application and tendered as an exhibit in these proceedings, Worimi asserted native title rights and interests in respect of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s787">Worimi said that he was authorised by the other claimants to that native title right, the authority having been given to him as custodian and protector of the Garuahgal women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s788">&#8226; Worimi said that the Land and all the other land between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour was given to him by his father, Leonard Dates, who received it from his father, Frederick Dates, a traditional elder of the Garuahgal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s789">Worimi claimed to be a traditional elder of the Garuahgal clan as the eldest son of Leonard Dates and because he is over 51 years of age.</sentence>
<sentence id="s790">&#8226; Worimi said that '[t] he land between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour was a special sacred place for women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s791">They came here to give birth and the babies were washed and baptised in the fresh water spring that runs along [the Land] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s792">Men were not allowed to visit this place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s793">My grandmother told me these stories '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s794">Worimi claimed that his grandmother lived a great part of her life in Boat Harbour except when she was ' banished from the land and taken to a Reserve in Karuah '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s795">Worimi claimed that his father told him stories about the Land and that he has carried on the association with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s796">&#8226; Worimi said that the Garuahgal women wish to reclaim their secret, sacred place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s797">The affidavit of 28 March 2006 ( Worimi 2006 )
 
&#8226; In the affidavit of 28 March 2006, Worimi said that his father had given him all the land between Boat Harbour and Birubi Beach for care and safe keeping.</sentence>
<sentence id="s798">He stated that his grandmother told him stories of how the Boat Harbour land was a secret, sacred place for women and that the tribal women came to the Land to give birth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s799">He stated that his grandmother told him how they washed the newborn babies in the freshwater stream that runs along the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s800">&#8226; Worimi also said that his father told him stories of the secret women's place and pointed out the special rock which was the boundary where men could not pass.</sentence>
<sentence id="s801">That rock was on the Land, adjoining the land at Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s802">&#8226; Worimi also described his own association with the Land as a place where he lived, camped and fished.</sentence>
<sentence id="s803">The affidavit of 25 May 2006 ( Worimi 2006 )
 
&#8226; In an affidavit of 25 May 2006, Worimi reiterated that there was a secret women's place on the Land where baptisms took place and where afterbirths were buried.</sentence>
<sentence id="s804">The affidavit of 15 September 2006 ( Worimi 2006 )
 
&#8226; In an affidavit affirmed on 15 September 2006, Worimi repeated his connection with the Garuahgal area including the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s805">He described the Garuahgal area as being "a state" of Worimi country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s806">&#8226; Worimi said that his father's mother taught him that there were sites sacred to Worimi women on and adjacent to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s807">&#8226; He said that as a Worimi man, he is not allowed to know most of the law and custom regarding those sites.</sentence>
<sentence id="s808">&#8226; He did not limit the use of the Land to women of the Garuahgal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s809">He said that Worimi women travelled to the Land and the area adjoining the Land to have their babies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s810">He said that after having their babies, the women would take them to a place near the Land, on an area of Kingsley Beach known as "the Poona".</sentence>
<sentence id="s811">There, the women bathed the babies in the sea water and gave them their tribal totem.</sentence>
<sentence id="s812">The women would then take the babies to a billabong adjacent to the Land to wash the sea water off the babies and would bury the afterbirth on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s813">&#8226; Worimi said that men are not allowed to go to the women's site at the Poona but there is no restriction on men going to the billabong or the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s814">&#8226; Worimi said that he is the custodian of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s815">His father had been the eldest initiated male in his family, which meant that he was responsible for making decisions about his country and his family and for protecting culturally significant places, including the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s816">Worimi says that on his father's death, he became custodian.</sentence>
<sentence id="s817">&#8226; Worimi stated that he now believes that he and his children may be the only persons who currently hold native title rights and interests in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s818">He said that he may be the only person who was given the native title rights and interests in the Land under traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s819">Affidavits of Worimi's family members ( Worimi 2007 )
 
133 Several members of Worimi's family affirmed affidavits in support of his claimant applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s820">Those affidavits, many of which are in similar form, are from Worimi's daughters (Rachel Dates, Priscilla Dates, Pur-ri (Beryl) Dates and Sheena Dates), mother (Beryl Mildred Dates), wife (Cynthia Dates) and sister (Debbie Dates).</sentence>
<sentence id="s821">The deponents stated a belief that they have native title rights and interests in the Land under traditional laws and customs, as taught by older family members.</sentence>
<sentence id="s822">RELEVANT PRINCIPLES 
 
134 The Land Council seeks a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s823">That means native title under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s824">In Yorta Yorta , the High Court emphasised that native title under the Act must be understood in accordance with the definition in s 223(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s825">That section provides:
 
 
 (1) The expression native title or native title rights and interests means the communal, group or individual rights and interests of Aboriginal peoples or Torres Strait Islanders in relation to land or waters, where: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) the rights and interests are possessed under the traditional laws acknowledged, and the traditional customs observed, by the Aboriginal peoples or Torres Strait Islanders; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) the Aboriginal peoples or Torres Strait Islanders, by those laws and customs, have a connection with the land or waters; and 
 
 (c) the rights and interests are recognised by the common law of Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s826">
 
 
 
135 In Yorta Yorta at [31], Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Hayne JJ raised the importance of identifying whether the body of traditional law and custom that intersects with the common law for the purposes of s 223(1) of the Act is that as existing at the time of sovereignty or that existing today but connected with a body of law and custom that existed at sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s827">Their Honours reiterated what had been said in Fejo v Northern Territory [1998] HCA 58 ; (1998) 195 CLR 96.</sentence>
<sentence id="s828">Native title, with its origin in the traditional laws acknowledged and the traditional customs observed by the indigenous people who possess the native title is recognised by the common law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s829">Their Honours went on to state that: ' An application for determination of native title requires the location of that intersection [between native title and the common law] and it requires that it be located by reference to [the Act].</sentence>
<sentence id="s830">In particular it must be located by reference to the definition of native title in s 223(1) '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s831">A determination of the existence of native title is a creature of the Act ( Yorta Yorta at [32]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s832">So too is a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s833">136 A number of principles relevant to the present case were set out in Yorta Yorta: 
 
&#8226; Laws or customs in which native title rights or interests find their origins must be laws or customs having a normative content and deriving, therefore, from a body of norms or normative system that existed before sovereignty (at [38]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s834">&#8226; Observable patterns of behaviour may not amount to rights or interests in relation to land or waters under the Act (at [42]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s835">&#8226; Upon the Crown acquiring sovereignty, the normative or law-making system which then existed could not thereafter validly create new rights, duties or interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s836">Rights or interests in land created after sovereignty and which owed their origin and continued existence only to a normative system other than that of the new sovereign power are not given effect (at [43] and [44]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s837">&#8226; This does not prevent the transmission of rights and interests under traditional laws and traditional customs which existed at sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s838">Nor does it prevent any alteration to, or development of, that traditional law and custom after sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s839">Account may at least be taken of developments of a kind contemplated by that traditional law and custom (at [44]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s840">&#8226; "Traditional" law or custom is apt to refer to a means of transmission of law or custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s841">In the context of the Act, the term "traditional" conveys an understanding of the age of the traditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s842">However, in the context of the Act, "traditional" laws and customs equate to the normative rules that existed before the assertion of sovereignty by the British Crown (at [46]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s843">It follows that the mere use of the word "traditional" does not establish the normative rules necessary for the establishment of native title under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s844">&#8226; The normative system under which the rights and interests are possessed, namely the traditional laws acknowledged and customs observed, must have had a continuous existence and vitality since sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s845">If that normative system has not existed throughout that period, the rights and interests which owe their existence to that system will have ceased to exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s846">Importantly, any later attempt to revive adherence to the tenets of that former system cannot and will not reconstitute the traditional laws and customs out of which right and interest must spring if they are to fall within the definition of native title (at [47]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s847">&#8226; If the society out of which the body of laws and customs arises ceases to exist as a group which acknowledges and observes those laws and customs, the laws and customs cease to have continued existence and vitality (at [50]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s848">CONSIDERATION OF THE EVIDENCE 
 The Land Council witnesses 
 
137 The Land Council relies not only upon the absence of any claimant application over the Land but also on the evidence from Aboriginal people associated with the area who have confirmed that, in their view, the native title rights and interests that Worimi asserts do not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s849">The Land Council has established that no Aboriginal person other than Worimi (and some of his immediate family who supported his claimant applications) asserts that native title exists in relation to Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s850">All of the Aboriginal witnesses called by the Land Council identified as Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s851">All are aware of the assertions made by Worimi concerning the existence of native title in the Land and gave evidence generally rejecting those assertions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s852">Some of those witnesses were parties to claimant applications for a determination of the existence of native title in respect of land in the Port Stephens area but none of the witnesses have filed native title claimant applications in relation to the Land or land in the immediate vicinity of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s853">138 Worimi says that the Court should draw a Jones v Dunkel (1959) 101 CLR 298 inference from the fact that other Worimi people did not give evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s854">I do not accept that submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s855">The Land Council duly resolved to dispose of the Land in accordance with the NSW Act and has filed this application for a determination of the absence of native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s856">It called a number of witnesses from different Worimi families, including women who have taken a particular interest in Worimi matters and traditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s857">No other person has been called to give evidence in support of Worimi's contentions in these proceedings, despite the length of time since his first application was filed and despite the fact that he asserts that native title is held by him as a Worimi man.</sentence>
<sentence id="s858">No other Worimi person has given evidence of the existence of laws and customs that connect Worimi people with Lot 576 or the land adjacent to it that he says is a women's site, prohibited to men.</sentence>
<sentence id="s859">139 Priscilla Dates gave evidence while in an advanced state of pregnancy with her tenth child.</sentence>
<sentence id="s860">It was clear that the giving of evidence, contrary to her father's case, caused her great personal distress.</sentence>
<sentence id="s861">She accepts that she had previously affirmed two affidavits supporting Worimi's assertions concerning the significance of the Land as a woman's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s862">She explains that she had been intoxicated when making the affidavits and that she affirmed them because she loves her father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s863">She has expressly recanted those earlier statements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s864">She gave clear evidence that she had never been to Boat Harbour, has never been taught about Aboriginal law or custom and knew nothing about the Land or Boat Harbour until a few years ago when her father first told her that women had their babies there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s865">Prior to the last few years she was unaware of any assertion of her family's association with Boat Harbour and the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s866">While Worimi says that Priscilla Dates is too young to remember, she says that her upbringing did not involve the passing on to her of any traditional knowledge, laws or customs associated with the Boat Harbour area or Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s867">140 Worimi submits that Priscilla Dates' evidence was unreliable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s868">Priscilla Dates did equivocate on some aspects of her evidence and she was clearly and understandably upset.</sentence>
<sentence id="s869">However, on the key questions of her knowledge of traditional laws and customs and her knowledge of the Land, she remained consistent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s870">I accept her evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s871">As Mr Kelvin Dates was not available for cross examination, I take note of his evidence to the extent that it is supported by documentary material or corroborative of the evidence of other witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s872">141 Worimi submits that Ms Quinlan demonstrated poor recollection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s873">I consider that she demonstrated a good recollection of relevant past events.</sentence>
<sentence id="s874">Worimi points out that a number of the witnesses were concerned about the Land Council's debts and focussed on housing and the needs of the community.</sentence>
<sentence id="s875">I found Ms Quinlan's evidence and that of the other Land Council witnesses persuasive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s876">142 Those persons are under the pressure of the debts owed by the Land Council but this does not derogate from their sworn evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s877">It explains why they may be more ready to sell the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s878">That is, I accept that those witnesses who gave evidence, particularly those deeply concerned with Aboriginal law and custom and Aboriginal interests in the area, would be unlikely to wish to sell land of importance to them by reason of custom or culture.</sentence>
<sentence id="s879">I understand that, while they may be loath to part with any part of the land that has been granted to them under the NSW Act, they are ready to sell land that does not otherwise have importance in terms of traditional laws and customs to ensure payment of the Land Council's debts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s880">The issue of the debts and the provision of housing do not of themselves impact on the question whether there is native title in Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s881">Maaiangal Land or Garuahgal Land 
 
143 There is no evidence to support Worimi's claim that there is a separate Garuahgal clan of which Ellen Dates and Leonard Dates were, and Worimi is, a member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s882">If there is a separate Garuahgal clan of which Worimi is a member through Ellen Dates and Leonard Dates, it would follow that his sister, Ms Quinlan, and his daughter, Priscilla Dates, are also members of that clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s883">Ms Quinlan identifies as an Aboriginal person of the Worimi tribe but does not know what the Garuahgal clan is.</sentence>
<sentence id="s884">144 Ms Brown, Ms Ridgeway-Bissett and Ms Quinlan each rejects the existence of or denies knowledge of a Worimi clan known as Garuahgal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s885">In his Notice of Intention to become a Party to the Stockton Bight application, Kelvin Dates described himself as Maaiangal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s886">The evidence called by the Land Council demonstrates that the Land falls within the area claimed by the Maaiangal witnesses to be part of the land of the Maaiangal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s887">Their evidence is to the effect that there can only be one clan claiming any particular land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s888">145 However, Worimi's evidence is that the Land is Garuahgal land and that there is no law saying that there can be only one clan with guardianship over a particular area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s889">There is evidence supporting Worimi's assertion of a Garuahgal clan or of a clan with a very similar spelling.</sentence>
<sentence id="s890">I am not satisfied that there is no such clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s891">I am not satisfied that, if there is, only one clan can claim particular land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s892">146 The native title applications over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach were made by the Maaiangal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s893">Members of that clan are clear that there are no traditional laws acknowledged or customs observed by Worimi people, at least, by the Maaiangal clan, in respect of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s894">If that is so, the existence of the native title applications over other parts of Worimi land do not cast doubt on the assertion of no native title in respect of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s895">147 Worimi asserts that Lot 576 is Garuahgal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s896">It would follow, on Worimi's case, that the evidence of the Maaiangal clan members is not relevant to his assertion of native title over Lot 576 because it is Garuahgal land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s897">If I were to consider surrounding country, the only claims brought have been by Maaiangal people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s898">I accept the uncontradicted evidence that Lot 576 and the area between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour is not, under traditional law and custom, a sacred women's site associated with birth and baptism of Worimi/Maaiangal women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s899">The evidence is that for those women there is a birthing site in the vicinity of Salamander Bay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s900">Worimi's case is that it is not the Maaiangal clan but the Garuahgal clan that exercised and is exercising the relevant native title rights over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s901">If that is the case, the asserted existence of traditional laws and customs observed by the Maaiangal clan over Stockton Bight and Bagnalls Beach is not relevant to the claim of a Garuahgal women's site on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s902">Worimi 
 
148 The Land Council points to the inconsistencies in Worimi's evidence over the period since the Land Council's application was filed, including:
 
&#8226; Worimi consistently asserted that he is an elder under Worimi/Garuahgal traditional law and custom because he had reached 51 years of age.</sentence>
<sentence id="s903">That proposition was rejected by the Land Council's witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s904">Worimi said in cross-examination that he is not an elder and accepted that elder status is not attained until a person reaches the age of 60.</sentence>
<sentence id="s905">&#8226; Worimi's mother, Beryl Mildred Dates, is Yorta Yorta.</sentence>
<sentence id="s906">Worimi had asserted that his mother acquired rights under Worimi law by virtue of her marriage to Leonard Dates, a Worimi man.</sentence>
<sentence id="s907">Beryl Mildred Dates was included as part of a claim group in Worimi's first claimant application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s908">The Land Council's witnesses reject this proposition and say that a woman retains her pre-marriage clan or tribal identity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s909">During cross-examination, Worimi said that because Leonard Dates had died, his mother lost her rights and ' has no right to have anything to do with the native title application, because my father is gone '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s910">&#8226; Early in the proceedings, at various directions hearings, Worimi said that he could not speak for the Land, Lot 576, because it was a site sacred to women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s911">In his affidavit of 20 January 2006, Worimi said that it was the land between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour that was a special place for women where they gave birth, that the babies were washed in the freshwater stream running along Lot 576 and that men were not allowed to visit that place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s912">He later said that men could go onto Lot 576 and go to the billabong on or near Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s913">In the affidavit of 18 December 2007, Worimi said there was no restriction on men going to the billabong and that they could camp on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s914">Indeed he says that he has camped on the Land many times since the age of 13 and that, as the custodian, he is obliged to care for and conserve the natural resources of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s915">During cross-examination he said that Lot 576 and the billabong were subject to an avoidance obligation and men could not go there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s916">He said that he had broken the law by doing so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s917">In cross-examination, Worimi identified the billabong as extending into Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s918">He confirmed that the Poona and the billabong were areas that men were obliged to avoid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s919">149 The Land Council also points out that Worimi's evidence changed in other ways in cross-examination after he had heard evidence of the Land Council witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s920">For example, Worimi claims in his affidavit of 20 January 2006 that Ellen Dates lived a greater part of her life in Port Stephens and in particular on the land at Boat Harbour and was banished from the land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s921">The Land Council witnesses gave evidence that Ellen Dates lived at Raymond Terrace and before that at the Karuah Mission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s922">Worimi's evidence in cross-examination was that Ellen Dates visited the Land by boat from Karuah Mission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s923">150 Mr Ridgeway's evidence also casts doubt on Worimi's assertion that he was taught traditional laws or customs by Big Bill Ridgeway.</sentence>
<sentence id="s924">In cross-examination, Worimi expressly rejected the statement in his affidavit of 18 December 2007 that Big Bill Ridgeway taught the children at the Karuah Mission about traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s925">Rather, Worimi stated that Big Bill Ridgeway only taught the children how to throw boomerangs and spears.</sentence>
<sentence id="s926">151 Worimi gave evidence that he had a right to go to Lot 576 to camp on the Land and to use the natural resources of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s927">The Land Council submits that the existence of such rights and the exercise of those rights are wholly inconsistent with the notion that the Land is to be avoided by men because it is a sacred site to women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s928">There is inconsistency in Worimi's various statements as to the precise area of the women's site and how much of Lot 576 forms part of that site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s929">I accept Worimi's evidence as to the location of the women's site and the prohibition on men going onto that site, either at the beach or at the billabong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s930">While his evidence has changed, it is not necessarily wholly inconsistent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s931">In cross-examination, Worimi identified the billabong prohibited to men as being on part of Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s932">That does not preclude men, including Worimi, from going onto other parts of Lot 576, away from the billabong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s933">152 The fact that Worimi describes some of the practices, such as hunting and fishing methods, differently from the description given by the other witnesses does not derogate from his evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s934">It could well be the case that there were different ways of observing traditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s935">As was pointed out in Western Australia v Sebastian (2008) 248 ALR 61 at [84], a ' body of laws and customs ' does not require identical practice, nor that each member of a group has precisely the same knowledge or comprehends the laws and customs in precisely the same way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s936">153 Worimi says that his family and his mother before him were removed by actions of others and that the removal was not voluntary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s937">In an area where non-Aboriginal communities developed, many Aboriginal families lived at Karuah, which is also part of Worimi land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s938">In deciding whether claimants, by traditional laws acknowledged and traditional customs observed, have a present connection with land, some interruptions to enjoyment of native title rights and interests is allowed ( Gale at [108], citing Yorta Yorta and De Rose ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s939">154 The Land Council relies upon the inconsistencies in Worimi's evidence as going to the very heart of Worimi's assertions as to the existence of native title in Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s940">The Land Council poses the question: ' How could it be said that native title rights and interests are rooted in a normative body of law and custom when the central assertion concerning the [L] and, that it is a sacred site for women to be avoided by men, can be so directly contradicted in Worimi's own evidence?</sentence>
<sentence id="s941">'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s942">155 The Land Council submits that Worimi's evidence does not represent a legitimate process of cultural reconnection but actions that are ' mischievous and destructive ' in preventing a small local Aboriginal Land Council from exercising its rights under beneficial legislation for the ultimate benefit of its members and the Aboriginal community.</sentence>
<sentence id="s943">The Land Council says that Worimi is motivated by his hostility to the Land Council and its former administrator for a failure to provide housing to his family and alleged poor treatment by the elders and staff of the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s944">The evidence of a women's site on or near the Land 
 
156 There is no dispute that Worimi is of Aboriginal descent, that he is a Worimi person, or that his ancestors are Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s945">His evidence that his grandparents and parents lived in the Port Stephens area is not in dispute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s946">His assertions that he was taught by his grandmother, father and father's brothers have not been directly disputed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s947">However, his sister, Ms Quinlan, said that she was not told or taught any traditional laws and customs by Ellen Dates, although she lived with her and was female.</sentence>
<sentence id="s948">The likelihood that Ellen Dates observed and taught traditional laws and customs is challenged by the evidence that Ellen Dates was a devout and observant Christian.</sentence>
<sentence id="s949">Further, Worimi's evidence that he was taught by Big Bill Ridgeway is disputed by Mr Ridgeway's son, whose description of his father makes it unlikely that Big Bill was a major source of Aboriginal custom, and was changed by Worimi during cross-examination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s950">Kelvin Dates, Worimi's brother, says that he was not taught any laws and customs by Leonard Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s951">However, he was not able to be cross-examined and he was not the eldest son, a position which Wormi claims gave him a special place and right to learn such things.</sentence>
<sentence id="s952">Worimi's assertion that he passed his knowledge of laws and customs to his children has been disputed by his daughter, Priscilla Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s953">157 Some of Worimi's descriptions of individual customs and methods of hunting and fishing and terminology were challenged by the other Worimi witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s954">I find that less persuasive, as different families might well have adopted different methods.</sentence>
<sentence id="s955">158 No Aboriginal man or woman who gave evidence, other than Worimi, knew of a women's site on or near the Land or between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s956">Specifically, there is no evidence to support Worimi's assertions of:
 
1. the existence of a site known as the "Poona" at Kingsley Beach or of any practice associated with birth or baptism in the area between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour or on Lot 576;
 
2. the existence of a "billabong" or "namby" on or in the vicinity of Lot 576 or that any such billabong was used for washing saltwater off babies after they had been baptised;
 
3. the use of the freshwater spring or stream running through Lot 576 for washing saltwater off babies after they had been baptised;
 
4. the giving of totems to babies on or near Kingsley Beach;
 
5. the burying of afterbirth on or near Lot 576;
 
6. the existence of an avoidance obligation on men relating to Lot 576 or Kingsley Beach or any other land in the vicinity of Boat Harbour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s957">It is important to recall that the key women's site, the birthing site identified by Worimi, is not on Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s958">It is on the beach nearby.</sentence>
<sentence id="s959">He has asserted that the waterhole associated with the birthing site was on Lot 576 and that the afterbirth was buried there.</sentence>
<sentence id="s960">Worimi's description of the location of the waterhole on Lot 576 or on land adjacent to Lot 576 was not consistent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s961">159 Worimi has not provided supporting evidence by other Aboriginal people, in particular Worimi women, of his contentions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s962">There is no other evidence supporting his primary assertion that the land between Birubi Beach and Boat Harbour, including the Land, was, under traditional laws and customs, a place associated with birth and baptism.</sentence>
<sentence id="s963">160 Worimi's assertions are based upon information and knowledge that he said was passed to him from his father's mother, Ellen Dates, and his father, Leonard Dates, who was the custodian and protector of the land and who passed that role to Worimi as the eldest son.</sentence>
<sentence id="s964">Ms Quinlan and Kelvin Dates' evidence is that Leonard Dates did not pass on any knowledge of traditional laws and customs to them but that does not necessarily contradict Worimi's evidence because Worimi's evidence was that the information was passed on to him as the eldest son.</sentence>
<sentence id="s965">161 That does not, however, apply to information from Ellen Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s966">Ms Quinlan lived with Ellen Dates and says that Ellen Dates was a very religious woman who lived by the Bible and did not live according to any traditional law and custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s967">Ms Quinlan had not been to the Land herself and has no knowledge of it as associated with a women's site.</sentence>
<sentence id="s968">Ms Quinlan says that Ellen Dates did not pass on any traditional knowledge to her and did not tell her of any women's site on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s969">The fact that Ellen Dates did not pass on any knowledge or traditional Aboriginal law and custom was confirmed by Kelvin Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s970">It would be expected that information concerning a women's site would have been passed to Ms Quinlan if Ellen Dates were aware of such a site and continued to observe law and custom in relation to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s971">162 The Land Council relies on Worimi's own evidence to demonstrate a lack of continuity in the practices said to have been carried out on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s972">Worimi acknowledges that, whether or not Lot 576 and the area at Kingsley Beach are women's sites and associated with the birth of children, whether Worimi, Maaiangal or Garuahgal, there has not been a continuous connection with such people and the observance of traditional laws and customs since sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s973">Accordingly, there has not been the requisite "connection" with the Land as required by s 223(1) of the Act ( Bodney v Bennell (2008) 167 FCR 84 at [171]---[174]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s974">This is not because of the physical presence or absence on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s975">It is because the practices of his own family, that he says are associated with the Land, were not observed at least from the time of his grandmother until his daughter went onto the Land in 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s976">I accept that, at least now, Worimi feels strongly about his Aboriginal heritage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s977">Worimi accepts that he has taken some of the customs observed by the Dunghutti people, as described and observed by his wife Cynthia, in practising with his daughter the customs connected with birth and baptism that he said were carried out on the Land and Kingsley Beach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s978">That could be said to reflect the incorporation, in the ordinary course, of other customs and practices into the traditional forms of the Garuahgal people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s979">163 As in Yorta Yorta , if there had been a women's site on or near the Land and Kingsley Beach, much has changed since it was used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s980">164 This baptism of Worimi's grandson by his daughter Beryl and wife Cynthia represents an attempt by Worimi to restore what he says his grandmother told him, as amended by his wife's practices.</sentence>
<sentence id="s981">It does not represent continuity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s982">Worimi has claimed that the site is sacred to all Worimi women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s983">No woman has supported this claim, apart from some members of his immediate family who supported his claimant applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s984">Worimi's evidence of native title rights and interests and their continuity 
 
165 In Gale, Madgwick J was dealing with a native title claimant application from which the claimants withdrew.</sentence>
<sentence id="s985">One of the respondents, Deerubbin Local Aboriginal Land Council, sought an order that there was no native title over the subject land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s986">Expert evidence had been filed in support of the claimant applications to which the Deerubbin Local Aboriginal Land Council had responded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s987">His Honour considered Yorta Yorta and drew from it a number of relevant principles, including:
 
&#8226; [N] ative title rights and interests derive from traditional laws and customs in the sense that they survived the acquisition of sovereignty over Australia: Yorta Yorta at [75].</sentence>
<sentence id="s988">
 
&#8226; The rights and interests must be presently 'possessed' under traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s989">This requires that the normative system under which those rights or interests are possessed ... be a system that has had a 'continuous existence and vitality' since sovereignty: Yorta Yorta at [47].</sentence>
<sentence id="s990">
 
&#8226; Some change to or adaptation of traditional law or custom or some interruption of enjoyment or exercise of native title rights or interests since sovereignty will not necessarily be fatal to a native title claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s991">
 
&#8226; The statutory questions (in s 223) are directed to the present possession of the rights or interests, not their exercise, and to the existence of a relevant, present connection.</sentence>
<sentence id="s992">It follows that the non-exercise of native title rights or interests by some of the persons now claiming such rights or interests ... will not inevitably be fatal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s993">
 
&#8226; The requirement in s 223(1)(b) for connection with land or waters by traditional laws and customs must be a connection which the peoples concerned have by their traditional laws and customs, that is the laws and customs acknowledged and observed by the ancestors of the claimants at the time of sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s994">It is the normative quality of the normative rules which rendered the Crown's radical title acquired at sovereignty subject to the rights and interests then existing and which are now identified as native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s995">
 
&#8226; It is an important qualification that the acknowledgment and observance of those rules need only have continued substantially, and not entirely, uninterrupted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s996">
 
&#8226; Nonetheless, it is necessary to demonstrate that it is the normative system of the pre-sovereign society out of which the claimed rights and interests arise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s997">This entails that it be shown that that society has continued to exist as a body united by its acknowledgement and observance of the traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s998">
 
&#8226; Acknowledgement and observance of those laws and customs must have continued substantially uninterrupted since sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s999">It is not enough that there be a body of laws and customs originating in the common acceptance by or agreement of a new society of indigenous peoples to acknowledge and observe them, notwithstanding that they are similar to or even identical with those of an earlier and different society.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1000">
 
166 Justice Madgwick concluded at [18] that there is a stringent requirement of continuity both of the society which had the rules giving rise to native title rights and interests and of observance of those traditional laws and customs which embodied those rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1001">At [118], Madgwick J found that, on the available evidence, the claimants did not constitute, even as the last member, ' a society that in any presently relevant sense observes traditional laws and customs '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1002">Aboriginality by descent and/or self-identification and acceptance as such is not enough to found a native title claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1003">It was not shown that there was ' a society that has continued to exist since before sovereignty and which was and is united by its acknowledgement of traditional laws and observance of traditional customs, allowing that the laws and customs may have adapted '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1004">Those laws and customs were not shown to have had a "continuous existence and vitality" since sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1005">Justice Madgwick concluded that there was no adequate reason not to make a determination that native title did not exist in relation to the subject land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1006">167 The positive assertion of native title rights and interests requires more than vague assertions of membership of a group of people and of "custodianship" of land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1007">Worimi's facts and contentions comprehensively fail to establish the elements of native title required by s 223 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1008">They do not establish native title within the meaning of Yorta Yorta .</sentence>
<sentence id="s1009">They do not identify the alleged content of the normative body of laws and customs acknowledged and observed by the pre-sovereignty society nor how those laws and customs have continued to be acknowledged and observed substantially uninterrupted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1010">While Worimi is not required positively to establish native title in order to resist the Land Council's application, he must present evidence which is sufficiently cogent with respect to those elements that the evidence does address to cast doubt on the assertion that native title does not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1011">168 Worimi asserts laws and customs in connection with the Land which, he acknowledges, are not observed by other Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1012">That is consistent with the evidence of the other witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1013">As in Gale , Worimi and those of his family who support his claims do not constitute a society that observes traditional laws and customs in respect of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1014">As in Gale , even if the Land was associated with the birth of children of the Garuahgal people, the present observance by Worimi and one of his daughters is ' at best an attempted re-creation of a society which may well have had native title rights and interests ' (at [119]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1015">169 As the High Court said in Yorta Yorta , the relevant laws and customs must be rules having normative content.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1016">Without that quality, there may be observable patterns of behaviour but not rights or interests in relation to land or waters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1017">Rights or interests created after sovereignty are insufficient, although there may be changes in the traditional laws and customs, at least to the extent that such changes and developments were contemplated by traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1018">170 As was said in Yorta Yorta at [47] and repeated in Bodney at [47], if the normative system has not existed throughout the period since sovereignty, the rights and interests which owe their existence to that system will have ceased to exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1019">The law and custom arise out of and go to define a particular society, a body of persons united in and by its acknowledgment and observance of a body of law and customs ( Yorta Yorta at [49]; Bodney at [46]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1020">' Unless a society has, and acknowledges and observes, laws and customs under which native title rights and interests are possessed, there can be no native title rights whether communal, group or individual ' ( Bodney at [157]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1021">It is therefore necessary for a person claiming native title to show that the normative system that existed at sovereignty is substantially the same as the one that exists today ( Bodney at [47]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1022">This must be established for each generation to establish that the laws and customs have continued to be acknowledged and observed substantially uninterrupted ( Bodney at [70]---[74]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1023">171 Where individual native title rights are claimed, they arise out of and depend upon the traditional laws and customs of the community in question ( Bodney at [148]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1024">Rights may be communally held or held by a sub-group or, indeed, by an individual, depending on the nature of the society said to be the repository of the traditional laws and customs that give rise to the native title rights and interests ( Northern Territory of Australia v Alyawarr, Kaytetye, Warumungu, Wakaya Native Title Claim Group [2005] FCAFC 135 ; (2005) 145 FCR 442 at [79] and [80]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1025">In the present case, the native title rights over a Worimi women's site would be held by Worimi women.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1026">They deny such rights for Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1027">172 Worimi asserts that his evidence establishes that he has rights and interests in relation to the Land which are rooted in pre-sovereignty Worimi society and up to the present time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1028">He says that the evidence establishes that those rights and interests have been transmitted in accordance with the traditional laws and customs and are still observed by Worimi and some members of his family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1029">This, he says, establishes that he has a connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1030">173 Even accepting the existence of a normative system of laws acknowledged and customs observed in connection with the Land, no evidence has been adduced of the conditions that existed between 1788 and the time of the stories said to have been told to Worimi by Ellen Dates and Leonard Dates about their experiences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1031">Worimi seems to rely on a presumption of continuity from pre-sovereignty times to the lifetime of Ellen Dates and Leonard Dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1032">According to Mr Ridgeway, Aboriginal people lived as part of the non-Aboriginal community around Port Stephens or on the Karuah Mission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1033">There is no basis on which to infer the continuity of the observance of laws and customs, the use and enjoyment of rights and interests in the Land or of Worimi connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1034">174 Worimi submits that native title rights and interests may be possessed by individuals or by a group of individuals in circumstances where other members of the same community or society do not possess those or other native title rights and interests in relation to that area (citing De Rose (No 2) at [33], [34] and [44]; Sebastian ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1035">Whether Worimi can establish native title where other members of the Worimi tribe state that there is no native title over the Land is, Worimi submits, not to the point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1036">He says that his individual rights and interests have been recognised, inter alia in De Rose (No 2) at [30], as sufficient to cast doubt on the Land Council's case of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1037">175 Worimi has given evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1038">His case as to who holds the relevant native title rights and interests has changed throughout the course of these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1039">In his affidavit of 18 December 2007, he claims that the native title rights and interests are held by his immediate family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1040">However, in cross-examination and in his affidavit of 1 May 2008, Worimi claimed that all Worimi people hold native title in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1041">176 As to the assertion that Worimi and his immediate family hold the native title rights and interests, I note that three members of his family, namely his brother Kelvin Dates, his sister Ms Quinlan and his daughter Priscilla Dates do not support his case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1042">However, other members of his family have supported his claimant applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1043">Worimi says candidly that he would have expected other Worimi women to have knowledge of the laws and customs of which he speaks and accepts that they do not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1044">However, the fact remains that Worimi has only adduced his own evidence of the detail of the beliefs and practices that he says relate to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1045">None of his family members have given evidence of the knowledge of or practice of traditional laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1046">177 As to Worimi's assertion that all Worimi people hold native title rights and interests in the Land, no other Aboriginal person, including those who have lived near the Land for all of their lives, have given evidence that suggests the existence of laws and customs in relation to the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1047">178 Worimi's case is that he and he alone seems to have the requisite knowledge, apart from those to whom he has passed it within his own family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1048">Accordingly, it is hard to see what further evidence the Land Council could have called to answer Worimi's evidence other than from other members of Worimi's family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1049">The witnesses for the Land Council include representatives of families long associated with the area.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1050">They give evidence not only of their own understanding but they also speak of their parents and, indeed, Worimi's grandmother and father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1051">179 Whether Worimi's claim is for himself, his immediate family or for all Worimi people, the claimed rights and interests must exist under a normative body of traditional law and custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1052">The asserted present connection with the claimed area must be a connection by and under the traditional laws acknowledged and customs observed by the relevant group or society.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1053">There must be substantially uninterrupted continuity in the acknowledgement and observance of the normative system of traditional law and custom in which the claimed rights and interests find their foundations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1054">Worimi has not adduced evidence supporting such a normative body of law and custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1055">He has not brought any evidence corroborating his own evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1056">In particular, he has not brought any evidence to support his claim of a women's site on or near Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1057">Nor has he adduced sufficient evidence regarding other activities, including hunting and fishing, said to have been carried out on or near Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1058">180 The Land Council submits that Worimi adduced no admissible evidence of his ancestry, the nature of the pre-sovereignty society or the foundational traditional laws and customs from which it is alleged Worimi's native title rights and interests derive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1059">It says that there is no admissible evidence of the continued observance (substantially uninterrupted) of those laws and customs to the present day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1060">It submits that the simple description of land and people as Worimi people and "traditional Worimi country" is not evidence of the continued association with an identified area of land by an identified Aboriginal society or group from before the acquisition of sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1061">In any event, the Land Council says that Worimi's evidence itself amply demonstrates a clear break in the continuity of the acknowledgement and observance of the very traditional laws and customs that he alleges are associated with the area said to be a sacred women's site and including Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1062">181 Worimi says that the laws and customs concerning the Land and Kingsley Beach were passed to him from his father and his father's mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1063">Let it be assumed that that information has been passed down from individual to individual (from the father to the eldest son) since pre-sovereignty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1064">The evidence from Worimi and the Land Council witnesses, including members of Worimi's family who would be part of the Garuahgal clan that he says is the relevant society, is to the effect that any laws and customs with respect to the birth of children ceased to be observed until Worimi recently sought to reinvigorate them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1065">182 The evidence is that there is no Maiaangal birthing site on or near the Land or a birthing site for Worimi women generally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1066">Acceptance of this evidence does not require, as Worimi submits, a full account of past and present birthing customs of Maiaangal or Worimi women ( Jango at [84]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1067">183 The evidence from the Land Council witnesses, and from Worimi himself, establishes that, whether or not there was once a women's site on or near the Land, the laws and customs in relation to such a site have not continued to be observed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1068">The lack of continuity in the laws acknowledged and customs observed in connection with Lot 576 is sufficient to establish a prima facie case of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1069">184 It follows from Yorta Yorta at [51]---[56] that native title, if it existed pre-sovereignty, ceases to exist for the purposes of the Act if the society, being the Worimi people, the Maiaangal clan or the Garuahgal clan, ceased to acknowledge and observe the laws and customs that Worimi describes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1070">The rights and interests to which those laws and customs give rise are not possessed under traditional laws acknowledged and traditional customs observed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1071">They ceased to exist and the later adoption of the laws and customs does not give rise to rights and interests rooted in pre-sovereignty traditional law and custom.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1072">185 The changes in Worimi's description of the persons who, he says, observe or observed the traditional laws and customs in respect of the Land have not assisted in the analysis of the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1073">As set out in Worimi 2007 and Worimi 2006 , he has changed the identification of the persons said to be relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1074">As to the identification of family members in the claim group, Worimi has included, variously apart from himself, his wife and children, all his sisters and their daughters and his mother.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1075">He was not consistent in his evidence, asserting that he was bringing the claim on behalf of the Garuahgal women, his family and all Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1076">Irrespective of the group said to hold native title over the Land, the requirements of s 223 of the Act are not satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1077">While Worimi was not required to establish native title in accordance with s 223 of the Act in order to resist the Land Council's application, given the time available to Worimi since these proceedings were commenced, he has had ample opportunity to formulate his contentions with reference to s 223 of the Act in order to cast sufficient doubt on the Land Council's case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1078">186 The evidence is that the observance of the traditional laws and customs ceased so far as a women's site on the Land is concerned.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1079">The evidence is not of adaptation of traditional laws and customs but of substantial interruption, amounting to cessation, of observance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1080">187 Worimi submits that the evidence of the seven Land Council witnesses is insufficient and that anthropological evidence is necessary or, at least, evidence from many other Worimi witnesses before the evidence from those seven witnesses can be accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1081">This ignores the fact that the decision of the Land Council to dispose of the Land was approved at a meeting held in accordance with the NSW Act and has been the subject of a number of Land Council meetings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1082">The application has been notified as required and it is not in dispute that Worimi's applications are known to other Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1083">Despite this, there has been no other person who has sought to oppose the application in the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1084">188 Much has been made in submissions of which party is better able to call evidence and the effect on the proof of a negative proposition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1085">On one hand, the Land Council has not called evidence from all the Worimi people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1086">It has called seven witnesses, some of whom have studied Worimi history and have knowledge of Worimi laws and customs and others from Worimi's family.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1087">It has, as I have said, been authorised to bring this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1088">Worimi asserts that (at least) his family, as part of the Garuahgal clan, has native title rights and interests over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1089">It is Worimi who has the greater means to produce evidence from his family or from other Garuahgal or Worimi people to contradict the proposition of no native title.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1090">In particular, if Worimi asserts that Lot 576 and Kingsley Beach are a women's site of which he cannot have personal knowledge, the absence of any evidence of the laws and customs associated with that site from a woman supporting his assertion is telling.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1091">The only evidence in support of Worimi's claims was filed in respect of his claimant applications and was from Worimi's mother, who is Yorta Yorta, and from his wife, sister and daughters (Priscilla Dates changed her evidence in these proceedings), who say little more than that they take their information from Worimi and support his assertions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1092">The failure on Worimi's part to call corroborative evidence lessens the burden of proof on the Land Council to establish the negative proposition ( Apollo Shower Screens at 565).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1093">It does not increase the burden on the Land Council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1094">189 I am satisfied that there has not been the necessary connection with the Land and the observance of the asserted laws and customs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1095">This is not because of Worimi's temporary absence in Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1096">It is because, on the evidence, I am satisfied that there was no women's site on or near Lot 576 and that there was no use of a waterhole on or near Lot 576 associated with the birth of Worimi children.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1097">If there were such a site or such use, it has long since ceased to be used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1098">Worimi's attempt to revive such use in the case of his daughter and the birth of his grandson is insufficient to give rise to native title rights and interests in the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1099">190 The group or communal rights that form the basis of Worimi's case are in respect of the claimed women's sight on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1100">The characterisation of Worimi's asserted native title rights and interests has changed over time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1101">Worimi also claims rights in respect of his own observance of traditional hunting and gathering customs on the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1102">However, Worimi appears to assert that these rights are held by all Worimi people or at least by the Garuahgal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1103">There is no sufficient evidence that any such rights, whether individual, group or communal, are possessed under a normative system of traditional laws acknowledged and customs observed by Worimi people or by the Garuahgal clan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1104">Worimi's account of traditional hunting and gathering law and custom has been disputed by the Land Council's witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1105">191 To the extent that Worimi asserts individual rights over the Land, they seem to be based on his evidence that, as the eldest son, he was the recipient of the information and was made the custodian of the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1106">He does not suggest his custodianship is only for his own or, indeed, only for his immediate family's benefit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1107">The evidence does not establish that Worimi's individual rights are possessed under a body of normative rules, under the traditional laws acknowledged and the traditional customs observed by the Worimi people or even by the Garuahgal clan ( De Rose (No 2) at [31]-[44]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1108">As such, it is hard to see how his asserted rights regarding custodianship of the Land are individual native title rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1109">The same applies to his asserted group or communal rights said to be enjoyed by his immediate family, Garuahgal women or Worimi women generally in respect of any women's site on or near Lot 576 and to the rights said to be held by all Worimi people in respect of hunting and gathering activities on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1110">192 However, in the context of whether Worimi's evidence casts doubt on the assertion that there is no native title in respect of the Land, I have considered his claims to such individual rights, said to have been handed to him by his father in circumstances where, he says, he is the only person who has present knowledge of those rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1111">I have also, in that context, considered his asserted traditional hunting and gathering rights and his claim to group or communal rights to the extent that he says that there is a women's site on or near the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1112">In the case of group and communal rights, a claim by a group or community may succeed in establishing native title even though not all of the members of the group or community have acknowledged and observed traditional laws and customs, as long as the group or community as a whole has done so sufficiently ( De Rose (No 2) at [58]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1113">There must, however, be a link between the rights and interests in relation to the Land said to be possessed by the group or community and the traditional laws and customs that the group or community claims to have acknowledged and observed ( De Rose (No 2) at [60]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1114">193 As to Worimi's assertion of his own use and use by his family of the Land for traditional purposes, again I am satisfied that any such traditional use had ceased and has been recently revived by Worimi.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1115">Priscilla Dates confirms that she was not taken there as a child and was and is unaware of any connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1116">Ms Quinlan did not go there with her parents, who were also Worimi's parents and was and is unaware of any connection with the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1117">Ms Quinlan says that Worimi's father's mother, Ellen Dates, with whom she lived and whom Worimi attributes as the source of his knowledge of traditional law and custom, did not observe traditional law and custom at all and did not do so in connection with Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1118">Kelvin Dates' evidence supports that of Ms Quinlan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1119">I accept that Worimi has made some effort to revive such observation but there has been no such connection with the Land for at least two generations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1120">Even accepting that there were laws acknowledged and customs observed in connection with the Land pre-sovereignty, there was no continuity of that observance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1121">CONCLUSION 
 
194 The Land Council has presented sufficient evidence from which the absence of native title over Lot 576 may be inferred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1122">Worimi's evidence is insufficient to cast doubt on the Land Council's case that there is no native title over Lot 576.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1123">The Land Council is entitled to a determination that there is no native title over the Land.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1124">I certify that the preceding one hundred and ninety-four (194) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1125">Associate:

Dated: 18 December 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr M Wright 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Watson Mangioni Lawyers Pty Ltd 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr J Waters 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Crown Solicitor for the State of NSW 
 
 Counsel for the Third Respondent: Mr F Austin (Pro bono) and Ms T Jowett (Pro bono) 

 Date of Hearing: 28-30 April 2008, 1-2 May 2008, 25-26 June 2008 
 
 Date of Final Submissions: 15 August 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 December 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1929.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>