<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hamilton v Diprose [2008] FCA 1072 (21 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1072.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">agreement for payment of legal costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application for directions under s 511 of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">claim by respondent that agreement should be set aside</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">power to enlarge proceeding to include determination of substantive rights</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">appropriate circumstances for exercise of such power</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This is an application under s 511 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) by the liquidator of Tasmanian Compliance Corporation Pty Ltd for directions as to the disposition of a sum of $60,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">When the matter came on before me on 20 June 2008 Mr Tree SC, who then appeared for the liquidator, advanced argument on the construction of the agreement of 20 March 2007 (the Agreement).</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">It seemed to me, however, that it was desirable to give notice to a person likely to be affected by any relief, and accordingly I directed that the application, an affidavit of Mr Hamilton filed on 30 May 2008 and a copy of the transcript of 20 June 2008 be served on Mr David John Diprose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Mr Diprose has appeared this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">He is not represented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Mr Buckley of counsel appeared for the liquidator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">2 Mr Diprose said that he wished to apply to the Court to have the Agreement set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">He alleged that the company and the other parties to the Agreement had breached it and that they "have set about to do a number of extraordinary damaging things, including, in my view, criminal defamation".</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">He said that there have been a "number of matters" which were breaches of the Agreement to such an extent that it was "null and void".</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The other parties to the Agreement are Knowledge Consulting Pty Ltd, Mr Glenn Richard Milliner and Mr John Charles White.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">3 Mr Buckley helpfully referred me to a recent decision of French J, Meadow Springs v Balanced Securities (2007) 25 ACLC 1 ,433.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">In that case French J at [48] pointed out that a direction given or a question determined under s 511 would protect the liquidator who acts in accordance with the direction or determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">His Honour thought it may be an open question whether it establishes a res judicata between the liquidator and any parties affected by it who are named as defendants in the application, but neither direction nor determination gives rise to a res judicata as between parties who may have competing interests affected by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">4 His Honour at [49] went on to note that there is sufficient flexibility in the procedures of the Court to enable proceedings begun as an application for directions under s 511 to be converted into proceedings for determination of substantive rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">(See also Australian Securities Commission v Melbourne Asset Management Nominees Pty Ltd (1994) 49 FCR 334 at 352.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">) 
 
5 However, although there is no doubt that such a power exists, I do not think it would be appropriate to exercise it in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The amount involved, $60,000, is, relatively speaking, not large in the context of costs which may be incurred in substantial proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Those proceedings would of necessity have to involve the joinder of the other parties to the agreement, and also there would be substantial delay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The nature of the allegations made by Mr Diprose rather suggest that the matters in dispute could be extensive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">6 I think in all the circumstances I will confine this hearing to the discrete question of construction raised by the liquidator in his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I will adjourn the hearing to 28 August 2008 at 10.15am.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">I will direct that any affidavit by Mr Diprose be filed and served by 15 August, and any affidavit in reply by the liquidator be filed and served by 22 August.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">I stress that any such affidavits are to be limited to the construction of the deed and such necessary facts arising from its surrounding circumstances, and should not deal with the grounds alleged by Mr Diprose for setting aside the Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Any action in that regard will be a matter for him to take action subsequently if he is so advised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Today's costs will be reserved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Associate:

Dated: 24 July 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: J A Buckley 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Toomey Maning &amp; Co 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: The respondent appeared in person 

 Date of Hearing: 21 July 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 July 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1072.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>