<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>AMI Australia Holdings Pty Ltd v Bade Medical Institute (Aust) Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1783 (26 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1783.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for adjournment of hearing dates</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">claimed medical condition not supported by evidence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">lateness of application for legal assistance</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 Presently before the Court is a Notice of Motion seeking the adjournment of a proceeding set down for hearing on 17, 18 and 19 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 The Applicant on the Motion is the Fourth Respondent in the principal proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Counsel for the First Applicant in the proceeding appeared at the hearing of the Motion and opposed the relief sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Counsel for the Third Respondent in the proceeding also appeared, but neither opposed nor supported the relief sought in the Motion .</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The order setting down the proceeding for hearing in December 2008 was made on 16 September 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">On that date the Applicant on the present Motion advised the Court of a medical condition that he maintained prejudiced his ability to meaningfully participate in any hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The dates for final hearing, however, were nevertheless selected with his concurrence and to accommodate his medical condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 On 14 November 2008 the present Applicant on the Motion foreshadowed that he would be seeking a vacation of the December 2008 dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Directions were then made for the filing of any Motion seeking such relief together with any such evidence that he would wish to rely upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">5 The Motion presently before the Court is that in fact filed on 30 September 2008, which seeks the following relief (without alteration):
 That a leave from all proceedings be granted for a period of 6 months to allow me to continue with cancer treatment, gain legal aid, find and brief legal counsel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">6 The Affidavit in support of the Motion was that sworn by the Applicant on the Motion on 19 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">It is understood that he seeks to establish by means of that Affidavit three propositions, namely:
 
(i) that his medical condition precludes him from meaningfully participating in the December 2008 hearing;
 
(ii) that he is unable to see a treating specialist at St Vincent's Hospital until 8 December 2008; and 
 
(iii) that he has an outstanding application for legal assistance and that the final hearing should not proceed until after that application is resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">7 The relief sought in the Motion is refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">But any further application he may wish to make after he has seen his specialist on 8 December 2008 may be made at the outset of the final hearing on 17 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">8 Considerable reservation was expressed during the hearing of the Motion as to the authenticity of the medical reports as annexed to the Affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Those reports were not on any recognisable letterhead and were expressed in terms not characteristic of a medical practitioner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">But there was no cross-examination of the Applicant and, in those circumstances, the reports were accepted as providing some evidence of the Applicant's medical condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">9 That medical evidence, however, fails to establish any reason to vacate the present hearing dates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">One joint medical report was provided by a " Consultant " and an " Associate Professor " who had operated upon the Applicant in Sweden.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The " Consultant " and " Associate Professor " were apparently medical practitioners practising in Uppsala in Sweden.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">But the joint medical report is dated 2005 and says nothing as to the Applicant's present medical condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">10 Also annexed to the Applicant's Affidavit was what was said to be notes from the Applicant's psychologist, Ms Tara Stern.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">No report was provided by that psychologist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The notes state in part that the Applicant presented with " issues " including " feeling overwhelmed " and " Anger at medical system, incompetence, corrupt institutions/business &amp; govt apathy ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">11 What purported to be notes from a Dr Dailey were also annexed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Those notes were dated 12 August 2008 and stated in relevant part (without alteration):
 I reviewed David again today for his metastic carcinoid tumour being treated with Sandostatin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">His biggest concern is that his anxiety now.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">He realises having problems coping and he is now willing to see one of the psychologist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">His general condition is fairly good.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">He has had minimal diarrhoea and now flushing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">He remains lethargic and tires easily and finds concentration some difficult.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">... 
That material, it is also considered, provides no real reason to adjourn the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">There is no evidence that his medical condition is such that he will not meaningfully be able to participate in the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">But, if a particular difficulty is experienced, it can be accommodated at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">12 The alternative basis upon which the application is being made is an outstanding request for legal assistance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">13 An application for legal aid was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">But the application which was annexed to the Affidavit remained undated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">It would appear to have been an application made after the dates for final hearing were set down in September 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">But, and whatever may have been the date upon which it was made, it was apparently that application which was refused on 15 October 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The letter from the Legal Aid Commission of New South Wales communicating that adverse decision stated in relevant part:
 Your application for legal aid has been carefully considered and has been refused under section 34(1) of the Legal Aid Commission Act 1979 because: The matter is not one for which aid is available under the Commission's policies and guidelines relating to Commonwealth administrative law matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">...</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">I enclose an application form for Pro Bono assistance which may be available from the Law Society of NSW.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">14 An appeal to the Legal Aid Review Committee was filed on 17 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Perhaps not surprisingly there is no further account as to the status of that appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">An " Application for Pro Bono Referral " was also filed on 17 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">15 Again, it is not considered that this alternative basis upon which the relief is sought in the Motion should prevail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The present proceeding was commenced by way of an Application filed on 14 December 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">A Statement of Claim was filed on 8 August 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Directions hearings were held in December 2007 and in April, June, August, September and November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">At some of those direction hearings the Applicant on the Motion attended; on other dates there was no attendance by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">16 Any application for legal assistance should have been made by the Applicant on the Motion at a far earlier date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">It is not considered that a party can fail to appear at directions hearings, delay seeking legal advice, and thereafter rely upon an outstanding application for legal aid or assistance as a reason to vacate dates -- especially dates set down with his concurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">17 The application for the vacation of the December 2008 hearing dates is thus refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">18 To the extent that the Applicant on the Motion asserts that his financial circumstances are such that he cannot afford to photocopy documents relevant to the final hearing, it is anticipated that that difficulty can be accommodated in a practical and sensible manner by those appearing for the Applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">All documents upon which the Applicants wish to rely have apparently already been provided to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">It is further hoped that copies of documents produced by a third party to the Applicants pursuant to a subpoena, and which may have some relevance to the issues to be resolved in December 2008, can also be provided to the Applicant on the Motion in a practical and sensible manner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">19 The Applicant on the Motion may make any such further application as he sees fit at the commencement of the final hearing on 17 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">If there is to be reliance upon further medical reports, it may be prudent for him to ensure that those medical practitioners upon whom he may wish to rely are available for cross-examination -- at least by means, perhaps, of telephone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">But such reservations as have been expressed in relation to the medical reports as presently filed are a matter for the Applicant on the Motion to address in such a manner as he sees fit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">20 Even short of again applying for the vacation of the December 2008 hearing dates, the Applicant on the Motion should feel free to make such applications as he sees fit during the course of the final hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">To the extent that any such difficulties as he may then experience can be accommodated, they will be accommodated in a manner consistent with the evidence then before the Court and the interests of the proper administration of justice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">ORDERS 
 
21 The orders of the Court are:
 
1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The Notice of Motion as filed on 30 September 2008 is dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The Applicant on the Motion , the Fourth Respondent in the principal proceeding, is to pay the costs of the First Applicant in the principal proceeding of and incidental to the hearing of the Motion .</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">There be no order as to costs as to the Third Respondent in the principal proceeding on the hearing of the Motion .</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">I certify that the preceding twenty-one (21) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Associate:

Dated: 26 November 2008

 Counsel for the First Applicant: Ms E Peden 
 
 Solicitor for the First Applicant: Bruce Stewart Dimarco 
 
 Counsel for the Third Respondent: Mr J Azzi 
 
 Solicitor for the Third Respondent: John B Hajje 
 
 The Fourth Respondent: The Fourth Respondent appeared in person 

 Date of Hearing: 26 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 26 November 2008 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1783.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>