<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIVK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 334 (13 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/334.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">judicial review</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">protection visa</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">allegation that migration agent provided false information and forged documents to refugee review tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">on review magistrate refused to determine allegation of fraud</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether necessary to give agent notice of allegation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">migration</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The appellant (who appears pro se) is a citizen of the People's Republic of China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">He came to Australia on a visitor's visa using a false Taiwanese passport.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Within seven weeks of his arrival he applied for a protection visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The basis of his claim for refugee status was that he was the target of Chinese officials for passing on confidential information about the government's treatment of Falun Gong adherents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">A delegate of the Minister refused the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That decision was affirmed by the Refugee Review Tribunal following a hearing which the appellant did not attend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The appellant sought review of the tribunal's decision in the Federal Magistrates Court on two grounds, one of which was that, due to the fraud of his migration agent, the appellant lost the opportunity to attend the tribunal hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">It seems the Magistrate refused to decide whether the migration agent acted fraudulently.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The principal question in issue is whether the Magistrate was entitled to decline to resolve that issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">2 The basis of the appellant's claim for refugee status may be stated shortly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The appellant was employed by the Fuqing Public Security Bureau (PSB) from June 1994 as a mechanical and electrical technician.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Some time after July 1999, a friend of the appellant was arrested for practising Falun Gong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The detainee's mother asked the appellant to protect her son through his contacts at the PSB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The appellant was unable to help his friend who subsequently died in detention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Thereafter the appellant decided to protest against what he saw as the cruel and inhuman treatment of Falun Gong practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">He collected internal PSB materials on Falun Gong and passed them on to his deceased friend's girlfriend, who was a practitioner of Falun Gong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">She was also the organiser of a propaganda group that distributed leaflets to the public.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">In March 2001, a member of the propaganda group was arrested and told authorities that someone within the PSB was leaking information to the group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The appellant believed he was being sought by the PSB and escaped to a remote village.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">He subsequently fled China and arrived in Australia on 4 May 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">3 To assist in the prosecution of his application for a protection visa, which was lodged on 15 June 2001, the appellant appointed a migration agent, Pricilla International Co Pty Ltd, to act on his behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The appellant authorised the Minister's department to send all correspondence relating to the application to the agent and to contact the agent if any additional steps were required to support his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">For the purposes of the application to the tribunal on 15 February 2002 an additional form was lodged purporting to appoint an individual, Priscilla Yu, as the appellant's authorised agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The authorisation form purports to be signed by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">He says, however, that his signature has been forged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">4 Correspondence from the tribunal was sent by registered post not only to the appellant but also to Ms Yu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">A letter sent to both on 10 December 2002 advised that the tribunal would hold a hearing to deal with the appellant's claim on 24 January 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The letter explained that the tribunal was unable to determine the case "on the papers" and therefore a hearing was necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">A "response to hearing" invitation form was attached to the letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">It invited the appellant to indicate whether he intended to appear at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">5 The letter sent to the appellant's address was returned to the tribunal as unclaimed mail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The migration agent returned the response to hearing form to the tribunal indicating that the appellant wished to attend the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The form was purportedly signed by the appellant but, again, he says his signature was forged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">6 The hearing before the tribunal took place on 24 January 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Neither the appellant nor his migration agent attended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Not surprisingly, the tribunal affirmed the delegate's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">7 The appellant applied to the Federal Magistrates Court to review the tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">One of the grounds upon which he challenged the lawfulness of the decision was that his failure to attend the hearing was a result of the fraudulent conduct of his migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">He filed two affidavits in support of his claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">There he deposed that he had engaged a migration agent, a Chinese man known to him only as Harry, to assist with the preparation of his visa application in June 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">He said that he contacted the agent from time to time to enquire about the progress of his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Each time he was told that the agent would be in touch if there was any news.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">According to the appellant, he last had contact with his agent some time in 2002 at which point he stopped making enquiries as he was granted permission to work and thus assumed he had been granted a visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">8 The appellant also deposed that he was unaware his application was before the tribunal, that there was a hearing on 24 January 2003 and that a decision had been handed down on 14 March 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">He said that he only became aware of those matters after he had been detained and taken to the Villawood Detention Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">9 As regards the correspondence sent to him by the tribunal both before and after the hearing, he said that he never received any.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">He explained that he had never resided at one of the addresses used by the tribunal (10 Sixth Ave, Campsie NSW 2194) and that he had already moved from the other address (319 Liverpool Rd, Ashfield NSW 2131) when it was used by the tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The tribunal sent a record of its decision to a post office box (PO Box 66, Beverly Hills NSW 2209) which the appellant shared with a friend.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">He said he did not receive that document.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">10 The tribunal obtained the addresses it used from the documents that were submitted to it purportedly on the appellant's behalf: the application for review, the agent authorisation form, a change of address form and the response to hearing form.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">As the appellant does not speak, read or understand English, it is apparent that those documents were prepared by someone else, almost certainly his migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Each document, with the exception of the change of address form, bears the stamp of Priscilla International.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Each document appears to be signed by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">However, he deposed that none of them were signed by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">He gave the same evidence about a s 417 letter that was sent to the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">11 In written submissions filed in the Federal Magistrates Court, the appellant contended that his agent knowingly provided the tribunal with incorrect information (ie erroneous or outdated mailing addresses and an indication that the appellant would attend the hearing) and signed documents on his behalf without his knowledge or authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">In effect, the appellant alleged that each document was a forgery and each signature was a counterfeit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">12 There were two hearings in the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The appellant gave evidence at each with the aid of an interpreter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">In some important respects what he said was inconsistent with the evidence in his affidavits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The first hearing was to deal with the respondents' motion to have the appellant's case dismissed as it was brought out of time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">The appellant, who was not represented, was invited to be cross-examined by counsel for the respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">During his cross-examination he claimed that a number of the forms submitted to the tribunal contained forged signatures.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">The appellant did, however, concede that the signature on the agent authorisation form was his.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">He also admitted that he had instructed his migration agent to make an application to the tribunal and that he was aware there was to be a hearing before the tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">He said that he did not attend the hearing as he did not receive the invitation letter from the tribunal or from his agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">The Magistrate said that there was sufficient doubt about whether the appellant had been notified of the tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Actual notification is necessary to trigger the running of the time limit under s 477 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Accordingly the Magistrate allowed the matter to proceed to a hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">13 At the hearing the appellant was represented by counsel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">He was called to give evidence to expand on what he said in his affidavits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">He was then cross-examined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">There he made concessions about his knowledge of the tribunal hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">Initially he denied his migration agent had told him of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Yet, when pressed, the appellant acknowledged that his agent had informed him about the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">He gave two reasons for his non-attendance: that his agent did not advise him to go and that his agent did not tell him the time or the date of the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">He explained that his agent had ceased communicating with him as he had not paid the agent's fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">14 The appellant's evidence about the forged signatures also conflicted with his affidavits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">He gave some answers consistent with his earlier claims that two documents --- the change of address form and the s 417 letter sent to the Minister --- bore his forged signature.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">He conceded, however, that the signature on the application for review form was his, only a few minutes after having denied that proposition while giving his evidence in chief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">He also conceded that he signed the response to hearing invitation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">If that form does bear his signature, it is likely, though not certain, that the contents of the document (which is in English) were explained to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">15 In view of what came out in cross-examination there are clearly doubts about the appellant's credibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Yet the case is very troubling on this aspect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">My reading of the transcript of both hearings leaves me with an uneasy feeling that the interpreters' translations of counsel's questions and the appellant's answers may have been incompetent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">On several occasions during cross-examination there was confusion on the part of both the interpreter and the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">The interpreted answers were at times unresponsive, incoherent and inexplicably inconsistent with other evidence given minutes before.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">There is a possibility that there was a departure from the standard appropriate for interpretation: Perera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 507 ; (1999) 92 FCR 6 , 23-24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Accordingly it was open to the Magistrate not to take the appellant's concessions at face value.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">16 In his closing submissions the appellant's counsel accepted that there were inconsistencies in the appellant's evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">He submitted that it was nevertheless open to the Magistrate to find that: the appellant was unaware of the time and place of the tribunal hearing as a result of the fraudulent conduct of his migration agent; the agent had forged the appellant's signature on various forms; and the agent knowingly included false information on a number forms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">Counsel submitted that, if made, these findings would satisfy the test for third party fraud articulated by French J in his dissenting judgment in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365 , 398-400.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">French J held that a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal was vitiated because the applicant was denied the opportunity to appear before the tribunal due to the fraudulent conduct of his migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">It is plain that counsel was reserving this point for an appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">17 The Magistrate dismissed the application on the basis that the appellant had failed to make out any ground of jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The fraud claim was dealt with in a very cursory manner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">All the Magistrate said (at [36]) was that:
 
 "The applicant has given evidence that he was not aware of the hearing due to the actions of his migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">The applicant did not serve any of the documents in this matter on the migration agent concerned and the agent has therefore not appeared or made any submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">In the circumstances I am not prepared to make any finding of fraud.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">" 
 

18 Although not conceded by the Minister, I take this passage to mean that the Magistrate declined to deal with the claimed fraud of the migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">The reason for declining to deal with the issue was that the migration agent had not been put on notice of the allegations made against him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">19 The Magistrate's decision is challenged on two grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">The first is that: "The judge failed to consider the misconduct of [the appellant's] previous migration agent, which has left [him] no opportunity to appear before [the] RRT member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">" The second ground of appeal is that: "The whole processing of [the appellant's] application has not been done fairly..." The appellant identified no acts of unfairness in support of the second ground so it can be put to one side.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">20 As to the first ground, which is, in substance, the only issue that arises for consideration on this appeal, reference must be made to SZFDE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 35 ; (2007) 237 ALR 64 ( SZFDE ), where the High Court upheld French J's dissenting judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">The High Court made clear that, even in circumstances where the tribunal acts blamelessly, it may nevertheless fall into jurisdictional error if its decision is affected by the fraud of a third party such as an applicant's migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The High Court said (at 77) that when a migration agent's fraudulent conduct stultifies the critically important natural justice provisions in Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Act, the decision of the tribunal is to be regarded in law as no decision at all.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">21 If the Magistrate had made findings of fact on the appellant's case that his agent had acted fraudulently, it would be possible to resolve this appeal by the application of the principles laid down by the High Court to the facts as found.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">But because there are no findings of fact it is necessary to determine whether the Magistrate erred by refusing to make findings in the absence of notice to the agent and, if he did, send the case back.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">22 In the absence of a detailed explanation it is difficult to know what legal justification the Magistrate had in mind in declining to deal with the case raised by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">What the Magistrate said (at [36]) was that, without the migration agent being put on notice about the allegations of fraud and being given an opportunity to tell his side of the story, it was improper to make an adverse finding of fact against him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">There is a rule (an aspect of procedural fairness) that, subject to statutory exceptions, an administrative decision-maker must provide an opportunity for a person to be heard before a decision is made that destroys, defeats or prejudices that person's rights, interests or legitimate expectations: see eg Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 , 584; Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 , 653.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Accordingly, findings adverse to the interests of a person will not be made without first providing the person an opportunity to be heard: Mahon v Air New Zealand Ltd [1984] AC 808 , 820-821; National Companies and Securities Commission v News Corporation Ltd [1984] HCA 29 ; (1984) 156 CLR 296 , 315, 324; Annetts v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 , 599-601.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">A person's reputation is protected by the rule: Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 , 577-578.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">23 The rules of procedural fairness applicable in administrative tribunals apply, usually equally, but sometimes with greater force, in curial proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">But the procedures in the two fora are not entirely the same and the rules must be modified to take account of the differences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">One difference is that curial proceedings are adversarial whereas administrative proceedings usually are not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">Being adversarial, in curial proceedings it is the parties, not the decision-maker, that define the issues to be contested, select the witnesses they intend to call, choose the evidence they wish to lead and to which they intend to object, and decide which arguments will be pursued and which will be abandoned: Jones v National Coal Board [1957] 2 QB 55, 63-64; Ratten v R [1974] HCA 35 ; (1974) 131 CLR 510 , 517; Crampton v R [2000] HCA 66 ; (2000) 206 CLR 161 , 173; Dhanhoa v R [2003] HCA 40 ; (2003) 217 CLR 1 , 9; Berowra Holdings Pty Ltd v Gordon [2000] HCA 32 ; (2006) 225 CLR 364 , 393.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">24 It is common for parties locked in adversarial litigation to make all sorts of allegations to advance their own cause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">If the opposite party is criticised he can be called to rebut the criticism.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">If a third party is criticised, he can be called by one of the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">In both circumstances the individual who has been criticised will have the opportunity to rebut the criticism.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">25 But it is often the case that a third party is criticised and not called as a witness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">The reason he is not called, assuming him to be available to give evidence, is that the party who may be adversely affected if the criticism is accepted has made a decision not to call that person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">That is the party's right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">In some cases the exercise of that right may lead to an adverse inference being drawn against that party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">However that may be, there is no rule to the effect that the criticised person must be given notice that he is to be attacked in evidence to be given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">There are good reasons why there is no such rule.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">As I have explained, it follows from the adversarial nature of our trial system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">In any event, even if given notice there is usually nothing the third party can do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">He cannot demand that he be permitted to give evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">If that were the position, trials would become unmanageable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">In limited circumstances a judge may allow a non-party to be heard: see eg r 2.13 of the Federal Court (Corporations) Rules 2000 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">But the circumstances in which leave will be granted are rare.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">26 In my view, therefore, there was no justification for the Magistrate to refuse to decide whether the migration agent had acted fraudulently on account of lack of notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">His failure amounts to an appealable error of law: Pettitt v Dunkley [1971] 1 NSWLR 376, 382, 388; QBE Insurance Ltd v Switzerland Insurance Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd [1996] HCA 1 ; (1996) 134 ALR 433 , 437; 260 Oxford Street Pty Ltd v Premetis [2006] NSWCA 96 [121]-[123].</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">27 I should in any event say that, even if the Magistrate could rightly decline to deal with the issue, he could hardly do so (as occurred here) without warning the appellant that he would lose his case because he had not given notice to the agent about the fraud allegation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">I say this on the assumption (which is not likely to be correct) that the onus of giving notice to the third party lay with the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">In reality, of course, the absence of the third party in a case such as this is the respondent's problem, and if any party should be penalised for not having given notice it should have been the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">28 Still, despite the error, this appeal may yet fail if, assuming the facts to be as the appellant says they were, he would, in any event, fail to establish jurisdictional error on the part of the tribunal: Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141 , 145.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">29 The issue, then, is whether the facts asserted by the appellant, if true, could constitute fraud on the tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">In SZFDE , a family applying for protection visas claimed that the decision of the tribunal refusing their applications was affected by the fraud of their migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">The agent had advised the family not to attend the hearing before the tribunal because he claimed the tribunal was not accepting any visa applications at the time and would therefore dismiss their applications.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">At the time the agent gave that advice his practising certificate as a lawyer and his registration as a migration agent had been cancelled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">The Magistrate found that the agent acted fraudulently for personal gain, extracted money under false pretences and dissuaded the applicants from attending the hearing by "fraudulent behaviour".</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">He therefore set aside the tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">30 On appeal to the Full Federal Court, the finding that the agent acted fraudulently was not challenged: SZFDE 154 FCR at 383.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">Nonetheless, the Full Court allowed the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">According to the majority the tribunal complied with the requirement to send the family a s 425 invitation to attend a hearing, and any fraudulent conduct by the migration agent did not therefore corrupt the tribunal's decision-making process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">French J disagreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">He would have dismissed the appeal on the basis that the fraud of the agent, which he characterised as "dishonest conduct" and "fraudulent advice", vitiated the tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">He said (at 399):
 
 "[W]here a person's participation in a decision-making process is affected by the material dishonesty of another which conveys a false impression to the decision-maker, then that dishonesty may be said to have distorted or vitiated the approach and to have affected the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Whether it has will depend upon a consideration of the circumstances of the particular case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">" 
 

31 The High Court, in allowing the appeal, discussed the meaning of fraud in different fields of law and concluded ( SZFDE 237 ALR at 68-70) that to amount to fraud, in the field of public law, the impropriety may not have to be as serious as in other civil suits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">The Court said (at 73) that where fraud by a migration agent subverts a s 425 invitation from the tribunal to attend a hearing, it "is a matter of the first magnitude" because of the central importance of the natural justice hearing rule in the legislative scheme laid out in Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">32 The allegedly fraudulent conduct of the migration agent in the present case is different from that in SZFDE .</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Here, the appellant does not say that the agent told him anything fraudulently false.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">Nor, as in SZFDE, is there any reason to explain why the agent may have acted fraudulently, for example out of self-protection to avoid the discovery that he was acting without a licence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">33 Nevertheless, there are many ways in which fraud may be manifested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">As Lord Macnaghten said in Reddaway v Banham [1896] AC 199 , 221, in a frequently cited speech, "fraud is infinite in variety".</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">In my opinion there can be little doubt that, if the appellant's claims be accepted, the migration agent was fraudulent in the relevant sense in his dealings with the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">The principal allegations are that his agent: falsely indicated in the response to hearing form that the appellant would attend the hearing when the agent knew that could not occur; and signed documents on the appellant's behalf without his knowledge, consent or authority and then forged his signature.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">34 As to false information, it will be fraudulent if it is made by a person who does not believe in its truth or is recklessly indifferent to its truth: Commercial Banking Company of Sydney Ltd v R H Brown &amp; Co [1972] HCA 24 ; (1972) 126 CLR 337 , 343.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">If the appellant's evidence is accepted, the only findings that are open are that the agent was deliberately fraudulent or, at the least, recklessly indifferent as to what he told the tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">The agent's conduct is particularly grievous because it is likely he knew that the appellant's non-attendance would be fatal to his application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">35 As to the forged signatures, it is not unusual for courts to treat a forgery as a fraud.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">In this case the appellant says the agent's dishonesty denied the appellant the opportunity to appear at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">It also conveyed to the tribunal the impression that the appellant was unwilling to attend, a fact upon which the tribunal placed great significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">36 To repeat, if the Magistrate found all the facts in the appellant's favour he would find that the jurisdiction of the tribunal had not been exercised and thus grant orders in the nature of certiorari to quash the tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">37 For these reasons I would allow the appeal, set aside the orders of the Magistrate and remit the matter to the Federal Magistrates Court for rehearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">I certify that the preceding thirty-seven (37) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Finkelstein.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">Associate:

Dated: 13 March 2008

 Counsel for the Appellant: The appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: A Mitchelmore 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 29 October 2007; 31 October 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 March 2008 
 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/334.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>