<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Karsten v Federal Republic of Germany [2008] FCA 331 (14 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/331.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">extradition act 1988 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">extradition offence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">extraditable person</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether a warrant is "in force"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">parity of sentencing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">no reason to go behind the face of the warrant and extradition request</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">extraditable person</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">qualifying extradition offence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether magistrate informed of consent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">abuse of process</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">extradition</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The present proceedings were first commenced by the Applicant by way of an Application filed on 17 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">On 7 November 2007 there was filed a Further Amended Application .</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The Further Amended Application seeks to challenge a notice issued under s 16 of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) on 24 October 2006 and a determination that the Applicant be surrendered pursuant to s 22 of that Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The Applicant contends that for the purposes of the Act that: 
 
(i) he is not an " extraditable person " within ss 6 and 16 ; 
 
(ii) the offence in respect of which extradition is sought is not an " extradition offence " within ss 5 and 16 ; and 
 
(iii) he is not an " eligible person " within s 22.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">These contentions, if made out, are said to constitute jurisdictional error on the part of the Respondent Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">3 On 19 February 2008 a Further Amended Notice of Motion was filed on behalf of the Respondent Minister seeking the dismissal of the Further Amended Application .</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">It is that Motion which is presently before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 It is considered that each of the Applicant's contentions should be rejected and that the orders as sought in the Respondent Minister's Motion should be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">THE FACTS: AN OVERVIEW 
 
5 Mr Christoph Karsten was born in January 1966 in Berlin and is a German national.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">6 A warrant of arrest for Mr Karsten dated 16 September 2003 was issued by the Hannover District Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The warrant recited that in late 1997 or early 1998 the Applicant agreed with a Mr Michael Schmeer to find someone who would be prepared to murder their former wives.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The warrant further recited that both the Applicant and Mr Schmeer were both divorced at the time and were unable to resolve problems relating to alimony and child visitation rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The warrant orders that the Applicant was to be remanded in custody on the ground that he was " strongly suspected of attempted incitement to murder ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">7 On 24 October 2006 the then Minister for Justice and Customs issued a notice under s 16(1) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) stating that an extradition request had been received from the Federal Republic of Germany.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">That notice identified the " extradition offence " as being:
 
 Attempted incitement to commit murder, contrary to sections 211 and 30 of the German Criminal Code .</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">

On 6 December 2006 a warrant for arrest was issued under s 12(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">8 A warrant under s 18(2) was thereafter issued on 20 December 2006 by Magistrate Madden, a magistrate of the Australian Capital Territory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">On the same day a letter was forwarded by the Magistrate to the then Attorney-General (the Honourable Phillip Ruddock) identifying the Applicant and stating:
 
As required by s 18(2)(b)(ii) of the Extradition Act 1988 I advise that on 20 December 2006 the abovenamed consented to being surrendered to the Federal Republic of Germany in relation to the following offence:
 
1. attempted incitement to commit murder contrary to sections 211 and 30 of the German Criminal Code (1 count).</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">I enclose a copy of the warrant under subsection 18(2)(b)(i) that I signed today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">9 On 5 July 2007 the Applicant was advised that the Minister had determined under s 22 that the Applicant was to be surrendered to Germany and that a warrant had been issued for his surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">THE EXTRADITION ACT 1988 (CTH) 
 
10 The Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) sets forth a four stage process for the extradition of a person from Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">These four stages have been summarised as follows by the Full Court in Harris v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 386 at 389:
 
 The Act contemplates four stages in extradition proceedings as follows: (1) Commencement; (2) Remand; (3) Determination by a magistrate of eligibility for surrender; (4) Executive determination that the person is to be surrendered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In summary form, the scheme is as follows: The commencement of proceedings is by the issue of a provisional warrant under s 12(1) or by the giving of a notice under s 16(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Once arrested, the person is required by s 15 to be taken before a magistrate and remanded in custody or on bail for such period as may be necessary for eligibility proceedings to be taken under s 19.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Where a person is on remand under s 15 and the Attorney-General has given a notice under s 16(1), provision is made under s 19 for a magistrate to conduct proceedings to determine whether the person is eligible for surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">If eligibility is so determined by the magistrate, provision is made by s 22 for the Attorney-General to decide whether the person is to be surrendered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">

This approach has subsequently been endorsed by Gleeson CJ in Vasiljkovic v Commonwealth [2006] HCA 40 at [29] , [2006] HCA 40 ; 227 CLR 614 and by Gummow J in Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 , 185 CLR 528 at 547.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">It has most recently been endorsed by a Full Court of this Court in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 at [9] per Jacobson, Bennett and Buchanan JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">11 The present proceedings seek to focus attention upon the decision to issue a notice pursuant to s 16 and the determination pursuant to s 22.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">Section 16(1) and (2) provide as follows: 
 
(1) Where the Attorney-General receives an extradition request from an extradition country in relation to a person, the Attorney-General may, in his or her discretion, by notice in writing in the statutory form expressed to be directed to any magistrate, state that the request has been received.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">(2) The Attorney-General shall not give the notice: 
 
(a) unless the Attorney-General is of the opinion: 
 
 
 (i) that the person is an extraditable person in relation to the extradition country; and 
 (ii) that, if the conduct of the person constituting the extradition offence, or any of the extradition offences, for which surrender of the person is sought, or equivalent conduct, had taken place in Australia at the time at which the extradition request was received, the conduct or the equivalent conduct would have constituted an extradition offence in relation to Australia; or 
 

(b) if the Attorney-General is of the opinion that there is an extradition objection in relation to the extradition offence, or all of the extradition offences, for which surrender of the person is sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">12 For present purposes it is relevant to note that the terms " extradition offence " and " extraditable person " are both further defined by ss 5 and 6 respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Section 5 defines the term " extradition offence ":
 
 "extradition offence" means: 
 (a) in relation to a country other than Australia--an offence against a law of the country: 
 
 
 (i) for which the maximum penalty is death or imprisonment, or other deprivation of liberty, for a period of not less than 12 months; or 
 (ii) if the offence does not carry a penalty under the law of the country--the conduct constituting which is, under an extradition treaty in relation to the country, required to be treated as an offence for which the surrender of persons is permitted by the country and Australia; or 
 
 
 (b) in relation to Australia or a part of Australia--an offence against a law of Australia, or a law in force in the part of Australia, for which the maximum penalty is death or imprisonment, or other deprivation of liberty, for a period of not less than 12 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">

Section 6 defines an " extraditable person " as follows:
 
 Where: 
 (a) either: 
 (i) a warrant is or warrants are in force for the arrest of a person in relation to an offence or offences against the law of a country that the person is accused of having committed either before or after the commencement of this Act; or 
 (ii) a person has been convicted of an offence or offences against the law of a country either before or after the commencement of this Act and: 
 
 
 (A) there is an intention to impose a sentence on the person as a consequence of the conviction; or 
 (B) the whole or a part of a sentence imposed on the person as a consequence of the conviction remains to be served; 
 
 
 (b) the offence or any of the offences is an extradition offence in relation to the country; and 
 (c) the person is believed to be outside the country; 
 the person is, for the purposes of this Act, an extraditable person in relation to the country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">

13 Section 22 does not operate by reference to whether a person is an " extraditable person " or a person who has committed an " extradition offence ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Section 22 uses different terminology, namely that of an " eligible person " and a " qualifying extradition offence .</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">" Those latter two phrases are defined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Section 22(1) and (2) thus provide as follows: 
 
 (1) In this section: 
 "eligible person" means a person who has been committed to prison: 
 (a) by order of a magistrate made under section 18; or 
 (b) by order of a magistrate made under subsection 19(9) or required to be made under subparagraph 21(2)(b)(ii) (including by virtue of an appeal referred to in section 21), being an order in relation to which no proceedings under section 21 are being conducted or available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">"qualifying extradition offence", in relation to an eligible person, means any extradition offence: 
 (a) if paragraph (a) of the definition of eligible person applies--in relation to which the person consented in accordance with section 18; or 
 (b) if paragraph (b) of the definition of eligible person applies--in relation to which the magistrate referred to in that paragraph or the court that conducted final proceedings under section 21, as the case requires, determined that the person was eligible for surrender within the meaning of subsection 19(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">(2) The Attorney-General shall, as soon as is reasonably practicable, having regard to the circumstances, after a person becomes an eligible person, determine whether the person is to be surrendered in relation to a qualifying extradition offence or qualifying extradition offences.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">

14 Section 16(2)(a), it will be noted, confers power by reference to whether the Attorney-General forms an " opinion "; and s 22(3) refers to the Attorney-General being " satisfied " of the matters there specified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">On behalf of the Respondent Minister, reference was made to the confined ambit of judicial review available where powers are so conferred: Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Gibbs J there observed at 118---19: 
 
 It is not uncommon for statutes to provide that a board or other authority shall or may take certain action if it is satisfied of the existence of certain matters specified in the statute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Whether the decision of the authority under such a statute can be effectively reviewed by the courts will often largely depend on the nature of the matters of which the authority is required to be satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">In such cases the authority will be left with a very wide discretion which cannot be effectively reviewed by the courts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">

15 In the present extradition process, an issue which assumes significance was the making of an order under s 18.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That section provides as follows:
 
 Consent to surrender 
 (1) Where: 
 (a) a person is on remand under section 15; and 
 (b) the Attorney-General has given a notice under subsection 16(1) in relation to the person; 
 the person may inform a magistrate that the person consents to being surrendered to the extradition country concerned in relation to the extradition offence, or all of the extradition offences, for which surrender of the person is sought by that country.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">(2) Where the person informs the magistrate that he or she so consents, the magistrate shall, unless the magistrate has reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily: 
 (a) advise the person that the effect of so consenting will be that: 
 
 
 (i) the person will be committed to prison without any proceedings being conducted under section 19 to determine whether the person is eligible for surrender in relation to any extradition offence; and 
 (ii) the person will, if the Attorney-General issues a surrender warrant or a temporary surrender warrant, be surrendered to the extradition country; and 
 
 
 (b) if, after the person has been advised as mentioned in paragraph (a), the person again consents to being surrendered: 
 
 
 (i) by warrant in the statutory form, order that the person be committed to prison to await surrender under a surrender warrant or temporary surrender warrant or release pursuant to an order under subsection 22(5); and 
 (ii) advise the Attorney-General in writing of the offence or the offences in respect of which the person has so consented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">
 
 AN EXTRADITABLE PERSON?</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">
 
16 It is difficult to conclude that the Applicant does not fall within the terms of s 6(a)(i) of the Extradition Act , namely a person in respect of whom there is " a warrant ... in force ... in relation to an offence ... against the law " of Germany.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">17 The warrant is that dated 16 September 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The Applicant by his Further Amended Application seeks to place emphasis, not so much upon whether the warrant was issued, but rather upon a contention as to whether the warrant was " in force ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">That contention is rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">18 The warrant as issued does not on its face disclose any limitation as to the period of time during which it is to operate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The manner of operation of a warrant issued under a foreign law, including any limitation as to the period of time during which it is to operate, is a question of fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">As contended by the Respondent Minister, the existence of the warrant and the absence of any limitation upon its face provided a sound basis upon which the Respondent Minister could lawfully form an " opinion " for the purposes of s 16(2): cf Buck v Bavone .</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Moreover, the request for extradition, being a document also before the Minister when giving the notice, also proceeds upon the assumption that the warrant issued in September 2003 remained in force when the request was being made in April 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">19 The approach urged upon the Court by Mr Karsten, namely an invitation to go behind the face of both the request and (more importantly) the warrant itself is an invitation which should be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Section 16(2) , framed as it is in terms of an " opinion ", should not be construed as requiring the Attorney-General or the Minister to become an expert in foreign law and construed in a manner which has the potential to frustrate the discharge by Australia of its obligations under extradition treaties: Tervonen v Minister for Justice &amp; Customs (No 2) [2007] FCA 1684 , 98 ALD 589.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Rares J there observed:
 
 [38] In Director of Public Prosecutions (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 at 540 Brennan CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ left open the meaning to be attributed to the word 'accused' in s 6(a)(i) of the Act, noting:
 It is sufficient to say that, in considering whether a person is an extraditable person under s 6(a)(i) of the Act, it is necessary to bear in mind the statutory object of enabling Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties with countries that adopt a variety of criminal procedures different from our own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">[39] The Attorney-General cannot be expected to be an expert in foreign law: Williams v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCAFC 33 ; 157 FCR 286 at 298 [49] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Minds may differ as to the proper construction of s 6(a)(i) and whether a particular warrant relied on by an extradition country falls within it (as the decision of the Full Court, which the High Court reversed in Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 , illustrates).</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">For this reason s 16(2)(a)(i) is framed so that the Attorney-General must form the opinion that the person is an extraditable person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">

 His Honour continued:
 
 [40] Having regard to the terms of the warrants and other material before him, I am of opinion that it was open to Senator Ellison to form the opinion that they met the criterion in s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Each warrant asserted that there was probable cause for suspecting that Mr Tervonen had committed an offence and that the Court which issued the warrant considered he ought be arrested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">...
 [42] Each warrant, on its face, was termed a 'warrant'.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">It was issued by a Finnish court for the arrest of Mr Tervonen who was stated to have been suspected on probable cause of having committed an offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The Minister could reasonably form the opinion that each document was a warrant, issued by a Finnish Court, in force, for the arrest of Mr Tervonen in relation to an offence against the law of Finland that he was accused of having committed within the meaning of s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">While other persons may not have formed the same view, having regard to the significant differences between the laws of other countries and Australia, to which Mason CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ referred to in Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 at 540, I am of opinion that it was open to Senator Ellison to form the view that each of the warrants was one which met the description in s 6(a)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">

An appeal from this decision has been allowed in part, although it was not necessary for the Full Court to make any comment in relation to the above observations of the learned trial judge: Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">See also Cabal v United Mexican States (No 3) [2000] FCA 1204 at [149] and [153], [2000] FCA 1204 ; 186 ALR 188 per French J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">20 The statutory expression " in force " is to be construed as requiring consideration simply to be given to " whether a person had been accused of a criminal offence and whether that accusation had led to the initiation of criminal proceedings ": Bertran v Vanstone [2000] FCA 359 at [55] , [2000] FCA 359 ; 173 ALR 63.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">21 For the purposes of the Motion, any challenge to the manner in which the Minister exercised the power conferred by s 16(2) on this basis has no reasonable prospects of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">22 Moreover, such further evidence as is now before the Court on the present Motion seems to amply support a finding that the warrant remains in force and that there is no reason to question that conclusion, even now.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Thus, an " Opinion " dated 16 April 2007, as subsequently provided under the signature of the Senior Chief Public Prosecutor for the Hannover Department of Public Prosecutions, states in part as follows: 
 
 ...The detention order by the Regional Court of Hannover dated September 16, 2003 was generated in the manner provided by law and fulfils the rules of the StPO [German Code of Criminal Procedure] under formal aspects as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The allegation of the prosecuted person that the detention order had expired in December 2005 is not true.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">According to StPO, an order for detention awaiting trial shall only become invalid, when it is lifted by a court... 

That Opinion stands in contrast to an affidavit filed in proceedings in the Australian Capital Territory by Mr Karsten, being an annexure to an Affidavit filed in the present proceedings in this Court, that asserts:
 
 ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">The warrant provided with the extradition request expired in December 2005 according to my sources ... 

No further details were provided nor were the " sources " identified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">For present purposes, it is considered that no conclusion is open other than that the warrant remains " in force ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Further written submissions filed on 5 March 2008 by Mr Karsten seek to annex further materials.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">Some of these materials are in German and have not been translated into English.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">To the extent that the Court has been able to consider those materials, the conclusion remains the same.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">23 Notwithstanding such consideration as has been given to materials that were not before the Minister when he reached his " opinion " for the purposes of s 16 , it must be recalled that the inquiry should be directed to a review of those materials that were before the Minister, being the basis upon which he formed his " opinion ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Confined to those materials, the Minister had a sound basis upon which he could issue the notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">24 Any deferral of the hearing of the present Motion to permit the Applicant a yet further opportunity to support his contention is not considered warranted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">The Applicant has made numerous references in the past to a desire to translate documents from German to English to advance his case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">It is, however, considered that he has had ample opportunity to file such evidence as he considers relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The opportunity in fact extended to Mr Karsten to file further materials questioning whether or not the warrant remains " in force ", or any other matter, has largely been an opportunity extended to an unrepresented party to determine whether those further materials may have disclosed some error not otherwise apparent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Given that the focus of any review of the decision of the Minister to issue the notice in October 2006 must be a scrutiny of the materials then before the Minister, being the materials upon which he formed his " opinion ", any further pursuit of this factual matter is considered neither relevant nor warranted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">AN EXTRADITION OFFENCE: "NOT LESS THAN 12 MONTHS"?</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 
25 The Applicant further seeks to focus attention upon the requirement that an " extradition offence " is relevantly an offence for which the maximum penalty was " imprisonment, or other deprivation of liberty, for a period of not less than 12 months ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The Applicant's contention is that the Respondent Minister " could not be satisfied that the statutory requirement was satisfied ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Section 16 , it should be noted, employs the language of an " opinion " being formed that the conduct of a person constitutes an " extradition offence ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">26 Again, it is difficult to see how the Applicant's contention can be sustained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">The Warrant of Arrest issued in September 2003 states in part as follows: 
 
 The actions of the accused constitute the criminal offence of attempted incitement to murder under Paras.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">211, 30 Section 1 , 49 Section 1 of the German Criminal Code .</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">The wording of the above provisions reads as follows, insofar as it is relevant in this case:
 Para.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">2.11 Section 1 
 The murderer shall be sentenced to life imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">...
 Para.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">30 Section 1 Sentence 1 and 2 
 
 
 Whoever attempts to induce or incite another to commit a serious criminal offence shall be punished according to the provisions governing an attempt to commit a serious criminal offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">However, the punishment shall be mitigated pursuant to Para.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">49 Section 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">
 
 
 Para.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">49 Section 1 No.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">1 
 
 
 It mitigation is prescribed or permitted under this provision, then the following shall apply to such mitigation: 
 
 
 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">Imprisonment for a term of not less than three years shall be substituted for life imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">
 
 
 
 Proceedings are not subject to a statute of limitations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">

Given the terms of the warrant, the conclusion may readily be reached that the offence for which the warrant against the Applicant was issued was an offence for which the maximum penalty was " imprisonment, or other deprivation of liberty, for a period of not less than 12 months " within the meaning of the definition of an " extradition offence " in s 5 of the Extradition Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">The request for extradition dated 21 April 2006 also stated that:
 
 ... the minimum punishment provided by law shall, in the case at hand, amount to three years of imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">The maximum imprisonment is fifteen years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">

27 As at the date when the s 16 notice was given, the material then available provided a sound basis for the requisite " opinion " being formed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">A discrete submission advanced on behalf of the Respondent Minister again focused attention upon the confined ambit of such judicial review as is available: Buck v Bavone .</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">Section 16(2)(a)(ii) -- as with s 16(2)(a)(i) -- again vests the decision-making function in the Attorney (or the Minister) if he is " of the opinion " that the person involved has committed an " extradition offence .</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">" That submission is again accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">28 A contrary conclusion advanced by Mr Karsten was based upon what was said to be a discrepancy between what the German Criminal Code may have provided in terms, and the sentences in fact imposed upon others involved in the events giving rise to the charges against him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">That " parity of sentencing " as urged by Mr Karsten dictated a different conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">It is considered that the " opinion " formed on 24 October 2006 was one open to be reached by the Minister on the materials before him and one which should be accepted for the purposes of the present Motion .</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">29 Albeit subsequent to the point in time when the s 16 notice was issued on 24 October 2006, it may further be noted that there was no later reason to revisit that conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">The " Opinion " provided in April 2007 thus also states in part as follows: 
 
 ... German police officers are not authorised to make offers to terminate criminal procedures.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Additionally, execution of imprisonment may, under Section 56 StPO, only be suspended on probation, when it does not exceed 2 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">In the case concerned here however, the minimum punishment provided by law is 3 years of imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">One could only go below this when other circumstances, which are regulated by law, come up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Such specific circumstances are not recognisable, however.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">For this reason, probationary suspension of the imprisonment to be imposed when a sentence is passed would, at the current state of knowledge, not be possible ... 

30 In any event, the approach being urged upon the Court by Mr Karsten to again impose a requirement upon the Attorney-General or the Minister to inquire into the penalty likely to be imposed is an approach which should be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">The definition of " extradition offence ", it has been said, is " not concerned with whether there are other alternate and lesser possible penalties, nor with the actual penalty likely to be imposed on the person whose extradition is being sought ": Dutton v O'Shane [2003] FCAFC 195 at [41] , [2003] FCAFC 195 ; 132 FCR 352 at 362 per Finn and Dowsett JJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">31 It is thus considered that there is no doubt that the offence for which extradition has been sought is in respect of an " extradition offence " as defined in s 5 of the Extradition Act or, alternatively, there was and remains a basis upon which the Respondent Minister could lawfully form that " opinion ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">AN ELIGIBLE PERSON: SECTIONS 18 AND 22?</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">
 
32 It is understood that the Applicant's contention in respect of the determination made under s 22 is that he was not an " eligible person " because " the applicant was not the subject of a valid order of a magistrate as the applicant's consent was not given voluntarily but under an operative mistake of fact ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">33 The " operative mistake of fact " to which the Applicant refers has previously been the subject of submissions, including the following statement in a letter from the Applicant to a Senior Legal Officer of the Extradition Unit dated 12 March 2007:
 
 My consent to being surrendered to the Federal Republic of Germany under s 18 of the Extradition Act 1988 was not given voluntarily.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">On 26/02/07 in the Supreme Court the District Public Prosecutor described my case as unusual and Justice Connolly considered my consent as have been tricked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">On 20/12/06 Magistrate Madden did not conduct or suggest any proceedings under s 19.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">

34 The contention of the Applicant is simply that s 22(1)(a) refers to an " order of a magistrate made under section 18 " and that there was no such order because the order as made was made in circumstances where the consent of the Applicant had not been given voluntarily.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">An order lawfully made under s 18 , upon such a contention, is a condition precedent to the making of a lawful determination pursuant to s 22.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">35 There are a number of reasons why this contention of the Applicant must fail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">36 First, by its terms, s 22(1)(a) requires there to be an " order of a magistrate made under section 18 ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">In the present case, the order was one made pursuant to s 18(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">That subsection relevantly applies where a person " informs the magistrate that he or she so consents" and clothes the magistrate with power " unless the magistrate has reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">37 In the present proceedings there is not understood to be any dispute as to Mr Karsten in fact informing the magistrate that he did consent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">Nor is there understood to be any dispute but that the magistrate had no " reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">38 For present purposes it may be assumed that a condition precedent to the authority of the Attorney-General to make a lawful determination under s 22(2) is the status of a person against whom such a determination is made as an " eligible person .</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">" It may further be assumed that that status in the present proceedings requires there to have been an " order of a magistrate made under section 18 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">" An " order " made in excess of the jurisdiction conferred upon a magistrate by s 18 , it may further be assumed, would not be an " order " at all but would be a nullity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">But the power or authority conferred on the magistrate in the present proceedings is a power or authority to make an " order " where a person has " inform [ed]" the magistrate that he consents and where the magistrate has no " reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">An undisclosed absence of consent or an undisclosed basis upon which consent has ostensibly been given does not strip the magistrate of power to make an order under s 18(2)(b)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">It may be noted that the warrant as issued under s 18(2) recited in part as follows:
 
 WHEREAS:
 ...
 (c) Christoph Herman Karsten has informed me that he consents to being surrendered to the Federal Republic of Germany...
 (d) I have no reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily;
 ... 

The conditions precedent to the exercise of the power conferred by s 22 would thus appear to have been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">39 Employing the language apposite to an analysis of " jurisdictional fact ", the jurisdictional facts for the purposes of s 18 would not be whether or not a person has in fact consented; the jurisdictional facts would at best be whether a person has "inform [ed] the magistrate that he or she so consents " and whether a magistrate " has reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">40 Insofar as inquiry may be directed to the former of these matters, the difficulty confronting the Applicant is the simple fact that whether or not he consented, albeit for a mistaken reason, is not on any view of the express terms of s 18 a constraint upon the power conferred upon the magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Why the Applicant informed the magistrate that he consented is of no immediate relevance; he either " inform [ed]" the magistrate of his consent or he did not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">And in the present proceedings he did so inform Magistrate Madden.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">41 The challenge advanced in the present proceedings focussed upon submissions as to an absence of consent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">No submission was advanced in the alternative seeking to contend that the magistrate had any " reason to believe " that the consent of which he was being informed " was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">The importance of a magistrate both being informed that a person consents, and not having any reason to believe that that consent " was not given voluntarily ", cannot be underestimated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">And it is of importance that s 18(2) is expressed, not in terms of a magistrate having to form a positive belief that a person is consenting voluntarily, but rather is expressed in terms of being obliged to take the steps outlined in s 18(2) " unless [he] has reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">The responsibility entrusted to a magistrate is not discharged upon a person informing him of his consent; if he has reason to question whether that consent is being voluntarily given, he should thereafter satisfy himself as to the basis upon which a person is consenting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">The nature and content of the responsibility of a magistrate in such circumstances need not be pursued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">In the present case, no submission was advanced that the magistrate had any reason to question the voluntariness of the consent of which he was being informed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">Nor has any fact or circumstance been referred to in the present proceedings which could form the basis of any such submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">42 Whether or not either of these two fields of inquiry can be properly characterised as " jurisdictional facts " thus need not be resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">The resolution of whether a fact is jurisdictional or not remains a matter of statutory construction: Timbarra Protection Coalition Inc v Ross Mining NL [1999] NSWCA 8 at [39] , 46 NSWLR 55 at 64 per Spigelman CJ (Mason P and Meagher JA agreeing).</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">Less difficulty may be experienced in characterising as a " jurisdictional fact " a question as to whether a person has informed a magistrate of his consent; greater difficulty, however, may be experienced in characterising as " jurisdictional " whether a magistrate had " reason to believe that the consent was not given voluntarily" .</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">The potential inconvenience consequent upon construing s 18 in such a manner may be a telling reason to conclude that such matters are not " jurisdictional ": cf Brock v United States of America [2007] FCAFC 3 at [30] per Black CJ, [2007] FCAFC 3 ; 157 FCR 121.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">43 An absence of consent (if established) -- it was accepted by the Respondent Minister in the present proceedings -- was, however, a consideration relevant to the exercise of discretion conferred by s 22(3)(f).</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">And, submitted the Minister, Mr Karsten's submission as to lack of voluntary consent was a submission in fact considered by the Minister.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">Given the invitations extended to Mr Karsten to make submissions prior to a determination being made pursuant to s 22 , and given the content of submissions in fact made (including submissions as to his lack of consent), that submission of the Minister is accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">44 Second, to now seek to impugn the surrender determination made pursuant to s 22 by reason of an asserted absence of voluntary consent when the s 18 decision was made is considered to be an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">45 At the time when the surrender determination was made under s 22 in July 2007 there had necessarily been in the present case the earlier decision of the magistrate made under s 18.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">That was the decision of the magistrate in December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">46 Intervening, namely in February 2007, was the decision of Connolly J of the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory: R v Karsten [2007] ACTSC 20 , 208 FLR 324.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">In those proceedings Mr Karsten sought to challenge the decision of the magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">Justice Connolly entertained a Notice of Appeal against the decision of the magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">Relevant to the order made by the magistrate are the following observations of his Honour: 
 
 [5] The Extradition Act (1988) of the Commonwealth provides two routes by which the question of whether surrender will occur may proceed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">By s 18, a person who has been remanded, may consent to their surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">The matter is then laid before the Commonwealth Attorney-General for determination as to whether surrender will, in fact, occur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">Or, pursuant to s 19, there may be a contested hearing in relation to whether there is eligibility to surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">[6] The common factual ground here is that Mr Karsten indicated his consent to being extradited and, as I understand it, there is no dispute that the learned Magistrate went through the necessary steps under s 18(2) which requires a magistrate, unless they have reason to believe the consent was not voluntary, to advise the person of the effect and consequences of their determination to surrender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">There is no specific provision in the Act relating to a variation of that determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">

His Honour's reasons for decision record the submission made through the Commonwealth Director of Public Prosecutions that the Supreme Court had:
 
 [7] ... no general jurisdiction ... to entertain firstly an appeal from a s 18 decision, and specifically no jurisdiction to permit a variation in the form of consent that was on the papers at least given at that hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">

The question before Connolly J was formulated by his Honour as being " whether or not this Court has the jurisdiction to entertain an application to allow Mr Karsten to withdraw his consent to an extradition ": [2007] ACTSC 20 at [1] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">That question was answered in the negative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">His Honour did, however, go on to further observe: 
 
 [18] There is a general discretion in the Attorney in relation to the extradition process, and it seems to me that the question of the voluntariness of consent would be a question that the Attorney would need to satisfy himself of.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">Clearly, if a situation was one where a person had no English skills at all, or had been tricked in some way into agreeing to consent, that would be a matter that would necessarily attract attention and the Attorney and [sic] would need to make a determination to that effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">

Before the Supreme Court Mr Karsten was legally represented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">A more general submission advanced on the hearing of the present Motion before this Court that Mr Karsten was thereafter represented by counsel, it is considered, should not be accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">What advice was given to Mr Karsten by his then legal representative when appearing in the Supreme Court remains, not surprisingly, unknown.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">47 Relevantly, however, by the time the s 22 determination was made, the only judicial challenge to the s 18 decision had been heard and resolved against Mr Karsten.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">In such circumstances it is considered that the requirements of s 22 had been met, namely that there was a lawful " order of a magistrate made under section 18 ", and that any condition precedent to the exercise of the power conferred by s 22 had been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">48 Even if the construction of s 22 which has been given to that section be incorrect, it is considered that it would be an abuse of process to now permit the Applicant to advance such a contention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">It would be an abuse of the process of the Court for a person the subject of extradition proceedings to seek to challenge an order made pursuant to s 18; to be informed that the means of challenge then being invoked were not available to him; to thereafter await a determination made under s 22; and, when that determination is adverse, to be permitted to then revert to his earlier position by asserting that there was no power to make the s 22 determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">49 Repetitious challenges to decisions made under the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth), or a failure to raise for resolution issues relevant to a decision the subject of review may constitute an abuse of process: Rivera v Minister Administering the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) [2007] FCAFC 191 at [13] ---[15] per Rares J, [2007] FCAFC 191 ; 99 ALD 235.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">See also Brock v Minister for Justice &amp; Customs [2007] FCA 2091.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">In the present proceedings, it is considered an abuse of process for the Applicant to now again seek to agitate the validity of the order made under s 18 and to thereby attempt to vitiate the subsequent s 22 determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">50 The separate and discrete administrative steps set forth in the 1988 Act may each be the subject of applications for judicial review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">The importance of each of those steps being discharged in accordance with law is self-evident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">The serious consequences to a person of an order for extradition not made in accordance with law may also be readily accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">51 But the Court should not endorse a course whereby a party is free to initially seek to challenge, in this case the order under s 18 of the 1988 Act; to thereafter abandon any challenge to the making of that order; to permit the extradition process to proceed, upon the basis that there is no legal impediment to the Attorney making a determination under s 22; and thereafter again seek to assert the invalidity of an order previously made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Presumably, had that determination been favourable to the Applicant, it would not have been asserted on his behalf that he could not take advantage of such a favourable decision because a condition precedent to the exercise of the s 22 power had not been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">Conversely, when the determination is adverse to the Applicant, it is considered to be an abuse of process to permit him to now assert the invalidity of the s 18 order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">52 Reason for reservation in reaching a conclusion as to an abuse of process is, however, occasioned by the Applicant's Affidavit filed in the present proceedings on 24 September 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">In that Affidavit Mr Karsten states:
 
 [3] When I was arrested and taken before the Magistrates Court of the ACT, I did not have a legal practitioner representing me until a legal aid solicitor came and advised me that if I had no one else she would appear on my behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">[4] I did not appreciate the fact that I should have had a lawyer representing me at that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">So that when she offered her services for me I believed that she was a Court appointed lawyer, with whom I was required to co-operate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">[5] The legal aid lawyer spoke to me about the governments case against me and advised that I was arrested and was going to be send [sic] back to Germany to face a criminal trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">I protested my innocence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">But was informed that that stage of the proceedings before the Magistrates Court I could not argue my case and that I had not [sic] alternative but to accept what the government was saying.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">She said that fighting the government was a waste of time [and] that I had no choice but to consent to the extradition application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">[6] I was in prison, I was accused of a crime I protested against and I was confused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">I believed that I had no alternative and against my will I consented to whatever it was that the Magistrate was asking me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">

An absence of consent was also the subject of hand-written submissions made by Mr Karsten to the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory, being submissions dated 24 January 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Notwithstanding differences between the hand-written account and the Affidavit as now filed, what is common to both is an explanation as to the circumstances in which Mr Karsten came to give his consent to the magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">53 The conclusion as to an abuse of process is nevertheless a conclusion which remains open.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">The s 22 determination was made on 5 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">Prior to that adverse determination being made, and after the decision of the Supreme Court on 26 February 2007, the Applicant took no further steps to challenge by any means of judicial review the order as made under s 18(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">The fact that Mr Karsten made submissions to the Minister, and thereby placed reliance upon seeking to persuade the Minister as to the merits of his case, is considered to only reinforce a conclusion as to an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">SECTION 31A: SUMMARY JUDGMENT 
 
54 The power of this Court to enter summary judgment has been considerably strengthened by the insertion of s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">That section provides as follows:
 
 Summary judgment 
 (1) The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if: 
 (a) the first party is prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and 
 (b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">(2) The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if: 
 (a) the first party is defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and 
 (b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">(3) For the purposes of this section, a defence or a proceeding or part of a proceeding need not be: 
 (a) hopeless; or 
 (b) bound to fail; 
 for it to have no reasonable prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">(4) This section does not limit any powers that the Court has apart from this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">

55 When introducing s 31A the Attorney-General in his Second Reading Speech (House of Representatives, 10 March 2005) the Attorney-General stated:
 
The bill also strengthens the power of the courts to deal with unmeritorious matters, by broadening the grounds on which federal courts can summarily dispose of unsustainable cases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">It is appropriate that this provision is of general application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">It will be a useful addition to the courts' powers in dealing with any unsustainable case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">56 In Commonwealth Bank of Australia v ACN 000 247 601 Pty Ltd (in liq) [2006] FCA 1416 Jacobson J helpfully summarised the principles to be applied to s 31A: 
 
 [30] ...The authorities relating to the proper construction and effect of s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act were exhaustively reviewed by Rares J in Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 at [31] ---[48].</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">His Honour stated the relevant principles at [45] and they may be summarised as follows:
 * In assessing whether there are reasonable prospects of success, the Court must be cautious not to do an injustice by summary dismissal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">* There will be reasonable prospects of success if there is evidence which may be reasonably believed so as to enable the party against whom summary judgment is sought to succeed at the final hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">* Evidence of an ambivalent character will usually be sufficient to amount to reasonable prospects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">* Unless only one conclusion can be said to be reasonable, the discretion under s 31A cannot be enlivened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">

57 In the present proceedings it is recognised that, when resolving the Minister's Motion , it is not necessary to conclude that Mr Karsten's case is either " hopeless " or " bound to fail ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">It is, however, considered that it has " no reasonable prospect [s] of success .</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">" It is considered that Mr Karsten has no reasonable prospects of any conclusion being reached other than that:
 
(a) he is an " extraditable person " within the meaning of ss 6 and 16 of the Extradition Act ; 
 
(b) the offence in respect of which his extradition is sought is an " extradition offence " within the meaning of ss 5 and 16 of the Act; and
 
(c) he is an " eligible person " under s 22 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">MISCELLANEOUS MATTERS 
 
58 Two further miscellaneous matters should be mentioned lest it be thought that they have been overlooked or not considered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">59 During the course of directions hearings held prior to the hearing of the present Motion, the Applicant requested that copies of documents be translated from German to English.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">The documents the subject of the requests were not then identified with any precision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">60 The requests for the provision of translated documents were thus previously refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">The legal and factual issues the subject of the Further Amended Application were considered to be within a sufficiently narrow compass that a request for the translation of unspecified documents was not considered necessary for the resolution of any issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">At the hearing of the Respondent Minister's Motion, the request for the translation of documents was revisited and the generic categories of documents which may have assumed relevance further pursued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">Even confined to more specific categories, it was considered that the hearing of the Motion should proceed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">The documents then identified as potentially being of some assistance to the contentions being pursued by Mr Karsten were not considered to have such relevance as to justify any further postponement of the Minister's Motion .</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">61 The second of the matters which should be addressed arises out of a request made by the Applicant by way of letter dated 12 December 2007 to the District Registry of the Court that he be provided with six copies of " transcripts to be made available to me free of charge...</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">The transcripts ", he maintained, " are required due to poor video link quality and to obtain legal advice in my self represented case ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">That request is also refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">The transcripts of what transpired at directions hearings prior to hearing are not considered to have any immediate relevance to the issues to be resolved on the present Motion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">
 
62 The Court may, in an appropriate case, order or make arrangements for the provision of transcripts to litigants free of charge or may make arrangements for a litigant to have access to a transcript, either by way of a computer or on loan from another party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">An appropriate case may include circumstances where a litigant is unable financially to obtain his own copy of a transcript or where it is necessary in the administration of justice that a copy be made available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">Unless the utility of making such arrangements is identified, it remains difficult to consider why such orders or arrangements should be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">ORDERS 
 
63 The orders of the Court are:
 
1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">The name of the Second Respondent be amended to "Minister for Home Affairs".</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">The Application filed on 17 July 2007, as amended by way of a Further Amended Application filed on 7 November 2007, be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">The Applicant to pay the costs of the Second Respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">I certify that the preceding sixty-three (63) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">Associate:

Dated: 14 March 2008


 Applicant: In person 
 
 Counsel for the Second Respondent: Mr T Glover (Australian Government Solicitor) 
 
 Date of Hearing: 28 February 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 14 March 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/331.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>