<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 435 (20 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/435.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">sentencing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring the commission of an offence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">refusing or failing to comply with a notice</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">s 155 of trade practices act 1974 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">criminal law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 This judgement concerns the sentence to be imposed on the defendant, Micheal Lee Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 Micheal Rana was charged with aiding, abetting, counselling, or procuring the commission of an offence contrary to s 155(5)(a) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (the Act) committed by NuEra Wellness Centre Pty Ltd, namely, the refusal or failure by NuEra Wellness Centre Pty Ltd to comply with a notice issued to it under s 155(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Micheal Rana is liable for committing the principal offence under s 11.2(1) of the Criminal Code (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The offence was said to have been committed on 22 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 The hearing of that charge was preceded by a number of directions hearings in which the Court ordered that any affidavits to be relied upon by the parties would be filed according to a timetable stipulated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Documents were filed by Micheal Rana as well as by his father, Paul Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The contents of those documents and the circumstances in which they were filed are set out at [6] to [37] of the reasons for judgment in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 374 ( Rana ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">They should be read in these reasons as if set out in full to the extent that they relate to Micheal Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">4 On 19 November 2007, the hearing of the charge against Micheal Rana was fixed to commence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">On that occasion the Court sought to take the appearance of the defendant, Micheal Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">No appearance was entered despite the fact that, as admitted later, Micheal Rana was present in court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">As a consequence a warrant for his arrest was issued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 On 14 December 2007, the warrant for arrest was executed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The Court received a report of the arresting officer which was described by Ms Orr, who appeared as counsel for the prosecutor, as follows:
 At the time of arrest Mr Micheal Rana denied his identity, said that the name Micheal Rana was a corporate fiction, that he was not an Australian citizen.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Mr Rana was arrested at 2/10 Georgia Crescent in Werribee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">That was an address that the police had attended previously and asked for Mr Rana and been told that he did not reside at that address.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Even on this occasion a person told the arresting officer that Mr Rana did not reside at this address, but Mr Rana appeared and arrest subsequently took place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">6 On 17 December 2007, an application for bail was made on Micheal Rana's behalf and was refused in view of the uncertainty that he would appear to answer the charge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">In circumstances described at [33] to [35] of Rana [2008] FCA 374 , the hearing of the charge was eventually listed for 22 December 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">7 On 22 December 2007, Mr Samargis appeared as counsel on behalf of Micheal Rana, and Micheal Rana entered a plea of guilty to the offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">On that occasion, the application for bail was successful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">8 In view of those circumstances the hearing of the plea in mitigation was fixed for 18 February 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">On that date, submissions were made by Mr Samargis and also by Ms Orr.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Significantly, on that occasion Micheal Rana himself gave evidence and was cross-examined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The essential features relevant to sentencing which Micheal Rana explained to the Court, were that he worked at the NuEra companies for the most part in an administrative capacity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">He said that at the time of the service of the notice under s 155 of the Act he was in the midst of domestic turmoil, his wife having at that stage suffered a miscarriage of their first child.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">9 Micheal Rana said he did not understand the documents which were filed in the course of the preparation for the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">He apologised for his conduct, both in respect of the filing of the documents and of the failure to comply with the notice under s 155.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">In relation to his failure to identify himself on 19 November 2007, he said that he had acted on the basis of what his father had said to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">10 His evidence presented a difficulty for the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">On the one hand, Micheal Rana apologised for his conduct and, on the other hand, the evidence showed at times that Micheal Rana seemed to have little understanding of the wrong that he had done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">11 A constant theme in much of Micheal Rana's evidence was related to the influence of his father and the fact that he had both failed to respond to the notice, and also sought to thwart the processes of the Court by the filing of the nonsensical documents referred to in the reasons for judgment delivered in Rana [2008] FCA 374 , as a result of the influence of his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">At the conclusion of that evidence, the Court indicated that it may be assisted in understanding more about Micheal Rana's attitude to his wrongdoing with the assistance of an expert report.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Mr Samargis obtained instructions and proceeded with the obtaining of such a report.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Indeed, the report was produced in very short time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">12 The matters which are required to be taken into account in this matter are set out in s 16A(2) of the Crimes Act 1914 (Cth) (the Crimes Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">It is to those matters which I now turn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">In favour of leniency for Micheal Rana is the fact that he has not been convicted of any offence before (s 16A(2)(b)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">His plea of guilty, entered on 22 December 2007, is a factor to be taken into account, although it was hardly made at the first opportunity and therefore carries little weight (s 16A(2)(g)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">13 Micheal Rana is now 26 and married with a child.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The circumstances of his involvement with the NuEra companies have caused devastation to his life.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">He is now bankrupt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">He lost the house in which he was living.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">He has been arrested and was in custody for eight days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">It is in Micheal Rana's favour that throughout the proceedings it has been obvious that he has the strong support of his wife, his mother and his in laws.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">That attests to loyalty which must be based on some characteristics which are positive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">14 Furthermore, since Micheal Rana's first appearance in the Court he has responded to the suggestion that he needed to demonstrate a greater understanding and responsibility of his wrongdoing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">He applied for and obtained some voluntary work with the Salvation Army and has inquired into doing community work with the local council.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Those efforts, timed as they were, should be taken into account as positive indications of an attempt to redress the wrongs which had been done (s16A(2)(f)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">15 At [49] to [50] of Rana [2008] FCA 374 there is a discussion about the importance of compliance with s 155 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">These reasons will not set those sections out but rely upon that discussion to inform the sentencing in this case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">16 Importantly in this case is the evidence which was given on behalf of the prosecution by Mr Small, which is described at [47] of Rana [2008] FCA 374.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">That evidence demonstrates the sad and pernicious effects of the offending conduct on vulnerable people.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Whilst Micheal Rana in cross-examination indicated some acceptance of responsibility for that, it is not entirely clear that his attitude as expressed was entirely genuine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">This is especially so when weighed against some of Micheal Rana's other answers which suggested or expressed the view that the clinics operated by the various NuEra companies were misunderstood and in fact provided soothing and valuable services to those that attended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">17 However, in sentencing Micheal Rana, the Court was assisted greatly by the report of Mr Joblin, a forensic psychologist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">He exposes clearly from consultation with Micheal Rana that what he describes as the psychological conflict in Micheal Rana's mind at present is the conflict between a son who has high admiration and loyalty to his father, and at the same time a dawning understanding that his father was involved in serious wrongdoing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Relevant sections of the report are as follows:
 
 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The fact that his father is now in custody has produced some considerable psychological conflict for Mr Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">He was emphatic that as he sees it, his father was simply dedicated to helping others and now he is in jail for trying to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">For Mr Rana that is unconscionable and a matter that results in psychological conflict.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">
 
 
 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Mr Rana reported that he has always respected his father for his dedication to helping others.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">He acknowledged that there has been negative media coverage about the "clinic".</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">However, Mr Rana believes that those are persons who are not directly involved in the clinic and do not understand the nature of the treatments given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">This may be somewhat of a rationalisation and again needs to be placed into the context of his extraordinary relationship with his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">
 
 ... 
 
 9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Mr Rana acknowledged that when his father is released, he will have no business dealings with him but he emphasised that he will be continuing his close relationship with his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">
 
 ... 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">From perusal of the affidavits and my discussion with him it does seem much of his difficulty has involved his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Mr Rana seems to have had a blind adherence to his father's dictates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">He reported, for example, that prior to going to court, his father had indicated to him that because they could not afford legal representation, his father and brother would run the defence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Mr Rana reported that his father indicated to him that if he attended court, he should sit in the back and literally say nothing in case anything he might say prejudiced the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">Thus, he reported that when he was asked about his presence in court or to account for himself in court and said nothing, he was acting on the instructions of his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">It is interesting to note that those instructions were not only from his father but also from his boss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Mr Rana indicated that he felt if he disobeyed his boss, he would lose his job.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Therefore, it does seem that Mr Rana's mute presentation in court related to this extraordinary relationship with his father and his directive that he say nothing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">12.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Mr Rana reported that he is somewhat confused about the court processes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">He acknowledged that he was a director of the company and as a result he had a large degree of responsibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">However, that is all in conflict with the relationship he had with his father who indicated to him that there should be no difficulties in his business and if the ACCC questioned him, the worst that could happen would [be] that he would be made bankrupt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">This extraordinary relationship with his father is not the result of limited intellect but may relate to Mr Rana's somewhat acquiescent personality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Mr Rana seemed to have been somewhat in awe of his father and during my interview with him any discussion about his father was positive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">In addition discussion about his father's history of employment and his various business was all positive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">It does seem that the idea of his father opening the "clinic" to assist others reflected the ambitions Mr Rana had had when he was in school.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Thus, he has had an extraordinary admiration for his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">... 15.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Mr Rana indicated his awareness that he should hate his father as he has caused the problems he now faces.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">However, he reported he cannot hate his father.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">... 23.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">I am of the opinion that Mr Rana has the basis now to consider the inappropriateness of his behaviour and thus the prognosis in terms of re-offending must be reasonably good.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">That is in spite of my awareness from his report that he ... still maintains a positive emotional relationship with his father because as he reports he['s] still "my father".</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">This does not mean however that relationship will dictate any further antisocial behaviour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">18 Ms Orr rightly pointed out that Mr Joblin tendered the opinion that Micheal Rana is not suffering from any mental illness, does not have an intellectual disability, that he is not psychotic and there is no mental impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">Mr Joblin stated that he does not regard Micheal Rana as psychologically well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Ms Orr sought to explain this opinion as a reference to the anxiety caused by involvement in the legal system.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Reading the report in full and in its context, the Court accepts that Mr Joblin was referring to the psychological conflict which he describes on a number of occasions as the conflict arising between the feeling and regard Micheal Rana has for his father and the recognition that there has been serious wrongdoing by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">19 The question which arises from this analysis is how best to reflect this in the appropriate sentence for Micheal Rana.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Micheal Rana's psychological conflict requires him to develop an understanding that he has been involved in a serious wrongdoing and to understand that it is important for him to exercise an independent evaluation of conduct which others suggest he engage in.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">It is clear enough that such an understanding has not yet fully developed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">A further period of imprisonment would not assist in the specific deterrence which is required against this background (s16A(2)(j)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">20 On the other hand, it is necessary for Micheal Rana to have a period in which he is under threat of consequences if he were to act unlawfully by failing to exercise his own judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">21 That particular object is best achieved by the imposition of a recognisance release order under s 20(1)(b) of the Crimes Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Section 20(1)(b) provides 
 (1) Where a person is convicted of a federal offence or federal offences, the court before which he is convicted may, if it thinks fit: (a) by order, release the person...upon his giving security...by recognizance...to the satisfaction of the court, that he comply with the following conditions: (i) that he will be of good behaviour for such period, not exceeding 5 years, as the court specifies in the order; ... (b) sentence the person to imprisonment in respect of the offence or each offence but direct, by order, that the person be released, upon giving security of the kind referred to in paragraph (a)... forthwith 
22 Micheal Rana has been convicted of a federal offence within the meaning of s 20(1)(b) of the Crimes Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">For that offence he is sentenced to two months imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">This period of time takes into account the nature of the offence and Micheal Rana's liability as principal offender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">Under s 20(1)(b) the Court directs that Micheal Rana be released forthwith upon giving security by recognisance in the sum of $1000 and on the condition that he be of good behaviour for a period of 18 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">This period allows for a sufficient period of time following Paul Rana's release from prison for Micheal Rana to demonstrate appropriate independence from the influence of his father or any other person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">I certify that the preceding twenty-two (22) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice North.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Associate:

Dated: 15 July 2008

 Counsel for the Prosecution: Ms R Orr 
 
 Solicitor for the Prosecution: Commonwealth Department of Public Prosecutions 
 
 Counsel for the Defendant: Mr J Samargis 
 
 Solicitor for the Defendant: Lawcorp Lawyers 

 Date of Hearing: 22 December 2007, 18 February &amp; 20 March 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 March 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/435.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>