<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Yap v Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission [2008] FCA 534 (24 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/534.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for reinstatement of deregistered company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application for orders against various respondents</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">numerous previous unsuccessful applications to reinstate company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">proceedings abuse of process</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">no reasonable prospect of success</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">application dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">direction that no further proceedings be filed without leave of court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 1 On 7 December 2007 Yap Cheng See filed an application in this Court seeking an order against the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC) for the reinstatement of a deregistered company, Cheshire Securities Pty Ltd (Cheshire).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">She sought compensation from ASIC for "wrongful deregistration on 20 June 2000".</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Orders were also sought against a variety of other parties in the following terms: 
 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Curtin University of WA to reinstate the company's 50-years [sic] LEASE executed on 11 August 1988 between Curtin U (Lessor) Cheshire (Lessee) and CS Yap (Guarantor).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Esanda F Ltd to reimburse the company all rents derived from its Student Housing "Don Watt House" from 17 November 1988 with interest compounded at Court rate till Judgment and to compensate its Guarantors (Arcola Pty Ltd and CS Yap) for wrongful seizure and sale of their properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The Registrar of Titles to: 
 
 
 
 
 
 a) revert Swan Loc 1978 in CT Vol 1794 Folio 145 back into the name of Yap Cheng See of 57 Whaleback Avenue Parkwood WA,
 b) revert Swan Loc 73 Lot 6 on Diagram 5694 CT Vol 1590 Folio 117 back into the name of Yap Cheng See of 57 Whaleback Av Parkwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">
 
 
 
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">ANZ and Challenge Bank to reimburse Arcola Pty Ltd rents derived from 58 58A 58B and 60 Second Avenue Rossmoyne from 17 November 1988 with interest at Court rate till Judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Challenge Bank to reimburse CS Yap all rents derived from Lot 896/No 235 Preston Point Rd Bicton from 25.5.88 with interest at Ct rate till Judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 
 
 
 
 a) Registrar of Titles to revert Lot 337 CT Vol 1773 Folio 274 and Lot 14 on Diagram 23627 CT Vol 1763 Folio 869 back into the name of Arcola Pty Ltd ACN 009 203 838 and 
 b) revert Lot 896/No 235 Preston Point Rd Bicton back into the name of Yap Cheng See of 57 Whaleback Avenue Parkwood.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">
 
 
 
 
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Bank of Singapore to compensate Cheshire Securities Pty Ltd for breach of fiduciary duty to the company and 
 
 
 
 
 
 a) Registrar of Titles to revert Portion of Perth Town Lot Y260 and being Lot 100 on Diagram 42401 CT Vol 1337 Folio 399 back into the name of Westpoint Holdings Pty Ltd ACN 009 308 301 and 
 b) Bank of Singapore to reimburse the company rents derived from its property from 23 February 1989 (date Bank released property to a stranger, Mr P Vivante pursuant to Transfer No EO29410 CSY48).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">
 
 
 
 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Commonwealth Bank to compensate Yap Cheng See all rents derived from Lot 26/No 254 Preston Point Rd Bicton consisting of original house and two Townhouses, from 25.5.88 with interest at Crt rate till Judgment and other damages as the Court sees fit and 
 
 
 
 
 
 a) Registrar of Titles to revert Lot 26/No 254 Preston Point Rd Bicton back into the name of Yap Cheng See of 57 Whaleback Avenue Parkwood WA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">
 
 
 
 
 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The DC Bailiff to pay Yap Cheng See $142,000 pursuant to writ of FiFa215/93 issued by M Ellison pursuant to DC1536/89 P Vivante &amp; Co Pty Ltd vs CS Yap which claim proved to be false and which action Esanda F Ltd funded evidence in CSY42 and CSY71.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The State of WA to compensate Cheshire Securities Pty Ltd as the Court sees just as it is the victim of Curtin U Student Housing project that WADC facilitated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Mr Peter Fermanis to repay Cheshire Securities Pty Ltd all monies he received from Public Trustee unlawfully pursuant to his SC CIV 1172/88 P Fermanis vs Cheshire Hldgs Pty Ltd CSY2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The bankruptcy of Yap Cheng See pursuant to WG 7047/98 effected by Granich &amp; Asso on 10.12.98 ought to be annulled as a result of fraud by P Vivante &amp; Co Pty Ltd in DC1536/89 in CSY78.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On 31.10.93 CS Yap was declared a vexatious litigant pursuant to SC CIV 2722/02 by Granich &amp; Asso ought to be rescinded for same reason as in par 10 evidence in CSY79.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">
 

2 An affidavit sworn by Mrs Yap on 5 November 2007 was filed with the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">It was in two volumes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">It was long and turgid and covered events dating back to 1987.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">It appeared to make allegations of fraud and improper conduct against a variety of parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">3 On 1 February 2008 I made directions that each respondent to the application who had appeared had leave to file a motion together with written submissions as to summary disposition of the proceedings under s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) (the Act) or as an abuse of the process of the Court or otherwise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">A timetable was set for the filing of the motions, submissions and reply submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">ASIC and Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd (Esanda) both filed motions and submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">ASIC had already filed an affidavit on 16 January 2008 in opposition to the reinstatement application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The Sheriff for Western Australia and the State of Western Australia who both entered conditional appearances, also filed submissions seeking dismissal pursuant to s 31A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">4 Mrs Yap's application had been served on Freehills on the basis that they were the solicitors for Esanda, Challenge Bank Ltd (Challenge) and Bank of Singapore Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">It was also served on the Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (ANZ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Mr John, a solicitor working at Freehills, swore his affidavit on behalf of Esanda and ANZ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">He sought leave to be heard on their behalf on the first return date of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">5 Mr John deposed that a substantial aspect of the claim contemplated by the application is the reinstatement of Cheshire to the Register of Companies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Much of the other relief sought in the application was relief sought by Cheshire which would not be able to be pursued if it were not reinstated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">He pointed out that Cheshire was previously known as Cheshire Holdings Pty Ltd and was deregistered on 13 April 1992 following a winding up order made by the Supreme Court of Western Australia on 5 September 1990.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">A copy of the relevant ASIC search was exhibited to the affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">6 As appeared from the present application the purpose of the proposed reinstatement of Cheshire was to enable it to pursue proceedings against Esanda and ANZ in relation to events which evidently occurred in 1988 and 1989.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Both Esanda and ANZ deny that they had any liability to Cheshire, Mrs Yap, Arcola Pty Ltd or Akibilt Pty Ltd.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">They opposed the application to reinstate Cheshire on the grounds that the issues raised by the application were res judicata and/or subject to an issue estoppel.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Mr John pointed out that the present application is the fifth attempt by Mrs Yap to reinstate Cheshire.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The four earlier applications were unsuccessful.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">They were as follows: 
 
(a) Action COR 220 of 1994 in the Supreme Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Steytler J then dismissed Mrs Yap's application to reinstate Cheshire together with a related application to stay its winding up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">A copy of Steytler J's unreported decision was exhibited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">It was delivered on 22 November 1995.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Mrs Yap appealed that decision to the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The appeal was dismissed on 9 April 1998 for want of prosecution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">An application for special leave to appeal against the decision of the Full Court was lodged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Mr John indicated Esanda did not receive any notice of the outcome of that appeal but presumed that it failed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">(b) While the decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court was pending, Mrs Yap brought a further application in the Supreme Court to reinstate Cheshire in Action COR 131 of 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">That application was dismissed by Master Sanderson on 11 July 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">His decision was appealed to the Full Court of the Supreme Court by notice of appeal dated 14 July 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Again, Esanda received no notice of any steps taken in relation to that appeal since it was filed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">(c) A further application to reinstate Cheshire was made by Mrs Yap on 1 September 1997 in the Supreme Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">It was dismissed by Master Sanderson on 19 September 1997.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">(d) In the following year another application was made in Action COR 209 of 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">It was dismissed on 19 August 1998.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">That was by a decision of Master Sanderson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">His decision was appealed to the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Although the notice of appeal was filed in 1998 for some reason it was not heard until February 2007 and dismissed on 8 February 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">7 Mr John was aware of two other unsuccessful applications to reinstate Cheshire, being applications by Mr Chong, who is Mrs Yap's son.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Those applications were: 
 
(a) Action COR 302 of 2001 in the Supreme Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Master Bredmeyer dismissed the application on 4 October 2001.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">(b) Action COR 81 of 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Master Newnes dismissed the application on 6 June 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">8 In the written submissions in support of its motion for the proceeding to be dismissed ASIC referred to the history of past applications to reinstate Cheshire.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">ASIC also mentioned past attempts at prosecution of civil claims against Esanda, Challenge and the Commonwealth Bank of Australia Ltd (Commonwealth Bank).</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">9 ASIC submitted that Mrs Yap's reasons for seeking reinstatement of Cheshire appeared to be to enable it to bring the same claims against Esanda, Challenge and the Commonwealth Bank as she had previously brought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">The matters sought to be determined in the application had already been considered and ruled upon in earlier proceedings and were therefore the subject of issue estoppel and res judicata .</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Although there was no issue estoppel strictly arising as between Cheshire and the defendants to the civil claims previously pursued by Mrs Yap, it was said nonetheless to be clear that she was pursuing substantially the same allegations in those proceedings as would be pursued by Cheshire if reinstated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">To that extent, the previous civil claims pursued by Mrs Yap indicated that the claims that would be brought by Cheshire had no prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Even if it could be argued that some allegations of fact in her affidavit were not dealt with in previous proceedings, it was clear enough that the questions in issue in this proceeding relied entirely on facts that could or should have been raised in the earlier proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">10 ASIC submitted that the application could only succeed if it were based on new material facts which had arisen or become known to Mrs Yap after her last application to the Supreme Court of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">In any event if Cheshire had any valid claims against any of the respondents they must have accrued prior to Cheshire being deregistered on 13 April 1992.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">Any cause of action was likely now to be statute barred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">11 Mrs Yap filed a response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Her response traversed events that had occurred over the last 20 years or so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">I do not propose to descend into an analysis of Mrs Yap's almost unintelligible claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">12 The remedies sought in the application substantially depend upon the reinstatement of Cheshire.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">In my opinion that application has no reasonable prospect of success.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">It is on the face of it an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">It seeks to relitigate issues that have been litigated over many years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">If there be, buried in the mound of material that Mrs Yap submits to this Court, some issue which has not been litigated it is not the task of the Court to unearth it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I will dismiss the application under s 31A of the Act and alternatively on the basis that it is an abuse of process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">13 I am satisfied that Mrs Yap has habitually, persistently and without reasonable grounds instituted vexatious proceedings in this and the Supreme Court of Western Australia, they being this proceeding and the other proceedings referred to in Mr John's affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">I therefore direct under O 21, r (1)(b) of the Federal Court of Australia Rules that in future Mrs Yap may not institute a proceeding in this Court without the leave of the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">I certify that the preceding thirteen (13) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice French.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Associate:
Dated: 24 April 2008 

 
 Mrs CS Yap appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr PV Ward and Mr T Palmer 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent:

Counsel for the State of Western Australia and the Sheriff of Western Australia by leave:

Solicitor for the State of Western Australia and the Sheriff of Western Australia:

Counsel for Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd and the Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd by leave:

Solicitor for Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd and the Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd: Blake Dawson

Mr MAG Jenkin




State Solicitor for Western Australia



Mr DW John




Freehills 
 
 Date of Hearing: 1 February 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 24 April 2008 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/534.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>