<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Comcare v Davies (No 2) [2008] FCA 566 (24 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/566.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">federal court rules 1979 (cth) o 35(7)(1)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">liberty to apply</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">variation of orders not entered</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 In this matter on 27 March 2008 reasons for decision were published allowing an appeal from the decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal given on 3 October 2007: Comcare v Davies [2008] FCA 393.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">2 One of the orders then made was that the decision of the Tribunal was to be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Liberty was reserved for the parties to apply within seven days should one or the other seek to have the orders varied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">That liberty was not invoked but the orders as made on 27 March 2008 have not yet been entered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 Today, however, an oral application was made in accordance with O 35(7)(1) of the Federal Court Rules 1979 (Cth) to vary Order 3 as made on 27 March 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The application is supported by both parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">4 Order 3 of the orders made on 27 March 2008 was that:
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The matter be remitted to the Tribunal for further consideration in accordance with law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">5 Pursuant to Order 35(7)(1) that Order is now varied such that the order in lieu thereof is as follows:
 
3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The matter be remitted to the Tribunal for further consideration in accordance with law for the determination of the following issues:
 
 
 (a) What may constitute suitable employment other than the Respondent's Bali Gardens business; and
 (b) The quantification of the Respondent's ability to earn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 


 
6 There will be no order for costs as to the application this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">ORDERS 
 
7 The orders of the Court are:
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Order 3 of the orders made on 27 March 2008, namely that " The matter be remitted to the Tribunal for further consideration in accordance with law " be varied pursuant to Order 35(7)(1) of the Federal Court Rules 1979 (Cth) such that the Order now read: 
 
3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">The matter be remitted to the Tribunal for further consideration in accordance with law for the determination of the following issues:
 
 
 (a) What may constitute suitable employment other than the Respondent's Bali Gardens business; and
 (b) The quantification of the Respondent's ability to earn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">
 


 
2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">There be no order as to costs of the present application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">I certify that the preceding seven (7) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Associate:

Dated: 24 April 2008

 Solicitor for the Applicant: P Woulfe (Dibbs Abbott Stillman) 

 Date of Hearing: 24 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 24 April 2008 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/566.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>