<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>pSivida Limited v New pSivida, Inc; in the matter of pSivida Limited [2008] FCA 627 (1 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/627.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">scheme of arrangement</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">reconstruction of company</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">features of scheme warranting particular attention</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 

 
1 This is an application by pSivida Limited pursuant to s 411 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) to convene a meeting of shareholders to consider a scheme of arrangement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The business of pSivida involves the development of pharmaceutical products for targeted and controlled drug delivery for local and international clients.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 The scheme is intended to effect a change of pSivida's domicile from Western Australia to Delaware in the United States of America, while maintaining listings on the ASX, NASDAQ and the Frankfurt Stock Exchange.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The pSivida scheme is represented diagrammatically in Part 1.1 of the Information Memorandum which was before me this morning in evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">3 Under the scheme it is proposed that by Court order the whole of the shareholders' shares in pSivida be transferred to New pSivida Inc, a company incorporated under the laws of Delaware.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">In exchange for this, New pSivida will issue CHESS Depositary Interests (CDIs) to pSivida shareholders other than the American Depository Shares (ADS) Depository and ineligible foreign shareholders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Each CDI will represent an interest in one fully paid share of the common stock in New pSivida.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">4 The scheme will also result in the issue of New pSivida shares to the ADS Depository for distribution to the ADS holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">An ADS is a security that is tradable on NASDAQ and the Frankfurt Stock Exchange.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">One ADS represents 10 ordinary shares in pSivida.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">If the scheme is approved, pSivida shareholders will receive one CDI for every 40 ordinary shares in pSivida.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The ADS holders will receive one New pSivida share for every four ADSs held.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">5 The scheme provides for the transfer of all of the assets and liabilities of pSivida to New pSivida and for the deregistration of pSivida without a winding up following the transfer of its assets and liabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">6 In accordance with the approach taken in Royal Victorian Institute for the Blind Ltd v RBS.RVIB.VAF Ltd [2004] FCA 735 ; (2004) 206 ALR 581 at [17] and SGIC Insurance Ltd v Insurance Australia Ltd (2004) 51 ACSR 470 at [6], New pSivida Inc has been joined as a defendant in this application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">7 Mr Jackman SC who appears for pSivida Limited has taken me through the Explanatory Memorandum and the evidence in support of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">I am satisfied that I should make the orders which are sought, however I should record that Mr Jackman pointed out that four features of the scheme which warranted particular attention.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">8 First, as the diagram illustrating the structure of the pSivida Group shows, two wholly owned subsidiaries of pSivida Limited will not remain as subsidiaries after the reconstruction, but the assets and liabilities will be transferred to New pSivida Inc. 
 
9 Secondly, after the scheme, pSivida will be deregistered without an order for the winding up of that company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">This will be effected pursuant to s 413(1)(d) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">10 Third, option holders in pSivida Limited will become option holders in New pSivida Inc.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">There is no scheme of arrangement with the option holders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">However, the liabilities comprising the options will be transferred to New pSivida and will become liabilities of that company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">A consequential order will be needed if the scheme is approved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The Court will have power to make that order pursuant to s 413(1)(g).</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">11 The fourth feature to which Mr Jackman referred was that the ADS Depository holds its shares through ANZ Nominees Ltd on behalf of pSivida's many ADS holders who are United States residents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">They account for approximately 388 million of the shares held by ANZ or approximately 53 per cent of the total shares issued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">This may have consequences in relation to the headcount test imposed by s 411(4)(a)(ii) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">12 This is not a matter which affects my discretion to convene a meeting of the shareholders of pSivida.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">However, it may become a relevant factor at the second court hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">In that event, the plaintiff may seek to rely on the recent amendment to s 411(4)(a)(ii) which adds the words "unless the court otherwise orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">" 
 
13 The scheme is a scheme for the reconstruction of the company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">It passes the test set out by Buckley J in Re South African Supply and Cold Storage (1904) 2 Ch 268 at 286.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The undertaking is being transferred to persons who are not outsiders so that substantially the same business will be carried on by substantially the same persons who previously conducted the business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">14 I have been provided with a helpful written outline of pSivida Ltd's submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">In accordance with the practice usually followed, I will mark the outline of submissions as MFI 1, but will not make any further reference to them in these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">15 I am satisfied that I should make orders in accordance with the short minutes of order which I have now signed and dated and placed with the Court papers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">I certify that the preceding fifteen (15) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Associate:
Dated: 15 May 2008


 Counsel for the Plaintiff: I M Jackman SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Blake Dawson 
 
 Date of Hearing: 1 May 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 1 May 2008 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/627.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>