<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Excell v Comcare [2008] FCA 757 (27 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/757.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">commonwealth employee</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">psychological condition</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">initial diagnosis then improvement followed by deterioration</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether permanent impairment became permanent prior to or after commencement of safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether question of law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">workers' compensation</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
1 The sole issue before the Administrative Appeals Tribunal constituted by the Honourable C R Wright QC, Deputy President, was whether the applicant's permanent impairment by reason of her psychological condition had become permanent prior to 1 December 1988, the date of commencement of the Safety, Rehabilitation and Compensation Act 1988 (Cth) (the 1988 Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">If so, the effect of s 124 of the 1988 Act is that Comcare would not be liable to pay lump sum compensation under s 24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">2 Under s 24 of the 1988 Act, Comcare is liable to pay compensation to an employee where they suffer an injury that results in permanent impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Section 124 is a transitional provision setting out the compensation payable under the 1998 Act in respect of impairment occurring prior to its commencement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Section 124(3) provides that a person is not entitled to compensation under s 24 of the 1988 Act in respect of a permanent impairment where there was no entitlement to receive lump sum compensation under the legislation in force at the time the impairment occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Under the previous legislation relevant to the applicant, the Compensation (Commonwealth Government Employees) Act 1971 (Cth) (the 1971 Act), no lump sum compensation was payable for permanent loss arising from a psychiatric condition because such a condition was not among the various forms of "loss", such as loss of hearing or loss of an arm at or above the elbow, specified in s 39.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">It was thus accepted that the applicant's impairment, once it had become permanent, would be compensable by way of lump sum under the 1988 Act but not the 1971 Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The time at which the applicant's impairment became permanent --- and the legislation in force at the time --- therefore determines whether the applicant is entitled to compensation: Brennan v Comcare (1994) 50 FCR 555 at 570.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">3 An impairment is permanent if it is likely to continue indefinitely: 1988 Act, s 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">That state of affairs must have been reached before the commencement date of the 1988 Act for s 124(3) to apply: Brennan v Comcare at 570.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">In the present case, the degree of the applicant's impairment was not in issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">It would be a matter for primary assessment by Comcare in the event of the applicant succeeding on this appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The applicant's impairment 
 
4 Comcare submitted to the Tribunal that the applicant's condition had become permanent before 1 December 1988 and had not deteriorated or become worse thereafter so as to provide a basis for a claim based on a new impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">5 The applicant is aged 52.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">From the age of 19 she worked in a clerical position with the Commonwealth Public Service.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In 1981 she transferred to the Social Security branch office at Glenorchy working in clerical and counter duties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Later she was promoted to a position involving regular face to face contact with benefit recipients and applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">From time to time some of these individuals became stressed and angry and would be abusive and threatening.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Sometimes such individuals recognised the applicant when she was away from the office and would insult her and behave offensively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">6 An incident in 1986 particularly affected her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">A man called Hicks came to the office and shouted in the applicant's presence that he would "get a shotgun and shoot the lot of you".</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Police were called but Hicks had left the building.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">It was later reported to the applicant that Hicks had assaulted somebody with a shotgun and been arrested by the police.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Hicks was subsequently convicted and sentenced to imprisonment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">7 On 16 February 1988 the applicant consulted her general practitioner Dr Ian Beltz.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">She was referred by him to Dr Warwick Ashley, a psychiatrist, in June of that year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">8 On 9 March 1988 the applicant made a claim for compensation in respect of "stress" attributed to a "high workload, working long hours, lack of staff and no backup".</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Liability was accepted for anxiety and depression with a date of injury of 16 February 1988, the date on which she first presented to her general practitioner with symptoms of stress.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">9 Another incident occurred in June 1988 when the applicant was told by a client that a security guard who worked at Glenorchy after the Hicks incident had been selling information to clients who were being investigated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The applicant realised that as a result her name and address would be known to the people she was investigating, some of whom had criminal records and a history of violence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">It was on this occasion that she had her first major panic attack.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">She described the attack in the following terms:
 I had difficulty breathing, I started to sweat, my heart beat quickly and I thought I might die because of the heart palpitations and breathing difficulty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">I could not think.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">I was shaking.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">When it (the attack) stopped I was exhausted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">10 The applicant eventually retired from the public service and was granted invalidity on 21 April 1989.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">In 1990 she undertook a return-to-work program.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">This continued through to late 1992.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Subsequently she obtained a Diploma of Remedial Massage and now operates a small practice on a part-time basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">11 On 8 February 2005, on the applicant's application, the description of her condition was changed from "anxiety/depression" to "post-traumatic stress disorder".</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">12 The applicant by her solicitors applied for a lump sum permanent impairment payment under s 24.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">This claim was rejected by Comcare on the basis that her impairment was permanent before 1 December 1988 and no lump sum payment would have been payable under the 1971 Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Comcare decided that disentitling provisions of s 124(3) of the 1988 Act applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Medical evidence before the Tribunal 
 
13 Reports from Dr Beltz and Dr Ashley were provided but they were not called to give evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">14 In a report of 25 July 1988 Dr Ashley referred to the applicant's fluctuating symptoms since he had first seen her and recorded a "fairly clear diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder, these stresses being work related".</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">15 In a report of 19 August 1988 Dr Ashley's opinion was to the effect (as summarised by the Tribunal) that her very stressed condition was not improving and was becoming well entrenched.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">On 25 August he certified her as unfit for work "from 3/9/88 indefinitely and should be retired/superannuated etc on health grounds".</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">On 15 September 1988, having seen her the previous day, he thought she was "slowly healing".</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">On 13 December he suggested to Dr Beltz that she had "relapsed somewhat, recently" due to hold-ups in the retirement process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">16 On 16 December 1988 Dr Ashley gave a report to the Director of Social Security, having seen the applicant on 14 December.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">He reported:
 Her psychiatric disability is of such a degree and nature that both Dr Weatherly and myself have supported her being retired on psychiatric grounds.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">17 Dr Weatherly (a psychiatrist, now deceased) had seen the applicant on 2 September 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">He diagnosed her as suffering from "chronic anxiety disorder with both panic and phobic elements".</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">18 In the course of 1989 Dr Ashley provided further reports to Dr Beltz, the gist of which was that the applicant was continuing to improve.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">However, in February 1990 there was a relapse of symptoms and signs of post-traumatic stress disorder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">In April 1990 she had "obviously improved".</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">In October 1991 she was "somewhat better than twelve months ago".</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">By October 1992, in a report to Comcare, Dr Ashley thought that her health had gradually improved and that she could work at the Department for up to five hours per week.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">In the last of his many reports to Comcare, in November 1994, Dr Ashley said that the applicant "remains vulnerable to any conflict and it is most unlikely that she could work for pay in any meaningful sense".</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">19 Two consultant psychiatrists gave evidence on behalf of the applicant at the Tribunal hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">20 Professor Saxby Pridmore saw the applicant for assessment in February 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">He diagnosed her as then suffering from a panic disorder with agoraphobia, social phobia and general anxiety disorder together with residual symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">He said she had "lived with her condition for sixteen years, and change is unlikely".</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">21 Professor Pridmore said that if he had been treating her he would probably treat her for "a couple of years" before he was willing to say her condition was permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">22 Dr David Weidmann examined the applicant on 17 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">He said in his report that 
 it is only with the fullness of time she has become totally and permanently impaired.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">By that I mean sometime in the early 1990s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">It seems to me to represent illogical thinking to now say that her condition was permanent prior to the 1st December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Whilst Dr Ashley may have been implying that, and saying words to that effect, clearly no-one else was agreeing with or listening to his opinion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Viewed without the benefit of hindsight, and viewed in the systemic sense (the labelling of impairment and [sic --- as?</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">] permanent or otherwise, is to a large degree systemic in nature) she was not totally and permanently impaired prior to 1st December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">23 He thought that looking back to 1988 it would have been "bordering on negligent not to view her as potentially treatable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">She was potentially treatable...".</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">24 In cross-examination Dr Weidmann accepted that notwithstanding the applicant was a lot better, the more significant symptoms have persisted from 1986 through to the time of the examination and those significant symptoms are permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">They were permanent because they have not disappeared and come back again.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">25 In answer to the Tribunal he said:
 If one looks at it with hindsight one can't avoid but calling it permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">But faced --- back then, nearly two decades ago, one doesn't have hindsight and at that time I don't think it would have been considered permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">26 Dr Ian Sale, a consultant psychiatrist, gave evidence for Comcare.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">He had examined the applicant on the instructions of Dobson, Mitchell and Allport in July 1990 in connection with a motor vehicle accident in February of that year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">27 The history the applicant gave then included her stress problems at work and the Hicks incident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">Dr Sale thought she had a significant anxiety disorder having features of both a generalised anxiety disorder and post-traumatic stress disorder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">He concluded that there was no psychological impediment to a return to work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">28 Dr Sale examined the applicant again, on the instructions of the Australian Government Solicitor for the purpose of the Tribunal proceeding, on 12 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">He was provided with most, if not all, of the medical reports of the other practitioners.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">He concluded that the applicant had been
 subject to fluctuating levels of anxiety and phobic symptoms over a period of close to twenty years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">There had been various diagnoses made, sometimes multiple diagnoses, but the common theme is of a propensity to experience anxiety symptoms, more so when away from the safety of her home, and especially in situations which do not allow ready escape (e.g.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">planes, buses, crowded supermarkets).</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">29 He continued:
 The causation of these difficulties is obviously difficult to assess after such a long time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Ms Excell is understandably keen to attribute these difficulties entirely to her workplace situation with the Department of Social Security circa 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">Other factors of possible relevance include a motor vehicle accident during 1986, an earlier medical history of recurrent pneumothorax (a frightening condition) and a marriage break down (there has also been a further road accident in 1999.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">When Ms Excell was asked about this she said it was an extremely trivial matter that was of no consequence).</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">...</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">Overall, the impression gained is that she has learned to live within the limitations her difficulties present her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">Her difficulties coping with travel seem to be the greatest source of distress to her in that they make it difficult for her to spend time with her only child, a son now in his 20's who left home about eight years ago.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">30 Dr Sale said that he believed it likely that the applicant's condition "was established prior to the 1 st December 1988".</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">31 He was asked by counsel for Comcare:
 Now, when you look back on a psychiatric condition some 21/22 years later, or thereabouts, and you obtain a history of continuing symptoms, perhaps varying in intensity from time to time, in your opinion, are you able to express any observations, perhaps might be a better way to put it, in relation to the permanence of them from the time of their inception?</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">--- Well, you might not have been able to do so at the time when you first met this person because you did not have the advantage of seeing what happens with the passage of time, but when you look back, if a condition is permanent, it had to have become permanent at some stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">It did not become permanent some significant time later just because you say it has; it had to be permanent at some stage before that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">The Tribunal's decision 
 
32 The learned Deputy President said:
 30.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Although this [Dr Sale's diagnosis of panic disorder with agoraphobia] differs from the diagnosis of Dr Ashley, Dr Weidmann and Professor Pridmore, I do not regard his disagreement as significant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Dr Sale conceded in cross-examination that her condition could be given a differential diagnosis of generalised anxiety disorder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">I do not believe anything turns upon the label or labels which are attached to the applicant's condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">All doctors have been talking about what is essentially the same chronic disorder which has impaired the applicant's functioning since 1986.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">That impairment increased until shortly after mid-1988, but although there have been fluctuations produced by situational variations in the applicant's lifestyle and her perceptions thereof, there have not been any such changes which can properly be characterised as new or increased changes to her levels of permanent impairment since 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">I do not accept Dr Weidmann's approach to the question of when the impairment became permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">I think his approach is not logical and I think that his responses to counsel during cross-examination tend to confirm this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">I accept the approach of Dr Sale which accords with my own views.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">31.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">Looking at the whole of the evidence I am left in no real doubt that however the applicant's psychological condition may be defined it was well entrenched before 1 December 1988 and had resulted in substantial impairment to the applicant before that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">Indeed, although there have been fluctuations in the intensity and duration of symptoms since 1 December 1988, the applicant's overall condition of impairment has not increased since that time, and viewed generally, she is now much improved and is likely to continue at about her current level.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">At the present she has managed to adapt her lifestyle to ameliorate many of her earlier symptoms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">However her underlying injury/disease remains and all indications suggest that it will continue indefinitely into the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Although it has been reasonable for doctors who have treated her to have made attempts to reduce her traumatised condition with massage and medication, the fact that they have done so, and have succeeded in reducing her level of impairment somewhat as a consequence, in no way militates against the conclusion that the impairment resulting from her condition was likely to continue indefinitely from the time of its establishment prior to 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">32.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">There certainly has been no new situation that has arisen since 1 December 1988 which, when assessed quantitatively or qualitatively can be characterised as a further or new impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">There is no sensible basis that I can see for concluding that an improvement in the applicant's condition from its original level of impairment can avail her claim under the transitional provisions of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">In my opinion it would be a nonsense to say that although her impairment now is less than it was before 1 December 1988, she has a "new" impairment which entitles her to claim lump sum compensation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">33 These conclusions need to be seen in the context of an earlier observation at [13].</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">The Tribunal there accepted the submission of Comcare that the mere fact that doctors may feel a need to observe and assess a person's condition over an extended period of time before feeling confident that the condition was "permanent" does not mean that the condition only became permanent at the time the diagnosis was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">In other words, medical practitioners could look back, and take into account the applicant's subsequent history, in coming to a conclusion as to whether or not her impairment was "permanent" as at 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">The Tribunal concluded:
 ...the decision as to when such a condition and the resultant impairment has become permanent is for the determining authority to decide on the basis of all the available evidentiary material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">In a case such as the present, that is Comcare in the first instance, or this Tribunal upon review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">A question of law?</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">
 
34 According to the applicant's notice of appeal, the question of law raised on the appeal is:
 Whether an employee is entitled to compensation pursuant to s 24 of the (1988 Act) where the employee suffers an impairment prior to the 1st December 1988 but which impairment significantly improves after the 1st December 1988 before becoming permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">35 On its face the notice of appeal does raise a question of law as required by s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Whether facts fully found fall within the provisions of a statute properly construed is usually a question of law: Hope v City of Bathurst [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">The formal requirement for a notice of appeal specified in O 53 r 3(2)(b) of the Federal Court Rules has been satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">36 However, as noted by Gummow J in TNT Skypak International (Aust) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1988] FCA 119 ; (1988) 82 ALR 175 at 178, in comparing the requirements of s 44 with the former provisions for appeals to the Taxation Board of Review:
 The existence of a question of law is now not merely a qualifying condition to ground the appeal, but also the subject matter of the appeal itself... 
37 The grounds in a notice of appeal from the Tribunal "would properly assume the resolution of the question of law in favour of the applicant": Australian Telecommunications Corporation v Lambroglou (1990) 12 AAR 515 at 524 per Ryan J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Such grounds should show "the links between the question of law, the circumstances of the particular case and the orders sought on the appeal": Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2003] FCAFC 232 ; (2003) 76 ALD 321 at [18] per Branson and Stone JJ (with whom Marshall J at [61] agreed).</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">38 Before going to the detail of the arguments of counsel for the applicant, I should say that on its face the question of law in the notice of appeal must be answered: Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">It is implicit in the question as stated that the impairment only "bec(ame) permanent" after 1 December 1988; it therefore must not have been permanent before that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">39 The Tribunal's reasoning is completely consistent with answering the question in the affirmative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The Tribunal, correctly, saw its task as determining whether or not the applicant's impairment was permanent before 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">Both parties conducted their cases accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">However, although there is a question of law properly stated in the applicant's notice of appeal, the answer to that question as stated does not assist her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">Her problem is that the Tribunal found, as a matter of fact, that her impairment was permanent before 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">40 In the light of the case presented to this Court, probably what the drafter of the notice had in mind was a situation where, before 1 December 1988, an impairment is permanent, or assessed by medical opinion as such.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Then after that date there is an improvement, but still later a relapse with the result that the person again has a permanent impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">41 In such a situation one conclusion would be that, viewed with hindsight (as the learned Deputy President, correctly in my view, held to be legitimate) the impairment was in truth always permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Alternatively, it might be found that what happened after 1 December 1988 was a new impairment, in which case the employee would be entitled to compensation under the 1988 Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">42 But in the present case there was ample evidence for the Tribunal to conclude that the applicant's impairment was permanent before 1 December 1988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">Any dispute on that finding can only raise questions of fact, which this Court has no jurisdiction to consider.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">Applicant's contentions on appeal 
 
43 Counsel for the applicant referred to Comcare v Levett (1995) 60 FCR 14 at [18]-[19].</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">In that case the employee had suffered a compensable injury to his back before 1 December 1988 which resulted in impairment, but not a permanent impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">After that date the impairment became permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">The Full Court held that he was not excluded from receiving compensation by s 124(3).</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">44 Counsel for the applicant contended that, by a parity of reasoning, the same result would follow if the applicant's injury was not permanent before the relevant date, improved thereafter, but still later became worse and permanent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">Counsel pointed to Dr Sale's opinion already noted that in his examination in 1990 the applicant was not incapacitated for work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">Counsel said that it was "a startling non sequitur" that since the applicant was permanently impaired in 2007 she must have been permanently impaired on 1 December 1988 even though she was not impaired in 1990.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">This arose, counsel said, from confusion between the concepts of injury and impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">Section 24(2)(b) of the 1988 Act requires, for the purpose of determining whether an impairment is permanent, regard to be had to the likelihood of an improvement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Therefore it is not possible to say with the benefit of hindsight that because the worker is now impaired she must have been always impaired.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">45 However, as previously noted, the impairment must have been permanent, that is to say likely to continue indefinitely, and that state of affairs must have been reached before the commencement date of the 1988 Act, if the applicant is to be excluded from lump sum compensation under that Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">46 The reasoning of the Tribunal critically turns on its finding of fact that the applicant's psychological condition was 
 well entrenched before 1 December 1988 and had resulted in substantial impairment to the applicant before that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">47 That was entirely a matter of fact.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">In essence the medical evidence uniformly (including Dr Weidmann's concessions in cross-examination) was to the effect that, in the light of subsequent events, it was at the time of the Tribunal hearing clear that the condition was permanent before 1 December 1988, whatever the prognosis may have been at that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">48 The appeal must be dismissed with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">I certify that the preceding forty-eight (48) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">Associate:

Dated: 27 May 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: J Green 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: John Green 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: B Dub&eacute; 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 24 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 May 2008 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/757.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>