<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Nicholls [2009] FCA 1002 (25 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1002.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">search warrants</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">application for the further stay of orders allowing the inspection of documents</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">by filing a notice of appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">federal court rules ) 52 r 15(2)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">extension of time to file notice of appeal not granted</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">therefore no notice of appeal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">further ground of stay being that similar matter is before the federal magistrates court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 On 23 July 2009, Mansfield J made orders allowing the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation to inspect documents seized by the Australian Federal Police and the Australian Tax Office from Mr Nicholls, at the time of execution of a search warrant on 6 May 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The search warrant had been issued by a Magistrate in this State on 5 May 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">At the time his Honour made that order, he made a further order staying that order for inspection until hearing a determination of an appeal on SAD 138 of 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The issue before his Honour in relation to the application by the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation to inspect documents was whether or not the documents were subject to legal professional privilege.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">It was Mr Nicholls' contention that the application for inspection should be refused because all of the documents were subject to legal professional privilege.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Mr Nicholls failed to make out his claim for legal professional privilege and so the order was made by his Honour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The appeal, which was the reason for the making of the stay order on 23 July 2009, was an appeal to the Full Court of the Federal Court from orders made by Mansfield J on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The issues with which he was concerned at that stage related to an application by Mr Nicholls to review decisions made by the Commissioner of Police and the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation, in relation to the issue of the search warrant on 5 May 2008 and its execution on 6 May 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On 15 January 2009, Mansfield J dismissed Mr Nicholls' application for review, both because it was incompetent and on the merits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Mr Nicholls appealed from those orders and that was the appeal which came before the Full Court of the Federal Court and which was the reason why the stay order was made by his Honour on 23 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">That was determined on 11 August 2009 and was dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The Full Court dismissed the appeal giving ex tempore reasons upholding the reasons for judgment for the orders made by Mansfield J on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Because that appeal has now been determined, the stay order which was made by Mansfield J on 23 July 2009 is no longer in force.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">That means, of course, that the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation is free to make the inspection which was the subject matter of the order made on 23 July 2009, unless there is some other impediment to the operation of his Honour's order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">On 21 August 2009 the applicant applied for a further stay of the orders made on 23 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The grounds of the application are to enable the respondent to file a notice of appeal from the orders of 23 July 2009, and for leave to file a notice of appeal out of time in relation to those orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">They were the only grounds identified in the notice of motion seeking a stay issued on 21 August 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Earlier today I heard the application for an extension of time within which to file and serve a notice of appeal from the orders made by Mansfield J and, for reasons given, dismissed that application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">The application for the stay, therefore, based upon Mr Nicholls bringing an appeal from his Honour's orders of 23 July 2009, must be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Mr Nicholls has said in other proceedings that he intends to seek special leave to appeal from the Full Court's decision given on 11 August 2009 from the High Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">However, he has not relied upon the fact of that application as a ground for a stay of the orders of 23 July 2009, nor could he in my opinion have done so, because he could not, I think, on any understanding identify a special leave point which would allow for the stay to be granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">During the hearing of this application, Mr Nicholls sought to rely upon a further ground for the stay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In SAD 138 of 2008, Mr Nicholls made an application on 20 August 2009 for the stay of the orders made by Mansfield J on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">That application was accompanied by an affidavit in which he exhibited an application which he had made to the Federal Magistrates Court on or about 20 August 2009 seeking a further review of a number of decisions, including the decisions which were the subject matter of the proceeding before Mansfield J on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">He abandoned that application for a stay (rightly, in my opinion) because there was no order in fact to be stayed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The order made by Mansfield J on 15 January 2009 simply dismissed the application, so there was no point in seeking a stay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">However, he now purports to rely upon the fact that he issued proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court as a reason for staying the orders made by Mansfield J on 23 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">I have allowed him to refer to the affidavit in SAD 138 of 2008, in order to finally deal with all of the interlocutory matters surrounding the two decisions of Mansfield J and the decision of the Full Court, and I allowed him to make reference to the proceeding which he has issued in the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">However in my opinion, the issue of that proceeding does not support the application for a stay, because the proceeding in the Federal Magistrates Court purports to have the Court review the decisions of the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation and the Commissioner of Police which were the subject matter of the proceeding before Mansfield J and disposed of by him on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">In my opinion, it would not be appropriate to stay the orders of 23 July 2009 made by Mansfield J, on the basis that the applicant wished to re-agitate in the Federal Magistrates Court the same issues which his Honour had disposed of on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Mr Nicholls said that the evidence which would support the application for a review of the decisions, which had been impugned in the proceedings before Mansfield J was different than that which had been adduced before his Honour in the proceeding disposed of on 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">He said he had obtained information during the currency of those proceedings and the proceedings disposed of by Mansfield J on 23 July 2009 and under the Freedom of Information Act , which would allow him to challenge those decisions on other evidential bases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">In my opinion, that also is not a good reason to stay the orders of 23 July 2009 made by Mansfield J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The time for Mr Nicholls to adduce evidence in relation to the decisions in which he complained was in the proceeding brought before Mansfield J which was disposed of in his orders of 15 January 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">It is not appropriate for the applicant to split his case or split his applications and rely upon different evidence for a review of the same decisions: Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">In my opinion, the fact of the issue of the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court does not support the application for a stay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The application then for a stay of Mansfield J's orders of 23 July 2009 is refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lander.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 4 September 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant Ms L Chapman 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 The Respondent appeared in person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Date of Hearing: 25 August 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 25 August 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1002.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>