<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Coast 2 Coast Earthmoving Pty Ltd v Stratti [2009] FCA 130 (13 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/130.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">default judgment</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">respondent had not entered an appearance or filed a defence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">service effective</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">respondent in default</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">judgment given.</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 
 BUCHANAN J: 
 These proceedings were commenced by application and statement of claim filed on 28 October 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">No defence has been filed by the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">On 28 November 2008, I made orders for substituted service on the respondent, having received evidence that efforts to serve him normally with the application and statement of claim had been to no avail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">I am satisfied from affidavit material, subsequently filed, that service was carried out in accordance with those orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The orders provided, amongst other things, that service would be deemed to be effective 14 days after the last of a series of steps of substituted service.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The last of those steps occurred on 5 December 2008 and service was therefore effected by 19 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The respondent has failed to file an appearance, to file a defence or to attend any directions hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Dr Greinke, who appears for the applicant, has today asked me to make an order for judgment on default under O 35A r 3 of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">He has persuaded me that it is appropriate to make such an order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">I gave Dr Greinke leave to file in Court written submissions which identify the justification for making the order and the calculation of the sum which is sought by way of judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The principal sum which is sought is $70,065.15.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">To that an amount of interest should be added to yield a total sum for which judgment will be given of $87,527.23.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Evidence has been filed concerning the costs which the applicant has incurred in relation to the present proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">They amount to $14,569.19.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Based upon that sum, a reasonable estimate of party-party costs is said to be $12,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Under O 62 r 36A of the Federal Court Rules , that sum should be reduced by one-third.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Costs are therefore sought in the sum of $8,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">I am satisfied that is a reasonable amount in the circumstances and the respondent will be required to pay costs in that amount.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">I make orders in the form of the orders handed up this morning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">I certify that the preceding four (4) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Buchanan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 20 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Dr A J Greinke 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Reichman Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 13 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 February 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/130.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>