<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nelson v Comcare [2009] FCA 1149 (8 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1149.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal on a question of law pursuant to s 44(1) of the administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">applicant contended that the administrative appeals tribunal failed to consider and address submissions which were seriously advanced by the applicant and worthy of serious consideration</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">applicant argued a case for compensation made under the safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth) in the alternative</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">alternative based upon aggravation of an existing psychiatric condition not considered or addressed by the tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">tribunal committed reviewable error of law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">tribunal's decision set aside</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">matter remitted to the tribunal for reconsideration according to law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 The applicant was employed by Centrelink at its Gosford Call Centre for a period of some years commencing in 2000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Not long after his employment commenced, he began to be stressed at work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The difficulties which he was experiencing at work came to a head in March 2003 when he was involved in a verbal altercation with a co-worker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The applicant has claimed compensation from the respondent under the Safety, Rehabilitation and Compensation Act 1988 (Cth) ( the Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">He made two claims, both of which were rejected by the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The first claim made by the applicant was a claim for Workers' Compensation made pursuant to s 14 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">That claim was dated 25 January 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">That claim was rejected on 3 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">In the letter rejecting the claim, the claim was described as: 
 
 ... aggravation of major depressive disorder, recurrent episode.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">
 

 The initial rejection by the respondent of the applicant's claim under s 14 of the Act was reviewed by an Independent Review Officer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">In a decision made on 27 September 2006, that officer confirmed the initial determination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The applicant then sought a review of that decision in the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ( the Tribunal ) (Application N2006/1488).</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">In mid 2006, lawyers representing the applicant forwarded a Compensation Claim for Permanent Injury to the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">At the same time, those lawyers requested: These additional claims were rejected by the respondent on 20 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">That decision was also reviewed and confirmed by a further decision given on 2 May 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The applicant then applied to the Tribunal for a review of the decision made by the respondent on 2 May 2007 to the effect that he was not entitled to compensation pursuant to ss 16 , 19 , 20 , 21 and 21A of the Act in respect of his claimed " aggravation of major depressive disorder, recurrent episode ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">On 19 March 2008, the Tribunal affirmed the two decisions made by the respondent dated 27 September 2006 and 2 May 2007 ( Nelson v Comcare [2008] AATA 214).</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The applicant appeals to this Court from that decision of the Tribunal pursuant to s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">An appeal under that section must be on a question of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The applicant's Notice of Appeal raises four questions of law and advances several grounds in support of his contentions in respect of those questions of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Despite the length of the Notice of Appeal, the applicant's appeal raises only one issue, namely, whether the Tribunal failed to address and make a determination concerning the applicant's contention that his underlying psychiatric condition was " aggravated " within the meaning of the definition of " disease " in s 4(1) of the Act by his employment with Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The applicant accepted that the above formulation of the matters which the applicant seeks to raise on appeal from the Tribunal captures the essence of the applicant's case on appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">THE RELEVANT LEGISLATIVE PROVISIONS 
 Section 14 of the Act provides that Comcare is liable to pay compensation in respect of an injury suffered by an employee if the injury results in death, incapacity for work or impairment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">At all relevant times, the terms injury , disease , aggravation , impairment and ailment were defined in s 4 of the Act as follows: 
 
 injury means:
 (a) a disease suffered by an employee; or
 (b) an injury (other than a disease) suffered by an employee, being a physical or mental injury arising out of, or in the course of, the employee's employment; or
 (c) an aggravation of a physical or mental injury (other than a disease) suffered by an employee (whether or not that injury arose out of, or in the course of, the employee's employment), being an aggravation that arose out of, or in the course of, that employment:
 but does not include any such disease, injury or aggravation suffered by an employee as a result of reasonable disciplinary action taken against the employee or failure by the employee to obtain a promotion, transfer or benefit in connection with his or her employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">disease means:
 (a) any ailment suffered by an employee; or
 (b) the aggravation of any such ailment;
 being an ailment or an aggravation that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment by the Commonwealth or a licensed corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">aggravation includes acceleration or recurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">impairment means the loss, the loss of the use, or the damage or malfunction, of any part of the body or of any bodily system or function or part of such system or function.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">ailment means any physical or mental ailment, disorder, defect or morbid condition (whether of sudden onset or gradual development).</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">
 

 It follows from the above definitions that: (a) When the expression injury is used in s 14(1) of the Act, it is intended to be used with the meaning accorded to it by the definition in s 4 ; (b) That definition includes "... a disease suffered by an employee "; (c) Disease means any ailment suffered by an employee or the aggravation of any such ailment being an ailment or an aggravation that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment by the Commonwealth or a licensed corporation; and (d) Aggravation is defined to include acceleration or recurrence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">THE TRIBUNAL DECISION 
 The Tribunal affirmed the decisions made by Comcare on 27 September 2006 and 2 May 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The Tribunal said (at [1] of its Reasons): 
 
 Mr Nelson ("The Applicant") was employed by Centrelink at its Gosford Call Centre.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">He has complained of a psychological condition, contending it was sustained because of his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">
 

 After briefly referring to the applicant's two applications in the Tribunal, the Tribunal formulated the issues which it had to decide as follows: 
 
 &#9679; Did the Applicant suffer from a psychological injury which resulted in impairment or an incapacity for work?</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">&#9679; If so, did the Applicant's employment with Centrelink contribute to the illness in a material degree?</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">&#9679; If yes, is the Applicant entitled to compensation for medical treatment under section 16 of the Act and to compensation for incapacity under sections 19 , 20 , 21 or 21A of the Act?</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">
 

 The Tribunal then referred to ss 4 , 14 , 16, 19 , 20 , 21 and 21A of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">It quoted extensively from ss 4 , 14 and 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">In particular, the Tribunal set out the definitions of disease and injury in the terms in which those definitions were expressed in s 4 of the Act at all relevant times.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The Tribunal then proceeded to examine the evidence before it and to make relevant findings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">These findings may be summarised as follows: The Tribunal then reviewed the medical evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Dr Butler, the applicant's treating psychiatrist, was of the opinion that the applicant had a psychological injury which was contributed to by his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">He said that the incident with the co-worker was only one of the reasons why the applicant had become symptomatic.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Dr Sagar, a psychiatrist who saw the applicant and testified at the behest of the respondent, described the applicant's condition as decompensation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">He said the applicant was in a melancholy depressive state.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">He said that the applicant had an obsessional or defensive narcissistic personality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Dr Sagar said that the incident with the co-worker was the straw that broke the camel's back.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">It was possible that the applicant had decompensated before joining Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The PTSD diagnosis in 1991 was significant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">Persons with that disorder typically, on securing a job, quickly have interpersonal problems at work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Dr Akkerman, a psychiatrist, also gave evidence on behalf of the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">He said that the applicant had a personality problem which was unaffected by his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">At [39]---[44] of its Reasons, the Tribunal referred to the parties' submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">At [40], the Tribunal noted that it was submitted on behalf of the applicant that the sole contributing factor to the applicant's condition was his employment with Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">There was no mention in this section of the Tribunal's Reasons of any submission directed to the concept of " aggravation of an ailment ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">At [45]---[60], the Tribunal considered each of the issues which it had identified at [3] of its Reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The Tribunal held that the applicant suffered from a psychological injury (Reasons at [45]---[47]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">It also held that the psychological injury from which the applicant suffered resulted in impairment and incapacity for work within the meaning of s 4 of the Act in March 2003, October 2003 and May 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">The Tribunal then considered the second issue which it had identified at [3] of its Reasons under the heading: " Did the Applicant's employment with Centrelink contribute to the condition in a material degree?</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">" At [50] of its Reasons, the Tribunal described this as " the crux of this case ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The Tribunal then discussed the concept of " material contribution " and the evidence relevant to that question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The Tribunal seemed to hold that the applicant already suffered from an underlying personality disorder when he commenced working for Centrelink (see [57] of the Tribunal's Reasons).</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">At [58] of its Reasons, the Tribunal said: 
 
 It does not follow, in our view, that the Applicant's work, through aggressive telephone calls and the co-worker incident, materially contributed to his condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The co-worker incident, in our view, produced only an episodic increase in his pre-morbid stress condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">
 
 The Tribunal then returned to the concept of " material contribution ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">At this point in its reasons, it referred to and discussed the judgment of Finn J in Comcare v Sahu-Khan [2007] FCA 15 ; (2007) 156 FCR 536.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">The Tribunal then concluded its Reasons with the following (at [60]): 
 
 After considering all the evidence, in particular the possible factors that may have contributed to the onset or aggravation of the Applicant's psychiatric condition, we find that the circumstances of the Applicant's employment with Centrelink did not substantially contribute to his disease.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Mr Nelson is not entitled to compensation pursuant to section 14 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">It follows that he is not entitled to compensation in respect of medical expenses under section 16, nor is he entitled to compensation for incapacity under sections 19 , 20 , 21 or 21A of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">
 

 The only places that the concept of " aggravation of an ailment " were mentioned at all in the Tribunal's Reasons was at [5] (when s 4 of the Act was extracted) and at [60].</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">CONSIDERATION AND DECISION 
 The applicant submitted that: It was submitted on behalf of the applicant that an ailment will be aggravated within the meaning of those expressions in the definitions contained in s 4 of the Act if it becomes more severe or is hastened in some way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The terms aggravation and acceleration in the present context have been given their normal English meanings in judgments of this Court (see Casarotto v Australian Postal Commission [1989] FCA 116 ; (1989) 86 ALR 399 at 404---405 and Martin v Australian Postal Corporation [1999] FCA 655 at [22] ---[28]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">In the present case, in order to make good the contention concerning aggravation of an existing ailment which the applicant submits was advanced to the Tribunal, the applicant would need to demonstrate that, at the time he commenced his employment with Centrelink, he was suffering an ailment within the relevant definition and that that ailment was aggravated (ie made more severe) by his employment by Centrelink or that the aggravation was contributed to in a material degree by his employment by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The notion of material contribution was explained by Finn J in Sahu-Khan [2007] FCA 15 ; 156 FCR 536.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">In that case, his Honour concluded that, in order to assess whether the aggravation of an ailment was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment, the Court was obliged to evaluate all relevant contributing factors in order to determine whether the employment made a contribution which was more than a mere contributing factor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">His Honour described the exercise as a matter of fact and degree ( Sahu-Khan [2007] FCA 15 ; 156 FCR 536 at [16] (p 542---543)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">The fundamental premise of the applicant's argument is that the Tribunal simply failed to address his case based upon alleged aggravation of an existing ailment (viz his underlying psychiatric condition).</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The Tribunal described the applicant's complaint at [1] of its Reasons as a complaint to the effect that his psychological condition was sustained because of his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">That language tends to suggest that the Tribunal regarded the applicant's case as being confined to a case based upon the contention that he sustained an ailment as an employee of Centrelink, being an ailment that was contributed to in a material degree by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The terms of the general formulation of the issue in [1] of the Tribunal's Reasons tend to suggest that the Tribunal did not regard aggravation of an existing ailment as being an alternative basis for the applicant's claims before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The language used by the Tribunal in the second dot point in [3] of its Reasons also suggests that the Tribunal did not have under consideration the question of aggravation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">As mentioned at [26]---[27] above, the Tribunal described the crux of the case as being captured in the heading to the last part of its Reasons for Decision, namely: " Did the Applicant's employment with Centrelink contribute to the condition in a material degree?</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">" At [58], the Tribunal appears to make a finding that the applicant's condition was not materially contributed to by his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Whilst it is true that the word aggravation appears in [60] of the Tribunal's Reasons, the substance of that paragraph is a finding directed to the question of whether or not the applicant's employment substantially contributed to his psychiatric condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">That is to say, the proposition being addressed in that paragraph of the Tribunal's Reasons is: Was the onset of the applicant's condition caused by or materially contributed to by the applicant's employment by Centrelink?</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">In [60] of its Reasons, there is no application of the mind of the Tribunal to the alternative case put by the applicant to the effect that his underlying psychiatric condition was made more severe or hastened by his employment by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">For these reasons, I am of the view that the Tribunal did fail to address the question of aggravation in its Reasons and in its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">But that is not the end of the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">The Tribunal would not be obliged to address the question of aggravation unless the applicant had advanced a case to the Tribunal based upon aggravation of his underlying psychiatric condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The submissions made on behalf of the applicant to the Tribunal were made orally.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">They were amplified by a Written Submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">In the Written Submission, the author of that document did not develop with any precision the reasons why it was contended on behalf of the applicant that the applicant had suffered a disease at work of the requisite kind.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">There is a heading in the document as follows: 
 
 Section 14 --- Aggravation of a Disease 
 

 
Under that heading, there is reference to s 14 and to the definitions of injury and disease in s 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">But, as I have said, there is no development of the argument so as to make clear the basis upon which the proposition that the applicant had suffered a disease of the requisite kind was being advanced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">In his oral submissions to the Tribunal, Counsel for the applicant did specifically put that the applicant had suffered an aggravation of a disease and thus an injury at work.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">A little later in his submissions, aggravation was mentioned again.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">It is also fair to say that the submissions made in the Tribunal on behalf of the applicant seemed also to rely upon sub-clause (a) of the definition of disease in the sense that Counsel argued that the applicant had sustained his psychological condition as a result of his employment by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Counsel for the respondent quite properly and fairly conceded that the question of aggravation had been argued before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">His submissions in the appeal proceeded upon the footing that the case based upon aggravation of the applicant's existing psychiatric condition had been understood and addressed by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">It was submitted on behalf of the respondent that conformably with the medical evidence adduced by the respondent before the Tribunal, the Tribunal found that the applicant suffered from underlying psychological disorders which were inevitably going to bubble to the surface in the workplace and that those disorders had not been aggravated by the applicant's employment by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">All that had happened was that the inevitable consequences of those disorders manifested themselves during the applicant's employment by Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Counsel for the respondent submitted that the medical evidence made clear that the applicant's underlying condition was such that it was always going to manifest itself in the ways that it did, no matter where he worked or what the circumstances of his employment turned out to be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">Counsel was at some pains to demonstrate that there was a significant body of medical evidence before the Tribunal which would have justified a conclusion being reached by the Tribunal to the effect that, notwithstanding the fact that the applicant did suffer from an underlying condition, the symptoms which manifested themselves from 2003 onwards were the inevitable result of that underlying condition rather than the result of exacerbating factors caused by his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">It is true that there is evidence to that effect submitted by Counsel for the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">However, there was also evidence called on behalf of the applicant to the effect that the applicant's underlying condition was made worse or more severe by his employment with Centrelink.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">I do not think that the respondent can answer the criticisms presently raised by the applicant by submitting, in effect, that, if the Tribunal had considered the question of aggravation, it would inevitably have come to the view that the applicant's underlying condition was not aggravated by his employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">Of course, I appreciate that the respondent does not quite put its submission in this way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The respondent's submission is that the Tribunal did, in fact, address the question of aggravation and gave it short shrift.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The respondent submitted that the Tribunal was entitled to give the question of aggravation short shrift because there was a substantial body of evidence that would justify the Tribunal taking that approach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The applicant did argue before the Tribunal that his underlying condition had been aggravated by his employment in the sense contemplated by the definitions in s 4 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">The argument was not developed much but this does not detract from the fact that the argument was put.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">The Tribunal was obliged to turn its mind to the argument and to deal with the question of aggravation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">It was a significant part of the applicant's case before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">The argument was seriously advanced by the applicant and was worthy of serious consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">Whilst it is true that the Tribunal is not required to consider and address every submission made to it, serious submissions of the type to which I have just alluded must be addressed ( Dennis Willcox Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1988) 79 ALR 267 at 276---277 per Jenkinson J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">It is an error of law for the Tribunal not to consider such a submission and not to reveal its consideration of that submission in its Reasons for Decision (see Hartnett v Migration Agents Registration Authority [2004] FCA 50 at [50] ; and Australian Postal Corporation v Sellick [2008] FCA 236 ; (2008) 245 ALR 561 at [88] ---[89] (pp 579---480)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">This statement of principle is consistent with the more general statements of principle directed to giving content to the concept of error of law made by the Full Court in Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 at [59] (pp 597---598).</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">In order to meet its obligations in this regard, it was incumbent upon the Tribunal to turn its mind by a rational process of reasoning to the question of aggravation and to come to a view as to whether or not the applicant's argument should be acceded to.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">In order to meet those requirements in the present case, the Tribunal was obliged to make reference to the relevant medical evidence, to come to a view about that evidence and to explain its reasons for doing so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">It was then obliged to relate that evidence to the notion of aggravation by reference to the relevant statutory provisions and authorities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">The Tribunal did none of those things.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">Counsel for the applicant also submitted that the Tribunal had committed a reviewable error of law by failing to give any or adequate reasons for its decision when it failed to address the applicant's case based upon aggravation of an existing ailment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">I think that the error committed by the Tribunal is more aptly described as a failure to consider and address that case rather than a failure to give reasons or adequate reasons for rejecting that case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">For these reasons, the Tribunal's decision must be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">I will make orders accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">The applicant seeks an order that, in the event that his appeal is successful, the matter be remitted to a differently constituted Tribunal to be determined according to law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">This application was not supported by any particular submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">I do not think that the applicant has made out a case for such an order and I decline to make an order in those terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">I certify that the preceding fifty-four (54) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Foster.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 8 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr D Richards 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Slater &amp; Gordon Lawyers 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Mr B Dub&eacute; of Sparke Helmore Lawyers (Appeared) 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Dibbs Barker 
 Date of Hearing: 17 December 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 8 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1149.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>