<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Shingles v Defence Force Retirement and Death Benefits Authority [2009] FCA 1211 (30 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1211.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">reasonable apprehension of bias</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">waiver of right to object at hearing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">right to object not waived</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">revival of bias in decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">decision contrived by preconceived view of appellant</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">denial of procedural fairness</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">issue critical to the decision not put to applicant by tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">administrative law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 In this matter it has been conceded by the respondent authority that during the hearing of this matter before the Administrative Appeals Tribunal a member of the Tribunal so conducted himself as to give rise to a reasonable apprehension of bias.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">While counsel for the appellant, Graham Shingles, took issue with comments made by the Tribunal Member during oral submissions, the two principal questions which arise in this appeal are, first, whether counsel nonetheless waived his right to object after the determination of the appeal to the Tribunal and, secondly, whether the Tribunal's decision itself bespeaks grounds for a reasonable apprehension of bias in the making of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">I need only deal with the latter matter in any detail, though I am satisfied that there was no election made to waive bias in any event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">As I will note below, two claims of denial of procedural unfairness hang off the matters founding the bias allegations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Factual Setting
 The procedural history of this matter is a somewhat protracted one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The appellant was discharged from the Army on 26 October 1971.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">It is for this reason that the law governing his application for invalidity benefits is the Defence Forces Retirement Benefits Act 1948 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Part 5 of that Act provided invalidity benefits for members of the scheme established by the Act who had been retired on the ground of invalidity or physical or mental incapacity to perform their duties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Section 51(6) provided for the Authority to treat members as if they had been retired on the grounds of incapacity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The initial classification of a member is made pursuant to s 51 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">That section provides that the Authority should determine the member's percentage of incapacity in relation to civil employment and should classify the person according to the percentage of incapacity as follows: 60% or more: Class A 30% or more but less than 60%: Class B Less than 30%: Class C 
 Section 52 provided for the rate of pension payable to a member classified in each class.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">A member classified Class C is not entitled to the payment of an ongoing pension.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Section 53 of the Act gives the authority power to review from time to time a member's classification according to matters set out in s 53(1A) and s 53(1B).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">A member initially classified Class C is not entitled to be reclassified at any later date: s 53(4).</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">On 26 February 2002, the Tribunal ordered by consent that, pursuant to s 51(6) of the 1948 Act, the appellant should be treated as if he had been retired from the Defence Force, on the ground of invalidity or physical or mental incapacity to perform his duties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">On 30 April 2002 the appellant provided an "Application for invalidity benefits &amp; Superannuation Productivity".</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">On 18 June 2002 the appellant was classified as Class C with effect from 27 October 1971.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">On 6 December 2002, following reconsideration, the Authority confirmed the decision and the appellant applied to the Tribunal for review of that decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">On 17 May 2004 the Tribunal affirmed the decision under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">That decision was set aside on appeal by the Federal Magistrates Court and the matter remitted to the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">On 2 March 2007, following a further hearing, the Tribunal again affirmed the decision, finding that the appellant had an incapacity of 25%.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">An appeal to the Federal Magistrates Court was dismissed and it is from that decision that the appellant now appeals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">The appellant, at the time of his discharge, suffered relevantly from os calcis exostosis (heel spurs) and from alcohol dependence either as a sequelae of Post Traumatic Stress Disorder or as a separate condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The appellant gave an account of his service in Vietnam and of his work history on his return to Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">He gave evidence about the effect his alcohol dependency had on his ability to obtain and more importantly retain employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The effects of alcohol dependence (which existed at the time of discharge) on the appellant's capacity for civil employment was a critical issue before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The Tribunal addressed the appellant's psychiatric impairment, which comprehended his alcohol dependence, at paras [60] to [68].</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Although the Tribunal appears to have accepted that the appellant had many jobs and could only retain them for a short period, it apparently did not accept that the alcohol dependence was the cause or was significant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Rather, the Tribunal concluded that the appellant had exaggerated the effects of his alcohol dependence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The Tribunal's reasons and decision were heavily influenced by its view of the appellant's credibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The Federal Magistrate's Decision
 An appeal from the Tribunal's decision was made to the Federal Magistrates Court under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Relevantly for present purposes, the Federal Magistrate found that the judgment of the Presiding Senior Member was affected by bias in that he was, from an early stage, inherently sceptical of Mr Shingle's evidence about his experiences both in Vietnam and as to his capacity to work in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">In the Tribunal's reasons, para 47, his Honour considered the Senior Member's bias about that evidence was based "upon his own experiences in Vietnam".</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">His Honour went on to observe that the Senior Member's experience overbore his better judgment and objectivity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Nonetheless, his Honour concluded that notwithstanding the Senior Member's comments to which I will later refer were such as to cause reasonable apprehension on the part of the lay observer that his judgment would be affected by bias, the appellant waived the right subsequently to object.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Further, the bias was not "repeated" in the Tribunal's decision itself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">The claim that Mr Shingles was denied procedural fairness because he was not given the opportunity to be heard on the question whether he exaggerated his capacity to retain employment was rejected by the Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">His Honour was of the view that the Tribunal's conclusions were ones it was entitled to reach following consideration of the material and that it was not necessary for the Tribunal to put each and every proposition to a witness as the evidence proceeds, not least because the Tribunal may only arrive at its conclusions once the evidence is concluded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The Appeal
 The principal grounds of appeal in this matter were that the learned Federal Magistrate erred in both his bias and procedural fairness conclusions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">In order to illuminate the basis upon which the appeal is being prosecuted, it will be necessary to refer in a little detail to particularly the transcript of the evidence before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">It is only by reference to what was said there that the underpinning of the bias claim is manifest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The denial of procedural fairness appeal has three bases: (1) the Tribunal decided the matter on the basis of the appellant's credit when this was not attacked by the respondent but rather was expressly disavowed; (2) the Tribunal found the appellant's account of his service in Vietnam was exaggerated and that he exaggerated the facts of his disabilities on his capacity to obtain and retain employment when this was not part of the respondent's case and was not put to the appellant in cross-examination; and (3) the Tribunal relied on its own knowledge and experience about Vietnam which was not in evidence and was not put to the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Applicable Principles
 (a) Reasonable Apprehension of Bias
 There is no controversy between the parties as to the principles to be applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The inquiry is whether a fair minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the Tribunal might not bring an impartial mind to the resolution of the question it is required to decide: Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2000) 205 CLR 337 at [6] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The development and application of the test of reasonable apprehension of bias avoids the need for a court: 
 
 "to attempt some analysis of the likely or actual thought processes of the decision-maker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It objectifies what otherwise would be a wholly subjective inquiry and it poses the relevant question in a way that avoids having to predict what probably will be done, or to identify what probably was done, by the decision-maker in reaching the decision in question: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at [184] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">
 
 What is in issue for present purposes is what are the principles to be applied where, from comments made during the course of a hearing, such a reasonable apprehension may be thought to arise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">It is accepted that they are as stated in the joint judgment of Brennan, Deane and Gaudron JJ and in that of Toohey J in Vakauta v Kelly [1989] HCA 44 ; (1989) 167 CLR 568.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">In the joint judgment the following principles were stated (at 572): 
 
 Where ... comments which are likely to convey to a reasonable and intelligent lay observer an impression of bias have been made, a party who has legal representation is not entitled to stand by until the contents of the final judgment are known and then, if those contents prove unpalatable, attack the judgment on the ground that, by reason of those earlier comments, there has been a failure to observe the requirement of the appearance of impartial judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">By standing by, such a party has waived the right subsequently to object.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">The reason why that is so is obvious.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In such a case, if clear objection had been taken to the comments at the time when they were made or the judge had then been asked to refrain from further hearing the matter, the judge may have been able to correct the wrong impression of bias which had been given or alternatively may have refrained from further hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">It would be unfair and wrong if failure to object until the contents of the final judgment were known were to give the party in default the advantage of an effective choice between acceptance and rejection of the judgment and to subject the other party to a situation in which it was likely that the judgment would be allowed to stand only if it proved to be unfavourable to him or her (at 572).</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">
 
 The qualification placed upon this was stated to be (at 573): 
 
 The statements which the learned trial judge had made about his preconceived views of Dr Lawson [an expert witness] were, however, effectively revived by what his Honour said in his reserved judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The appellant's failure to object to the comments made in the course of the trial cannot, in our view, properly be seen as a waiver of any right to complain if comments made about Dr Lawson in the judgment itself would, in the context of those earlier comments, have the effect of conveying an appearance of impermissible bias in the actual decision to a reasonable and intelligent lay observer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">... the line between comments which would be likely to have that effect and comments which would not is necessarily an imprecise one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">
 
 The judgment of Toohey J was to like effect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Because of their present relevance I would note in particular at the following observations made by his Honour (at 587): 
 
 There is no reason why, in authority or in principle, a litigant who is fully aware of the circumstances from which ostensible bias might be inferred, should not be capable of waiving the right later to object to the judge continuing to hear and dispose of the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">That is not to say that the litigant in such a position must expressly call upon the judge to withdraw from the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">It may be enough that counsel make clear that objection is taken to what the judge has said, by reason of the way in which the remarks will be viewed .</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">It will then be for the judge to determine what course to adopt, in particular whether to stand down from the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">For counsel to invite the judge to withdraw from the case may be quite premature, particularly if the judge acknowledges the apparent bias in what has been said and thereafter takes steps to dispel that apprehension.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">But, as Dawson J noted in Re J.R.L.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">; Ex parte C.J.L.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">[(1986) [1986] HCA 39 ; 161 CLR 342 at 372], suspicion of bias based on preconceptions existing independently of the case "may well be ineradicable".</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">In that situation there will be no option but to ask the judge to disqualify himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">In any event objection must be taken: see Re McCrory; Ex parte Rivett [(1995) 21 VLR 3 at 6].</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">(Emphasis added.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">) 
 
 (b) Denial of Procedural Fairness
 I should emphasise at the outset that what is complained of here is not that, when confronted with inconsistencies in the appellant's evidence, the Tribunal made choices unfavourable to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Rather it is that the Tribunal made it a critical issue in the matter that the appellant "[had] attempted to exaggerate the facts of his disabilities in his obtaining and retaining employment" and that this was not put to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Both parties accept that, for present purposes, the law is sufficiently stated in the reasons of the High Court in SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592 at [29] - [32] : 
 
 No submission was made on behalf of either the appellant or the minister that the existence or content of the obligation to accord procedural fairness was directly affected by any provision of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">Rather, the argument proceeded, for the most part, by reference to what had been said by the Full Court of the Federal Court in [ Commissioner for Australian Capital Territory Revenue v Alphaone Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1074 ; (1994) 49 FCR 576].</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Full Court (Northrop, Miles and French JJ) said: 
 

 
 
 
 Where the exercise of a statutory power attracts the requirements for procedural fairness, a person likely to be affected by the decision is entitled to put information and submissions to the decision-maker in support of an outcome that supports his or her interests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">That entitlement extends to the right to rebut or qualify by further information, and comment by way of submission, upon adverse material from other sources which is put before the decision-maker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">It also extends to require the decision-maker to identify to the person affected any issue critical to the decision which is not apparent from its nature or the terms of the statute under which it is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">The decision-maker is required to advise of any adverse conclusion which has been arrived at which would not obviously be open on the known material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Subject to these qualifications however, a decision-maker is not obliged to expose his or her mental processes or provisional views to comment before making the decision in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">[emphasis added] 
 
 

 
 
 Particular attention was directed in argument in this court, as it had been in the courts below, to the tribunal's conclusion that the three identified elements of the appellant's story were not "plausible".</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Was that a conclusion "which would not obviously be open on the known material"?</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">Or was it no more than a part of the "mental processes" by which the tribunal arrived at its decision?</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">
 

 
 
 Stated in this way, the argument seeks to elucidate the content of the requirements of procedural fairness by setting up a dichotomy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">There are two reasons to exercise considerable care in approaching the problem in that way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">First, it is far from clear that the two categories that are identified (conclusions not obviously open on the known material, and mental processes of decision-making) encompass all possible kinds of case that may fall for consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Secondly, there is a very real risk that focusing upon these two categories will distract attention from the fundamental principles that are engaged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">
 

 
 
 In Alphaone the Full Court rightly said (at 590-591]: 
 

 
 
 
 It is a fundamental principle that where the rules of procedural fairness apply to a decision-making process, the party liable to be directly affected by the decision is to be given the opportunity of being heard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">That would ordinarily require the party affected to be given the opportunity of ascertaining the relevant issues and to be informed of the nature and content of adverse material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">[emphasis added] 
 
 
 THE TRANSCRIPT OF THE HEARING AND THE TRIBUNAL'S REASONS 
 By way of background I should emphasise that the issue before the Tribunal was "the percentage of total incapacity of [Mr Shingles] in relation to civil employment ": s 51(2): see Re Bos and Defence Forces Retirement and Death Benefits Authority (1977) 20 ALR 663 at 666-667.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Mr Shingles gave a deal of evidence of his history of obtaining and retaining employment and of the difficulties his alcohol abuse posed in both of those respects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">His evidence was that he had 28 jobs in 18 years and that many of these were in the early years after discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I should note that the Tribunal was constituted by two members --- a Senior Member who had had service experience in Vietnam, and a Member who was a medical practitioner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">As the bias claim relates to comments made by the Senior Member, I will for ease in exposition refer only to that member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">(a) The Transcript
 On the first page of the transcript at the first day of hearing the following exchange is recorded between the Senior Member and Mr Shingles' counsel: 
 
 Mr White: If the Tribunal would be assisted by the applicant traversing all of the matters then I will take him through.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: Well, having read what he has said about his Vietnam service, we're rather hoping that Mr Dillon [the Authority's counsel] might explore that in some detail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: If he doesn't, we will.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Is there anything in particular the senior Member has in mind, otherwise - - - 
 

 
 
 Senior Member: I've got lots of things in mind but I will save that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">
 
 Mr Dillon's exploration of Mr Shingle's Vietnam service was quite brief.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">He concluded by asking the Tribunal member if he had any further questions, to which the member replied (Tr 35): 
 
 Well, I will, after you have finished.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">
 

 
At Transcript 39, the Tribunal took up the subject of Vietnam service.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">I would note the following:
 
 
 Now, I want to go back to, your stay in Vietnam.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">So, I'm looking at your statement, paragraph 17, you're saying, "Many patrols went out each night and many soldiers were brought in injured as a result of booby traps and clashes with Vietnamese"?---Yes, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">
 

 
 
 And this was happening at Vung Tau, was it?---A couple of times, sir, yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">
 

 
 
 A couple of times?---Yes, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">
 

 
 
 Really, and were they causalities in your unit?---No, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">
 

 
 
 Did you see the causalities?---At times I did, sir, yes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">
 

 
 
 I see, and where did you see these casualties?---At 1 Field Hospital at the chopper pad, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">
 

 
 
 Well, if they occurred at [V]ung Tau, there was hardly a need to bring them in by chopper, was there?---That's where they were, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">
 

 
 
 And you say that they were due to incidents which occurred on the perimeter at [V]ung Tau?---Yes, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">
 

 
 
 Right?---I think that was mainly D and E Platoon involved there, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">
 

 
 
 How many soldiers did you see shoot themselves in the leg or the foot?---The actual one I was involved with, sir, was Michael Keating.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">
 

 
 
 Yes, but did you see it?---No, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">
 

 
 
 No, and you say three, what about the others?---No, I never seen them, sir.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">
 

 
 
 Right?---If you mean, like, I didn't see it, sir, I seen it, but not when it happened, I was there a couple of minutes after it happened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">I actually helped carry him to the hospital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">
 
 At the very end of his final submissions, Mr Shingle's counsel indicated that he would conclude "unless the Tribunal would be assisted by me addressing any other matter".</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">Then ensued the following exchange (Tr 73-75): 
 
 Senior Member: No, I'll just mention it to you, cautionary; it seems to me that the question of the credit of the applicant hasn't been drawn into issue in these proceedings, has it ?</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">
 

 
 
 Mr White: It doesn't seem to have been drawn into issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: I mean were it to be so one would have to approach the evidence, etcetera with that in mind.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">Let me honest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">You look at some of the early psychiatric matters; either they were very poor history-takers or else he was completely confused as to what he was doing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Not necessarily.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Mr Dinnen said this morning that it was not uncommon that people wouldn't say things unless on direct question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: Well, you can take some of Dr Duncan's early reports, he had him as a driver in Vietnam.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">He had him with 7 and 8RAR.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">
 

 
 
 Mr White: There are all sorts of things like that scattered throughout these notes, Senior Member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">He had him as a menswear shop assistant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">I mean these are little anomalies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Whether or not they ultimately go to credit is a different question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">In my submission they don't.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: I mean look at his own statement, paragraph 17: 
 

 
 
 
 Many patrols went out each night and many soldiers were brought in injured as a result of booby traps and clashes with the Vietnamese.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">
 
 

 
 
 Now, if he's talking about [V]ung Tau he's lying through his teeth.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The only danger to any Australian soldier in Vung Tau was booze and bar girls.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">
 

 
 
 Mr White: None of that has ever been put to the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: No, it hasn't been and that's my caveat, it never has.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">
 

 
 
 Mr White: No.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: But going through the reports it's clear that you know it's a very confused history.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">
 

 
 
 Mr White: First of all it hasn't been challenged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">Secondly, the Tribunal is prohibited from relying on its own knowledge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: Lucky for your client.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Well, it would place us in an incredibly difficult position even though the Tribunal has now at the end of the case said what his view is about [V]ung Tau.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">
 

 
 
 Senior Member: Well, let me say this much.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">I'm certainly very conscious of the laws of evidence and that Tribunals particularly should not place their own opinions or experience in the place of evidence and as you've pointed out there has been no challenge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">What I am saying is though that I have certain views as to over-emphasis in the affidavit and what we term or have termed are very confusing histories taken by various medical practitioners, so that it would not --- and I want to hear you on this --- I can certainly for myself take into account that some of the histories are of themselves inconsistent and any evidence must be taken into account that the applicant for many reasons, PTSD plus his alcoholism, etcetera he's a poor historian.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Well, it may be an additional factor as well if the Tribunal please and that is the questions asked might also play a part in differences --- I don't say inconsistencies --- between one report and another.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">So in my submission it's not just the applicant being a poor historian for whatever reason but what was asked I think has changed over the years as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">It's clear from Dr Dinnen once the PTSD was acknowledged as - - - 
 

 
 
 Senior Member: What he's asked is one thing but a history is another thing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">
 

 
 
 Mr White: Suffice to say that if there were challenges to that then no doubt the applicant would have given evidence about things like that but it [wasn't] done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">(Emphasis added.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">) 
 
 During the final submissions of the Authority's counsel the Tribunal observed (Tr 78): 
 
 I mean this is one of those cases where it would have been very helpful, Mr Dillon, if we could have got somebody from the unit at the time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">I mean what were all the surrounding circumstances?</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Apparently he threatened the CSM, but we don't have his service documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Apparently he was never charged with any military offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">
 

 
 
 Mr Dillon: No, there is a record, I think it's T4, of his service record and there is no recorded offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">Yes, I certainly take your point.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">
 

 
Later the member commented in relation to Mr Shingles' involvement in engagements with the enemy in Vietnam (Tr 79):
 
 
 It would be interesting to have the unit war diary on that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">
 
 The Authority, acknowledged and made submissions on inconsistencies in the history but went on (Tr 79): 
 
 We did not challenge Mr Shingles' credibility as such but we have recognised that the histories given to the doctors have been very flawed and inconsistent in many ways and in significant ways that cause us to submit that some of the assessments shouldn't be accepted by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">
 

 (b) The Tribunal's Reasons
 The appellant relies upon some number of passages in the Tribunal's reasons which, when considered in the context of the Senior Member's comments during the hearing, are said to "have the effect of conveying an appearance of impermissible bias in the actual decision to a reasonable and intelligent lay observer": Vakauta at 573.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">I set these out in order: On 10 September 1970 the Applicant commenced his Vietnam service, being posted to 2 nd Australian Ordnance Depot at Vung Tau.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">Although the Applicant has given accounts of his service in South Vietnam, we regard that account as exaggerated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">It is unfortunate that the Respondent did not investigate the Applicant's claims more thoroughly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">Had the services of a research organisation such as "Writeway" been engaged, their report would have been of material assistance to the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">Following discharge from the Army the Applicant returned to live at Woodonga with his wife.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">For a period of months he did not work but contented himself with going to the hotel each day and drinking until he had run out of money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">Asked about his source of income at this time, he told this Tribunal that his wife was working, whereas he had told the previous Tribunal his wife was not working.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">(Emphasis added.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">) 
 Whereas the Applicant claims that a supervisor informed him he was to be "sacked" because of his frequent absences, there is no evidence that he received any warnings from his employers that his attendance record or work was unsatisfactory.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">We find it difficult to believe that the Applicant would have been peremptorily dismissed from employment with a Commonwealth Authority without first being subjected to a formal warning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">Apparently after voluntarily terminating his employment with the Department of Army the Applicant and his wife moved to Sydney.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">They lived on the Northern Beaches, and we know from the Applicant's Record of Service that at a time he was in the Army, his mother was living at Fairlight which is a suburb of the Northern Beaches.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">Upon arriving in Sydney the Applicant did not initially seek employment but contented himself with attending hotels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">After about one month, because he needed money, he obtained a paid job as a lube operator, lasting for some three months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">The Applicant then purchased an orange juice run.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">This franchised business failed because the Applicant did not devote enough time and attention to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">He places the failure to properly attend to the business upon his frequenting hotels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">(Emphasis added.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">)
 Despite the Applicant maintaining that he was unable to retain employment because of his alcoholism and the effects of his PTSD, document T97, p220, is a reference dated 4 July 1977 which concludes "I will be sorry to loose him but he goes with my best wishes for the future".</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">Whereas document T97, p221, is a reference from the Secretary Manager of the Cowra Services Club Ltd which reads inter alia, "Graham carried out his duties in a satisfactory and competent manner and I would have no hesitation in recommending him for a similar position".</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">We are not persuaded to take those expressions as to his worth at other than face value.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">In cross-examination the Applicant conceded that when he obtained the job at Bandiana he was able to perform the tasks required of him, and that at any time he needed to get a job he was able to get one.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">We are therefore satisfied that the Applicant has attempted to exaggerate the effects of his disabilities in his obtaining and retaining employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">Post discharge the Applicant did not immediately seek work but on his account was drinking heavily.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">However, he did ultimately obtain a job and although he says he left before he could be sacked, there is no evidence of any official warning that his behaviour was placing his job in jeopardy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">He and his then wife moved to Sydney and again he was able to obtain employment when he felt of the need.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">The Applicant claimed that his real problem was the inability to retain employment due to his alcohol abuse.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">This statement does not fit with the very positive references the Applicant obtained from the Cowra Services Club and the Galloping Grape Restaurant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">Whereas it is not now disputed that the Applicant does have PTSD and alcohol dependence, the evidence is that the symptoms of PTSD, if they affected the Applicant at all at time of discharge, were mild in the extreme.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">Likewise, his alcohol dependence was present but given the references referred to above and his ability to obtain employment whenever he needed to, we find that he has exaggerated it effects upon him at time of discharge and thereafter until probably about 1979 --- the time of his first conviction for an alcohol-related offence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">As to the Tribunal's final comment, I would note in passing that, in his affidavit that was before the Tribunal, Mr Shingles noted that: 
 
 On or about 13/12/73 I lost my driving licence for three years as a result of drink driving.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">
 
 Consideration
 I will consider first the bias appeal and then will refer briefly to procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">Though the Federal Magistrate appears to have made a finding of actual bias because of the Senior Member's comments at the hearing, my own view is that the proper characterisation of the matter at that point in the Tribunal's review was that the circumstances would have founded a reasonable apprehension of bias in the Senior Member.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">The parties to the appeal have accepted the appropriateness of this characterisation of the position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">Where the parties part company is on the question whether the appellant waived its right to object.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">The respondent contends that the appellant had reasonable time after the hearing within which to raise the bias issue but did not do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">He was legally represented.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">He merely waited until the decision was made and, finding it to be adverse, objected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">It was too late.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">The right, it is said, had been waived.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">The appellant's case in contrast is that, notwithstanding the Tribunal's comments at the hearing, counsel did challenge the senior Member who then appeared in the comments he made (at Tr 74) to have retreated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">It was in these circumstances not unreasonable not to object to the Senior Member continuing to sit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">While it is not strictly necessary for me to express a final conclusion on this difference, my own view accords with the appellant's submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">The appellant, having raised the issues of Mr Shingles' credit not having been challenged and of the impropriety of the Senior Member relying on his own knowledge, the response made by the Senior Member was sufficient to make it unnecessary to object to his continuing to sit: cf Vakauta at 587 per Toohey J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">The Senior Member's comments could reasonably be taken to signal a retreat to the confines of what was permissible to an administrative decision-maker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">I am in consequence not satisfied that the right to object was waived.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">I consider the Federal Magistrate erred in so concluding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">The fundamental issue raised in Mr Shingles' bias appeal is whether the Tribunal's decision, considered in the context of the comments made at the hearing, has the effect of conveying "the appearance of impermissible bias in the actual decision".</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">I consider that it does.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">The reasonable and intelligent lay observer might reasonably apprehend, in light of the Senior Member's comments, commentary and attitudes revealed at the hearing relating to Mr Shingles' war service, that Mr Shingles' claim might have been prejudged and that the evidence of this in the decision itself was afforded both in how the Tribunal characterised (disparagingly) Mr Shingles' own evidence on his obtaining and retaining employment and in the tone of some of the language used to describe his evidence (eg "For a period of months he did not work but contented himself with going to the hotel" ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">I am satisfied that the decision arrived at might reasonably be said to have been contrived by a preconceived view taken of Mr Shingles with the consequence that the case he advanced might not have been fairly addressed on its merits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">I am not concerned to analyse the Tribunal's actual thought processes or to identify what was done by the Tribunal in reaching its decision: Jia , at [185].</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">Nonetheless, against the background of the Tribunal's conceded apparent bias at the hearing stage, I am satisfied the reasonable observer might well conclude that the attitudes and predisposition to Mr Shingles there manifest, were not curbed as the Senior Member's retreat might have suggested.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">Rather, they were reflected in the Reasons for Decision and particularly was this so in the manner in which the Tribunal used the evidence to reach the finding that (at Reasons [35]): 
 
 ... the Applicant has attempted to exaggerate the effects of his disabilities in obtaining and retaining employment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">
 

 
In this the lay observer might properly have said the Tribunal made an issue of a matter that was not manifest as an issue to be addressed in the case with which the Tribunal had to deal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">This leads to the second basis of the Appellant's case before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">(b) Denial of Procedural Fairness 
 In reaching its "exaggeration" conclusion in relation to the effects of Mr Shingles' disabilities, the Tribunal was not simply expressing a conclusion which followed from perceived inconsistencies in the evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">Rather, the Tribunal was calling into question Mr Shingles' credibility directly: he was attempting to create a misleading picture of his disabilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">That was not an issue that was ever raised with him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">The Authority, while relying upon conclusions to be drawn from inconsistencies, disclaimed any attack on Mr Shingles' credibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">Yet the Tribunal, without warning, made it "an issue critical to the decision": Alphaone , at 591-592.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">In the course of final submissions counsel for the Authority accepted that the Tribunal did not bring home to the appellant that this was a critical issue in the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">In this Mr Shingles clearly was denied procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">CONCLUSION 
 In addition to the grounds specified in the Notice of Appeal, the appellant has sought leave to raise a further ground of appeal involving an alleged error of law in its construction of s 51 of the 1948 Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">Given the conclusions at which I have already arrived, I do not consider it appropriate to grant the leave sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">I would, though, venture the view that where the Parliament amends a provision of an Act (here s 53) but does not expressly amend another which deals with a precursor, but like, provision to that amended (ie s 51) so that the two are no longer harmonious, a Court is likely to be slow to assume in the absence of clear contextual justification that there was a legislative intent manifest to impliedly amend that provision or to so change the purpose of the Act through the amendment as to change via contemporary principles of statutory construction the meaning of the unamended provision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">I am satisfied the Federal Magistrate erred in concluding both that the appellant waived its right to allege bias and that bias was not revived in the decision itself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">I equally am satisfied that his Honour erred in finding that there had been no denial of procedural fairness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">I will order that: 
(i) the appeal be allowed;
 
(ii) the decision of the Federal Magistrate be set aside;
 
(iii) the appeal to the Federal Magistrate be allowed;
 
(iv) the decision of the Tribunal be allowed;
 
(v) the matter be remitted to a differently constituted Tribunal to be heard and determined according to law; and
 
(vi) the respondent pay the appellant's costs of the appeal and of the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">I certify that the preceding fifty-one (51) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Finn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">Associate: 
 
 
Dated: 30 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr R M Niall 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: KCL Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr A Dillon 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 15 October 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1211.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>