<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hughes, in the matter of Firepower Operations Pty Ltd (In Liquidation) [2009] FCA 1331 (5 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1331.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for issue of examination summons under s 596a of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">corporations</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 This is an application which is brought by Mr Bryan Kevin Hughes, as Liquidator of Firepower Operations Pty Ltd (In Liquidation) under s 596A of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) for the issue of an examination summons to Mr Timothy Francis Johnston.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Section 596A of the Corporations Act provides as follows: 
 
 The Court is to summon a person for examination about a corporation's examinable affairs if: 
 

 
 (a) an eligible applicant applies for the summons; and
 
 (b) the Court is satisfied that the person is an officer or provisional liquidator of the corporation or was such an officer or provisional liquidator during or after the 2 years ending:
 (i) if the corporation is under administration --- on the section 513C day in relation to the administration; or
 (ii) if the corporation has executed a deed of company arrangement that has not yet terminated --- on the section 513C day in relation to the administration that ended when the deed was executed; or
 (iii) if the corporation is being, or has been, wound up --- when the winding up began; or
 (iv) otherwise --- when the application is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">
 The provisions of s 596A require that the Court issues an examination summons if the conditions referred to therein, are fulfilled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Unlike s 596B of the Corporations Act , the Court does not have a discretion as to whether to order that an examination summons should issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The distinction is of some importance because the range of persons who are eligible to be examined pursuant to an application made under s 596B is considerably wider than those who may be examined pursuant to an application made under s 596A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">In support of the application made under s 596A , the applicant relies upon an affidavit of Ms Kazi Mai Lyn Klopper which annexes a company search of Firepower Operations Pty Ltd. The liquidator of a company in liquidation is an "eligible applicant" for the purposes of s 596A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The company search discloses that Mr Bryan Kevin Hughes was appointed the Liquidator of Firepower Operations Pty Ltd on 4 August 2008, and continues to act in that capacity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">I am satisfied that he is an eligible applicant under s 596A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">I am also satisfied on the basis of the information in the company search that Mr Johnston was a director, and therefore, an officer, of the company at the time its winding up began.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">He is, therefore, a person to whom s 596A(b)(iii) applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">In those circumstances, I am prepared to make the orders for the issue of an examination summons to Mr Johnston.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">In my view, however, the examination summons should be returnable as soon as practicable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">On that basis, I will order that the examination summons be returnable before a Registrar of this Court at 10:15 am on 26 November 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">I certify that the preceding seven (7) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Siopis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">Associate:
Dated: 17 November 2009
 
 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr Stephen Penrose 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Tottle Partners 
 Date of Hearing: 5 November 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 5 November 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1331.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>