<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus (No 5) [2009] FCA 1221 (28 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1221.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">review of registrar's decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">de novo review</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">potential to fragment the taxation process</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">referral of outstanding issues to mediation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 (Revised from Transcript) 
 The litigation between the present parties has been ongoing for a considerable period of time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">A number of judgments have already been given: Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus [2007] FCA 1878 ; Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus [2007] FCA 2117 ; Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus (No 3) [2008] FCA 1986 , 69 ACSR 264 ; Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus (No 4) [2009] FCA 1085.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The facts giving rise to the litigation need not be now repeated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">At the comparative outset of the litigation, on 26 November 2007, orders were made that the Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd ("the Trustee") was to pay the costs of Mr Rickus " forthwith " and that such costs were to be paid on an indemnity basis: Motor Trades Association of Australia Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd v Rickus [2007] FCA 1878.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">It gives rise to a considerable degree of disquiet to learn that the making of those orders is still occasioning dispute between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">That part of the dispute which presently manifests itself is an application by the Trustee to review a decision of a Deputy District Registrar of this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On 18 June 2009 Deputy District Registrar Cujes made orders that: 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The full taxation proceed on the basis there exists a valid retainer agreement between the First Respondent (Mr Rickus) and his legal representatives for the purposes of the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">
 

 
 
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The First Respondent is granted leave, pursuant to Order 13 sub-rule 2(1) of the Federal Court Rules , to file and serve an amended bill of costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 

 
Those orders were accompanied by a letter from the Deputy District Registrar also dated 18 June 2009 to the solicitors for both the Trustee and Mr Rickus.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The letter recorded (in part) what the Deputy District Registrar referred to as her " preliminary oral decision ... in respect of ... the validity of " a written retainer as between Mr Rickus and his legal advisers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The letter helpfully recorded a finding that " the retainer between Mr Rickus and his lawyers was partly oral, partly written and/or partly to be implied by conduct ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Reference was made by the Deputy District Registrar to s 42 of the Legal Practitioners Act 1981 (SA) and to a decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia in Catto v Hampton Australia Ltd (In Liq) [2008] SASC 231.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">That decision was relied upon as authority for the proposition that " a successful litigant is entitled to recover from the other party amounts paid by the former in connection with the litigation, notwithstanding the unenforceability of any agreement between the litigant and solicitor... ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The letter concluded:
 
 
 I would continue to strongly urge the parties to attend a confidential conference or mediation with a view to, at the very least, narrowing and refining the issues in dispute, but hopefully reaching settlement on a commercial basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">
 

 The Trustee's application for review invokes O 62 r 11 of the Federal Court Rules which provides as follows: 
 
 Every taxation of costs and every decision of a taxing officer shall be subject to review by a Judge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">
 

 In summary form, the Trustee seeks to contend that: the Deputy District Registrar's decision is beyond power; and is, in any event wrong as a matter of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">
Counsel for Mr Rickus contends that:
 The Outlines of Written Submissions filed on behalf of Mr Rickus and the Trustee in support of these competing contentions make reference to a myriad of Affidavits .</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">A folder of Affidavits to be relied upon by the parties as filed contained some 13 Affidavits .</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Three more were later filed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">When addressing the question as to whether there was a valid retainer between Mr Rickus and his legal advisers, the written submissions went well beyond a reference to the terms of the 16 November 2006 letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Reference was made to the area of practice of the solicitor named in the letter, the Minutes of meetings at which the Trustee was advised as to the intent of Mr Rickus to obtain legal advice and discussions which apparently took place at the time when Mr Rickus was initially seeking advice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">It may be doubted that such evidence would have assumed any relevance had it ultimately been relied upon.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">At the outset of the hearing this morning, however, the ambit of the evidence was considerably reduced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">It may presently be assumed that O 62 r 11 has been properly invoked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Left to one side is a question as to whether the " preliminary decision " of the Deputy District Registrar, albeit a decision given effect by an order, is a " decision " within the meaning of r 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Also left to one side is the question as to whether or not the Deputy District Registrar had power to make the decision that she did or to make the consequential order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Left unresolved is whether or not the Deputy District Registrar should have referred any question as to the validity of a retainer agreement to a Judge of this Court for resolution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">That was the course which was said to be appropriate by the Family Court in Twigg v McIlwraith (1988) 89 FLR 473.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">As recognised by that Court, it was expected " [a]s a matter of commonsense as well as convenience to the litigants " that the question referred " be one of substance ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">And it may further be assumed for present purposes that the " review " to be undertaken is a hearing de novo : Pacific Dunlop Ltd v Australian Rubber Gloves (unreported, FCA, Olney J, 17 August 1993); Boys v Australian Securities Commission [2001] FCA 1440 per Carr J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Whether such an assumption is correct, given the reservation expressed by Hely J in Cachia v Westpac Financial Services Ltd [2003] FCA 817 , need not be now resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">See also: Miller v Wertheim [2004] FCA 988.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The amount of money dividing the parties is comparatively small.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">There was broad agreement for the purposes of this morning's hearing that: as at the date of the November 2007 orders, no moneys had been paid by Mr Rickus to his legal advisers; since the date of those orders, he has paid a sum of approximately $85,000; if the fees are to be calculated by reference to the Federal Court scale of fees, the amount of fees payable would be approximately $55,000 to $60,000; and if the fees are to be calculated by reference to the terms of the November 2006 letter, those fees would be approximately $114,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">
The fees incurred this morning, with the Trustee and Mr Rickus both being represented by Senior and Junior Counsel, would have gone a long way to bridging the difference in the amount that will ultimately be paid in accordance with the November 2007 orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">The principal matter dividing the parties is whether the November 2006 letter extended beyond an agreement confined to the provision of advice and extended to an agreement in respect to the litigation which ultimately followed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Notwithstanding the care with which the written submissions have been prepared and the other issues there canvassed, it is nevertheless considered that the question as to the construction and application of the November 2006 letter should be now resolved and the matter thereafter referred to mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Such an order may be made pursuant to s 53A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The Deputy District Registrar, who has an intimate knowledge of the factual issues by reason of her consideration of the matters to date, urged recourse to mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The dispute is eminently suitable for mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The dispute, it is considered, can be more expeditiously resolved by mediation than by a decision of this Court on the limited matters now before it and thereafter further deliberation by the Deputy District Registrar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Further delay will inevitably be occasioned by the taxation process resuming.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Although there was a measure of agreement that mediation may serve a useful purpose if the ambit of the November 2006 letter is to be resolved, an order for mediation may be made irrespective of the wishes of the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Section 53A thus provides as follows: 
 
 Mediation and arbitration 
 (1) Subject to the Rules of Court, the Court may by order refer the proceedings in the Court, or any part of them or any matter arising out of them, to a mediator or an arbitrator for mediation or arbitration, as the case may be, in accordance with the Rules of Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">(1A) Referrals under subsection (1) to a mediator may be made with or without the consent of the parties to the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">However, referrals to an arbitrator may be made only with the consent of the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">(2) The Rules of Court may make provision for the registration of awards made in an arbitration carried out under an order made under subsection (1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">
 

 
 In making an order for mediation it is presently envisaged that there should be embraced within that mediation all aspects of any outstanding dispute arising from Orders 1 and/or 2 as made on 26 November 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">A further reason in support of an order for mediation, rather than resolving the application for review as now made pursuant to O 62 r 11 on all of the issues canvassed by the Outlines of Written Submissions , is the fact that the taxation exercise presently being undertaken by the Deputy District Registrar has not as yet concluded.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Although the discrete nature of the questions sought to be now reviewed may be appreciated, it is considered generally undesirable to undertake a review of an incomplete taxation process.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">To do so has the potential to fragment that process and potentially encourage a series of like applications to the present --- each being (arguably) addressed to an equally discrete " decision ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Such a process, if pursued, would have the potential to unjustifiably deny a party the benefit of an order obtained long ago and expose such a party to a forensic course of attrition pursued by an opponent more committed to securing a settlement than to compliance with the terms of an order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">There has been no suggestion, it should be noted, that that is the course now being pursued by the Trustee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Mediation at this stage has the potential to resolve all outstanding matters that divide the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">With respect to the November 2006 letter, it is considered that that letter is nothing other than a letter of engagement with respect to the giving of advice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">It is not possible to construe that letter as also being a letter of engagement with respect to the subsequent litigation that engulfed the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">That conclusion is reached by reason of: the subject-matter summarised at the outset of the letter, namely " Terms of Engagement --- MTAA Super, Directorship Advice "; the terms of the letter expressing the " scope of the engagement " as being " to advise ... in connection with your removal from the office of chairman of directors as well as your removal from office as an independent director which the board of directors of the trustee of MTAA Super resolved to give effect to at its meeting held on 10 October 2006 "; the cost estimate quantified at " approximately $5,000.00 "; and the absence of any reference to such matters as would normally be included in a retainer embracing potential litigation, including such matters as anticipated Counsel fees; the expected duration of any litigation; the risks inherent in any litigation; and disbursements associated with litigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">
This conclusion has been reached notwithstanding the fact that the 16 November 2006 letter also refers to:
 the costs estimate being " your costs " and the fact that the letter continues on to state in cl 3.4: " Additionally, if your matter is a litigation matter, the Court (in circumstances we can explain to you if you wish) may order you to pay other moneys including the costs of other parties ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">There is a further reference to litigation in cl 3.5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Passing references to " litigation " cannot transform this letter into an agreement as to the terms upon which the solicitors would conduct litigation on Mr Rickus's behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">Even if it were permissible to depart from the terms of the letter itself, it is not considered that such further materials as were referred to by Senior Counsel on behalf of Mr Rickus take the matter any further.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">In contrast to the Affidavit material filed, that additional material was within a limited compass.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">Reference was thus made to instructions given by Mr Rickus on 14 November 2006, two days before the 16 November 2006 letter was forwarded to him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">The prospect of litigation had apparently been raised with Mr Rickus prior to 16 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">But the instructions given on 14 November 2006 were confined to instructions " to confer with Mr Moshinsky of counsel as to his availability to accept a brief to represent my interests ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">No agreement to retain Counsel in accordance with the terms of the November 2006 letter --- or any other terms --- can be discerned from the giving of those instructions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Nor is the identification of any agreement as between Mr Rickus and his solicitors to be found in an email forwarded the same day by the solicitors to Mr Moshinsky inquiring in part: " If we need counsel support in this process --- would you be prepared to act?</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">" Nor can any agreement as at November 2007 be discerned from an Affidavit of Mr Rickus sworn on 19 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The paragraphs of that Affidavit now relied upon merely set forth the reasons why he chose the solicitors he did and the fact that he has continued to retain those solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The final matter relied upon by Senior Counsel on behalf of Mr Rickus to found an agreement is the fact that Mr Rickus is said to be a man experienced in commerce and with a degree of knowledge as to the manner in which solicitors conduct their affairs, that knowledge " including litigious matters ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Knowledge is not agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">The November 2006 letter is thus an agreement confined to the terms upon which advice was to be provided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Neither that letter taken on its own --- nor in conjunction with the other matters relied upon by Senior Counsel for Mr Rickus --- changes the confined nature of the agreement reached as at November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Although it is with diffidence that consideration is even given to making a further order that anything be done " forthwith " in this litigation, it is envisaged that the mediation that is to take place should occur within the immediate future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Inquiries should be made as to the availability of a mediator suitable to both parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">If agreement is not forthcoming, a list of mediators who are available to conduct the mediation in the immediate future should be provided and one will be selected by the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">ORDERS 
 The Court orders that: 
1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The parties are to bring in short minutes of proposed orders within 14 days to give effect to these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">I certify that the preceding twenty-one (21) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 29 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: Mr F M Douglas QC with Mr F Assaf 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: HBL Ebsworth 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr M Livesey QC with Mr B Doyle 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: DMAW Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 28 October 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 28 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1221.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>