<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>TVBO Production Limited v Australia Sky Net Pty Limited [2009] FCA 1132 (7 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1132.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">interception by taiwan-based corporation of signals during authorised transmission by another enterprise of episodes of a television series</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">re-transmission of episode via satellite to subscribers of a-sky-net pay television service in australia</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">conduct was an electronic transmission of the episode by means of that transmission and thus a communication within s 10 of the copyright act 1968 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">the communication was made to the public</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">the taiwanese corporation thereby infringed the first applicant's copyright in the episode transmitted as described</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">chairman of directors of the taiwan corporation held to have authorised the infringement</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">applicants proceeded against two respondents in their absence</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">applicants must prove the case pleaded by them against those respondents on the balance of probabilities</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">copyright</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 These proceedings were commenced on 23 May 2007 by the first and second applicants against the first three respondents only.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">At that time, the applicants alleged, amongst other things, that those respondents had infringed the first applicant's copyright in the 42 episode television drama series entitled "Twin of Brothers" .</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">In the initial Statement of Claim, the applicants claimed declarations, injunctions, delivery up of infringing copies, damages and additional damages pursuant to s 115(4) of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) ( the Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">In that pleading, the applicants also claimed relief pursuant to ss 52 , 53 (g) and 82 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ( the Trade Practices Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Twin of Brothers is set at the end of the Sui Dynasty and is about two ordinary men who learn martial arts skills and gain access to a secret treasure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">At the same time, they inadvertently learn the "immortality routine".</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The brothers become the most wanted people in the martial arts world and must rely on the help of a nun and the Tong Dynasty princess to survive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">On 27 March 2008, by their Amended Statement of Claim, the first and second applicants joined the fourth respondent ( CSC ), a Taiwanese company, as an additional respondent in the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">At the same time, they added causes of action for infringement of copyright and the authorisation of infringement of copyright in a second television drama series entitled " Once Upon a Time in Shanghai ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">The causes of action based upon the Trade Practices Act which had been pleaded in the first version of the Statement of Claim were abandoned when the Amended Statement of Claim was filed and served.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">On 17 July 2008, a Notice of Appearance was filed on behalf of CSC by the firm of solicitors who were then acting for all of the other respondents, namely, S Moran &amp; Co.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Subsequently, on 30 July 2008, a Defence to the Amended Statement of Claim was filed by all four respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">This document was entitled Consolidated Defence to Amended Statement of Claim by the First to Fourth Respondents .</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">A Further Amended Statement of Claim was filed on 27 November 2008 pursuant to leave granted by me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">In that pleading, the third applicant was added as an applicant party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Additional matters were pleaded at that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Those matters concerned the relationships amongst the applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">No new allegations which could be said to have altered the substance of the applicants' case were made in this pleading.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Before the Further Amended Statement of Claim was filed, a Notice of Ceasing to Act was filed on behalf of the second and fourth respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">This document was filed on 8 October 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">On 26 November 2008, I made orders for service of the Further Amended Statement of Claim on the second and fourth respondents in Taiwan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Service was subsequently effected in accordance with the orders which I made on that occasion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">I also ordered on 26 November 2008 that the respondents file and serve their Defences to the Further Amended Statement of Claim by 7 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">In addition, I made directions on that occasion designed to bring to the attention of the second and fourth respondents in Taiwan the fact that the applicants had amended their Statement of Claim and the substance of the orders which I made on 26 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Included within those orders was an order confirming that all questions of liability were fixed for final hearing before me on 9 February 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The first and third respondents filed a Defence to the Further Amended Statement of Claim on 10 December 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The second and fourth respondents took no further part in the proceedings after 8 October 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">For this reason, the Consolidated Defence filed on 30 July 2008 must stand as the Defence of the second and fourth respondents for present purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">When the proceedings were called on for hearing on 9 February 2009, there was no appearance either by or on behalf of either the second respondent or the fourth respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">On 10 February 2009 (Day Two of the hearing) I accepted certain undertakings given to the Court by the first and third respondents and made certain orders in respect of the claims made by the applicants against the first and third respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Those orders were made as a result of and in conformity with Terms of Settlement agreed between the applicants, on the one hand, and the first and third respondents, on the other hand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">It is anticipated that the proceedings as between those parties will shortly be disposed of on a final basis in accordance with those Terms of Settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">On 10 February 2009, the applicants pressed their case against the second and fourth respondents in the absence of those two respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">These Reasons for Judgment determine the case on liability and for non-monetary relief which the applicants ultimately pressed against the second and fourth respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">In the end, that case was confined to the infringement of copyright case in respect of Twin of Brothers , the applicants having decided by the second day of the trial to abandon their case against the second and fourth respondents in respect of the series entitled Once Upon a Time in Shanghai .</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">As I have already mentioned, the applicants proceeded against the second and fourth respondents in their absence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">They claimed declaratory and injunctive relief against them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">As the hearing in February 2009 was always intended to deal only with the question of liability, the applicants wished to reserve their position in respect of monetary relief (damages or account of profits).</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">For the applicants to succeed, they must prove their case on the balance of probabilities in the usual way.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Of course, they are relieved of the burden of dealing with any evidence tendered on behalf of the second and fourth respondents since no evidence was tendered on behalf of those respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">I am satisfied that, at all times from late March 2008, the second and fourth respondents were aware of the allegations contained in the Amended Statement of Claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">They had filed a Defence to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">I am also satisfied that, in all probability, those respondents became aware of: Pursuant to O 32 r 2(1)(d) of the Federal Court Rules , if, when a proceeding is called on for trial, any party is absent, the Court may proceed with the trial generally or so far as concerns any claim for relief in the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">I have dealt with the case against the second and fourth respondents pursuant to that provision in the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">THE APPLICANTS AND THE ALLEGATIONS MADE BY THEM 
 The applicants are wholly owned subsidiaries of Television Broadcasts Limited ( TVB ) which is the world's largest producer and distributor of Chinese language programs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Its major business activities are television broadcasting, program licensing, video broadcasting and satellite broadcasting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The first applicant ( TVBO ) was incorporated on 26 June 2002 for the purpose of owning film and television rights and in order to undertake the licensing of such rights.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">It is the owner of the copyright in each episode of the Twin of Brothers series for the whole world except the territory of Hong Kong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">TVB is the owner of the copyright in Twin of Brothers in the territory of Hong Kong.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The applicants allege that: TVB Australia (the third applicant); or alternatively TVBI (the second applicant) 
is the exclusive licensee in Australia of: 
 
 (i) The right to communicate to the public (except by the internet) the Twin of Brothers series; and
 (ii) The right to authorise, including by way of sub-licence, the right to communicate the Twin of Brothers series to the public (except by the internet).</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">
 In the Consolidated Defence, the second and fourth respondents admit that each episode of the series Twin of Brothers is a separate cinematograph film within the meaning of s 10(1) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">Most of the remaining allegations referred to in [22] above were put in issue by the second and fourth respondents by way of non-admission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The allegations referred to in sub-pars (k), (l) and (m) of [22] above were not addressed by the second and fourth respondents in any pleading.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">The first time that those allegations were made was in the Further Amended Statement of Claim filed on 27 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The applicants go on to allege that, from at least 28 January 2007, CSC has, in Australia, without the licence of the applicants, communicated the whole or a substantial part of each episode of the Twin of Brothers series and thus infringed the applicants' copyright in each episode of that series.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">They also allege that CSC authorised the first respondent's infringement of the copyright in each of the cinematograph films comprising the Twin of Brothers series or participated in a common design with the first respondent whereby TVBO's copyright in each of those films was infringed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The second respondent is said to have directed and procured and authorised the first respondent's and CSC's infringement of the applicants' copyright in the Twin of Brothers series and also to have participated in a common design with the first respondent, the third respondent and CSC to infringe TVBO's copyright in each film comprising the Twin of Brothers series.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Additional damages pursuant to s 115(4) of the Act are claimed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">COPYRIGHT IN "TWIN OF BROTHERS" 
 Section 184 of the Act provides that the Regulations made under the Act may make provision applying any of the provisions of the Act (other than those of Pt XIA) specified in the Regulations, in relation to a country (other than Australia) so specified, in a number of different ways set out in that section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">Regulation 4(1) of the Copyright (International Protection) Regulations 1969 provides that a provision of the Act that applies in relation to (amongst other things) cinematograph film made or first published in Australia applies in relation to such film made or first published in a Berne Convention country or in a WTO country: 
 
 (a) In the same way as the provision applies, under the Act, in relation to an Australian work or subject-matter; and
 (b) As if the foreign work or subject matter were made or first published in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">
 

 China is a Berne Convention country and a WTO country within the meaning of that Regulation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Section 90(2) of the Act provides that copyright subsists in a cinematograph film if the film was made in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">By reason of reg 4(1) of the Copyright (International Protection) Regulations 1969 , s 90(2) applies to a cinematograph film made or first published in Hong Kong as if it had been made or first published in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Thus, copyright under the Act will subsist in any cinematograph film made in Hong Kong and protection will be afforded to such film under the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The evidence demonstrates that the Twin of Brothers series was made in Hong Kong in the period from July 2003 to August 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Copyright therefore subsists in each episode of the Twin of Brothers series.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Under s 98 of the Act, the owner of copyright in a cinematograph film is the maker of that film.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Section 22(4)(b) of the Act provides that: 
 
 (b) the maker of the cinematograph film is the person by whom the arrangements necessary for the making of the film were undertaken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">
 

 The Co-Production Agreement between TVB and TVBO dated 8 January 2003 was tendered in evidence before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">The applicants also proved that 12 episodes of Twin of Brothers were delivered by TVB to TVBO during the period between 1 January 2004 and 30 June 2004 and that a further 30 episodes of that series were delivered by TVB to TVBO in the period between 1 July 2004 and 31 December 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Clauses 1 and 4 of the Co-Production Agreement provide that: The applicants also tendered two VCD box sets of the title Twin of Brothers , one for sale in Hong Kong and one for sale in Macau.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The box set for sale in Hong Kong bore the following statement on its packaging: 
 
 &#169; Television Broadcasts Limited &amp; TVBO Production Limited (Release in 2004) 
 

 That tender was made for the purpose of placing the applicants in a position to rely upon the presumptions contained in s 131 of the Act, should it become necessary to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Section 131(1) provides that a person shall be presumed to be the maker of the film where the name of a person appears on copies of a cinematograph film made available to the public in such a way as to imply that the person was the maker of that film.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">Subsections 131(2) and 131(3) provide that where articles or things embodying the film have been supplied commercially and, at the time of supply, the article or their container bore a label with a "&#169;" and the year and name of a person, then it is presumed that the film was made in that year and that the person so named is the owner of the copyright in that film.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">These presumptions operate in favour of the applicants, unless the contrary is established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">I do not think that the applicants need to rely upon these presumptions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">However, in the present case, the applicants are entitled to rely upon the presumptions raised by s 131 of the Act with the consequence that, unless the contrary is established, the Court will presume that TVB and TVBO are the owners of copyright in the cinematograph films which comprise the series Twin of Brothers and that those films were made in 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The specific provisions of the Twin of Brothers Co-Production Agreement rebut the presumption that the cinematograph films were made in circumstances where s 98(3) of the Act does not apply.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">In light of the above matters, I find that copyright subsists in each film that makes up the series Twin of Brothers and that TVBO is the owner of that copyright in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The only licences granted by TVBO in respect of broadcast rights in Australia are those which were granted to TVB Australia and TVBI.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">INFRINGEMENT BY THE FOURTH RESPONDENT 
 The applicants tendered certain paragraphs of an affidavit sworn by the third respondent in certain proceedings in the Supreme Court of New South Wales in order to prove several facts and matters relevant to an understanding of the way in which subscribers to the first respondent's subscription service are able to view television signals in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">In that affidavit, the third respondent swore that: The retransmission of the Taipei channels is only made possible by the fourth respondent leasing capacity on the Measat-2 satellite.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Having leased such capacity, the fourth respondent then sends its signal containing the Taipei channels from its base station in Taiwan to the Measat-2 satellite.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">The signal is then downlinked by the satellite to the east coast of Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">This enables subscribers of the first respondent's service located in New South Wales, Victoria and Queensland to view the channels.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">To some extent, the arrangements between the first and fourth respondents are documented in an agreement entered into between them dated 25 January 2002.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Under that agreement, the fourth respondent: (a) Is to transmit by satellite the Information Data, Sound and TV Picture Service System ( DTH ) that are received by the customers' antenna and digital decoder; (b) Was responsible for the supply and maintenance of audio and video contents of the system; and (c) Was responsible for the transmission and maintenance of the satellite signals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">THE ROLE OF THE SECOND RESPONDENT 
 In the Consolidated Defence, the second respondent admitted that, at all material times, he was a director of both the first and the fourth respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">He also admitted that he was actively involved in the management and control of the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">He is the Chairman of Directors of the fourth respondent and actively represents it in commercial negotiations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">The second respondent is described in material available on the fourth respondent's website as follows: 
 
 Mr Chih-Lung Wang who is the pioneer in Taiwan satellite broadcasting industry founded Chinese Satellite Communication Group in 1989.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">After 17 years of hard work, he has successfully build [sic] four Chinese DTH platforms, C-Sky-Net, I-Sky-Net, A-Sky-Net and 146-Sky-Net.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">These platforms carry more than satellite TV channels for millions of overseas household [sic] to enjoy the quality TV programs from Taiwan, Hong Kong and China without boarders [sic] and time gap via our four satellites' DTH platforms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">
 

 The applicants submitted that I should infer that the second respondent was actively involved in the management and control of the fourth respondent and also had a substantial involvement in the management of the first respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">On the evidence before me, and in the absence of evidence to the contrary, I am prepared to draw those inferences and do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">THE TRANSMISSION OF EPISODE 5 OF "TWIN OF BROTHERS" 
 The evidence establishes that, on 28 January 2007, the fourth respondent transmitted Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers to subscribers of the first respondent's pay television service in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">The transmission was made on Channel 8 of the first respondent's pay television service and was available only to subscribers of that service.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">It was encrypted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">The applicants submitted that this transmission probably occurred in the following way: Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers was originally broadcast by the Fujian Media Group on its channel SETV.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">That organisation is based in China.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">That broadcast occurred with the permission and licence of TVBO.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">That broadcast was received by the fourth respondent and intercepted by it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">It was then retransmitted to Australia without the permission of the appropriate entities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">It is clear that the retransmission by the fourth respondent of Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers on this occasion was not licensed by or on behalf of TVBO.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">I accept these submissions and make findings accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">THE RETRANSMISSION BY THE FOURTH RESPONDENT OF EPISODE 5 IS AN INFRINGEMENT OF COPYRIGHT 
 Pursuant to s 86(c) of the Act, the owner of the copyright in relation to a cinematograph film has the exclusive right to communicate the film to the public.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">Section 10 of the Act provides that, in the Act, unless the contrary intention appears, communicate means: 
 
 make available online or electronically transmit (whether over a path, or a combination of paths, provided by a material substance or otherwise) a work or other subject-matter, including a performance or live performance within the meaning of this Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">
 

 
In the same section, the expression to the public means:
 
 
 to the public within or outside Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">
 

 Section 101(1) of the Act provides that copyright in a cinematographic film is infringed by a person who: 
 
 ... not being the owner of the copyright, and without the licence of the owner of the copyright, does in Australia, or authorizes the doing in Australia of, any act comprised in the copyright.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">
 

 
Pursuant to s 13(1) of the Act, an act comprised in the copyright in a work or other subject matter is a reference to an act which, under the Act, the owner of the copyright has the exclusive right to do.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Having regard to the means deployed by the fourth respondent to transmit to Australia Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers , it seems to me that it communicated by electronic transmission that episode to the public in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">It caused the requisite signals to be transmitted from its base station in Taiwan to subscribers of the first respondent's pay television service within Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">It determined the content of the communication (see s 22(6) of the Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">It was not a broadcast within the meaning of that word as defined in s 10 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">The fourth respondent's transmission emanated from Taiwan, but this circumstance does not absolve it from liability.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">The transmission was received by pay TV subscribers within Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The fourth respondent did not have a licence to transmit that episode to the first respondent's subscribers within Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">I find that, unless restrained, the fourth respondent will, in all probability, repeat this conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">For these reasons, I consider that the fourth respondent infringed TVBO's copyright in Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers .</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">THE LIABILITY OF THE SECOND RESPONDENT 
 Section 101(1A) of the Act is in the following terms: 
 
 (1A) In determining, for the purposes of subsection (1), whether or not a person has authorised the doing in Australia of any act comprised in a copyright subsisting by virtue of this Part without the licence of the owner of the copyright, the matters that must be taken into account include the following: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) the extent (if any) of the person's power to prevent the doing of the act concerned;
 (b) the nature of any relationship existing between the person and the person who did the act concerned;
 (c) whether the person took any other reasonable steps to prevent or avoid the doing of the act, including whether the person complied with any relevant industry codes of practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">
 
 

 The concept of authorisation was discussed in Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 ; (2006) 156 FCR 380 at [20] (p 385) (per Branson J) and at [136]---[147] (pp 408---411) (per Kenny J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">After reviewing a number of authorities which, by 2006, were largely of historical significance, Kenny J approached the question of authorisation by applying the terms of s 101(1A) construed in light of the historical position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Her Honour held that it is usually not a straightforward matter for the Court to determine what degree of control can constitute a sufficient basis for a finding of authorisation ( Cooper [2006] FCAFC 187 ; 156 FCR 380 at [142] (p 410)).</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Her Honour said that it will always be a question of fact and degree in each case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">Even mere inactivity or indifference might be sufficient if those things are coupled with other factors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">There is not a great deal of evidence directed to the position of the second respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">However, he has not appeared to defend himself against the allegations made against him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">His involvement with the first and fourth respondents cannot be denied (as to which see [43]---[45] above).</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">It is reasonable, I think, in the circumstances, for me to conclude that he played a significant role in the conduct of the fourth respondent which resulted in the unlawful transmission of Episode 5 of Twin of Brothers .</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">He seems to be the most senior executive active in the business of the fourth respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">In the circumstances, I am prepared to infer that the second respondent authorised the infringement by the fourth respondent which I have found.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">I do so bearing in mind the terms of s 101(1A) and the observations of the Full Court in Cooper [2006] FCAFC 187 ; 156 FCR 380.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">It also seems to me that the second respondent participated in a common design with others whereby TVBO's copyright in the Twin of Brothers films was infringed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">CONCLUSION 
 For the above reasons, I am prepared to make the orders sought as against the second and fourth respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">There will be orders accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">I certify that the preceding fifty-nine (59) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Foster.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">Associate:
 
Dated: 7 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: Mr JV Nicholas SC with Mr CN Bova 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Marque 
 
 Counsel for the First and Third Respondents: Mr M Green 
 
 
 The Second and Fourth Respondents did not appear 
 
 Solicitor for the First, Second and Third Respondents: S Moran &amp; Co 
 Date of Hearing: 10 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1132.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>