<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Asmar, in the matter of an Election for offices of the Health Services Union [2009] FCA 1294 (6 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1294.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">application for an inquiry under s 200 of the fair work (registered organisations) act 2009 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether reasonable grounds exist for such an application</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">whether any irregularities have occurred in the conduct of an election for offices in theunion</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether the union had allowed the property or resources of the union to be used to help a candidate against another candidate during the conduct of the election process</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">industrial law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 Because of internal disputes, the Victoria No 1 Branch ("the Branch") of the Health Services Union ("the Union") became dysfunctional.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">As a result the Union applied to the Court to approve a scheme which would enable the Branch to function effectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">On 4 August 2009, such a scheme was approved by the Court: see Health Services Union, in the matter of the Health Services Union [2009] FCA 829.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Under the scheme, the National Executive of Union declared all elected offices in the Branch vacant and an Administrator was appointed pending the conduct of elections.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Under the timetable which was subsequently fixed for the conduct of the election, nominations for all Branch positions were called for on 1 October 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Nominations closed on 14 October 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Ballot papers were posted to members on 5 November 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The ballot will close on 7 December 2009 and it is expected that the poll will be declared for all positions on 8 December 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">At least three candidates have been nominated for each of the elected offices within the Branch.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Most of these candidates have formed themselves into "teams" which are led by the member of the team who has been nominated for the position of Branch Secretary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The three team leaders are Ms Diana Asmar, Mr Doug Byron and Mr Marco Bolano.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr Jamie Martorana and Ms Carol Carmichael are members of Mr Bolano's team.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The evidence suggests that two other employees of the Union, Ms Tanya Tromp and Mr David Irwin, are supporters of that team.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Some of the candidates are paid employees of the Branch who work as organisers or in other roles.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The Administrator appointed under the scheme approved by the Court, Mr John Vines, has been concerned to ensure that the resources of the Union were not used to support the election campaigns of any candidates.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">On 16 October 2009, he distributed by e-mail a memorandum to all Branch employees which read: 
 
 " Memo to HSU Victoria No 1 Branch Staff 
 

 
 
 All staff are reminded that [the relevant Federal Court order] specifically requires that the Administrator shall not: 
 
 permit the use of union funds or resources for campaigning or electioneering; permit the employees of the Branch to campaign or electioneer during their working hours; and permit any new material to be posted on the Branch's website, other than ordinary Branch business, until the declaration of the ballot, and for the avoidance of any doubt, the website must not be used for electioneering or campaigning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">
 
 
 In accordance with this order, staff who are engaged in electioneering or campaigning are
 (i) required to take leave (Long Service Leave, Annual leave or ADOs) for any period in which they are electioneering or campaigning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">(ii) not permitted to use the union resources including photocopying for any campaigning or electioneering
 (iii) not permitted to use the Union provided fuel card for any car use associated with electioneering or campaigning.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">
 

 
 
 It is understood that in some instances, Staff while on leave may be required to undertake union duties relating to urgent matters.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Staff who are required to do so are required to notify me by email of any such instances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">
 

 
 
 For those staff not engaged in electioneering or campaigning, the next 7 weeks will be a difficult period as the number of available staff will be significantly limited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">This will mean that our resources will be thinly spread.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Your continued professionalism in the face of these difficulties will be greatly appreciated".</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">
 
 The applicant, Ms Asmar, alleges that, notwithstanding Mr Vines' directions, certain employees of the Union, who are members of Mr Bolano's team, have used the resources of the Union to further their campaigns for election.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The employees concerned are Mr Bolano, Mr Martorana and Ms Carmichael.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Ms Asmar alleges that these employees (or some of them) have: These complaints were raised with Mr Vines by solicitors acting on behalf of Ms Asmar.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">As a result he has issued further directives and sought an explanation from at least one employee arising from complaints.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">On 4 November 2009, Ms Asmar filed an application for an inquiry relating to the election pursuant to s 200 of the Fair Work (Registered Organisations) Act 2009 (Cth) ("the Act").</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">The application seeks interim orders that, pending the hearing and determination of the proceeding: 
 
 "1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">... Mr Bolano, Ms Carmichael, Mr Martorana, Ms Tromp and Mr Irwin ... refrain from using data contained on the Union's membership register for the purposes of sending sms messages to Union members; 
 

 ... Mr Bolano, Ms Carmichael, Mr Martorana, Ms Tromp and Mr Irwin ... refrain from using the Union slogan "Stronger Together" and photographs depicting candidates in Union supplied clothing in promotional material in support of the Bolano ticket;
 ... Mr Bolano, Ms Carmichael, Mr Martorana, Ms Tromp and Mr Irwin ... refrain from conducting meetings of Union members using Union resources and representing those meetings as Union meetings both to members and to employers".</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">Section 200(1) of the Act provides that: 
 
 "If a person who is, or within the preceding period of 12 months has been, a member of an organisation claims that there has been an irregularity in relation to an election for an office in the organisation or a branch of the organisation, the person may make an application for an inquiry by the Federal Court into the matter".</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">
 

The term "irregularity" is relevantly defined in s 6 of the Act to include "a contravention of s 190.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">" Section 190 provides that an organisation or branch commits an offence "if it uses, or allows to be used, its property or resources to help a candidate against another candidate in an election under this Part for an office or other position".</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Section 201 of the Act provides that: 
 
 "Where 
 

 
 
 (a) an application for an inquiry has been lodged with the Federal Court under s 200; and
 (b) the Court is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for an application; 
 

 
 
 the Court must fix a time and place for conducting the inquiry, and may give such directions as it considers necessary to ensure that all persons who are or may be justly entitled to appear at the inquiry are notified of the time and place fixed and, where the Court fixes a time and place, the inquiry is taken to have been instituted".</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">
 
 Unlike some other remedial provisions in the Act (see, for example, ss 163 and 164), no provision is made for the making of interim orders pending the completion of an inquiry which has been instituted under s 200.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The application suggests that the Court has power to make interim orders under s 204 of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">During argument, counsel for Ms Asmar did not seek to rely on this provision but pointed, somewhat tentatively, to s 208 as providing power for the Court to make the interim orders sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">For reasons which will become apparent, I do not find it necessary to determine whether or not the Court has power to make interim orders in the course of an election inquiry which is instituted in the course of an election (and before the poll has been declared).</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">This is because s 201 of the Act requires the Court to be satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for the application, made under s 200, before any inquiry is taken to have been instituted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The approach taken by the Court to the preliminary issue identified by s 201(b) of the Act was explained by French J in Re Post; Re Election for Offices in Transport Workers Union of Australia, Western Australian Branch (1992) 40 IR 162 at 166-7 as follows: 
 
 "The question for the Court ... is whether it is satisfied that there is reasonable ground for the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">It will not be so satisfied if the grounds relied upon could not, even if made out, constitute "an irregularity in relation to an election for an office in the organisation".</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The question whether there is such an irregularity lies at the heart of this jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Nor will it be so satisfied if the allegations of fact relied upon in the application do not at least offer good grounds for suspicion that there has been such an irregularity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The Court will not entertain an application of a speculative nature based upon the applicant's opinion that there has been an irregularity unless that opinion rests upon some substantial factual foundation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">Necessary conditions to establish the requisite state of satisfaction can be multiplied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It is harder to state what is sufficient to satisfy the Court beyond the words of the section itself which require a an evaluative judgment at this preliminary stage".</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">
 
 Much of the affidavit evidence relied upon by the applicant contained hearsay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Insofar as it dealt with the sending of SMS messages to the mobile phones of members, it suggested that a small number of members had received messages supporting the Bolano team.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">It is not clear, on the evidence, how, whoever it was who sent the messages, obtained the mobile telephone numbers of the members to whom messages were sent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">In the few cases in which the deponent of an affidavit received a message, the deponent said that he or she had provided Mr Bolano or some other person associated with his campaign with his or her telephone number but had not done so for the purpose of receiving campaign material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">Some of these deponents were shop stewards at their workplaces and it is understandable that they would have provided Mr Bolano, an organiser, with their telephone numbers to facilitate contact on Union business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">What is important, for present purposes, is that there is no evidence that enables me to infer that Mr Bolano or anyone else obtained mobile telephone numbers of members by resort to Union records.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The evidence relied on by the applicant supports the allegation that Union meetings were convened at some hospitals using notices on Union letterhead.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Those meetings were attended by some Union employees who, although supposedly on leave, were said to be present on Union (as distinct from electoral) business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">Those employees used the meetings to encourage members to vote for the Bolano team.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Mr Bolano and other employees said to have been involved have not, as yet, denied that such conduct occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">In fairness to them, it must be said that some of the affidavits on which the applicant relies were not served until late on 4 November 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Such conduct as is alleged, if it occurred, would have constituted contraventions of the directions given by Mr Vines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">It does not, however, follow that such conduct constituted an irregularity for the purposes of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">It would only have done so had it given rise to a contravention of s 190.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">That could only have happened if the Union (or, possibly, the Branch) used or allowed its property or resources to be used to assist Mr Bolano and members of his team in the course of the election campaign.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Counsel for the applicant accepted that neither the Union nor the Branch had used Union resources in convening and conducting the workplace meetings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">She submitted, however, that the Union and/or the Branch had, nonetheless, allowed the property and resources of the Union to be used because action had not been taken to prevent the impugned conduct of the Union employees occurring.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">I do not accept these submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">The evidence establishes that Mr Vines had taken reasonable steps to ensure that the Union's property and resources were not used for electoral purposes.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">He issued clear directives requiring employee candidates to take leave during the campaign and not to use any of the Union's property and resources to support their candidacy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">If these directives were not obeyed it was no fault of Mr Vines and it cannot, in my opinion, be said that, by inaction, he allowed the alleged misconduct to take place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">The evidence establishes that members of the Bolano team distributed leaflets and posters which contained the material about which the applicant complains.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">There is evidence that the slogan "Stronger Together" was used from time to time in Union publications, but it cannot be said that the slogan was in any sense the property or a resource of the Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Mr Bolano appears to have chosen to use the slogan to identify his team but there is no evidence to suggest that the Union or the Branch allowed this to occur.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">The clothing worn by members of the Bolano team, when the photographs appearing in campaign leaflets and posters were taken, was clothing supplied by the Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">It was worn by officials in the course of their daily duties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Similar clothing was available to be purchased by members.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">I do not consider that such clothing can properly be considered to be the property or resources of the Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">It is open, on the evidence, to conclude that the various items of clothing were given to employees by the Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">There is no suggestion that the Union asserted any property rights in the clothing or that the employees were under an obligation to return the clothing on the occurrence of any particular event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">As Kirby J said in Re Jarman; Ex parte Cook (No 2) [1996] HCA 7 ; (1996) 136 ALR 233 at 241, the institution of an inquiry under s 201 is a serious matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The onus is on an applicant to persuade the Court that there exist reasonable grounds for the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">For the reasons given I am not satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to consider that any irregularity has occurred in relation to the election.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">I would, therefore, dismiss the application by the applicant for an inquiry.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">It follows that no interim orders can or should be made in the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">I certify that the preceding twenty-two (22) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 6 November 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Ms A Duffy 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Holding Redlich 
 
 Counsel for Mr M Bolano and Others: Mr M McKillop 
 
 Solicitor for Mr M Bolano and Others: Earl &amp; Associates 
 
 Counsel for the Health Services Union: Mr D Langmead 
 
 Solicitor for the Health Services Union: Slater &amp; Gordon 
 
 Counsel for Mr D Byron Mr H Borenstein SC 
 
 Solicitor for Mr D Byron Macpherson + Kelley 
 
 Counsel for the Administrator (Mr J Vines): Mr S Moore 
 
 Solicitor for the Administrator (Mr J Vines): Maurice Blackburn 
 
 Counsel for the Returning Officer: Mr R McClure 
 
 Solicitor for the Returning Officer: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 6 November 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 November 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1294.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>