<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hu v Commonwealth Ombudsman [2009] FCA 1516 (17 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1516.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">commonwealth ombudsman decided not to investigate appellant's complaint about migration agent registration authority (mara)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">federal magistrate dismissed appellant's application for review of ombudsman's decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">appellant believed migration agent had sent a forged contract to mara</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">s 6 ombudsman's act 1976</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">ombudsman found no complaint made by appellant to mara concerning legitimacy of contract and no decision made by mara on this issue</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether discretion of ombudsman is fettered</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">contents of contract did not impact on appellant's earlier complaint about migration agent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">whether the ombudsman denied the appellant natural justice</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">s 5 and s 6 administrative decisions judicial review act 1977 (cth) (adjr act)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether order for review available under s 16 adjr act</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">whether federal magistrate erred in failing to order default judgment against respondent under r 4.05 and r 13.03a federal magistrate court rules 2001</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">whether discovery should have been granted by federal magistrate pursuant to s 45 federal magistrates act 1999 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">whether federal magistrate gave adequate reasons</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">s 78b judiciary act 1903 (cth) notices</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">whether constitutional issues arose</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c15">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 I have before me a notice of appeal from Mr Hu from a decision of Jarrett FM of 14 August 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">In that decision his Honour dismissed Mr Hu's application for judicial review of a decision of the Commonwealth Ombudsman pursuant to the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) ("ADJR Act").</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">By letter of 27 April 2009 the Commonwealth Ombudsman had decided not to investigate a complaint of Mr Hu against the Migration Agents Registration Authority (MARA).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Before me Mr Hu seeks the following orders: Appeal against the whole of the judgment made by Federal Magistrate Jarrett on 14 August 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The whole of the judgment made by Federal Magistrate Jarrett on 14 August 2009 be set aside.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">Quash the Commonwealth Ombudsman's decision made by Mr Pezzanite on 27 April 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">Quash the Migration Agents Registration Authority's decision made by Ms Moser on 19 June 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">The Office of the Migration Agents Registration Authority reviews their decision on my complaint against the migration agent Ms Jennifer Li-Chien Lu, which was to take no further action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Commonwealth Ombudsman pays all the costs and fees to Appellant in the appeal proceedings and Federal Magistrates Court proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">
 
 (reproduced as in the original document) 
 

 Further, by an application filed 17 August 2009 Mr Hu gave notice pursuant to s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) (" Judiciary Act ") that the appeal raised an issue under the Constitution of the Commonwealth or involving its interpretation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Mr Hu's affidavit filed in support of this application asserts, in summary, that various decisions made by the learned Federal Magistrate contravened the doctrine of separation of powers enshrined in the Constitution .</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Similarly, Mr Hu gave another notice pursuant to s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) on 1 October 2009 alleging various constitutional issues arising from a directions hearing on 22 September 2009 before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">At the hearing of the appeal on 1 December 2009 Mr Hu produced a letter from the solicitor for the Commonwealth Attorney-General stating that the Commonwealth Attorney-General did not wish to intervene in the proceedings before the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Background
 The background facts to these proceedings are helpfully summarised in paras [1]-[12] and [15]-[17] of the judgment of Jarrett FM.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I do not understand this summary to be disputed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In those paragraphs his Honour observed as follows: 
 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Mr Hu feels aggrieved by a decision made on 27 April, 2009 by a delegate of the Commonwealth Ombudsman, Mr Pezzanite.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The decision challenged in these proceedings, made pursuant to s.6 of the Ombudsman Act 1976 , is that the Commonwealth Ombudsman would not investigate a complaint made on 20 March, 2009 by Mr Hu against an officer of the Migration Agents' Registration Authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Mr Hu seeks an order, amongst many others, that the Commonwealth Ombudsman's decision not to investigate his complaint be set aside pursuant to s.5 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1975 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Mr Hu's complaint against the Authority's officer was initiated on 20 March, 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">It concerns the actions of an officer of the Authority, Ms Vee Moser, who responded to an enquiry by Mr Hu about a complaint made by him to the Authority in 2008 concerning a particular migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">That complaint was finalised by the Authority in September, 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">The Authority's decision in relation to that complaint was the subject of a complaint to the Commonwealth Ombudsman in late 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">In December, 2008 the Ombudsman decided not to investigate that complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">That decision was the subject of a judicial review application that I determined on 19 March, 2009 ( Hu v Giles [2009] FMCA 368).</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">I dismissed the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">The current application has its genesis in Ms Moser's response to an email sent by Mr Hu to the Authority on 22 January, 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">The email was addressed to Mr Brad Abbott.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">He had been an officer of the Authority during the currency of Mr Hu's first complaint to the Authority in 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Mr Abbott was involved in the handling of Mr Hu's first complaint and was a point of contact for Mr Hu with the Authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The email of 22 January, 2009 asked that Mr Abbott sign an email that he had sent on 18 September, 2008 (relating to the first complaint made by Mr Hu to the Authority).</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">Mr Hu made two further requests, but they are difficult to understand.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">I set them out in full: 
 
 
 
 
 o Secondly, I have inquire is about how to protect my family privacy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">I stronger doubt about Chris Campbell leak my privacy for illegal purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">I hope to temporarily freeze my authority to MARA about my privacy .</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">o Furthermore, if my case has not been finalized, I request the MARA Committee to charge my complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">If my case already has been done, I request the MARA Committee to send me the formal MARA official decision letter with the appointed authority signature by post .</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">
 
 

 
 
 
 (faithfully reproduced).</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">
 
 

 
 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">On what appears to be 29 January, 2009, Ms Moser replied to Mr Hu's email of 22 January.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">She said: 
 
 
 
 
 o Mr Abbott is no longer employed at the Migration Agents Registration Authority (MARA).</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">I am therefore unable to provide you with a "signed email" as requested .</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">o A decision on your complaint (file ref0316914-4362) was made on 9 September 2008 and notified by email to you.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Following this, you raised some issues regarding the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">On 2 October 2008 you indicated that you did not want MARA to contact you any more .</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">o We now consider the matter closed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">As you have been advised you have a right to approach the Commonwealth Ombudsman if you are dissatisfied with our decision .</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">o In relation to your concerns about privacy, MARA will not release personal information about you unless it is required to do so by law .</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">
 
 
 
 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">On 30 January, 2009 Ms Moser sent to Mr Hu copies of some documents that had been received by the Authority from the migration agent that was the subject of Mr Hu's complaint to the Authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">According to the evidence, they were received by him on 5 February, 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The documents so provided included three documents that were said to comprise the contract of retainer between Mr Hu and the relevant migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">In fact the three pages referred to are a letter from the migration agent to Mr Hu dated 12 March, 2007 (2 pages) and an authority bearing the letterhead of Bond &amp; Forsyth (1 page).</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Bond &amp; Forsyth appear to be the employer of the migration agent with whom Mr Hu fell into dispute.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">The latter document authorises the migration agent to act on Mr Hu's behalf.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">It also contains some acknowledgments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">It bears the date 12 March, 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The copies of the documents supplied to Mr Hu bear a certification on each page in the following terms: 
 
 
 
 
 This is a true and accurate copy 
 of the original 
 (signed) 
 JOEY SIEN POONG CHUNG 
 The Justice of The Peace 180711 
 Date: 04 June 2008 
 
 
 
 
 9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Mr Hu says that the documents provided by Ms Moser are forgeries, perhaps prepared by the migration agent in response to his complaint to the Authority about her.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">As evidence of this, he argues that the documents are not signed on all pages by him as one might expect them to be, they are not in a sufficiently legal form and that the one page that does bear his signature is different to that which he remembers signing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Further, he says that his signature was not witnessed by "The Justice of The Peace" that certification having been placed in the documents long after he signed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">4 June, 2008 is the date of the migration agent's response to the complaint made by Mr Hu to the Authority.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">It seems reasonable to assume that the certification by "The Justice of The Peace" was placed on the documents for that purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">I do not consider it reasonable to read the certification as some form of witnessing of Mr Hu's signature on the relevant documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">It does not purport to be so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">It merely appears to be certification of the correctness of the copy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">On 5 February, 2009 Mr Hu sent an email to Ms Moser in the following terms: 
 
 
 
 
 o I have received the registered post mail today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Thank you very much for your help .</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">o After I checked the documents inside, I did not find the email from documents which I put it in the attachment name unsigned email .</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">o And I also hope to confirm whether the other three documents in the attachment were the copies of the contract between the agent and I which Mara received from my former agent Ms Liu .</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">o Best Regards, 
 
 

 
 
 
 (faithfully reproduced).</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">
 
 

 
 
 12.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">On 6 February, 2009 Ms Moser responded to Mr Hu: 
 
 
 
 
 o We will send the signed email you have requested below in the post today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">With regards to the other three documents, as far as we are aware they are the contract .</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">o Signed ---Vee* Moser 
 
 

 
 
 .... 
 

 
 
 15.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Mr Hu's complaint to the Ombudsman was delegated to Mr Pezzanite for action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Notwithstanding the terms of Mr Hu's complaint, it was approached by Mr Pezzanite as a more general complaint about the reasoning process that led to the dismissal of his original complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">In particular Mr Pezzanite understood that Mr Hu was concerned by the Authority's view that the letter and the authority with it were "the contract" between Mr Hu and the relevant migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Consistent with that understanding, on 16 April, 2009 Mr Pezzanite wrote to Mr Hu: 
 
 
 
 
 o So that we may better understand your complaint, could you please answer the following queries :
 o 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Do you believe that some or all of the three documents provided to you by the MARA, referred to by it as "the contract", are fake?</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">
 o 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Do you allege that the Migration Agent provided these fake documents to the MARA or do you allege that the MARA produced fake documents?</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">
 o 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">Did you enter into any other contract with this Migration Agent?</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">If so, could you please provide us with a copy of it?</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">
 o 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">What impact have these documents had on your complaint to the MARA?</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">
 o 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">If the documents are fake, what information presented in those documents do you believe has been to your detriment?</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">
 o 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">What outcome are you hoping to achieve through this complaint?</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">
 o Once we receive your responses, we will then be in a better position to determine whether we need to contact the MARA and investigate the issues you have raised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">
 
 
 
 
 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Mr Hu's response made it clear that his complaint was against Ms Moser " and her conducts ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">He also made it clear that he asserted that the documents said by the Authority to be the contract of retainer with the migration agent were not genuine and that they were not signed on every page by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">17.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">Thereafter followed an exchange of correspondence between Mr Hu and Mr Pezzanite which culminated in the decision now under review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">I will not set out in full the terms of that correspondence, suffice it to say that it consists largely of requests by Mr Pezzanite for explanations and Mr Hu's answers to those requests.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">
 

 I adopt this summary of background facts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">Mr Hu's understanding of the legal process
 With respect, in my view Mr Hu's submissions both in Court and in writing reflect significant misapprehensions as to the nature of the legal process, the role of the Judge and Counsel, appropriate conduct of legal representatives, and indeed the basis of his own claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">Further, with respect, Mr Hu's command of written English, while good, is sufficiently uncertain such that difficulties arise with identifying his claims and understanding his contentions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">These issues have considerably complicated these proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">So, for example: These issues have not assisted Mr Hu's case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">Grounds of appeal
 The grounds of appeal specified in Mr Hu's notice of appeal are as follows: Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify and apply grounds --- Section 5 ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 
 Failure by Federal Magistrate to make order of review --- Section 16 ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 
 Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify default --- Reg 13.03A FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 
 Failure by Federal Magistrate to make order on default --- Reg 13.03B FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 
 Failure by Federal Magistrate not to allow discovery --- Section 45 FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 
 Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify apparent forged information in documents from filed affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">Failure by Federal Magistrate to give adequate reasons for the decision "dismissed" --- Whether a denial of natural justice --- Whether Federal Magistrate erred in fact in no finding that Commonwealth Ombudsman breached the grounds of section 5 of Judicial Review Act 1977.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">
 
 (reproduced as in the original document) 
 

 I will now turn to these grounds of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">Ground 1: Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify and apply grounds --- Section 5 ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 
 Section 5 of the ADJR Act provides as follows: 
 
 (1) A person who is aggrieved by a decision to which this Act applies that is made after the commencement of this Act may apply to the Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court for an order of review in respect of the decision on any one or more of the following grounds: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) that a breach of the rules of natural justice occurred in connection with the making of the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) that procedures that were required by law to be observed in connection with the making of the decision were not observed; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) that the person who purported to make the decision did not have jurisdiction to make the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (d) that the decision was not authorized by the enactment in pursuance of which it was purported to be made; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (e) that the making of the decision was an improper exercise of the power conferred by the enactment in pursuance of which it was purported to be made; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (f) that the decision involved an error of law, whether or not the error appears on the record of the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (g) that the decision was induced or affected by fraud; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (h) that there was no evidence or other material to justify the making of the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (j) that the decision was otherwise contrary to law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">
 
 

 
 
 (2) The reference in paragraph (1)(e) to an improper exercise of a power shall be construed as including a reference to: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) taking an irrelevant consideration into account in the exercise of a power; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) failing to take a relevant consideration into account in the exercise of a power; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) an exercise of a power for a purpose other than a purpose for which the power is conferred; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (d) an exercise of a discretionary power in bad faith; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (e) an exercise of a personal discretionary power at the direction or behest of another person; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (f) an exercise of a discretionary power in accordance with a rule or policy without regard to the merits of the particular case; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (g) an exercise of a power that is so unreasonable that no reasonable person could have so exercised the power; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (h) an exercise of a power in such a way that the result of the exercise of the power is uncertain; and 
 
 

 
 
 
 (j) any other exercise of a power in a way that constitutes abuse of the power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">
 
 

 
 
 (3) The ground specified in paragraph (1)(h) shall not be taken to be made out unless: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) the person who made the decision was required by law to reach that decision only if a particular matter was established, and there was no evidence or other material (including facts of which he or she was entitled to take notice) from which he or she could reasonably be satisfied that the matter was established; or 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) the person who made the decision based the decision on the existence of a particular fact, and that fact did not exist.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">
 
 

 The first ground of appeal was not particularised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">In his written submissions however Mr Hu made (in summary) the following contentions: In my view however this ground of appeal is without merit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">I form this view for the following reasons: First, Mr Hu's contentions in respect of this ground of appeal include reliance on material which is irrelevant, including speeches by staff of the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">Second, in relation to Mr Hu's claims concerning s 5(1)(j) I am unable to see how the respondent has acted contrary to law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">In particular I note that s 6(1) of the Ombudsman Act vests the respondent with a very broad discretion not to investigate an action the subject of a complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">Despite Mr Hu's objections at the hearing to the respondent's contention that there is nothing in this section that indicates that the discretion is fettered in any way, no material submitted by Mr Hu suggests any fetter on the discretion of the respondent in terms of s 6(1).</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">A plain reading of the section supports a finding that the respondent's discretion is unfettered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Third, in relation to his claims concerning s 5(1)(b) ,(e) and (g) the basis of Mr Hu's claim is untenable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">This is because it is clear that Mr Hu confuses the alleged fraud and forgery of the migration agent with the requirements of s 5 of the ADJR Act, which require, inter alia , that the decision of the decision-maker be tainted by fraud.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">The decision-maker is the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">Fourth, and significantly, it is in fact clear from the decision of the Federal Magistrate that his Honour identified and considered all grounds in s 5 of the ADJR Act sought to be advanced by Mr Hu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">As the respondent also submitted, it is also evident from the transcript in the proceedings before his Honour that the Federal Magistrate sought clarification of each and every ground in s 5 of the ADJR Act advanced by the appellant (TS No BRG 311 of 2009 pp 10-11 and 20).</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Finally, it is clear that, with respect to Mr Hu's claims pursuant to s 5 of the ADJR Act, his Honour made the following findings: In respect of the failure of the respondent to identify the relevant documentation as forgeries, the respondent had considered Mr Hu's concerns.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">However the respondent ultimately considered Mr Hu's concerns irrelevant because there was no dispute that there was an engagement of the migration agent by Mr Hu, and the substance of his complaint about the agent went to the agent's actions and inaction rather than the form or content of the contract of retainer (at [27]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">In particular, I note that the respondent's letter to Mr Hu of 27 April 2009 following extensive correspondence targeted at gaining a complete understanding of Mr Hu's complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">The letter concluded: 
 
 
 
 After carefully considering the information you have supplied we have decided not to investigate your complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The reason for this decision is that it is not apparent that you: 
 
 
 
 Dispute that there was a contract between yourself and the Migration Agent, Jennifer Liu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">Dispute the date of "the contract" (12 March 2007), or contend that the date of the contract was a relevant issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">Are alleging that the information contained in "the contract" provided to you by the MARA is incorrect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">Rather you appear to be questioning the contract's legal validity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">You have not provided our office with any indication of what alternate facts might exist that you believe MARA has failed to take into account, other than expressing the general view that MARA should have not placed any reliance on the contract when it investigated your compliant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">Have provided any specific reasons as to why you believe your complaint against your Migration Agent should be reopened, other than your general allegations about "the contract".</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">Have provided any information to show that an investigation by our office is likely to produce a specific remedy for you in your dealings with the MARA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">
 
 
 
 I have concluded for the above reasons, that an investigation of your complaint is not warranted in all the circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">Specifically, I am not satisfied that the information you have provided to our office discloses that MARA relied upon inaccurate and/or false information in its investigation of your complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">I can appreciate that this is not an outcome you would have hoped for, however I hope you will see that we have given careful consideration to all the information you provided and have formed a view that is reasonable in all the circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">
 
 
 

 No order could be made as sought by Mr Hu with respect to the breaches of MARA's service standards in the absence of that entity being joined as a party to the proceedings (at [23]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">No absence of natural justice had been established in the presence of substantial correspondence between Mr Hu and the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">As his Honour observed: 
 
 
 
 The evidence, and specifically the correspondence between Mr Pezzanite and Mr Hu, demonstrates that care was taken to understand the underlying complaints made by Mr Hu and to seek explanation about those complaints.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">The reasons for deciding not to investigate Mr Hu's complaint are clear and cogent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">(at [33]) 
 
 
 

 No material has been placed before me in these proceedings to persuade me that the decision of his Honour was attended by error such that an appeal should be allowed on this ground.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">Ground 2: Failure by Federal Magistrate to make order of review --- Section 16 ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 
 Section 16 of the ADJR Act provides as follows: 
 
 Powers of the Federal Court and the Federal Magistrates Court in respect of applications for order of review 
 

 
 
 (1) On an application for an order of review in respect of a decision, the Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court may, in its discretion, make all or any of the following orders: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) an order quashing or setting aside the decision, or a part of the decision, with effect from the date of the order or from such earlier or later date as the court specifies; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) an order referring the matter to which the decision relates to the person who made the decision for further consideration, subject to such directions as the court thinks fit; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) an order declaring the rights of the parties in respect of any matter to which the decision relates; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (d) an order directing any of the parties to do, or to refrain from doing, any act or thing the doing, or the refraining from the doing, of which the court considers necessary to do justice between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">
 
 

 
 
 (2) On an application for an order of review in respect of conduct that has been, is being, or is proposed to be, engaged in for the purpose of the making of a decision, the Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court may, in its discretion, make either or both of the following orders: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) an order declaring the rights of the parties in respect of any matter to which the conduct relates; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) an order directing any of the parties to do, or to refrain from doing, any act or thing the doing, or the refraining from the doing, of which the court considers necessary to do justice between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">
 
 

 
 
 (3) On an application for an order of review in respect of a failure to make a decision, or in respect of a failure to make a decision within the period within which the decision was required to be made, the Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court may, in its discretion, make all or any of the following orders: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) an order directing the making of the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) an order declaring the rights of the parties in relation to the making of the decision; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) an order directing any of the parties to do, or to refrain from doing, any act or thing the doing, or the refraining from the doing, of which the court considers necessary to do justice between the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">
 
 

 
 
 (4) The Federal Court or the Federal Magistrates Court may at any time, of its own motion or on the application of any party, revoke, vary, or suspend the operation of, any order made by it under this section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">
 

 Unfortunately, other than reference to an "order for review" Mr Hu did not specify the order he sought in terms of s 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">The respondent submitted that Mr Hu sought an order in terms of s 16(1)(b), namely referral of the matter by the Court back to the respondent for further consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">In any event however, I agree with the respondent that the types of orders that can be made pursuant to s 16 of the ADJR Act are dependent upon the Court being satisfied that one or more of the grounds in s 5 of the ADJR Act have been substantiated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">In light of my findings in relation to s 5 there is no basis upon which an order pursuant to s 16 is justified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">Ground 3: Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify default --- Reg 13.03A FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 
 Unfortunately Mr Hu has not particularised this ground of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">So far as I can understand, it appears that this ground of appeal relates to failure of the respondent to file material in the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court in accordance with the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">I form this view based on the identification by Mr Hu in his submissions of r 4.05 and r 13.03A(2)(a),(b)(iv) and (vii) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules and the following specific written submission: 
 
 Under Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 , Rule 4.05 , Rule 13.03A(2)(a)(b) ,(iv) and (vii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">The respondent did not file affidavit with response, and in any time of the proceeding, delay the time for appellant's preparing for respondent's supporting documents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">Those conducts were definitely default.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">The default conducts made the appellant have totally a few hours to prepare the litigations, infringing the appellant's legal right.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">
 

 
 
 (reproduced as in the original document) 
 

 So far as appears relevant, r 4.05 provides: 
 
 (1) A person filing an application or response, whether seeking final, interim or procedural orders, must also file an affidavit stating the facts relied on.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">
 

 Further, so far as appears relevant, r 13.03A provides:
 
 
 Rule 13.03A 
 

 
 
 ... 
 

 
 
 (2) For rule 13.03B , a respondent is in default if the respondent: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) has not satisfied the applicant's claim; and 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) fails to: 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (i) give an address for service before the time for the respondent to give an address has expired; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (ii) file a response before the time for the respondent to file a response has expired; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (iii) comply with an order of the Court in the proceeding; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (iv) file and serve a document required under these Rules; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (v) produce a document as required by Part 14 ; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (vi) do any act required to be done by these Rules; or 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 (vii) defend the proceeding with due diligence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">
 
 
 

 Turning to the Court file from the Federal Magistrates Court, it appears that: At the hearing before his Honour on 15 July 2009 Mr Hu said the following: 
 
 And, also, the relevant rules applied to them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">The response must file (indistinct) affidavit and the response must give precisely and briefly state any orders sought and the basis on which orders are sought, but they failed in this.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">So, that caused untrue statement take into this - consideration and make loss to me and also I think in this proceeding, Ms Jenna filed documents on - the last affidavit on 2 June, but send me - I mean handing me the affidavit just 10 minutes before entering the Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">I thought they have deafult in the Court and if your Honour says they are default, then they should actually get order in my application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">(TS No BRG 311 of 2009 15 July 2009 p 8 ll 1-9) 
 

 From this summary I understand that the following issues are potentially relevant to this ground of appeal: Ms Lye's affidavit, answering the description in r 4.05(1) was filed on behalf of the respondent 10 days after the response was filed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">Arguably, by filing the affidavit late, the respondent has failed to "do any act required to be done by these Rules", in particular r 4.05(1) and r 13.03A(2)(b)(vi).</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">As I have already noted, the respondent filed an amended response on 15 July 2009 (that is, out of time) after emailing a copy of this document to Mr Hu the previous evening.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">The respondent also handed to his Honour a written outline of submissions at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">In relation to these issues I make the following observations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">First, in relation to the filing of Ms Lye's affidavit 10 days after the response was filed, while this may have been in breach of the rules it is difficult to see how Mr Hu was prejudiced given that the hearing was not until 15 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">Second, in relation to the filing of the amended response by the respondent on 15 July 2009, and the submission of a written outline by the respondent on the same day, I note from the transcript of the hearing before his Honour that: I note further that none of this activity related to directions made by his Honour in this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">The only directions of his Honour were dated 3 June 2009 when his Honour ordered that: The application is listed for trial on 15 July 2009 with an agreed hearing estimate of one (1) day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">The applicant file and serve any further affidavits on which he intends to rely at hearing no later than 4.00 pm on 10 June 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">
 
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">Costs reserved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">
 

 At para 35 and para 36 of the reasons for decision his Honour found that any non-compliance by the respondent with directions was insignificant, and that no prejudice was occasioned to Mr Hu by these events.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">I agree.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">I have also examined the response of the respondent filed 22 May 2009, and compared it with the amended response filed 15 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">Both are documents of one and a half pages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">The only amendments to the response included in the amended response were: updating the reference in the response to the orders sought by Mr Hu in his amended application filed 22 May 2009; updating the reference in the response to Mr Hu's amended application for review filed 22 May 2009; updating the reference to orders which the Federal Magistrates Court did not have power to make to include Orders 32, 33, 34 and 35 sought by Mr Hu; including a new ground of opposition as follows: 
 
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">Order 31 seeks the Respondent to pay the Applicant's costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">The Respondent contends that costs should follow the event.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">
 
 

 In my view the amended response relied on by the respondent, and accepted for filing by his Honour, contained such minor changes to the original response that Mr Hu did not suffer prejudice from the late filing of this document.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">I do not accept Mr Hu's contention that, as a result of the filing of the amended response on 15 July 2009, that he had "only a few hours to prepare the litigations (sic)".</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">I am unable to identify any error in his Honour's judgment whereby his Honour declined to make orders in default in Mr Hu's favour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">Ground 4: Failure by Federal Magistrate to make order on default --- Reg 13.03B FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 
 Ground 4 relates to ground 3 in the notice of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">In his submissions, Mr Hu contended: 
 
 Under Rule 13.03B(2)(b)(d)(e) and (3), the Magistrate should order the respondent to pay appellant's cost in the proceeding and judgment against the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">But the Magistrate failed in identifying the respondent's default conducts and failed in making default order on the appellant's favour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">
 

 I understand that Mr Hu contends that the Federal Magistrate should have given judgment in his favour or made an order against the respondent in terms of r 13.03B(2)(d) because of the failure of the respondent to file an affidavit in support of its response on the same date as the response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">This ground of appeal is untenable for the same reasons that I have given in relation to ground 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Ground 5: Failure by Federal Magistrate not to allow discovery --- Section 45 FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 
 Section 45 of the Federal Magistrates Act 1999 (Cth) provides as follows: 
 
 (1) Interrogatories and discovery are not allowed in relation to proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court unless the Federal Magistrates Court or a Federal Magistrate declares that it is appropriate, in the interests of the administration of justice, to allow the interrogatories or discovery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">
 

 
 
 (2) In deciding whether to make a declaration under subsection (1), the Federal Magistrates Court or a Federal Magistrate must have regard to: 
 

 
 
 
 (a) whether allowing the interrogatories or discovery would be likely to contribute to the fair and expeditious conduct of the proceedings; and 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) such other matters (if any) as the Federal Magistrates Court or the Federal Magistrate considers relevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">
 
 

 It appears that Mr Hu first raised the issue of discovery at the actual hearing before his Honour on 15 July 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">The transcript shows the following statement by Mr Hu: 
 
 If it would --- can't make that, I think I should take the --- sought order number 2 into the specific (indistinct) together which was --- or the Commonwealth Ombudsman's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">I mean just the Commonwealth Ombudsman's office to investigate my complaint.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">I just want to add this into those 12 orders I especially want.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Discovery of or inspection to the court contract and to transfer the (indistinct) in the Court and prosecuting authority because this issue has happened over three years since I have made the arrangement, make a contract with this agent and MARA's delegate, Mr Cambere and Moser and also Ombudsman's delegate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">(TS No BRG 311 of 2009 15 July 2009 p 25 ll 7-15) 
 

 In NAQR &amp; Anor (No.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">1) v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FMCA 271 Driver FM took the view that there is a rebuttable presumption in proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court that discovery and interrogatories will not be permitted, consistent with Parliament's direction under s 33 of the Federal Magistrates Act that the Court should act informally and use streamlined procedures (at [5]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">In my view this accurately represents the position in respect of s 45 of the Federal Magistrates Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">I also consider however that s 45 of the Federal Magistrates Act vests Federal Magistrates with discretion to order discovery in the circumstances prescribed by the section.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">In my view the fifth ground of appeal cannot be substantiated for two reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">First, on the basis that his Honour had discretion to order discovery in this case, no satisfactory case has been made to me warranting interference with the decision of his Honour in circumstances contemplated by Dixon, Evatt and McTiernan JJ in House v R [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499 at 505.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">Second, and in any event, Mr Hu has not established that the interests of the administration of justice would have been served by his Honour making an order allowing discovery pursuant to s 45.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">I accept the submission of the respondent that, in light of the fact that the first time Mr Hu raised the issue of discovery was at the hearing itself before his Honour, it would not have contributed to the "fair and expeditious conduct of the proceedings" for his Honour to have ordered discovery at such a late stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">Ground 6: Failure by Federal Magistrate to identify apparent forged information in documents from filed affidavit
 A substantial proportion of Mr Hu's written submissions concerned the alleged failure of his Honour to identify apparently forged documents provided to Mr Hu by Ms Moser of MARA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">The first point to note is that it was not the task of the Federal Magistrate to investigate whether documentation provided by MARA to Mr Hu was forged by the migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">In the circumstances of this case it was the task of the Federal Magistrate to consider whether there were grounds for an order of review of the decision of the respondent for any of the reasons set out in s 5 of the ADJR Act (cf comments of Mason CJ in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 94 ALR 11 at 26).</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">Mr Hu's submissions in relation to this ground of appeal are, in substance, an attack on the qualifications and professional standards of his Honour in failing to identify forgeries claimed to exist by Mr Hu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">In this respect this ground of appeal is completely without merit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">Nonetheless secondly, Mr Hu submits that the respondent failed to take into account relevant considerations in making the decision not to investigate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">This is potentially a ground for an order of review in terms of s 5(1)(f) of the ADJR Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">In particular I note comments of Dixon J in Avon Downs Pty Ltd v FCT [1949] HCA 26 ; (1949) 78 CLR 353 at 360: 
 
 But it is for the commissioner, not for me, to be satisfied of the state of the voting power at the end of the year of income.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">His decision, it is true, is not unexaminable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">If he does not address himself to the question which the subsection formulates, if his conclusion is affected by some mistake of law, if he takes some extraneous reason into consideration or excludes from consideration some factor which should affect his determination, on any of these grounds his conclusion is liable to review.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">
 

 
(cf Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Applicant S20/2002 [2003] HCA 30 ; (2003) 198 ALR 59 at [8] , Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118-9)
 However, Mr Hu's submissions in respect of this issue are untenable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">The considerations to which the respondent should have had regard are, in Mr Hu's submissions, as follows: Finally, and in any event, his Honour considered the issue of forgery raised by Mr Hu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">His Honour observed that Mr Hu had not denied the existence of a contract between himself and the migration agent, but rather was concerned that a subsequent copy provided to MARA by the migration agent was not in the form that he recalled, and included an improper certification.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">He alleges in particular that his wife would have signed the documentation had it been legitimate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">It is clear that before both his Honour and this Court Mr Hu: At [27] of the reasons for decision his Honour found as follows: 
 
 In summary, Mr Pezzanite concluded that whilst Mr Hu had some issue about the characterisation of the three documents referred to above as a contract with the relevant migration agent, the issues were ultimately irrelevant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">They were irrelevant because there was no dispute there was an engagement of the migration agent by Mr Hu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">The substance of his complaint about the agent went to the agent's actions and inaction rather than the form or content of the contract of retainer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">
 

 Later his Honour said: 
 
 In my view, the evidence simply does not establish any of the matters complained of by Mr Hu concerning the conduct of the Commonwealth Ombudsman or Mr Pezzanite.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">The evidence, and specifically the correspondence between Mr Pezzanite and Mr Hu, demonstrates that care was taken to understand the underlying complaints made by Mr Hu and to seek explanation about those complaints.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">The reasons for deciding not to investigate Mr Hu's complaint are clear and cogent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">(at [33]) 
 

 In my view it was open to the Federal Magistrate to make these findings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">Finally, Mr Hu submitted that the documents provided to him by Ms Moser were clearly forged because his wife's signature did not appear on them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">The presence or absence of the signature of Mr Hu's wife is neither here nor there in the absence of relevant evidence and a case based upon that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">In this respect no appellable error appears on the face of his Honour's reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">Ground 7: Failure by Federal Magistrate to give adequate reasons for the decision "dismissed" --- Whether a denial of natural justice --- Whether Federal Magistrate erred in fact in no finding that Commonwealth Ombudsman breached the grounds of section 5 of Judicial Review Act 1977
 In my view this ground of appeal is untenable in that: Adequate reasons were given by his Honour in relation to Mr Hu's application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">In particular, I note his Honour's observations at [13]-[14] where his Honour said as follows: 
 
 
 13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">On 20 March, 2009 Mr Hu made the complaint relevant to this application to the Commonwealth Ombudsman.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">It is clear that his complaint is against Ms Moser, whose only participation in this affair seems to have been to answer Mr Hu's emails of January and February, 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">In his letter of complaint, Mr Hu asserts that: " In my understanding, Ms Moser has made a decision, which was not reasonably open to make in the circumstances .</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">" The decision is said to be contained in Ms Moser's reply to Mr Hu on 6 February 2009 set out above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">Mr Hu's assertion is that Ms Moser has decided that the three documents referred to in her email were the contract between him and the relevant migration agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">
 
 

 
 
 
 14.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">The difficulty with Mr Hu's argument is that Ms Moser decided no such thing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">She merely relayed information to Mr Hu at his request.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">She merely provided copies of documents on the Authority's file to Mr Hu.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">She played no part in the determination of Mr Hu's complaint to the Authority about the agent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">That was done by others within the Authority and is the subject of my earlier decision: Hu v Giles [2009] FMCA 368.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">
 
 

 As his Honour observed in para [32] of the reasons for decision, Mr Hu has not been the subject of a denial of natural justice by the respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">Indeed I note that Mr Paul Bluck of the respondent's office also undertook a further informal review of Mr Hu's complaint and the respondent's formal handling of the matter at the commencement of these proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court, to assist Mr Hu understand the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">I am not persuaded by Mr Hu's general claim that his Honour erred in respect of his findings concerning s 5 of the ADJR Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">Notices of Constitutional Matters
 Finally, Mr Hu has filed two Notices of a constitutional matter under s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">The first notice filed 29 September 2009 ("first notice") provides as follows: 
 
 NOTICE OF A CONSTITUTIONAL MATTER 
 

 YUANYUAN HU, the appellant gives notice that the above proceeding involves a matter arising under the Constitution or involving its interpretation within the meaning of section 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">In the proceeding of [2009] FMCA 785 , Ombudsman's office has influenced the decisions of Federal Magistrate Jarrett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">In the proceeding of [2009] FMCA 785 , Federal Magistrate Jarrett did not interpret the legislation, but replace the practicing of Ombudsman's exercising of the legislation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">The matter is one to section 78B(1) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">
 

 
 
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">The matter is one to section 78B(2) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">
 

 
 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">The matter is one to section 78B(3)(a) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">
 

 
 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">The matter is one to section 78B(5) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">
 

 The second notice filed 1 October 2009 ("second notice") provides as follows: YUANYUAN HU, the appellant gives notice that the above proceeding involves a matter arising under the Constitution or involving its interpretation within the meaning of section 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">In the proceeding of QUD201/2009, Ombudsman's office has influenced the decisions of Federal Justice Collier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">In the proceeding of QUD201/2009, Federal Justice Collier did not interpret the legislation, but not obey the legislation under 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 .</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">
 
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">The matter is one to section 78B(1) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">
 

 
 
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">The matter is one to section 78B(2) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">
 

 
 
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">The matter is one to section 78B(3)(a) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">
 

 
 
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">The matter is one to section 78B(5) of the Judiciary Act 1903 applies.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">
 

 Mr Hu contended at the hearing before me that he had served a notice on the Commonwealth Attorney-General.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">A copy of a letter to Mr Hu from the Australian Government Solicitor on behalf of the Commonwealth Attorney-General dated 5 November 2009 was tendered as an exhibit by Mr Hu at the hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">In the letter Mr Hu was informed that the Commonwealth Attorney-General would not be intervening in the Federal Court proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">It is not clear whether the second notice was served on all State and Territory Attorneys as required by O 51 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules .</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">Further, it is not clear whether the first notice was served on any of the Attorneys as required by O 51 r 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">In the absence of evidence to this effect, constitutional issues raised in the notices do not arise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">In any event however: Mr Hu did not press issues in respect of the notices at the hearing before me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">In relation to the first notice there is no basis for an allegation that the respondent influenced the decisions in proceedings before his Honour.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">I agree with the respondent that, although Mr Hu may be dissatisfied with his Honour's decision, that decision is not tainted by any error, including one arising in respect of the Constitution .</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">In any event the basis upon which Mr Hu alleges a constitutional issue in terms of s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) is not clear to me.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">In relation to the second notice I am unable to identify any matter arising under the Constitution .</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">It does not appear that Mr Hu has alleged bias in respect of my orders of 22 September 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">In relation to draft directions submitted by the respondent for consideration in relation to the directions hearing of 22 September 2009, this is consistent with O 10 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules which provides: 
 
 
 On a directions hearing, each party shall, so far as is practicable, apply for any interlocutory order or directions which he may require.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">
 
 

 
Mr Hu has not challenged the validity of O 10 r 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">In relation to the fact that the appeal was heard by me in accordance with s 25(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) when Mr Hu had pressed for the appeal to be heard by a Full Bench, in the absence of a challenge to the validity of s 25(1A) no error or constitutional matter arises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">Conclusion
 In my view the appropriate orders are that the appeal be dismissed, and that Mr Hu pay the respondent its costs to be taxed if not otherwise agreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">I certify that the preceding fifty-eight (58) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Collier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 16 December 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr G Del Villar 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 1 December 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 December 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1516.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>