<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tung-Liang Liang v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2009] FCA 189 (3 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/189.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">judicial review of decision of migration review tribunal refusing grant of business skills visa for breach of business operation limitation condition prescribed by regulation attaching to visa held</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">business skills visa</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">finding that applicant had not complied substantially with visa condition</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">visa refused because appellant conducted more than two "main businesses"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">meaning of "main business"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">meaning of "business"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">visa also refused because appellant did not continue to meet visa criteria between application and final decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">appellant did not have an ownership interest in a main business at the time of the tribunal's decision</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">meaning of "continues"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">appeal dismissed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">"main business"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">"business"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">"continues"</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">migration</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">words and phrases</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 The Appellant, Tung-Liang Liang, applied under the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act) for what is known as a Business Skills (Permanent) Visa as long ago as November 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">Also covered by that application were his wife and their son.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The application was initially refused by a delegate of the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (the Minister), the active Respondent in the present appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">In turn, that refusal decision was affirmed by the Migration Review Tribunal (the Tribunal).</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The Tribunal's decision was quashed on judicial review by the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The matter was then remitted to the Tribunal for hearing afresh.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">On the second hearing of the application for the review by the Tribunal of the refusal decision, the Tribunal again decided to affirm the refusal of the visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">In turn, the Appellant again sought the judicial review of that decision by the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On this occasion, that court decided to dismiss the judicial review application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Following the grant of extension of time within which to appeal, it is from that decision that the Appellant appeals to this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">There are two grounds of appeal: That the learned Federal Magistrate erred in finding that the decision of the Second Respondent, made on 11 July 2009, affirming the decision of the First Respondent delegate to refuse to grant the appellant a Business Skills (Permanent) Visa was not affected by jurisdictional error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">The jurisdictional errors of the Second Respondent were that it: 
 (a) Failed to properly understand or apply Regulation 1.11 of the Migration Regulation in that it found the appellant had nominated a third " Main Business " in contravention of Regulation 1.11(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">It did so because the Tribunal treated the Appellant's first two businesses discretely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">It was then submitted they were in fact the same business but trading under different names; and/or
 (b) Failed properly to understand or apply criterion 845.221 in Schedule 2 to the Regulations by wrongly holding that the Appellant did not satisfy criteria 845.221 because he did not continue to particularly satisfy criteria 845.213 and 845.216 of Schedule 2 to the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">
 Before turning to the merits of these grounds, reference should be made to pertinent provisions of the Act and the Migration Regulations 1994 (the Regulations).</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">By s 65 of the Act, if, after considering a valid visa application, the Minister is satisfied, materially, that the criteria for that class of visa as prescribed either by the Act or the Regulations have been satisfied, the Minister is to grant that visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">If not so satisfied, the Minister is obliged by s 65 of the Act to refuse to grant the visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The Minister is permitted to delegate the performance of this function.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Section 41 of the Act permits the making of regulations which provide that visas, or visas of a specified class, are subject to specified conditions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Section 31(3) of the Act permits the making of regulations which prescribe criteria for a visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Section 504 of the Act empowers the Governor-General to make such regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Materially, the effect of reg 2.03 of the Regulations is that, for the purposes of s 31(3) of the Act, one looks to Sch 2 to the Regulations for the prescribed criteria of the grant to a person of a visa of a particular class.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Within Sch 2 to the Regulations, those criteria presently pertinent for the grant of a Business Skills (Permanent) Visa are found within sub-class 845.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Consideration of this appeal requires that a number of the clauses within sub-class 845 be set out: 
 845.1 Interpretation 

 
Note 1 AUD , ownership interest and qualifying business are defined in regulation 1.03; and main business is defined in regulation 1.11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Note 2 As to beneficial ownership of an asset or ownership interest, see regulation 1.11A.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Note 3 There are no interpretation provisions specific to this Part.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">
 845.2 Primary criteria 

 
Note The primary criteria must be satisfied by at least 1 member of a family unit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">The other members of the family unit who are applicants for a visa of this subclass need satisfy only the secondary criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">
 845.21 Criteria to be satisfied at time of application 

 
 845.211 The applicant holds a temporary substantive visa other than any of the following visas: 

 
 (a) a special purpose visa; 
 (b) a Border (Temporary) (Class TA) visa; 
 (c) a Diplomatic (Temporary) (Class TF) visa; 
 (d) a Domestic Worker (Temporary) (Class TG) visa; 
 (e) a Transit (Temporary) (Class TX) visa; 
 (ea) a Maritime Crew (Temporary) (Class ZM) visa; 
 (eb) Superyacht Crew (Temporary) (Class UW) visa; 
 (f) a transitional (temporary) visa that the applicant is taken to hold because he or she held, or applied for, a visa referred to in paragraph (a), (b), (c), (d) or (e) before 1 September 1994.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">

 
 845.212 One or more of the following circumstances has existed for a total of at least 272 days in the period of 12 months ending immediately before the application is made: 

 
 (a) the applicant has been in Australia as the holder of a temporary substantive visa other than a visa referred to in clause 845.211; 
 (b) the applicant has been in Australia as the holder of a Bridging A (Class WA) visa granted on the basis of a valid application for a Temporary Business Entry (Class UC) visa, and a Subclass 457 visa was subsequently granted on the basis of the applicant, or the spouse or former spouse of the applicant, satisfying subclause 457.223 (7A) of Schedule 2; 
 (c) the applicant has been in Australia as the holder of a Bridging B (Class WB) visa granted on the basis of a valid application for a Temporary Business Entry (Class UC) visa, and a Subclass 457 visa was subsequently granted on the basis of the applicant, or the spouse or former spouse of the applicant, satisfying subclause 457.223 (7A) of Schedule 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">

 
 845.213 The applicant: 

 
 (a) has had an ownership interest in 1 or more established main businesses in Australia for the period of 18 months immediately preceding the making of the application; and 
 (b) continues to have an interest of that kind.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">

 
 845.214 The assets in Australia of the applicant, or the applicant and his or her spouse together: 

 
 (a) have a net value of at least AUD250 000; and 
 (b) had a net value of at least AUD250 000 throughout the period of 12 months ending immediately before the application is made; and 
 (c) have been lawfully acquired by the applicant, or the applicant and his or her spouse together.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">

 
 845.215 The assets owned by the applicant, or by the applicant and his or her spouse together, in the main business or main businesses in Australia: 

 
 (a) have a net value of at least AUD100 000; and 
 (b) had a net value of at least AUD100 000 throughout the period of 12 months ending immediately before the application is made; and 
 (c) have been lawfully acquired by the applicant, or the applicant and his or her spouse together.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">
 
 
 845.216 In the 12 months immediately preceding the making of the application, the applicant, as the owner of an interest in a main business or main businesses in Australia, maintained direct and continuous involvement in the management of that business or those businesses from day to day and in making decisions that affected the overall direction and performance of that business or those businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">

 
 845.217 The applicant has overall had a successful business career.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">

 
 845.218 Neither the applicant nor his or her spouse (if any) has a history of involvement in business or investment activities of a nature that is not generally acceptable in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">

 
 845.219 The applicant has signed a declaration in a form approved by the Minister that the applicant acknowledges the Government's requirements in relation to residence in Australia as the holder of a Subclass 845 visa.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">

 
 845.22 Criteria to be satisfied at time of decision 

 
 845.221 The applicant continues to satisfy the criteria in clauses 845.213 to 845.218.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">

 
 ... 
 Regulation 1.03 defines some presently relevant terms for the purposes of sub-class 845: 
 "ownership interest" has the meaning given to it in subsection 134 (10) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">

 
 "qualifying business" means an enterprise that: 
 (a) is operated for the purpose of making profit through the provision of goods, services or goods and services (other than the provision of rental property) to the public; and 
 (b) is not operated primarily or substantially for the purpose of speculative or passive investment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">
 Also to be noted is reg 1.11, which provides: 
 " Main business " 

 
 (1) For the purposes of these Regulations and subject to subregulation (2), a business is a main business in relation to an applicant for a visa if: 
 (a) the applicant has, or has had, an ownership interest in the business; and 
 (b) the applicant maintains, or has maintained, direct and continuous involvement in management of the business from day to day and in making decisions affecting the overall direction and performance of the business; and 
 (c) the value of the applicant's ownership interest, or the total value of the ownership interests of the applicant and the applicant's spouse, in the business is or was at least 10% of the total value of the business; and 
 (d) the business is a qualifying business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">

 
 (2) If an applicant has, or has had, an ownership interest in more than 1 qualifying business that would, except for this subregulation, be a main business in relation to the applicant, the applicant must not nominate more than 2 of those qualifying businesses as main businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">

Within s 134(10) of the Act "ownership interest" is defined as follows:
 
 "ownership interest" , in relation to a business, means an interest in the business as: 
 (a) a shareholder in a company that carries on the business; or 
 (b) a partner in a partnership that carries on the business; or 
 (c) the sole proprietor of the business; 
 including such an interest held indirectly through one or more interposed companies, partnerships or trusts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">
 First Ground of Appeal
 In the visa application the Appellant nominated two "main businesses", each stated to be conducted by the same company, Golden Net International Pty Ltd (GNI).</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">On the one hand, GNI, when trading as GNI Finance Corporation, was said to carry on a business of finance origination.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">On the other hand, and separately specified on the application form, GNI was said to conduct a business involving the export of meat, offal and coffee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">By the time the Tribunal came to review afresh the refusal decision, the Appellant had caused a company by the name of United Link Corporation Pty Ltd (United) to be registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">The Tribunal found that this occurred on 11 April 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">It seems that United commenced business forthwith upon its registration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Its business concerned computers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That business was promoted before the Tribunal on the rehearing as a "main business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">On the rehearing before the Tribunal, the Appellant's representative advanced a submission that the true position in law was that one business had been nominated by the Appellant at the time when the visa application was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">From this it followed, so it was submitted, that the business nomination limit in para (2) of the definition of "main business" had not been reached at the time the application was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">It followed, it was submitted, that it was possible to nominate and to rely upon United's business as a "main business" for the purposes of meeting the specified visa criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">It was put to the Tribunal that, for the purposes of the Regulations, a legal entity could not operate more than one business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Hence, so the submission went, as GNI Finance Corporation was nothing more than a name under which GNI carried on business, rather than the name of a separate legal entity, there was but one business which could be carried on by GNI.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">The Tribunal rejected this submission stating (reasons para 35): 
 The criteria speak of businesses and just as 2 companies, or separate legal entity, could share a business, one legal entity could have more than one business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">[sic] 
 The Tribunal accepted the position factually propounded by the Appellant in his visa application, ie that GNI operated two discrete businesses, one under the name GNI Finance Corporation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">There was no alternative case advanced for the Appellant before the Tribunal on the rehearing that one or the other of the businesses nominated on the visa application form could not be a "main business" because it was not a "qualifying business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">In the Federal Magistrates Court, the Appellant's contention was that it was not lawfully possible for the Tribunal to have concluded that the meaning of the word "business" in the definition of "main business" was such that, even though several types of enterprise might be discernable in its operations, there could in law only be one "business" carried on by that legal entity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">In disposing of that contention, the learned Federal Magistrate noted that in Nassif v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 481 ; (2003) 129 FCR 448 Branson J, having observed that the word "business" was not defined for the purposes of the Regulations, derived assistance as to its meaning as found in standard dictionaries.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">In that case her Honour concluded that it was not a characteristic of the meaning of the word "business" that a business could only be carried on by one legal entity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">The learned Federal Magistrate considered that the converse of this also followed from the word's ordinary meaning, ie that a single legal entity could also carry on more than one "business" (reasons for judgment, para 41).</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Having reached that conclusion, his Honour then found that it was open to the Tribunal, as a matter of fact, to conclude that GNI operated two businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">It seems from the learned Federal Magistrate's reasons for judgment that, in the course of oral submissions, the Appellant also advanced a case, which was not revealed by the grounds of judicial review that it had specified, that the Tribunal had erred by failing to consider whether each of the "main businesses" was a "qualifying business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">The learned Federal Magistrate noted (reasons for judgment, para 51) that neither party had put before the Tribunal matters relevant to establishing a "qualifying business" which was a subject "taken as said".</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">His Honour then opined (reasons for judgment, para 52), by reference to Saffron v Societe Miniere Cafrika [1958] HCA 50 ; (1958) 100 CLR 231 ( Saffron's Case ), "The matter never having been put in issue before this time cannot now be raised".</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">On the appeal to this Court, the Appellant's submission was that the Tribunal had erred because it did not properly turn its mind to the question of whether the two businesses specified on the visa application form were "qualifying businesses" as defined by reg 1.03 of the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">It was submitted that only by so doing could the Tribunal properly have determined that those businesses were separate "main businesses" for the purposes of reg 1.1(2) of the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">From this it was said to follow that the rejection of United's business as a "main business" was erroneous because it did not violate the regulatory prohibition against the nomination of more than two "main businesses".</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">In turn, the learned Federal Magistrate was said to have fallen into error by failing to hold that the identified alleged error on the part of the Tribunal was jurisdictional.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">The learned Federal Magistrate was also submitted erroneously to have concluded that, because the question of whether the originally specified main businesses were qualifying businesses had not been raised before the Tribunal, it could not be raised as a jurisdictional error ground before the Federal Magistrates Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The Appellant submitted that "the failure of the Tribunal to even turn its mind to the question of whether the main businesses nominated on the visa application form were 'qualifying businesses', was a fundamental failure to understand the task before it".</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">For his part, the Minister submitted that the Tribunal's findings that the two originally nominated businesses were the Appellant's main businesses should be regarded as subsuming a finding by the Tribunal that they were "qualifying businesses".</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">The Minister further submitted that, in the circumstances, the Tribunal was entitled to act upon the Appellant's nomination on his visa application form of two "main businesses".</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">I doubt, with respect, whether the Appellant's "qualifying business" argument, having regard to the pleadings, arises given the way in which the first appeal ground is cast.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">The point was though one fully explored in the Appellant's written and oral submissions and one with which the Minister fully engaged in submissions in response.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The following features of the Appellant's case before the Tribunal on the rehearing bear emphasis by repetition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">His case there proceeded upon the acceptance by the Tribunal of the legal premise that it was not possible for one legal entity (GNI) to carry on two discrete businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">It was never put to the Tribunal that, were this legal premise to be found unmeritorious, one or the other of the nominated businesses could not in any event be a "main business" because it was not a "qualifying business" for the purposes of the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">That was not the subject of any legal or factual controversy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">The Tribunal's reasons display an appreciation (para 12 and para 34) of a need for the nominated main business or businesses each to be a "qualifying business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">There was nothing in the way in which the businesses were described on the visa application form or in other material or submissions before the Tribunal to raise an interrogative note about whether the Appellant's own nomination of the two main businesses on the application form was flawed because one or the other or each were not and could never be "qualifying businesses".</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">In Repatriation Commission v Warren (2008) 167 FCR 511 ( Warren's Case), Lindgren and Bennett JJ (with whom in this regard I agreed) comprehensively summarised the effect of earlier authorities bearing upon the question as to whether an External Merits Review Tribunal commits legal error by not considering an issue even if it is not raised or the subject of challenge by the parties to the review proceeding before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">Their Honours stated (para 78): The following principles, which we take to be established, must be understood against the background that the tribunal under consideration, like the Tribunal here, is required to "review" a primary decision, is given all the powers and discretions that were conferred on the original decision-maker, is not bound by the rules of evidence, is required to proceed with little formality and technicality, and is, of course, bound to apply the provisions of the relevant statute, even if there is no challenge by the parties: The general rule that a litigant is bound by, and accordingly is entitled to act on, admissions and concessions does not automatically apply, although cases concerned with the exercise of judicial power may be of assistance ( Kuswardana at 194 per Bowen CJ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">A party to the proceeding is not necessarily precluded from arguing on "appeal" matters that were conceded before the tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Whether the party is so precluded depends on the nature of the matter conceded, its conduct of its case, whether the concession represented an agreement by the parties as to the facts to be decided and other relevant circumstances ( Kuswardana at 195 per Bowen CJ and at 199 per Fox J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Where a concession is made, there must be some difficulty in finding an "error of law" when the contrary of the concession is raised for the first time in this Court ( Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Raptis (1989) 20 ATR 1262 at 1267 per Gummow J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">A tribunal does not err in law in failing to regard as material a fact which counsel failed in submissions to contend was material ( Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Perkins (1993) 26 ATR 8 at 10 per Davies J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">There is a difference between factual matters not canvassed before the tribunal and a new issue relating to the validity of a regulation ( Tefonu Pty Ltd v Insurance and Superannuation Commissioner [1993] FCA 412 ; (1993) 44 FCR 361 at 367 per Beazley J).</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">Even though the parties may be ' able, in practical terms, to narrow the issues by concession ... even a concession does not permit the [t]ribunal to avoid its duty as an administrative decision-maker to make the correct or preferable decision ... on all relevant aspects of the matter before it ' ( Peacock v Repatriation Commission (2007) 161 FCR 256 at [23]); A concession ' does, however, permit the decision-maker to reach the correct or preferable decision by reference to the concession as well as to its findings on disputed questions ' ( Peacock at[23]; and see Comcare v Fiedler [2001] FCA 1810 ; (2001) 115 FCR 328 at 337 --- 338).</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">The Court will more readily permit a matter to be raised for the first time in this Court on an appeal from a tribunal where: 
(a) the matter is a pure question of law, such as a question as to the validity of a regulation ( Kuswardana at 195; Tefonu at 367) or a question as to whether the tribunal had applied the correct standard of proof on the true construction and application of legislation ( Ferriday at 527---528 per Lee J);
 
(b) the matter goes to a misapprehension that was shared by the parties before the tribunal and therefore by the tribunal itself ( Perpetual Trustee Co (Canberra) Ltd v Commissioner for ACT Revenue [1994] FCA 1150 ; (1994) 50 FCR 405 at 418-419 per Wilcox J) such as a shared misapprehension as to the applicable law (cf Thomas at 120 per Beazley J); or 
 
(c) the matter goes to a condition precedent to the availability of a power, the exercise of which will have a serious impact on the individual ( Kuswardana ) .</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">[Full internal case references and citations omitted]
 Of the propositions summarised in the passage quoted from Warren's case, the present is but an example of a case where a Tribunal has not erred in law by failing to regard as material a fact which the representative of a party before it failed in submissions to contend was material.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">A finding by the Tribunal that each of the businesses nominated on the visa application form by the Appellant as a "main business" was indeed a "main business" necessarily, in the circumstances, carried with it a finding, a "satisfaction", that each business, factually, met the definition of "qualifying business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">The Appellant contended that the reference by the learned Magistrate to Saffron 's Case was inapt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">With respect, I agree.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Unlike the circumstances of Saffron's Case, the proceeding before the Federal Magistrates Court was in no sense an appeal by way of rehearing where a particular point had not been taken in a court below.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Rather, it was a judicial review proceeding in respect of the Tribunal's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">Further, having regarding to s 65 of the Act, it was a judicial review proceeding in respect of an ultimate conclusion by the Tribunal, sitting in place of the ministerial delegate, that it was not "satisfied" that the relevant criteria for the grant of the visa sought were met.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Such "satisfaction" based decisions are not unexaminable on judicial review, as the High Court noted in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 275-276 by reference with approval to remarks on that subject made by Gibbs J (as his Honour then was) in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1975) 135 CLR 110 at 118-119.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">Thus, as highlighted in the summary given in Warren's Case, the fact that a party to a proceeding before a merits review tribunal has not raised a particular issue either of fact or law will not of itself render that administrative decision immune from challenge on judicial review on the basis, for example, that a particular fact which was required by statute to be found was not found.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">If a required jurisdictional fact were not found by an administrative tribunal it would be nothing to the point that the tribunal had not been asked to find it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">It is just that in this case the Tribunal has, at the necessary level of factual detail in the circumstances, been satisfied that there were two "main businesses" originally nominated.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">It was not required, in circumstances where the parties conducted their cases on the basis that it was a given, separately to consider the subsidiary question as to whether, as a matter of fact, those "main businesses" were "qualifying".</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">The Appellant accepted that identification of this particular error on the part of the learned Federal Magistrate did not mean that the first ground of appeal must necessarily succeed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">The Appellant also advanced the argument that the Tribunal's conclusion that, at the time of the application, GNI operated, as nominated, two "main businesses", was erroneous, because those businesses "are in fact the same business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">There was no error in the way in which the learned Federal Magistrate approached the meaning of the word "business" and its reach.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">As did Branson J in Nassif (at 454-455), I gain assistance as to the meaning the word from standard dictionaries.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">The word undoubtedly has chameleon like qualities, taking its meaning from the context in which it is used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">In both the Oxford and the Macquarie Dictionaries the meaning of the word "business", when used in a commercial sense, is "enterprise".</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">That is the sense in which it is used in the terms "main business" and "qualifying business" in the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">That this is so is reinforced by its being treated, in the definition of "qualifying business", as a synonym for "enterprise".</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">So construed, there is nothing about the meaning of the word "business" as used in the context of the Regulations which carries with it the necessary corollary that a legal entity can only ever, on its true meaning, have or conduct but one "business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">Such a construction of the word "business" accords with common experience.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">It is by no means unusual for a legal entity to cease one particular field of commercial endeavour by the disposal of what is aptly termed a "business" without ceasing altogether to trade.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">Given this meaning of the word, whether or not GNI had one or two "main businesses" was nothing more than a question of fact and one for the Tribunal alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The learned Federal Magistrate well appreciated this (reasons for judgement, para 44).</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">It is certainly not one this Court on subsequent appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">However approached, ground 1 of the appeal must fail.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">Second Appeal Ground
 The second ground of appeal was premised upon its being permissible for the Tribunal to have considered United's business as a second "main business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">The dismissal of the first ground of appeal and the business nomination limit found in the definition of "main business" in reg 1.11 have the necessary consequence that there was no error in the Tribunal's concluding that it was not able to consider United's business for the purposes of deciding whether it was satisfied that the Appellant met the visa criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">This consequence was accepted by the parties and, in the court below, by the learned Federal Magistrate (reasons for judgement, para 54).</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">The point was though fully argued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">I conceive that it is appropriate to address it in the event that the conclusion which I have reached in respect of the first appeal ground is in error.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">The learned Federal Magistrate dealt with the point on a similar basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">The central point raised is, what is the true meaning and effect of the words "continues to" as they appear thus in cl 845.221: "the applicant continues to satisfy the criteria in clauses 845.213 to 845.218"?</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">On the assumption that it was not otherwise precluded by considering United's business to be a "main business", and having referred to cl 845.213, cl 845,216, cl 845.221, and the definition of "main business", the Tribunal observed: 
 [T]he definition of main business must be met by the business the applicant has an ownership interest or is the owner of an interest, both at the time of the application and at the time of this decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">For these reasons the Tribunal finds that United is not a main business as it does not meet the definition of main business as the visa applicant did not have an ownership interest in United for at least 18 months immediately preceding the making of the visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">Therefore the applicant does not have an ownership interest in one or more established main businesses , at the time of this decision, and the Tribunal finds accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">Further, the visa applicant is not involved in the management of a business or makes decisions affecting that business as the owner of an interest in a main business or main businesses in Australia, at the time of this decision, and the Tribunal finds accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">[Italics and emphasis in original] 
 In the Federal Magistrates Court attention centred upon whether the words "continues to" ought to be afforded the meaning given to those same words in another clause of Sch 2 to the Regulations by Allsop J (as his Honour then was) in Rao v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1755 ( Rao's Case)or that which commended itself to a Full Court in Xiang v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 81 ALD 301 ( Xiang's Case) in respect of like words in yet another clause in Sch 2 to the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">In the result, the learned Federal Magistrate considered that contextual similarities as between the words as used in cl 845 and as used in the provisions considered in Rao's Case favoured following the construction of "continues to" adopted in that case rather than, as the Appellant had submitted, that given to those same words by the Full Court in Xiang's Case Put succinctly, the differing positions are these.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">The Appellant's submission, said to be supported by Xiang's Case, was that there was nothing in the language of either cl 845.213 or cl 845.221 which required that, in the interval between date of application and date of decision, a visa applicant have an interest in a particular business or indeed any business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">The Appellant noted in submissions, as is the case, that the learned Federal Magistrate had made reference to the word "continuous" in his reasons for judgement (para 67 and para 81) in a context which suggested a belief by him that this word appeared in cl 845,221, which is not the case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">This error, it was submitted, may have influenced his Honour's interpretative preference.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">It was further part of the Appellant's submission that the words "of that kind" in cl 845.213 (b) indicated that the "main business" at the time of decision need not be one and the same as that at the time of application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">The Minister's submission, said to be supported by Rao's Case, was that a visa applicant had to maintain a direct and continuous involvement in the main business (or businesses) nominated at the time of application and throughout the interval up to and including the date of decision; Xiang's Case was said to be distinguishable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">The following passage from Xiang's Case, which was cited by the learned Federal Magistrate, sets out the views of the Full Court with respect to the meaning of the words "continues to", as well as that earlier voiced by Allsop J in Rao's Case: 
 [8] The tribunal also fell into error in the meaning it placed on the word "continues" in subcl 806.221 of the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">According to the tribunal it means that a visa applicant must do more than establish that he or she is a special need relative at the time of application and at the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">It also requires the applicant to satisfy this definition throughout the entire intervening period, or at least for a substantial part of that period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">According to the tribunal "[t]o hold otherwise would deny any use or purpose to the inclusion of the word 'continues' in the regulations".</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">Although not the subject of complaint, it should be noted that the tribunal said that unless an applicant was a special need relative during the period between the time of the application and the time of decision, the applicant would not satisfy subcl 806.213 of the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">Even if the tribunal were correct in its construction (which it is not, for reasons soon to be explained), it was wrong to hold that this would result in a failure to satisfy subcl 806.213.</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">It could only lead the tribunal to the conclusion that the visa applicant had failed to satisfy subcl 806.221, namely the criteria at the time of decision, and not that she had failed to do so at the time of the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">

 
 [9] Returning to the meaning of the word "continues" in subcl 806.221, that meaning cannot be considered in isolation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">Its meaning must be gathered from the context.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">The context is that a visa applicant must be a "special need relative" both at the time of application, and at the time of decision, to satisfy that criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">It will be remembered that a special need relative is defined as a relative who is willing and able to provide the requisite assistance to an Australian or New Zealand citizen or resident.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">The first point to note is that the word to be construed is the verb "continues" and not the adjective "continuing".</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">Second, it is plain that the word "continues" is not concerned with any activity on the part of the visa applicant, but rather with the applicant's status; a status which has a temporal condition.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">

 
 [10] Finally, the question whether the applicant meets the criteria at the time of application and at the time of decision is determined at the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">Relevantly, the question is whether the applicant was (at the time of application) and still is (at the time of decision) a "special need relative".</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">That is to say, the applicant "continues" that status if the applicant still is a "special need relative" at a particular time; that time being when the decision is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">Possibly the draftsman assumed that a person who was a "special need relative" at the time of the application and continues to satisfy that condition on the day of decision would be a "special need relative" throughout the intervening period.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">But, whatever may be the assumption, there is no legal requirement that this be so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">This conclusion is probably inconsistent with the decision in Rao v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1755.There on a slightly differently worded regulation Allsop J decided that the word "continues" was not intended to limit the enquiry whether the visa applicant in that case had satisfied the relevant criteria at the time of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">On the other hand, the judgment in that case may be supported because the word "continues" was used in a different context.</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">This issue need not be resolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">
 The relevant visa class considered in Xiang's Case is evident from the passage quoted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">The "slightly differently worded regulation" considered by Allsop J in Rao's Case was that part of the Regulations which governed eligibility for the Student (Temporary) (Class TU Subclass 560) visa sought by the visa applicant in that case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">One condition to which that applicant's existing visa was subject was condition 8105, which prescribed that the holder must not engage in work in Australia (other than in relation to her course of study or training) for more than 20 hours per week during any week when the institution at which the holder was studying was in session.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">Within Subclass 560, cl 560.21 set out the criteria to be satisfied at the time of application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">Subclause 560.22 set out the criteria to be satisfied at the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">Subclause 560.213 provided: 
 If the application is made in Australia, the applicant has complied substantially with the conditions to which the visa (if any) held, or last held, by the applicant is, or was, subject.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">

In turn, cl 560.227 provided:
 
 If the application is made in Australia, the applicant continues to satisfy the criterion in cl560.213.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">[Emphasis added] 

There was a finding of fact at tribunal level in Rao's Case that, in the interval between date of application and date of decision, the visa applicant had consistently breached the working hours limitation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">The learned Federal Magistrate was keenly aware of the authority of a decision of a Full Court of this Court, if in point, as the following passage reveals.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">I cite it not only to highlight this but also because it evidences a correct understanding by his Honour of the language actually employed in cl 845.221 and the essence of why his Honour preferred the meaning given to the words "continues to" in Rao's Case: 
 [75] It follows that for the decision in Xiang to be binding the context in which the word "continues" is used has to be materially similar to the context in that case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">In my view for reasons which follow the context in which the word "continues" appears in clause 845.221 is not similar to the context to which the word appeared in clause 806.221.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">

Though His Honour's use of the word "continuous" both before and after this passage was unfortunate, this passage is pivotal in his reasons for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">Noting this, and reading the reasons as a whole, I am not persuaded that the erroneous references to "continuous" were material to his Honour's interpretative conclusion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">What was material was the learned Federal Magistrate's apprehension that it had been recognised in Xiang's Case that the meaning to give to the word "continues" may depend on whether it was used in relation to a status or an activity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">It was because his Honour considered that it was used in the latter context that he concluded that, in this regard, there had been no error made by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">The requirement for a duality of satisfaction by a visa applicant of particular criteria at both the time of application and the time of decision is not unique to cl 845, nor even to those considered in Xiang's Case and Rao's Case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">It is a feature which permeates the Regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">It is a further permeating feature that the verb "continues" is employed so as to require satisfaction on the part of the administrative decision maker at the time of decision that a visa applicant "continues to" satisfy nominated criteria which were first required to be satisfied at the time of application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">Against this background, it is highly unlikely, in my opinion, that it was intended by the Governor-General-in-Council when making and amending the Regulations that the meaning, as opposed to the effect in context, of "continues to" would vary throughout those regulations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">Though, pursuant to s 25(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), I am presently exercising the appellate jurisdiction of the Court, I consider that I am bound by any decision given in the appellate jurisdiction by a Full Court of this Court which is in point: NAKG of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 1600 at [48] per Jacobson J; S ZBPQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 568 at [5] per Hely J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">Xiang's Case is in point to the extent that the Full Court has counselled that "continues" is a word the effect of which depends on the context in which it is used.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">It must not, as the Full Court stated in the passage quoted above, be read in isolation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">The Full Court noted usages of the word in respect of both an activity and a status.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">As it happened, it was in the latter context that it was used in Xiang's Case to the end that there it did not carry with it any requirement that the status be held in the interval between application date and decision date by the visa applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">In Rao's Case, as the Full Court noted, the word "continues" was used in a different context.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">In those parts of the Regulations considered in Xiang's Case and in Rao's Case, as well as in the present case, "continues" is used as a transitive verb.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">So used, the sense of the word is "to carry on, keep up, maintain, go on with, persist in (an action, usage, etc.) (Oxford Dictionary, 2 nd Ed, 1989) or "to go forwards or onwards in any course or action; keep on" (Macquarie Dictionary, Online Edition).</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">When used for the purposes of cl 845.221 in conjunction with "a status which has a temporal condition", it requires nothing more than that that status is possessed at the time when the assessment falls to be made, relevantly, at the time when the administrative decision in respect of the visa application is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">If a visa criterion contains a temporal limitation in relation to possession of a particular status at the time of application, a visa applicant who then has that status and who also has that status at the time when the decision in respect of that application is made, necessarily "continues" to have that status.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">Furthermore, the visa applicant will "continue" to have that status at the time of decision irrespective of whatever his or her status may be in the period which elapses after the date of application and before the date of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">On the other hand, in respect of an activity based criterion carrying with it no temporal limitation, satisfaction at the time of decision that the visa applicant "continues to" meet that criterion will necessarily require scrutiny of whether that activity was maintained in the interval.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">The point may illustrated by reference to the operation of cl 845.221 with respect to the "continues to satisfy" criteria referred to in that clause.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">The criterion in cl 845.212 is status based and also temporally focussed by reference to the time of application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">If that criterion is met at the time of application, it will "continue" to be met at the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">I shall pass over cl 845.213 for the moment because it requires more detailed analysis in light of the circumstances of this case and the submissions made on the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Subclauses 845.214 and 845.215 are status based by reference to assets and, in part, temporarily limited by reference to the period ending immediately before the application is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">Insofar as they are not temporally limited in that way, asking whether the visa applicant "continues to" meet them involves in any event no inquiry as to the position obtaining during the period which has elapsed since the time of application, only what is the position at the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">Subclause 845.216 entails a status ("as the owner of an interest") but a status possessed while engaging in activity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">However, there is a temporal limitation in respect of that activity, "In the 12 months immediately preceding the making of the application".</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">In light of that limitation, if there is satisfaction that the visa applicant met this criterion at the time of the application, there must necessarily at the time of decision be satisfaction that the applicant "continues to satisfy" this criterion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">Subclauses 845.217 and 845.218 are different.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">Each of them is activity focussed; "overall had a successful business career" and "has a history of involvement".</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">Deciding whether a visa applicant "continues to satisfy" these criteria will necessarily involve examining what that applicant has been doing in whatever interval has elapsed between the time of application and the time of decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">The conclusion one reaches as to the position which obtained at the time of application in respect of these criteria may differ from that reached at the time of decision because of what has occurred in the interval.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">I apprehend that each of these conclusions as to the meaning and effect of "continues to" is consistent with the Full Court's observations in Xiang's Case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">These are Delphic qualities attending ascertaining the effect of cl 845.221 in relation to continued satisfaction of cl 845.213, even with the benefit of the guidance offered in Xiang's Case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">As a matter of first impression, cl 845.213 appears to be status based in the sense that it looks to the possession of an "ownership interest" in a "main business" or businesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">Subclause 845.213(a) carries a temporal limitation which looks to the 18 months immediately preceding the application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">There is though a further and cumulative temporal limitation itself utilising the transitive verb "continues" found in cl 845.213(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">The evident concern of the further temporal limitation in cl 845.213(b) is that the "ownership interest" in one or more "main businesses" over the period of 18 months immediately preceding the application must be maintained, "continue", throughout whatever period elapses thereafter until the application is made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">In other words, the intention, reflected in the language of cl 845.213(b), is that there should be no gap in the holding of an "ownership interest".</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">Further, the continued interest must be one "of that kind".</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">In context, the reference in cl 845.213(b) to "of that kind" is, in my opinion, to be read as a reference to the "main business" or businesses referred to in cl 845.213(a).</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">The use of "kind" in drafting might in other contexts admit of a more generic coverage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">The embrace of the word has given rise in other contexts to sharp divisions of judicial opinion, see, for example, Bird v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 23 ; (1988) 165 CLR 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">Here though, "kind" is governed not by an indefinite but by a very specific definite article, "that".</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">It is also necessary to recall that "main business" is itself a defined term.</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">One feature of that definition, to which I have already referred, is a limit on the number of businesses which may be nominated as a "main business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">To give "of that kind" an open ended, generic construction so as to embrace yet another business, albeit one akin to that or those nominated, would be to subvert: 
(a) The limitation found in the definition of "main business"; and
 
(b) The very managerial particular involvement, found in para (1)(b) of the definition, required for a business to be a "main business".</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">There is no obvious reason for such subversion in respect of this particular visa subclass.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">On the other hand, construing "of that kind" as a reference to the "main business" or businesses referred to in cl 845.213(a) sits comfortably with a subclass the intent of which seems to be to provide a basis for the granting of a visa to those (and to the family of those) who have made a significant and continuing investment in and managerial involvement with at least one and not more than two nominated main businesses in Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">Another feature of para (1)(b) of the definition of "main business" in reg 1.11 of the Regulations is that it is activity related.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">Furthermore, the language employed in respect of the activity is "maintains or has maintained continuous involvement".</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">Necessarily, the determining of whether at the time of decision the requirements of this paragraph are met requires an assessment of an activity over a continuum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">What has the visa applicant been doing in relation to the "main business" or businesses since the date of application?</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">Further, the requirements specified in the paragraphs of the definition are cumulative.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">Even though the other criteria in the definition of "main business" in reg 1.11 of the Regulations are status based with the consequence in respect of satisfaction as at date of decision described in Liang's Case, the criterion in para 1(b) is not.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">To satisfy that criterion as at the date of decision, the visa applicant must do more than just be engaging in that activity at that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">It follows that, because not all paragraphs in the definition of "main business" in reg 1.11 of the Regulations are activity related, I am not in complete agreement with the learned Federal Magistrate's observation in respect of so much of the Tribunal proceeding that related to United (reasons for judgment, para 84) that, "the issue was not the visa applicant's status but rather his activity".</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">However that may be, the learned Federal Magistrate upheld (reasons for judgment, para 85), as not attended by legal error, the Tribunal's conclusion (reasons, para 34) that the Appellant did not have an interest in a main business at the time of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">Having regard to the activity related aspect of "main business" and when United was established, this conclusion flowed inevitably from what I regard as the correct meaning and application of cl 845.221, read with cl 845.213.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">Further, and again as found by the Tribunal (ibid) the Appellant did not have (and could never have had) an ownership interest in United in the 18 months preceding the date of the visa application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">Thus, were it necessary to decide the appeal by reference to ground 2, I should dismiss it, albeit for reasons which differ somewhat from those of the learned Federal Magistrate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">It is difficult in the circumstances not to feel some sympathy for the Appellant with the outcome.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">In the period of time that it ultimately took to decide his application, business events were not static.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">Had the application been decided when each of GNI's businesses was operating, the fate of the application may well have been different.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">Equally though, as the process elongated it was a matter for the Appellant as to whether or not GNI continued to operate the two nominated "main businesses".</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">If it did not, then the provisions of the Regulations governing this subclass were unforgiving.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">For these reasons the appeal must be dismissed, with costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">I certify that the preceding sixty-one (61) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 3 March 2009
 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr M Steele 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: Sciacca's Lawyers &amp; Consultants 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Ms A Wheatley 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Clayton Utz 
 Date of Hearing: 9 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 March 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/189.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>