<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Trade Commission v Isaac Jewellery Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 37 (3 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/37.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal limited to questions of law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">jurisdictional fact</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether tribunal erred in its application of the export market development grants (change in ownership of business) guidelines 2006 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether tribunal erred in its consideration of s 94(1)(b)(i) of the export markets development grants act 1997 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">administrative law</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">administrative law</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 The appellant ('Austrade') appeals from the decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ('the Tribunal') pursuant to s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) ('the AAT Act').</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The Tribunal had determined that the respondent ('Isaac Jewellery') was not a business to which s 94(1)(b) of the Export Markets Development Grants Act 1997 (Cth) ('the EMDG Act') applied and was therefore entitled to receive grants pursuant to the EMDG Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The EMDG Act provides for the grant of assistance to small and medium Australian enterprises to assist them in developing export markets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Pursuant to s 7 of such Act a business is not eligible for a grant if it has been a grantee in respect of eight or more previous grant years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Part 8 Division 2 of the EMDG Act applies where there is a change in the ownership of the business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">To ensure that grants under the EMDG Act might continue to be payable to a grantee, s 93(2) of the EMDG Act provides: 
 To achieve this, this Division requires the CEO of Austrade to treat certain particulars of the previous owner of the business as being those of the new owner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">
 Section 94 of the EMDG Act provides: 
 Change in ownership of business etc. 
 (1) Subsection (2) applies if: 
 (a) at any time, a person (the previous owner ) carried on a particular business (the old business ) in Australia; and 
 (b) at a later time, another person (the new owner) carries on: 
 (i) the business or a part of the business (the relevant part ); or 
 (ii) a business (the new business ) that, at that time, is similar to the old business, or a part of the old business (the relevant part ), carried on by the previous owner before that time, to such an extent that the CEO of Austrade is satisfied that the new business should be treated as a continuation of the old business; and 
 (c) the new owner applies for a grant in respect of a grant year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Note: Decisions whether 2 businesses are similar are subject to guidelines determined by the Minister under section 101.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">(2) For the purposes of this Act, the CEO of Austrade must treat particulars of the previous owner as being those of the applicant in the following ways: 
 (a) any eligible expenses incurred by the previous owner in the capacity of owner of the business (or of the relevant part) are to be treated as having been incurred by the new owner; 
 (b) if the CEO had decided that the previous owner met the grants entry requirements --- the new owner is to be treated as if the CEO had decided that it had met the grants entry requirements; 
 (c) any grant, or advance on account of grant, paid or payable (whether under this Act or under the repealed Act) to the previous owner in the capacity of owner of the business (or of the relevant part) is to be treated as having been paid, or as being payable, to the new owner; 
 (d) any other aspect of the business (or of the relevant part) is to be treated as if it had been carried on by the new owner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Note: For eligible expenses , repealed Act and grants entry requirements see section 107.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">
 FACTS 
 ABJ Australia Pty Limited ('ABJ') conducted a business as a designer, manufacturer and wholesaler of jewellery in Sydney for approximately 25 years.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Its directors were Mr Isaac Atakliyan ('Mr Atakliyan') and his brother Aram.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The business exported substantial quantities of manufactured jewellery and received grants under the EMDG Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">In 2004 following a disagreement each brother formed new companies and commenced separate businesses both engaged in the manufacture of jewellery.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The equipment and the stock used in the business of ABJ were divided between the two brothers.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">In July 2005 Isaac Jewellery Pty Ltd ('Isaac Jewellery') was incorporated and Mr Atakliyan became its sole director and share holder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">In around September 2005 Mr Atakliyan purchased a property in Market Street, Sydney and conducted the operations of Isaac Jewellery from that premises.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">The purchase price was partly met using a portion of the proceeds of the sale from the property which had been formerly owned by himself and Aram, and had been used by ABJ for the conduct of its business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">On 6 July 2007 Isaac Jewellery lodged an application form with Austrade for a grant under the EMDG Act in respect of claimed expenditure incurred during 2006/2007 in the amount of $120,114.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Section 101(1)(d) of the EDMG Act empowers the Minister for Trade ('the Minister') to determine, by legislative instrument, 'guidelines to be complied with by the CEO in determining, for the purposes of subparagraph 94(1)(b)(ii), whether a business or part of a business (the old business ) that was carried on by a person is similar to a business (the new business ) being carried on by another person to such an extent that the new business should be treated as a continuation of the old business' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">The Export Market Development Grants (Change in Ownership of Business) Guidelines 2006 (Cth) ('the Guidelines') in respect of s 94 were made by the Minister on 19 July 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Section 4(2) of the Guidelines specifies eleven criteria which must be considered by Austrade in determining whether the new business is similar to the old business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Austrade, having applied the criteria, rejected the application for a grant by Notice of Determination of Grant dated 27 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Austrade considered Isaac Jewellery to be a continuation of the business previously conducted by ABJ.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Since ABJ had exhausted its entitlement to grants, Isaac Jewellery's application for a further grant was refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Isaac Jewellery thereafter sought a review by Austrade of the decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">The review was duly held but it concluded that Isaac Jewellery was ineligible upon the following grounds: 
 Section 94 of the EMDG Act applies if a person is carrying on a business (new business) which is similar to one carried on previously by another person (old business) and the two businesses are similar to such an extent that Austrade is satisfied that the new business should be treated as a continuation of the old business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">We note that in your case the old business, ABJ Australia Pty Ltd, has been the recipient of the maximum entitlement of seven grants up until the 2003-04 grant year.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Austrade has carefully examined and taken into account the criteria set out in the Ministerial Guideline EMDG (Change of Ownership Guideline) 2006 in deciding whether Isaac Jewellery P/L should be treated as a continuation of the old business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">Accordingly, Austrade has concluded that there are too many similarities NOT to warrant the application of Section 94 and that Isaac Jewellery P/L therefore be treated, for EMDG purposes, as continuing the old business thus inheriting the grant history of ABJ Australia P/L.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">As ABJ Australia P/L has received 7 prior grants, I regret to advise that Isaac Jewellery P/L are [sic] no longer eligible for a grant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">
 Isaac Jewellery sought judicial review of Austrade's review decision before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The Senior Member, in determining the review in favour of Isaac Jewellery said: 
 I have identified the two questions that I must consider as whether Isaac Jewellery carries on:
 (a) the business, or part of the business, carried on by ABJ : section 94(1)(b)(i); or
 (b) a business similar to the business, or part of the business, carried on by ABJ, to such an extent that the new business should be treated as a continuation of the old business: section 94(1)(b)(ii);
 The questions are most conveniently addressed together.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">In applying section 94, I, as the decision-maker standing in Austrade's shoes, am required to take into account the Export Market Development Grants (Change in Ownership of Business) Guidelines 2006 (the "Guidelines"): s 101(1)(d).</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">
 Having taken into account the criteria specified in the Guidelines, the Senior Member concluded: 
 I have therefore come to the view, having regard to the factors identified in the Guidelines, that Isaac Jewellery is [sic] neither carries on the same business, or part of the same business, carried on by ABJ, nor does it carry on a business similar to the business, or part of the business, carried on by ABJ to such an extent that the new business should be treated as a continuation of the old business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">
 QUESTIONS OF LAW 
 Austrade submits that the Tribunal made two errors of law in reaching its decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Firstly, Austrade submits that the Tribunal misconstrued and misapplied s 94(1)(b) of the EMDG Act by conflating the matters to be considered under ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Secondly Austrade submits that the Tribunal erred in applying the Guidelines to s 94(1)(b)(i) of the EMDG Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">The Guidelines only apply to s 94(1)(b)(ii) of the EMDG Act and require the decision-maker to have regard to the similarities (if any) and the differences (if any) between the eleven aspects of the old and new businesses specified in the Guidelines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Austrade submits that those similarities and differences are irrelevant to any consideration arising under s 94(1)(b)(i) of the EMDG Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Austrade submits that by such errors, the Tribunal misdirected itself concerning the relevance of the Guidelines as evidenced by the Tribunal's finding that 'having regard to the factors identified in the Guidelines... Isaac Jewellery... neither carries on the same business or part of the same business, carried on by ABJ...' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Such reason was the only basis which the Tribunal gave for its decision under s 94(1)(b) and Austrade submits that the Tribunal accordingly failed to correctly apply s 94(1)(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">SUBMISSIONS OF ISAAC JEWELLERY 
 Isaac Jewellery submits that s 94(1) of the EMDG Act constitutes a precondition to the operation of s 94(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">The facts which must be proved to the satisfaction of the decision-maker or which must be proved objectively in s 94(1) are jurisdictional facts which must exist before the operation of s 94(2) is enlivened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">It is submitted that the determination under s 94(1) does not turn on the satisfaction of the CEO of Austrade or, on review, of the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">Accordingly, the criteria for the application of s 94(1)(b)(i) can be determined conclusively only by a court of competent jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">Isaac Jewellery submits that no question of law is involved in the appeal and accordingly the appeal is incompetent under s 44 of the AAT Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">Isaac Jewellery also submits that Austrade did not contend that any of the matters advanced by Isaac Jewellery under s 94(1)(b)(i) of the EMDG Act were irrelevant to the consideration of the matters in that subparagraph and refutes the submission of Austrade that the Tribunal conflated its task by considering ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii) together.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">NATURE OF APPEAL 
 In Comcare v Etheridge and Others [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522 at 527 the Full Court considered the nature of an appeal under s 44(1) of the AAT Act and determined that an appeal 'on a question of law' is narrower than an appeal 'that merely involves a question of law' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The Court at 527 referred to the observations in Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2003] FCAFC 232 ; (2003) 38 AAR 55 which expressed approval of the observation of Ryan J in Australian Telecommunications Corporation v Lambroglou (1990) 12 AAR 515 at 527 where his Honour said: 
 If the question, properly analysed, is not a question of law no amount of formulary like "erred in law" or "was open as a matter of law" can make it into a question of law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">
 Order 53 rule 3(2)(b) of the Federal Court Rules (Cth) requires a notice of appeal to state the question or questions of law to be raised on the appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">The question of law raised by Austrade's Notice of Appeal requires the Court to determine whether the provisions of the EMDG Act have been properly applied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The question asked in Austrade's notice of appeal is stated as follows: 
 Whether the Tribunal misconstrued and misapplied section 94(1)(b)(i) of the Act when it determined whether Isaac Jewellery Pty Ltd fell within that provision by having regard to the Guidelines that apply to a d [sic] subsection of the Act, namely section 94(1)(b)(ii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">
 The Court concludes that, since no factual questions are involved in such determination, the question as submitted is one solely of law 'directing the Court's attention to the manner in which the Tribunal failed to discharge its obligations according to law...' : see Collins v Administrative Appeals Tribunal and Another [2007] FCAFC 111 ; (2007) 163 FCR 35 at [55] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">JURISDICTIONAL FACT 
 In Corporation of the City of Enfield v Development Assessment Commission and Another [2000] HCA 5 ; (1999) 199 CLR 135 at [28] the High Court of Australia observed: 
 The term "jurisdictional fact" (which may be a complex of elements) is often used to identify that criterion, satisfaction of which enlivens the power of the decision-maker to exercise a discretion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">
 In Gedeon v Commissioner of New South Wales Crime Commission [2008] HCA 43 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 1465 at [43] the High Court said: 
 The expression "jurisdictional fact" was used somewhat loosely in the course of submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Generally the expression is used to identify a criterion the satisfaction of which enlivens the exercise of the statutory power or discretion in question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">If the criterion be not satisfied then the decision purportedly made in exercise of the power or discretion will have been made without the necessary statutory authority required of the decision maker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">
 Section 94(1) of the EMDG Act provides that the provisions of subsection (2) thereof apply if the requirements specified in ss 94(1)(a) and 94(1)(b) are satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The fulfilment of the requirements in s 94(1)(b)(ii) is conditional upon the satisfaction of the CEO of Austrade, and such satisfaction is to be determined by the application of the Guidelines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">Once a determination has been made that the requirements are met, s 94(2) then directs Austrade to treat the particulars of the previous owner as being those of the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Such determination requires a judgment to be made by the CEO of Austrade.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">As was observed in Australian Postal Corporation v Forgie and Another [2003] FCAFC 223 ; (2003) 130 FCR 279 at [40] of a decision making process: ' [t] his intellectual process involves matters of judgment and degree' .</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">That is, a decision is required.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">In the application of both s 94(1)(b)(i) and (ii) a value judgment must be made by the decision-maker.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Under s 94(1)(b)(i) a decision is required to be made in respect of the question whether the new owner is carrying on the old business or a part thereof.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">It follows that there has been a decision made by Austrade in respect of which an appeal may lie to this Court pursuant to s 44 of the AAT Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Accordingly, the Court rejects the submission that the requirements of s 94(1) constitute jurisdictional facts, and that s 94(1)(b)(i) is capable of determination by objective facts.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">DID THE TRIBUNAL ERR?</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">
 The statement by the Tribunal that the questions arising under ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii) 'are most conveniently addressed together' could mean that the decision-maker was saying no more than it was expedient to consider the facts giving rise to Isaac Jewellery's application for a grant when considering both subparagraphs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">So construed, the Tribunal's decision would be unremarkable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">However, the challenged statement is also consistent with another interpretation, namely that the issues arising under both subparagraphs were to be determined against the same criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Such a construction would be erroneous since the issues to be determined under each subparagraph require the application of different criteria.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">The Court infers from the next statement of the Tribunal, namely ' [i] n applying s 94, I, as the decision-maker... am required to take into account the Export Market Development Grants (Change in Ownership of Business) Guidelines 2006' , that the Tribunal approached the interpretation of ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii) as if the Guidelines applied to both subparagraphs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">By virtue of s 101(1)(d) of the EMDG Act the Guidelines are applicable to s 94(1)(b)(ii) but not to s 94(1)(b)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">Such construction is reinforced when the Tribunal's findings are considered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Although the issues to be considered under ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii) are distinct, the Tribunal did not attempt to consider the requirements of the two subsections separately.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">The Tribunal, in stating that 'I have therefore come to the view, having regard to the factors identified in the Guidelines, that Isaac Jewellery is [sic] neither carries on the same business, or part of the same business, carried on by ABJ...' , indicated that it considered that the Guidelines were relevant in determining the question under s 94(1)(b)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">Further, the Court considers that the Tribunal should not have considered s 94(1)(b)(i) of the EMDG Act in its review of Austrade's decision.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">The test under s 94(1)(b)(i) requires a factual consideration of whether the new owner is carrying on the business or part of the business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">This does not require an investigation of the similarities between the old business and the new business, as subparagraph (i) does not anticipate a new business being in existence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">The only question to be considered under such subparagraph is whether the business, previously conducted by its former owner, is being conducted by the new owner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Since there is no issue that the old business, namely ABJ, had ceased to operate, the Tribunal had no reason to consider s 94(1)(b)(i).</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">The issue for determination was whether the new business was similar to the old business as provided for in s 94(1)(b)(ii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">This distinction appears to have been overlooked by the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">The Court therefore concludes that the Tribunal misconstrued and misapplied s 94 of the EMDG Act by failing to perceive that the circumstances to which s 94(1)(b)(i) applied were not relevant to the review before the Tribunal, and further by considering that the Guidelines applied to both ss 94(1)(b)(i) and 94(1)(b)(ii).</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Isaac Jewellery referred to the fact that Austrade had not drawn such distinctions before the Tribunal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">However, the conduct of Austrade before the Tribunal cannot operate as a constraint upon the consequences which flow from a misinterpretation of s 94 of the EMDG Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The appeal is allowed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I certify that the preceding thirty-six (36) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Cowdroy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 3 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellant: Ms Henderson 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: Collins House 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr Lloyd SC with Mr Reynolds 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Pearl Chew Legal 
 Date of Hearing: 12 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 February 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/37.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>