<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rose v Sakkara Properties Pty Limited [2009] FCA 304 (1 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/304.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">unconscionable conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">inequality of bargaining power</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">position of special disadvantage or disability</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">whether deeds entered into as a result of duress and improper pressure</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">whether any failure to permit redemption of mortgages</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">whether any conduct amounted to unconscionable conduct or duress and improper pressure</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">whether contracts unjust in the circumstances relating to their execution</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">contracts review act 1980 (nsw)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">misleading and deceptive conduct</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether false representation</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">trade practices act 1974 (cth) part v</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">trade practices</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">contracts</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">trade practices</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 INTRODUCTION 
 This proceeding involves two separate claims, although much of the factual background is common to both claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The principal claim involves both the first applicant, Mr Christopher Rose, as well as the second applicant, Riva Properties Pty Limited ( Riva ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The second claim involves only Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">Riva is controlled by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The principal claim concerns four agreements entered into on 18 December 2006 (together the Impugned Agreements ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The parties to the Impugned Agreements were Mr Rose and Riva, on the one hand, and the respondents, Sakkara Properties Pty Limited ( Sakkara Properties ), RMB Australia Holdings Limited ( RMB ) and Sakkara Capital Investments Pty Limited ( Sakkara Capital ), on the other.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">It is convenient to refer to the three respondents together as the Lenders .</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Mr Rose and Riva claim that they have rescinded the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">Alternatively, they claim declarations that the Impugned Agreements are void, orders that the Impugned Agreements be set aside and cancelled or orders refusing to enforce the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Mr Rose and Riva claim that the Impugned Agreements were entered into as a consequence of duress and improper pressure alleged to have been brought to bear on Mr Rose by the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Alternatively, they claim that the Impugned Agreements were entered into as a result of unconscionable conduct on the part of the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">Mr Rose also asserts that two of the Impugned Agreements, being guarantees executed by him, were unjust in the circumstances relating to their execution, within the Contracts Review Act 1980 (NSW) ( Contracts Review Act ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The conduct complained of by Mr Rose and Riva is that the Lenders wrongfully refused to permit redemption of mortgages given to the Lenders by Moruben Properties Pty Limited ( Moruben ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Moruben is also controlled by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">In addition, Mr Rose and Riva claim that the Lenders wrongfully threatened to appoint administrators to Riva, Moruben and other companies controlled by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The two Impugned Agreements that are guarantees by Mr Rose relate to obligations owed by Riva to Sakkara Properties and to RMB and Sakkara Capital respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Riva has failed to meet those obligations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Accordingly, by cross-claim, the Lenders claim judgment against Mr Rose under the guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Mr Rose accepts that, if he and Riva fail to obtain the relief claimed in the proceeding, he has no answer to the cross-claim by the Lenders in respect of his obligations under the guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Under the guarantees, Mr Rose covenanted that he would not further encumber any property of his until the obligations guaranteed by him are satisfied.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">I shall refer below to the precise terms of the covenants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">The Lenders say that Mr Rose has, notwithstanding that covenant, further encumbered property owned by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">Accordingly, as I understand the position, Mr Rose also accepts that, if he and Riva fail to obtain the relief claimed in the proceeding, injunctions should be granted restraining Mr Rose from further encumbering his property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">Mr Rose accepts that, unless restrained, he does not regard himself as bound by the covenants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">In the second claim, Riva asserts that it suffered loss by misleading and deceptive conduct that it alleges was engaged in by the Lenders in connection with the sale by Riva to Chevron Lifestyle Properties Pty Ltd ( Chevron Lifestyle ) of apartments in a property at Chevron Island, Queensland ( the Chevron Island Property ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">The apartments were constructed by Riva with the assistance of finance provided by the Lenders on the security of mortgages of the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">Riva says that the Lenders represented to it that they were agreeable, or would be agreeable, to Riva's selling unsold apartments in the Chevron Island Property in one line to Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Riva says that, because the Lenders were not agreeable to such a sale, the alleged representations were misleading or deceptive in contravention of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ( Trade Practices Act ) and that Riva suffered loss by reason of having to pay the sum of $102,500 to Chevron Lifestyle as consideration for the rescission of the contract for sale that Riva entered into with Chevron Lifestyle in reliance upon the alleged representations.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">I shall first say something about the parties and various financing arrangements entered into by the Lenders with companies controlled by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">I shall then say something about the witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">After that, I shall deal with the circumstances of Riva's contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">Finally, I shall deal with the circumstances that led up to the execution of the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">The Parties and the Financing Arrangements
 In his evidence in chief, Mr Rose described himself as a property developer, although to the extent that he engaged in such an activity, he did so through a series of limited liability companies controlled by him, each separate property development being undertaken by a different company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">One of the issues turns on that distinction, having regard to the provisions of the Contracts Review Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">Under s 6(2) of the Contracts Review Act , a person may not be granted relief in relation to a contract so far as the contract was entered into in the course of, or for the purpose of, a trade, business or profession carried on by the person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">The Lenders say that the Impugned Agreements were entered into by Mr Rose in the course of the business carried on by him as a property developer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">In addition to Riva and Moruben, Mr Rose also controlled the following companies: Quadwest Developments Pty Ltd ( Quadwest ); Quadrant Properties Pty Ltd ( Quadrant Properties ); Quadrant Property Services Pty Ltd ( Quadrant Services ); Quadrant Projects Pty Ltd ( Quadrant Projects ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">
The companies controlled by Mr Rose are conveniently referred to as the Quadrant Group .</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Each of the Lenders is a financier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Sakkara Properties and Sakkara Capital are related to each other and are part of the Sakkara Group .</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">RMB is an Australian subsidiary of an international financier.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">Various finance facilities were entered into between the members of the Quadrant Group on the one hand, and one or more of the Lenders, on the other.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">Sakkara Capital managed RMB's involvement in the various facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Different facilities were entered into in relation to each development of the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">In some instances, the facilities were cross-collateralised , in that one development was sometimes provided as security for facilities granted in connection with a different development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">It is desirable to say something about the facilities relating to each development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">The Riva Facilities
 In February 2004, Riva acquired the Chevron Island Property for the purposes of constructing 21 residential apartments and the subsequent sale of the apartments.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">On 16 February 2004, Riva entered into a facility agreement with Sakkara Properties ( the Riva Equity Agreement ) for the provision of finance up to a total of $2 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">The obligations of Riva under the Riva Equity Agreement were secured by a registered mortgage of the Chevron Island Property and a fixed and floating charge over the whole of the assets of Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Advances were made to Riva by Sakkara Properties pursuant to the Riva Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">On 23 December 2004, Riva entered into a loan agreement with Sakkara Capital and RMB for the provision of a further facility of $2 million for the purposes of refinancing ( the Riva Mezzanine Agreement ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">An advance was made pursuant to the Riva Mezzanine Agreement, part of which was applied in repayment of advances made under the Riva Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The obligations of Riva under the Riva Mezzanine Agreement were also secured by a registered mortgage of the Chevron Island Property and a fixed and floating charge over the whole of Riva's assets.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">On 23 December 2004 Quadrant Properties executed a Guarantee and Indemnity in favour of Sakkara Capital and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">The Guarantee and Indemnity is curious in so far as it fails to identify Sakkara Capital and RMB by name.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">However, it is common ground that the Guarantee and Indemnity executed by Quadrant Properties on 23 December 2004 was given in favour of Sakkara Capital and RMB in respect of the obligations of Riva under the Riva Mezzanine Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">On 8 June 2006, Mr Rose executed a mortgage ( the Milsons Point Mortgage ) over his home in Milsons Point (the Milsons Point Property ) in favour of Sakkara Capital and RMB to secure the payment of all amounts payable by Mr Rose or by Quadrant Properties to Sakkara Capital and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">In the Milsons Point Mortgage, Mr Rose also personally covenanted to pay the amount secured by the Milsons Point Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Thus, Mr Rose was personally liable, without limit, for the obligations of Riva under the Riva Mezzanine Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">The Moruben Facilities
 In or before June 2004, Moruben was granted an option to acquire land in Moruben Road, Balmoral, NSW (the Moruben Road Property ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">On 16 June 2004, in connection with the proposed development and resale of the Moruben Road Property, Moruben entered into a development facility agreement with Sakkara Properties ( the Moruben Equity Agreement ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">The limit of the Moruben Equity Agreement was $300,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">By clause 6.1 of the Moruben Equity Agreement, Moruben acknowledged and agreed that, in addition to the payment of all other money payable to Sakkara Properties, Moruben must pay to Sakkara Properties an amount calculated as 10% of the Net Project Profit of the Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">Project was defined as the acquisition of the Moruben Road Property, obtaining all approvals necessary to carry out the design and construction of six luxury apartments, managing and carrying out all work necessary to construct the development, marketing and selling the apartments and any other incidental works and matters required for completion of the development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">Net Project Profit was defined as the amount agreed by Sakkara Properties and Moruben in good faith to be the profit derived in relation to the Moruben Road Property calculated by reference to the difference between Revenue for the Project less Project Costs, as detailed in the Feasibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Revenue was defined as the proceeds of sales of the Moruben Road Property, plus any other revenue received by Moruben for the Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">The term Project Costs was defined as the cost to Moruben and the Project of acquisition costs, construction costs, financing costs, selling costs and such other costs incurred on the Project as the parties may agree.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Feasibility was defined as the detailed Project feasibility annexed to the Moruben Equity Agreement, as varied with the written consent of Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Net Project Profit was to be determined only after there had been paid from sale of the Project all amounts owing to any senior lender, any mezzanine debt provider and all amounts owing to Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">Under clause 6.6(a) of the Moruben Equity Agreement, Moruben was required to make available to Sakkara Properties all records, vouchers, receipts, accounts and plans relating to the Project, its purchase and sale, to enable Sakkara Properties to assess the Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Further, under clause 6.6(b) Moruben agreed that it would not sell, assign or otherwise dispose of the Project unless it ensured that any sale, assignment or disposal was for a fair and proper consideration and otherwise on terms appropriate to an arms length commercial transaction and was on terms acceptable to Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">Such terms could include arrangements to ensure that Sakkara Properties will achieve an economic return on its debt as contemplated by the Moruben Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Finally, by clause 6.6(c), Moruben acknowledged that the 10% of Net Project Profit to be paid to Sakkara Properties represented additional interest payable to Sakkara Properties in consideration of the facilities granted to Moruben and that a proper financial return to Sakkara Properties was calculated by adding the 10% of Net Project Profit to all other money payable to Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">However, under clause 6.4 of the Moruben Equity Agreement, Sakkara Properties was to receive a minimum Internal Rate of Return of 40% prior to any distribution to Moruben of Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">Internal Rate of Return was defined as the rate of interest determined by Sakkara Properties (expressed as a percentage) at which all future payments under the facility made available under the Moruben Equity Agreement must be discounted in order that the net present value of those cash flows should be equal to zero.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">By clause 8 of the Moruben Equity Agreement, Mr Rose guaranteed to Sakkara Properties that Moruben would promptly and diligently comply with all of its obligations under the Moruben Equity Agreement relating to the physical delivery and management of the Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">However, nothing in clause 8 was to impose upon Mr Rose any liability to Sakkara Properties for the repayment of any debt of Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Thus, the parties expressly excluded any liability on the part of Mr Rose for money obligations of Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">The effect of clause 3(d) of the Moruben Equity Agreement was that Moruben could only make a drawing under the Moruben Equity Agreement if Sakkara Properties held the Security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">Security was defined as being: 
(a) a charge over Moruben's option to buy the Moruben Road Property and any contract entered into pursuant to that option, and a fixed and floating charge over the whole of Moruben's assets and undertaking; and
 
(b) after completion of the purchase of the Moruben Road Property, a second mortgage over the Moruben Road Property and a deed of priority between Moruben, Sakkara Properties, and any senior lender consented to by Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">There was some doubt about whether such a second mortgage was ever granted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">No second mortgage was in evidence and, at one stage during the hearing, Mr Rose and Riva suggested that no mortgage had in fact been given, notwithstanding an allegation in the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim that Moruben had granted an equitable mortgage over the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Ultimately, that suggestion was abandoned and the proceeding was conducted on the basis that it was common ground that at least an equitable mortgage of the Moruben Road Property was given to Sakkara Properties to secure Moruben's obligations under the Moruben Equity Agreement ( the Moruben Equity Mortgage ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">The existence of the Moruben Equity Mortgage is of critical importance as will appear below.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">On 28 March 2006, Sakkara Properties wrote to Moruben in relation to the Moruben Equity Agreement, the term of which had expired on 15 December 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Sakkara Properties notified Moruben that the term had been extended until 31 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">Mr Rose accepted the extension on behalf of Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">On 15 April 2005, Moruben entered into a loan agreement with Sakkara Capital and RMB ( the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement ) for the provision of advances up to $1,700,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Moruben's obligations under the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement were to be secured by a registered mortgage over the Moruben Road Property, as well as fixed and floating charges over all of the assets of Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">By mortgage dated 15 April 2005 ( the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage ), which was registered in due course, Moruben mortgaged the Moruben Road Property to Sakkara Capital and RMB to secure the punctual payment of the Secured Money.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">Secured Money was defined as all amounts that are payable, owing but not payable or that otherwise remain unpaid, by Moruben to RMB and Sakkara Capital on any account at any time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">Clause 15 of the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage provided that: when RMB and Sakkara Capital were satisfied that all the Secured Money had been irrevocably paid and discharged in full or satisfied and no amount remained contingently payable, or may become payable, on the security of the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage; and on payment or retention of all expenses incurred by or payable to RMB and Sakkara Capital, 
RMB and Sakkara Capital must, at the request and cost of Moruben, reconvey, surrender or release to Moruben any remaining part of the Moruben Road Property, which would then be discharged from the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">By fixed and floating charge given by Moruben on 15 April 2005, Moruben charged all its assets to Sakkara Capital and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">That charge contains an express power for Sakkara Capital and RMB to appoint a receiver or receivers of any of the charged property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Under s 436C of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Corporations Act ), a chargee, such as RMB and Sakkara Capital were in relation to Moruben, has power to appoint an administrator of a company granting such a charge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">The significance of that will become apparent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Also on 15 April 2005, a deed of priority was executed by Sakkara Capital and RMB, Moruben and BOS International (Australia) Limited ( BOS ), in connection with the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement ( the BOS Priority Deed ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">By the BOS Priority Deed, the mortgage and charges given to BOS as security for advances made by it to Moruben were given priority over the mortgage and charges given to Sakkara Capital and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">Clause 4.1 of the BOS Priority Deed relevantly provided to the following effect: 
(a) Subject to (c) below, BOS may exercise any power, under or in respect of its first ranking registered mortgage over the Moruben Road Property without first notifying RMB and Sakkara Capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">(b) RMB and Sakkara Capital may not exercise any power under or in respect of their second ranking registered mortgage over the Moruben Road Property or their second ranking fixed and floating charge over the assets of Moruben without the consent of BOS unless BOS has been fully and finally paid all amounts advanced by BOS to Moruben in connection with the development of the Moruben Road Property and BOS is satisfied that any such payment is not able to be avoided for any reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">(c) BOS will give to RMB and Sakkara Capital fourteen days notice before realising any property that is subject to a security interest under those securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">(d) RMB and Sakkara Capital may exercise a power under or in respect of their second ranking registered mortgage and their second ranking fixed and floating charge without the prior written consent of BOS if, and to the extent that, BOS's first ranking registered mortgage and the second ranking securities in favour of RMB and Sakkara Capital do not create or evidence a security interest over the same property of Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">A similar deed of priority had been entered into with Bank of Western Australia Limited in relation to the Riva Mezzanine Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The term "power" was defined, both in the BOS Priority Deed and in the priority deed with Bank of Western Australia Limited, as including any power, right, discretion and remedy of a chargee or receiver, as applicable, whether under the Priority Deed, under the security or under any law.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Thus, the term power, when used in clause 4.1 would include the right to appoint a receiver or administrator to Moruben or Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">That is of significance in relation to the alleged threat by the Lenders about which Riva and Mr Rose complain.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">The Quadwest Facility
 In November 2005, Quadwest acquired land in Adelaide Terrace, Perth WA (the Adelaide Terrace Property ) for the purposes of development into apartments and resale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">The funds used for the purchase of the Adelaide Terrace Property were provided by Sakkara Properties pursuant to a loan agreement dated 15 March 2005 ( the Quadwest Loan Agreement ).</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">Riva and Moruben were also parties to the Quadwest Loan Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">The obligations of Quadwest under the Quadwest Loan Agreement were secured by a mortgage over the Adelaide Terrace Property and charges by Quadwest in favour of Sakkara Properties and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">In addition, Quadwest's obligations were secured by a registered mortgage over the Moruben Road Property and a registered mortgage over the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">There was thus cross-collateralisation of the Chevron Island Property and the Moruben Road Property in relation to the Adelaide Terrace Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">Default under the Financing Facilities with the Lenders
 As at November and December 2006, the critical times in relation to the principal claim made by Riva and Mr Rose, the various facilities described above were either overdue or in default.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">The Riva Equity Agreement had expired on 16 February 2006, although it had been extended to 31 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">The Riva Mezzanine Agreement had expired on 30 September 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">The Moruben Equity Agreement had expired on 15 December 2005, although it had been extended to 31 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">The Moruben Mezzanine Agreement expired on 15 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">The Quadwest Loan Agreement had expired on 30 September 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">Thus, the Riva Mezzanine Agreement, the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement and the Quadwest Loan Agreement were in default according to their terms.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">In addition, notwithstanding the extension of the Riva Equity Agreement and the Moruben Equity Agreement to 31 December 2006, they were in default by reason of cross default provisions linking them to the Riva Mezzanine Agreement and the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">The Witnesses
 Mr Rose gave evidence orally and was extensively cross examined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">In addition, oral evidence was given by Mr Neil Wilson, the managing director of the Sakkara Group and Mr Gordon Bevan, the former chief operating officer of the Sakkara Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">Both were extensively cross-examined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">Mr Stephen Camilleri was an officer of the Sakkara Group at relevant times.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">Mr Camilleri played an important role on behalf of the Sakkara Group in relation to the Quadwest Group, but was not called to give evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">Mr Rose
 In the witness box, Mr Rose initially presented as a plausible witness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s126">However, his evidence was shown to be quite unreliable on several occasions, such that I would not be prepared to accept his oral evidence where in conflict with the evidence of the other witnesses.</sentence>
<sentence id="s127">I shall recount several such instances of Mr Rose's unreliability.</sentence>
<sentence id="s128">One of the complaints by Riva and Mr Rose in the proceeding is that, in an alleged conversation with Mr Bevan on 8 December 2006, Mr Bevan threatened that Sakkara Capital and RMB would move to appoint an administrator to all companies in the Quadrant Group to which they had exposure, including Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s129">A file note purporting to record that threat was tendered on behalf of Mr Rose and Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s130">The file note, which bears the date 8 December 2006, purports to record a telephone call between Mr Rose and Mr Bevan " at approximately 11 am " on 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s131">In his evidence in chief, Mr Rose said that he had a practice in relation to meetings that he attended, which entailed his sitting down and typing a file note on a computer, within one to two days after the meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s132">He said that it was sometimes shorter than one to two days and sometimes it was immediately after the meeting, but certainly no later than a couple of days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s133">When giving his evidence in chief, Mr Rose was asked about the file note bearing the date 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s134">He said that it was prepared in accordance with that usual practice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s135">When asked about the file note in cross-examination, Mr Rose said that it was typed a few days later than 8 December 2006 but that he could not recall the exact date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s136">When it was put to him that it was a lot more than a few days, Mr Rose persisted in saying that he could not recall the exact date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s137">When it was specifically put to him that it was not prepared until some time in late 2007, his response again was that he could not recall when it was done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s138">Ultimately, however, Mr Rose accepted that the file note was created in October 2007 and modified in November 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s139">Specifically, he accepted that he did not create the file note until well after this proceeding had been commenced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s140">He accepted that, until challenged with those facts, he had been prepared to put the file note forward as a contemporaneous record of what Mr Bevan had said to him on 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s141">He also accepted that he intended that the Court should believe that it had been brought into existence shortly after the discussion to which it referred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s142">It is also significant that, when giving oral evidence concerning the alleged threat to appoint an administrator, purportedly recorded in the spurious file note, Mr Rose, on three occasions, referred to a threat to appoint a receiver .</sentence>
<sentence id="s143">He has never complained about a threat to appoint a receiver, although it is possible that Mr Bevan may have adverted to that possibility, something to which I shall return later.</sentence>
<sentence id="s144">The reference to the threat to appoint an administrator was an integral part of the initial complaint made by Mr Rose and Riva in the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s145">The inconsistency in referring to appointment of a receiver and appointment of an administrator, when coupled with the spurious file note, is highly damaging to Mr Rose's credibility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s146">Another matter relevant to the assessment of Mr Rose's credibility arises out of evidence he gave concerning the Milsons Point Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s147">In the course of his evidence in chief, Mr Rose was asked about his state of mind when he accepted a proposal from the Lenders contained in a letter of 8 December 2006, pursuant to which the Impugned Agreements were executed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s148">He answered that there were a number of concerns and pressures that he had.</sentence>
<sentence id="s149">One was that the facilities granted to Riva and Moruben by senior lenders (BOS and Bank of Western Australia Limited), which he had personally guaranteed, were to expire at the end of 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s150">He said that he was also acutely aware of the financial position in which he would find himself, if he were unable to access any funds from the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s151">He ended by saying that he was also concerned about losing his own home, given that Sakkara Capital [and RMB] also had a mortgage over that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s152">Clearly, he was then referring to the Milson's Point Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s153">In cross-examination, Mr Rose accepted that he understood that he had given a mortgage over his home to secure the obligations of Quadrant Properties and that he understood that Quadrant Properties had given a guarantee of the obligations owed by Riva to Sakkara Capital and RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s154">However, when it was put to him that the reason he was concerned about losing his home was that he knew that he was personally " on the line for all of Riva's liabilities ", he said that that was not the reason.</sentence>
<sentence id="s155">It was put to him that he had said, in his evidence in chief, that he was concerned about losing his home because he understood the way in which the securities were interlocked.</sentence>
<sentence id="s156">Mr Rose's response was that he was concerned about " the threat that Gordon Bevan gave saying that they would appoint receivers [sic]".</sentence>
<sentence id="s157">In later cross-examination, Mr Rose would not agree that, prior to 8 December 2006, he was personally liable, by reason of the covenants in the Milson's Point Mortgage, for the obligations owed by Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s158">He would not accept that that was why he said he was concerned about losing his own home.</sentence>
<sentence id="s159">Later still in cross-examination, Mr Rose said that he was concerned that, if an administrator were appointed to all the companies in the Quadrant Group, then one of the assets that would be seized would be his own home.</sentence>
<sentence id="s160">He said that he believed that, if Gordon Bevan's threat to appoint a receiver [sic] to all the companies were carried out, then his home would be captured by that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s161">In re-examination, when asked what his understanding was as to how, if a receiver or administrator were appointed to all of his companies, that would capture his home, Mr Rose said that he had personally guaranteed senior debt facilities and he knew that an event of default was the appointment of an administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s162">However, that response appears to be a complete non sequiter .</sentence>
<sentence id="s163">It was not suggested that there was a mortgage over the Milson's Point Property in favour of the senior lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s164">There is no basis for concluding that the appointment of receivers or administrators would result in the Milson's Point Mortgage being enforced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s165">Mr Rose's evidence in relation to the matter was wholly unconvincing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s166">Where there is any conflict between Mr Rose, on the one hand, and Mr Bevan or Mr Wilson on the other, I prefer the evidence of the latter two over that of Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s167">That conclusion underlies the factual findings that I make below concerning the alleged misleading and deceptive conduct in relation to the sale of the Chevron Island Property to Chevron Lifestyle and also the communications that led to the execution of the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s168">Mr Wilson
 Mr Wilson is the managing director of the Sakkara Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s169">Mr Wilson and Mr Rose worked together for a developer for a number of years from the late 1980s or early 1990s, through to the mid 1990s.</sentence>
<sentence id="s170">They were close working colleagues and were friends as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s171">They each left the employment of that developer, at different times, and went their separate ways.</sentence>
<sentence id="s172">Mr Wilson and Mr Rose subsequently met by chance, as a result of which Mr Rose commenced dealing with the Sakkara Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s173">I consider that Mr Wilson made an honest and fair attempt to give accurate evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s174">He presented in the witness box as a credible and honest witness and I consider that his evidence is on the whole reliable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s175">Mr Bevan
 Mr Bevan is a solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s176">He commenced practice as a solicitor in 1974.</sentence>
<sentence id="s177">His practice, until the middle of 2005, was concerned with banking, finance and property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s178">Mr Bevan had a practice of maintaining a day book in which he made notes of conferences and attendances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s179">He did not maintain a separate book for separate matters, but made a separate note in the day book as each attendance or conference occurred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s180">The notes do not purport to record everything that occurred, or even everything that might have been regarded as important.</sentence>
<sentence id="s181">Rather, Mr Bevan regarded his notes as a prompt for himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s182">In the middle of 2005, Mr Bevan became a director of the Sakkara Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s183">Mr Bevan continued the practice of maintaining a day book while working with Sakkara Group during 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s184">My assessment of Mr Bevan is that he is an honest and credible witness, who was making a genuine effort to recall relevant circumstances as best he could.</sentence>
<sentence id="s185">That is not to say that his recollection was perfect but, on the whole, I regard his evidence as reliable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s186">RIVA'S AGREEMENT WITH CHEVRON LIFESTYLE 
 Riva's allegations concerning the Chevron Island Property in the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim may be summarised as follows: The Lenders deny that the representations were made as alleged but accept that, if the representations alleged were made, they were false.</sentence>
<sentence id="s187">However, the Lenders say that, even if representations were made, Riva has failed to establish that it has suffered any loss as a consequence of having entered into the contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s188">In particular, they rely on the fact that Riva has made no attempt to show whether, after the contract with Chevron Lifestyle was rescinded, it subsequently sold the units in the Chevron Island Property that were the subject of that contract and, if so, the amount of the proceeds of sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s189">More specifically, there is no evidence to indicate whether the amount of any such proceeds was greater or less than the price at which Riva had agreed to sell the units to Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s190">Further, the only evidence of the value of the units suggests that their combined value was significantly greater than the prices payable by Chevron Lifestyle, such that an inference can be drawn that Riva was better off as a consequence of the rescission of the contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s191">In the circumstances, I would not be persuaded, on the balance of probabilities, that, even if there had been misleading and deceptive conduct on the part of the Lenders that induced Riva to enter into the contract with Chevron Lifestyle, Riva suffered any loss or damage as a consequence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s192">In any event, for the reasons I shall now explain, I am not persuaded that there was any conduct on the part of the Lenders that was misleading or deceptive in relation to the sale of the units to Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s193">Where one party alleges that the conduct of another was misleading or deceptive, it is incumbent upon the first party to establish, on the balance of probabilities, precisely what the conduct was that is alleged to be misleading.</sentence>
<sentence id="s194">In addition, the precise circumstances that rendered the conduct misleading must be established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s195">Where the conduct is the making of oral representations, the words spoken must be proved with a degree of precision that enables the Court to be satisfied, on the balance of probabilities, that the words spoken were misleading in the circumstances established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s196">The question of whether spoken words were misleading may, although not necessarily, depend upon what may have been relatively subtle nuances flowing from the use of a particular word, phrase or grammatical construction or the presence or absence of some qualifying word or phrase or condition (see, for example, Watson v Foxman (1995) 49 NSWLR 315 at 318-319).</sentence>
<sentence id="s197">There is no contemporaneous documentary evidence of the representations alleged by Mr Rose to have been made by Mr Wilson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s198">The sole evidence of the alleged representations is oral evidence given by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s199">To the extent that that evidence is inconsistent with Mr Bevan's evidence, I reject it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s200">I consider that the evidence of the conversation given by Mr Wilson indicates what happened.</sentence>
<sentence id="s201">Accordingly, I shall recount only that version.</sentence>
<sentence id="s202">Mr Wilson accepted that he had a conversation with Mr Rose in March 2006 concerning the sale of the unsold units in the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s203">Mr Rose broached the subject by saying that, in his opinion, the Gold Coast market was deteriorating and that he felt an inline sale would be beneficial to the Chevron Island Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s204">He said that he had a potential inline buyer that would see the " mezzanine deck " portion of the project receive a full return of principal and interest; however, the equity portion of the loan would only receive the principal plus an 8% return, which would leave a 2% shortfall, and there would be no profit share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s205">Mr Wilson responded by saying that Mr Rose had not managed the Chevron Island Project as well as he had managed previous projects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s206">Mr Wilson told Mr Rose that he had " dropped the ball on this one ", that he had been focussed on the Adelaide Terrace Project, as well as other things, and that, as a consequence, the Chevron Island Project had suffered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s207">Mr Wilson also told Mr Rose that, nevertheless, he agreed that the Gold Coast market looked like it was going to deteriorate and that he would generally be supportive of a transaction that realised full principal and interest under the Riva Mezzanine Agreement and an 8% return under the Riva Equity Agreement with no profit share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s208">However, Mr Wilson told Mr Rose that that was a discussion he would need to have with his colleagues and with the Investment Committee of RMB, because he could not make decisions on his own.</sentence>
<sentence id="s209">Mr Rose nodded and said " OK ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s210">In cross-examination, Mr Rose acknowledged that he knew, from his previous dealings with Mr Wilson, that there would always be a formal process in relation to anything that they agreed, although he said that he was accustomed to accept Mr Wilson's word and that if something was agreed between them, it would be done in the way that they had agreed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s211">He gave no specific examples.</sentence>
<sentence id="s212">Riva relies on a subsequent communication that it says corroborates Mr Rose's evidence that representations were made as alleged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s213">On 10 October 2006, Mr John Batiste, head of lending for the Sakkara Group, wrote to Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s214">After referring to the contract with Chevron Lifestyle, Mr Batiste said as follows: 
 As discussed at the abovementioned meeting [on 5 October 2006] the Lenders at no time agreed to [Riva] entering into the [contract with Chevron Lifestyle].</sentence>
<sentence id="s215">The Lenders have reservations that the Lenders will be repaid the indebtedness by [Riva] should the contract be completed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s216">In the circumstances, the Lenders reiterate that the Lenders do not agree to the completion of the contract without [Riva] demonstrating to the Lender's [sic] satisfaction the capacity of [Riva] to repay the indebtedness of [Riva] to the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s217">In the absence of such evidence, the Lenders reserve their rights under the terms of their security documentation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s218">

 On 17 October 2006, Mr Rose sent a facsimile communication to Mr Batiste, in response to the letter of 10 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s219">After referring to the contract with Chevron Lifestyle, Mr Rose went on to say: 
 As part of my own personal endeavours to market the project prior to practical completion, I met with Neil Wilson in early March 2006 (prior to exchanging contract with [Chevron Lifestyle]) to advise him of Riva's intention to sell to [Chevron Lifestyle] the remaining apartments at a discounted price.</sentence>
<sentence id="s220">During this discussion I explained to Neil that the price was the best "arms length sale" we could negotiate without third party assistance and that the sale would be insufficient to generate a development profit and could result in a reduction in the rate of return that Riva could pay to RMB/Sakkara.</sentence>
<sentence id="s221">Neil acknowledged this and encouraged me to get the best price possible from [Chevron Lifestyle] rather than to get to completion and have almost 50% of the building unsold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s222">

 
 In our attempt to mitigate loss and reliant upon the consent from Neil Wilson, we exchanged 9 contracts of sale with [Chevron Lifestyle] on the 10 th of May 2006 for a combined sale price of $4.6 million.</sentence>
<sentence id="s223">We advised you of this on the 5 th June 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s224">[Emphasis added] 

 There was no specific response to Mr Rose's facsimile of 17 October 2006 by Mr Batiste or anyone else on behalf of the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s225">However, Mr Wilson told Mr Batiste that the assertion in the facsimile was incorrect.</sentence>
<sentence id="s226">Even so, the facsimile does not refer to a representation by Mr Wilson that the Lenders were agreeable to a sale, the terms of which had not even been settled at that stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s227">If anything, the facsimile is inconsistent with a representation such as is alleged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s228">To encourage Mr Rose to get the best price possible is not a representation that the Lenders would be agreeable to a sale at an unspecified price.</sentence>
<sentence id="s229">It is inherently unlikely that Mr Wilson would make a statement intended to bind, not only Sakkara Properties and Sakkara Capital, but also RMB, without obtaining express authority to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s230">The discussion in March 2006 took place in a coffee shop.</sentence>
<sentence id="s231">That is to say, it was attended with a degree of informality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s232">I accept the version of the conversation given by Mr Wilson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s233">I do not consider that that discussion involved the making of any representation by Mr Wilson that the Lenders were agreeable to, or would be agreeable to, a sale of units in the Chevron Island Project in one line, such as is alleged by Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s234">I do not consider that the statements that Mr Wilson made to Mr Rose on that occasion were, in the circumstances, misleading or deceptive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s235">It may be that Mr Rose was encouraged by the response that he received from Mr Wilson to pursue negotiations for the sale of the unsold units in one line.</sentence>
<sentence id="s236">Be that as it may, that is a different matter altogether from a representation that the Lenders were agreeable or would be agreeable to a sale of the remaining units on terms that were not specified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s237">As I have said, the language of the facsimile of 17 October 2006 is inconsistent with such a representation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s238">I do not consider that Riva has established that any of the Lenders engaged in any misleading or deceptive conduct in connection with the sale of units in the Chevron Island Property to Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s239">This claim must be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s240">EXECUTION OF THE IMPUGNED AGREEMENTS 
 Mr Rose and Riva rely on three separate causes of action in relation to the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s241">All depend upon the same factual matrix.</sentence>
<sentence id="s242">They assert that there were two aspects of duress or unfair pressure brought to bear on them by the Lenders, which, they say, give rise to the three causes of action on which they rely.</sentence>
<sentence id="s243">The first is that the Lenders threatened to appoint administrators to the companies of the Quadrant Group, in circumstances where it was unlawful for them to do so, because of the provisions of the BOS Priority Deed and the priority deed with the Bank of Western Australia Limited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s244">The second is that the Lenders refused, or at least threatened to refuse, to permit Moruben to redeem the Moruben Equity Mortgage and the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage, in circumstances where Moruben had evinced its willingness and ability to redeem by payment of all money secured by those two mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s245">It is convenient to deal with each of those aspects separately.</sentence>
<sentence id="s246">Threat To Appoint Administrators
 In the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim, Mr Rose and Riva make the following allegations concerning the threat to appoint administrators: Mr Rose gave evidence of the alleged threat of 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s247">He relied upon his spurious file note of that date as corroborating his evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s248">For the reasons given above, I do not accept Mr Rose's evidence when it is inconsistent with that of Mr Bevan or Mr Wilson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s249">For the reasons given above, I reject the spurious file note as having no weight whatsoever.</sentence>
<sentence id="s250">Indeed, the circumstances surrounding the creation of the file note firmly suggest that no threat such as is alleged was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s251">However, Mr Rose and Riva also pointed to internal memoranda of the Lenders that, they say, tend to support the allegation of a threat by Mr Bevan to appoint administrators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s252">I consider that the documents, if anything, confirm that no threat was made on 8 December 2006 as alleged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s253">On 13 November 2006, Mr Camilleri sent an email to Mr Bevan in connection with the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s254">In the email, Mr Camilleri pointed out to Mr Bevan the prohibition on RMB and Sakkara Capital from exercising any power under its securities without the prior written consent of BOS.</sentence>
<sentence id="s255">In the course of cross-examination, Mr Bevan agreed that it was unlikely that such consent would be given and that he did not ask for it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s256">Mr Bevan accepted that, while it was not highly unusual for a senior lender to consent to a subordinate lender appointing a receiver, it was rare.</sentence>
<sentence id="s257">In an email of 4 December 2006, from Mr Bevan to Messrs Camilleri and Wilson, Mr Bevan referred to Mr Camilleri's confirmation that they could not " move on the Riva security without the consent of the senior lender ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s258">In response, Mr Wilson said that they needed to have an investment committee meeting on the question of the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s259">At some time on 4 December 2006, Mr Bevan made a note in his day book concerning strategy in relation to Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s260">His note was as follows: 
 Threaten to appoint a receiver/manager to: 

 
 Riva Properties Pty Limited
 Quadrant Properties Pty Limited
 - to approach Bank of Western Australia to obtain consent to act based upon Riva Properties being in default by reason of:
 &#183; expired Facility;
 &#183; changed circumstances; 
 - need the consent of Bank of Western Australia to act under our security --- limitation as contained in the Deed of Priority with Bank of Western Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s261">

 
I have added the emphasis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s262">It is significant that the note refers to the appointment of a receiver/manager and not to the appointment of an administrator .</sentence>
<sentence id="s263">Later on 4 December 2006, Mr Bevan sent another email to Mr Camilleri, with a copy to Mr Wilson, saying, relevantly, as follows: 
 I suggest that we be in a position to put to the IC meeting scheduled for 5:00 pm today a proposal which, in the absence of Chris Rose changing his position to satisfy concerns on the Riva Project, that we: 

 
 (1) take steps to appoint a Receiver to Riva Properties Pty Ltd, Qaudrant [sic] Properties Pty Ltd; 

 
 (2) threaten to take steps to appoint a Receiver to Quadrant Properties Services Pty Ltd / Quadrant Projects Pty Ltd (before we can appoint a Receiver we need to establish an indebtedness by these 2 companies it may just be a matter of timing dependent upon the ability of Chris Rose to pay out the Mezzanine debt and profit share on Moruben Road and Quadwest).</sentence>
<sentence id="s264">

 
 As discussed, we cannot act upon our security without the consent of the senior lender (limitation in the Deed of Priority).</sentence>
<sentence id="s265">That extends to the appointment of a receiver .</sentence>
<sentence id="s266">In this regard, I believe that you have identified that Ross Harding at BOSI is the contact person.</sentence>
<sentence id="s267">Given the possible consequences to Quadrant/Riva I suggest we await the result and direction of the IC meeting before contact is made with him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s268">We need to formally request consent to act on our security and you and I will need to draft that request.</sentence>
<sentence id="s269">It may be that the threat of the appointment of the receivers will be enough to bring Chris Rose back to the table.</sentence>
<sentence id="s270">

 
I have added the emphasis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s271">No mention was made of an administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s272">The proposed meeting of the Investment Committee was in fact held on 4 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s273">The conclusion reached by the Investment Committee was recorded in an email from Mr Camilleri to Mr Bevan and Mr Wilson and others early on 5 December 2006, relevantly saying: 
 With reference to yesterday's IC meeting regarding the Quadrant exposure, it was agreed that the following actions are to occur: 

 
 &#183; Gordon Bevan is to advise Chris Rose that unless cross collateralisation of securities and personal guarantee is forthcoming in respect of the Riva loan facility, RMB/Sakkara will move to appoint a Receiver to Riva and other companies in the group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s274">&#183; Chris Rose will be granted until midday today (5/12/06) to advise his position regarding the stance taken by RMB/Sakkara in this matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s275">&#183; Should Chris refuse to grant cross collateralisation and personal guarantee, contact is to be made with [the relevant officer] at BOSI to advise of RMB/Sakkara intention to appoint a Receiver and seek BOSI consent as required under the terms of the priority deed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s276">

 
 For information, the existing BOSI senior debt facility for the Riva on Chevron Project expires on 30/12/2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s277">

 
 Again, I have added the emphasis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s278">No mention was made of an administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s279">More significantly, the need for the consent of BOS was specifically noted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s280">
 Mr Bevan acknowledged that he was aware that there was an express power to appoint a receiver in the deed of charge in favour of RMB and Sakkara Capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s281">He was also aware that there is a provision in the Corporations Act that entitles a chargee to appoint an administrator to the assets charged by a company.</sentence>
<sentence id="s282">He also knew that, while Sakkara Capital and RMB had an entitlement to appoint a receiver, he could not act on that entitlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s283">He said that his strategy involved approaching the senior lenders to obtain consent to act.</sentence>
<sentence id="s284">In his evidence in chief, Mr Bevan said that, on 5 December 2006, he had at least two conversations with Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s285">In one of those conversations, Mr Rose asked him what would be proposed if agreement could not be reached on the provision of further securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s286">Mr Bevan responded that RMB and Sakkara Capital would look to their securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s287">Mr Rose asked what that would mean and Mr Bevan said that they would take steps to appoint a receiver .</sentence>
<sentence id="s288">There was no discussion about the identity of the companies to which the receiver would be appointed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s289">I accept that evidence.</sentence>
<sentence id="s290">It is significant that Mr Bevan referred to appointment of a receiver and not an administrator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s291">Further, the conversation was three days before the threat alleged by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s292">Mr Rose and Riva make no complaint about any such conversation on 5 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s293">In cross-examination, Mr Bevan agreed that Mr Camilleri's email of 5 December 2006 accurately recorded what was decided at the meeting of the Investment Committee held on 4 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s294">While he acknowledged that his role was to advise Mr Rose that, unless cross-collateralisation of securities and a personal guarantee was forthcoming, Sakkara and RMB would move to appoint a receiver to Riva and other companies in the Quadrant Group, he denied that he in fact carried out that instruction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s295">Mr Rose's evidence was that a threat to appoint administrators was made in a conversation on 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s296">Mr Rose said that, in response to the alleged threat, he told Mr Bevan that he did not think Sakkara Capital and RMB had the right to appoint administrators, because the priority deeds would limit or restrict them in doing that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s297">His evidence was that Mr Bevan told him that, in his view, Sakkara Capital and RMB had the right to appoint administrators.</sentence>
<sentence id="s298">It may be that there was a conversation between Mr Rose and Mr Bevan before 8 December 2006, in which Mr Bevan told Mr Rose of the possibility that, if some accord could not be reached concerning the Riva facilities, RMB and Sakkara Capital would consider taking steps to enforce their securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s299">I do not consider that that carried with it an implicit, and certainly not an explicit, threat to do so without obtaining the consent of the senior lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s300">The email exchanges to which I have referred make it clear that Mr Bevan was very conscious of the need to obtain consent of the senior lenders before taking steps to enforce the securities given by Moruben and Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s301">It is inherently unlikely that he would have made a threat to Mr Rose to act in contravention of the arrangements with the senior lenders, of which he was expressly aware.</sentence>
<sentence id="s302">No complaint, in any event, is made in respect of any threat to appoint a receiver.</sentence>
<sentence id="s303">The only threat is that alleged to have been made on 8 December 2006 to appoint an administrator that was the subject of the spurious file note.</sentence>
<sentence id="s304">I have already indicated my conclusion concerning Mr Rose's credibility in relation to this factual issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s305">I find that there was no conversation between Mr Bevan and Mr Rose on 8 December 2006 that constituted a threat to appoint administrators to any members of the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s306">This aspect of the claim by Mr Rose and Riva must be rejected.</sentence>
<sentence id="s307">Redemption of the Moruben Road Mortgages
 In their Third Further Amended Statement of Claim, Mr Rose and Riva allege improper pressure, unconscionable conduct and unfairness on the part of the Lenders in refusing to permit Moruben to redeem their securities over the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s308">The Lenders were aware that the Quadrant Group was under pressure from the Australian Taxation Office to pay overdue instalments of tax and that all of the facilities with the Lenders were either overdue or in default.</sentence>
<sentence id="s309">In that context, Mr Rose was anxious to obtain a discharge of the securities over the Moruben Road Property and other assets of Moruben so that Moruben could borrow sufficient funds from another lender to discharge the indebtedness secured on the Moruben Road Property, as well as provide additional funds for the ongoing purposes of the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s310">The allegations in the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim may be summarised as follows: On 15 April 2005, Moruben acquired the Moruben Road Property and, by registered mortgage of that date, Moruben mortgaged the Moruben Road Property to RMB and Sakkara Capital.</sentence>
<sentence id="s311">By equitable mortgage, Moruben mortgaged the Moruben Road Property to Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s312">Moruben was entitled to have both of those mortgages redeemed upon payment of the whole of any principal sum, accrued interest and costs owing under the mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s313">On 30 November 2006, Moruben requested the Lenders to account for the amount required to redeem the two mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s314">On 5 December 2006, Moruben again requested the Lenders to account for the amount required to redeem the two mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s315">The Lenders refused to account in answer to the requests and wrongfully refused and neglected to permit the redemption of the two mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s316">Between 1991 and 2005 Mr Rose, on the one hand, and the Lenders, on the other hand, dealt with each other upon the basis of a common assumption that, where a company in the Sakkara Group provided mezzanine finance to a company associated with Mr Rose, the company in the Sakkara Group would not obtain from Mr Rose a personal guarantee in respect of financial accommodation provided to the company associated with him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s317">In reliance upon that assumption, Mr Rose continued to obtain, for companies associated with him, mezzanine finance from companies within the Sakkara Group, which provided mezzanine finance on the basis of the common assumption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s318">On 7 December 2006, Mr Bevan, acting on behalf of the Lenders, " made a demand " on Mr Rose and Riva that the two mortgages of the Moruben Road Property would not be redeemed unless they agreed to enter into the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s319">On 8 December 2006, the same demand was made again by letter of that day from Mr Camilleri to Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s320">The making of those demands was unlawful and thereby placed improper pressure on Mr Rose and Riva to agree to execute the Impugned Agreements in that: 
- Moruben was entitled to redeem the mortgages of the Moruben Road property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s321">- The obligations under the Moruben Equity Agreement and the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement were separate and independent of the obligations of Riva under the Riva Equity Agreement and the Riva Mezzanine Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s322">- Moruben was entitled to redeem the two mortgages of the Moruben Road Property upon payment of the payout figure without entering into the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s323">- The demands referred to above were inconsistent with and repugnant to the contractual and equitable right of Moruben to redeem the two mortgages of the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s324">- The demands constituted a penalty clogging Moruben's equity of redemption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s325">- The Lenders knew that Riva and Mr Rose occupied a position of special disadvantage in relation to the Impugned Agreements and took advantage of their superior bargaining power by entering into the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s326">One aspect of the claim is that Mr Rose and the Lenders, through Mr Wilson, dealt with each other upon the basis of a common assumption that, where a company in the Sakkara Group provided mezzanine finance to a company associated with Mr Rose, a personal guarantee would not be obtained from Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s327">Mr Wilson accepted that he had had a number of conversations with Mr Rose concerning guarantees in which Mr Rose asked if the Sakkara Group required personal guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s328">Mr Wilson said that his answer was that the Sakkara Group do not normally look for guarantees when going into a deal because they want to make the deal work with only registered mortgage security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s329">In cross-examination, Mr Wilson accepted that his practice on behalf of the Lenders was not to seek personal guarantees " going into a deal ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s330">It is difficult to see where the allegation of a common assumption leads.</sentence>
<sentence id="s331">There was no evidence that, going into a deal, the Lenders ever required personal guarantees from the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s332">Mr Wilson's evidence was, in effect, that, if the value of the property and the development proposed was not satisfactory, the Lenders would not go into a deal, even with personal guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s333">In the present case, however, the question of a personal guarantee from Mr Rose arose only because of the substantial default on the part of the members of the Quadrant Group and the prospect of a loss in relation to the Riva facilities in connection with the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s334">I do not consider that Riva and Mr Rose have established that any arrangement was entered into between Riva and the Lenders on the basis of any common assumption that personal guarantees would never be called for, even in the event of substantial default, such that it would be unconscionable, in any way, for the Lenders to depart from such an assumption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s335">Mr Rose and Riva complain about a wrongful refusal to permit Moruben to redeem the mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s336">The allegation is that the Lenders wrongfully refused to permit redemption, not that they merely threatened to refuse redemption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s337">The manner in which the claim is otherwise formulated is slightly unusual, in so far as it alleges a demand that the mortgages of the Moruben Road Property would not be redeemed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s338">There is no allegation of tender by Moruben of any amount secured by the mortgages: merely an allegation of a refusal to account for the amount required to discharge the mortgages, coupled with a refusal to permit redemption.</sentence>
<sentence id="s339">Further, in so far as Riva and Mr Rose seek rescission of the Impugned Agreements, restitutio in integrum would, of necessity, involve Moruben, since the mortgages over the Moruben Road Property were in fact discharged and a compromise was reached with Moruben over the amount of the Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s340">Curiously, however, Moruben is not a party to the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s341">The essence of the complaint, as finally formulated, is to be found in a letter of 8 December 2008 from Mr Camilleri to Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s342">In order to put that letter in context, it is necessary to recount a series of communications between the parties that led up to the signature of that letter by Mr Rose, whereby he effectively agreed that the Impugned Agreements would be executed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s343">During September 2006, an internal memorandum concerning the Quadrant Group was produced by one or other of the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s344">The memorandum recorded a review of the financing arrangements between the Lenders and the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s345">Two forthcoming events prompted the review, being: The forthcoming expiry of the term of the Quadwest Loan Agreement on 30 September 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s346">The potential for loss in connection with the facilities granted to Riva in relation to the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s347">
The memorandum noted that there was no obvious means by which the indebtedness under the Quadwest Loan Agreement could be repaid at expiry on 30 September 2006, given that sale of the units in the Moruben Road Property and the Chevron Island Property had not yet commenced.</sentence>
<sentence id="s348">The memorandum noted that various arrangements with the Quadrant Group were not cross-collateralised and suggested an action plan or strategy, whereby an overarching agreement would be entered into with the Quadrant Group to deal with the issues of:
 The same plan or strategy was taken up in an Action Plan of 11 October 2008, which also referred to a " Work Out Strategy ", involving entering into an overarching agreement with the Quadrant Group, which would deal with, inter alia , cross-collateralisation of all facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s349">The Action Plan also referred to the possibility of the overarching agreement providing for a personal guarantee from Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s350">An updated version of the Action Plan of 20 October 2006 repeated the same workout strategy.</sentence>
<sentence id="s351">That workout strategy was confirmed in successive iterations of the Action Plan on 27 October 2006, 3 November 2006, 10 November 2006 and 17 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s352">I have referred above to the letter of 10 October 2006 from Mr Batiste to Mr Rose, which referred to the contract with Chevron Lifestyle and asserted that the Lenders had at no time agreed to Riva entering into the contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s353">On 17 October 2006, Mr Batiste wrote to Mr Rose concerning the various financing arrangements with the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s354">After referring to the loan balances and expiry dates of all of the facilities and to the profit share in relation to the equity facilities, the letter observed that three of the facilities had by then expired and suggested that it was in the best interests of all parties to agree upon and formalise arrangements for repayment of all of the facilities (other than a separate loan agreement between Quadrant Properties and Sakkara Capital and RMB which was to expire on 8 June 2007).</sentence>
<sentence id="s355">Mr Batiste's letter of 17 October 2006 suggested that the " imminent sell down " of the Moruben Road Property offered the most sensible avenue by which to resolve the issues " in a timely fashion ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s356">The letter proposed that the sale proceeds from the Moruben Road Property be utilised, after repayment of the senior debt facilities: first to repay the Moruben and Quadwest facilities in full; and secondly, in reduction of the Riva facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s357">
The letter also proposed that the various facilities be " cross collateralised " and that all of the arrangements be formalised by way of a " multi partite deed '.</sentence>
<sentence id="s358">The letter invited Mr Rose's response in relation to the proposal concerning the application of sale proceeds from the Moruben Road Property and any alternative proposal that he may have for repayment of the various facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s359">Mr Batiste's letter crossed with the communication from Mr Rose to Mr Batiste, also of 17 October 2006, to which I have referred above.</sentence>
<sentence id="s360">In that communication, Mr Rose also said that Riva still did not have sufficient funds to undertake the marketing activities for the Chevron Island Property that had been suggested by Mr Batiste.</sentence>
<sentence id="s361">Mr Rose said that, as a director of Riva, he was not in a position to allow Riva to incur additional debts and financial obligations without the means to repay them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s362">On 23 October 2006, Mr Rose responded to Mr Batiste's letter of 17 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s363">In his response, Mr Rose confirmed agreement to repay the outstanding loan facilities owed by Quadwest and Moruben from the proceeds of the sale of the Moruben Road Property, which he said he expected to be able to achieve within the next 14 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s364">However, he said that he would like a response to his communication of 17 October 2006 concerning the marketing of the Chevron Island Property before commenting on Mr Batiste's proposals in the letter of 17 October 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s365">Notwithstanding Mr Rose's stated expectation that the Moruben Road Property would be sold within 14 days of 23 October 2006, sale was not achieved within that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s366">Mr Camilleri then took up the question of the Chevron Island Property again.</sentence>
<sentence id="s367">On 10 November 2006, Mr Camilleri sent to Mr Rose a letter from Mr Batiste dated 9 November 2006 concerning the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s368">The letter said that the Lenders' main concern in relation to the contract with Chevron Lifestyle was that: the sale does not appear to be at or near market value; the Lenders at no time agreed to Riva entering into the contract; and there would be a material adverse impact on Riva's capacity to repay the monies owed to the Lenders should the contract with Chevron Lifestyle be completed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s369">
The letter said that values obtained by the Lenders' consultant were, in aggregate, $2,205,000 higher than the prices provided for in the contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s370">The letter of 9 October 2006 sought Mr Rose's urgent advice as to how he proposed to deal with the contract with Chevron Lifestyle, given the Lenders' stated position on the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s371">The letter also required prompt finalisation and execution of an overarching agreement dealing with: Mr Rose responded to the letter of 9 November 2006 by facsimile of 15 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s372">Mr Rose's facsimile asserted that each project was funded independently from the other and that it was the intention of Riva to maintain that position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s373">That assertion was inaccurate, since, as I have pointed out above, there was already a degree of cross-collateralisation in relation to the Adelaide Terrace Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s374">Mr Rose said that a new finance facility was being negotiated that would address the repayment of the Quadwest and Moruben facilities before the end of November.</sentence>
<sentence id="s375">That last observation is a reference to a letter of 13 November 2006 received by Moruben from Ashe Morgan Winthrop, thanking Moruben for the opportunity to assist with funding requirements for the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s376">The letter enclosed a terms sheet for a proposed commercial facility for $5 million, inclusive of an interest provision of $410,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s377">By the letter, Ashe Morgan Winthrop offered " to use all reasonable endeavours " to obtain finance for Moruben on the basis of the terms sheet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s378">Thus, it was not a firm offer of financial assistance but only an invitation to treat.</sentence>
<sentence id="s379">On 20 November 2006, Mr Rose requested the provision of " the current payout figures " for the Moruben facilities as at the end of that week, namely, 24 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s380">On the same day, he received a response by email to his personal assistant saying that the Moruben " payout figure " as at 24 November was $2,367,669.24 and that interest would accrue at the daily rate of $1,153.96 until the end of November.</sentence>
<sentence id="s381">Significantly, there was no complaint from Mr Rose that the response did not specify the legal costs for the discharge of the mortgages and other securities given by Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s382">On 23 November 2006, Mr Bevan sent an email to Mr Wilson and Mr Camilleri concerning a conversation that he had had with Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s383">In the email, Mr Bevan recorded that Mr Rose had said that he was endeavouring to secure as much as he could from Ashe Morgan Winthrop on the security of the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s384">To that end, Mr Rose had asked Mr Bevan that Sakkara Properties give consideration to setting " a realistic profit share figure " under the Moruben Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s385">Mr Rose said he would pay out such a figure at the time of refinancing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s386">There is no reason to doubt that the email fairly reflects a conversation between Mr Rose and Mr Bevan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s387">It is significant that, at that stage, Mr Rose accepted the need for agreement between Sakkara Properties and Moruben as to the profit share, before finalisation of the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s388">Mr Bevan's email of 23 November 2006 went on to note that the profit share was not ascertainable at that point in time and that it was necessary to make an estimate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s389">Mr Bevan suggested that they " wait and see " what Mr Rose's " wish list " of payments that he would make from the proceeds of refinancing would be, before giving any consideration to the request for agreement on a " realistic profit share ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s390">Mr Wilson responded to Mr Bevan's email by asking if they were still preparing an overarching deed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s391">He said that they could not afford to wait for Mr Rose, since time was running out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s392">Later on 23 November 2006, Mr Rose sent an email requesting " end of November payout figures " in respect of the Quadwest and Moruben facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s393">His email said that his " numbers " were currently based upon 30 September 2006 loan balances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s394">That supports a conclusion that, for Mr Rose, the term " payout figure " referred to the amount owing under the facility and did not include legal costs that might be payable in connection with the discharges of securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s395">The allegation in the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim refers to the " payout figure " as the amount required to discharge the mortgages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s396">On 24 November 2006, Mr Camilleri responded to Mr Rose's email, setting out the projected balances, as at 30 November 2006, under the Moruben facilities and the Quadwest facilities as follows: 
 Borrower Loan Balance Risk Fee / Profit Share 
 
Quadwest $465,425.24 $408,434.23
 
Moruben $285,759.65 To be determined.</sentence>
<sentence id="s397">Mr Camilleri noted in his email that Mr Rose had obtained " a payout figure " under the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement direct from RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s398">The use of the term " payout figure " is significant in that it indicates that that term was being used as referring to the amount owing under a relevant facility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s399">Once again, there was no complaint by Mr Rose that he was not given particulars of the legal costs that would be incurred in connection with the discharges of the securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s400">On 28 November 2006, Ashe Morgan Winthrop wrote to Moruben offering a loan facility in the amount of $5,500,000, inclusive of $440,000 of capitalised interest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s401">The purpose of the loan was stated to be the refinance of existing debt primarily secured on the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s402">The letter from Ashe Morgan Winthrop provided that Mr Rose was to give a guarantee in respect of the facility.</sentence>
<sentence id="s403">On 28 November 2006, Mr Bevan and Mr Wilson had a meeting with Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s404">During the meeting, Mr Rose said that he could not pay out the profit share in respect of the Moruben Road Project (and the Adelaide Terrace project) and asked that payment of the profit share be deferred.</sentence>
<sentence id="s405">Mr Rose said that the offer he had received from Ashe Morgan Winthrop would preclude him from being able to offer cross-collateralisation in respect of the profit share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s406">He asked whether Sakkara Properties would be prepared to accept a personal guarantee instead.</sentence>
<sentence id="s407">Mr Rose said that he was " good for it ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s408">Mr Wilson told Mr Rose that he, Mr Rose, knew how he, Mr Wilson, felt about personal guarantees but, since they had been working together for a long time and had done a number of successful projects, it was something they would consider in that instance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s409">On 29 November 2006, Mr Camilleri sent to Messrs Bevan and Wilson a draft of a letter to Mr Rose outlining proposed variations to the various Quadrant Group facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s410">Mr Camilleri said that Mr Rose was meeting with Ashe Morgan Winthrop that morning to finalise the terms of refinance for the Moruben Road Project and that Mr Rose wanted to have the letter by 10 am that day.</sentence>
<sentence id="s411">In the afternoon of 29 November 2006, Mr Camilleri sent the draft letter to Mr Rose by email, in which Mr Camilleri referred to recent discussions with Messrs Bevan and Wilson.</sentence>
<sentence id="s412">The draft letter set out " the proposed variations in key terms of the existing [loan] facilities ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s413">The proposals involved repayment of the indebtedness under the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement in full, and repayment of the principal and interest under the Moruben Equity Agreement in full.</sentence>
<sentence id="s414">The existing security was to be retained and cross-collateralised with the indebtedness of Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s415">The profit share under the Moruben Equity Agreement was to be paid no later than 1 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s416">A priority deed was to be entered into with Ashe Morgan Winthrop.</sentence>
<sentence id="s417">The draft letter also proposed that, in relation to Riva, the facility term be extended to 1 July 2007 and that an overarching deed be entered into to deal, relevantly, with the following: Mr Rose responded to Mr Camilleri's proposal by email sent later on 29 November 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s418">Mr Rose said that the main two issues with which he did not agree were the cross-collateralisation and personal guarantee from him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s419">He said that, once agreement on the terms sheet had been agreed, he would need to meet with BOS, the senior lender, to get their agreement to the rescission of the contract with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s420">Mr Bevan sent an email to Mr Wilson and Mr Camilleri early on the morning of 30 November 2006, in which he recorded that the draft letter accurately reflected the discussions with Mr Rose, notwithstanding that, the previous evening, Mr Rose had indicated that he was not happy with respect to the cross-collateralisation and the provision of a personal guarantee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s421">Mr Bevan said that it was his understanding that the cross-collateralisation proposal had been in the discussions from the outset and that he found it difficult that Mr Rose was " back peddling " on that issue.</sentence>
<sentence id="s422">Mr Bevan also said that Mr Rose had indicated that any reference made by him to the provision of a personal guarantee was only if the outstanding profit share was not to be secured by mortgage, as it now was to be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s423">Mr Bevan said that, in that context, he believed that they could drop the personal guarantee requirement, provided they took the security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s424">It is significant that the proposal for a personal guarantee by Mr Rose appears, therefore, to have come from Mr Rose himself.</sentence>
<sentence id="s425">On the other hand, Mr Bevan accepted in the email that the guarantee was proffered by Mr Rose in relation to the outstanding profit share under the Moruben Equity Agreement, against the possibility that payment of the profit share would not be secured.</sentence>
<sentence id="s426">Mr Bevan's email of 30 November 2006 went on to say that, without the cross-collateralisation, he believed the return from the Riva Mezzanine Agreement would be marginal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s427">Mr Bevan also observed that another " pressure point " that was available was the profit share under the Quadwest Facility, which was then due and which Mr Rose had asked to be postponed and secured on the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s428">The email ended by saying that, if they were looking at a shortfall in respect of the Riva facilities, they must put the cross-collateralisation in place.</sentence>
<sentence id="s429">Mr Camilleri responded to Mr Bevan, indicating that a loss of $931,033 was projected in respect of the Riva Mezzanine Agreement on the basis of valuations that had been obtained.</sentence>
<sentence id="s430">As I have indicated above, Mr Camilleri also pointed out that Sakkara Capital and RMB were prohibited from exercising any power under its securities without the prior written consent of the senior lender, unless the senior lender had been fully and finally paid all moneys secured.</sentence>
<sentence id="s431">On Friday, 1 December 2006, Mr Rose sent to Mr Camilleri a calculation of the Net Project Profit for the Moruben Road Development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s432">The calculation showed a profit of $3,140,803, with Sakkara Properties' 10% share being $314,803 [sic].</sentence>
<sentence id="s433">Mr Rose clearly did not put that figure forward as having been fixed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s434">It was put forward as a proposal for acceptance by Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s435">Mid morning on 1 December 2006, Mr Matthew Barry of Deacons, who were acting for Moruben, emailed Ms Emma Young and Ms Mary Breen, of Blake Dawson Waldron, who were acting for the Lenders, saying that on 5 December 2006 Moruben intended to pay out the mortgages to BOS and the Lenders which was secured on the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s436">The email said that the original documents relating to the Moruben Road Property, including the certificates of title, would be expected on settlement and asked for confirmation of " the payout figure for the loans ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s437">No reference was made to legal costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s438">Ms Breen forwarded the email to Mr Camilleri, who replied shortly afterwards, saying that the Lenders intended to retain their security over the Moruben Road Property and that " the payout figure " should be obtained from RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s439">At some time on 1 December 2006, Mr Bevan spoke to Mr Rose by telephone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s440">Mr Rose said that he wished to pay out all mezzanine and profit share owing by Quadwest and Moruben but to leave Riva to stand alone.</sentence>
<sentence id="s441">He said that he was looking to refinance the liabilities secured on the Moruben Road Property on the following Tuesday and that a " payout " was needed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s442">Again, no specific mention was made of legal costs connected with the discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s443">Late on 1 December 2006, Mr Rose sent to Mr Camilleri a calculation of the Internal Rate of Return under the Moruben Equity Agreement, showing that Sakkara Properties' minimum share of the Net Project Profit, was $355,818.</sentence>
<sentence id="s444">Mr Rose's calculation also stated that the principal sum outstanding under the Moruben Equity Agreement as at December 2006 was $285,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s445">Thus, Mr Rose considered that he had the material necessary to calculate the latter sum and to calculate the former.</sentence>
<sentence id="s446">Early on the morning of Monday, 4 December 2006, Mr Bevan reported by email to Messrs Camilleri and Wilson that Mr Rose had advised him at 5 pm on the previous Friday that: Mr Bevan's email of 4 December 2006 also said that there was to be no release of security until they had received all project accounting from the Quadrant Group to determine the share of the Net Project Profit under the Moruben Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s447">Mr Bevan asked Mr Camilleri to inform Mr Rose of that requirement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s448">The Moruben Equity Agreement provided for that information to be provided to Sakkara Properties if it required it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s449">Mr Bevan went on to say that the proposal by Mr Rose was another shift from his stated position.</sentence>
<sentence id="s450">He said that, without the cross security to the Moruben Road Property, the Lenders looked vulnerable to loss.</sentence>
<sentence id="s451">He expressed the view that the Lenders needed to be satisfied with the arrangements on Riva before the Moruben and Quadwest securities were released.</sentence>
<sentence id="s452">Significantly, he said such release would " be difficult to resist from a legal view given present security position ", a comment to which Mr Rose and Riva attach considerable significance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s453">In his email of 4 December 2006, Mr Bevan also referred to Mr Camilleri's confirmation that they could not enforce the Riva security without the consent of the senior lender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s454">He asked Mr Camilleri to look at the Moruben security to see if the Lenders could make a claim for the exposure to Riva, " based upon definition items in the security documents ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s455">Mr Bevan then observed that Mr Rose was maintaining that he would not permit cross-collateralisation to the Moruben Road Property for the possible shortfall from Riva and would not provide a personal guarantee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s456">He said that the only other security available was the Milson's Point Property, Mr Rose's home, which, Mr Bevan said, was " tied to the Rose Bay project ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s457">The reference to the Rose Bay project is unclear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s458">Mr Bevan said that the Moruben Road Property remained the best option for security and that, with the repayment of the mezzanine and profit share, they would have no present claim against that security.</sentence>
<sentence id="s459">Thus, it is clear enough that Mr Bevan was looking for a basis on which the Lenders could decline to discharge the mortgages over the Moruben Road Property at that stage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s460">In an email later on 4 December 2006, from Mr Bevan to Messrs Camilleri and Wilson, to which reference has been made above in connection with the alleged threat to appoint administrators, Mr Bevan asked Mr Camilleri to ask Mr Rose to provide " the project details " for the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s461">Mr Bevan said " that should slow him down on his settlement proposals ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s462">The email went on to say that " we have security and leverage now that will be lost if we allow the repayment of the moneys due on Moruben Road and Quadwest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s463">Our weakness is the contracted link across the securities ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s464">Riva and Mr Rose attach some significance to the contents of those emails, as suggesting that Mr Bevan was conscious of the imposition of pressure on Mr Rose and Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s465">The emails indicate that Mr Bevan was mindful of the fact that the discharge of the securities given by Moruben would result in loss of bargaining power that might otherwise be available to compel some further security in relation to the indebtedness of Riva, which was at risk.</sentence>
<sentence id="s466">Mr Camilleri acted as he was instructed, by sending an email to Mr Rose on 4 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s467">In the email, Mr Camilleri acknowledged receipt of the calculation of 1 December 2006 of the profit share and told Mr Rose that Sakkara Properties would need to review the books and records relating to the Moruben Road Project before reaching agreement on the profit share amount payable to it from the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s468">Sakkara was entitled to that material under clause 6.6(a) of the Moruben Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s469">Mr Rose responded by email shortly afterwards, saying that he was planning to pay out the Moruben facilities on Wednesday 6 December 2006 and would need to agree on " the payout figure " forthwith.</sentence>
<sentence id="s470">He said that, by his calculations, the minimum Internal Rate of Return was going to be greater than the 10% share of the Net Project Profit in any event and that he was happy " to personally guarantee any difference that you may find between the IRR and the books and records ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s471">He ended by saying that he would require " the mortgage " to be discharged upon refinance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s472">That must be taken to be a reference to the Moruben Equity Mortgage as well as to the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s473">It is significant that Mr Rose was still prepared to give a personal guarantee, albeit for a much smaller sum than the likely shortfall on the Riva facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s474">According to an email sent by Mr Camilleri to Messrs Bevan and Wilson shortly after 4 pm on 5 December 2006, Mr Rose then put forward a proposal along the following lines: The Lenders can retain a mortgage over the Moruben Road Property, which would be subordinated to the proposed $5 million facility from Ashe Morgan Winthrop.</sentence>
<sentence id="s475">The Lenders' priority with respect to the Moruben Road Property would be limited to an aggregate sum of $350,000 and it could not be called upon for 12 months.</sentence>
<sentence id="s476">Mr Rose would meet costs associated with securing rescission of the contract with Chevron Lifestyle, the marketing costs associated with the Chevron Island Property and interest on the Riva senior debt.</sentence>
<sentence id="s477">Mr Rose would agree that any marketing program for Riva must be acceptable to Sakkara.</sentence>
<sentence id="s478">
There is no reason to doubt that the email fairly recorded a proposal from Mr Rose, which involved some personal responsibility for Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s479">Later on 5 December 2006, Deacons wrote to Blake Dawson Waldron attaching a copy of company searches for Moruben and for Quadrant Property Services.</sentence>
<sentence id="s480">Deacons said that they had been instructed as follows: Moruben is ready, willing and able to pay out the loan relating to the Moruben Road Property, subject to " the appropriate discharge amount " being provided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s481">Moruben has had discussions with the Lenders as to " the quantum of discharge amount " in relation to the Moruben Road Property but does not agree with the proposal for the discharge presented by the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s482">Moruben has incurred significant costs as a result of not settling the transaction that day and will continue to incur further costs until the transaction is settled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s483">
Deacons requested Blake Dawson Waldron to provide " the discharge amount in relation to the discharge and release " of the Moruben Road Property " with a breakdown as to how that total was obtained ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s484">The letter ended by saying that Deacons looked forward to prompt confirmation of " the payout figures ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s485">Blake Dawson Waldron forwarded the Deacons letter to Mr Camilleri by email early on 6 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s486">Shortly after noon on 6 December 2006, Mr Camilleri sent an email to Blake Dawson Waldron setting out details of the amounts " required to payout [sic]" the various loans as at that date.</sentence>
<sentence id="s487">It is not clear whether that information was forwarded to Deacons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s488">However, shortly after that email was sent, Mr Barry sent an email to Ms Breen asking for a response to the letter of 5 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s489">Ms Breen responded later in the day that she had been instructed that the clients were meeting at 10 am the following day and she would let him know as soon as she received instructions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s490">A meeting took place on 7 December 2006 involving Mr Bevan, Mr Camilleri and Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s491">Mr Rose said that a personal guarantee would be provided because a mortgage over the remaining lots of the Moruben Road Property was no longer available.</sentence>
<sentence id="s492">Mr Rose accepted in cross-examination that, at the meeting, he put forward a proposal that involved his providing a personal guarantee for amounts equal to the principal amounts then owing by Riva, if he failed to perform certain functions .</sentence>
<sentence id="s493">That may be a reference to the proposal that he would give a personal guarantee if security could not be provided for outstanding profit share.</sentence>
<sentence id="s494">It is not entirely clear.</sentence>
<sentence id="s495">He accepted that the bottom line was that he could be liable for $2 million in respect of the Riva Mezzanine Agreement and $450,000 on the Riva Equity Agreement if he failed to perform the functions that were discussed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s496">He subsequently said that he could not recall who put forward the proposal and that his recollection was that the proposal came from either Mr Bevan or Mr Camilleri.</sentence>
<sentence id="s497">I consider that it is more probable that Mr Rose put forward the proposal, as he first accepted.</sentence>
<sentence id="s498">That is significant in so far as it indicates his preparedness to accept a personal liability, at least in some circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s499">On 8 December 2008, Deacons wrote to Blake Dawson Waldron again.</sentence>
<sentence id="s500">They said that they were instructed as follows: Despite the meeting of the clients on 7 December 2006 to discuss " the quantum of the discharge amount ", their client did not reach agreement on the proposal for the discharge presented by Blake Dawson Waldron's client.</sentence>
<sentence id="s501">Since 6 December 2006, Moruben has been ready, willing and able to pay out the loan, subject to the Lenders providing " the appropriate discharge amount ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s502">Moruben has incurred significant costs and expenses as a result of not settling this transaction on 6 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s503">
Deacons then requested that Blake Dawson Waldron provide them with " the discharge amount... with a breakdown as to how that total was obtained ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s504">The letter went on to say that, if a discharge amount was not provided by 5 pm on 8 December 2006, their instructions were that the matter would " be elevated and further legal action would be instigated ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s505">The letter finished by requesting prompt confirmation of " the payout figures ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s506">Neither Deacons' letter of 5 December 2006 nor their letter of 8 December 2006 made any specific mention of legal costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s507">They spoke only in terms of " the discharge amount " and " the payout figures ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s508">At 1.53 pm on 8 December 2006, Mr Camilleri sent to Mr Rose a letter setting out the terms of " RMB/Sakkara's counter proposal " to the offer put forward by Mr Rose at the meeting of 7 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s509">Although the letter enclosed with the email was signed by Mr Camilleri, it was clearly endorsed " DRAFT ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s510">Mr Camilleri's email said that he and Mr Bevan would be happy to discuss the matter further with Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s511">At 2.22 pm, Mr Rose sent an email to Mr Camilleri asking that Mr Camilleri " issue " the letter as an " execution version for me ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s512">A copy of Mr Camilleri's earlier email was sent to Mr Bevan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s513">Mr Bevan made a handwritten note on his copy of a telephone conversation with Mr Rose at 2.25 pm on 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s514">I accept that Mr Bevan's note fairly recorded the substance of the conversation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s515">It said as follows: 
 OK with terms --- we are to send without the draft stamp --- needs urgently including payout --- what are the costs?</sentence>
<sentence id="s516">

 
It is significant that that appears to be the first occasion on which there was any express reference made to costs in relation to discharge of mortgages by Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s517">It is also significant that a distinction was drawn between the payout figure and costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s518">Mr Bevan sent an email to Mr Camilleri at 2.34 pm on 8 December 2006 saying that Mr Rose had phoned and confirmed that he was agreeable to the terms and wanted to sign a clean copy without " DRAFT " on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s519">Mr Bevan asked Mr Camilleri to work out the costs that needed to be paid to the solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s520">He said that Mr Rose said that he did not know the amount but wanted to settle as soon as possible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s521">Thus, as soon as a figure for costs was requested, steps were taken to provide it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s522">At 2.51 pm, Mr Bevan sent to Mr Rose the form of the letter without " DRAFT " endorsed on it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s523">At some time later on 8 December 2006, Mr Rose signed the foot of the letter, acknowledging and agreeing to the proposed variations in terms of the existing facilities provided to the companies mentioned in the letter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s524">The terms of the letter are critical to the allegation that, by the letter, the Lenders made a demand and refused to permit Moruben to redeem its securities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s525">The terms of the letter, with handwritten amendments made by Mr Rose shown in bold italics, are as follows: 
 8 December 2006 

 
 Mr Chris Rose
 Riva Properties Pty Ltd
 Suite 2, Level 11
 80 Mount Street
 North Sydney NSW 2059 

 
 Dear Chris 

 
 Various Mezzanine Finance &amp; Equity Finance Facilities 

 
 Following on from our discussion of 7 th December 2006, outlined below are RMB/Sakkara's proposed variations in the terms of the existing facilities provided to the Quadrant Group viz: 

 
 Quadwest Developments Pty Ltd 

 
 Lender: Sakkara Properties Pty Ltd 

 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s526">Loan to be repaid in full (including risk fee).</sentence>
<sentence id="s527">
 In addition, all outstanding legal fees currently owed to Middletons and Blake Dawson Waldron to be paid in full.</sentence>
<sentence id="s528">
 Moruben Developments Pty Ltd 

 
 Lender: RMB Australia Holdings Limited &amp; Sakkara Capital Investments Pty Ltd 

 Loan to be repaid in full.</sentence>
<sentence id="s529">
 Lender: Sakkara Properties Pty Ltd 

 Loan to be repaid in full (including profit share capped at $300,000).</sentence>
<sentence id="s530">
 Riva Properties Pty Ltd 

 
 Lender: RMB Australia Holdings Limited &amp; Sakkara Capital Investments Pty Ltd 
 Lender: RMB Australia Holdings Limited &amp; Sakkara Properties Pty Ltd 

 Facility Term to be extended to 1 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s531">Chris Rose to provide a Guarantee and Indemnity of $2,450,000 which may be called upon in the event of: 
 (1) A failure to meet the following undertakings
 &#183; fund and coordinate all marketing --- with all proposed sales and marketing to be acceptable to Sakkara (agreed hurdle);
 &#183; Meet all holding costs on Chevron Island Property (including senior debt interest) that is not capitalised ;
 &#183; Rescind contract with Chevron Lifestyle Properties --- with consent of BOSI;
 &#183; Use best endeavours to achieve "Landsburys' values (formal valuation to be completed) subject to an agreed hurdle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s532">

 
 The hurdle may be that all sales must be completed by 30 June 2007 and any sale must be within 5% of the Landsbury's valuation of the subject apartment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s533">

 
 (2) Any Riva Properties Pty Ltd mezzanine loan principal or equity loan principal (excluding interest) remaining outstanding subsequent to the sale of all apartments in the "Riva on Chevron" project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s534">

 
 The agreed order in which sales proceeds of the 'Riva' project are disbursed is to be: 

 senior debt; mezzanine interest mezzanine principal equity principal equity interest profit share
 
 The variations will be documented by way of a Deed and Guarantee and Indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s535">The Deed and Guarantee and Indemnity will need to be executed prior to settlement of the Moruben Developments Pty Ltd refinance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s536">Both parties agree that time is of the essence in this regard, and must be consummated on or before the 13 th of December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s537">

 
 All legal fees and other costs associated with the above variations are to be met by Quadrant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s538">

 
 This counter-proposal is subject to RMB's formal approval, which we undertake to obtain immediately upon your acceptance of the terms proposed herein.</sentence>
<sentence id="s539">

 
 In order that we may progress this matter, would you please acknowledge your agreement to the proposed variations by signing below (where indicated) and return a copy to this office.</sentence>
<sentence id="s540">

 
 Yours sincerely 

 
 Steve Camilleri
 Operations Manager, Lending 

 
 I acknowledge and agree to the proposed variations in the terms of the existing facilities provided to the above companies .</sentence>
<sentence id="s541">

 
 [Mr Rose's signature] 

 
 8/12/2006 

 Mr Rose and Riva complain that that letter constitutes a demand or threat that the mortgages of the Moruben Road Property would not be discharged and the charges given by Moruben would not be discharged unless the Impugned Agreements were entered into.</sentence>
<sentence id="s542">They point specifically to the following words: 
 The variations will be documented by way of a deed and guarantee and indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s543">The deed and guarantee and indemnity will need to be executed prior to settlement of the Moruben Developments Pty Ltd refinance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s544">

 
It is significant that Mr Rose endorsed a further sentence immediately after the very passage that is said to constitute the threat or demand, thus indicating his express acceptance of that aspect of the proposal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s545">On 12 December 2006, drafts of the Impugned Agreements were sent by Blake Dawson Waldron to Deacons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s546">In their email of 12 December 2008, under cover of which they sent the drafts, Blake Dawson Waldron said that Sakkara Properties did not propose to hand over any discharge of its security in relation to the loans to Quadwest and Moruben at settlement, on the basis that the security was not registered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s547">The email also asked for a certificate confirming that Mr Rose did not consider it necessary to obtain independent legal advice prior to execution of the forms of Guarantee and Indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s548">Later on 12 December 2006, Mr Rose proceeded to obtain legal advice in relation to the Impugned Agreements from Mr Robert Schneider, solicitor, as to whether there were provisions that would be inconsistent with any subsequent action by Mr Rose to impugn the guarantees, for example, by asserting that the Lenders had engaged in unconscionable conduct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s549">Mr Schneider expressed the view that the guarantees contained such provisions but very much doubted whether the Lenders would agree to any variation, let alone the deletion, of such provisions, given that they were fundamental to the efficacy of the guarantees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s550">Mr Schneider expressed the view that it would be extremely difficult for Mr Rose to impugn the guarantees successfully in the future, should the Lenders seek to enforce them, in circumstances where he had not, either prior to or at the time of executing the guarantees and the proposed variation agreements, reserved his right to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s551">Mr Rose then instructed Deacons to request further concessions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s552">Importantly, he instructed Deacons to request that the guarantee provided by Quadrant Properties be released.</sentence>
<sentence id="s553">That they did.</sentence>
<sentence id="s554">Deacons informed Blake Dawson Waldron that Quadrant Properties had no assets and that it was proposed, in due course, that it be " wound down ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s555">After obtaining instructions from Mr Camilleri and Mr Bevan, Blake Dawson Waldron responded to Deacons that the Lenders required that the guarantee remain in place at that stage and that, if Deacons' client wished to commence any winding down of Quadrant Properties at a later date, it should request the consent to the release of the guarantee at that time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s556">Deacons responded late on Thursday, 14 December 2006 that it was intended that Quadrant Properties be liquidated the following week and accordingly requested Blake Dawson Waldron to obtain consent to the release of the guarantee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s557">On 15 December 2006, Blake Dawson Waldron responded to Deacons that the Lenders agreed that the guarantee by Quadrant Properties would no longer be required, provided Mr Rose provided a statutory declaration confirming that Quadrant Properties had no assets and that Mr Rose agreed to wind up the company by a specified time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s558">They said that the obligation to wind up Quadrant Properties by that date would be incorporated into the guarantees to be provided by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s559">Deacons were asked for the time by which Mr Rose agreed to wind up Quadrant Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s560">There was no evidence as to why it was pressing for Quadrant Properties to be wound up and for it to be released from the guarantee at that time, other than the fact that its guarantee linked Mr Rose personally to the indebtedness of Riva through the Milson's Point Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s561">That is of great significance in relation to Mr Rose's motivation in accepting the proposal of 8 December 2006 and executing the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s562">On the afternoon of 15 December 2006, Deacons provided to Blake Dawson Waldron, with a copy to Mr Camilleri and Mr Bevan and others, a form of statutory declaration by Mr Rose in relation to Quadrant Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s563">A statutory declaration was given by Mr Rose in that form at the time of execution of the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s564">By that statutory declaration, Mr Rose declared that there was a deficiency in the net asset position in Quadrant Properties and that a meeting of creditors had been set for 3 January 2007, to appoint a liquidator.</sentence>
<sentence id="s565">Mr Rose executed the Impugned Agreements on 18 December 2006, without any further complaint to the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s566">On the same day, the sum of $5,060,000 was advanced by Ashe Morgan Winthrop on the security of the Moruben Road Property and all securities given by Moruben to the Lenders were discharged.</sentence>
<sentence id="s567">The sum of $5,060,000 was dispersed as follows: 
 1.</sentence>
<sentence id="s568">$2,395,671.57 RMB
 2.</sentence>
<sentence id="s569">$287,168.88 Sakkara Properties
 3.</sentence>
<sentence id="s570">$300,000.00 Sakkara Properties
 4.</sentence>
<sentence id="s571">$468,868.11 Sakkara Properties
 5.</sentence>
<sentence id="s572">$411,455.53 Sakkara Properties
 6.</sentence>
<sentence id="s573">$1,800.31 Blake Dawson Waldron
 7.</sentence>
<sentence id="s574">$11,340.39 Blake Dawson Waldron
 8.</sentence>
<sentence id="s575">$19,087.02 Middletons Lawyers
 9.</sentence>
<sentence id="s576">$2,500.00 Blake Dawson Waldron
 10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s577">$690,000.00 BOS
 11.</sentence>
<sentence id="s578">$21,951.00 Office of State Revenue
 12.</sentence>
<sentence id="s579">$5,080.00 Gadens Lawyers
 13.</sentence>
<sentence id="s580">$ 27,500.00 Ashe Morgan Commercial
 14.</sentence>
<sentence id="s581">$121.00 bank cheque fees
 15.</sentence>
<sentence id="s582">$5,894.94 Deacons
 16.</sentence>
<sentence id="s583">$660.00 Henry Davis York
 17.</sentence>
<sentence id="s584">$9,102.50 Blake Dawson Waldron
 18.</sentence>
<sentence id="s585">$2,480.00 Office of State Revenue
 Total: $5,060,000.00 

 It is apparent that the indebtedness owing to BOS, the senior lender in respect of the Moruben Road Property, was repaid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s586">At that stage, the amount owing was $690,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s587">In addition, all of the indebtedness of Moruben to the Lenders under the Moruben Equity Agreement and the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement, was repaid.</sentence>
<sentence id="s588">Specifically, the sum of $300,000 was paid to Sakkara Properties as its share of the Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s589">The guarantee by Quadrant Properties was subsequently released when Quadrant Properties was wound up.</sentence>
<sentence id="s590">Subsequently, the Milsons Point Mortgage was also discharged, since it no longer secured any indebtedness.</sentence>
<sentence id="s591">The Impugned Agreements
 The four Impugned Agreements were entered into on 18 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s592">The Impugned Agreements consist of two forms of Loan Agreement Variation Deed and two forms of Guarantee and Indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s593">The parties to the first Loan Agreement Variation Deed are Riva, RMB and Sakkara Properties and Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s594">The parties to the second Loan Agreement Variation Deed are Riva, RMB and Sakkara Capital and Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s595">The first Loan Agreement Variation Deed recites the Riva Equity Agreement and recites that RMB had, on 23 December 2004, agreed to participate in the funding to Riva under the Riva Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s596">The deed also recites the Guarantee and Indemnity of 18 December 2006 by Mr Rose of the obligations of Riva under the Riva Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s597">The operative provisions of the first Loan Agreement Variation Deed varied the Riva Equity Agreement in three respects.</sentence>
<sentence id="s598">First, by new Clause 17, Riva undertook that it would fund and diligently and prudently coordinate all sale and marketing activities in connection with the sale of the Chevron Island Property and would rescind or terminate or procure the rescission or termination of the agreement of 18 May 2006 with Chevron Lifestyle.</sentence>
<sentence id="s599">Riva also undertook that it would enter into contracts for sale of all residential units comprising the Chevron Island Property and ensure that completion occurred under those contracts by 30 June 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s600">The prices at which the units were to be sold were specified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s601">Secondly, by a new clause 18, the order of distribution of the proceeds of sale of the Chevron Island Property was specified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s602">Finally, the term of the facility under the Riva Equity Agreement was extended to 1 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s603">By the first Guarantee and Indemnity, Mr Rose guaranteed to RMB and Sakkara Properties the due and punctual payment by Riva of the whole or any part of any moneys that remain unpaid at any time under or in connection with the Riva Equity Agreement, up to a maximum of $450,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s604">Clause 2.3(a) provided that, if Riva defaults in the due and punctual payment of any guaranteed money, Mr Rose must pay that money on demand to, or as directed by, RMB and Sakkara Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s605">However, by clause 12, clause 2.3 was made conditional, inter alia , upon Riva failing to comply with the new clause 17 of the Riva Equity Agreement or upon any guaranteed money remaining following the sale of all residential units comprising the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s606">In addition, by clause 7.3 of the first Guarantee and Indemnity, Mr Rose covenanted that he would: The second Loan Agreement Variation Deed made the same amendments to the Riva Mezzanine Agreement of 23 December 2004 as had been made to the Riva Equity Agreement by the first Loan Agreement Variation Deed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s607">Specifically, it extended the time for repayment to 1 July 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s608">In addition, by clause 6.1, Mr Rose, in his capacity as sole director and sole secretary of Quadrant Properties, covenanted that, on or before 3 January 2007, he would either appoint an administrator or convene a meeting of creditors for the purpose of appointing a liquidator to Quadrant Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s609">Riva and Mr Rose acknowledged that RMB and Sakkara Capital had executed the second Loan Agreement Variation Deed on the basis of that covenant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s610">By the Second Guarantee and Indemnity, Mr Rose gave a guarantee of the obligations of Riva under the Riva Mezzanine Agreement in terms similar to the first Guarantee and Indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s611">As a result of the transactions that were settled on 18 December 2006, the default in respect of the facilities of the Lenders relating to the Moruben Road Projects was rectified and it was no longer open to the Lenders to enforce their securities in respect of the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s612">In addition, the effect of the variation of the facilities with Riva was to remove any default, by extending the time for repayment of both facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s613">Further Sakkara Properties accepted $300,000 in respect of its share of the Net Project Profit for the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s614">The undertaking by Riva to rescind its contract with Chevron Lifestyle and to undertake a fixed regime for the realisation of the Chevron Island Property was a quid pro quo for Sakkara Properties accepting the sum of $300,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s615">The guarantees by Mr Rose were no doubt an inducement for the Lenders to enter into the Loan Agreement Variation Deeds with Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s616">Disposition of the Wrongful Refusal of Redemption Claims
 I consider that the evidence leads to the conclusion that, at the time when he decided to accept the terms of the letter of 8 December 2006 and subsequently to sign the Impugned Agreements, Mr Rose had in mind that he was obtaining a considerable advantage for himself personally, in addition to the advantageous extension, from the point of view of Riva, of its facilities, which were either overdue or in default and were due for repayment by the end of December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s617">Further, he secured an advantageous compromise of the amount of the share of Sakkara Properties in the Net Project Profit for the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s618">I do not consider that Mr Rose was induced by any undue or unfair pressure on the part of the Lenders or by any unconscionable conduct on the part of the Lenders to accept the letter of 8 December 2006 or to execute the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s619">Further, I do not consider that either of the two deeds of Guarantee and Indemnity executed by Mr Rose was unjust in the circumstances relating to their execution by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s620">More specifically, I do not consider that the agreement of 8 December 2006, which was constituted by Mr Rose's acceptance of the letter of that date, was unjust in the circumstances relating to its execution by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s621">I do not consider that the Lenders used unfair pressure or unfair tactics against Mr Rose in relation to the execution of the forms of Guarantee and Indemnity.</sentence>
<sentence id="s622">It is true that the Quadrant Group, as a whole, was under some financial pressure, as the Lenders knew.</sentence>
<sentence id="s623">Various companies in the Quadrant Group were in default of their financing arrangements and they needed funds to discharge obligations to the Australian Taxation Office.</sentence>
<sentence id="s624">Nevertheless, the Quadrant Group as a whole derived benefits as a consequence of the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s625">Moruben had no entitlement to a discharge of the Moruben Equity Mortgage prior to the final determination of the Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s626">Nevertheless, Moruben was able to secure discharge of the securities, notwithstanding that the Moruben Road Development was not complete because not all of the apartments had been sold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s627">Thus, the Quadrant Group was able to use the unsold part of the Moruben Road Property to raise funds for the benefit of the Quadrant Group as a whole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s628">That was a benefit to Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s629">Further, the default by Riva was remedied, in that an extension of more than six months for the time for discharge of the facilities granted to Riva was secured.</sentence>
<sentence id="s630">That was also a benefit for Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s631">Finally, and very significantly, while Mr Rose undertook personal obligations by means of the Deeds of Indemnity and Guarantee, with a limitation on his liability of $2,450,000, he also secured the release of an unlimited guarantee related to the obligations of Quadrant Properties, which as at 18 December 2006, were well in excess of $2,450,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s632">I consider that Mr Rose was conscious of his personal position and the exposure of the Milsons Point Property to liabilities of Riva, through Quadrant Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s633">Mr Rose was personally better off as a consequence of the consummation of the agreement constituted by acceptance of the letter of 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s634">Mr Rose had information available to him that would have enabled him to calculate the payout figures for all of the indebtedness of Moruben to the Lenders, other than the amount of the Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s635">That could not be determined until the sale of all of the apartments in the Moruben Road Property, although it would have been open to the parties to agree on an estimate of value for the purposes of an earlier discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s636">At no stage was any attempt made to tender any amount in order to secure discharge of the mortgages over the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s637">Had there been a formal tender, the Lenders may have taken a different course.</sentence>
<sentence id="s638">However, they were never put in the position of having to respond to a formal tender.</sentence>
<sentence id="s639">Certainly, the legal costs of the discharge would be secured by the mortgages and would have to be paid in order to compel a discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s640">It may be that Mr Rose did not know what the legal costs of the discharge of the securities would be.</sentence>
<sentence id="s641">However, at no stage did Mr Rose, or those acting for him, specifically ask for an estimate of legal costs involved in the discharge.</sentence>
<sentence id="s642">No demand had been made for costs at the time when Mr Rose signed the letter of 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s643">Indeed, on 13 December 2006, Blake Dawson Waldron wrote to Deacons specifying the amounts " required to discharge the mortgages as at 14 December 2006 ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s644">At the end of the letter, Blake Dawson Waldron stated that they required payment of attached invoices and that their costs and disbursements in acting for the Lenders in respect of the discharge of the securities over the Moruben Road Property were $1,492.38.</sentence>
<sentence id="s645">The letter ended by saying that, once the Impugned Agreements had been finalised, Blake Dawson Waldron would advise Deacons of their fees for acting for the Lenders in that regard, which they also required to be paid on settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s646">There is no substance in the contention advanced on behalf of Mr Rose and Riva that they could not determine a payout figure for the redemption of the mortgages of the Moruben Road Property without first being given details of legal costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s647">The definition of Net Project Profit in the Moruben Equity Agreement refers to an amount agreed by the parties, in good faith, to be the profit derived in relation to the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s648">However, it is clear, from the language of the relevant provision of the Moruben Equity Agreement, that a calculation was to be made by reference to the difference between two amounts, each of which is defined by reference to the actual result of the Moruben Road Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s649">Specifically, Revenue was defined as the proceeds of sales of the Moruben Road Property, or parts of it, plus any other revenue received by Moruben from the Project.</sentence>
<sentence id="s650">That must be understood as referring only to the actual proceeds received, not to some estimate of what might be received in the future.</sentence>
<sentence id="s651">The bargain between Moruben and Sakkara Properties was that Sakkara Properties would be entitled to 10% of the Net Project Profit from the Moruben Road Project and that its entitlement to that share was to be secured by a mortgage of the Moruben Road Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s652">Until the Project was completed and Net Project Profit could be determined, Sakkara Properties was entitled to maintain its security for its share of Net Project Profit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s653">While Sakkara Properties could, of course, agree to accept an estimate, it was not bound to do so.</sentence>
<sentence id="s654">The crux of the complaint made by Mr Rose and Riva, that the Lenders threatened to refuse, wrongfully, to allow Moruben to redeem the mortgages of the Moruben Road Property, depends upon the construction of the letter of 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s655">They point specifically to the following sentence: 
 The Deed and Guarantee and Indemnity will need to be executed prior to settlement of the Moruben Developments Pty Ltd refinance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s656">

 
However, that sentence must be understood in the context in which it appears.</sentence>
<sentence id="s657">It is not a threat.</sentence>
<sentence id="s658">The sentence is but one sentence in a letter of over a page and a half, in which a detailed proposal was being put forward to Mr Rose and Riva for their consideration.</sentence>
<sentence id="s659">The proposal provided benefits to Riva and it was in no way expressed as an ultimatum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s660">Mr Rose had put forward a proposal and the letter of 8 December 2006 is expressed to be a " counter proposal ".</sentence>
<sentence id="s661">Even then, it is expressed to be subject to " formal approval " by RMB.</sentence>
<sentence id="s662">One of the terms of the proposal being put forward involved a guarantee and indemnity by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s663">The requirement that the guarantee and indemnity be executed prior to settlement of the refinancing is understandable: that was the quid pro quo for the Lenders' agreeing to the discharge of their security on the basis of a compromise concerning the Net Profit Share and the extension of the Riva facilities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s664">Sakkara Properties agreed to limit its share of the Net Project Profit to $300,000 and to release its security, notwithstanding that the Project had not yet been completed and notwithstanding that Mr Rose had earlier estimated Sakkara Properties' share to be $314,803 and had calculated the minimum Internal Rate of Return to be $355,818.</sentence>
<sentence id="s665">Mr Rose accepted the counter proposal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s666">Indeed, he added a further requirement that time was to be of the essence and that the arrangements were to be consummated by 13 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s667">He subsequently secured the release of his personal obligations in respect of the Riva Mezzanine Agreement, through the Quadrant Properties guarantee, as a consequence of the release of that guarantee.</sentence>
<sentence id="s668">I do not consider that, in all of the circumstances, there was any wrongful threat on the part of the Lenders to refuse to discharge the securities given by Moruben.</sentence>
<sentence id="s669">Moruben had no entitlement to a discharge of the Moruben Equity Mortgage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s670">It had no entitlement to a discharge of the Moruben Mezzanine Mortgage without tender of the amount secured, which it did not do until 18 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s671">Mr Rose and Riva may have been under some pressure because of the financial pressure on the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s672">However, I do not consider that the circumstances that I have described amount to the bringing to bear of any undue or unfair pressure on either of them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s673">It cannot fairly be said that the conduct of the Lenders should be characterised as unconscionable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s674">Mr Rose and Riva were, by reason of financial pressure, relevantly in a position of disadvantage to the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s675">However, inequality of bargaining power is not of itself sufficient to render the conduct of a stronger party unconscionable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s676">Mr Rose and Riva must establish that they suffered a special disability or were placed in some special situation of disadvantage, which rendered them unable to make a worthwhile judgment as to what was in their own best interests and that the Lenders knowingly took advantage of that disability or disadvantage.</sentence>
<sentence id="s677">No special disability or special disadvantage has been established in the present instance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s678">A person will not be in a position of special disadvantage or disability as a result of inequality of bargaining power.</sentence>
<sentence id="s679">Many, if not most, contracts are made between parties of unequal bargaining power and good conscience does not require parties to contractual negotiations to forfeit their advantages, or neglect their own interests ( ACCC v C.G.</sentence>
<sentence id="s680">Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd (2003) 214 CLR 51 at [11]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s681">Unconscientious exploitation of another's inability or diminished ability to conserve his or her own interests is not to be confused with taking advantage of a superior bargaining position ( ACCC v C.G.</sentence>
<sentence id="s682">Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd at [14]).</sentence>
<sentence id="s683">Notwithstanding that Riva, Moruben and Quadwest were all in default, that Moruben had no contractual entitlement to the discharge of the mortgages over the Moruben Road property in the absence of tender of all monies owing under the Moruben Mezzanine Agreement and had no contractual entitlement to redemption of the Moruben Equity Mortgage because the amount of the Net Project Profit could not be calculated, Mr Rose was seeking indulgences from the Lenders that would permit him to obtain an extension of the facilities granted to Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s684">He had no contractual entitlement to such an extension and therefore had to make concessions to the Lenders to obtain such a concession.</sentence>
<sentence id="s685">One of the terms that the Lenders dictated was the provision of personal guarantees by him.</sentence>
<sentence id="s686">While the situation may have been difficult for Mr Rose, and the Quadrant Group generally, it is not a situation that justifies a conclusion that the Lenders brought undue pressure or duress to bear on Mr Rose or Riva or that their conduct was in any way unconscionable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s687">As I have said, the Lenders contend that relief under the Contracts Review Act is precluded by the operation of s 6(2).</sentence>
<sentence id="s688">Clearly enough, the Loan Agreement Variation Deeds entered into by Riva were entered into in the course of the business carried on by Riva, namely, the development of the Chevron Island Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s689">However, Mr Rose was not personally engaged in the development of the Moruben Road Property, the Chevron Island Property or the Adelaide Terrace Property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s690">To the extent that those developments involved carrying on businesses, those businesses were carried on by Moruben, Riva and Quadwest respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s691">However, that is not an end of the matter.</sentence>
<sentence id="s692">It is clear that Mr Rose was engaged in an enterprise involving property development.</sentence>
<sentence id="s693">He described himself in his evidence in chief as a property developer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s694">He engaged in that activity through the instrumentality of the various limited liability companies that formed the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s695">As part of that activity, Mr Rose regularly gave personal guarantees in respect of the obligations of one or more of the companies in the Quadrant Group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s696">The Quadrant Group was an enterprise conducted by Mr Rose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s697">It is an enterprise that can fairly be characterised as a business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s698">I would be disposed to conclude that all of the Impugned Agreements were entered into in the course of that business.</sentence>
<sentence id="s699">However, it is not necessary for me to reach a conclusion on that question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s700">APPLICATION FOR LEAVE TO AMEND 
 Mr Rose claims to have rescinded the Impugned Agreements, either by a letter of 9 February 2007 written by his solicitors or by the filing of an amended statement of claim in the proceeding dated 15 August 2007.</sentence>
<sentence id="s701">The Lenders say that neither of those events constituted an effective rescission.</sentence>
<sentence id="s702">They also say that it is not possible for the Court to order rescission, or the setting aside, of the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s703">The Lenders say that there has been no rescission and there can be no rescission because of the impossibility of providing substantial restitutio in integrum to the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s704">Because of the benefits that accrued to Moruben and Riva on the one hand, and the corresponding detriment to one or other of the Lenders on the other hand, there may well be a real question as to whether restitutio in integrum could have been, or could be, provided by Riva and Mr Rose, even if duress or undue pressure, unconscionable conduct or unfairness were established.</sentence>
<sentence id="s705">In particular, a significant aspect of both the question of undue or unfair pressure or unconscionable conduct and the question of restitutio in integrum concerns the release of the guarantee given by Quadrant Properties of the obligations of Riva.</sentence>
<sentence id="s706">Those obligations were secured by the Milson's Point Mortgage and by personal covenants given by Mr Rose in the Milsons Point Mortgage to pay moneys owing by Quadrant Properties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s707">The significance of the guarantee by Quadrant Properties and the Milson's Point Mortgage is that, quite apart from the Impugned Agreements, Mr Rose was personally liable for the indebtedness of Riva prior to his accepting the terms of the letter of 8 December 2006.</sentence>
<sentence id="s708">His liability under the Milson's Point Mortgage exceeded the amount now owing under the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s709">At this stage I do not propose to deal with the question of whether restitutio in integrum was or is possible.</sentence>
<sentence id="s710">The question does not arise if there was no undue pressure brought to bear on Mr Rose and Riva, if there was no unconscionable conduct on the part of the Lenders that induced the execution of the Impugned Agreements and if no order ought to be made under Contracts Review Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s711">I have already referred to the absence from the proceeding of Moruben as a party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s712">Moruben secured an advantage, not only in relation to the discharge of the securities over its properties, including the Moruben Road Property, but also in having the net profit share capped at $300,000.</sentence>
<sentence id="s713">Thus, the question of restitutio in integrum may require an investigation of the final outcome of the development of the Moruben Road Property to determine whether the Net Project Profit exceeded the Internal Rate of Return as defined in the Moruben Equity Agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s714">In their written submissions, the Lenders asserted that rescission of the Impugned Agreements was not available to Mr Rose and Riva because it was not possible or practicable to put the Lenders substantially in the position they were in prior to entering into the Impugned Agreements.</sentence>
<sentence id="s715">Following some discourse between the parties on the question of who bore the onus of establishing that restitutio in integrum was either possible or not possible, Mr Rose and Riva sought leave to amend the Application in the proceeding, to seek additional relief by way of the taking of accounts and the conduct of an enquiry for the purpose of determining what order should be made to ensure restitutio in integrum , assuming the Court were disposed to make declarations that the Impugned Agreements had been rescinded or to make an order that they be rescinded, set aside or cancelled.</sentence>
<sentence id="s716">The leave was opposed by the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s717">Accordingly, at the completion of all submissions by both parties, I directed that Mr Rose and Riva serve on the Lenders a detailed outline of their contentions that, as at the respective dates at which they claimed to have effected rescission, they were in a position to provide restitio in integrum to the Lenders and that, as at the day on which any relevant Court order may be made, they will be in a position to provide restitio in integrum to the Lenders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s718">The parties subsequently jointly asked the Court to vacate that direction on the following basis: I have not yet expressed a view as to whether the former course is appropriate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s719">It may be that Mr Rose and Riva should be put to an election as to whether they wish to proceed with their application for leave to amend, even if they fail to make out any of the causes of action, against the possibility that, on appeal, a different result might ensure.</sentence>
<sentence id="s720">That is to say, if there are contentious matters that would need to be resolved, if the leave to amend were granted, the question of amendment should be dealt with before the final disposition of the proceeding at first instance.</sentence>
<sentence id="s721">Accordingly, if the application for leave to amend is to the dismissed, it will be dismissed on the basis that Mr Rose and Riva no longer wish to pursue it and it will not be open to them to pursue it in the event of a different result being obtained on appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="s722">CONCLUSION 
 It follows from what I have said that all of the claims made by Mr Rose and Riva must be dismissed and that there should be a judgment for the Lenders in the proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s723">It also follows that there should be judgment for the Lenders against Mr Rose on their cross-claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s724">In addition, injunctions should be granted restraining Mr Rose from breaching his covenants that he will not further encumber his property.</sentence>
<sentence id="s725">I shall direct the parties to bring in short minutes of the orders that would follow from my conclusions, including the precise calculation of the amount for which judgment should be entered, and the terms of relevant injunctions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s726">At the conclusion of the hearing, senior counsel for the Lenders indicated that, if the respondents were successful, an application for a special order for costs would be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s727">The parties agreed that, in the circumstances, it was preferable to defer the question of costs until after the Court's conclusions have been published.</sentence>
<sentence id="s728">Accordingly, I propose to fix a time for further argument on the questions of costs, in the light of the conclusions I have reached.</sentence>
<sentence id="s729">I certify that the preceding one hundred and seventy-eight (178) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Emmett.</sentence>
<sentence id="s730">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 1 April 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: AS Martin SC with MR Tyson Solicitors for the Applicants: HWL Ebsworth Counsel for the Respondents: JE Marshall SC with DFC Thomas Solicitors for the Respondents: Blake Dawson 
 Date of Hearing: 15-18 December 2008 and 9-11 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 1 April 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/304.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>