<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Worldwide Timber Traders Pty Ltd (ABN 93 009 384) v Brouwer (No 2) [2009] FCA 447 (5 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/447.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">moving for judgment on admissions made in open court</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">power of the court to enforce a settlement agreement</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">implied term that payment be within a reasonable time if no term stipulated in agreement</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">contract</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 BACKGROUND 
 The trial of this proceeding was originally listed for 7-9 April 2008 inclusive.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">On 1 April 2008, the respondents applied (without notice and without an affidavit in support), to adjourn the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">The applicant opposed the late motion to adjourn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The applicant's witnesses were ready.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">One had been booked to fly from Melbourne to Perth for the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The proceedings had been on foot since 2005.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The parties agreed that only one day rather than three was needed for the trial.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Witnesses for all the parties were available to give evidence on 9 April 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">On that basis I listed the matter for trial on 9 April 2008 to commence at an earlier time.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">On the morning the trial was to commence, the parties agreed to an adjournment to enable mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">The matters which follow are consequent on the outcome of the mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">MEDIATION AND AGREEMENT 
 The mediation ensued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">The details of the mediation are unknown to me except to the extent that they have been disclosed by the parties for the purposes of consideration of the applicant's motion for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">On 19 August 2008, the applicant moved for judgment consequent upon what was said to be an agreement reached during the mediation before a Deputy District Registrar of this Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The applicant was then represented by different solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The solicitor who then represented the applicant held a different understanding from that held by the solicitor for the respondents as to the terms of the agreement reached at the mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">The essential difference was whether there had been an agreement that the respondents would consent to a judgment being entered in favour of the applicant.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">ADMISSIONS 
 In the course of the hearing on 19 August 2008, I pointed out to the parties the threshold difficulty in my inquiring as to anything which transpired in the course of the confidential mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Notwithstanding that difficulty, the solicitor for the respondents, in open Court, and apparently on instructions made the following statements in relation to the agreement: 
 The agreement was reached that my client pays $17,500 in full and final settlement of the claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">So that is the case and I am making the concession in open Court ... 

 
He continued:
 
 The immediate term of the deed is that my clients pay the $17,500 ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">There was an agreement and I am conceding there was an agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">
 He stressed however, that there had not been agreement that judgment may be entered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">With that exception only, he accepted that the terms of the draft deed presented by the applicant's solicitors were acceptable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The applicant has treated the statements made by counsel for the respondents in open Court as being admissions as to the existence of an enforceable agreement and have sought to enforce payment under the agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Payment has not been forthcoming.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">THE MOTION 
 On 10 February 2009, the applicant requested that the Court enter judgment against the respondents for $17,500 --- the sum in respect of which the concession was made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">During the hearing on that date the solicitor for the respondents made further submissions as to the respondents' liability to pay the applicant the sum of $17,500 again, the only aspect not agreed was that the respondents had agreed to a judgment being entered against them for the sum of $17,500.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">I do not intend to attempt to go behind the confidentiality of the mediation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Notwithstanding the admission as to an agreement in principle having been reached, to inquire further into the mediation detail would be inappropriate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">POWER TO ENFORCE ADMITTED SETTLEMENT AGREEMENTS 
 By O 72 r 7 of the Federal Court Rules (the Rules) a mediation conference must be conducted as a structured process in which the mediator assists the parties by encouraging and facilitating discussion between the parties so that, amongst other things, if agreement is reached and the parties consent, the agreement can be included in a consent order under O 35 r 10 of the Rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">However, the applicant's motion for judgment is not based either on O 72 r 7 or O 35 r 10.</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">The applicant applies for judgment on the basis of the Court's power conferred by O 18 r 4 to pronounce judgment on the admissions made by the respondents' solicitor in open Court on 19 August 2008 and again on 10 February 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">Order 18 r 4 is in the same terms as O 33 r 4 of the Rules of the High Court of Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">Barwick CJ referred to that Rule in "Certina", Re Registered Trade Mark (1970) 44 ALJR 191 at 192 and 193.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">His Honour observed that admissions on which the Court may act include oral admissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">His Honour went on to say in "Certina" that the respondent's unequivocal admission was sufficient to support a judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">At the same time, his Honour emphasised that judgment on admissions is given only where an applicant makes out a clear and unanswerable case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Judgment is not given on admissions where a serious question of fact or law requires consideration: Greig &amp; Murray &amp; Co Ltd v Hutchinson (1889) 15 VLR 706.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">As observed in Maisey, G.W.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">&amp; Anor v. Mudgeeraba Village Estates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [1985] FCA 191 by Neaves J, the power which a rule such as O 18 r 4 of the Rules confers must be exercised with great caution though in a clear case a proper exercise of the power will obviate the delay involved in a hearing and will save unnecessary expense.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">Neaves J followed "Certina" 44 ALJR 191 and also observed that the power is clearly discretionary as indicated by the Court of Appeal in New South Wales in Termijtelen v Van Arkel (1974) 1 NSWLR 525.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">In that case, his Honour declined to exercise the discretion.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The applicant also submits that although there can be no doubt that the Court has jurisdiction to enter judgment on an admission, alternatively, it is open to the applicant to make a summary judgment application.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">It is argued that the Court can accede to such an application by the exercise of the Court's accrued and pendent jurisdiction as discussed in Darling Downs Investments Pty Ltd v Ellwood (1988) 18 FCR 510 and in We Two Pty Ltd v Shorrock (No 2) [2005] FCA 934 ; (2005) 220 ALR 749 per Finkelstein J at [14]-[19].</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">In We Two , Finkelstein J dealt with a submission that the Court had no jurisdiction to deal with the claim for relief arising out of a settlement agreement because the agreement was based on non-federal law which the Court has no jurisdiction to determine.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">However, his Honour was considering a submission that enforcing an agreement reached at settlement was beyond the Court's reach for it was a simple common law claim with no federal element.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">As his Honour observed, there is no doubt that when the Court exercises its federal jurisdiction it can also deal with accrued and pendent claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">His Honour continued at [15]-[19]: ...</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">If an action is compromised by terms of settlement those terms can be given effect by consent orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">If the settlement breaks down and the wronged party requires the assistance of the court to enforce the settlement so as to bring the litigation to its intended conclusion, the court can make the appropriate order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">It will make no difference if the enforcement of the settlement agreement is sought, as it is here, in the action itself or by a separate proceeding: compare Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 , 586 [1999] HCA 27 ; ; 163 ALR 270 at 312; [1999] HCA 27 at [141] - [142] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In each case the necessary federal element is in the "matter" or controversy the subject of the underlying action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">The position might be different if the terms of settlement travel far beyond the settlement of the action.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">Enforcement of the extended aspects may or may not be within the court's pendent jurisdiction and each case will have to be looked at separately.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">
 ... 
 It has always been the case that a court has jurisdiction on motion in the action to enforce terms of settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The practice dates back to the Chancery Court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">In Daniell's Chancery Practice, 8th ed, Stevens and Sons, London, 1914, vol 1, p 646, the practice was described in this way:
 
"When an action is compromised by agreement out of Court, it was formally necessary to institute an action for specific performance of the agreement in the event of any party refusing to carry it out.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">But since the Judicature Act such a compromise may be converted into an order of the Court upon a motion by any party interested and enforced like a judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">But a consent order, embodying a new agreement between the parties beyond the scope of the action, can only be enforced in a fresh suit, which is also the proper method of determining the validity of the compromise, if disputed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">"
 
 
 ... 
 The adoption of a summary procedure is apt in the current circumstances.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">The validity of the terms of settlement is not called into question.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">No contested question of fact need be decided.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">All that is required is to determine what the parties meant by the settlement agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">From start to finish this is a question of construction.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">RESPONDENTS' ARGUMENTS 
 The argument now advanced for the respondents is as follows: The agreement was reached at a mediation conference.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Secondly, although it was later publicly conceded that an agreement was reached, the concession was not unequivocal to the effect that there was a concluded and enforceable agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">Thirdly, the agreement was subject to the parties executing a formal deed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">Fourthly, to the extent that counsel maintained that the respondents did not agree to judgment being entered against the respondents for the agreed sum, the concession was qualified.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">To find there was a concluded and binding agreement, the Court would need to embark on an exercise that would involve, not only a decision on contested questions of fact but it would also need to look at what transpired at the mediation conference: (see We Two [2005] FCA 934 ; 220 ALR 749 (at [19])).</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">It is implicit in O 72 r 7(1)(b)(ii) that an agreement reached at a mediation conference can only be the subject of an order or a judgment if the parties consent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">As to the first submission, it is difficult to know precisely what is meant by this submission other than, presumably, that the negotiation giving rise to the reaching of the agreement was confidential.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">That is certainly so but that does not mean that an ultimate agreement which was admitted in open court (if it be an admission and an agreement) retains any such confidentiality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">The solicitor for the respondents was not obliged to admit to the existence of an agreement but seemed willing to do so other than to stress that it was not a term of the agreement that they consent to judgment being entered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">As to the second point, to the extent that agreement may not have been concluded, I can only infer as I put to counsel that this was because the time for payment had not been specified in the agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">As I understand it this was the aspect which was said to be unresolved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">In my view, a term was to be implied into the admitted agreement that the payment of $17,500 would be made by the respondents to the applicant within a reasonable period of time after being presented with a mutually acceptable deed recording the terms of the agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">As to the implication of a term as to reasonable time when the agreement provides no specificity concerning time for performance: see Laurinda Pty Ltd v Capalaba Park Shopping Centre Pty Ltd [1989] HCA 23 ; (1989) 166 CLR 623 , Louinder v Leis [1982] HCA 28 ; (1982) 149 CLR 509 and Perri v Coolangatta Investments Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 29 ; (1982) 149 CLR 537.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">THE DEED 
 It is the deed itself which manifests the difficulty.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">It is common ground that the parties were to execute a deed to reflect the terms of the settlement agreement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">A draft deed was presented to the respondents' solicitor but the deed was unacceptable as it contemplated execution of a minute of consent judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">It was explained in the course of a hearing before me on 19 August 2008 that the reference to judgment being obtained in the deed was the only 'sticking point' to use the term expressed by the respondents' solicitor.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">While it is certainly not for me to rewrite the bargain of the parties reached, it is not clear to me why a deed is necessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">As the reference in the deed to consenting to judgment was the only 'sticking point' when the matter was before me on 19 August 2008, I adjourned it for a few days to enable the parties to reach agreement on the terms so as to bring the matter back on so that final orders could be made.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Agreement was not reached and the applicant changed solicitors.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">In the absence of agreement, the new solicitors subsequently sought the additional relief which is the subject of these reasons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">CONCLUSION 
 Whether or not execution of a deed is superfluous, doing so was, nevertheless, on any account, part of the agreement reached by the parties.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">In light of the concession that the only difficulty in the draft deed relates to consenting to judgment, it will be an easy amendment to remove that requirement from the deed and to present it for execution.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">So far as I understand, that has never been done.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">The requirement that there be a deed recording the terms of settlement between the parties is not something I can ignore.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">I do not believe I can therefore at this stage give the applicant the judgment it seeks.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">I have said now on a number of occasions that given the small amount involved in this dispute the delay and costs in its reaching finalisation is most regrettable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">I would have thought the obvious way forward was to present a deed which did not include any reference to the respondents' consenting to judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">If the respondents then decline to execute the deed the matter can be reviewed but I would have thought at that stage the applicant would be in a much stronger position to move for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">For those reasons the application will have to be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">I do not presently propose making any orders for costs unless I am persuaded otherwise by submissions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">If there are to be submissions, they should not exceed two pages in length and are to be filed and served within 10 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">Therefore the orders I will make will be that: The application be dismissed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">Submissions in writing (if any) regarding costs are not to exceed two pages in length and are to be filed and served within 10 days.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">I certify that the preceding twenty-six (26) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice McKerracher.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">Associate: 
 
 
Dated: 5 May 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: MJ Hawkins 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mountains Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: E Carlose 
 Date of Hearing: 10 February 2009 
 
 Date of Final Written Submissions: 16 March 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 5 May 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/447.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>