<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union v Contract Blinds Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 572 (28 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/572.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">representative proceedings under part iva of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">whether court should approve settlement of proceedings under s 33v</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">applicable principles</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">settlement fair and reasonable, and in the interest of all claimants including group members</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">settlement approved</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 This is an application under s 33V of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) for the Court to approve the settlement of this proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application is made by a notice of motion dated 23 April 2009 and supported principally by three affidavits of Kelvin Andrew Reidy affirmed on 23 April, 24 April and 19 May 2009 respectively.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">Mr Reidy is a solicitor employed by the first applicant, the Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">The background to this proceeding is as follows.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">The first and second applicants commenced the proceeding as a representative proceeding under Part IVA of the Federal Court of Australia Act by an application and statement of claim filed on 27 February 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">The first and second applicants sued on their own behalf and as representative parties within the meaning of Part IVA of the Act on behalf of the persons named as the third to thirty-fifth applicants in the schedule attached to the application ("the group members").</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">The statement of claim alleged that: 
&#8226; The Union and the respondent, Contract Blinds Pty Ltd, were parties to the Furnishing Industry National Award 2003.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">&#8226; The second applicant and the group members were employed by Contract Blinds pursuant to contracts of employment that were subject to the terms of the Award.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">&#8226; Contract Blinds had breached the Award and the contracts of employment by underpaying the entitlements of the second applicant and the group members, occasioning loss and damage to them.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">Specifically, Contract Blinds had not paid a shift loading of 30% on the ordinary rate of pay to persons working shifts finishing after midnight and at or before 8.00am, as it was required to do under the Award.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Further, Contract Blinds was in breach of the contracts of employment as a result of a failure to pay the whole of the superannuation contributions to which the second applicant and the group members were entitled, because Contract Blinds had calculated superannuation contributions by reference to the underpaid wages.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">&#8226; Further, after the Union notified Contract Blinds of its failure to pay the 30% shift loading, in breach of the contracts of employment and s 792 of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth), Contract Blinds reduced the ordinary rate of pay of the second applicant and the group members and commenced to pay 30% shift loading on the reduced rate of pay.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">&#8226; Further, in breach of the contracts of employment and s 792 of the Workplace Relations Act , Contract Blinds unilaterally altered the shift arrangements worked by the second applicant and the group members.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">By way of relief, the applicants sought, amongst other things, orders for compensation under s 807(1)(b) of the Workplace Relations Act , orders for payments under s 719(6) of that Act, penalties under ss 807(1)(a) and 719 (1), and injunctive relief under 807(1)(c).</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">The respondent filed a defence dated 2 May 2008, which was subsequently amended.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">Particulars of pleadings and alleged loss and damage were given.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Discovery was completed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">On 14 November 2008, pursuant to ss 33J and 33X of the Federal Court of Australia Act , the Court approved the form of the Opt-Out Notice that was to be given to the group members in accordance with the process set out in the affidavits of Mr Reidy of 24 October 2008 and 12 November 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">These affidavits contemplated a process whereby the Opt-Out Notice was translated into certain languages for the benefit of the group members with first languages other than English.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">A copy of the Opt-Out Notice (with an appropriate translation) was to be given to the group members at a meeting called for this purpose.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">Interpreters were to be present to ensure that questions raised by the group members were conveyed to a solicitor also present at the meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">Any of the group members not attending the meeting was to receive the Opt-Out Notice (with an appropriate translation) by personal service.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">In an affidavit of 10 December 2008, Mr Reidy confirmed that these steps had been taken.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">The solicitor and interpreters in attendance at the meeting of group members also deposed to the course of that meeting.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">On 2 December 2008, one of the group members, Nestor Aguda, opted out of the representative proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">Subsequently, in an affidavit of 26 March 2009, Mr Reidy stated that there were nine additional persons not included in the proceeding who were members of the Union and employees of Contract Blinds with claims like those of the group members.</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">By agreement between the parties, the claims of these nine persons were included in a mediation conducted on 25 February 2009, as a result of which the dispute was resolved and a deed of settlement executed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">This deed was expressed to be subject to Court approval.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Steps were taken removing Nestor Aguda as a group member from the representative proceeding and adding the nine additional individuals to the group members.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">It is unnecessary to rehearse these steps here.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">On 24 April 2009, the Court approved the form of the Notice of Proposed Settlement to be given to the group members as required by ss 33X(4) and 33Y (2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">For the purpose of giving the Notice of Proposed Settlement, the Court approved a process similar to that previously used for giving the Opt-Out Notice.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">In an affidavit of 19 May 2009, Mr Reidy stated that each of the group members had been given a Notice of Proposed Settlement appropriately and in conformity with the Court's order.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">The Notice of Proposed Settlement allowed any of the group members to object to the settlement or the terms of settlement by filing a Notice of Objection with the Court by 19 May 2009.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">No objection was filed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">In an earlier affidavit of 23 April 2009, Mr Reidy informed the Court that the Union would not look to the second applicant or any of the group members for any amount as contribution towards its costs and would not seek an order under s 33ZJ of the Federal Court of Australia Act for reimbursement of its costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">Mr Reidy further said that the deed of settlement provided that: 
(a) Contract Blinds would pay a total of $280,000 by way of wages in settlement of the claims of the second applicant and the group members; and
 
(b) Contract Blinds would pay an additional $40,000 to the Union on account of its costs of the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Mr Reidy also set out the mechanism pursuant to which the $280,000 was to be distributed, including that Contract Blinds would pay half of the $280,000, less applicable taxes, within 24 days of the Court approving the settlement, and the balance within 4 months of the first payment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">I turn now to consider whether settlement of the proceeding ought to be approved under s 33V of the Federal Court of Australia Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">The relevant principles are now well settled: see, for example, Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Chats House Investments Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 250 at 258 per Branson J; Williams v FAI Home Security Pty Ltd (No 4 ) [2000] FCA 1925 ; (2000) 180 ALR 459 at 465-6 [19] per Goldberg J; Neil v P &amp; O Cruises Australia Ltd [2002] FCA 1325 at [6] - [7] per Weinberg J; Jarrama Pty Ltd v Caltex Australia Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1114 at [10] per Crennan J; Courtney v Medtel Pty Ltd (No 5) (2004) 212 ALR 311 at 317-8 [37]-[42] per Sackville J; Crawford v Bank of Western Australia Ltd [2005] FCA 949 at [16] - [21] per Lee J; Georgiou v Old England Hotel Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 705 at [18] per Young J; Darwalla Milling Co Pty Ltd v F Hoffman-La Roche Ltd (No 2) (2006) 236 ALR 322 at 332 [30] and [31] per Jessup J; and Haslam v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 897 at [17] --- [20] per Gordon J.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">The Court must assess whether the proposed settlement is fair and reasonable, having regard to the claims made on behalf of the group members who will be bound by the settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">In making this assessment, the Court may, and ordinarily will, take into account the amount offered to the group members, the prospects of success in the proceeding, the likelihood of the group members obtaining judgment for an amount significantly in excess of the amount nominated in the settlement offer, the terms of any advice from counsel and any independent expert, the likely duration and cost of the proceeding if continued to judgment, and the attitude of the group members to the settlement: see Williams v FAI Home Security [2000] FCA 1925 ; 180 ALR 459 at [19] .</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">The Court must also be satisfied that the settlement has been made in the interests of the group members as a whole, and not merely the interests of the first and second applicants and the respondent: see ACCC v Chats House 71 FCR at 258.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Counsel for the applicants has submitted that the proposed settlement is fair and reasonable, having regard to the claims made on behalf of the group members, and should therefore be approved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">The respondent indicated its agreement with the orders proposed by the applicants.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">In his affidavit of 23 April 2009, Mr Reidy deposed that, based on the agreed amount of settlement, the second applicant and the group members would recover 85.15% of their claims.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">An opinion of senior and junior counsel concerning the settlement was exhibited to Mr Reidy's affidavit as a confidential exhibit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">This opinion was supportive of the settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">All group members have been appropriately notified of the settlement and none have made an objection to it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">Mr Reidy deposed to having answered a query raised by the group members with the second applicant (who is shop steward for the Union at Contract Blinds), noting that no further query had been forthcoming.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">I have considered various factors bearing on the settlement, including: (1) the claims made by the applicants for themselves and on behalf of the group members, including the quantum of the claim made on behalf of each of the group members; (2) the prospects of success as best they may be divined, particularly from the nature of the claims and the pleadings; (3) the opinion of counsel and the affidavits of Mr Reidy; (4) the likely complexity, duration and cost of proceeding to trial plus the anxiety for all concerned; (5) the usual risks and delay associated with proceeding to trial and judgment; (6) the settlement mechanism for claim quantification and the absence of any objection by any group member; and (7) the favourable settlement amount against the total sum claimed, being about 85.15%.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">This last-mentioned factor is a most important one, and weighs heavily in favour of the approval of the settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">Some other considerations also support the settlement; and others might be thought neutral.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">None can be said to weigh very much against the settlement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">I am satisfied that the settlement is fair and reasonable and in the interest of all claimants, including the group members as a whole.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">The settlement should therefore be approved.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Accordingly, I approve the settlement of this proceeding pursuant to s 33V of the Federal Court of Australia Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">I certify that the preceding seventeen (17) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Kenny.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 28 May 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: Dr Hanscombe SC and Mr S Moore 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Constructions Forestry Mining and Energy Union 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Ms V Sadler of Cornwall Stodart 
 Date of Hearing: 28 May 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 28 May 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/572.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>