<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jemella Australia Pty Ltd v GHD Australia Direct Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 599 (29 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/599.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">trade marks</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">infringement of trade marks</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">determining an account of profits</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">default of appearance by respondent</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c4">imperfect evidentiary foundation as to profits</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c5">court to take pragmatic approach in assessing profits</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c6">trade marks act (cth) ss 126, 127</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c7">costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c8">whether costs should be fixed in a gross sum</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c9">whether reasonable to fix costs without giving applicant an opportunity to be heard or detailed rationale in advance of amount sought</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c10">respondents not given notice by applicant of intention to fix costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c11">costs sought based on time costing</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c12">held costs should be taxed not fixed</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c13">federal court rules (cth) o 62 r 4(2)</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c14">intellectual property</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c15">practice and procedure</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 This is a sequel to orders that I made on 12 September 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">At that time I gave judgment by default to the Applicant, Jemella Australia Pty Ltd (Jemella Australia), in respect of its claim for the infringement of a registered trademark of which, at the time, it had a licence from the owner of that mark, Jemella Limited, the Fifth Respondent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">These reasons should be read in conjunction with those which I gave at the time when the default judgment was entered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">By orders made that day the Respondents, other than Jemella Limited, were directed to file affidavits directed to the subject of an assessment of damages or an account of profits at the election of Jemella Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Today is the day appointed for the hearing of assessment of damages or an account of profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">I am satisfied, on the material before me, that each of Mr John Gubecka, the Second Respondent, Ms Anne-Marie Rachel La Porta, the Third Respondent, and Mr Damon Jakin, the Fourth Respondent, have been given notice of today's date, being the appointed date for hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">As it transpires, the solicitors acting for those individuals have had their instructions withdrawn.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">None of those Respondents appeared today when the matter was called on.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">It seems to me, though, that they have been given proper notice of today's hearing.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">I, therefore, see no injustice in proceeding to hear the matter even though they have not appeared.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">Section 126 of the Trade Marks Act 1995 (Cth) (the Trade Marks Act ) provides materially: 
 The relief that a court may grant in an action for an infringement of a registered trademarks includes: 

 
 (a) ... 

 
 (b) At the option of the plaintiff, but subject to section 127 , damages or an account of profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">

 Section 127 of the Trade Marks Act is not pertinent to the present proceeding.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Of the options presented by s 126 , Jemella Australia has elected to claim profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">Its claim for profits is on the basis that the account of profits be taken in respect of what it submits is a joint and several liability on the part of the individual respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">I should record that in October 2008, following the default judgment, the First Respondent, GHD Australia Direct Pty Ltd (GHD Australia Direct), was deregistered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">The proceeding today, therefore, is for an account of profits as against Mr Gubecka, Ms La Porta and Mr Jakin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">Jemella Australia did alternatively seek nominal damages under s 126.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">It seems to me, though, that an election involves a choice as to one or the other and that, in effect, the choice is one for the person who has brought the action rather than for the court, having regard to the language in s 126(b).</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">Jemella Australia also seeks an order pursuant to O 62 r 4(2)(c) of the Federal Court Rules that its costs of the proceeding, including the costs of today's assessment, be fixed in a gross sum.</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">The case in respect of which default judgment was entered, as it emerged from the statement of claim, was this: 
(a) From about early 2007, the Respondents carried on a business of selling hairstyling products via the internet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s20">(b) The Respondents imported into Australia hairstyling irons and associated documents and packaging, hereafter the counterfeit irons, bearing the GHD trademark without consent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s21">(c) The Respondents advertised for sale and sold the counterfeit irons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s22">(d) The Respondents have infringed the GHD trademark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s23">(e) The Respondents have earned profits as a result of the infringement of the trademark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s24">Apart from damages under the Trade Marks Act an assessment of damages was also sought under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (Trade Practices Act).</sentence>
<sentence id="s25">My attention has been drawn to what appears to be a slip in the orders made on 12 September 2008, in that in para 1(j) there is a reference to s 82 of the Trade Marks Act , which should be instead a reference to the Trade Practices Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s26">I direct that order be amended accordingly.</sentence>
<sentence id="s27">Of the Respondents, two, Mr Gubecka and Mr Jakin, have filed affidavits pursuant to the orders made on 12 September.</sentence>
<sentence id="s28">Ms La Porta has not, but I note that Mr Gubecka deposes to his affidavit being the subject of authorisation by her to make it on her behalf as well.</sentence>
<sentence id="s29">I am satisfied, therefore, that each of the individual respondents has complied with the order made on 12 September 2008.</sentence>
<sentence id="s30">In Liquideng Farm Supplies Pty Ltd v Liquid Engineering 2003 Pty Ltd (2009) 79 IPR 437, a Full Court of this Court considered the subject of the taking of an account of profits under the Trade Marks Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="s31">That case is particularly pertinent in that it, too, was decided against the background of what one might term an imperfect evidentiary foundation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s32">To describe the evidence in the present case in relation to the profits as imperfect is, in no way, to voice a criticism of Jemella Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s33">It has done the best it can to adduce evidence on that subject and further to secure, by court order, affidavits from those whom one might think know rather more on that subject.</sentence>
<sentence id="s34">The result, nonetheless, is an imperfection in terms of allowing a precise assessment of an account of profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="s35">There are some principles which emerge from Liquideng (2009) 79 IPR 437 which are pertinent.</sentence>
<sentence id="s36">They are these: 
(a) In determining an account of profits the court must do the best it can on the whole of the material before it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s37">Mere speculation or guesswork is not generally appropriate.</sentence>
<sentence id="s38">Some foundation is needed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s39">Nonetheless, the exercise of taking an account of profits calls for an allowance to be made for a lack of precision where evidence before the court is incomplete, inexact and generalised.</sentence>
<sentence id="s40">(b) A pragmatic approach is the correct approach to take.</sentence>
<sentence id="s41">The court should take into account the evidence before it, at least insofar as it provides indicators, limited though, they may be, as to the proper figure, rather than simply taking an open-ended approach and settling upon gross sales.</sentence>
<sentence id="s42">(c) Where the evidence before the court gives some indications as to an appropriate figure, the proper approach is for the court to proceed and do the best it can, on the basis of what is before the court.</sentence>
<sentence id="s43">Where it's not possible to calculate a figure, the court should give the benefit of the doubt to the holder or authorised user of the registered mark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s44">That is because knowledge of precise costs is in the hands of the infringer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s45">That said, simply to treat gross revenue as profits with an arbitrary discount, where the evidence suggested that there were costs, would be contrary to principle, even allowing for assessment being an inexact science.</sentence>
<sentence id="s46">(d) No allowance should be made in respect of wages incurred by, or on behalf of the infringer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s47">An infringing party ought not be permitted to have the benefit of remuneration or directors fees for carrying on its infringing activities.</sentence>
<sentence id="s48">I approach the taking of the account of profits in this case on these bases.</sentence>
<sentence id="s49">The evidence before me proves, in my opinion, that the registered mark, GHD, has become well-known, and associated with hairstyling products of a particular good repute and quality.</sentence>
<sentence id="s50">That being so, remarks made by Windeyer J in Colbeam Palmer Limited v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25 are pertinent: 
 All profits made by an infringer by selling goods of that kind under that name may in some cases be said to be attributable to his use of the mark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s51">In cases of that sort the buyer of the goods is taken to have bought them because of the mark under which they were sold.</sentence>
<sentence id="s52">If that mark was for him an inducement, not necessarily the sole inducing cause of his buying the goods, the infringing seller is accountable to the owner of the mark for the profit he made by the sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s53">
 Those sentiments apply equally in respect of a claim by an authorised licensee of the registered mark.</sentence>
<sentence id="s54">There is not an exact correspondence as between the affidavits of Mr Gubecka and Mr Jakin as to the number of counterfeit irons imported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s55">Mr Gubecka's evidence is that 175 counterfeit irons were imported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s56">Mr Jakin's evidence is that, to the best of his recollection, in the period of his involvement in the ordering and sale of the counterfeit irons about 160 were purchased.</sentence>
<sentence id="s57">Of the two, Mr Gubecka appears to have had the greater involvement in the activities of GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s58">I note that it is to his affidavit that invoices from a Chinese company, Mount Rise Limited, in respect of the sale of the counterfeit irons, are exhibited.</sentence>
<sentence id="s59">Further, on the face of those invoices, the buyer is shown as Mr Gubecka, rather than Mr Jakin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s60">I accept that Mr Jakin has done the best he can from his recollection, but it is a recollection that is unassisted by documentation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s61">Further, the disparity may well be attributable to Mr Jakin's later cessation of involvement in the activities of GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s62">For those reasons it seems to me preferable to act, for the purposes of assessment, on Mr Gubecka's evidence as to the number of counterfeit irons imported.</sentence>
<sentence id="s63">The attempted importation itself was an infringement of the registered mark by use.</sentence>
<sentence id="s64">There has been a subsequent and further infringement in the sale of the counterfeit irons, manifesting that the importation was for the purposes of sale.</sentence>
<sentence id="s65">Mr Gubecka's evidence is that the price at which the counterfeit irons were sold --- and all of them were --- was between AUD$205 and AUD$240.</sentence>
<sentence id="s66">That range corresponds with the recollection of Mr Jakin in part.</sentence>
<sentence id="s67">His recollection is that the range was $190 to $230 with a "buy it now" price of $215.</sentence>
<sentence id="s68">Again, though, Mr Jakin's affidavit attesting to that range is unassisted by documentation of GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s69">I prefer Mr Gubecka's evidence in that regard.</sentence>
<sentence id="s70">Again, that is not to say that I am, in any way, critical of Mr Jakin.</sentence>
<sentence id="s71">His recollection is certainly close to the greater precision that Mr Gubecka is able to give.</sentence>
<sentence id="s72">Jemella Australia submits that given that there is a range of sale prices before me, that it is appropriate to adopt an average of $222.50 per unit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s73">The giving of greater precision as to the precise cost of sale of each unit is a subject uniquely in the hands of those individual respondents involved in the activities of GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s74">In those circumstances, it seems to me, consistent with principle as recited by the Full Court in Liquideng (2009) 79 IPR 437, to give the benefit of the doubt to Jemella Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s75">It also seems to me that in so doing, a fair approach is to adopt the average submitted as appropriate by Jemella Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s76">Jemella Australia accepts, correctly, with respect, that on the taking of an account, allowance must be made for the cost of purchasing the counterfeit irons including, in that regard, the telegraphic transfer fee in respect of purchase costs as evident in the material exhibited to Mr Gubecka's affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s77">Adopting then the average approach, and allowing for purchase costs, it is possible to tabulate an amount of profit per unit in respect of the 175 counterfeit irons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s78">'Schedule A --- Calculation of Profits' to Jemella Australia's submissions which provides that tabulation is annexure "A" to the reasons for judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s79">That tabulation is cast on the sales at the minimum of $205, the maximum of $240 per unit, and then gives a median sale, or what I have termed an average.</sentence>
<sentence id="s80">The end result of that, if one looks to that average, is a profit of $12,786.</sentence>
<sentence id="s81">There are some indications of other costs associated with the sale of the units, apart from the cost of their purchase and associated telegraphic transfer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s82">Business activity statement data is exhibited to Mr Gubecka's affidavit.</sentence>
<sentence id="s83">Further, from other affidavit evidence read, it is apparent that the units concerned were promoted by the use of the internet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s84">It is not possible, in the absence of an explanation from any of the individual respondents, particularly Mr Gubecka, to give any precision at all to how much of the expenses set out in the business activity statements ought properly to be regarded as attributable to the sales of the counterfeit irons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s85">Again, that is a subject uniquely within the province of those behind GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s86">I apprehend though, from Liquideng (2009) 79 IPR 437, that I ought, in the face of some indications on the affidavit material before me of additional expenses, at least to make some allowance for those as best I can.</sentence>
<sentence id="s87">Postage and handling is one, but this seems to be incorporated, in any event, into the cost of sales, so I do not propose to make any allowance for that.</sentence>
<sentence id="s88">Another, though, are internet costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s89">There may well also be some costs associated with the transporting of the counterfeit irons to the post office, although these would seem necessarily to be modest.</sentence>
<sentence id="s90">I make that observation because it seems, on the evidence, that there were bulk dispatches of counterfeit irons, rather than numerous individual trips.</sentence>
<sentence id="s91">There must also have been some cost of storage although, again, how much should be allowed in that regard is moot.</sentence>
<sentence id="s92">I note that Mr Jakin deposes that the business was conducted from the residence of Mr Gubecka and Ms La Porta, who is Mr Gubecka's partner.</sentence>
<sentence id="s93">It seems to me that it gives recognition to the indications and to principle to allow some additional amount then per unit in respect of costs, other than labour costs, associated with the sale of the counterfeit irons.</sentence>
<sentence id="s94">Doing the best I can, albeit at the expense of precision, I propose to allow $10 per unit, by way of what one might term "incidental costs" to recognise expenses such as advertising, storage and costs of transport to post office.</sentence>
<sentence id="s95">These fall for deduction from the tabulated amount of $12,786.</sentence>
<sentence id="s96">In total, the incidentals amount to $1750.</sentence>
<sentence id="s97">That then leaves a net amount of $11,036.14.</sentence>
<sentence id="s98">It seems to me that this is the amount to allow by way of an account of profits in respect of the infringements, the subject of default judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s99">The question then becomes, should each or any of the individual respondents be held liable for the amount of profits assessed?</sentence>
<sentence id="s100">On the evidence, GHD Australia Direct was effectively the alter-ego of Mr Gubecka and Ms La Porta.</sentence>
<sentence id="s101">Ms La Porta was nominally sole director, secretary and shareholder.</sentence>
<sentence id="s102">However, it is quite apparent, on the evidence, that Mr Gubecka had operational responsibility for the activities of GHD Australia Direct.</sentence>
<sentence id="s103">The case is one where it has been pleaded, and default judgment has been entered, on the basis that the respondents were jointly and severally liable.</sentence>
<sentence id="s104">Mr Jakin's involvement is more passing than that of Mr Gubecka and Ms La Porta, but it is not an insignificant involvement.</sentence>
<sentence id="s105">It is apparent, from his own affidavit, that he was a participant in the plan to bring the counterfeit irons into Australia and to market them via the internet.</sentence>
<sentence id="s106">It is significant that he does not depose to having received nothing from the enterprise.</sentence>
<sentence id="s107">There has been no application by, or on behalf of any of the individual respondents to set aside the default judgment.</sentence>
<sentence id="s108">In those circumstances, it seems to me that I should regard GHD Australia Direct as the alter-ego of each, in conformity with the case pleaded and in respect of which judgment by default was entered.</sentence>
<sentence id="s109">An assessment of damages under the Trade Practices Act would yield no different or better result for Jemella Australia.</sentence>
<sentence id="s110">There remains then, a question as to whether costs should be fixed?</sentence>
<sentence id="s111">I do have evidence before me as to the amount of costs which have been incurred as between solicitor and client and by way of disbursements including, in that regard, counsel's fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s112">That evidence also goes to the extent of providing some guidance from an experienced solicitor as to the amounts that one might expect would be allowed on a party and party taxation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s113">Having said that, and without descending to the detail, the overall amounts do seem to me to be rather large, both in respect of solicitor's costs and counsel's fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s114">It may, though, do something of an injustice to Jemella Australia to proceed on that basis and fix costs that are reasonable, in my opinion, without giving Jemella Australia a detailed opportunity to be heard in relation to costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s115">The appropriate way in which such an opportunity is afforded is by way of a direction for costs to be taxed.</sentence>
<sentence id="s116">That then allows the detailed explanation to be given to an officer of the court who is familiar with the process of taxation.</sentence>
<sentence id="s117">In making that observation, I have also taken into account that the costs of both solicitor and counsel seem to have been formulated on a time costing basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="s118">I have nothing to suggest, and certainly do not infer, that that was anything other than a way that was authorised as between solicitor and client.</sentence>
<sentence id="s119">Nonetheless, time costing can be conducive to inefficiency.</sentence>
<sentence id="s120">I deliberately use the word "can" in that regard, because, again, the subject is one which ought properly to be explored, in fairness to Jemella Australia and also to the respondents, with the court's taxing officer.</sentence>
<sentence id="s121">Another matter which I take into account in deciding that it is just to direct that costs be taxed rather than fixed is that the individual respondents have not been given notice, either of an intention to seek a fixing of costs, or of a detailed rationale upon which a particular sum was to be promoted to the court as to the reasonable sum to fix in respect of costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s122">I accept fully that there is a convenience associated with a fixing of costs, but, equally, it seems to me that, in fairness both to Jemella Australia and the respondents, this is not a case where I ought to proceed to fix costs today.</sentence>
<sentence id="s123">I certify that the preceding thirty-nine (39) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan.</sentence>
<sentence id="s124">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 5 June 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Ms J Payne 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: McInnes Wilson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: No Appearance by the Respondents 
 Date of Hearing: 29 May 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 29 May 2009 
 SCHEDULE A --- CALCULATION OF PROFITS 
 
 SALES COST OF SALES PROFIT No of units Sales @ $205 per unit Sales @ $240 per unit Median sales # Cost as per invoices (USD) Total cost AUD* Cost per unit (AUD) Profit @ $205 per unit Profit @ $240 per unit Profit @ Median # 13 $ 2,655.00 $ 3,120.00 $ 2,892.50 $ 1,750.00 $ 2,225.53 $ 171.19 $ 439.47 $ 894.47 $ 666.97 80 $ 16,400.00 $ 19,200.00 $ 17,800.00 $ 9,900.00 $ 11,902.50 $ 148.78 $ 4,497.50 $ 7,297.50 $ 5,897.50 14 $ 2,870.00 $ 3,360.00 $ 3,115.00 $ 1,900.00 $ 2,258.13 $ 161.30 $ 611.87 $ 1,101.87 $ 856.87 68 $ 13,940.00 $ 16,320.00 $ 15,130.00 $ 8,500.00 $ 9,765.20 $ 143.61 $ 4,174.80 $ 6,554.80 $ 5,364.80 175 $ 35,875.00 $ 42,000.00 $ 38,937.50 $ 22,050.00 $ 26,151.36 $ $ 9,723.64 $ 15,848.64 $ 12,786.14 
 
 NOTES: 
 
 # $222.50 per unit 
 
 * As per blank transfer requests, includes transfer fees.</sentence>
<sentence id="s125">
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/599.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>