<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Leonie's Travel Pty Limited v International Air Transport Association (No 3) [2009] FCA 767 (21 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/767.html</AustLII>
<catchphrases>
<catchphrase "id=c0">exercise of discretion to award costs</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c1">necessary participation in proceedings</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c2">costs follow the event</catchphrase>
<catchphrase "id=c3">costs</catchphrase>
</catchphrases>
<sentences>
<sentence id="s0">
 These representative proceedings concern a dispute over the alleged failure of the respondents to treat a fuel surcharge as part of the applicable fare for the purpose of calculating the commission to be paid to the applicant and members of the group.</sentence>
<sentence id="s1">The application proceeded to final hearing in relation to the liability of the second respondent and was dismissed as against the second respondent: Leonie's Travel Pty Ltd v International Air Transport Association (No 2) [2009] FCA 646.</sentence>
<sentence id="s2">This brief judgment concerns an outstanding issue in relation to the costs of the first respondent, the International Air Transport Association (IATA).</sentence>
<sentence id="s3">When the proceedings were commenced, the applicant brought them against IATA as well as a number of individual airlines.</sentence>
<sentence id="s4">Ultimately the applicant accepted that it was unnecessary to maintain the proceedings against IATA and the proceedings against it were discontinued.</sentence>
<sentence id="s5">IATA seeks its costs but the applicant submits that each party should bear their own costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s6">It is unnecessary to rehearse the details of the submissions made in support of these competing positions.</sentence>
<sentence id="s7">Having commenced the proceedings against IATA unnecessarily, the applicant should, in the ordinary course, pay IATA its costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s8">The only point of possible substance telling against such an order, is that some of those costs were said to have been incurred unnecessarily.</sentence>
<sentence id="s9">That is, IATA participated, it was submitted, in the proceedings at a time when it was apparent the proceedings would not continue against it.</sentence>
<sentence id="s10">However I do not accept the IATA's participation was, at any relevant point, unnecessary.</sentence>
<sentence id="s11">It is true that the solicitors for the applicant informed IATA in late February 2007 and before the discontinuance, that there would be a discontinuance if the other respondents raised no point about the non-joinder of IATA.</sentence>
<sentence id="s12">Ultimately the applicant secured that commitment from the other respondents.</sentence>
<sentence id="s13">However the intimation in late February 2007 was obviously conditional.</sentence>
<sentence id="s14">While there may be cases where, in analogous circumstances, a party continuing to participate in the proceedings ought not get their costs, this is not such a case.</sentence>
<sentence id="s15">IATA was, in my opinion, entitled to continue to participate in the proceedings having been joined as a party.</sentence>
<sentence id="s16">IATA should have its costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="s17">Accordingly I will order that the applicant pay IATA's costs of the proceedings.</sentence>
<sentence id="s18">I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Moore .</sentence>
<sentence id="s19">Associate:
 
 
Dated: 21 July 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: B Coles QC and N Beaumont 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Slater &amp; Gordon 
 Counsel for the First Respondent E Muston Solicitor for the First Respondent Minter Ellison Date of Last Written Submissions: 23 May 2007 Date of Judgment: 21 July 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/767.html 
 
 </sentence>
</sentences>
</case>