<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Koosasi v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1260 (21 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1260.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hope v Bathurst City Council [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/16.html</AustLII>
<text>The material before this Court includes the respondent's statement of facts and contentions before the Tribunal. This document at [27] advanced the contention that 'Great Bamboo Pty Ltd was not an eligible business because it was not a business in the necessary sense' . In support of this contention it made reference to Mason J's consideration in Hope v Bathurst City Council [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 of the meaning of 'business' in a phrase such as 'carrying on a business' . There his Honour stated that in the context of the rating provisions of the Local Government Act 1919 (NSW) the phrase 'carrying on a business' denoted activities 'engaged in for the purpose of profit on a continuous and repetitive basis' (at 8-9). The respondent's statement of facts and contentions before the Tribunal argued that Mr Koosasi's business did not appear 'to have been carried out on an ongoing or repetitive basis' .

At [28] the same document advanced the alternative contention that Great Bamboo was not an eligible business because it did not meet any of the requirements listed in the definition of 'eligible business' in s 134(10). In support of this contention the document made reference to the absence of evidence that Mr Koosasi had developed business links with the international market. It also noted that Great Bamboo had not created and was unlikely to create employment, that it had not introduced new or improved technology into Australia nor had it increased commercial activity or competitiveness in the Australian economy.

At [39] of its written reasons for decision the Tribunal conflated the two submissions of the respondent identified above, noting: 
 
 'The respondent also submits that the business is not an "eligible" business as it has only completed four export transactions since its registration in January 2003 and such limited number could not be considered continuing or repetitive ... there is no evidence the company has developed links with international markets; and the company has not created employment; exports of wheat, flour and juice has not introduced any new or improved technology to Australia.' (a reference to authority omitted)</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>