<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wearne v Southern Cross University [2006] FCA 1033 (11 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1033.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Berbatis [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 169 ALR 324</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/2.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Paragraphs 105-109 of the Statement of Claim will be struck out on the ground that they do not disclose a reasonable cause of action. Nonetheless I consider it appropriate that Dr Wearne be granted leave to replead, should she be so advised, the alleged contravention of s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act. The phrase 'conduct that is unconscionable within the meaning of the unwritten law, from time to time, of the States and Territories' is not confined to conduct of the kind considered by Amadio (see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Berbatis [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 169 ALR 324 esp at [13]-[28]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Fox Symes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1071</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1071.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The power conferred on the Court by O 11 r 16 is to be exercised to ensure that a party complies with the rules of pleading ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Fox Symes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1071 ( 'Fox Symes' ) at [95]). Ordinarily the party should be given an opportunity to replead in accordance with the rules ( Fox Symes at [95]). However, if a party's pleading is repeatedly struck out, it may be inferred that the party is unable to plead a reasonable cause of action as required by the rules ( Fox Symes at [109]).

12 The principal rules of pleading are, for present purposes, to be found in Orders 11 and 12 of the FCRs. Order 11 r 2 provides:
 
 'Subject to these Rules 
 
 
 (a) a pleading of a party shall contain, and contain only, a statement in a summary form of the material facts on which the party relies, but not the evidence by which those facts are to be proved; 
 (b) paragraph (a) has effect subject to this Order and to Order 4 (which relates to commencement of proceedings) and to Order 12 (which relates to particulars).' 
 


Order 11 r 4 provides:
 
 'Where any document or spoken words are referred to in a pleading, it is permissible to state the effect of the document or spoken words without setting out the precise terms thereof.' 
 

Order 12 r 1(1) provides:
 
 'A party pleading shall state in the pleading or in a document filed and served with it the necessary particulars of any claim, defence or other matter pleaded by him.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian [1995] IRCA 660</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/irc/1995/660.html</AustLII>
<text>22 The University submitted that while an implied term of mutual trust and confidence is part of the law of the United Kingdom, there remains a question whether such a term may be implied by law in an Australian contract of employment. I accept that the law is not certain in this respect ( Heptonstall v Gaskin (No 2) (2005) 138 IR 103 at [22]-[23]). However, the implied term as pleaded (which does not involve mutual obligations) finds some support in Australian authorities ( Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian [1995] IRCA 660 Madgwick J's consideration of this issue was not disapproved by the Full Court on appeal in Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian Pty Ltd (1996) 142 ALR 144; Perkins v Grace Worldwide (Aust) Pty Ltd (1997) 72 IR 186). It would not be appropriate on the present motion to foreclose argument on the important question of whether an Australian employer has the implied obligation pleaded in par 10 of the Statement of Claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian Pty Ltd (1996) 142 ALR 144</tocase>
<text>22 The University submitted that while an implied term of mutual trust and confidence is part of the law of the United Kingdom, there remains a question whether such a term may be implied by law in an Australian contract of employment. I accept that the law is not certain in this respect ( Heptonstall v Gaskin (No 2) (2005) 138 IR 103 at [22]-[23]). However, the implied term as pleaded (which does not involve mutual obligations) finds some support in Australian authorities ( Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian [1995] IRCA 660 Madgwick J's consideration of this issue was not disapproved by the Full Court on appeal in Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian Pty Ltd (1996) 142 ALR 144; Perkins v Grace Worldwide (Aust) Pty Ltd (1997) 72 IR 186). It would not be appropriate on the present motion to foreclose argument on the important question of whether an Australian employer has the implied obligation pleaded in par 10 of the Statement of Claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/14.html</AustLII>
<text>34 I therefore conclude that Dr Wearne has not adequately pleaded a claim pursuant to s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act. It is therefore unnecessary for me to give detailed consideration to pars 107 and 108 of the Statement of Claim. I am, however, inclined to doubt that par 107 adequately pleads circumstances of 'special disadvantage' for the purpose of the unconscionable dealings doctrine expounded by the High Court in Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447 (' Amadio' ) esp per Mason J at 462.

35 Paragraphs 105-109 of the Statement of Claim will be struck out on the ground that they do not disclose a reasonable cause of action. Nonetheless I consider it appropriate that Dr Wearne be granted leave to replead, should she be so advised, the alleged contravention of s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act. The phrase 'conduct that is unconscionable within the meaning of the unwritten law, from time to time, of the States and Territories' is not confined to conduct of the kind considered by Amadio (see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Berbatis [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 169 ALR 324 esp at [13]-[28]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Concrete Constructions (NSW) Pty Limited v Nelson [1990] HCA 17 ; (1990) 169 CLR 594</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/17.html</AustLII>
<text>33 I accept, at least, that the argument that such conduct was 'conduct in trade and commerce' could not be characterised as clearly untenable (see, for example, Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501). However, par 106 does not plead that the relevant conduct was 'in trade or commerce' ; it is drawn on the apparent assumption that it is sufficient for the relevant contract to be in respect of trade or commerce. In Concrete Constructions (NSW) Pty Limited v Nelson [1990] HCA 17 ; (1990) 169 CLR 594 at 603 the High Court observed with respect to the identical expression in s 52 of the Trade Practices Act:
 
 'it is plain that s. 52 was not intended to extend to all conduct, regardless of its nature, in which a corporation might engage in the course of, or for the purposes of, its overall trading or commercial business. Put differently, the section was not intended to impose, by a side-wind, an overlay of Commonwealth law upon every field of legislative control into which a corporation might stray for the purposes of, or in connection with, carrying on its trading or commercial activities.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>13 As this proceeding was instituted before 1 December 2005, the power conferred on the Court by O 20 r 2 is to be exercised to ensure that a clearly untenable case that cannot possibly succeed does not proceed to trial ( General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125; Murex Diagnostics Australia Pty Limited v Chiron Corporation (1995) 55 FCR 194). The lower threshold of 'no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding' , for which s 31A(2)(b) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) now provides, has no application in respect of a proceeding instituted before 1 December 2005 (Item 44 of Part 2 of Schedule 1 of the Migration Litigation Reform Act 2005 (Cth)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Griggs v Noris Group of Companies (Including SA Helicopters Pty Ltd and Captured Pty Ltd) (2006) 94 SASR 126</tocase>
<text>23 The University further complained of Dr Wearne's failure to identify the basis upon which an implication of the kind which she alleges may be made. However, as I understand Dr Wearne's case, she will contend that the implied term presently pleaded in par 10 of the Statement of Claim is to be implied as a matter of law into every employment contract. She does not accept that the necessary implication depends upon the express terms of the contract and the actual intention of the parties (cf Griggs v Noris Group of Companies (Including SA Helicopters Pty Ltd and Captured Pty Ltd) (2006) 94 SASR 126). Again it would not be appropriate to foreclose argument on this important question.

24 Although par 10 of the Statement of Claim will be struck out for the reason identified in [21] above, it is appropriate that Dr Wearne be granted leave to replead the implied term. I am not satisfied that her case in this respect is clearly untenable.

25 The Statement of Claim does not plead as a material fact that the University breached the implied term in one or more specified ways and then particularise the specified breach or breaches. Rather the Statement of Claim provides a narrative of Dr Wearne's experiences as an employee of the University and her dealings with other employees of the University. The narrative concludes with par 111 of the Statement of Claim which opens as follows:
 
 'The respondent breached the term of the contract set out in paragraph 10 above in that the following conduct of the respondent, was, separately and cumulatively, calculated or likely to damage or destroy the relationship of trust and confidence between the parties: 
 
 ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Heptonstall v Gaskin (No 2) (2005) 138 IR 103</tocase>
<text>22 The University submitted that while an implied term of mutual trust and confidence is part of the law of the United Kingdom, there remains a question whether such a term may be implied by law in an Australian contract of employment. I accept that the law is not certain in this respect ( Heptonstall v Gaskin (No 2) (2005) 138 IR 103 at [22]-[23]). However, the implied term as pleaded (which does not involve mutual obligations) finds some support in Australian authorities ( Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian [1995] IRCA 660 Madgwick J's consideration of this issue was not disapproved by the Full Court on appeal in Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian Pty Ltd (1996) 142 ALR 144; Perkins v Grace Worldwide (Aust) Pty Ltd (1997) 72 IR 186). It would not be appropriate on the present motion to foreclose argument on the important question of whether an Australian employer has the implied obligation pleaded in par 10 of the Statement of Claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Murex Diagnostics Australia Pty Limited v Chiron Corporation (1995) 55 FCR 194</tocase>
<text>13 As this proceeding was instituted before 1 December 2005, the power conferred on the Court by O 20 r 2 is to be exercised to ensure that a clearly untenable case that cannot possibly succeed does not proceed to trial ( General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125; Murex Diagnostics Australia Pty Limited v Chiron Corporation (1995) 55 FCR 194). The lower threshold of 'no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding' , for which s 31A(2)(b) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) now provides, has no application in respect of a proceeding instituted before 1 December 2005 (Item 44 of Part 2 of Schedule 1 of the Migration Litigation Reform Act 2005 (Cth)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 204 ALR 26</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/3.html</AustLII>
<text>38 It is premature, in my view, to give detailed consideration to whether the Statement of Claim adequately pleads an appropriate nexus between the losses allegedly suffered by Dr Wearne and the relief claimed by her. I note, however, that the High Court observed with respect to the Trade Practices Act in Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 204 ALR 26 at [45] :
 
 'The Act's references to "loss or damage" can be given no narrow meaning. Section 4K of the Act provides that loss or damage includes a reference to injury. It follows that the loss or damage spoken of in ss 82 and 87 is not confined to economic loss. What kinds of detriment constitute loss or damage, when a detriment is to be identified as occurring or likely to occur, and what remedies are to be awarded, may all raise further difficult questions. Especially is that so when it is recalled that remedies may be awarded to compensate, prevent or reduce loss or damage that has been or is likely to be suffered by conduct in contravention of the Act.' (citation omitted)

39 I am not satisfied that Dr Wearne does not have a reasonable cause of action, or reasonable causes of action, against the University. The application for the proceeding to be dismissed or permanently stayed therefore fails.

40 However, I conclude that the Statement of Claim does not comply with the rules of pleading. Its deficiencies are so extensive that it would be counterproductive, in my view, for individual paragraphs or groups of paragraphs to be struck out. The Statement of Claim will therefore be wholly struck out. However, in my view it is appropriate that Dr Wearne have one final opportunity to plead her case against the University.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Perkins v Grace Worldwide (Aust) Pty Ltd (1997) 72 IR 186</tocase>
<text>22 The University submitted that while an implied term of mutual trust and confidence is part of the law of the United Kingdom, there remains a question whether such a term may be implied by law in an Australian contract of employment. I accept that the law is not certain in this respect ( Heptonstall v Gaskin (No 2) (2005) 138 IR 103 at [22]-[23]). However, the implied term as pleaded (which does not involve mutual obligations) finds some support in Australian authorities ( Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian [1995] IRCA 660 Madgwick J's consideration of this issue was not disapproved by the Full Court on appeal in Burazin v Blacktown City Guardian Pty Ltd (1996) 142 ALR 144; Perkins v Grace Worldwide (Aust) Pty Ltd (1997) 72 IR 186). It would not be appropriate on the present motion to foreclose argument on the important question of whether an Australian employer has the implied obligation pleaded in par 10 of the Statement of Claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501</tocase>
<text>33 I accept, at least, that the argument that such conduct was 'conduct in trade and commerce' could not be characterised as clearly untenable (see, for example, Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501). However, par 106 does not plead that the relevant conduct was 'in trade or commerce' ; it is drawn on the apparent assumption that it is sufficient for the relevant contract to be in respect of trade or commerce. In Concrete Constructions (NSW) Pty Limited v Nelson [1990] HCA 17 ; (1990) 169 CLR 594 at 603 the High Court observed with respect to the identical expression in s 52 of the Trade Practices Act:
 
 'it is plain that s. 52 was not intended to extend to all conduct, regardless of its nature, in which a corporation might engage in the course of, or for the purposes of, its overall trading or commercial business. Put differently, the section was not intended to impose, by a side-wind, an overlay of Commonwealth law upon every field of legislative control into which a corporation might stray for the purposes of, or in connection with, carrying on its trading or commercial activities.'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>