<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hamilton-Smith v George [2006] FCA 1551 (21 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1551.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth of Australia v Riley (1987) 5 FCR 8</tocase>
<text>80 In Commonwealth of Australia v Riley (1987) 5 FCR 8, the Full Court of this Court said, albeit in the context of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 (Cth) (at 34):
 
 'Counsel submitted that there were two other categories of material which should also be disregarded: evidence of conversations which is not in the form of direct speech and statements of conclusions of witnesses. We disagree. Section 26(1)(a) of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 deals with the form of evidence in a proceeding under the Act namely: 
 
 
 "a document, duly authenticated, that purports to set out testimony given on oath, or declared or affirmed to be true, by a person in a foreign state is admissible as evidence of the matter stated in the testimony". 
 
 
 That provision is wide enough to authorise the proof of the substance of a conversation by a narrative using indirect speech. There is nothing in the Treaty to limit the application of that provision in proceedings to which the Treaty applies; Article XI(3) merely requires the transmission of "such evidence, as according to the laws of the requested state, would justify his trial or committal for trial ...". The provision deals only with the sufficiency, not the form, of evidence. The rule that evidence of conversations shall be given in direct speech is, in Australia, a rule of practice rather than of law; a practice that is probably now disregarded as often as it is followed. To apply to affidavits prepared in another country the rules of mere practice of our own courts would be substantially to diminish the utility of the Act; cf R v Governor of Pentonville Prison; Ex parte Passingham [1983] 2 AC 464.'

83 In my opinion, there is a rule of practice at common law that requires a witness to recount the actual words used in a conversation if he or she is able to do that: Commonwealth of Australia v Riley (supra); LMI Australasia Pty Ltd v Baulderstone Hornibrook Pty Ltd (supra); J H Wigmore, 3 Wigmore on Evidence SS766 (Chadbourn rev 1970). If the witness is unable to recall the actual words used, he or she can give evidence of the substance or effect of what was said. A witness might say he or she cannot remember the actual words used. I think that as a matter of practice it is also open to the Court to infer that that is the case. I would be disposed to draw that inference in the case of the relevant paragraphs in Mr Gawronski's affidavit bearing in mind the lapse of time between the conversation and the swearing of the affidavit, the apparent length and complexity of the conversation and the fact that an actual word used is from time to time identified by quotation marks. However, I do not need to finally determine the point because I think the evidence is admissible by reason of the provisions of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>George v Hamilton-Smith (No 2) [2006] FMCA 1018</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/1018.html</AustLII>
<text>39 I turn now to examine the Federal Magistrate's reasons for judgment ( George v Hamilton-Smith (No 2) [2006] FMCA 1018). The Magistrate noted that the appellant was unsuccessful in having the bankruptcy notice issued by the respondent set aside. He referred to the proceedings between Bernsteen and the appellant. Those proceedings involved a claim by Bernsteen and a cross-claim by the appellant and had not yet come on for trial. The Federal Magistrate did not consider those proceedings to be of significance unless Bernsteen sought to be substituted for the respondent.

40 The Federal Magistrate outlined the events before the State Magistrate in the State Magistrates Court proceedings on 13 June 2006 and the circumstances leading to the entry of judgment against the appellant with costs. The Federal Magistrate discussed the arguments that the appellant said that she would put in favour of her (then) application for leave to appeal from the orders made by the State Magistrate. The Federal Magistrate described the appellant's submissions in the following way:
 
 'The debtor argues that the decision of the learned Magistrate was so clearly wrong and so clearly appellable that I should exercise my discretion not to make a sequestration order so that what he describes as the "very real dispute between the parties" can be allowed to be litigated. He argues that given the small amount of the judgment debt this would be the appropriate course of action to take because of the lengthy delay that may occur between now and the final determination of the dispute, assuming that the Supreme Court of South Australia allows his appeal. Alternatively, he asks that the court adjourn the hearing of the petition until the matter is decided.'

41 The Federal Magistrate said that the relevant paragraphs of Mr Gawronski's affidavit were put forward to prove that there was a 'secret agreement' between the respondent and the liquidator of Bernsteen. He rejected the tender of the relevant paragraphs of Mr Gawronski's affidavit (ie, paragraphs 13.1 to 13.5 inclusive) because the paragraphs were not 'in proper form because the conversations deposed to were not set out in direct speech but consisted of a summary of the conversation'. The Federal Magistrate said that there was insufficient evidence that the creditor's petition was brought for an improper or collateral purpose.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>George v Hamilton-Smith [2006] FMCA 566</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/566.html</AustLII>
<text>28 The respondent applied for a review of the Registrar's decision to adjourn the hearing of the creditor's petition to 5 June 2006. On the review Federal Magistrate Raphael upheld the Registrar's decision to adjourn the hearing of the creditor's petition and in fact he altered the adjourned date from 5 June 2006 to 20 June 2006: George v Hamilton-Smith [2006] FMCA 566. The following passages from the Federal Magistrate's reasons of 21 April 2006 should be noted (at [4], [12] and [13]):
 
 
 '4. The debtor claims she is solvent. She says that she has tendered payment of the petitioning creditor's debt and has a substantial cross claim against Bernsteen which would effectively nullify any debt that she has to that company. Bernsteen is not in a position to make any payment to her as it is a company in liquidation. She argues that another petitioning creditor, CFS, who had initially claimed a sum in excess of $20,000.00, has had its claim reduced to some $4,297.53 which has now been paid. What the debtor does not do is provide the court with any evidence about her financial circumstances. There is no affidavit indicating what real property she owns, what is the status of her bank accounts and what other assets are owned by her. There is no evidence of other creditors. There is no evidence that it was the debtor herself who paid the CFS debt or provided the funds for the tender to the petitioning creditor. This lack of evidence meant that Registrar Christie was unable to be satisfied that the debtor was solvent and I am likewise unable to be satisfied of her solvency. As Registrar Christie said in her judgment: 
 
 
 
 
 "The debtor has not put before me the strong and tangible evidence necessary to establish that she is able to pay all her debts as and when they fall due (see Weinberg J in Esanda Finance Corporation Limited v Velissaris [1999] FCA 1359 at [17] ." 
 
 
 
 
 ... 
 12. Even though the existence of the proceedings may not constitute sufficient cause to dismiss the sequestration order their existence might bear heavily upon an application for adjournment. We are now in April. The proceedings between the debtor and Bernsteen are set down for hearing in May. The proceedings between the debtor and the creditor are set down for hearing in early June. I have heard nothing about any additional creditors but I am aware that the debtor has obtained an order for security for costs in the sum of $6,000.00 against Bernsteen in respect of those proceedings. It is possible, given the existence of these proceedings, that Bernsteen could obtain a similar (and probably larger) order against the debtor if she was permitted to pursue her cross claim. 
 13. I have taken all these matters into account when considering whether or not to adjourn this petition. As much as there is a public interest in bringing petitions to finality and thus preventing the possibility of insolvent trading or the incurring of debts a bankrupt is unable to repay there is also the fact that the making of a sequestration order has quasi criminal consequences: Re A Judgment Debtor [1908] 3 K.B. 474. It puts severe restraints upon a bankrupt's freedom of movement and ability to do business and it is these effects which must be weighed by a court considering an adjournment rather than the prejudice to the debtor or the prejudice to the creditor as suggested by Registrar Christie at [27] of her judgment. In truth evidence on both of these matters is sorely lacking but I note that the debtor has not been totally unsuccessful in her previous litigious skirmishes, e.g. in reducing the CFS debt down to a manageable figure. I am of the view that whilst the current timetable for the forthcoming proceedings remains fixed with hearings in May and June the petition should be adjourned to allow those proceedings to be heard. But if the debtor is unable to mount her cross claim without a significant adjournment or if the claim against the creditor is delayed then the rationale for the adjournment of the petition (the speedy resolution of outstanding disputes) will no longer apply. Registrar Christie was unaware of the date of the hearing of the claim in the Magistrates Court between the creditor and the debtor but I have been informed that it is to take place on 13 June. I will adjourn the petition until 20 June 2006 but I will grant the parties liberty to apply so that in the event that these hearing dates are not kept to an application can be made for an earlier hearing. The petition and any such application will be returnable before Registrar Christie.'

29 On 20 June 2006 Registrar Christie heard and refused an application for discovery by the appellant which had only been filed the day before and she made the sequestration order which was reviewed by the Federal Magistrate.

30 On 5 July 2006 Federal Magistrate Raphael heard the application for review and on 19 July 2006 he made the sequestration order which is the subject of this appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>LMI Australasia Pty Ltd v Baulderstone Hornibrook Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 688 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 31</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/688.html</AustLII>
<text>81 In J D Heydon, Cross on Evidence (7 th ed, 2004) page 476, the following passage appears (footnotes omitted):
 
 'The limits of one restriction on the form of testimony should be noted. Witnesses are commonly interrupted as they endeavour to recount conversations in indirect speech, and urged to give the actual words used. This is a counsel of virtue, but it is questionable whether it is a rule of law. A witness may give the witness's best recollection of the substance, effect or purport of what was said, even though the exact words cannot be recollected, and the witness may also recount the impression made on the witness by whatever words were used. If so, it is hard to see why witnesses must be compelled into uttering untruths on oath by giving a form of words in direct speech with which they are not happy and which they cannot actually recollect in preference to their own words in indirect speech, so long as mere conclusions are avoided. "The rule that evidence of conversations shall be given in direct speech is, in Australia a rule of practice rather than of law; a practice that is probably now disregarded as often as it is followed". This is particularly so where the conversations took place a long time ago. Similarly, there is no provision in the Cth and NSW: Evidence Acts 1995 or the Tas: Evidence Act 2001 which makes inadmissible evidence of a conversation given in indirect speech, though the possibility of discretionary rejection under s 135 is available.' 
 

See also, LMI Australasia Pty Ltd v Baulderstone Hornibrook Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 688 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 31 at [8] - [9] .

82 In my opinion, by and large the relevant paragraphs fall within the second form referred to above. It would appear that the Federal Magistrate considered that the paragraphs fell within the third form (see his reference to a 'summary of the conversation') and, in so doing, in my respectful opinion, he erred. No doubt there appear to be one or two objectionable passages in the relevant paragraphs and I refer, for example, to the reference to the respondent bragging. Furthermore, the evidence is clearly only admissible against the respondent and is not admissible to prove Mr Macks' state of mind. Subject to those considerations, I think the evidence in the relevant paragraphs falls within the second form identified above and the only question is whether it should have been excluded because the appellant had not established by express evidence that Mr Gawronski could not give the evidence in direct speech. It would seem that that was not the basis upon which the Federal Magistrate excluded the evidence but it is a matter that needs to be considered.

83 In my opinion, there is a rule of practice at common law that requires a witness to recount the actual words used in a conversation if he or she is able to do that: Commonwealth of Australia v Riley (supra); LMI Australasia Pty Ltd v Baulderstone Hornibrook Pty Ltd (supra); J H Wigmore, 3 Wigmore on Evidence SS766 (Chadbourn rev 1970). If the witness is unable to recall the actual words used, he or she can give evidence of the substance or effect of what was said. A witness might say he or she cannot remember the actual words used. I think that as a matter of practice it is also open to the Court to infer that that is the case. I would be disposed to draw that inference in the case of the relevant paragraphs in Mr Gawronski's affidavit bearing in mind the lapse of time between the conversation and the swearing of the affidavit, the apparent length and complexity of the conversation and the fact that an actual word used is from time to time identified by quotation marks. However, I do not need to finally determine the point because I think the evidence is admissible by reason of the provisions of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Makhoul v Barnes (1995) 60 FCR 572</tocase>
<text>55 The fact that the Registrar determined this question against the appellant on the application to set aside the bankruptcy notice did not give rise to an issue estoppel preventing the appellant from raising the question again on the hearing of a creditor's petition: Makhoul v Barnes (1995) 60 FCR 572. However, the Court is not bound to allow the matter to be raised again and ordinarily the Court will accept that the judgment debt is still owing. In Makhoul v Barnes the Full Court of this Court said (at 582):
 
 'However, the Court has a discretion whether to make a sequestration order even where an act of bankruptcy has been committed. If the Court determines that the circumstances are such that the Court should go behind the judgment debt relied upon in a bankruptcy notice and having done so is not satisfied that there has been shown to be real consideration for it, it will, in the sense discussed above in the exercise of that discretion, dismiss the petition notwithstanding a proved act of bankruptcy. Where the Court has already investigated that question on an application to set aside the bankruptcy notice, it would no doubt rarely, if ever, do so again. But this is not because an issue estoppel has been raised. It is because the debt has already been investigated by the Court so that it would not be an appropriate case to revisit the matter. Rather, the Court would (at least ordinarily) accept the judgment as evidence of the debt.'

56 It is true that these remarks were made in the context of a claim to go behind a judgment debt, but I see no reason why they do not also apply in a case where the claim is that the judgment debt has been satisfied. I have read the transcript of submissions before the Federal Magistrate and it was not put to him that he should investigate and determine the question of whether there had been an accord and satisfaction. Furthermore, his reasons for judgment suggest that he was not asked to do this. He does refer to the reasons for judgment of Registrar Christie on the application to set aside the bankruptcy notice but this was in a different context, namely, in the context of considering the appellant's prospects of success in the State Magistrates Court proceedings.

57 I have given anxious consideration to whether the appellant should be able to raise this point on appeal. If she is, it is a point that cannot be determined by me. The matter would need to go back to a Federal Magistrate for determination of the point after hearing evidence in much the same way as the Registrar did when she heard the application to set aside the bankruptcy notice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Sarina; Ex parte Council of the Shire of Wollondilly (1980) 43 FLR 163; 48 FLR 372</tocase>
<text>60 Under s 52(2)(a) of the Act the Court may dismiss a creditor's petition if it is satisfied by the debtor that he or she is able to pay his or her debts. The onus of establishing that fact is on the debtor. The debtor must establish that he or she is able to pay his or her debts within a reasonable time. If a debtor establishes his or her ability to pay his or her debts then a sequestration order should not be made even if the debtor is unwilling to pay the debt which forms the basis of the petition: Re Sarina; Ex parte Council of the Shire of Wollondilly (1980) 43 FLR 163 per Deane J; (1980) 48 FLR 372 per Bowen CJ CA, Sweeney and Lockhart JJ. It is also true, as the appellant submitted, that a debtor with few or no assets and a modest income may have no difficulty in establishing an ability to pay his or her debts. At the same time a mere assertion of solvency or ability to pay debts may not be sufficient. A Court will assess the whole of the evidence and the fact that a debtor has not produced certain evidence relevant to his or her financial situation may be relevant to the question of whether the debtor has satisfied the onus of establishing the fact that the debtor can pay his or her debts.

61 In this case, the appellant's counsel conceded before the Federal Magistrate that he was not contending that the appellant could satisfy the Court that she was able to pay her debts. The relevant passage in the transcript of the submissions is in the following terms:
 
 'His Honour: Have you filed an affidavit giving us any idea what your client's financial circumstances are? 
 
 Mr Sallis: No your Honour. 
 His Honour: No, all right. 
 Mr Sallis: Therefore, I can't argue with you about solvency. 
 His Honour: No.'

62 That concession was made in the context of previous statements by the Registrar and the Federal Magistrate to the effect that the evidence of the appellant's financial circumstances was very limited. In my opinion, the concession made before the Federal Magistrate is an answer to the argument the appellant now seeks to put on the appeal. The Federal Magistrate would have been entitled to rely on the concession and simply to have noted that the submission that the appellant fell within s 52(2)(a) was not pressed. It was not a matter where the onus was on the petitioning creditor or one where the Court was under an obligation to investigate the matter; the onus was squarely on the appellant and it was open to her to abandon the point.

63 The appellant submitted that she is able to press the insolvency point on appeal because the Federal Magistrate did not rely on the concession. The focus of the Federal Magistrate's reasons is s 52(2)(b) of the Act and whether 'other sufficient cause' why a sequestration order ought not to be made had been established. He did say in the course of his reasons that although the appellant had asserted that she was able to pay her debts as and when they fell due, she had provided no evidence about her assets or liabilities. He referred to his observations in his reasons for judgment delivered on 21 April 2006 which are set out in [28] above.

64 It would not be proper to read the Federal Magistrate's reasons for judgment as if he had put the concession to one side. The concession was a concession that further evidence was required and yet had not been put forward and that, in those circumstances, the contention that the matter in s 52(2)(a) had been established could not succeed.

65 On appeal, the appellant's counsel submitted that no concession had been made or, alternatively, if it had it is irrelevant because the Magistrate did not rely on it. For the reasons I have given, I reject both of those submissions. It was not suggested that the concession was made by mistake or accident and that the appellant should be permitted to withdraw the concession on appeal for one or other of those reasons.

66 Even if I am wrong and the Federal Magistrate did not rely on a concession, in my opinion, a conclusion that the appellant had not established that she was able to pay her debts was a conclusion that was reasonably open to the Magistrate. The appellant's evidence consisted of, first, no more than assertion that she was solvent and able to pay her debts and, secondly, details relating to the claims of the respondent, CFS and Bernsteen. The evidence put forward by the appellant established the following:
 
 1. As at 6 April 2006 the appellant was working in a business and receiving an income of about $1,200 per week.
 2. The debt which she owed to CFS had been paid although there was no evidence as to the source of the moneys used to repay the debt.
 3. Bernsteen has a claim against the appellant for the sum of $29,068.55 and the appellant has a counterclaim against Bernsteen which she quantifies at a figure in excess of $50,000. There was no evidence as to the strength of either the claim or counterclaim and neither has come on for trial.
 4. Bernsteen has obtained orders for costs against the appellant. The making of those orders is the subject of an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court of Australia. However, the orders have given rise to existing liabilities subject to any orders staying the enforcement of the liabilities. The liability of the appellant to Bernsteen for the costs awarded by the Magistrates Court of South Australia is for the sum of $12,000. The enforcement of that judgment has been stayed by order of a State Magistrate. The liability of the appellant to Bernsteen for the costs awarded by the Supreme Court of South Australia is for the sum of $11,191.80. The enforcement of that judgment has not been stayed.
 5. Bernsteen has a liability to the appellant for the costs of the appellant's successful application to set aside the bankruptcy notice and that liability has been quantified or is likely to be quantified in the sum of $6,221.78.
 6. The appellant has a liability (not yet quantified) for costs to the respondent upon the discontinuance of an application for a stay of the judgment debt and the appellant may have an offsetting claim for costs against the respondent for an unsuccessful attempt by the respondent to have the appellant's State Magistrates Court proceedings struck out as an abuse of process.

67 These matters are no doubt relevant to the appellant's financial circumstances and go some way towards establishing that the appellant is able to pay her debts. However, the onus is not on the petitioning creditor; it is on the judgment debtor. Furthermore, the appellant's assertions of solvency cannot be given any great weight particularly in light of the approach she took before the Magistrate (see [61] above).

68 The appellant must have some ongoing expenses and, presumably she would say, some means of meeting some or all of those expenses. It was the absence of any evidence relevant to those matters which led the Magistrate to conclude that the appellant had not discharged the onus of establishing that she is able to pay her debts (see [28] and [42] above). That conclusion was open to him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rozenbes v Kronhill [1956] HCA 65 ; (1956) 95 CLR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1956/65.html</AustLII>
<text>71 The relevant principles as to what constitutes an improper purpose were stated by the High Court in Rozenbes v Kronhill [1956] HCA 65 ; (1956) 95 CLR 407. The Court referred to a number of English authorities on what amounts to 'extortion'. The Court said that the question is whether the court process is being used for illegitimate purposes such as recovering a larger amount from the debtor than could be recovered by legal proceedings. The Court said (at 417):
 
 'The case seems finally to establish that the ultimate principle involved is that a court will not allow its process to be abused. There is an abuse of process if a pending bankruptcy petition, or a threat of proceedings in bankruptcy, is used as a means of extortion. The word "extortion" is not a technical term, and it has in bankruptcy law "no special and artificial significance divorced altogether from the ordinary implication of the word". The court will look strictly at the conduct of a creditor using or threatening bankruptcy proceedings, and extortion may be held to have taken place if the creditor has used, or attempted to use, a pending petition, or a threat of a petition, in order to extract from the debtor money which the debtor is not bound to pay, or in order to obtain some secret and unfair advantage over other creditors. But extortion will not be held to have taken place "in the absence of mala fides or anything amounting to oppression in fact". There must be a real intention on the part of the creditor to use the process for some other end than its legitimate end, and there must be a real exertion of pressure.'

72 The other point which emerges from the case (at 419) is that even if an improper purpose is established it does not follow that a sequestration order will not be made. The Court retains a discretion to make such an order.

73 Although the improper purpose point was not referred to in the appellant's Notice of Intention to Oppose Petition, there is no doubt that it was raised as a ground of challenge both before the Registrar on 20 June 2006 and the Federal Magistrate on 5 July 2006.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>