<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>United Salvage Pty Ltd v Louis Dreyfus Armateurs SNC [2006] FCA 1611 (23 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1611.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Meehan v Jones [1982] HCA 52 ; (1982) 149 CLR 571</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/52.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Meehan v Jones [1982] HCA 52 ; (1982) 149 CLR 571, the Court considered a contract which referred to "a satisfactory agreement ... for the supply of a satisfactory quantity of crude oil." In that case, it was submitted that the contract was illusory and that it merely gave a discretion or option to one party as to whether the promise would be carried out. The Court rejected this submission, and although it agreed that it was for the purchaser to determine whether he had entered into a satisfactory agreement for the supply of a satisfactory quantity of crude oil, it also held that the purchaser had an obligation to act honestly in deciding whether the terms of an offer of finance were satisfactory. In addition, Gibbs CJ observed at 578-579 that the expression "satisfactory" could be given content. This observation is relevant in the present circumstances. Although each case must turn on its factual context, in my opinion, the Court can and will give content to the expression "satisfactory deed of release" as expressed in the Offer of Compromise in the present case.

14 Having regard to the evidence, it is my view that the insertion of this requirement played no significant part in the rejection of the Offer of Compromise because there was no reference to it in the challenges to the terms of the Offer made by the plaintiffs'solicitors. The subsequent offer made in January 2006 by the plaintiffs seeking twice the amount offered by the defendants indicates that it was the amount of the award offered by the defendants which was the real cause of the dissatisfaction of the plaintiffs. The requirement relating to a "satisfactory deed of release" was not an operative cause of the rejection.

15 For these reasons, I do not accept that the Offer of Compromise was uncertain, illusory or oppressive in any sense, or incapable of being accepted by a reasonable addressee.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>