<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEIV v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1798 (21 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1798.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/71.html</AustLII>
<text>10 Federal Magistrate Emmett concluded that the Tribunal was not obliged to deal with claims that are not articulated and which do not clearly arise on the material before it. No claim was made to the Tribunal for persecution on the grounds of political opinion. Her Honour observed, with reference to NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [58] , that an unarticulated claim must be raised squarely on the material available to the Tribunal before it has a duty to consider it. Her Honour also relied on Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473 at [1] where Gleeson CJ stated that, although the Tribunal proceedings are not adversarial, the decision of the Tribunal must be considered in the light of the basis upon which the application was made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1901.html</AustLII>
<text>31 The Tribunal is required to deal with ' the case raised by the material or evidence before it ' ( NABE at [58] citing Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157). The Tribunal is not limited to the ' case ' articulated by an applicant if evidence and material which it accepts raise a case not articulated. A claim ' not expressly advanced will attract the review obligation of the Tribunal when it is apparent on the face of the material before the Tribunal ' ( NABE at [58]) (emphasis added). At [59], the Full Court discussed whether the Tribunal is required to consider a claim not expressly raised and observed that there is no general rule that the Tribunal can disregard a claim which arises clearly from materials before it: '[t] he Tribunal is not required to consider a case that is not expressly made or does not arise clearly on the materials before it ' (at [61]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/26.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The absence of a finding of a relevant fact may amount to jurisdictional error ( NABE at [55]). A failure to make a finding on a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying on established facts can amount to a failure to accord procedural fairness and a constructive failure to exercise jurisdiction ( NABE at [55] citing Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389 at [24] and [95]). The task of the Tribunal and the way in which it discharges that function flow from the powers and procedures prescribed for the Tribunal in the conduct of reviews and the use of the word "review" ( NABE at [56]). That includes a requirement to consider all of the claims of the applicants ( NABE at [57] approving Allsop J, with whom Spender J agreed, in Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 194 ALR 244 at [42]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1801</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1801.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The Court in NABE approved the reference by Selway J in SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364 at [17] to the observation by Kirby J in Dranichnikov , at 405, that '[t] he function of the Tribunal, as of the delegate, is to respond to the case that the applicant advances ' and of the Full Court in Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1801 at [49] that the Tribunal ' can only deal with the claims actually made '. The Court at [60] also approved the statement of Selway J at [18] that the question ultimately is ' whether the case put by the [applicant] before the tribunal has sufficiently raised the relevant issue that the tribunal should have dealt with it '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 194 ALR 244</tocase>
<text>30 The absence of a finding of a relevant fact may amount to jurisdictional error ( NABE at [55]). A failure to make a finding on a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying on established facts can amount to a failure to accord procedural fairness and a constructive failure to exercise jurisdiction ( NABE at [55] citing Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389 at [24] and [95]). The task of the Tribunal and the way in which it discharges that function flow from the powers and procedures prescribed for the Tribunal in the conduct of reviews and the use of the word "review" ( NABE at [56]). That includes a requirement to consider all of the claims of the applicants ( NABE at [57] approving Allsop J, with whom Spender J agreed, in Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 194 ALR 244 at [42]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SCAR [2003] FCAFC 126 ; (2003) 128 FCR 553</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/126.html</AustLII>
<text>66 The applicants were represented and present at the hearing before the Tribunal. There is no basis for a suggestion that the Tribunal interfered with or prevented them from presenting their case. Nor can it be said that the conduct of the applicants' solicitor during the hearing rendered the Tribunal's invitation to appear and give evidence pursuant to s 425 of the Act ' a hollow shell or an empty gesture ' ( Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SCAR [2003] FCAFC 126 ; (2003) 128 FCR 553 at [33] ; in any event, see Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 at [94] , [134] and [212]). It has not been shown why the Tribunal was under any obligation to inquire into the solicitor (or migration agent)/client relationship in relation to the matters being put to the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/142.html</AustLII>
<text>66 The applicants were represented and present at the hearing before the Tribunal. There is no basis for a suggestion that the Tribunal interfered with or prevented them from presenting their case. Nor can it be said that the conduct of the applicants' solicitor during the hearing rendered the Tribunal's invitation to appear and give evidence pursuant to s 425 of the Act ' a hollow shell or an empty gesture ' ( Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SCAR [2003] FCAFC 126 ; (2003) 128 FCR 553 at [33] ; in any event, see Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 at [94] , [134] and [212]). It has not been shown why the Tribunal was under any obligation to inquire into the solicitor (or migration agent)/client relationship in relation to the matters being put to the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>29 The High Court discussed the task of the Tribunal in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at [70] [75]. The task of the Tribunal is to review the decisions of the Minister or the Delegate. The Tribunal may affirm, vary or remit the decision, or set it aside and substitute a new decision (s 415(2) of the Act). As pointed out by McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ at [73], the duty of the Tribunal is to take account of all relevant considerations, as identified by the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/263.html</AustLII>
<text>10 Federal Magistrate Emmett concluded that the Tribunal was not obliged to deal with claims that are not articulated and which do not clearly arise on the material before it. No claim was made to the Tribunal for persecution on the grounds of political opinion. Her Honour observed, with reference to NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [58] , that an unarticulated claim must be raised squarely on the material available to the Tribunal before it has a duty to consider it. Her Honour also relied on Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473 at [1] where Gleeson CJ stated that, although the Tribunal proceedings are not adversarial, the decision of the Tribunal must be considered in the light of the basis upon which the application was made.

30 The absence of a finding of a relevant fact may amount to jurisdictional error ( NABE at [55]). A failure to make a finding on a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying on established facts can amount to a failure to accord procedural fairness and a constructive failure to exercise jurisdiction ( NABE at [55] citing Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389 at [24] and [95]). The task of the Tribunal and the way in which it discharges that function flow from the powers and procedures prescribed for the Tribunal in the conduct of reviews and the use of the word "review" ( NABE at [56]). That includes a requirement to consider all of the claims of the applicants ( NABE at [57] approving Allsop J, with whom Spender J agreed, in Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 194 ALR 244 at [42]).

31 The Tribunal is required to deal with ' the case raised by the material or evidence before it ' ( NABE at [58] citing Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157). The Tribunal is not limited to the ' case ' articulated by an applicant if evidence and material which it accepts raise a case not articulated. A claim ' not expressly advanced will attract the review obligation of the Tribunal when it is apparent on the face of the material before the Tribunal ' ( NABE at [58]) (emphasis added). At [59], the Full Court discussed whether the Tribunal is required to consider a claim not expressly raised and observed that there is no general rule that the Tribunal can disregard a claim which arises clearly from materials before it: '[t] he Tribunal is not required to consider a case that is not expressly made or does not arise clearly on the materials before it ' (at [61]).

32 The Court in NABE approved the reference by Selway J in SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364 at [17] to the observation by Kirby J in Dranichnikov , at 405, that '[t] he function of the Tribunal, as of the delegate, is to respond to the case that the applicant advances ' and of the Full Court in Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1801 at [49] that the Tribunal ' can only deal with the claims actually made '. The Court at [60] also approved the statement of Selway J at [18] that the question ultimately is ' whether the case put by the [applicant] before the tribunal has sufficiently raised the relevant issue that the tribunal should have dealt with it '.

33 If the Tribunal makes an error in misunderstanding or misconstruing a claim advanced by the applicant, that can amount to jurisdictional error because of a failure to consider a claim. The claim must, however, ' emerge clearly from the materials before the Tribunal ' ( NABE at [68]). There was no suggestion that the Tribunal is required to consider a claim not made or abandoned before the Tribunal.

34 A claim made to the Department and referred to in the Delegate's decision would, ordinarily, be before the Tribunal. However, where a claim has been made to the Delegate and not advanced at all before the Tribunal and does not arise from the material before the Tribunal, the Tribunal is entitled to assume that the claim is no longer made. The Tribunal is conducting a review of the Delegate's decision but on the basis of the claims advanced and materials before the Tribunal. If a claim does not so arise and is abandoned, especially where the applicants are legally represented, the Tribunal is entitled to take the view that the applicants do not make that claim or a case based on that claim.

35 The conclusion by Emmett FM that the claim to persecution on the ground of political opinion or imputed political opinion was abandoned and that the Tribunal was not obliged to consider it has not been shown to be in error. This ground is rejected.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NBDF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1355.html</AustLII>
<text>21 In NBDF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1355 the appellant had, as here, sought to raise fresh grounds of appeal not relied on before the Federal Magistrates Court. As Branson J pointed out at [22], leave is required to argue on appeal an issue not raised below. There, as here, neither the appellant's written submissions nor his affidavit addressed the basis on which the Court must be satisfied that it is expedient and in the interests of justice for the issue to be raised for the first time on appeal. Her Honour said at [26] that it is not appropriate to grant an appellant leave to raise an issue simply because, as he contended, it would be just to allow him to do so. If the issue upon which an appellant wishes to rely for the first time is without merit, leave should not be granted to raise the issue before this Court.

22 The affidavit contains general, broad assertions that the applicants' ' migration agent ' was ' undermining ' the case before the Tribunal, that the agent's behaviour was ' unethical ', that he had done ' damage ' to the applicants, had made submissions without instructions and had ' damaged the credibility of our refugee application immeasurably before the eyes of the Tribunal '. The male applicant said that he had not known what was being said, as the discussions were not interpreted.

23 He also says that his counsel in the hearing before Emmett FM ' has disappointed us by advancing mostly unsustainable arguments with only one exception '. He asserts, with respect to his previous lawyers that ' one has seriously damaged our case while being paid by us and the other has done our case without much competence '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/70.html</AustLII>
<text>19 Whether a decision is interlocutory or final depends on the legal effect of the judgment ( Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at [4] ). There is a conflict of authority in this Court as to the position where a Federal Magistrate finds an appeal incompetent for failure to comply with s 477 of the Act yet also makes a decision "on the merits" to dismiss the appeal ( SZGAP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2005) 227 ALR 683 at [68]-[69]). That conflict does not require resolution here. For the reasons which follow, the proposed grounds of appeal have no prospects of success. It follows that, independently of the applicants' explanation for what is a very short delay, neither leave to file an extension of time nor leave to appeal should be granted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364</tocase>
<text>32 The Court in NABE approved the reference by Selway J in SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364 at [17] to the observation by Kirby J in Dranichnikov , at 405, that '[t] he function of the Tribunal, as of the delegate, is to respond to the case that the applicant advances ' and of the Full Court in Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1801 at [49] that the Tribunal ' can only deal with the claims actually made '. The Court at [60] also approved the statement of Selway J at [18] that the question ultimately is ' whether the case put by the [applicant] before the tribunal has sufficiently raised the relevant issue that the tribunal should have dealt with it '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>42 None of the matters raised or information cited are referred to in the Tribunal's reasons. They do not form the reason or part of the reason for its decision. The Tribunal was not obliged to provide particulars of its reasoning, nor of defects in the applicants' case ( SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 at [206] , [223]).

43 Section 424A(1) has no application. This ground is without merit. This was not a ground relied upon before the Federal Magistrate where the applicants were legally represented and no good reason is given why it is now being raised for the first time on appeal or why it is in the interests of justice for it to be considered.

44 Leave to rely on this ground should be refused.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZGAP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2005) 227 ALR 683</tocase>
<text>19 Whether a decision is interlocutory or final depends on the legal effect of the judgment ( Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at [4] ). There is a conflict of authority in this Court as to the position where a Federal Magistrate finds an appeal incompetent for failure to comply with s 477 of the Act yet also makes a decision "on the merits" to dismiss the appeal ( SZGAP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2005) 227 ALR 683 at [68]-[69]). That conflict does not require resolution here. For the reasons which follow, the proposed grounds of appeal have no prospects of success. It follows that, independently of the applicants' explanation for what is a very short delay, neither leave to file an extension of time nor leave to appeal should be granted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>W284 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1788</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1788.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>