<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGLL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1507 (3 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1507.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>SZGLL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 568</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/568.html</AustLII>
<text>This appeal from a decision of a Federal Magistrate ( SZGLL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 568) turns upon quite a narrow question, which is becoming common in this area of the law. There was an acknowledged breach of s 424A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) by the Refugee Review Tribunal in a proceeding which led to the affirmation by that Tribunal of a decision by a delegate of the Minister not to grant protection visas to the appellants. The learned Federal Magistrate was satisfied that at least two reasons for the Tribunal decision were not affected in any way by the breach of s 424A.

The substantial matter in this appeal is a contention that that the learned Federal Magistrate was wrong in so concluding, and that the breach of s 424A should have led to the setting aside of the Tribunal decisions. The two reasons can be described in shorthand as the 'no Convention' ground and the 'State protection' ground. The Tribunal did find against the appellants on each ground. In my respectful opinion, it cannot be concluded that the breach of s 424A had no relevance to either of those grounds.

The appellants are husband and wife who are citizens of Fiji, having lived there all their lives, of Indian ethnicity who practise the Hindu religion. They claimed to have a well-founded fear of persecution if they returned to Fiji upon the basis of both race and religion. In their protection visa application, the following detailed reasons were given for the application: 
 
 'I wish to draw Decision Makers attention towards the following reasons which has prevented me to return to my Home Country (Fiji). 
 
 A : I belong to Hindu religion and the area where I have lived was extensively dominated by the Indigious Fijians and it is well documented that there has been a long term tension between Hindu and Indigious Fijians who has never liked us Indians in their Country. 
 
 I myself formed a small social group in the area called "Savini" and we had thirty seven members in this group. The aim of this group was not to create any discriminations nor trouble but this was a simple group supporting Hindus and to promote the aims and objectives of Hindu religion which no doubt was very much disliked by the local indigious Fijians and they commenced to harass and intimidate the members of our group and wwere threatened that if they did not terminate their association with our group than the death warrants will be delivered. This was brought to my attention and I along with other members continued my work and the situation got heated and it became incrasibly for me to handle the heated situation. It was in October 2001 when in the late evening some unknown Indigious fijans gained forced entry in to my House and Indiscriminately assaulted me and my lady wife, No doubt it was a very threatening situation and my wife was extremely frightened and upset due to this incident and she decided to move and live with her brothers in Raki Raki and I was the only person who was forced to live alone and run my business with out any support. After this incident I was in a situation where it became terribly difficult and virtually impossible for me to run my business alone mainly due to the fear from the local Indigious Fijians mainly because Local indigious Fijians commenced to harass me in the area where I was running my business like daily few indigious Fijians will come and sit in front of my shop, drink "Kawa" and scream which was frightening for the customers which rapidly decreased and badly effected my business. On numerous occasions they spray painted the doors and walls of my shop and there were three major breakins which put me in a loss. It was in December 2001 when my Car was stolen and never recovered. Now I was in a position where I had no choice but to sell my business and move to another area and became very difficult for me sell my businss because peoples were aware of my situation, therefore, no one was willing to take a chance and buy my running business. Finally I was successful in selling my business in April/May 2002 and moved to "B A" and was extremely shocked to note that I was being followed by the Indigious Fijians as The Decision maker knows that Fiji is extensively dominated by the Indigious Fijians and they are quite united too. As soon as I noted that my enemies are still chasing me I quickly decided to come to Australia for Holidays and told every one in the area that am going abroad to live permanently so that my enemies willforget about me. I came to Australia in July 2002 snd stayed here up until October 2002. 1 was quite sure that upon my return to fiji my opponents will completely forget about me and I wil be able to live there peacefully. upon my return to Fiji in October 2002 I moved to another area which was approximately 10 Kilometers away from my area and started tio drive a taxi, it was one evening when I was driving a Cab that I was picked by one member of my opponents and he said you liar you are still round and left. I am definitely not sure how they were able to find exact location of my residence and it was on 24.12.2202 when On or about 4 am sis unknown Indigious Fijians gained forced entry in to my house, tied my wife with ropes and was ordered to sit in a corner robbed my house and before leaving Myself and my lady wife were indiscriminately assaulted and deprived from the valuable personal belongings and when Next day I went to report this matter to the local police I was called a liar, ill treated and accused of lodging a bogus police report and unfortunately was unable to gain any protection from the Police and decided to move to live with my Wife's family until such time I can find a safer place to live. 
 
 Cut the story short because am not here to write a book about my problems and waste decision makers time but am only here to humbly ask the decision maker to please accept that Indo/fijians are not safe in fiji and are subject to persecution such as you may be aware that all the senior position in thE government goes to Indigious Fijians and they have more facilities and protection from the authorities than Indo/Fijians.I personally along with many indo/Fijians has been subject to persecution. I have numerously visited Australia and Newzealand but never sought a protection in any country but Now I have been placed in a situation where I had no choice but to seek protection in Australia. 
 
 please Sympathetically consider.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MZXGR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1167</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1167.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, it cannot be said that there is any 'independent and unimpeachable' basis for the Tribunal's decision, uninfected by any jurisdictional error under s 424A (see MZXGR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1167 at [7] ). Thus, although the matter is by no means free from doubt, the appeal should be allowed, the orders of the Federal Magistrate's Court set aside and in lieu thereof it be ordered that the decision of the Tribunal be set aside and the matter remitted to the Tribunal for determination according to law. The first respondent is to pay the costs of the appellants of the proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court and of this appeal. 


 I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles. 


 Associate:

Dated: 15 November 2006

 Solicitor for the Appellants: Mr Chandra Jayawardena 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr T Reilly 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Phillips Fox 
 
 
 The Second Respondent submitted 

 Date of Hearing: 3 November 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 November 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1507.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>