<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Applicant S291 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2006] FCA 1172 (8 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1172.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Abebe v The Commonwealth of Australia [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/14.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant suggests that the Tribunal should have drawn his attention to specific passages in the independent country information. It was submitted that those passages were directly related to the applicant's experiences and, had he been able to explain his relationship with those events, the Tribunal would have assessed his risk of persecution differently. This submission must fail. It is not the function of the Tribunal to establish the applicant's case for him. As Gummow and Hayne JJ observed in Abebe v The Commonwealth of Australia [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 576 [187] : 
 
 'The proceedings before the Tribunal are inquisitorial and the Tribunal is not in the position of a contradictor. It is for the applicant to advance whatever evidence or argument she wishes to advance in support of her contention that she has a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason. The Tribunal must then decide whether that claim is made out.'

The applicant was obliged to raise all of the factual matters which were relevant to his case. That included providing the Tribunal with sufficient details of his personal experiences to allow the Tribunal to make an assessment of his claim. The Tribunal could not have known whether the independent country information referred to arrests of people close to the applicant (such as Dr Rajab) unless the applicant provided specific details of his associates which would enable the Tribunal to recognise circumstances referred to in the country information. The applicant raised the arrests of university colleagues only briefly and vaguely, and did not provide any particular information. If the applicant had additional material which he wished to place before the Tribunal then it was incumbent upon him to place it before the Tribunal.

Furthermore, the vast majority of the independent country information which was relied upon by the Tribunal had in fact been provided by the applicant himself, and following the Tribunal hearing, the applicant was offered the opportunity to provide further information. The applicant took up the offer and provided further independent country information to the Tribunal. It is clear that the applicant was not only afforded the opportunity but also exercised his right to comment before the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth and Anor v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant submits that the failure to comply with s 431 of the Migration Act gives rise to procedural unfairness. He submits that procedural fairness arises at the pre-hearing stage of the Tribunal hearing and continues during and beyond the hearing and until the Tribunal fulfils its statutory functions by the provisions and publication of its decision. He claims the Tribunal's decision was vitiated by its failure to afford him procedural fairness. The applicant relies upon Ainsworth and Anor v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 and Johns v Australian Securities Commission and Ors [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408 as authority for the proposition that procedural fairness may require an opportunity to oppose publication of a decision.

The applicant's reliance on Ainsworth is misplaced. In that case, the Criminal Justice Commission published a report which made adverse factual findings against Ainsworth, in circumstances where Ainsworth had never been given the opportunity to be heard upon the basis for those findings. The report attracted a duty of procedural fairness because its contents had the potential to ' destroy, defeat or prejudice a person's rights, interests or legitimate expectations ' (see Annetts and Anor v McCann and Ors [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 598 per Mason CJ, Deane and McHugh JJ). In contrast, in these proceedings the applicant was given an opportunity to be heard upon the findings which were included in the Tribunal's decision. The Tribunal had invited the applicant to a hearing, which he attended. Accordingly the Tribunal's duty of procedural fairness was discharged in respect of the factual and legal findings which it made in that decision, and ultimately its decision that the applicant was not a refugee.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Annetts and Anor v McCann and Ors [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/57.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant's reliance on Ainsworth is misplaced. In that case, the Criminal Justice Commission published a report which made adverse factual findings against Ainsworth, in circumstances where Ainsworth had never been given the opportunity to be heard upon the basis for those findings. The report attracted a duty of procedural fairness because its contents had the potential to ' destroy, defeat or prejudice a person's rights, interests or legitimate expectations ' (see Annetts and Anor v McCann and Ors [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 598 per Mason CJ, Deane and McHugh JJ). In contrast, in these proceedings the applicant was given an opportunity to be heard upon the findings which were included in the Tribunal's decision. The Tribunal had invited the applicant to a hearing, which he attended. Accordingly the Tribunal's duty of procedural fairness was discharged in respect of the factual and legal findings which it made in that decision, and ultimately its decision that the applicant was not a refugee.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Johns v Australian Securities Commission and Ors [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/56.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant submits that the failure to comply with s 431 of the Migration Act gives rise to procedural unfairness. He submits that procedural fairness arises at the pre-hearing stage of the Tribunal hearing and continues during and beyond the hearing and until the Tribunal fulfils its statutory functions by the provisions and publication of its decision. He claims the Tribunal's decision was vitiated by its failure to afford him procedural fairness. The applicant relies upon Ainsworth and Anor v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 and Johns v Australian Securities Commission and Ors [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408 as authority for the proposition that procedural fairness may require an opportunity to oppose publication of a decision.

Johns concerns a decision by the Australian Securities Commission to allow transcript of interviews it had conducted with the appellant to be released to the public. In that case, the High Court held that the applicant ought to have been given an opportunity to make submissions before that decision was made and accordingly it was invalid. On this basis the applicant says that the Tribunal's decision to publish its reasons was also a decision which is reviewable.

I accept that the decision by the Tribunal to publish its reasons on the internet in the form which it did was a decision which might be challenged. Indeed, after a request by the applicant, the Tribunal removed the reasons from the internet. If the Tribunal had refused to remove its reasons from the internet, it may have been open to the applicant to challenge that decision and seek injunctive relief to restrain the continued publication on the basis that it was inappropriate for the Tribunal to have published its reasons without giving the applicant an opportunity to make submissions about the details which should not be published. That is, the applicant might have successfully made an allegation that procedural fairness had been denied in relation to the decision to publish . However, any errors which may have occurred in the Tribunal's decision to publish were incapable of affecting its decision on the applicant's refugee status, which had been concluded before publication and in respect of which fair procedures had been observed.

It follows that this ground of challenge must be rejected.

The applicant's third challenge to the decision relates to the failure of the Tribunal to disclose to the applicant a file note dated 29 April 1998 and made by an officer of the Department, which was provided to the Tribunal. The file note referred to inconsistencies between the applicant's application for a protection visa and that of his brother, whose application for a protection visa was also being determined by the Department.

The file note contains information which is potentially adverse to the applicant, in that it suggests the account provided by him is inconsistent with the account provided by his brother. It also incorrectly summarises the information contained in the applicant's protection visa application, stating that he claimed only one brother was detained by authorities, when in fact his application states that the Libyan government ' jailed many of my brothers and cousins since 1984 ' and refers specifically to two brothers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 80 ALJR 228</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/72.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant has submitted that the failure by the Tribunal to provide the file note to the applicant was a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal. He relies upon the decision of the High Court in Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 80 ALJR 228.

The decision in VEAL also concerned a decision made by the Refugee Review Tribunal. In that case, the Department had received an unsolicited letter which contained allegations relating to the appellant. The letter was passed on to the Tribunal by the Department, but the Tribunal did not tell the appellant about the letter or about the allegations contained in it. The Tribunal made a decision refusing a protection visa on the basis that the applicant lacked credibility, but explicitly indicated in its reasons that it had given no weight to the letter in arriving at its decision.

The High Court held that the Tribunal had failed to afford the applicant procedural fairness. The Court held that information that was credible, relevant and significant must be provided to an affected person and that an opportunity must be given to the person to deal with the information before a decision was reached: see at [17]. It stated that credible, relevant and significant information was information ' that cannot be dismissed from further consideration by the decision-maker before making the decision ' and noted that whether information is credible, relevant and significant does not depend ' upon whatever characterisation of the information the decision-maker may later have chosen to apply to the information when expressing reasons for the decision that has been reached ': see at [17].

At [19] in VEAL , the Court said: 
 
 'As has later been rightly said, " the necessity to disclose such material in order to accord procedural fairness is not based on answering a causal question as to whether the material did in fact play a part in influencing the decision " . It follows that asking whether, despite what was said in its reasons, the Tribunal may have been subconsciously affected by the information distracts attention from the relevant inquiry. The relevant inquiry is: what procedures should have been followed? The relevant inquiry is neither what decision should the decision-maker have made, nor what reasons did the decision-maker give for the conclusion reached.'

The second respondent submits that VEAL is distinguishable from the present case on the basis of Bennett J's decision in SZECD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 31 ; (2006) 150 FCR 53. In that decision, Bennett J distinguished the decision in VEAL on the basis that although procedural unfairness had been established in respect of one basis of the Tribunal's decision, there was a separate and independent basis for its conclusion which was not affected by procedural unfairness: see at [28], [40]-[41].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kioa and Ors v West and Anor [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/81.html</AustLII>
<text>The content of procedural fairness requirements will depend upon the circumstances of the exercise of the power: see Wilson J in Kioa and Ors v West and Anor [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 584-5 per Mason J; 601 per Wilson J; 611-2 per Brennan J; 633 per Deane J. However, common law procedural fairness will generally require that an applicant be given the opportunity to comment upon information held by the Tribunal which is adverse to his or her interest. As Mason J said in Kioa at 582: 
 
 'It is a fundamental rule of the common law doctrine of natural justice expressed in traditional terms that, generally speaking, when an order is to be made which will deprive a person of some right or interest or the legitimate expectation of a benefit, he is entitled to know the case sought to be made against him and to be given an opportunity of replying to it ...'

I do not accept this submission. The obligations of procedural fairness at common law relate to two 'rules': the bias rule and the hearing rule: see M Aronson, B Dyer and M Groves, Judicial Review of Administrative Action , 3 rd ed, Lawbook Co, 2004 at 370. The bias rule prevents a Tribunal from acting in a way which shows actual or apprehended bias towards an applicant. The hearing rule acts to ensure that an individual is given an opportunity to be heard before a decision is taken and to meet the case which is put against him or her: see the passage in Kioa cited at [19] above. The precise content of the hearing rule is dependent upon the context in which the decision is being made. In any event, if an allegation of procedural fairness is to be made out, the applicant must demonstrate that either the bias rule or the hearing rule has been breached by the Tribunal.

The decision of the Tribunal to publish its reasons upon the internet, in the form in which it did so, could not vitiate the decision which had already been made by the Tribunal relating to the applicant's refugee status. No suggestion has been made that the Tribunal's decision to publish its reasons indicated bias on the part of the Tribunal. Nor is there any suggestion that the hearing given by the Tribunal had been in some way deficient. If a breach of neither of these principles is alleged, a claim of procedural unfairness is not made out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/61.html</AustLII>
<text>The obligations of the Tribunal are to be determined by reference to the Migration Act as it existed on 7 January 1999, the date of its decision. The Migration Act did not then include s 422B , which provides that Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act (which relates to the conduct of the Tribunal's review) is taken to be an exhaustive statement of the natural justice hearing rule. It is clear that s 422B of the Migration Act now operates to exclude the requirement for decision-makers to abide by common law principles of procedural fairness: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61. However, it is equally clear from decisions of the High Court that common law principles of procedural fairness were not excluded from the Migration Act as it existed prior to the enactment of s 422B: see Plaintiff S157/2002 v The Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476 at [37] - [38] per Gleeson CJ; at [83] per Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Anor; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 at [26] per Gleeson CJ and Hayne J; at [95] per Gaudron J; at [128] per McHugh J; at [188] per Kirby J. Accordingly, it is open to the applicant to raise a breach of common law procedural fairness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>NAVM v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 99</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/99.html</AustLII>
<text>Nonetheless, it is not always necessary for the Tribunal to provide to an applicant copies of any country information upon which it relies. The Tribunal's obligations may be discharged if it provides to the applicant orally the substance of adverse material: see NAVM v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 99 at [31] [33]. The important element is that the information provided by the Tribunal enables a person to make a submission concerning its relevance or to adduce competing material.

In the present case, it is apparent from the transcript that the Tribunal discussed the independent country information at some length with the applicant. In particular, it raised its concerns that the independent country information did not support the contention that the Libyan government persecuted devout Muslims who were not fundamentalists. In my opinion, the applicant clearly was provided with the substance of the information which was contained in independent country information.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Plaintiff S157/2002 v The Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/2.html</AustLII>
<text>The obligations of the Tribunal are to be determined by reference to the Migration Act as it existed on 7 January 1999, the date of its decision. The Migration Act did not then include s 422B , which provides that Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act (which relates to the conduct of the Tribunal's review) is taken to be an exhaustive statement of the natural justice hearing rule. It is clear that s 422B of the Migration Act now operates to exclude the requirement for decision-makers to abide by common law principles of procedural fairness: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61. However, it is equally clear from decisions of the High Court that common law principles of procedural fairness were not excluded from the Migration Act as it existed prior to the enactment of s 422B: see Plaintiff S157/2002 v The Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476 at [37] - [38] per Gleeson CJ; at [83] per Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Anor; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 at [26] per Gleeson CJ and Hayne J; at [95] per Gaudron J; at [128] per McHugh J; at [188] per Kirby J. Accordingly, it is open to the applicant to raise a breach of common law procedural fairness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Anor; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/22.html</AustLII>
<text>The obligations of the Tribunal are to be determined by reference to the Migration Act as it existed on 7 January 1999, the date of its decision. The Migration Act did not then include s 422B , which provides that Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act (which relates to the conduct of the Tribunal's review) is taken to be an exhaustive statement of the natural justice hearing rule. It is clear that s 422B of the Migration Act now operates to exclude the requirement for decision-makers to abide by common law principles of procedural fairness: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61. However, it is equally clear from decisions of the High Court that common law principles of procedural fairness were not excluded from the Migration Act as it existed prior to the enactment of s 422B: see Plaintiff S157/2002 v The Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476 at [37] - [38] per Gleeson CJ; at [83] per Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Anor; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 at [26] per Gleeson CJ and Hayne J; at [95] per Gaudron J; at [128] per McHugh J; at [188] per Kirby J. Accordingly, it is open to the applicant to raise a breach of common law procedural fairness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/54.html</AustLII>
<text>In arriving at this conclusion, I am mindful of the observations of the High Court in Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141. In that case, the Court considered the circumstances in which it was appropriate not to order a new trial because it would inevitably result in the making of the same order as that made at the first trial. Whilst the Court observed that ' not every departure from the rules of natural justice at a trial will entitle the aggrieved party to a new trial ', it cautioned at 145: 
 
 'Where, however, the denial of natural justice affects the entitlement of a party to make submissions on an issue of fact ... it is more difficult for a court of appeal to conclude that compliance with the requirements of natural justice could have made no difference .... when the Full Court is invited by a respondent to exercise these powers in order to arrive at a conclusion that a new trial, sought to remedy a denial of natural justice relevant to a finding of fact, could make no difference to the result already reached, it should proceed with caution. '

The procedural unfairness alleged in the present case is directed to a finding of fact, namely a finding as to the applicant's credibility. However, I am nonetheless satisfied that this is a case in which the provision of the information could have made no difference to the result, because the applicant's credibility was determined in his favour.

The Tribunal made no adverse findings on the applicant's credibility, but rather believed his factual account. The applicant submitted that the Tribunal impliedly made adverse credibility findings, because it did not find that he had a well-founded fear of persecution. However, the examples pointed to by the applicant were those in which the Tribunal did not agree with the applicant's assessment of events, not where it disbelieved his account of the facts. The Tribunal accepted that the applicant and his brothers and cousins had been detained by the Libyan government. It accepted his description of what had occurred at his place of work and the details of his education. What it did not agree with was the applicant's explanation for these events. While the applicant believed that they resulted from religious persecution, the Tribunal disagreed. The Tribunal did not believe the applicant was lying about the facts. It just considered that he was wrong in his interpretation of them. In terms of the applicant's credibility, the Tribunal clearly found in the applicant's favour.

The material contained in the file note was credible, relevant and significant only in respect of the issue of the applicant's credibility. It could not have been relevant to any of the other findings made by the Tribunal. The Tribunal's decision did not include any adverse findings upon the applicant's credibility, but rather was based upon its assessment of his risk of persecution in Libya, derived from independent country information and from its assessment of his personal circumstances. Giving the applicant an opportunity to comment upon the file note could not possibly have altered the Tribunal's findings in respect of matters unrelated to his credibility.

For these reasons, I consider that this ground must also be rejected. Regardless of whether a breach of procedural fairness has in fact occurred, I consider that to order the matter to be remitted to the Tribunal would be futile and if a breach of procedural fairness were in fact established, I would exercise my discretion not to order a re-hearing. Accordingly, this ground must fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZECD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 31 ; (2006) 150 FCR 53</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/31.html</AustLII>
<text>The second respondent submits that VEAL is distinguishable from the present case on the basis of Bennett J's decision in SZECD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 31 ; (2006) 150 FCR 53. In that decision, Bennett J distinguished the decision in VEAL on the basis that although procedural unfairness had been established in respect of one basis of the Tribunal's decision, there was a separate and independent basis for its conclusion which was not affected by procedural unfairness: see at [28], [40]-[41].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>