<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Coggin v Telstar Finance Company (Q) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 191 (10 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/191.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Simply No-Knead (Franchising) Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 1365 ; (2000) 104 FCR 253 at [37]</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1365.html</AustLII>
<text>57 The notion of unconscionability in s 51AC is wider than that of "unconscionable within the meaning of the unwritten law...of the States and Territories" in s 51AA: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Simply No-Knead (Franchising) Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 1365 ; (2000) 104 FCR 253 at [37] (Sundberg J), Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 4WD Systems Pty Ltd (2003) 59 IPR 435 at [183] (Selway J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 4WD Systems Pty Ltd (2003) 59 IPR 435 at [183]</tocase>
<text>57 The notion of unconscionability in s 51AC is wider than that of "unconscionable within the meaning of the unwritten law...of the States and Territories" in s 51AA: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Simply No-Knead (Franchising) Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 1365 ; (2000) 104 FCR 253 at [37] (Sundberg J), Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 4WD Systems Pty Ltd (2003) 59 IPR 435 at [183] (Selway J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hurley v McDonald's Australia Ltd (2000) ATPR 41-741 at [22]</tocase>
<text>58 In Hurley v McDonald's Australia Ltd (2000) ATPR 41-741 at [22] a Full Court of this Court said in regard to s 51AC (emphasis in original):
 
 "For conduct to be regarded as unconscionable, serious misconduct or something clearly unfair or unreasonable , must be demonstrated - Cameron v Qantas Airways Ltd (1994) 55 FCR 147 at 179. Whatever " unconscionable " means in sections 51AB and 51AC , the term carries the meaning given by the Shorter Oxford English Dictionary, namely, actions showing no regard for conscience , or that are irreconcilable with what is right or reasonable - Qantas Airways Ltd v Cameron (1996) 66 FCR 246 at 262. The various synonyms used in relation to the term " unconscionable " import a pejorative moral judgment - Qantas Airways Ltd v Cameron (1996) 66 FCR 246 at 283-4 and 298."

59 A convenient starting point is the submission of counsel for the respondents that Mr Nagy and Mr Pavia were the agents of Mr Coggin in this transaction and were not the agents of Telstar or Mr Cunningham. Nothing could be further from the truth. The reality is that Mr Nagy and Mr Pavia were old comrades in arms from their door to door cookware selling days. And they were sufficiently familiar with Mr Cunningham to wake him up in the early hours of the morning, moor the Lady Christina at his private mooring (no doubt by prior arrangement), and borrow $400 from him to pay the skipper. Messrs Nagy, Pavia and Cunningham at all times worked together in pursuit of their own interests, and against the interests of Mr Coggin. This is most strikingly demonstrated by their exclusion of Mr Coggin from the meeting on 24 December 1999 at which they made the agreement recorded in Mr Cunningham's note ([37] above). They saw the only role of Mr Coggin as being "Joe's Father" who was to provide a boat as collateral for their venture. This is consistent with what Mr Gray told Mrs McIlwee, that Telstar was to make a loan Mr Coggin "for a business venture for Joe Nagy who is the son-in-law of Mr Coggin".

60 Mr Cunningham was the director of a finance company which usually did not lend on secured transactions, let alone maritime ones. Nor, as far as the evidence reveals, did this Brisbane finance company engage in wholesaling of goods in other States. As the respondents' counsel submitted, "this type of transaction was not common for Telstar".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/75.html</AustLII>
<text>73 Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 was a s 46 case where, amongst other issues, individuals were sought to be made liable as persons involved in the contraventions. It was argued that the individuals did not know that their principal's conduct was engaged in for the purpose, or had the likely effect, of substantially lessening competition in the market as defined. Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ at [48] firmly rejected this argument, saying: 
 
 "It is wholly unrealistic to seek to characterise knowledge of circumstances in that way. Only a handful of lawyers think or speak in that fashion, and then only at a late stage of analysis of any particular problem. In order to know the essential facts, and thus satisfy s 75B(1) of the Act and like provisions, it is not necessary to know that those facts are capable of characterisation in the language of the statute." 


Their Honours did not specifically refer to the leading case on accessorial liability under the Act, Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661, although it was cited in argument (at 58). However, Yorke v Lucas , in applying criminal law principles to accessorial liability under the Act, proceeded on the basis that to form the requisite intent for aiding and abetting a crime, the defendant "must have knowledge of the essential matters which go to make up the offence whether or not he knows that those matters amount to a crime" (at 667). Since, as already noted, the assessment of conduct as unconscionable or not under s 51AC may involve the consideration and weighting of 13 statutory criteria, and an infinite number of other criteria which appear relevant to the judge, it would be quite unworkable to suppose that there could be no finding of accessorial liability unless the individual, at the time of the contravention, considered the same factors, and gave them the same weight, as did the judge at the subsequent trial. Apart from anything else, the morally obtuse would have an undeserved advantage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/65.html</AustLII>
<text>73 Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 was a s 46 case where, amongst other issues, individuals were sought to be made liable as persons involved in the contraventions. It was argued that the individuals did not know that their principal's conduct was engaged in for the purpose, or had the likely effect, of substantially lessening competition in the market as defined. Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ at [48] firmly rejected this argument, saying: 
 
 "It is wholly unrealistic to seek to characterise knowledge of circumstances in that way. Only a handful of lawyers think or speak in that fashion, and then only at a late stage of analysis of any particular problem. In order to know the essential facts, and thus satisfy s 75B(1) of the Act and like provisions, it is not necessary to know that those facts are capable of characterisation in the language of the statute." 


Their Honours did not specifically refer to the leading case on accessorial liability under the Act, Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661, although it was cited in argument (at 58). However, Yorke v Lucas , in applying criminal law principles to accessorial liability under the Act, proceeded on the basis that to form the requisite intent for aiding and abetting a crime, the defendant "must have knowledge of the essential matters which go to make up the offence whether or not he knows that those matters amount to a crime" (at 667). Since, as already noted, the assessment of conduct as unconscionable or not under s 51AC may involve the consideration and weighting of 13 statutory criteria, and an infinite number of other criteria which appear relevant to the judge, it would be quite unworkable to suppose that there could be no finding of accessorial liability unless the individual, at the time of the contravention, considered the same factors, and gave them the same weight, as did the judge at the subsequent trial. Apart from anything else, the morally obtuse would have an undeserved advantage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wardley v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 at 525 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/55.html</AustLII>
<text>75 The principal element is the value of the vessel as at the end of 1999, this being the time Mr Coggin lost control of her. There is no doubt that there was sufficient causal relationship between the unconscionable conduct and the loss in the "common law practical or common-law sense": Wardley v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 at 525.

76 I do not think Telstar should be given credit for the monies it advanced. It has not filed a cross-claim. Telstar, through Mr Cunningham, was intimately involved in the way Mr Coggin was drawn into the whole transaction, including the Easy Drink dealership acquisition. Telstar's conduct was seriously unconscionable. It would not be fair to allow it to unpick the transaction and reconstruct something acceptable. Mr Coggin should be put back in the position he was before he encountered the respondents.

77 A claim was also made for loss of rental. This is not so clear, since the availability of solvent lessees at the time is problematic. A better measure is to allow interest on the value of the vessel to date. Counsel agreed that an appropriate rate was ten per cent per annum (not per month).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spencer v The Commonwealth [1907] HCA 70 ; (1907) 5 CLR 418 at 431</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1907/70.html</AustLII>
<text>79 On the other hand, a valuation for finance purposes, which contemplates the possibility of a fire sale environment, would be unfair to Mr Coggin. Rather I think the proper measure is market value or current price: Spencer v The Commonwealth [1907] HCA 70 ; (1907) 5 CLR 418 at 431.

80 On behalf of the respondents Mr Nicholas Lockyer, another experienced marine surveyor, valued the vessel on a fair market value, as is where is basis, as at 24 December 1999 at $82,000. Mr Lockyer gave his opinion for the purposes of this case and had not inspected the vessel. His report includes two earlier valuations , both for insurance purposes:
 
&#8226; 11 December 1997, C B Tanner, $106,000
 
&#8226; 23 April 1998, R W Beale, $135,000

81 I accept Mr Lockyer's definition of fair market value for these purposes, namely, the price achievable between a willing vendor and a willing purchaser where the vessel has been professionally presented and marketed by brokers in the local domestic market, taking into account recent prices obtained for similar vessels within that market.

82 That being so, I think the best evidence of value was the price in fact achieved, namely $95,000. Despite counsel's criticism, I conclude that Telstar took reasonable steps to sell the vessel by placing her with a number of brokers. There is nothing to suggest that the sale which in fact took place was other than at arms' length. The sale was effected after some negotiation and an increase of the buyers' offer.

83 There should be a deduction for repairs carried out on Telstar's instructions amounting to $1589.05, but not for a further sum of $500 which seems to have been a gratuity to Mr Cunningham's secretary.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>