<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SBPD v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1174 (21 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1174.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MLGXAL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 966</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/966.html</AustLII>
<text>This is an application for leave to appeal from a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court given on 28 April 2006. On that date the Federal Magistrates Court dismissed an application to quash a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal of 15 December 2005. It did so pursuant to r 13.03A(c) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules, because the applicant did not then appear. Consequently, the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court was an interlocutory judgment requiring leave to appeal under s 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth): See MLGXAL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 966.

The applicant has not appeared on his motion. He has been notified of the hearing date in accordance with the Court's direction by letter to his address for service dated 13 July 2006. He applied for a fee waiver to be able to file his application. On that document he provided a mobile telephone number. Efforts to contact him at that mobile telephone number, both today and on earlier occasions by the Court, have proved unsuccessful. Not only has the applicant not appeared today and not appeared before the Federal Magistrates Court on the hearing of his application then, but he also did not appear before the Tribunal at the hearing which it fixed for him to give oral evidence and to make submissions.

He did not contact the Tribunal to explain his failure to attend. One cannot help but have the suspicion that the applicant is simply using the opportunities provided to him under the law to prolong his stay in Australia. His application for a protection visa was refused, first by a delegate of the first respondent on 15 September 2005, and then by the Tribunal on 15 December 2005, in essence, because his claims were not established to the satisfaction of the initial decision-maker or the Tribunal on the material before them. As the applicant has not appeared today on his own motion, I am entitled to proceed in his absence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>