<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1777 (19 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1777.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Edison Mission Operations and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 853</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/853.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The CEPU contests the allegations against it. On 7 April 2006, I ordered that the contested proceeding between the ACCC and the CEPU concerning the CEPU's liability under ss 76 and 80 of the TPA be heard prior to the penalty hearing as between the ACCC and Edison: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Edison Mission Operations and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 853. There was no appearance for Edison at the hearing of the contested proceeding between the ACCC and the CEPU.

5 The hearing proceeded by viva voce evidence. The ACCC called five witnesses. Four of the witnesses, Colin Sutherland ('Sutherland'), Paul Burns ('Burns'), Wayne Buckley ('Buckley') and Mark Pearson ('Pearson') were employees of Edison or a related company at all relevant times. Sutherland was a general manager of Edison Mission Energy Australia Pty Ltd ('EME') and a director of Edison and certain of its related entities including Valley Power Pty Ltd ('Valley Power'). Burns was the manager of community and employee relations for EME and was stationed at Loy Yang B. Sutherland and Burns had the principal carriage of discussions between Edison and the CEPU in August 2001. Pearson was the maintenance manager of EME's plant at Loy Yang B. Buckley held the position of maintenance coordinator for EME at Loy Yang B and reported directly to Pearson. Nothing in this case turns on any distinction between the various corporate entities within the Edison group of companies and, where the context permits, I refer to them simply as 'Edison'. The other witness was David Nabulsi ('Nabulsi'), the sole director of a company called DJN Electrical &amp; Instrumentation Pty Ltd ('DJN'). Prior to August 2001, DJN regularly supplied services to Edison at Loy Yang B in its capacity as an electrical contractor.

6 In addition, the ACCC relied on an affidavit of Rodney McKemmish ('McKemmish') sworn 7 September 2006. Exhibit RMCK-3 to McKemmish's affidavit is his expert forensic report in relation to the authenticity and source of certain emails which were discovered by Edison and which are relevant to the ACCC's case against the CEPU. The affidavit was received in evidence subject to the CEPU's objection to those parts of the affidavit in which McKemmish purported to express an opinion identifying the author of certain emails. The objection is a good one and I uphold it. McKemmish is not in a position to give admissible evidence concerning the authorship of the emails. His evidence is only admissible to the extent to which he addresses the authenticity and technical source of the emails. Apart from this objection, the CEPU did not dispute McKemmish's evidence.

7 The CEPU did not call any witnesses or rely on any affidavit material in support of its case.

8 There are two main issues in this proceeding. The first concerns the nature, scope and terms of the contract, arrangement or understanding that was made or arrived at between the respondents. The ACCC submitted that the true nature, scope and terms of the contract, arrangement or understanding can be inferred from the circumstances surrounding a written heads of agreement between Edison and the CEPU, which was signed on behalf of Edison on 23 August 2001 ('the heads of agreement'). The ACCC's primary argument was that the contract, arrangement or understanding was not confined to the literal terms of the heads of agreement, and that it prevented or hindered Edison from acquiring services from electrical contractors including DJN because they did not have a certified agreement with the CEPU. Further, the ACCC argued that the contract, arrangement or understanding was given effect by Edison. Alternatively, the ACCC argued that the same consequences follow even if the contract, arrangement or understanding is entirely embodied in the heads of agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>Gibbins v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union (1986) 12 FCR 450</tocase>
<text>103 Section 45E was originally introduced into the TPA by the Trade Practices (Boycotts) Amendment Act 1980 (Cth). While there are minor differences in the drafting of that section in comparison to the current s 45E, it had essentially the same objects and a similar operation: see Gibbins v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union (1986) 12 FCR 450 (' Gibbins' ). The original s 45E was repealed by the Industrial Relations Reform Act 1993 (Cth). In 1996, s 45E was re-enacted it its current form by the Workplace Relations and Other Legislation Amendment Act 1996 (Cth). Section 45EA was also introduced by that Act.

105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

170 My conclusion regarding the scope of the contract, arrangement or understanding between Edison and the CEPU is similar to the conclusion reached by Smithers J in Gibbins , a case concerning the original form of s 45E. In Gibbins , the second respondent ('Borthwicks'), entered into an agreement with the Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union ('AMIEU') as a result of conciliation proceedings under the Conciliation and Arbitration Act 1904 (Cth). Essentially, the agreement provided that the Borthwicks would not 'invite or engage' carriers of livestock who were banned by the AMIEU to come onto its abattoir works to deliver stock. Smithers J observed at 467:
 
 'It is clear that the immediate purpose of including the provisions in the agreement was, with the consent of Borthwicks, to lessen the likelihood that banned carriers would come upon the abattoir and to ensure, again with Borthwicks' consent, that if they did the stock were not to be unloaded or killed by Borthwicks' Union employees. But it went further than that. It obviously was designed to prevent Borthwicks from engaging banned carriers for carrying services.' 


Smithers J held that the exclusionary purpose was part of a wider understanding between the parties, at 470-471:
 
 'It is clear that the conciliation agreement not only governs by its own strength but has given rise to an understanding of a slightly wider nature, namely by the exclusion from an invitation to come onto the works or from being engaged to come onto the works, not only of carriers who have passed the picket lines but to those who according to Union judgment have done so or have done the equivalent.' 


Smithers J found that the wider understanding arose out of the conciliation agreement and in connection with its implementation: at 472.

171 The CEPU submitted that the existence of an agreement or arrangement in the week of 13 August would render the subsequent heads of agreement a sham. The CEPU's submissions on this point are misguided. To adapt the words of Smithers J in Gibbins , the heads of agreement was expressed in its own terms, but it implemented a wider arrangement or understanding. In my opinion, Edison and the CEPU intended that the heads of agreement should be controlled by, and operate in accordance with, the arrangement that had been agreed upon by the parties and put into place in the week of 13 August.

172 The CEPU also argued that DJN's continued presence on site at Loy Yang B gives rise to an inference that the agreement was not intended to exclude DJN from continuing to supply services at Loy Yang B. The fact that DJN continued to perform some work on site at Loy Yang B in August and September 2001, under pre-existing contractual arrangements and as a subcontractor, does not affect my conclusion that the arrangement rendered DJN ineligible from continuing to supply services to Edison. Rather, as Burns' file note of the 9 August meeting shows, Edison implemented a process of 'grandfathering' DJN's existing contracts.

217 In Gibbins , Smithers J imposed liability on the union under s 80(1) of the TPA. His Honour found at 474 that it was 'beyond question' that the AMIEU, which was a party to a contract, arrangement or understanding which contravened s 45E, had aided, abetted, counselled and procured Borthwicks' contraventions. Then, as now, a union could not contravene s 45E as a principal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Corke Instrument Engineering Australia Pty Ltd (2005) 223 ALR 480</tocase>
<text>104 There is little judicial consideration of the current form of ss 45E and 45EA: cf Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Corke Instrument Engineering Australia Pty Ltd (2005) 223 ALR 480 ( 'Corke' ). There is, however, considerable authority in relation to phrases that occur in s 45E and in other provisions of Pt IV of the TPA. Those authorities are helpful in construing s 45E in a way that gives a consistent meaning to phrases that are used elsewhere in the TPA: see Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 381-382 [69] - [71] .

180 In closing submissions, senior counsel for the CEPU appeared to present an alternative argument that the second person must be 'in contemplation' of the parties at the time of making the agreement. He relied on Corke , where Finkelstein J refused to grant an interlocutory injunction in relation to an agreement that allegedly contravened s 45E. In my opinion, Corke does not provide any support for the argument. The provision in question in Corke obliged one of the respondents, Corke Instrument Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd ('Corke'), to negotiate a specific site agreement with the union for each construction project, and provided that the site agreement must be agreed before work commences on the project. His Honour observed that it was entirely by chance that the deed containing the provision was made after Corke had entered into a particular supply agreement. His Honour said that the purpose for the inclusion of the provision in the deed was no different from the purpose for its inclusion in an earlier certified agreement and it was not included for the purpose of interfering with the supply of services from Corke. In this context, his Honour observed that it was inherently unlikely that the plant owner who contracted with Corke for its services was even in the contemplation of the CEPU or Corke when the certified agreement was negotiated: at 484 [14]. The present case is very different. The parties clearly had in contemplation that the provision would prevent or hinder a defined class of electrical contractors from performing work at Loy Yang B.

181 In any event, I am satisfied on the balance of probabilities that the parties knew that DJN, in particular, would be prevented from supplying services to Edison under the arrangement. Nabulsi gave evidence that he had discussions with Mooney over the years about the possibility of DJN signing an EBA with the CEPU. Burns gave evidence that from time to time he and Mooney discussed which contractors were being engaged by Edison to carry out particular work at Loy Yang B, and whether those contractors had an EBA with the CEPU. The evidence clearly establishes that Mooney was in close discussion with Sutherland and Burns during the period between 13 August and 23 August 2001. I infer from this evidence that the CEPU was aware that DJN performed work at Loy Yang B, that it did not have an EBA with the CEPU, and that the provision would exclude DJN from working at Loy Yang B if it did not enter into an EBA with the CEPU.

182 There was some debate in the course of argument as to whether the purpose of the provision, as alleged by the ACCC, would fall within para (a) or para (b) of s 45E(3). The ACCC relied on both paragraphs. In my opinion, the purpose of the provision that I have found to exist falls within the scope of both paras (a) and (b). It is therefore unnecessary for me to resolve the question of which paragraph applies.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/28.html</AustLII>
<text>104 There is little judicial consideration of the current form of ss 45E and 45EA: cf Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Corke Instrument Engineering Australia Pty Ltd (2005) 223 ALR 480 ( 'Corke' ). There is, however, considerable authority in relation to phrases that occur in s 45E and in other provisions of Pt IV of the TPA. Those authorities are helpful in construing s 45E in a way that gives a consistent meaning to phrases that are used elsewhere in the TPA: see Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 381-382 [69] - [71] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472</tocase>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1678.html</AustLII>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

109 In Leahy , Merkel J discussed the concepts of 'arrangement' and 'understanding' where multiple parties were alleged to have been involved, in different capacities, in price fixing contravening s 45 of the TPA. In that case, the ACCC brought proceedings against eight corporations and eight individuals. A number of the respondents admitted to contraventions of the TPA. The remaining respondents did not seriously challenge the ACCC's case against the admitting respondents, but rather they sought to distinguish their actions from those of the admitting respondents. The contesting respondents submitted that, unlike the other respondents, they had not initiated any of the price increases in the pricing 'cycle' at the heart of the ACCC's case. While the contesting respondents did not dispute that price increases were communicated amongst competitors in the Ballarat petrol market, they argued that their price increases were the result of competitive market forces and not made pursuant to an understanding to increase petrol prices in the event of a 'price-increase call' by the initiating respondents. His Honour stated at 200 [54]:
 
 'It is well established that, for the purposes of ss 45(2) and 45A , the term "understanding" is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or arrangement. An understanding will usually, but may not necessarily, involve some reciprocity of obligation: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 at 360 (ACCC v Amcor); Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 397. At the least, there must be a meeting of minds of those said to be parties to the understanding and a consensus as to what is to be done; not merely a hope as to what might be done or might happen. Thus, ordinarily, an understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each party that the other party/parties will act in a particular way: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 149 ; (2003) 129 FCR 339 at [409] '.

110 On appeal, in Apco , the Full Court of this Court (Heerey, Hely and Gyles JJ) considered whether an understanding necessarily involves the making of a commitment to a particular course of action, as opposed to giving rise to a mere expectation or hope that a party will act in a certain way. After considering Merkel J's findings in Leahy , their Honours said at 43,234 - 43,235:
 
 'Whilst the appellants attacked the factual finding that the parties arrived at the price-fixing understanding outlined in [330] of the reasons for judgment, they did not dispute that the primary judge had enunciated the correct legal principles which are applicable in determining whether parties have entered into an understanding. In particular, the primary judge referred to the following observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 ; (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] (emphasis in original) which were specifically endorsed by the Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] : 
 
 
 
 "The cases require that at least one party 'assume an obligation' or give an 'assurance' or 'undertaking' that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have 'aroused' that expectation by things he said at the meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an 'understanding' in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word 'understanding' with the words 'agreement' and 'arrangement' and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required."
 
 
 
 The primary judge's inference at [371] that Anderson [the Director and General Manager of one of the respondent companies] expected that his competitors would hold their increased price for a time whilst he was deciding whether or not to match their prices represents Anderson's assessment of what was likely to occur, without any assurance being given to him that the competitors would act in that way. It is no more than what Lindgren J described as a "factual expectation" which falls short of an "understanding".' 


Special leave to appeal the Full Court's decision was refused by the High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v APCO Service Stations Pty Ltd [2006] HCATrans 272.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078</tocase>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

110 On appeal, in Apco , the Full Court of this Court (Heerey, Hely and Gyles JJ) considered whether an understanding necessarily involves the making of a commitment to a particular course of action, as opposed to giving rise to a mere expectation or hope that a party will act in a certain way. After considering Merkel J's findings in Leahy , their Honours said at 43,234 - 43,235:
 
 'Whilst the appellants attacked the factual finding that the parties arrived at the price-fixing understanding outlined in [330] of the reasons for judgment, they did not dispute that the primary judge had enunciated the correct legal principles which are applicable in determining whether parties have entered into an understanding. In particular, the primary judge referred to the following observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 ; (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] (emphasis in original) which were specifically endorsed by the Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] : 
 
 
 
 "The cases require that at least one party 'assume an obligation' or give an 'assurance' or 'undertaking' that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have 'aroused' that expectation by things he said at the meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an 'understanding' in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word 'understanding' with the words 'agreement' and 'arrangement' and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required."
 
 
 
 The primary judge's inference at [371] that Anderson [the Director and General Manager of one of the respondent companies] expected that his competitors would hold their increased price for a time whilst he was deciding whether or not to match their prices represents Anderson's assessment of what was likely to occur, without any assurance being given to him that the competitors would act in that way. It is no more than what Lindgren J described as a "factual expectation" which falls short of an "understanding".' 


Special leave to appeal the Full Court's decision was refused by the High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v APCO Service Stations Pty Ltd [2006] HCATrans 272.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.

113 In the present case, there were no detailed submissions on the meaning of 'arrangement' or 'understanding' for the purposes of ss 45E and 45EA. Senior counsel for the ACCC generally used the composite phrase 'contract, arrangement or understanding', while senior counsel for the CEPU tended to restrict his language to 'agreement'. In my opinion, there is no reason why the reasoning in Apco and Amcor should not apply. It follows that an 'arrangement' or 'understanding' for the purposes of ss 45E and 45EA must be proven by evidence of a consensus or meeting of minds between Edison and the CEPU under which one party or both parties committed to a particular course of action; it is not sufficient that there is a mere expectation that a party or parties will act in a certain way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383</tocase>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

106 The cases on s 45 of the TPA make it clear that for an arrangement or understanding to occur, there must be a 'meeting of the minds' of the parties: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done, not just a mere hope as to what might be done or might happen: Email at 385.

107 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434 (' Lutovi' ), the meaning of an 'arrangement' was considered in the context of s 260 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth). Gibbs and Mason JJ (Murphy J agreeing) said at 444:
 
 'In the context of s 260 an arrangement is something less than a binding contract or agreement, something in the nature of an understanding which may not be enforceable at law ( Newton v Federal Commissioner of Taxation). ... It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.' 


The High Court's formulation in Lutovi has been applied in the context of 'arrangement or understanding' under s 45 of the TPA: see, eg, Email at 396; and David Jones at 463-464. In Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 (' TNT' ), Franki J referred to the above passage from Lutovi and said at 25:
 
 'I lean with respect to the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd ... at 89; 17,842 where he said: 
 
 
 
 "I have to remember that the concept of an understanding is broad and flexible. It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct."'

109 In Leahy , Merkel J discussed the concepts of 'arrangement' and 'understanding' where multiple parties were alleged to have been involved, in different capacities, in price fixing contravening s 45 of the TPA. In that case, the ACCC brought proceedings against eight corporations and eight individuals. A number of the respondents admitted to contraventions of the TPA. The remaining respondents did not seriously challenge the ACCC's case against the admitting respondents, but rather they sought to distinguish their actions from those of the admitting respondents. The contesting respondents submitted that, unlike the other respondents, they had not initiated any of the price increases in the pricing 'cycle' at the heart of the ACCC's case. While the contesting respondents did not dispute that price increases were communicated amongst competitors in the Ballarat petrol market, they argued that their price increases were the result of competitive market forces and not made pursuant to an understanding to increase petrol prices in the event of a 'price-increase call' by the initiating respondents. His Honour stated at 200 [54]:
 
 'It is well established that, for the purposes of ss 45(2) and 45A , the term "understanding" is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or arrangement. An understanding will usually, but may not necessarily, involve some reciprocity of obligation: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 at 360 (ACCC v Amcor); Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 397. At the least, there must be a meeting of minds of those said to be parties to the understanding and a consensus as to what is to be done; not merely a hope as to what might be done or might happen. Thus, ordinarily, an understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each party that the other party/parties will act in a particular way: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 149 ; (2003) 129 FCR 339 at [409] '.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.

112 Parallel conduct can constitute circumstantial evidence from which an arrangement or understanding may be inferred: Email at 386. Where there is no direct evidence of an arrangement or understanding, an inference that such an arrangement or understanding existed may be drawn from evidence that the parties' conduct exhibits 'a concurrence of time, character, direction and result': David Jones at 468 applying R v Associated Northern Collieries [1911] HCA 73 ; (1911) 14 CLR 387 (' Northern Collieries' ) at 400. Inferences of an arrangement or understanding are apt to be drawn from circumstantial evidence when the facts are particularly within the knowledge of a party who is not called to give evidence: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 (' Jones v Dunkel' ); see also David Jones at 465.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446</tocase>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

107 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434 (' Lutovi' ), the meaning of an 'arrangement' was considered in the context of s 260 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth). Gibbs and Mason JJ (Murphy J agreeing) said at 444:
 
 'In the context of s 260 an arrangement is something less than a binding contract or agreement, something in the nature of an understanding which may not be enforceable at law ( Newton v Federal Commissioner of Taxation). ... It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.' 


The High Court's formulation in Lutovi has been applied in the context of 'arrangement or understanding' under s 45 of the TPA: see, eg, Email at 396; and David Jones at 463-464. In Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 (' TNT' ), Franki J referred to the above passage from Lutovi and said at 25:
 
 'I lean with respect to the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd ... at 89; 17,842 where he said: 
 
 
 
 "I have to remember that the concept of an understanding is broad and flexible. It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct."'

108 In David Jones at 463-464, Fisher J agreed with Franki J's comments in TNT and also favoured the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81.

112 Parallel conduct can constitute circumstantial evidence from which an arrangement or understanding may be inferred: Email at 386. Where there is no direct evidence of an arrangement or understanding, an inference that such an arrangement or understanding existed may be drawn from evidence that the parties' conduct exhibits 'a concurrence of time, character, direction and result': David Jones at 468 applying R v Associated Northern Collieries [1911] HCA 73 ; (1911) 14 CLR 387 (' Northern Collieries' ) at 400. Inferences of an arrangement or understanding are apt to be drawn from circumstantial evidence when the facts are particularly within the knowledge of a party who is not called to give evidence: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 (' Jones v Dunkel' ); see also David Jones at 465.

174 Under s 45E of the TPA, I am not limited to an examination of the words of cl 4.1. This is not a proceeding to enforce a contract. Section 45E is not concerned only with written agreements; it is also concerned with the making of an 'arrangement' or arriving at an 'understanding'. An arrangement or understanding may be informal and unenforceable: Lutovi at 444. The concept of an 'understanding' is a broad and flexible one: L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd , supra, at 89; TNT at 25; and David Jones at 463-464. For the reasons explained above, I am satisfied that there was a broader arrangement between the parties which overshadowed and controlled the language used in the heads of agreement. It was understood and agreed between the CEPU and Edison that the heads of agreement imposed an obligation on Edison not to retain electrical contractors at the Loy Yang B site if they did not have a current certified agreement with the CEPU, and that this is the way in which Edison would implement it. Nothing in cl 4.1 prevented Edison implementing its arrangement with the CEPU in this way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465</tocase>
<text>106 The cases on s 45 of the TPA make it clear that for an arrangement or understanding to occur, there must be a 'meeting of the minds' of the parties: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done, not just a mere hope as to what might be done or might happen: Email at 385.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609</tocase>
<text>40 Burns' file note of the 10 August teleconference states:
 
 'Telephone hook up R. Driscoll, C Sutherland, J Bacchi, C Weber (LV) BW, MP, WB &amp; PB 
 
 - Col outlined mtg above [arrowup] and proposed settlement. 
 
 1 Grandfather existing contracts 
 2.' 


The vertical arrow in the note points to the first part of the page that sets out Burns' note of the 9 August meeting: see [22] above.

41 In his evidence, Burns said that Sutherland outlined what had happened at the 9 August meeting and proposed that the issues be settled. There was then general discussion about the two issues that the CEPU had asked the company to address concerning site access and the requirement that contractors have a certified EBA in place with the CEPU. By the end of the meeting, Burns said that agreement was reached as to what Edison was going to do: 
 
 'We in essence agreed that we would only employ electrical contractors that had a certified EBA in place and that the one contractor that the only contractor that seemed to be impacted which was DJN, would continue the work which it had been commissioned to do until that had concluded.' 


Burns recollected that Pearson or Buckley mentioned during the teleconference that the only contractor who appeared to be affected by this agreement was DJN. Burns also gave evidence that the reference to 'Grandfather existing contracts' in his handwritten note referred to the fact that DJN would be permitted to continue work it had already been commissioned to do until that work was concluded.

42 Pearson's understanding of what was discussed in the teleconference was that Edison was minded to proceed down the path of entering into an agreement with the CEPU that would put a limitation on Loy Yang B maintenance, such that only electrical contractors who had certified agreements with the CEPU would be engaged. Pearson said it was explained that Edison was proceeding down this path in order to get the Simon Engineering site agreement for the peaker plant signed, so that construction of the plant could commence. Pearson also said that towards the end of the meeting, or just afterwards, Warrillow instructed him, and Buckley, that they were not to engage electrical contractors who did not have a certified agreement with the CEPU and that they should look at putting that instruction into place.

106 The cases on s 45 of the TPA make it clear that for an arrangement or understanding to occur, there must be a 'meeting of the minds' of the parties: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done, not just a mere hope as to what might be done or might happen: Email at 385.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/55.html</AustLII>
<text>107 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434 (' Lutovi' ), the meaning of an 'arrangement' was considered in the context of s 260 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth). Gibbs and Mason JJ (Murphy J agreeing) said at 444:
 
 'In the context of s 260 an arrangement is something less than a binding contract or agreement, something in the nature of an understanding which may not be enforceable at law ( Newton v Federal Commissioner of Taxation). ... It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.' 


The High Court's formulation in Lutovi has been applied in the context of 'arrangement or understanding' under s 45 of the TPA: see, eg, Email at 396; and David Jones at 463-464. In Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 (' TNT' ), Franki J referred to the above passage from Lutovi and said at 25:
 
 'I lean with respect to the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd ... at 89; 17,842 where he said: 
 
 
 
 "I have to remember that the concept of an understanding is broad and flexible. It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct."'

174 Under s 45E of the TPA, I am not limited to an examination of the words of cl 4.1. This is not a proceeding to enforce a contract. Section 45E is not concerned only with written agreements; it is also concerned with the making of an 'arrangement' or arriving at an 'understanding'. An arrangement or understanding may be informal and unenforceable: Lutovi at 444. The concept of an 'understanding' is a broad and flexible one: L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd , supra, at 89; TNT at 25; and David Jones at 463-464. For the reasons explained above, I am satisfied that there was a broader arrangement between the parties which overshadowed and controlled the language used in the heads of agreement. It was understood and agreed between the CEPU and Edison that the heads of agreement imposed an obligation on Edison not to retain electrical contractors at the Loy Yang B site if they did not have a current certified agreement with the CEPU, and that this is the way in which Edison would implement it. Nothing in cl 4.1 prevented Edison implementing its arrangement with the CEPU in this way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>107 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434 (' Lutovi' ), the meaning of an 'arrangement' was considered in the context of s 260 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth). Gibbs and Mason JJ (Murphy J agreeing) said at 444:
 
 'In the context of s 260 an arrangement is something less than a binding contract or agreement, something in the nature of an understanding which may not be enforceable at law ( Newton v Federal Commissioner of Taxation). ... It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.' 


The High Court's formulation in Lutovi has been applied in the context of 'arrangement or understanding' under s 45 of the TPA: see, eg, Email at 396; and David Jones at 463-464. In Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 (' TNT' ), Franki J referred to the above passage from Lutovi and said at 25:
 
 'I lean with respect to the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd ... at 89; 17,842 where he said: 
 
 
 
 "I have to remember that the concept of an understanding is broad and flexible. It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct."'

108 In David Jones at 463-464, Fisher J agreed with Franki J's comments in TNT and also favoured the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81.

130 The CEPU drew support for this argument from judicial consideration of the words 'particular persons' in s 4D of the TPA in Bullock v Federated Furnishing Trades Society of Australasia (1985) 5 FCR 464 (' Bullock' ); see also TNT at 75-76. Prior to 1986, s 4D referred to 'particular persons' as the target of the proscribed provision. In Bullock, the Full Court left open the question whether Gray J had been correct in limiting the words 'particular persons' in s 4D to 'persons whose identity is known or can be ascertained': at 473. In apparent response to the decisions in Bullock and TNT, the words 'or classes of persons' were added to s 4D by the Trade Practices Revision Act 1986 (Cth): see Gummow J's discussion in South Sydney at 589-590 [75]. The scope of s 45E has not been similarly expanded to include 'classes of persons'. According to senior counsel for the CEPU, it can therefore be inferred that the legislature did not intend to expand the scope of s 45E. Thus, it was submitted, the section requires the identification of a particular second person.

139 It is convenient to consider the ACCC's primary case, and the CEPU's response to it, before turning to consider the ACCC's alternative argument that in any event the heads of agreement contained a provision that contravened s 45E(3). For ease of reference, I will use the expression 'arrangement' rather than the more cumbersome 'contract, arrangement or understanding'. Obviously, the terms 'arrangement' and 'understanding' are much broader than the term 'contract', and they are often equated in the authorities: TNT at 25; and Amcor at 359-360 [75]. However, neither party suggested that anything turns on the differences that exist between the three concepts.

174 Under s 45E of the TPA, I am not limited to an examination of the words of cl 4.1. This is not a proceeding to enforce a contract. Section 45E is not concerned only with written agreements; it is also concerned with the making of an 'arrangement' or arriving at an 'understanding'. An arrangement or understanding may be informal and unenforceable: Lutovi at 444. The concept of an 'understanding' is a broad and flexible one: L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd , supra, at 89; TNT at 25; and David Jones at 463-464. For the reasons explained above, I am satisfied that there was a broader arrangement between the parties which overshadowed and controlled the language used in the heads of agreement. It was understood and agreed between the CEPU and Edison that the heads of agreement imposed an obligation on Edison not to retain electrical contractors at the Loy Yang B site if they did not have a current certified agreement with the CEPU, and that this is the way in which Edison would implement it. Nothing in cl 4.1 prevented Edison implementing its arrangement with the CEPU in this way.

222 As to whether the CEPU was involved in Edison's contravention of s 45EA, it is necessary to bear in mind the width of the concept of 'give effect to'. It is defined in s 4(1) as including the doing of 'an act or thing in pursuance of or in accordance with' the contract, arrangement or understanding. An act or thing may be done in accordance with a contract, arrangement or understanding even though the person who did that act or thing did not have the contract, arrangement or understanding in mind at the time: TNT at 68. Independent decisions made by parties to a contract, arrangement or understanding can nevertheless give effect to an arrangement made between them: Dowling v Dalgety Australia Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 109.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v APCO Service Stations Pty Ltd [2006] HCATrans 272</tocase>
<text>110 On appeal, in Apco , the Full Court of this Court (Heerey, Hely and Gyles JJ) considered whether an understanding necessarily involves the making of a commitment to a particular course of action, as opposed to giving rise to a mere expectation or hope that a party will act in a certain way. After considering Merkel J's findings in Leahy , their Honours said at 43,234 - 43,235:
 
 'Whilst the appellants attacked the factual finding that the parties arrived at the price-fixing understanding outlined in [330] of the reasons for judgment, they did not dispute that the primary judge had enunciated the correct legal principles which are applicable in determining whether parties have entered into an understanding. In particular, the primary judge referred to the following observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 ; (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] (emphasis in original) which were specifically endorsed by the Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] : 
 
 
 
 "The cases require that at least one party 'assume an obligation' or give an 'assurance' or 'undertaking' that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have 'aroused' that expectation by things he said at the meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an 'understanding' in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word 'understanding' with the words 'agreement' and 'arrangement' and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required."
 
 
 
 The primary judge's inference at [371] that Anderson [the Director and General Manager of one of the respondent companies] expected that his competitors would hold their increased price for a time whilst he was deciding whether or not to match their prices represents Anderson's assessment of what was likely to occur, without any assurance being given to him that the competitors would act in that way. It is no more than what Lindgren J described as a "factual expectation" which falls short of an "understanding".' 


Special leave to appeal the Full Court's decision was refused by the High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v APCO Service Stations Pty Ltd [2006] HCATrans 272.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344</tocase>
<text>109 In Leahy , Merkel J discussed the concepts of 'arrangement' and 'understanding' where multiple parties were alleged to have been involved, in different capacities, in price fixing contravening s 45 of the TPA. In that case, the ACCC brought proceedings against eight corporations and eight individuals. A number of the respondents admitted to contraventions of the TPA. The remaining respondents did not seriously challenge the ACCC's case against the admitting respondents, but rather they sought to distinguish their actions from those of the admitting respondents. The contesting respondents submitted that, unlike the other respondents, they had not initiated any of the price increases in the pricing 'cycle' at the heart of the ACCC's case. While the contesting respondents did not dispute that price increases were communicated amongst competitors in the Ballarat petrol market, they argued that their price increases were the result of competitive market forces and not made pursuant to an understanding to increase petrol prices in the event of a 'price-increase call' by the initiating respondents. His Honour stated at 200 [54]:
 
 'It is well established that, for the purposes of ss 45(2) and 45A , the term "understanding" is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or arrangement. An understanding will usually, but may not necessarily, involve some reciprocity of obligation: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 at 360 (ACCC v Amcor); Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 397. At the least, there must be a meeting of minds of those said to be parties to the understanding and a consensus as to what is to be done; not merely a hope as to what might be done or might happen. Thus, ordinarily, an understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each party that the other party/parties will act in a particular way: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 149 ; (2003) 129 FCR 339 at [409] '.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.

113 In the present case, there were no detailed submissions on the meaning of 'arrangement' or 'understanding' for the purposes of ss 45E and 45EA. Senior counsel for the ACCC generally used the composite phrase 'contract, arrangement or understanding', while senior counsel for the CEPU tended to restrict his language to 'agreement'. In my opinion, there is no reason why the reasoning in Apco and Amcor should not apply. It follows that an 'arrangement' or 'understanding' for the purposes of ss 45E and 45EA must be proven by evidence of a consensus or meeting of minds between Edison and the CEPU under which one party or both parties committed to a particular course of action; it is not sufficient that there is a mere expectation that a party or parties will act in a certain way.

139 It is convenient to consider the ACCC's primary case, and the CEPU's response to it, before turning to consider the ACCC's alternative argument that in any event the heads of agreement contained a provision that contravened s 45E(3). For ease of reference, I will use the expression 'arrangement' rather than the more cumbersome 'contract, arrangement or understanding'. Obviously, the terms 'arrangement' and 'understanding' are much broader than the term 'contract', and they are often equated in the authorities: TNT at 25; and Amcor at 359-360 [75]. However, neither party suggested that anything turns on the differences that exist between the three concepts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140</tocase>
<text>111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206</tocase>
<text>109 In Leahy , Merkel J discussed the concepts of 'arrangement' and 'understanding' where multiple parties were alleged to have been involved, in different capacities, in price fixing contravening s 45 of the TPA. In that case, the ACCC brought proceedings against eight corporations and eight individuals. A number of the respondents admitted to contraventions of the TPA. The remaining respondents did not seriously challenge the ACCC's case against the admitting respondents, but rather they sought to distinguish their actions from those of the admitting respondents. The contesting respondents submitted that, unlike the other respondents, they had not initiated any of the price increases in the pricing 'cycle' at the heart of the ACCC's case. While the contesting respondents did not dispute that price increases were communicated amongst competitors in the Ballarat petrol market, they argued that their price increases were the result of competitive market forces and not made pursuant to an understanding to increase petrol prices in the event of a 'price-increase call' by the initiating respondents. His Honour stated at 200 [54]:
 
 'It is well established that, for the purposes of ss 45(2) and 45A , the term "understanding" is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or arrangement. An understanding will usually, but may not necessarily, involve some reciprocity of obligation: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 at 360 (ACCC v Amcor); Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 397. At the least, there must be a meeting of minds of those said to be parties to the understanding and a consensus as to what is to be done; not merely a hope as to what might be done or might happen. Thus, ordinarily, an understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each party that the other party/parties will act in a particular way: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 149 ; (2003) 129 FCR 339 at [409] '.

111 As these passages from Leahy and Apco indicate, the authorities have expressly refrained from holding that the consensus or meeting of minds required by the words 'arrangement' or 'understanding' must involve a reciprocity of obligation. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Amcor Printing Papers Group Ltd (2000) 169 ALR 344 (' Amcor' ) at 359-360 [75], Sackville J said:
 
 'An arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2) of the TP Act is apt to describe something less than a binding contract or agreement: Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Qld) Pty Ltd (1975) 5 ALR 465; 24 FLR 286 at 290 1 (Aust Ind Ct, FC) per Smithers J. However, in order for there to be an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2), there must be a meeting of the minds of those said to be parties to the arrangement or understanding. There must be a consensus as to what is to be done and not merely a hope as to what might be done or happen: Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 at 385 (Lockhart J); Ira Berk at FLR 291 per Smithers J. Ordinarily, an arrangement or understanding involves communication between the parties arousing expectations in each that the other will act in a particular way: Email at 395. There is no necessity for an element of mutual commitment between the parties to an arrangement or understanding, although in practice such an arrangement or understanding would ordinarily involve reciprocity of obligation: Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230 1; 116 ALR 643 per Lockhart J.' 


There are, however, several cases in which the courts have said that an assumption of mutual obligations or reciprocal commitments will be the common situation: eg Trade Practices Commission v Parkfield Operations Pty Ltd (1985) 5 FCR 140 at 144. In Trade Practices Commission v Service Station Association Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 206 at 230-231 and 238, the Full Court endorsed Lockhart J's observation in Email at 397 that it is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be an understanding involving a commitment by one party as to the way it should behave, without some reciprocal obligation by the other party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Associated Northern Collieries [1911] HCA 73 ; (1911) 14 CLR 387</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1911/73.html</AustLII>
<text>73 On Monday 20 August, Sutherland sent an email to Mighell which stated:
 
 'Dean - Attached is a draft agreement as prepared by our solicitors. Please call me call me on Tuesday, if you can. 
 
 Regards 
 Col [Sutherland] '

74 The email attached a draft heads of agreement between Edison and the CEPU that had been prepared by Corrs. The draft heads of agreement was phrased in language that differed considerably from the 13 August letter. Clause 4.1 of the draft heads of agreement provided:
 
 
 '4 THE COMPANY SHALL 
 
 
 
 
 
 4.1 The Company [Edison] shall request that companies that: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) are contracted to work for the Company at the Site; and 
 (b) who employ people whose employment is governed by the National Electrical, Electronic and Communications Contracting Industry Award 1998; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 have acceptable industrial arrangements in place before work is commenced.'

75 Sutherland gave evidence that he thought that the draft heads of agreement would be 'the solution' he and Burns were looking for. He was not examined on whether he spoke to Mighell on Tuesday 21 August as foreshadowed in his 20 August email, although Sutherland confirmed that it was his intention to speak to him the day after sending the email.

77 On 23 August, an email was sent to Burns' email address at 3.49 pm from an officer of the CEPU, Jesse Maddison ('the CEPU's email'). The CEPU's email stated:
 
 'Col [Sutherland] , 
 Please find attached document as discussed. 
 
 Peter [Mooney]
 
 * ==================== * 
 Jesse Maddison 
 Industrial Officer 
 Electrical Trades Union of Australia 
 516-520 Swanson Street 
 Carlton South VIC 3053'

78 A marked-up version of the draft heads of agreement was attached to the CEPU's email. An additional sentence had been added to cl 4.1, which is of particular significance in the present case. As revised, cl 4 provided:
 
 
 '4 THE COMPANY SHALL 
 
 
 
 
 
 4.1 The Company shall request that companies that: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) are contracted to work for the Company at the Site; and 
 (b) who employ people whose employment is governed by the National Electrical, Electronic and Communications Contracting Industry Award 1998; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 have acceptable industrial arrangements in place before work is commenced. What constitutes acceptable industrial arrangements includes having a current certified agreement with the union. ' 
 


 
Sutherland was not asked any questions about the discussion with Mooney that Mooney refers to in the CEPU's email.

79 Upon receipt of the CEPU's email, Burns and Sutherland discussed Edison's proposed response. They agreed that the proposed changes should be accepted and a response put back to the CEPU as a matter of urgency. Sutherland recalled thinking that he had had enough of this issue and it was of paramount concern to press on in order to get the Simon Engineering site agreement signed. Burns said that he was standing beside Sutherland as Sutherland dictated the reply email to Ms Jongerius, Burns' personal assistant. Sutherland said that they discussed the response by telephone he said he was in Melbourne but confirmed that the actual words of the email were at his suggestion. I prefer, and accept, Burns' evidence.

80 The reply email was sent to the CEPU from Burns' email address at 4.19 pm. It stated:
 
 'Urgent Attention: Dean Mighell, Peter Mooney 
 
 This note is to confirm Edison Mission Energy's acceptance of your attached document (no changes made by EME) as the text of our Agreement pertaining to contract labour on the proviso that the Simon Engineering Valley Power Site Agreement is appropriately signed today. Our signed copy of the Contract Labour Agreement will be delivered to your office tomorrow morning in exchange for a copy of the signed Simon Engineering EBA. 
 
 Regards, 
 Col Sutherland\Paul Burns.'

81 Burns said that he understood that the revised cl 4.1 specified that an EBA certified with the union would be a prerequisite for the contractors that Edison would employ. He considered that cl 4.1 represented a change in Edison's practices, as Edison had not previously insisted that contractors have a certified EBA with the union in place prior to carrying out work at the Loy Yang B site. He said that Pearson and Buckley would implement the change because maintenance work was undertaken by their department.

112 Parallel conduct can constitute circumstantial evidence from which an arrangement or understanding may be inferred: Email at 386. Where there is no direct evidence of an arrangement or understanding, an inference that such an arrangement or understanding existed may be drawn from evidence that the parties' conduct exhibits 'a concurrence of time, character, direction and result': David Jones at 468 applying R v Associated Northern Collieries [1911] HCA 73 ; (1911) 14 CLR 387 (' Northern Collieries' ) at 400. Inferences of an arrangement or understanding are apt to be drawn from circumstantial evidence when the facts are particularly within the knowledge of a party who is not called to give evidence: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 (' Jones v Dunkel' ); see also David Jones at 465.

121 In many cases it will be necessary and appropriate to infer the subjective purpose from evidence of the conduct of the parties: see Northern Collieries at 402 per Isaacs J. Statements as to purpose from the witness box may be highly probative, but they must be tested closely and received with great caution: ASX Operations Pty Ltd v Pont Data Australia Pty Ltd (No 1) (1990) 27 FCR 460 ( 'Pont Data' ) at 482-483.

163 Sutherland's covering email to Mighell on 20 August said:
 
 'Dean Attached is the draft agreement as prepared by our solicitors. Please call me on Tuesday, if you can. 
 
 Regards 
 
 Col' 


The terms of this email indicate Sutherland had previously discussed the question of a draft agreement with Mighell and that Mighell was aware that a draft agreement between Edison and the CEPU dealing with contract labour was being prepared by Edison's solicitors.

164 It is clear that Sutherland was in direct discussion with CEPU officers about the heads of agreement. In addition to the suggestion in the 20 August email that Mighell should call Sutherland on Tuesday, the CEPU's email of 23 August shows that Sutherland was in direct discussion with Mooney about the heads of agreement. Between 20 August and 23 August, most probably on 23 August, Sutherland told Burns that the way the draft heads of agreement was worded was not satisfactory to the CEPU because it did not give the union anything. This exchange confirms that Sutherland was in direct discussion with Mooney, and perhaps other CEPU officers, about the heads of agreement.

165 In my opinion, the fact that Edison sought and obtained Corrs' assistance in drafting the heads of agreement in the week of 13 August does not alter the probability that the 13 August letter was dispatched by Sutherland on 13 August. It is not uncommon for those charged with finding a solution to a commercial problem to arrange a solution and then seek legal advice in relation to the documentation of that solution, especially when the matter is urgent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/8.html</AustLII>
<text>112 Parallel conduct can constitute circumstantial evidence from which an arrangement or understanding may be inferred: Email at 386. Where there is no direct evidence of an arrangement or understanding, an inference that such an arrangement or understanding existed may be drawn from evidence that the parties' conduct exhibits 'a concurrence of time, character, direction and result': David Jones at 468 applying R v Associated Northern Collieries [1911] HCA 73 ; (1911) 14 CLR 387 (' Northern Collieries' ) at 400. Inferences of an arrangement or understanding are apt to be drawn from circumstantial evidence when the facts are particularly within the knowledge of a party who is not called to give evidence: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 (' Jones v Dunkel' ); see also David Jones at 465.

158 Senior counsel for the ACCC urged me to apply the principles enunciated by the High Court in Jones v Dunkel to support the inference that Edison and the CEPU made an arrangement to the effect alleged by the ACCC. While it is clearly open to me to infer from the CEPU's failure to call evidence from key players at the CEPU who would have direct knowledge of the events in question that those witnesses would not assist the CEPU's case, there are limits to the Jones v Dunkel principle. The principle allows me to draw inferences that are open on the evidence more confidently than might otherwise be the case; but it cannot be used to make up for gaps in the evidence. In this case, the inferences that I have drawn from the evidence are so clear that I do not need to rely upon Jones v Dunkel . It is, nonetheless, correct that the absence of evidence adduced by the CEPU from Mighell and Mooney allows me to infer with greater confidence that the CEPU received the letter of 13 August from Sutherland and that it did so before Mooney signed the Simon Engineering MOU on 15 August. More generally, the absence of evidence from the CEPU allows me to conclude, more confidently, that Edison had communicated to the CEPU by 15 August the fact that Edison agreed to the CEPU's requirement that electrical contractors not be permitted to perform work at Loy Yang B unless they had a current certified agreement with the CEPU.

159 The CEPU advanced a series of reasons why I should infer that the 13 August letter was not sent to the CEPU.

160 First, it argued that to infer that the 13 August letter was sent is inconsistent with the fact that Burns and Sutherland agreed to seek advice from Corrs on 10 August or in the week of 13 August. Sutherland gave evidence that he recalled having some discussions by telephone with Burns at Loy Yang B and arising from those discussions they thought that Edison should get some advice from Corrs. He said that Burns agreed to approach Corrs to get the advice. He also said that he believed his discussion with Burns by telephone took place on 10 August and that the proposed legal advice was to relate to both the site access issue and the electrical contractors issue. Sutherland said that Burns made the contact with Corrs, although Sutherland was involved in an initial meeting with Corrs. Sutherland confirmed that Corrs drafted the heads of agreement. On the other hand, Burns said he was not involved in giving any instructions to Corrs to prepare the draft heads of agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>News Ltd v South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd [2003] HCA 45 ; (2003) 215 CLR 563</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/45.html</AustLII>
<text>114 Section 45E is directed at a contract, arrangement or understanding containing a provision which has been included for a proscribed purpose, or for purposes including the proscribed purpose. The test of 'purpose' is a subjective test; it is determined by examining the subjective purposes of the parties for including the provision in the contract, arrangement or understanding: News Ltd v South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd [2003] HCA 45 ; (2003) 215 CLR 563 (' South Sydney' ) at 573 [18] per Gleeson CJ, at 580 [43] per McHugh J, at 585-587 [60], [62]-[63] per Gummow J, and at 636-637 [212] per Callinan J; and Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) 19 FCR 10 (' Hughes' ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) 19 FCR 10</tocase>
<text>114 Section 45E is directed at a contract, arrangement or understanding containing a provision which has been included for a proscribed purpose, or for purposes including the proscribed purpose. The test of 'purpose' is a subjective test; it is determined by examining the subjective purposes of the parties for including the provision in the contract, arrangement or understanding: News Ltd v South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd [2003] HCA 45 ; (2003) 215 CLR 563 (' South Sydney' ) at 573 [18] per Gleeson CJ, at 580 [43] per McHugh J, at 585-587 [60], [62]-[63] per Gummow J, and at 636-637 [212] per Callinan J; and Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) 19 FCR 10 (' Hughes' ).

125 In Pont Data , the Full Court considered the approach to the determination of purpose under s 4F which, like s 45E(3), operates where a particular provision was included in a contract, arrangement or understanding for a proscribed purpose. Their Honours said at 476:
 
 'In its operation upon provisions stated to have a particular purpose, s 4F uses the words "the provision was included in the contract ... for that purpose or for purposes that included or include that purpose". This indicates that s 4F, in this operation, requires one to look to the purposes of the individuals by whom the provision was included in the contract, arrangement or understanding in question. It therefore directs attention to the "subjective" purposes of those individuals.' 


The Court adopted the test of purpose as construed by Toohey J in Hughes at 37-38, where his Honour said:
 
 'I accept the view that it is the subjective purpose of those engaging in the relevant conduct with which the court is concerned. All other considerations aside, the use in s 45(2) of "purpose" and "effect" tends to suggest that a subjective approach is intended by the former expression. The application of a subjective test does not exclude a consideration of the circumstances surrounding the reaching of the understanding.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tillmanns Butcheries Pty Ltd v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union (1979) 27 ALR 367</tocase>
<text>115 The proscribed purpose can be one of a number of purposes, but it must be an operative purpose. In argument, senior counsel for the ACCC seemed to suggest that s 45E imposes a lower threshold than this, relying on the absence of the word 'substantial' in s 45E and the inapplicability of s 4F to ss 45E(3). Section 4F(1) provides that a reference to the 'purpose' of a provision of a contract, arrangement or understanding means the purpose, or one of the purposes, for including the provision, so long as it was or is a 'substantial purpose'. While it is true that s 4F does not apply to s 45E(3), this does not mean that an incidental purpose, which is not an operative purpose, will be sufficient to satisfy s 45E. Like s 45E(3), s 45D(1) is outside the ambit of s 4F and does not contain any explicit requirement that the purpose be a 'substantial' purpose. The High Court has construed s 45D(1) as requiring that the purpose be an operative subjective purpose: Tillmanns Butcheries Pty Ltd v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union (1979) 27 ALR 367 at 382-383 per Deane J. In my opinion, s 45E(3) should be construed in the same way. The reference to 'purpose' in s 45E connotes an operative subjective purpose.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd [2001] FCA 862 ; (2001) 111 FCR 456</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/862.html</AustLII>
<text>116 The issue of 'purpose' was investigated by the High Court in South Sydney in the context of s 45 and s 4D of the TPA. The case concerned a sporting club, South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd ('Souths'), which alleged that News Ltd and the Australian Rugby Football League Ltd ('ARL') had entered into a contract, arrangement or understanding in contravention of s 45 of the TPA. The alleged agreement between News Ltd and ARL was for the merger of two rugby league competitions. It provided for a unified rugby league competition to be conducted between, ultimately, fourteen teams only. The trial judge held that although the fourteen-team term was part of a contract, arrangement or understanding made between News Ltd and ARL, it did not have the purpose of preventing, restricting or limiting the supply or acquisition of services from particular persons or classes of persons. The Full Court overturned the trial judge's decision (Merkel and Moore JJ, Heerey J dissenting): see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd [2001] FCA 862 ; (2001) 111 FCR 456. Merkel J found that the trial judge had conflated the purpose of the merger, joint venture and regional participation provisions of the agreement, with the purpose of the fourteen-team term provision: at 522-523 [264]. Merkel J held at 531 [295] that the agreement had the purpose of preventing the supply or acquisition of services from a particular class of persons by restricting or limiting supply or acquisition to or from the clubs or entities selected to be included in the merged competition. Moore J found that by operation of the fourteen-team term, the services supplied by Souths and other affected clubs would be limited and restricted: at 501-502 [186]. In dissent, Heerey J held that the exclusion of clubs from the merged competition was not a purpose at all: at 474 [78]. Heerey J agreed with the trial judge that while the fourteen-team term limited, and was intended to limit, the number of clubs in the competition, it did not follow that the provision was included for the purpose of preventing the supply of services to, or the acquisition of services from, clubs in excess of the fourteen: at 467 [37].

117 The High Court overturned the Full Court's decision (Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Callinan JJ, Kirby J dissenting). Each of their Honours' separate reasons for judgment considered the proper approach to assessing the 'purpose' of a provision in a contract, arrangement or understanding for the purposes of ss 45 and 4D of the TPA. Gleeson CJ stressed the distinction between the purpose and the motive for including a provision in a contract, arrangement or understanding at 573 [18]:
 
 '... Purpose is to be distinguished from motive. The purpose of conduct is the end sought to be accomplished by the conduct. The motive for conduct is the reason for seeking that end. The appropriate description or characterisation of the end sought to be accomplished (purpose), as distinct from the reason for seeking that end (motive), may depend upon the legislative or other context in which the task is undertaken... [I]n the context of competition law, it is necessary to identify purpose by describing what is sought to be achieved by reference to what is relevant in market terms. The purpose of the fourteen team term was the objective, in relation to the nature of their business arrangements, that News and ARL sought to achieve; not the reason why they sought to achieve that objective. They may have had different, and multiple, reasons for their conduct. The manifest effect of a provision in an agreement, in a given case, may be the clearest indication of its purpose. In other cases, it may be difficult, or even impossible, to determine the purpose (of a kind relevant to the operation of the Act) of a provision in a written contract merely by reading the document. And, of course, the legislation deals with contracts, arrangements or understandings.' 


His Honour found that, in the circumstances of the case, it was necessary for the agreement to state how many clubs would participate in the merged competition, and by selecting fourteen as the number News Ltd and ARL did not have a purpose of excluding any particular club or clubs: at 575 [23] and at 576 [27].

118 While the manifest effect of the provision may provide, as Gleeson CJ said, the clearest indication of subjective purpose, care must be taken that evidence of the effect of a provision does not render the test an objective one. Gummow J warned against this danger at 586 [63]. It must be kept in mind that the effect that the parties sought to achieve through inclusion of the provision in a contract, arrangement or understanding is crucial to the test of subjective purpose.

119 Both McHugh and Gummow JJ expressed some hesitation about determining purpose under s 4D by reference to the subjective purpose of the makers of the provision, but in the end they both accepted the correctness of the subjective interpretation of the section: at 580 [41]-[43] per McHugh J and at 585 [59]-[60] per Gummow J, cf Kirby J at 606 [130]. McHugh J agreed with Gummow J that the trial judge applied a subjective test of purpose and his findings should be upheld: at 581 [46].

120 Section 45E(3) requires consideration of the subjective purpose for inclusion of the provision in a contract, arrangement or understanding, not the purpose of the contract, arrangement or understanding as a whole. As Callinan J said in South Sydney at 638 [216] in relation to purpose under s 45:
 
 'It is the purpose of the provision that is important. The discovery of that purpose is by no means necessarily to be gained by an examination of the provision itself only. As with any term of an agreement or arrangement, a provision may, sometimes must, be read with, and seen for its true meaning, effect and purpose, the relevant agreement or arrangement as a whole.' 


Gummow J agreed with Callinan J on this point: see at 587 [65].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>ASX Operations Pty Ltd v Pont Data Australia Pty Ltd (No 1) (1990) 27 FCR 460</tocase>
<text>121 In many cases it will be necessary and appropriate to infer the subjective purpose from evidence of the conduct of the parties: see Northern Collieries at 402 per Isaacs J. Statements as to purpose from the witness box may be highly probative, but they must be tested closely and received with great caution: ASX Operations Pty Ltd v Pont Data Australia Pty Ltd (No 1) (1990) 27 FCR 460 ( 'Pont Data' ) at 482-483.

125 In Pont Data , the Full Court considered the approach to the determination of purpose under s 4F which, like s 45E(3), operates where a particular provision was included in a contract, arrangement or understanding for a proscribed purpose. Their Honours said at 476:
 
 'In its operation upon provisions stated to have a particular purpose, s 4F uses the words "the provision was included in the contract ... for that purpose or for purposes that included or include that purpose". This indicates that s 4F, in this operation, requires one to look to the purposes of the individuals by whom the provision was included in the contract, arrangement or understanding in question. It therefore directs attention to the "subjective" purposes of those individuals.' 


The Court adopted the test of purpose as construed by Toohey J in Hughes at 37-38, where his Honour said:
 
 'I accept the view that it is the subjective purpose of those engaging in the relevant conduct with which the court is concerned. All other considerations aside, the use in s 45(2) of "purpose" and "effect" tends to suggest that a subjective approach is intended by the former expression. The application of a subjective test does not exclude a consideration of the circumstances surrounding the reaching of the understanding.'

126 On the facts in Pont Data , the relevant provisions were included in the agreements because one of the parties, ASX Operations Pty Ltd, had insisted upon their inclusion. The other party, Pont Data Australia Pty Ltd, had objected to the inclusion of the provisions. In those circumstances, the Court considered that it was appropriate to look to the purposes of the party as a result of whose efforts the provisions were included: at 477. In the present case, the CEPU instigated the requirement that resulted in the provision, but neither party submitted that either Edison or the CEPU objected to its inclusion. Thus, in my view, it is appropriate to consider the subjective purposes of both Edison and the CEPU in determining whether the provision was included for the proscribed purpose.

127 I reject the CEPU's submission that s 45E requires consideration of the subjective purposes of Edison, to the exclusion of the CEPU's purposes. The language of the section does not suggest that the inquiry as to purpose is limited to a consideration of the purpose of the party to the contract, arrangement or understanding upon which liability is directly imposed. In my opinion, the subjective purposes of each of the parties to a contract, arrangement or understanding are relevant to the determination of the purpose for which that provision was included. I doubt that s 45E requires the Court to search, perhaps vainly, for a common purpose: Pont Data at 477; see also South Sydney per McHugh J at 579 [38]. However, I do not need to express any final view on this issue because I have concluded on the evidence that there was no relevant disparity between the CEPU's purpose and Edison's purpose for including the provision.

133 In any event, in Pont Data , the Full Court considered the phrase 'particular persons or classes of persons' in the context of s 4D. The Court found that the phrase allowed for the identification of persons by reference to a negative characterisation; namely, persons who may not be supplied with information unless they accepted and became bound by the restraints imposed by the agreements at issue. The Full Court said at 488:
 
 'It was said [by the appellants] that the persons or classes excluded must still be "identified" if s 4D is to apply. That may be conceded, but they are identified, in the present case, by the characteristic that they may not be supplied with the information in question, unless they accept and become bound by the restraints imposed by the Dynamic Agreement. Such persons come within a particular category or description defined by a collective formula: cf Pearks v Moseley, Re Moseley's Trusts (1980) 5 App Case 714 at 723. They ordinarily would be treated as constituting a particular class, even though at any one time the identity of all the members of the class might not readily be ascertainable. What distinguishes the class and makes it particular is that its members are objects of an anti-competitive purpose, with which s 4D is concerned.'

134 In Rural Press , the High Court did not find any error in the Full Court's conclusion in Pont Data that a particular class can be defined by its exclusion from supply or acquisition: at 90-91 [88] per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, see also Gleeson CJ and Callinan J at 62 [7]; and Gummow J in South Sydney at 590 [77].

135 It follows that, if and to the extent that s 45E requires the second person to be particularly or specifically identified, that requirement can be satisfied by the use of a negative or exclusionary formula, as in Pont Data .

136 It was not in dispute that there was a contract, arrangement or understanding between Edison and the CEPU in relation to Edison's engagement of electrical contractors to perform work at the Loy Yang B site. The parties differed about the nature, scope and content of that contract, arrangement or understanding.

137 As I have already noted, the ACCC put its case in essentially two ways. Its primary case was that prior to 23 August 2001 Edison and the CEPU made a contract or arrangement, or arrived at an understanding, that all electrical contractors performing work at Loy Yang B must have a current certified agreement with the CEPU prior to commencing work at the site. The ACCC contended that this contract, arrangement or understanding was broader than, and overshadowed and controlled, the provision that was subsequently inserted in the heads of agreement.

179 Section 45E does not require that the provision be included for the purpose of preventing or hindering a person who is particularly or specifically identified. It is sufficient for the purposes of s 45E that the 'second person' be identified by reference to a group of persons who possess a particular characteristic: Pont Data at 488. Here, the relevant group of persons comprised electrical contractors performing, or who wished to perform, work at Loy Yang B who did not have a current certified agreement with the CEPU. The provision in question here specifically identifies and defines the particular group of persons from whom Edison agreed to refuse to acquire services.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Devenish v Jewel Food Stores Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 7 ; (1991) 172 CLR 32</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/7.html</AustLII>
<text>128 In the context of Pt IV of the TPA, 'preventing' and 'hindering' commonly refer to conduct which has the object of ceasing the supply or acquisition of goods or services. 'Hindering' has been given a broad construction by the courts; the concept encompasses conduct which in any way affects to an appreciable extent the ease of the usual way of supplying or acquiring an article: Devenish v Jewel Food Stores Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 7 ; (1991) 172 CLR 32 (' Devenish' ) at 45-46 per Mason CJ. Preventing or hindering can be engaged in by threat or verbal intimidation, as well as by physical interference with the actual activities: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1980) 43 FLR 129 at 153. The concept is not to be limited by any pre-conceived notion of a 'secondary boycott': see Devenish at 41-42 per Mason CJ, at 51-52 per Deane J, and at 58 per Toohey J; Australian Builders' Labourers' Federated Union of Workers Western Australian Branch v J-Corp Pty Ltd (1993) 42 FCR 452 at 459 per Lockhart and Gummow JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1980) 43 FLR 129</tocase>
<text>128 In the context of Pt IV of the TPA, 'preventing' and 'hindering' commonly refer to conduct which has the object of ceasing the supply or acquisition of goods or services. 'Hindering' has been given a broad construction by the courts; the concept encompasses conduct which in any way affects to an appreciable extent the ease of the usual way of supplying or acquiring an article: Devenish v Jewel Food Stores Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 7 ; (1991) 172 CLR 32 (' Devenish' ) at 45-46 per Mason CJ. Preventing or hindering can be engaged in by threat or verbal intimidation, as well as by physical interference with the actual activities: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1980) 43 FLR 129 at 153. The concept is not to be limited by any pre-conceived notion of a 'secondary boycott': see Devenish at 41-42 per Mason CJ, at 51-52 per Deane J, and at 58 per Toohey J; Australian Builders' Labourers' Federated Union of Workers Western Australian Branch v J-Corp Pty Ltd (1993) 42 FCR 452 at 459 per Lockhart and Gummow JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Builders' Labourers' Federated Union of Workers Western Australian Branch v J-Corp Pty Ltd (1993) 42 FCR 452</tocase>
<text>128 In the context of Pt IV of the TPA, 'preventing' and 'hindering' commonly refer to conduct which has the object of ceasing the supply or acquisition of goods or services. 'Hindering' has been given a broad construction by the courts; the concept encompasses conduct which in any way affects to an appreciable extent the ease of the usual way of supplying or acquiring an article: Devenish v Jewel Food Stores Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 7 ; (1991) 172 CLR 32 (' Devenish' ) at 45-46 per Mason CJ. Preventing or hindering can be engaged in by threat or verbal intimidation, as well as by physical interference with the actual activities: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1980) 43 FLR 129 at 153. The concept is not to be limited by any pre-conceived notion of a 'secondary boycott': see Devenish at 41-42 per Mason CJ, at 51-52 per Deane J, and at 58 per Toohey J; Australian Builders' Labourers' Federated Union of Workers Western Australian Branch v J-Corp Pty Ltd (1993) 42 FCR 452 at 459 per Lockhart and Gummow JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Bullock v Federated Furnishing Trades Society of Australasia (1985) 5 FCR 464</tocase>
<text>130 The CEPU drew support for this argument from judicial consideration of the words 'particular persons' in s 4D of the TPA in Bullock v Federated Furnishing Trades Society of Australasia (1985) 5 FCR 464 (' Bullock' ); see also TNT at 75-76. Prior to 1986, s 4D referred to 'particular persons' as the target of the proscribed provision. In Bullock, the Full Court left open the question whether Gray J had been correct in limiting the words 'particular persons' in s 4D to 'persons whose identity is known or can be ascertained': at 473. In apparent response to the decisions in Bullock and TNT, the words 'or classes of persons' were added to s 4D by the Trade Practices Revision Act 1986 (Cth): see Gummow J's discussion in South Sydney at 589-590 [75]. The scope of s 45E has not been similarly expanded to include 'classes of persons'. According to senior counsel for the CEPU, it can therefore be inferred that the legislature did not intend to expand the scope of s 45E. Thus, it was submitted, the section requires the identification of a particular second person.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/75.html</AustLII>
<text>105 The authorities on s 45 of the TPA explain the concept of a 'contract, arrangement or understanding' as it is used in Pt IV: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' Leahy' ); Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] ATPR 42-078 (' Apco' ); Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 (' Rural Press' ); Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 43 FLR 383 (' Email' ); and Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd (1986) 13 FCR 446 (' David Jones' ). Some assistance is also to be gained from authorities that have considered s 45E in its original form: Gibbins ; see also Keith Russell Simplicity Funerals Pty Ltd v Cremation Society of Australia (ACT) Ltd (1982) 57 FCR 472.

110 On appeal, in Apco , the Full Court of this Court (Heerey, Hely and Gyles JJ) considered whether an understanding necessarily involves the making of a commitment to a particular course of action, as opposed to giving rise to a mere expectation or hope that a party will act in a certain way. After considering Merkel J's findings in Leahy , their Honours said at 43,234 - 43,235:
 
 'Whilst the appellants attacked the factual finding that the parties arrived at the price-fixing understanding outlined in [330] of the reasons for judgment, they did not dispute that the primary judge had enunciated the correct legal principles which are applicable in determining whether parties have entered into an understanding. In particular, the primary judge referred to the following observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 ; (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] (emphasis in original) which were specifically endorsed by the Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] : 
 
 
 
 "The cases require that at least one party 'assume an obligation' or give an 'assurance' or 'undertaking' that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have 'aroused' that expectation by things he said at the meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an 'understanding' in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word 'understanding' with the words 'agreement' and 'arrangement' and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required."
 
 
 
 The primary judge's inference at [371] that Anderson [the Director and General Manager of one of the respondent companies] expected that his competitors would hold their increased price for a time whilst he was deciding whether or not to match their prices represents Anderson's assessment of what was likely to occur, without any assurance being given to him that the competitors would act in that way. It is no more than what Lindgren J described as a "factual expectation" which falls short of an "understanding".' 


Special leave to appeal the Full Court's decision was refused by the High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v APCO Service Stations Pty Ltd [2006] HCATrans 272.

134 In Rural Press , the High Court did not find any error in the Full Court's conclusion in Pont Data that a particular class can be defined by its exclusion from supply or acquisition: at 90-91 [88] per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, see also Gleeson CJ and Callinan J at 62 [7]; and Gummow J in South Sydney at 590 [77].

225 There is utility in making a declaration of the kind sought by the ACCC: see Rural Press at 92 [95]. It will record the consequences of the Court's findings in a legally binding way, and will mark the Court's disapproval of the CEPU's conduct. However, it is essential that the terms of the declaration are tied to the proven facts: see Rural Press at 91 [90]; cf Bass v Permanent Trustee Company Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334; and Electricity Supply Association of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2001] FCA 1296 ; (2001) 113 FCR 230. I propose to vary the terms of the declarations sought by the ACCC to ensure that they accord with and are sufficiently tied to the factual findings I have made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/34.html</AustLII>
<text>142 The High Court's enunciation of the civil standard of proof in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 is frequently cited, but Dixon J's statement at 361-362 bears repeating:
 
 'Except upon criminal issues to be proved by the prosecution, it is enough that the affirmative of an allegation is made out to the reasonable satisfaction of the tribunal. But reasonable satisfaction is not a state of mind that is attained or established independently of the nature and consequence of the fact or facts to be proved. The seriousness of an allegation made, the inherent unlikelihood of an occurrence of a given description, or the gravity of the consequences flowing from a particular finding are considerations which must affect the answer to the question whether the issue has been proved to the reasonable satisfaction of the tribunal. In such matters "reasonable satisfaction" should not be produced by inexact proofs, indefinite testimony, or indirect inferences.' 


I have applied these principles to the determination of the issues in this case.

143 Based on the factual findings and applying the legal principles which I have set out above, I am satisfied that prior to 23 August 2001 Edison and the CEPU made or entered into an arrangement that included a provision that Edison would not engage electrical contractors to perform work at Loy Yang B unless they have a current certified agreement with the CEPU prior to commencing work at the site. The arrangement involved a commitment on Edison's part not to permit electrical contractors who did not have a certified agreement with the CEPU to work at Loy Yang B. In exchange, the CEPU committed to signing the Simon Engineering site agreement. The evidence establishes, in my view, that Edison and the CEPU made or entered into this arrangement prior to 15 August 2001. The heads of agreement was entered into in accordance with, and was controlled by, this arrangement. I will elaborate my reasons for these findings in the course of considering the arguments advanced by the CEPU.

144 The CEPU submitted that the evidence showed only one 'meeting of the minds' between Edison and the CEPU that is, the heads of agreement of 23 August 2001. The CEPU contended that the communications and events surrounding the making of the heads of agreement are insufficient to prove that there was a meeting of the minds between Edison and the CEPU; rather, they are evidence of the negotiations and canvassing of proposals which ultimately culminated in the heads of agreement on 23 August. In my view, these submissions do not grapple with the overall force and effect of the evidence that is before the Court.

203 In his reasons for judgment, Dixon J explained why Mallan could not be held liable as an accessory to the principal offence, at 215-216:
 
 'On the interpretation I have given to s. 230 (1), for more than one reason s. 5 of the Crimes Act cannot apply to a public officer so as to make him an accessory to the offence of the company. In the first place, the public officer's act on behalf of the company making it an offender ipso facto amounts to a substantive offence on his part under s. 230 (1). In the second place, the sub-section makes him the actor, the principal, for whose guilty conduct the company is responsible vicariously. It would be an inversion of the conceptions on which the degrees of offending are founded to make the person actually committing the forbidden acts an accessory to the offence consisting in the vicarious responsibility for his acts. 
 
 But if the interpretation were placed on s. 230 (1) opposed to that which I have adopted, I should think it would equally follow that s. 5 of the Crimes Act could not be applied to make the public officer liable under that provision. For it would mean that by s. 230 (1) the legislature had made the company responsible as an offender for the knowing and wilful understatement of income by the public officer to the exclusion of any such liability of the public officer. If that conclusion were reached it would be impossible to make him liable for the same conduct under a provision dealing with accessories. There is a number of cases which show that the application of sections dealing with aiding and abetting may be excluded by the nature of the substantive offence or the general tenor or policy of the provisions by which it is created: cf. R. v. Tyrrell ; Morris v. Tolman ; Ellis v. Guerin .'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Rail Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/24.html</AustLII>
<text>173 The CEPU submitted that, as the heads of agreement is a binding contract, the Court's task is to interpret the words of the contract, without regard to negotiations which transpired beforehand, so long as the words of the contract are clear: Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Rail Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 (' Codelfa' ). It said that cl 4.1 of the heads of agreement merely obliged Edison to 'request' that electrical contractors have acceptable industrial arrangements. On the CEPU's preferred reading, cl 4.1 simply provided that having a current certified agreement with the CEPU was one way, but not the mandated way, that an electrical contractor could have acceptable industrial arrangements for the purposes of the heads of agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81</tocase>
<text>107 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434 (' Lutovi' ), the meaning of an 'arrangement' was considered in the context of s 260 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth). Gibbs and Mason JJ (Murphy J agreeing) said at 444:
 
 'In the context of s 260 an arrangement is something less than a binding contract or agreement, something in the nature of an understanding which may not be enforceable at law ( Newton v Federal Commissioner of Taxation). ... It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.' 


The High Court's formulation in Lutovi has been applied in the context of 'arrangement or understanding' under s 45 of the TPA: see, eg, Email at 396; and David Jones at 463-464. In Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 (' TNT' ), Franki J referred to the above passage from Lutovi and said at 25:
 
 'I lean with respect to the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd ... at 89; 17,842 where he said: 
 
 
 
 "I have to remember that the concept of an understanding is broad and flexible. It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct."'

108 In David Jones at 463-464, Fisher J agreed with Franki J's comments in TNT and also favoured the views expressed by Smithers J in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81.

174 Under s 45E of the TPA, I am not limited to an examination of the words of cl 4.1. This is not a proceeding to enforce a contract. Section 45E is not concerned only with written agreements; it is also concerned with the making of an 'arrangement' or arriving at an 'understanding'. An arrangement or understanding may be informal and unenforceable: Lutovi at 444. The concept of an 'understanding' is a broad and flexible one: L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd , supra, at 89; TNT at 25; and David Jones at 463-464. For the reasons explained above, I am satisfied that there was a broader arrangement between the parties which overshadowed and controlled the language used in the heads of agreement. It was understood and agreed between the CEPU and Edison that the heads of agreement imposed an obligation on Edison not to retain electrical contractors at the Loy Yang B site if they did not have a current certified agreement with the CEPU, and that this is the way in which Edison would implement it. Nothing in cl 4.1 prevented Edison implementing its arrangement with the CEPU in this way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Workers' Union v John Holland Pty Ltd (2001) 103 IR 205</tocase>
<text>177 The CEPU submitted that the surrounding circumstances show that the provision was included for the purpose of securing the signing of the Simon Engineering site agreement. Senior counsel for the CEPU submitted that the present case is analogous to Australian Workers' Union v John Holland Pty Ltd (2001) 103 IR 205. That case involved a prohibition under s 298K of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) on dismissing an employee for 'a prohibited reason, or for reasons that include a prohibited reason'. The applicants claimed that the employer had terminated the employment of the second applicant for a 'prohibited reason', namely, because the second applicant was a member of Australian Workers' Union. In determining the reason for the employer's termination of the second applicant's employment, Goldberg J had regard to a broader industrial crisis created by another entity that was affecting the employer. Goldberg J concluded that the second applicant's membership of the union was not the reason for the employer's termination of his employment; the major reason was to solve the broader industrial relations problem that the employer faced: at 214 [41] and at 216 [49]. So too here, the CEPU submitted, the operative reason or purpose for including the provision was to secure the CEPU's signing of the Simon Engineering site agreement.

178 This argument faces insurmountable difficulties. Edison's reason for entering into an agreement with the CEPU may have been to secure the signing of the Simon Engineering site agreement and to ensure that construction work on the peaker plant commenced without further delay. But that was the motive for the agreement, not the purpose of including the provision: South Sydney at 573 [18]. The purpose of the provision is the end that it seeks to achieve. Here, Edison's operative purpose for including the provision was to restrict the electrical contractors it could engage at Loy Yang B to those who had a current certified agreement with the CEPU, conformably with the request from the CEPU. That was also the manifest effect of the provision. Notably, the CEPU's argument does not address its own purpose for including the provision in its arrangement with Edison. On any view of the evidence, the CEPU's purpose for including the provision was to limit the electrical contractors who could be engaged to work at Loy Yang B to those who had a current certified agreement with the CEPU. The CEPU did not include the provision in order to get the Simon Engineering site agreement signed; that was the leverage that the CEPU used to get Edison to agree to include the provision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Mallan v Lee [1949] HCA 48 ; (1949) 80 CLR 198</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/48.html</AustLII>
<text>202 The principles of accessorial liability were discussed by the High Court in Mallan v Lee [1949] HCA 48 ; (1949) 80 CLR 198 (' Mallan' ). The case involved a complaint laid against a company and its public officer, Mallan, for understating the company's income for the purposes of its income tax return . The company was charged pursuant to s 230(1) of the Income Tax Assessment Act with the principal offence. Mallan was charged as an accessory to the company's offence under s 5 of the Crimes Act 1914 (Cth). Section 230(1) of the Income Tax Assessment Act provided:
 
 'Any person who, or any company on whose behalf the public officer, or a director, servant or agent of the company, in any return knowingly and wilfully understates the amount of any income or makes any misstatement affecting the liability of any person to tax or the amount of tax shall be guilty of an offence.' 


The Court held that s 230(1) imposed liability for the offence on Mallan as a principal, and on the company vicariously for Mallan's acts. Thus, Mallan could not be held liable as an accessory to the principal offence.

205 Mason J considered the application of Mallan and the exclusion of the doctrine of secondary participation at common law. His Honour identified a number of circumstances in which it may be appropriate to exclude liability for secondary participation. In particular, his Honour stated that the doctrine of secondary participation may be inapplicable 'to a class of persons whom the substantive offence was designed to protect' or 'where the substantive offence itself involves some element of secondary participation'. Mason J continued at 491-492:
 
 'It is inherent in the concept of secondary participation, however, that a person may be convicted on the basis of aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring the commission of a statutory offence although the statute creating the offence deals only with the liability of the principal offender. So much was stated by Coke and Hale (3 Co. Inst. 59; 1 P.C. 613, 614, 704). And it has been settled at common law at least since R. v. Potts . This is also the case even where the offence is of such a nature that the person could not have committed it as a principal offender: cf. R. v. Goldie ; Ex parte Picklum , at pp. 263-264; Mallan v. Lee ; Reg. v. Australian Industrial Court ; Ex parte C. L. M. Holdings Pty. Ltd . , at pp. 245-246.' 


A similar view was expressed by Wilson, Deane and Dawson JJ at 501:
 
 'The application of that section [section 351] may be excluded by necessary implication (see Mallan v Lee, per Dixon J.; Morris v Tolman ; Ellis v Guerin ) and it would be excluded if it appeared that the offence of culpable driving created by the legislature was intended to apply only to the driver of the vehicle involved and not to a secondary participant. The mere absence in the section of any reference to secondary participation does not, however, show any intention to exclude it: see Hale's Pleas of the Crown (1800), vol 1, p 704; R v Potts .'

206 Mason J held at 492 that the mere description of the offender under s 52A of the Crimes Act 1900 (NSW) as the driver of a motor vehicle cannot be seen as evidencing a legislative intention to exclude the operation of the common law with respect to secondary participation. Nor, his Honour opined, could such an intention be otherwise extracted from the nature of the offence or the terms of the section by which it was created. Accordingly, the applicant was liable to conviction on the basis that he aided, abetted, counselled or procured the commission of the offence of culpable driving by his employee. The same conclusion was reached by Gibbs CJ at 477; see also Wilson, Deane and Dawson JJ at 503.

207 In reliance on Dixon J's approach in Mallan , as affirmed in Giorgianni , the CEPU submitted that the question whether a statutory provision excludes accessorial liability is to be determined by having regard to the way in which a section is structured and the purposes for which it was enacted. If such an approach is applied in the present case, the CEPU argued, there is a strong inference that the legislature did not intend a union, as a necessary party to a contravention of ss 45E and 45EA, to be caught by the accessorial liability provisions of the TPA.

208 It is important to note that the statutory provisions at issue in Giorgianni and Mallan differed in material respects from the provisions of the TPA in the present case. In Mallan , the Income Tax Assessment Act provided that the company on whose behalf the alleged accessory had acted was vicariously liable for his acts. In Giorgianni , the legislation deemed an accessory, who was not a 'driver', to be liable as a principal for the offence of culpable driving. Nevertheless, Mallan and Giorgianni recognise that accessorial liability can be excluded by a sufficiently clear expression of a contrary legislative intention.

214 Insofar as it is possible to discern the policy of the legislation, it is unlikely that the legislature intended to exclude a union from liability in relation to a contravention of ss 45E and/or 45EA. Unions are not a class of persons whom the legislation is designed to protect: see Mallan v Lee ; cf R v Tyrell [1894] 1 QB 710. Quite the opposite, ss 45E and 45EA were designed to prohibit certain types of industrial action by unions. Although liability is imposed on a union as principal for the purposes of some provisions of Pt IV of the TPA, the fact that this course is not taken in relation to ss 45E and 45EA does not, of itself, evidence a legislative intention to exclude a union from liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Giorgianni v The Queen [1985] HCA 29 ; (1984) 156 CLR 473</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/29.html</AustLII>
<text>204 In Giorgianni v The Queen [1985] HCA 29 ; (1984) 156 CLR 473 ( 'Giorgianni' ), the High Court considered the circumstances in which the doctrine of secondary participation may be excluded. In that case, the applicant was charged with culpable driving under s 52A of the Crimes Act 1900 (NSW), in reliance on s 351. Section 351 enabled an accessory to be convicted as a principal offender. The applicant was the lessee of a truck that suffered a brake failure and collided with two motor vehicles while being driven by the applicant's employee. An issue before the Court was whether the applicant could be convicted of the offence of culpable driving as a principal by reason that he had aided, abetted, counselled or procured the commission of the offence by his employee.

207 In reliance on Dixon J's approach in Mallan , as affirmed in Giorgianni , the CEPU submitted that the question whether a statutory provision excludes accessorial liability is to be determined by having regard to the way in which a section is structured and the purposes for which it was enacted. If such an approach is applied in the present case, the CEPU argued, there is a strong inference that the legislature did not intend a union, as a necessary party to a contravention of ss 45E and 45EA, to be caught by the accessorial liability provisions of the TPA.

208 It is important to note that the statutory provisions at issue in Giorgianni and Mallan differed in material respects from the provisions of the TPA in the present case. In Mallan , the Income Tax Assessment Act provided that the company on whose behalf the alleged accessory had acted was vicariously liable for his acts. In Giorgianni , the legislation deemed an accessory, who was not a 'driver', to be liable as a principal for the offence of culpable driving. Nevertheless, Mallan and Giorgianni recognise that accessorial liability can be excluded by a sufficiently clear expression of a contrary legislative intention.

218 It is also worth noting that ss 76(1) and 80(1) of the TPA catch accessorial conduct of the kinds falling within paras (d), (e) or (f), which includes persons who are directly or indirectly knowingly concerned in, or party to, a contravention: cf Giorgianni . The application of accessorial liability to persons who are parties to a contravention indicates that the legislature intended that accessorial liability would attach to parties to a contract, arrangement or understanding which contravenes the principal provision.

219 I am satisfied that ss 76(1) and 80(1) apply to a union which is a party to a contract, arrangement or understanding which contravenes ss 45E and 45EA. It follows that the CEPU is not excluded from accessorial liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1) of the TPA in relation to contraventions of ss 45E and 45EA.

220 The next question is whether the CEPU's conduct attracts liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1). The principles of accessorial liability applicable to the present case can be shortly stated. It is necessary to prove knowledge of the essential elements constituting the contravention: Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661 at 670. The requirement of 'knowledge' is actual and not constructive knowledge: Giorgianni at 504-507; Compaq Computer Australia Pty Ltd v Merry (1998) 157 ALR 1 at 5. Actual knowledge may be established as a matter of inference from the circumstances surrounding the contravention: Pereira v Director of Public Prosecutions [1988] HCA 57 ; (1998) 82 ALR 217 at 219.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Tyrell [1894] 1 QB 710</tocase>
<text>214 Insofar as it is possible to discern the policy of the legislation, it is unlikely that the legislature intended to exclude a union from liability in relation to a contravention of ss 45E and/or 45EA. Unions are not a class of persons whom the legislation is designed to protect: see Mallan v Lee ; cf R v Tyrell [1894] 1 QB 710. Quite the opposite, ss 45E and 45EA were designed to prohibit certain types of industrial action by unions. Although liability is imposed on a union as principal for the purposes of some provisions of Pt IV of the TPA, the fact that this course is not taken in relation to ss 45E and 45EA does not, of itself, evidence a legislative intention to exclude a union from liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/65.html</AustLII>
<text>220 The next question is whether the CEPU's conduct attracts liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1). The principles of accessorial liability applicable to the present case can be shortly stated. It is necessary to prove knowledge of the essential elements constituting the contravention: Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661 at 670. The requirement of 'knowledge' is actual and not constructive knowledge: Giorgianni at 504-507; Compaq Computer Australia Pty Ltd v Merry (1998) 157 ALR 1 at 5. Actual knowledge may be established as a matter of inference from the circumstances surrounding the contravention: Pereira v Director of Public Prosecutions [1988] HCA 57 ; (1998) 82 ALR 217 at 219.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Compaq Computer Australia Pty Ltd v Merry (1998) 157 ALR 1</tocase>
<text>220 The next question is whether the CEPU's conduct attracts liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1). The principles of accessorial liability applicable to the present case can be shortly stated. It is necessary to prove knowledge of the essential elements constituting the contravention: Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661 at 670. The requirement of 'knowledge' is actual and not constructive knowledge: Giorgianni at 504-507; Compaq Computer Australia Pty Ltd v Merry (1998) 157 ALR 1 at 5. Actual knowledge may be established as a matter of inference from the circumstances surrounding the contravention: Pereira v Director of Public Prosecutions [1988] HCA 57 ; (1998) 82 ALR 217 at 219.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pereira v Director of Public Prosecutions [1988] HCA 57 ; (1998) 82 ALR 217</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/57.html</AustLII>
<text>220 The next question is whether the CEPU's conduct attracts liability under ss 76(1) and 80(1). The principles of accessorial liability applicable to the present case can be shortly stated. It is necessary to prove knowledge of the essential elements constituting the contravention: Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661 at 670. The requirement of 'knowledge' is actual and not constructive knowledge: Giorgianni at 504-507; Compaq Computer Australia Pty Ltd v Merry (1998) 157 ALR 1 at 5. Actual knowledge may be established as a matter of inference from the circumstances surrounding the contravention: Pereira v Director of Public Prosecutions [1988] HCA 57 ; (1998) 82 ALR 217 at 219.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dowling v Dalgety Australia Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 109</tocase>
<text>222 As to whether the CEPU was involved in Edison's contravention of s 45EA, it is necessary to bear in mind the width of the concept of 'give effect to'. It is defined in s 4(1) as including the doing of 'an act or thing in pursuance of or in accordance with' the contract, arrangement or understanding. An act or thing may be done in accordance with a contract, arrangement or understanding even though the person who did that act or thing did not have the contract, arrangement or understanding in mind at the time: TNT at 68. Independent decisions made by parties to a contract, arrangement or understanding can nevertheless give effect to an arrangement made between them: Dowling v Dalgety Australia Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 109.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c40">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bass v Permanent Trustee Company Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/9.html</AustLII>
<text>225 There is utility in making a declaration of the kind sought by the ACCC: see Rural Press at 92 [95]. It will record the consequences of the Court's findings in a legally binding way, and will mark the Court's disapproval of the CEPU's conduct. However, it is essential that the terms of the declaration are tied to the proven facts: see Rural Press at 91 [90]; cf Bass v Permanent Trustee Company Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334; and Electricity Supply Association of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2001] FCA 1296 ; (2001) 113 FCR 230. I propose to vary the terms of the declarations sought by the ACCC to ensure that they accord with and are sufficiently tied to the factual findings I have made.

231 In the present case, the ACCC sought injunctive relief against the CEPU in extremely wide terms. Effectively, the first order seeks to restrain the CEPU from aiding, abetting, counselling, procuring, inducing or attempting to induce, or being knowingly concerned in or party to Edison making a contract, arrangement or understanding with the CEPU where the contract, arrangement or understanding contains a provision that was included for the purposes described in s 45E(3). The second order goes further and seeks to restrain the CEPU from aiding, abetting, etc any person making a contract, arrangement or understanding with the CEPU that contains a provision contravening s 45E(3). The third order seeks to restrain the CEPU from counselling, procuring, inducing or attempting to induce Edison to give effect to a provision of a contract, arrangement or understanding between Edison and the CEPU where the provision was included for a purpose proscribed by s 45E(3). The fourth order is similar to the third except that it seeks to restrain the CEPU from counselling etc any person to give effect to a provision of a contract, arrangement or understanding between that person and the CEPU which contains a provision included for a proscribed purpose. None of the proposed injunctions are confined to the particular contract, arrangement or understanding which gave rise to Edison's contraventions in this case, and none are limited in time. In my opinion, the injunctions are cast far too widely.

232 The first question is whether the Court should exercise its discretion to grant any injunction against the CEPU or its officers in the circumstances which now prevail. The arrangement between Edison and the CEPU came to an end in late November 2003. DJN resumed work at Loy Yang B in early 2004. There is no suggestion in the evidence that the accessorial conduct on the part of the CEPU has recurred, or that it is likely to recur. On the other hand it is relevant to take into account the deliberate nature of the conduct that the CEPU engaged in during August 2001.

233 The terms of the injunctive orders proposed by the ACCC raise questions as to the appropriateness of granting any injunctive relief. In an attempt to keep the injunctions within proper bounds, the ACCC's proposed orders are replete with definitional provisions that attempt to mirror the requirements of s 45E(1), (3) and (7). Despite these extensive definitions, the ACCC's draft orders do not capture the exception which appears in s 45E(8). The extensive definitional clauses that are attached to the draft orders mean that each order takes on a rather abstract appearance that largely restates the requirements of s 45E(1), (3) and (7) of the TPA. Two of the proposed orders refer specifically to a contract, arrangement or understanding between Edison and the CEPU, but even those orders are not aimed at the August 2001 arrangement because that ended long ago. The other two orders are directed to conduct that, inter alia, procures or induces any person to make, or to give effect to, any arrangement between that person and the CEPU where it contains a provision that would satisfy the requirements of s 45E(1), (3) and (7). As a result, these orders very much have the appearance of orders that attempt to restate the general prohibition that appears in s 45E of the TPA.

234 In my opinion, the terms of the injunctive orders proposed by the ACCC are plainly inappropriate. On the authorities, any injunction must have a clear and sufficient connection with the proven conduct that attracts the jurisdiction of the Court. Any injunction must also be capable of being expressed clearly and in a manner which can be understood by those required to comply with it. I would not contemplate an injunction that operates indefinitely. Where an injunctive order is sought in respect of a class of conduct, similar to proven conduct that has come to an end, I consider that it should only operate for a limited period of time. This is a course commonly taken in the authorities.

235 On balance, I am persuaded that this is a case in which it is appropriate to grant an injunction for a limited period, and in quite specific terms, that will operate by way of deterrence and mark the Court's disapproval of the CEPU's conduct. In my view, the injunction must have a close nexus with the proven conduct that attracts the jurisdiction of the Court. I consider that it should operate for a period of three years and no longer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c41">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Electricity Supply Association of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2001] FCA 1296 ; (2001) 113 FCR 230</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1296.html</AustLII>
<text>225 There is utility in making a declaration of the kind sought by the ACCC: see Rural Press at 92 [95]. It will record the consequences of the Court's findings in a legally binding way, and will mark the Court's disapproval of the CEPU's conduct. However, it is essential that the terms of the declaration are tied to the proven facts: see Rural Press at 91 [90]; cf Bass v Permanent Trustee Company Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334; and Electricity Supply Association of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2001] FCA 1296 ; (2001) 113 FCR 230. I propose to vary the terms of the declarations sought by the ACCC to ensure that they accord with and are sufficiently tied to the factual findings I have made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c42">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>ICI Australia Operations Pty Limited v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248</tocase>
<text>226 The principles governing the grant of final injunctive relief under s 80 of the TPA, in a case such as this, are not in doubt. Section 80(1) confers a wide power on the Court to grant an injunction where it is satisfied that a person has engaged or is proposing to engage in conduct that constitutes or would constitute conduct of the description in paras (a)-(f). It has been described as a 'widely drawn remedial provision available to restrain conduct which may infringe upon [the] public interest by contraventions of the provisions of the Act in Part IV and Part V': per French J in ICI Australia Operations Pty Limited v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248 ( 'ICI' ) at 268. The breadth of the Court's discretion is underscored by s 80(4) which permits the Court to grant injunctive relief whether or not the person intends to engage in conduct of the kind restrained, or the person has previously engaged in conduct of that kind, or there is an imminent danger of substantial damage to any person if the conduct is repeated or continued.

228 In ICI, the Full Court at 257-258 and 267-268 rejected a submission that s 80 creates a presumption in favour of a grant of a final injunction where a contravention or proposed contravention of the TPA is made out. Lockhart J said at 256-257 that the public interest character of s 80, and the breadth and flexibility of its statutory provisions, do not mean that traditional equitable doctrines are irrelevant. It remains relevant to consider questions of repetition of conduct, whether it has ever occurred before, or whether imminent substantial damage is likely, although the absence of any one or more of those elements is not fatal to the grant of an injunction. Equally, the public interest character of s 80 means that deterrence is a relevant consideration. French J said that there is room within the statutory framework and its underlying policy for an injunction which is not intended to restrain an apprehended repetition of contravening conduct, but to deter an offender from repeating the offence: ICI at 268. In Trade Practices Commission v Mobil Oil Australia Ltd (1985) 4 FCR 296, Toohey J said that in the case of a particularly flagrant breach and in the absence of any evidence of an intention on the offender's part to continue the conduct, it might nonetheless be appropriate to mark the Court's disapproval by an injunction as well as a monetary penalty: at 300.

229 As to the terms in which a final injunction should be granted, the Court's discretion is as wide as the phrase 'as the Court determines to be appropriate'. On first principles, it is plain that the terms of an injunction should be clear and unambiguous, leaving no room for doubt as to the nature and scope of the future conduct that falls within its boundaries: see, eg, ICI at 259 per Lockhart J. A final injunction should not be granted in terms which simply enjoin the respondent not to breach the Act: see Trade Practices Commission v Walplan Pty Ltd (1985) 7 FCR 495; Commodore Business Machines Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 92 ALR 563 at 574; ICI per Lockhart J at 259-260; and BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2004) 207 ALR 452 ( 'BMW' ) at 465-466 [36]-[39].

230 The terms of an injunction will not be appropriate if it extends to conduct that does not have an appropriate nexus with the contravening conduct that attracts the operation of s 80: see ICI at 367 per Gummow J. Depending upon the nature of the contravening conduct, it may be legitimate to grant an injunction against a respondent preventing it from engaging in conduct in a similar manner, or to like effect, as the conduct which was the subject of the established contravention: see ICI at 261; and BMW at 465 [36]. The desirability of granting an injunction in this extended form will depend on the circumstances of the case and the existence of a sufficient nexus with the conduct that contravenes the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c43">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Z-Tek Computer Pty Ltd (1997) 78 FCR 197</tocase>
<text>227 There are at least three limitations on the Court's power under s 80. They were summarised by Merkel J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Z-Tek Computer Pty Ltd (1997) 78 FCR 197 at 203-204 in these terms:
 
 'First, the power is confined by reference to the scope and purpose of the TPA and in particular s 80. It is within the scope and purpose of s 80 to grant injunctive relief which is designed to prevent a repetition of the conduct for which the relief is sought. 
 
 Secondly there is a contextual limitation within s 80 itself. As the jurisdiction to grant an injunction is enlivened by an alleged or actual contravention of a provision of Pt IV, IVA or V of the TPA, there must be a sufficient nexus or relationship between the contravention and the injunction granted. It is that nexus or relationship that enables determination by the Court of whether the injunction sought is "appropriate". 
 
 Thirdly, there is the constitutional limitation which requires that the injunction granted be related to the case or controversy the subject of the proceeding.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c44">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Mobil Oil Australia Ltd (1985) 4 FCR 296</tocase>
<text>228 In ICI, the Full Court at 257-258 and 267-268 rejected a submission that s 80 creates a presumption in favour of a grant of a final injunction where a contravention or proposed contravention of the TPA is made out. Lockhart J said at 256-257 that the public interest character of s 80, and the breadth and flexibility of its statutory provisions, do not mean that traditional equitable doctrines are irrelevant. It remains relevant to consider questions of repetition of conduct, whether it has ever occurred before, or whether imminent substantial damage is likely, although the absence of any one or more of those elements is not fatal to the grant of an injunction. Equally, the public interest character of s 80 means that deterrence is a relevant consideration. French J said that there is room within the statutory framework and its underlying policy for an injunction which is not intended to restrain an apprehended repetition of contravening conduct, but to deter an offender from repeating the offence: ICI at 268. In Trade Practices Commission v Mobil Oil Australia Ltd (1985) 4 FCR 296, Toohey J said that in the case of a particularly flagrant breach and in the absence of any evidence of an intention on the offender's part to continue the conduct, it might nonetheless be appropriate to mark the Court's disapproval by an injunction as well as a monetary penalty: at 300.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c45">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Walplan Pty Ltd (1985) 7 FCR 495</tocase>
<text>229 As to the terms in which a final injunction should be granted, the Court's discretion is as wide as the phrase 'as the Court determines to be appropriate'. On first principles, it is plain that the terms of an injunction should be clear and unambiguous, leaving no room for doubt as to the nature and scope of the future conduct that falls within its boundaries: see, eg, ICI at 259 per Lockhart J. A final injunction should not be granted in terms which simply enjoin the respondent not to breach the Act: see Trade Practices Commission v Walplan Pty Ltd (1985) 7 FCR 495; Commodore Business Machines Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 92 ALR 563 at 574; ICI per Lockhart J at 259-260; and BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2004) 207 ALR 452 ( 'BMW' ) at 465-466 [36]-[39].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c46">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commodore Business Machines Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 92 ALR 563</tocase>
<text>229 As to the terms in which a final injunction should be granted, the Court's discretion is as wide as the phrase 'as the Court determines to be appropriate'. On first principles, it is plain that the terms of an injunction should be clear and unambiguous, leaving no room for doubt as to the nature and scope of the future conduct that falls within its boundaries: see, eg, ICI at 259 per Lockhart J. A final injunction should not be granted in terms which simply enjoin the respondent not to breach the Act: see Trade Practices Commission v Walplan Pty Ltd (1985) 7 FCR 495; Commodore Business Machines Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 92 ALR 563 at 574; ICI per Lockhart J at 259-260; and BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2004) 207 ALR 452 ( 'BMW' ) at 465-466 [36]-[39].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c47">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2004) 207 ALR 452</tocase>
<text>229 As to the terms in which a final injunction should be granted, the Court's discretion is as wide as the phrase 'as the Court determines to be appropriate'. On first principles, it is plain that the terms of an injunction should be clear and unambiguous, leaving no room for doubt as to the nature and scope of the future conduct that falls within its boundaries: see, eg, ICI at 259 per Lockhart J. A final injunction should not be granted in terms which simply enjoin the respondent not to breach the Act: see Trade Practices Commission v Walplan Pty Ltd (1985) 7 FCR 495; Commodore Business Machines Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 92 ALR 563 at 574; ICI per Lockhart J at 259-260; and BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2004) 207 ALR 452 ( 'BMW' ) at 465-466 [36]-[39].

230 The terms of an injunction will not be appropriate if it extends to conduct that does not have an appropriate nexus with the contravening conduct that attracts the operation of s 80: see ICI at 367 per Gummow J. Depending upon the nature of the contravening conduct, it may be legitimate to grant an injunction against a respondent preventing it from engaging in conduct in a similar manner, or to like effect, as the conduct which was the subject of the established contravention: see ICI at 261; and BMW at 465 [36]. The desirability of granting an injunction in this extended form will depend on the circumstances of the case and the existence of a sufficient nexus with the conduct that contravenes the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>