<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Midamarine Pty Limited v International Sports Clothing Pty Ltd and [2006] FCA 1591 (22 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1591.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352</tocase>
<text>9 His Honour's Reasons reflect the following observations concerning his Honour's assessment of the evidence before him and the legal issues:
 
 
 (a) The Applicant applied for the Registered Design on 24 December 2001. The Registered Design was granted on 27 May 2003 and since September 2004 Midamarine has, through arrangements with a licensee, Britz Innovation Pty Ltd ('Britz Innovation') and a related company Kalinin Pty Ltd ('Kalinin'), a company trading as 'Britz Marketing', been selling an inflatable surfcraft described as the ' Wavestar '. The Applicant also sells another surfcraft article described as the ' Surfster '.
 (b) The Applicant contends that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design.
 (c) In June 2005, Mr Russell Joel Binkin ('Mr Binkin'), 'an associate of the applicant, provided a sample of the Wavestar to Mr Corrick and endeavoured to persuade him that he should licence the design of the Wavestar from the applicant. Mr Corrick was provided with artwork, which came from the applicant. I am satisfied that the sample of the Wavestar and the artwork contained clear notification of a Registered Design, and the artwork and sample contained the Warning which presently appears on the physical exhibit of the Wavestar. It is to be expected, I would have thought, that there was copyright in somebody in that formulation of the Warning.' [6]
 (d) 'After the meeting and the supply of the sample and artwork, Mr Corrick indicated he was not interested in pursuing a licence for the product.' [7]
 (e) In January 2006, Midamarine and Britz Marketing entered into an exclusive distributorship in relation to the Wavestar surfcraft. In February 2006, Mr Corrick commenced negotiations with the National Rugby League ('NRL') and the Australian Football League ('AFL') to use the trade marks of NRL and AFL sporting teams on surfcraft or surf mats. 
 (f) On 8 September 2006, a director of Midamarine, Mr Michael Arenson, learnt that DMC was supplying a surfcraft article to 'Amart All Sports' which was said by Mr Arenson to be strikingly similar to the Wavestar . 
 (g) On 22 September 2006, Mr Arenson saw a reproduction of the DMC article. Mr Arenson spoke to Mr Corrick and wrote a letter to him on 24 September 2006 drawing his attention to the similarities in the design features between the Wavestar article and the DMC article. Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the fact that the warning label endorsed on the DMC article was a direct copy of the Warning Notice on the Wavestar article. In particular, Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the reproduction on the DMC article of the claim, 'The shape of this inflated product is a Registered Design' . 
 (h) On 27 September 2006, the solicitors for DMC applied to register a design of a surfcraft in the name of DMC and, in that Application, Mr Corrick was described as the designer. His Honour observed that: 'No documents supporting his design exist, for the good reason that, in fact, the DMC product is a direct and complete copy of the Wavestar. ' [11]
 (i) His Honour noted: 'It is now conceded that the DMC surf mat is indeed a copy - and a deliberate copy of the Wavestar ' . This, in my view, had to be so. The visual comparison leads to that conclusion. The fact that the Wavestar was left with Mr Corrick, the comparison of the two and the identity of the words used in the Warning on the back of the DMC surf mat and, in particular, "the shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design", lead inevitably to the conclusion that the DMC product is a direct copy of the Wavestar '. [12] 'The words on the Wavestar reflect the contention by Mr Arenson that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design. The presence of those words on the DMC product is, in my opinion, damning evidence of copying by DMC of the Wavestar.' [13] 
 (j) Counsel for DMC contended that the Wavestar is not an embodiment of the Registered Design and in any event, the Registered Design is invalid. As to the latter question, his Honour concluded that for interlocutory purposes, the Applicant is to be treated as the owner of a valid Registered Design having regard to differences in the features of shape reflected in the examples of prior art. 'Indeed, the attack on the validity of the Registered Design is seriously undermined by DMC's own application for registration of the design of the DMC product, which application is tainted with dishonesty and fraudulent claims. I accept that it has been acknowledged that the application will be withdrawn or otherwise expunged.' [16]
 (l) His Honour addressed Midamarine's contention that DMC had applied the Registered Design or a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design to articles sold and offered for sale by DMC. At [23], the features of shape, configuration, pattern or ornamentation contained within the Registered Design, capable of being judged by the eye, are identified by his Honour. At [24], his Honour observes, 'I have inspected the inflated DMC product and compared it with the Registered Design. The inflated DMC product possesses each of the features identified in the Applicant's written submissions (those identified at [23]), with the exception that the handles do not protrude from the top of the surf mat as depicted in the Registered Design. The handles on the Wavestar also do not protrude from the top of the surf mat, as depicted in the Registered Design. His Honour concluded that, 'For present purposes, being the interlocutory purposes, I am satisfied that, to the eye, the shape of the DMC product is substantially the same as that of the Registered Design. It is, in my opinion, strongly arguable that the design, which has been applied to the DMC product, is an obvious imitation of the Registered Design. That is, in the words of the test in Malleys (Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352) , to be found at p 354 of the report: "Not the same but a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences".' [27]
 (m) His Honour observed that even if the design applied to the DMC article is not an obvious imitation of the Registered Design, the test for fraudulent imitation is even more strongly arguable [28]. His Honour identified the tests approved by the High Court in Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 and the High Court's approval of the observations of Lehane J in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167. His Honour concluded: 'I am satisfied that there is a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation. It seems inevitable that, if the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design, then the DMC product is a fraudulent imitation. The design of the Wavestar and the DMC product is almost identical. It could not have been independently created. It is now admitted that the DMC product is a copy of the Wavestar .' [31] 'So, also, is the embarrassing identity of the direct words of the warning label, including the imprinting of the words: "The shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design". ' 
 (n) At [33], his Honour said this: 'It is not denied that Mr Corrick was supplied with a sample of the Wavestar surf mat and had discussed obtaining a licence of the design. It seems plain that there is a strongly arguable case of obvious imitation or fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design.' 
 (o) On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour considered the observations of the High Court in Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618 at 625 and the principles affirmed by the High Court in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46 and weighed in the balance the implications arising out of a consideration that DMC had 'in the face of warnings' from Midamarine and 'with eyes wide open' embarked upon a course of importing, selling and offering for sale articles to which a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design had been applied. At [39], his Honour said this: 'In my judgment, the balance of convenience strongly favours the grant of the injunction sought. The chronology of events, and in particular the history of the design of the DMC product that is to say no design, but a direct copy indicates that the respondents have decided to import and distribute the DMC product with their eyes open to the likely consequences of so doing.' 
 (p) At [40], his Honour further referred to submissions by counsel for Midamarine and quoted this submission, 'No reasonable trader, having received the sales pitch from Mr Binkin [in June 2005] for the Wavestar , could reasonably ignore the existence of the rights [claimed in the design]' . (The words in the square brackets are explanatory words inserted into counsel's submission by his Honour). 
 (q) As to the question of damage accruing to Midamarine, his Honour said this: 'In this particular case, the applicant is shown to be an established manufacturer and supplier of the Wavestar surf mats. It is strongly arguable that that product has the benefit of the protection of the Registered Design. It has been creating a market for its product and supplying its product to distributors since 2004. [35]. 'Earlier this year, the applicant entered into an exclusive distributor arrangement with Britz Marketing. I accept that its fortunes are tied to its ability to distribute its products via Britz Marketing. The Wavestar is now exclusively sold by Britz Marketing under the name Wahu Wavetube . That surf mat is sold in an extensive range of shops, including Toyworld, Big W, Rebel Sports, Target and Toy'R'Us. Mr Britz says the Wahu Wavetube has been heavily promoted'. [36] 'Since the First Respondent [DMC] began, in October 2006, to sell the DMC product, Amart All Sports has ceased all sales of the Wahu Wavetube and has acquired, instead, the DMC product. I accept that the inability to sell surf mats to the applicant's design to Amart has a significant impact on the ability of the applicant to make sales.' 
 (r) On the question of an assessment of potential wider injury, his Honour concluded that, 'There is a serious over-statement of those risks in the evidence on behalf of the applicant'. [38] His Honour concluded that there was 'a deal of exaggeration in the injury inherent' in the contentions of Mr Britz that Britz Marketing would have to give serious consideration to sourcing surf mats from a different and cheaper source than Midamarine if DMC products continued to be sold. 
 (s) At [41], his Honour reached this conclusionary observation, 'The strength of the applicant's case of deliberate copying by the first respondent favours the grant of the interlocutory injunction. The impugned DMC products are clearly and objectively a deliberate copy of the Wavestar . The person responsible for the design and manufacturer of the DMC product knew that the product was a copy of the Wavestar , and knew of the claim that the design of the Wavestar product was protected by a Registered Design. In those circumstances, it seems to me that DMC has embarked on a task of ordering and importing the impugned products with its eyes wide open as to the potential consequences of so doing, namely, that it will be exposed to the present application.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/816.html</AustLII>
<text>9 His Honour's Reasons reflect the following observations concerning his Honour's assessment of the evidence before him and the legal issues:
 
 
 (a) The Applicant applied for the Registered Design on 24 December 2001. The Registered Design was granted on 27 May 2003 and since September 2004 Midamarine has, through arrangements with a licensee, Britz Innovation Pty Ltd ('Britz Innovation') and a related company Kalinin Pty Ltd ('Kalinin'), a company trading as 'Britz Marketing', been selling an inflatable surfcraft described as the ' Wavestar '. The Applicant also sells another surfcraft article described as the ' Surfster '.
 (b) The Applicant contends that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design.
 (c) In June 2005, Mr Russell Joel Binkin ('Mr Binkin'), 'an associate of the applicant, provided a sample of the Wavestar to Mr Corrick and endeavoured to persuade him that he should licence the design of the Wavestar from the applicant. Mr Corrick was provided with artwork, which came from the applicant. I am satisfied that the sample of the Wavestar and the artwork contained clear notification of a Registered Design, and the artwork and sample contained the Warning which presently appears on the physical exhibit of the Wavestar. It is to be expected, I would have thought, that there was copyright in somebody in that formulation of the Warning.' [6]
 (d) 'After the meeting and the supply of the sample and artwork, Mr Corrick indicated he was not interested in pursuing a licence for the product.' [7]
 (e) In January 2006, Midamarine and Britz Marketing entered into an exclusive distributorship in relation to the Wavestar surfcraft. In February 2006, Mr Corrick commenced negotiations with the National Rugby League ('NRL') and the Australian Football League ('AFL') to use the trade marks of NRL and AFL sporting teams on surfcraft or surf mats. 
 (f) On 8 September 2006, a director of Midamarine, Mr Michael Arenson, learnt that DMC was supplying a surfcraft article to 'Amart All Sports' which was said by Mr Arenson to be strikingly similar to the Wavestar . 
 (g) On 22 September 2006, Mr Arenson saw a reproduction of the DMC article. Mr Arenson spoke to Mr Corrick and wrote a letter to him on 24 September 2006 drawing his attention to the similarities in the design features between the Wavestar article and the DMC article. Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the fact that the warning label endorsed on the DMC article was a direct copy of the Warning Notice on the Wavestar article. In particular, Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the reproduction on the DMC article of the claim, 'The shape of this inflated product is a Registered Design' . 
 (h) On 27 September 2006, the solicitors for DMC applied to register a design of a surfcraft in the name of DMC and, in that Application, Mr Corrick was described as the designer. His Honour observed that: 'No documents supporting his design exist, for the good reason that, in fact, the DMC product is a direct and complete copy of the Wavestar. ' [11]
 (i) His Honour noted: 'It is now conceded that the DMC surf mat is indeed a copy - and a deliberate copy of the Wavestar ' . This, in my view, had to be so. The visual comparison leads to that conclusion. The fact that the Wavestar was left with Mr Corrick, the comparison of the two and the identity of the words used in the Warning on the back of the DMC surf mat and, in particular, "the shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design", lead inevitably to the conclusion that the DMC product is a direct copy of the Wavestar '. [12] 'The words on the Wavestar reflect the contention by Mr Arenson that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design. The presence of those words on the DMC product is, in my opinion, damning evidence of copying by DMC of the Wavestar.' [13] 
 (j) Counsel for DMC contended that the Wavestar is not an embodiment of the Registered Design and in any event, the Registered Design is invalid. As to the latter question, his Honour concluded that for interlocutory purposes, the Applicant is to be treated as the owner of a valid Registered Design having regard to differences in the features of shape reflected in the examples of prior art. 'Indeed, the attack on the validity of the Registered Design is seriously undermined by DMC's own application for registration of the design of the DMC product, which application is tainted with dishonesty and fraudulent claims. I accept that it has been acknowledged that the application will be withdrawn or otherwise expunged.' [16]
 (l) His Honour addressed Midamarine's contention that DMC had applied the Registered Design or a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design to articles sold and offered for sale by DMC. At [23], the features of shape, configuration, pattern or ornamentation contained within the Registered Design, capable of being judged by the eye, are identified by his Honour. At [24], his Honour observes, 'I have inspected the inflated DMC product and compared it with the Registered Design. The inflated DMC product possesses each of the features identified in the Applicant's written submissions (those identified at [23]), with the exception that the handles do not protrude from the top of the surf mat as depicted in the Registered Design. The handles on the Wavestar also do not protrude from the top of the surf mat, as depicted in the Registered Design. His Honour concluded that, 'For present purposes, being the interlocutory purposes, I am satisfied that, to the eye, the shape of the DMC product is substantially the same as that of the Registered Design. It is, in my opinion, strongly arguable that the design, which has been applied to the DMC product, is an obvious imitation of the Registered Design. That is, in the words of the test in Malleys (Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352) , to be found at p 354 of the report: "Not the same but a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences".' [27]
 (m) His Honour observed that even if the design applied to the DMC article is not an obvious imitation of the Registered Design, the test for fraudulent imitation is even more strongly arguable [28]. His Honour identified the tests approved by the High Court in Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 and the High Court's approval of the observations of Lehane J in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167. His Honour concluded: 'I am satisfied that there is a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation. It seems inevitable that, if the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design, then the DMC product is a fraudulent imitation. The design of the Wavestar and the DMC product is almost identical. It could not have been independently created. It is now admitted that the DMC product is a copy of the Wavestar .' [31] 'So, also, is the embarrassing identity of the direct words of the warning label, including the imprinting of the words: "The shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design". ' 
 (n) At [33], his Honour said this: 'It is not denied that Mr Corrick was supplied with a sample of the Wavestar surf mat and had discussed obtaining a licence of the design. It seems plain that there is a strongly arguable case of obvious imitation or fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design.' 
 (o) On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour considered the observations of the High Court in Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618 at 625 and the principles affirmed by the High Court in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46 and weighed in the balance the implications arising out of a consideration that DMC had 'in the face of warnings' from Midamarine and 'with eyes wide open' embarked upon a course of importing, selling and offering for sale articles to which a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design had been applied. At [39], his Honour said this: 'In my judgment, the balance of convenience strongly favours the grant of the injunction sought. The chronology of events, and in particular the history of the design of the DMC product that is to say no design, but a direct copy indicates that the respondents have decided to import and distribute the DMC product with their eyes open to the likely consequences of so doing.' 
 (p) At [40], his Honour further referred to submissions by counsel for Midamarine and quoted this submission, 'No reasonable trader, having received the sales pitch from Mr Binkin [in June 2005] for the Wavestar , could reasonably ignore the existence of the rights [claimed in the design]' . (The words in the square brackets are explanatory words inserted into counsel's submission by his Honour). 
 (q) As to the question of damage accruing to Midamarine, his Honour said this: 'In this particular case, the applicant is shown to be an established manufacturer and supplier of the Wavestar surf mats. It is strongly arguable that that product has the benefit of the protection of the Registered Design. It has been creating a market for its product and supplying its product to distributors since 2004. [35]. 'Earlier this year, the applicant entered into an exclusive distributor arrangement with Britz Marketing. I accept that its fortunes are tied to its ability to distribute its products via Britz Marketing. The Wavestar is now exclusively sold by Britz Marketing under the name Wahu Wavetube . That surf mat is sold in an extensive range of shops, including Toyworld, Big W, Rebel Sports, Target and Toy'R'Us. Mr Britz says the Wahu Wavetube has been heavily promoted'. [36] 'Since the First Respondent [DMC] began, in October 2006, to sell the DMC product, Amart All Sports has ceased all sales of the Wahu Wavetube and has acquired, instead, the DMC product. I accept that the inability to sell surf mats to the applicant's design to Amart has a significant impact on the ability of the applicant to make sales.' 
 (r) On the question of an assessment of potential wider injury, his Honour concluded that, 'There is a serious over-statement of those risks in the evidence on behalf of the applicant'. [38] His Honour concluded that there was 'a deal of exaggeration in the injury inherent' in the contentions of Mr Britz that Britz Marketing would have to give serious consideration to sourcing surf mats from a different and cheaper source than Midamarine if DMC products continued to be sold. 
 (s) At [41], his Honour reached this conclusionary observation, 'The strength of the applicant's case of deliberate copying by the first respondent favours the grant of the interlocutory injunction. The impugned DMC products are clearly and objectively a deliberate copy of the Wavestar . The person responsible for the design and manufacturer of the DMC product knew that the product was a copy of the Wavestar , and knew of the claim that the design of the Wavestar product was protected by a Registered Design. In those circumstances, it seems to me that DMC has embarked on a task of ordering and importing the impugned products with its eyes wide open as to the potential consequences of so doing, namely, that it will be exposed to the present application.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/32.html</AustLII>
<text>9 His Honour's Reasons reflect the following observations concerning his Honour's assessment of the evidence before him and the legal issues:
 
 
 (a) The Applicant applied for the Registered Design on 24 December 2001. The Registered Design was granted on 27 May 2003 and since September 2004 Midamarine has, through arrangements with a licensee, Britz Innovation Pty Ltd ('Britz Innovation') and a related company Kalinin Pty Ltd ('Kalinin'), a company trading as 'Britz Marketing', been selling an inflatable surfcraft described as the ' Wavestar '. The Applicant also sells another surfcraft article described as the ' Surfster '.
 (b) The Applicant contends that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design.
 (c) In June 2005, Mr Russell Joel Binkin ('Mr Binkin'), 'an associate of the applicant, provided a sample of the Wavestar to Mr Corrick and endeavoured to persuade him that he should licence the design of the Wavestar from the applicant. Mr Corrick was provided with artwork, which came from the applicant. I am satisfied that the sample of the Wavestar and the artwork contained clear notification of a Registered Design, and the artwork and sample contained the Warning which presently appears on the physical exhibit of the Wavestar. It is to be expected, I would have thought, that there was copyright in somebody in that formulation of the Warning.' [6]
 (d) 'After the meeting and the supply of the sample and artwork, Mr Corrick indicated he was not interested in pursuing a licence for the product.' [7]
 (e) In January 2006, Midamarine and Britz Marketing entered into an exclusive distributorship in relation to the Wavestar surfcraft. In February 2006, Mr Corrick commenced negotiations with the National Rugby League ('NRL') and the Australian Football League ('AFL') to use the trade marks of NRL and AFL sporting teams on surfcraft or surf mats. 
 (f) On 8 September 2006, a director of Midamarine, Mr Michael Arenson, learnt that DMC was supplying a surfcraft article to 'Amart All Sports' which was said by Mr Arenson to be strikingly similar to the Wavestar . 
 (g) On 22 September 2006, Mr Arenson saw a reproduction of the DMC article. Mr Arenson spoke to Mr Corrick and wrote a letter to him on 24 September 2006 drawing his attention to the similarities in the design features between the Wavestar article and the DMC article. Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the fact that the warning label endorsed on the DMC article was a direct copy of the Warning Notice on the Wavestar article. In particular, Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the reproduction on the DMC article of the claim, 'The shape of this inflated product is a Registered Design' . 
 (h) On 27 September 2006, the solicitors for DMC applied to register a design of a surfcraft in the name of DMC and, in that Application, Mr Corrick was described as the designer. His Honour observed that: 'No documents supporting his design exist, for the good reason that, in fact, the DMC product is a direct and complete copy of the Wavestar. ' [11]
 (i) His Honour noted: 'It is now conceded that the DMC surf mat is indeed a copy - and a deliberate copy of the Wavestar ' . This, in my view, had to be so. The visual comparison leads to that conclusion. The fact that the Wavestar was left with Mr Corrick, the comparison of the two and the identity of the words used in the Warning on the back of the DMC surf mat and, in particular, "the shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design", lead inevitably to the conclusion that the DMC product is a direct copy of the Wavestar '. [12] 'The words on the Wavestar reflect the contention by Mr Arenson that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design. The presence of those words on the DMC product is, in my opinion, damning evidence of copying by DMC of the Wavestar.' [13] 
 (j) Counsel for DMC contended that the Wavestar is not an embodiment of the Registered Design and in any event, the Registered Design is invalid. As to the latter question, his Honour concluded that for interlocutory purposes, the Applicant is to be treated as the owner of a valid Registered Design having regard to differences in the features of shape reflected in the examples of prior art. 'Indeed, the attack on the validity of the Registered Design is seriously undermined by DMC's own application for registration of the design of the DMC product, which application is tainted with dishonesty and fraudulent claims. I accept that it has been acknowledged that the application will be withdrawn or otherwise expunged.' [16]
 (l) His Honour addressed Midamarine's contention that DMC had applied the Registered Design or a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design to articles sold and offered for sale by DMC. At [23], the features of shape, configuration, pattern or ornamentation contained within the Registered Design, capable of being judged by the eye, are identified by his Honour. At [24], his Honour observes, 'I have inspected the inflated DMC product and compared it with the Registered Design. The inflated DMC product possesses each of the features identified in the Applicant's written submissions (those identified at [23]), with the exception that the handles do not protrude from the top of the surf mat as depicted in the Registered Design. The handles on the Wavestar also do not protrude from the top of the surf mat, as depicted in the Registered Design. His Honour concluded that, 'For present purposes, being the interlocutory purposes, I am satisfied that, to the eye, the shape of the DMC product is substantially the same as that of the Registered Design. It is, in my opinion, strongly arguable that the design, which has been applied to the DMC product, is an obvious imitation of the Registered Design. That is, in the words of the test in Malleys (Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352) , to be found at p 354 of the report: "Not the same but a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences".' [27]
 (m) His Honour observed that even if the design applied to the DMC article is not an obvious imitation of the Registered Design, the test for fraudulent imitation is even more strongly arguable [28]. His Honour identified the tests approved by the High Court in Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 and the High Court's approval of the observations of Lehane J in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167. His Honour concluded: 'I am satisfied that there is a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation. It seems inevitable that, if the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design, then the DMC product is a fraudulent imitation. The design of the Wavestar and the DMC product is almost identical. It could not have been independently created. It is now admitted that the DMC product is a copy of the Wavestar .' [31] 'So, also, is the embarrassing identity of the direct words of the warning label, including the imprinting of the words: "The shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design". ' 
 (n) At [33], his Honour said this: 'It is not denied that Mr Corrick was supplied with a sample of the Wavestar surf mat and had discussed obtaining a licence of the design. It seems plain that there is a strongly arguable case of obvious imitation or fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design.' 
 (o) On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour considered the observations of the High Court in Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618 at 625 and the principles affirmed by the High Court in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46 and weighed in the balance the implications arising out of a consideration that DMC had 'in the face of warnings' from Midamarine and 'with eyes wide open' embarked upon a course of importing, selling and offering for sale articles to which a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design had been applied. At [39], his Honour said this: 'In my judgment, the balance of convenience strongly favours the grant of the injunction sought. The chronology of events, and in particular the history of the design of the DMC product that is to say no design, but a direct copy indicates that the respondents have decided to import and distribute the DMC product with their eyes open to the likely consequences of so doing.' 
 (p) At [40], his Honour further referred to submissions by counsel for Midamarine and quoted this submission, 'No reasonable trader, having received the sales pitch from Mr Binkin [in June 2005] for the Wavestar , could reasonably ignore the existence of the rights [claimed in the design]' . (The words in the square brackets are explanatory words inserted into counsel's submission by his Honour). 
 (q) As to the question of damage accruing to Midamarine, his Honour said this: 'In this particular case, the applicant is shown to be an established manufacturer and supplier of the Wavestar surf mats. It is strongly arguable that that product has the benefit of the protection of the Registered Design. It has been creating a market for its product and supplying its product to distributors since 2004. [35]. 'Earlier this year, the applicant entered into an exclusive distributor arrangement with Britz Marketing. I accept that its fortunes are tied to its ability to distribute its products via Britz Marketing. The Wavestar is now exclusively sold by Britz Marketing under the name Wahu Wavetube . That surf mat is sold in an extensive range of shops, including Toyworld, Big W, Rebel Sports, Target and Toy'R'Us. Mr Britz says the Wahu Wavetube has been heavily promoted'. [36] 'Since the First Respondent [DMC] began, in October 2006, to sell the DMC product, Amart All Sports has ceased all sales of the Wahu Wavetube and has acquired, instead, the DMC product. I accept that the inability to sell surf mats to the applicant's design to Amart has a significant impact on the ability of the applicant to make sales.' 
 (r) On the question of an assessment of potential wider injury, his Honour concluded that, 'There is a serious over-statement of those risks in the evidence on behalf of the applicant'. [38] His Honour concluded that there was 'a deal of exaggeration in the injury inherent' in the contentions of Mr Britz that Britz Marketing would have to give serious consideration to sourcing surf mats from a different and cheaper source than Midamarine if DMC products continued to be sold. 
 (s) At [41], his Honour reached this conclusionary observation, 'The strength of the applicant's case of deliberate copying by the first respondent favours the grant of the interlocutory injunction. The impugned DMC products are clearly and objectively a deliberate copy of the Wavestar . The person responsible for the design and manufacturer of the DMC product knew that the product was a copy of the Wavestar , and knew of the claim that the design of the Wavestar product was protected by a Registered Design. In those circumstances, it seems to me that DMC has embarked on a task of ordering and importing the impugned products with its eyes wide open as to the potential consequences of so doing, namely, that it will be exposed to the present application.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/1.html</AustLII>
<text>9 His Honour's Reasons reflect the following observations concerning his Honour's assessment of the evidence before him and the legal issues:
 
 
 (a) The Applicant applied for the Registered Design on 24 December 2001. The Registered Design was granted on 27 May 2003 and since September 2004 Midamarine has, through arrangements with a licensee, Britz Innovation Pty Ltd ('Britz Innovation') and a related company Kalinin Pty Ltd ('Kalinin'), a company trading as 'Britz Marketing', been selling an inflatable surfcraft described as the ' Wavestar '. The Applicant also sells another surfcraft article described as the ' Surfster '.
 (b) The Applicant contends that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design.
 (c) In June 2005, Mr Russell Joel Binkin ('Mr Binkin'), 'an associate of the applicant, provided a sample of the Wavestar to Mr Corrick and endeavoured to persuade him that he should licence the design of the Wavestar from the applicant. Mr Corrick was provided with artwork, which came from the applicant. I am satisfied that the sample of the Wavestar and the artwork contained clear notification of a Registered Design, and the artwork and sample contained the Warning which presently appears on the physical exhibit of the Wavestar. It is to be expected, I would have thought, that there was copyright in somebody in that formulation of the Warning.' [6]
 (d) 'After the meeting and the supply of the sample and artwork, Mr Corrick indicated he was not interested in pursuing a licence for the product.' [7]
 (e) In January 2006, Midamarine and Britz Marketing entered into an exclusive distributorship in relation to the Wavestar surfcraft. In February 2006, Mr Corrick commenced negotiations with the National Rugby League ('NRL') and the Australian Football League ('AFL') to use the trade marks of NRL and AFL sporting teams on surfcraft or surf mats. 
 (f) On 8 September 2006, a director of Midamarine, Mr Michael Arenson, learnt that DMC was supplying a surfcraft article to 'Amart All Sports' which was said by Mr Arenson to be strikingly similar to the Wavestar . 
 (g) On 22 September 2006, Mr Arenson saw a reproduction of the DMC article. Mr Arenson spoke to Mr Corrick and wrote a letter to him on 24 September 2006 drawing his attention to the similarities in the design features between the Wavestar article and the DMC article. Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the fact that the warning label endorsed on the DMC article was a direct copy of the Warning Notice on the Wavestar article. In particular, Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the reproduction on the DMC article of the claim, 'The shape of this inflated product is a Registered Design' . 
 (h) On 27 September 2006, the solicitors for DMC applied to register a design of a surfcraft in the name of DMC and, in that Application, Mr Corrick was described as the designer. His Honour observed that: 'No documents supporting his design exist, for the good reason that, in fact, the DMC product is a direct and complete copy of the Wavestar. ' [11]
 (i) His Honour noted: 'It is now conceded that the DMC surf mat is indeed a copy - and a deliberate copy of the Wavestar ' . This, in my view, had to be so. The visual comparison leads to that conclusion. The fact that the Wavestar was left with Mr Corrick, the comparison of the two and the identity of the words used in the Warning on the back of the DMC surf mat and, in particular, "the shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design", lead inevitably to the conclusion that the DMC product is a direct copy of the Wavestar '. [12] 'The words on the Wavestar reflect the contention by Mr Arenson that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design. The presence of those words on the DMC product is, in my opinion, damning evidence of copying by DMC of the Wavestar.' [13] 
 (j) Counsel for DMC contended that the Wavestar is not an embodiment of the Registered Design and in any event, the Registered Design is invalid. As to the latter question, his Honour concluded that for interlocutory purposes, the Applicant is to be treated as the owner of a valid Registered Design having regard to differences in the features of shape reflected in the examples of prior art. 'Indeed, the attack on the validity of the Registered Design is seriously undermined by DMC's own application for registration of the design of the DMC product, which application is tainted with dishonesty and fraudulent claims. I accept that it has been acknowledged that the application will be withdrawn or otherwise expunged.' [16]
 (l) His Honour addressed Midamarine's contention that DMC had applied the Registered Design or a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design to articles sold and offered for sale by DMC. At [23], the features of shape, configuration, pattern or ornamentation contained within the Registered Design, capable of being judged by the eye, are identified by his Honour. At [24], his Honour observes, 'I have inspected the inflated DMC product and compared it with the Registered Design. The inflated DMC product possesses each of the features identified in the Applicant's written submissions (those identified at [23]), with the exception that the handles do not protrude from the top of the surf mat as depicted in the Registered Design. The handles on the Wavestar also do not protrude from the top of the surf mat, as depicted in the Registered Design. His Honour concluded that, 'For present purposes, being the interlocutory purposes, I am satisfied that, to the eye, the shape of the DMC product is substantially the same as that of the Registered Design. It is, in my opinion, strongly arguable that the design, which has been applied to the DMC product, is an obvious imitation of the Registered Design. That is, in the words of the test in Malleys (Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352) , to be found at p 354 of the report: "Not the same but a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences".' [27]
 (m) His Honour observed that even if the design applied to the DMC article is not an obvious imitation of the Registered Design, the test for fraudulent imitation is even more strongly arguable [28]. His Honour identified the tests approved by the High Court in Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 and the High Court's approval of the observations of Lehane J in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167. His Honour concluded: 'I am satisfied that there is a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation. It seems inevitable that, if the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design, then the DMC product is a fraudulent imitation. The design of the Wavestar and the DMC product is almost identical. It could not have been independently created. It is now admitted that the DMC product is a copy of the Wavestar .' [31] 'So, also, is the embarrassing identity of the direct words of the warning label, including the imprinting of the words: "The shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design". ' 
 (n) At [33], his Honour said this: 'It is not denied that Mr Corrick was supplied with a sample of the Wavestar surf mat and had discussed obtaining a licence of the design. It seems plain that there is a strongly arguable case of obvious imitation or fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design.' 
 (o) On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour considered the observations of the High Court in Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618 at 625 and the principles affirmed by the High Court in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46 and weighed in the balance the implications arising out of a consideration that DMC had 'in the face of warnings' from Midamarine and 'with eyes wide open' embarked upon a course of importing, selling and offering for sale articles to which a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design had been applied. At [39], his Honour said this: 'In my judgment, the balance of convenience strongly favours the grant of the injunction sought. The chronology of events, and in particular the history of the design of the DMC product that is to say no design, but a direct copy indicates that the respondents have decided to import and distribute the DMC product with their eyes open to the likely consequences of so doing.' 
 (p) At [40], his Honour further referred to submissions by counsel for Midamarine and quoted this submission, 'No reasonable trader, having received the sales pitch from Mr Binkin [in June 2005] for the Wavestar , could reasonably ignore the existence of the rights [claimed in the design]' . (The words in the square brackets are explanatory words inserted into counsel's submission by his Honour). 
 (q) As to the question of damage accruing to Midamarine, his Honour said this: 'In this particular case, the applicant is shown to be an established manufacturer and supplier of the Wavestar surf mats. It is strongly arguable that that product has the benefit of the protection of the Registered Design. It has been creating a market for its product and supplying its product to distributors since 2004. [35]. 'Earlier this year, the applicant entered into an exclusive distributor arrangement with Britz Marketing. I accept that its fortunes are tied to its ability to distribute its products via Britz Marketing. The Wavestar is now exclusively sold by Britz Marketing under the name Wahu Wavetube . That surf mat is sold in an extensive range of shops, including Toyworld, Big W, Rebel Sports, Target and Toy'R'Us. Mr Britz says the Wahu Wavetube has been heavily promoted'. [36] 'Since the First Respondent [DMC] began, in October 2006, to sell the DMC product, Amart All Sports has ceased all sales of the Wahu Wavetube and has acquired, instead, the DMC product. I accept that the inability to sell surf mats to the applicant's design to Amart has a significant impact on the ability of the applicant to make sales.' 
 (r) On the question of an assessment of potential wider injury, his Honour concluded that, 'There is a serious over-statement of those risks in the evidence on behalf of the applicant'. [38] His Honour concluded that there was 'a deal of exaggeration in the injury inherent' in the contentions of Mr Britz that Britz Marketing would have to give serious consideration to sourcing surf mats from a different and cheaper source than Midamarine if DMC products continued to be sold. 
 (s) At [41], his Honour reached this conclusionary observation, 'The strength of the applicant's case of deliberate copying by the first respondent favours the grant of the interlocutory injunction. The impugned DMC products are clearly and objectively a deliberate copy of the Wavestar . The person responsible for the design and manufacturer of the DMC product knew that the product was a copy of the Wavestar , and knew of the claim that the design of the Wavestar product was protected by a Registered Design. In those circumstances, it seems to me that DMC has embarked on a task of ordering and importing the impugned products with its eyes wide open as to the potential consequences of so doing, namely, that it will be exposed to the present application.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/46.html</AustLII>
<text>9 His Honour's Reasons reflect the following observations concerning his Honour's assessment of the evidence before him and the legal issues:
 
 
 (a) The Applicant applied for the Registered Design on 24 December 2001. The Registered Design was granted on 27 May 2003 and since September 2004 Midamarine has, through arrangements with a licensee, Britz Innovation Pty Ltd ('Britz Innovation') and a related company Kalinin Pty Ltd ('Kalinin'), a company trading as 'Britz Marketing', been selling an inflatable surfcraft described as the ' Wavestar '. The Applicant also sells another surfcraft article described as the ' Surfster '.
 (b) The Applicant contends that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design.
 (c) In June 2005, Mr Russell Joel Binkin ('Mr Binkin'), 'an associate of the applicant, provided a sample of the Wavestar to Mr Corrick and endeavoured to persuade him that he should licence the design of the Wavestar from the applicant. Mr Corrick was provided with artwork, which came from the applicant. I am satisfied that the sample of the Wavestar and the artwork contained clear notification of a Registered Design, and the artwork and sample contained the Warning which presently appears on the physical exhibit of the Wavestar. It is to be expected, I would have thought, that there was copyright in somebody in that formulation of the Warning.' [6]
 (d) 'After the meeting and the supply of the sample and artwork, Mr Corrick indicated he was not interested in pursuing a licence for the product.' [7]
 (e) In January 2006, Midamarine and Britz Marketing entered into an exclusive distributorship in relation to the Wavestar surfcraft. In February 2006, Mr Corrick commenced negotiations with the National Rugby League ('NRL') and the Australian Football League ('AFL') to use the trade marks of NRL and AFL sporting teams on surfcraft or surf mats. 
 (f) On 8 September 2006, a director of Midamarine, Mr Michael Arenson, learnt that DMC was supplying a surfcraft article to 'Amart All Sports' which was said by Mr Arenson to be strikingly similar to the Wavestar . 
 (g) On 22 September 2006, Mr Arenson saw a reproduction of the DMC article. Mr Arenson spoke to Mr Corrick and wrote a letter to him on 24 September 2006 drawing his attention to the similarities in the design features between the Wavestar article and the DMC article. Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the fact that the warning label endorsed on the DMC article was a direct copy of the Warning Notice on the Wavestar article. In particular, Mr Arenson drew Mr Corrick's attention to the reproduction on the DMC article of the claim, 'The shape of this inflated product is a Registered Design' . 
 (h) On 27 September 2006, the solicitors for DMC applied to register a design of a surfcraft in the name of DMC and, in that Application, Mr Corrick was described as the designer. His Honour observed that: 'No documents supporting his design exist, for the good reason that, in fact, the DMC product is a direct and complete copy of the Wavestar. ' [11]
 (i) His Honour noted: 'It is now conceded that the DMC surf mat is indeed a copy - and a deliberate copy of the Wavestar ' . This, in my view, had to be so. The visual comparison leads to that conclusion. The fact that the Wavestar was left with Mr Corrick, the comparison of the two and the identity of the words used in the Warning on the back of the DMC surf mat and, in particular, "the shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design", lead inevitably to the conclusion that the DMC product is a direct copy of the Wavestar '. [12] 'The words on the Wavestar reflect the contention by Mr Arenson that the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design. The presence of those words on the DMC product is, in my opinion, damning evidence of copying by DMC of the Wavestar.' [13] 
 (j) Counsel for DMC contended that the Wavestar is not an embodiment of the Registered Design and in any event, the Registered Design is invalid. As to the latter question, his Honour concluded that for interlocutory purposes, the Applicant is to be treated as the owner of a valid Registered Design having regard to differences in the features of shape reflected in the examples of prior art. 'Indeed, the attack on the validity of the Registered Design is seriously undermined by DMC's own application for registration of the design of the DMC product, which application is tainted with dishonesty and fraudulent claims. I accept that it has been acknowledged that the application will be withdrawn or otherwise expunged.' [16]
 (l) His Honour addressed Midamarine's contention that DMC had applied the Registered Design or a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design to articles sold and offered for sale by DMC. At [23], the features of shape, configuration, pattern or ornamentation contained within the Registered Design, capable of being judged by the eye, are identified by his Honour. At [24], his Honour observes, 'I have inspected the inflated DMC product and compared it with the Registered Design. The inflated DMC product possesses each of the features identified in the Applicant's written submissions (those identified at [23]), with the exception that the handles do not protrude from the top of the surf mat as depicted in the Registered Design. The handles on the Wavestar also do not protrude from the top of the surf mat, as depicted in the Registered Design. His Honour concluded that, 'For present purposes, being the interlocutory purposes, I am satisfied that, to the eye, the shape of the DMC product is substantially the same as that of the Registered Design. It is, in my opinion, strongly arguable that the design, which has been applied to the DMC product, is an obvious imitation of the Registered Design. That is, in the words of the test in Malleys (Malleys Ltd v J W Tomlin Pty Limited [1961-62] 35 ALJR 352) , to be found at p 354 of the report: "Not the same but a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences".' [27]
 (m) His Honour observed that even if the design applied to the DMC article is not an obvious imitation of the Registered Design, the test for fraudulent imitation is even more strongly arguable [28]. His Honour identified the tests approved by the High Court in Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 and the High Court's approval of the observations of Lehane J in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167. His Honour concluded: 'I am satisfied that there is a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation. It seems inevitable that, if the Wavestar is an embodiment of the Registered Design, then the DMC product is a fraudulent imitation. The design of the Wavestar and the DMC product is almost identical. It could not have been independently created. It is now admitted that the DMC product is a copy of the Wavestar .' [31] 'So, also, is the embarrassing identity of the direct words of the warning label, including the imprinting of the words: "The shape of this inflatable product is a Registered Design". ' 
 (n) At [33], his Honour said this: 'It is not denied that Mr Corrick was supplied with a sample of the Wavestar surf mat and had discussed obtaining a licence of the design. It seems plain that there is a strongly arguable case of obvious imitation or fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design.' 
 (o) On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour considered the observations of the High Court in Beecham Group Limited v Bristol Laboratories Pty Limited [1968] HCA 1 ; (1967-68) 118 CLR 618 at 625 and the principles affirmed by the High Court in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill [2006] HCA 46 and weighed in the balance the implications arising out of a consideration that DMC had 'in the face of warnings' from Midamarine and 'with eyes wide open' embarked upon a course of importing, selling and offering for sale articles to which a fraudulent or obvious imitation of the Registered Design had been applied. At [39], his Honour said this: 'In my judgment, the balance of convenience strongly favours the grant of the injunction sought. The chronology of events, and in particular the history of the design of the DMC product that is to say no design, but a direct copy indicates that the respondents have decided to import and distribute the DMC product with their eyes open to the likely consequences of so doing.' 
 (p) At [40], his Honour further referred to submissions by counsel for Midamarine and quoted this submission, 'No reasonable trader, having received the sales pitch from Mr Binkin [in June 2005] for the Wavestar , could reasonably ignore the existence of the rights [claimed in the design]' . (The words in the square brackets are explanatory words inserted into counsel's submission by his Honour). 
 (q) As to the question of damage accruing to Midamarine, his Honour said this: 'In this particular case, the applicant is shown to be an established manufacturer and supplier of the Wavestar surf mats. It is strongly arguable that that product has the benefit of the protection of the Registered Design. It has been creating a market for its product and supplying its product to distributors since 2004. [35]. 'Earlier this year, the applicant entered into an exclusive distributor arrangement with Britz Marketing. I accept that its fortunes are tied to its ability to distribute its products via Britz Marketing. The Wavestar is now exclusively sold by Britz Marketing under the name Wahu Wavetube . That surf mat is sold in an extensive range of shops, including Toyworld, Big W, Rebel Sports, Target and Toy'R'Us. Mr Britz says the Wahu Wavetube has been heavily promoted'. [36] 'Since the First Respondent [DMC] began, in October 2006, to sell the DMC product, Amart All Sports has ceased all sales of the Wahu Wavetube and has acquired, instead, the DMC product. I accept that the inability to sell surf mats to the applicant's design to Amart has a significant impact on the ability of the applicant to make sales.' 
 (r) On the question of an assessment of potential wider injury, his Honour concluded that, 'There is a serious over-statement of those risks in the evidence on behalf of the applicant'. [38] His Honour concluded that there was 'a deal of exaggeration in the injury inherent' in the contentions of Mr Britz that Britz Marketing would have to give serious consideration to sourcing surf mats from a different and cheaper source than Midamarine if DMC products continued to be sold. 
 (s) At [41], his Honour reached this conclusionary observation, 'The strength of the applicant's case of deliberate copying by the first respondent favours the grant of the interlocutory injunction. The impugned DMC products are clearly and objectively a deliberate copy of the Wavestar . The person responsible for the design and manufacturer of the DMC product knew that the product was a copy of the Wavestar , and knew of the claim that the design of the Wavestar product was protected by a Registered Design. In those circumstances, it seems to me that DMC has embarked on a task of ordering and importing the impugned products with its eyes wide open as to the potential consequences of so doing, namely, that it will be exposed to the present application.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Dart Industries Inc. (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>10 The questions to be determined on this Application are whether, in all the circumstances, the decision of his Honour is attended with sufficient doubt so as to warrant the decision being reconsidered by the Full Court and whether substantial injustice would result if leave is refused, supposing the decision to be wrong ( D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Dart Industries Inc. (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398 and 399 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ). At pp 399 and 400, their Honours said this:
 
 'In our opinion, the principles discussed in Niemann and in other cases to which we have referred provide general guidance which a court should normally accept. However, there will continue to be cases raising special considerations, and the court should not regard its hands as tied in any case beyond this; that by s 24(1A) the legislature has evinced a policy against the bringing of interlocutory appeals except where the court, acting judicially, finds reason to grant leave. 
 
 When the court comes to exercise its discretion on a particular application, an important distinction to be observed is that between the common interlocutory decision on a point of practice ... and an interlocutory decision determining a substantive right where leave will more readily be granted. ... 
 
 In the present case, the interlocutory decisions in respect of which leave is sought are certainly attended with difficulty, and their correctness is open to dispute. If they are wrong, significant consequences will be suffered by the applicants. We regard this as a clear case for the grant of leave.' 
 
 
 In Yap Cheng See v Granich &amp; Associates [2001] FCA 1735 per North, Merkel and Gyles JJ, the Court noted the distinction to be drawn between an interlocutory decision on a point of practice or procedure and an interlocutory injunction 'on a point of substance' [6].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yap Cheng See v Granich &amp; Associates [2001] FCA 1735</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1735.html</AustLII>
<text>10 The questions to be determined on this Application are whether, in all the circumstances, the decision of his Honour is attended with sufficient doubt so as to warrant the decision being reconsidered by the Full Court and whether substantial injustice would result if leave is refused, supposing the decision to be wrong ( D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Dart Industries Inc. (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398 and 399 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ). At pp 399 and 400, their Honours said this:
 
 'In our opinion, the principles discussed in Niemann and in other cases to which we have referred provide general guidance which a court should normally accept. However, there will continue to be cases raising special considerations, and the court should not regard its hands as tied in any case beyond this; that by s 24(1A) the legislature has evinced a policy against the bringing of interlocutory appeals except where the court, acting judicially, finds reason to grant leave. 
 
 When the court comes to exercise its discretion on a particular application, an important distinction to be observed is that between the common interlocutory decision on a point of practice ... and an interlocutory decision determining a substantive right where leave will more readily be granted. ... 
 
 In the present case, the interlocutory decisions in respect of which leave is sought are certainly attended with difficulty, and their correctness is open to dispute. If they are wrong, significant consequences will be suffered by the applicants. We regard this as a clear case for the grant of leave.' 
 
 
 In Yap Cheng See v Granich &amp; Associates [2001] FCA 1735 per North, Merkel and Gyles JJ, the Court noted the distinction to be drawn between an interlocutory decision on a point of practice or procedure and an interlocutory injunction 'on a point of substance' [6].

32 Fourthly , Mr Corrick says that he first conceived of the possibility of marketing and selling inflatable surfcraft featuring the designs and logos of the NRL and AFL teams during the course of his holidays during December 2005 and January 2006 at Noosa in Queensland. Mr Corrick says that on his return to Sydney he proposed the notion to the NRL and AFL in February 2006 and then developed a concept and design but did so in circumstances where he was not aware of Midamarine's Registered Design. Mr Corrick says that he spent $30,000 developing the concept of the surfcraft endorsed with the designs, for approval of the NRL and AFL. In May 2006, licence agreements with the NRL and AFL were negotiated. Mr Corrick says that he does not have any documents in his possession, power or control in relation to the 'design process undertaken in developing the DMC surf mat' . DMC concedes that it copied the Wavestar article although DMC and Mr Corrick contend that that conduct occurred without any knowledge of or reference to the Registered Design or an assertion of such rights by Midamarine. That matter is the subject of controversy for the purposes of the action.

33 Fifthly , Mr Corrick in his affidavit says that Mr Binkin came to him with three product proposals for endorsement with NRL team graphics, 'a team branded rug or floor covering, wall hangings and the surf mat' . The surf mat was just one of a number. Mr Corrick says he did not proceed with any of the proposals. There was an existing licensee for floor mats and the NRL was not satisfied that the proposal concerning floor coverings and wall hangings was sufficiently differentiated. Although Mr Corrick mentioned the surf mat proposal to the NRL, 'the NRL was not interested' . However, by May 2006, Mr Corrick and DMC had established confidential licensing arrangements with each of the NRL, ARU and AFL to manufacture and supply inflatable surf mats displaying the names and logos of the various teams in the National football competitions administered by those bodies.

34 I am not satisfied that his Honour's decision is attended with doubt as to the conclusions he reached concerning these matters going to the strength of the arguable question to be determined at the trial of the action.

35 His Honour then considered where the balance of convenience lay and whether Midamarine had demonstrated that it had and would continue to suffer injury or damage not compensable by an award of damages. As to the question of irreparable harm, his Honour noted that Midamarine had embarked upon a process of developing the Wavestar and Surfster devices, had established a position as a manufacturer and supplier particularly of the Wavestar surf mats and had embarked upon a course of creating a market for the product and supplying the product to distributors since 2004. A part of that incremental process involved establishing an exclusive distribution arrangement with Mr Britz and his companies. His Honour also noted that the intervention of DMC had resulted in the loss of all future sales for the Wavestar article to an important buyer, Amart All Sports. His Honour accepted evidence that the loss of sales to Amart All Sports had a significant impact on the ability of Midamarine to make sales of its Wavestar product. His Honour formed the view that the impact of the conduct of DMC upon Midamarine's incremental development of the market for its product [35] was significant. The question seemed to be not one of just assessing lost sales but an assessment of the injury to the incremental development of the market by Midamarine and emblematic of that affect was the impact upon the purchasing behaviour of Amart All Sports and inferentially others.

36 It is correct that his Honour was critical of the evidence of Midamarine as to a wider injury or impact of the conduct of DMC. However, the assessment of the impact upon Midamarine in its development of the market was found, by his Honour, upon all the evidence to be a significant impact and thus injurious of Midamarine in a way difficult of assessment.

37 On the question of the balance of convenience, his Honour had regard to the strength of the arguable case established by Midamarine and the features of the conduct discussed in these Reasons which led to his Honour's conclusion that Mr Corrick had embarked upon a course of conduct astute to the assertions by Midamarine of rights derivative of its Registered Design. His Honour noted the exchanges between Mr Binkin and Mr Corrick, the submission of the two email graphic depictions, the copying of the Warning Instructions containing the reference to the shape of the inflated Wavestar product being a Registered Design, the lack of any evidence of independent design, the contention that DMC was at one point entitled to a Registered Design for its article although now to be discontinued. For interlocutory purposes, his Honour accepted Midamarine's evidence directed to the conscious quality of the conduct particularly the contentions, on all the evidence, that DMC adopted the features of shape, pattern and ornamentation in circumstances amounting to obvious imitation and, having regard to the evidence of knowledge, in a way amounting to fraudulent imitation.

38 I am not satisfied that his Honour's decision in support of the Orders in relation to irreparable damage and the assessment of the balance of convenience is attended by doubt.

39 DMC relies upon three further matters namely, the adequacy of Midamarine's undertaking as to damages, the imminent trial of the matter to commence during the early part of December (possibly 6 December 2006) and DMC's offer to keep proper records relating to importation and sale.

40 As to Midamarine's undertaking, DMC contends that any loss it suffers by reason of the Order will not realistically be recoverable having regard to the financial strength of Midamarine. Midamarine has provided the usual undertaking as to damages and there is a differentiation in the financial standing of Midamarine and DMC. However, in circumstances where Midamarine has satisfied the elements required to be discharged, according to principle, in the exercise of the discretion in the making of an interlocutory injunction Order pending trial, it seems to me that Midamarine ought not to be deprived of the benefit of the interlocutory Order on the ground that it is a corporation incrementally establishing in a market for its products and its financial standing is disproportionate to that of DMC. There is no evidence that Midamarine is in financial difficulty.

41 As to the imminence of the trial, DMC contends that because the trial of the action is to take place in the early part of December, the discretion ought to be exercised against making an interlocutory Order. However, because the trial is imminent, there is a real prospect that the period of the interlocutory restraint confronting DMC is likely to be short and the effect of the Order less burdensome.

42 As to the offer to keep proper records, two things should be said. Firstly, an undertaking to keep proper records is designed to preserve the evidence which would be relied upon by a successful applicant at trial in identifying the basis for an accurate calculation of its compensable loss in money terms. In circumstances where injury or harm not susceptible of compensation in money terms accrues to an applicant by reason of the respondent's conduct, an undertaking to keep proper records is less relevant. Secondly, as indicated in these Reasons, Spender J reached conclusions concerning the strength of the arguable case based upon evidence which suggests a strongly arguable case of fraudulent imitation of the Registered Design. In those circumstances, a question arises as to whether an applicant ought to be deprived of an interlocutory Order and put in a position of reliance upon an interlocutory undertaking of such a respondent. It seems to me that in the circumstances of this case, the Applicant ought not to be put in such a position.

43 Accordingly, I am not satisfied that by reason of the three further matters, his Honour's decision leading to the making of the interlocutory Order is attended by doubt.

44 Accordingly, I propose to dismiss the Application for leave to appeal and order DMC to pay Midamarine's costs of and incidental to the Notice of Motion. 
 I certify that the preceding forty-four (44) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood. 

 Associate:

Dated: 22 November 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: Ms Downes 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mr Hall, Swaab Attorneys 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Respondent appeared by its Solicitor 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Mr Philp, Bennett &amp; Philp, Solicitors 
 
 Date of Hearing: 9 November 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 November 2006 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1591.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>