<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Slick v Westpac Banking Corporation (ACN 007 457 141)(No 1) [2006] FCA 1711 (4 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1711.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Biscayne Partners Pty Ltd v Valance Corp Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 874</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2003/874.html</AustLII>
<text>12 The reasons why a failure to complain may have relevance or may assist in resolution of an issue were stated by Einstein J in Biscayne Partners Pty Ltd v Valance Corp Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 874 at [150] . What underlies his Honour's explanation is that a failure to complain may point to a finding of absence of any real ground for complaint or reliance where a plaintiff would be expected to have spoken. But the principle assumes that the person had knowledge of the alleged misrepresentation at the relevant time. That is to say, how can a failure to complain about that which the party was unaware have any real probative value?

13 Whether the failure to complain goes to credit or to an issue in the proceeding will depend on the facts and circumstances of each case. In the present proceedings it may be that the proposed cross-examination goes in some way to the issue of reliance as shown in the authorities relied upon by the respondents. However, in light of the material which the respondents wish to explore as set out in the draft list of proposed topics of cross-examination, I am inclined to the view that the cross-examination will go in some significant respects to Mr Seward's credit.

14 To the extent that the proposed cross-examination will go to credit I am not satisfied that it would have substantial probative value. Moreover, I am not persuaded that a sufficient evidentiary basis has been established on the present motion to warrant reopening cross-examination. In particular, it appears from evidence adduced in the proceedings that in the period from 2001-2002 BWC was suffering increasing financial difficulties but it is not established on this motion that Mr Seward was at that time aware, as the applicants contend, that Quadrant had allowed Mr Blom to present projections to the applicants without revealing that Blom's earlier (and less optimistic) projections had failed.

15 Insofar as the respondents call in aid the "most walks of life" ordinary human nature test referred to by Einstein J in Biscayne , the material referred to in the respondents' affidavits on the motion seems to me to be insufficient to justify the exercise of my discretion. I do not consider that the topics listed in the draft list illustrate with a sufficient degree of confidence that the evidence would have sufficient evidentiary value to justify me in exercising my discretion in this matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Brown v Petranker (1991) 22 NSWLR 717</tocase>
<text>7 The principles stated in Brown v Petranker (1991) 22 NSWLR 717 at 728-9 by Clarke JA (with whom Handley JA and Waddell AJA agreed) applied to an application by a party to recall a witness to give further evidence in chief. Nevertheless, in my opinion the overriding principle stated by Clarke JA seems to be the appropriate test. That is, the exercise of the court's discretion is dependent upon whether the interests of justice require leave to be granted or refused. Inquiry includes an examination of any prejudice to the other party; see also R v Gassy (No 3) (2005) 93 SASR 454 at [318].

8 The principles stated by Jeffrey J in Henning v Lynch [1974] 2 NSWLR 254 at 259, to which Clarke JA referred with approval in Brown v Petranker, also dealt with reopening to tender additional evidence. In my view the test of "accident, mistake or want of foresight" to which Jeffrey J referred is only a guiding factor. The overriding consideration is the interests of justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cordelia Holdings Pty Ltd v Newkey Investments Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 48</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/48.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The respondents rely upon a number of authorities for the proposition that a failure to complain prior to the commencement of proceedings may be a significant factor from which the court can draw an inference that the party did not rely on any such representation. Thus, it is submitted by the respondents that the proposed cross-examination goes to an issue in the cause rather than to credit; see Dukemaster Pty Ltd v Bluehive Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 377 at [58] ; see also Cordelia Holdings Pty Ltd v Newkey Investments Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 48 at [71] - [77] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dukemaster Pty Ltd v Bluehive Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 377</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/377.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The respondents rely upon a number of authorities for the proposition that a failure to complain prior to the commencement of proceedings may be a significant factor from which the court can draw an inference that the party did not rely on any such representation. Thus, it is submitted by the respondents that the proposed cross-examination goes to an issue in the cause rather than to credit; see Dukemaster Pty Ltd v Bluehive Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 377 at [58] ; see also Cordelia Holdings Pty Ltd v Newkey Investments Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 48 at [71] - [77] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/22.html</AustLII>
<text>16 It is true, as the High Court said in Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118 at [31] , that a factual finding should, so far as possible, turn on the basis of "contemporary materials, objectively established facts and the apparent logic of events". Nevertheless, I do not see that a sufficient basis has been established to allow the issue of failure to complain to be explored in the manner proposed; nor do I consider that the observations of the High Court in MWJ v The Queen [2005] HCA 74 ; (2005) 222 ALR 436 at [39] - [40] on the application of the rule in Browne v Dunn assist in the resolution of this motion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Henning v Lynch [1974] 2 NSWLR 254</tocase>
<text>8 The principles stated by Jeffrey J in Henning v Lynch [1974] 2 NSWLR 254 at 259, to which Clarke JA referred with approval in Brown v Petranker, also dealt with reopening to tender additional evidence. In my view the test of "accident, mistake or want of foresight" to which Jeffrey J referred is only a guiding factor. The overriding consideration is the interests of justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ishac v David Securities Pty Limited (No 5) (unreported, Young J, 24 March 1992)</tocase>
<text>6 In Ishac v David Securities Pty Limited (No 5) (unreported, Young J, 24 March 1992) His Honour listed four common situations where it is appropriate to allow further cross-examination. Only the first is relevant to the present case. It is where there is a bona fide omission by cross-examining counsel to deal with the subject and the omission comes to the cross-examiner's attention shortly after the witness has left the witness box. I do not consider that his Honour was attempting to lay down an exhaustive list. Rather, he set out guiding factors for the exercise of the discretion in situations which may be thought commonly to arise.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>MWJ v The Queen [2005] HCA 74 ; (2005) 222 ALR 436</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/74.html</AustLII>
<text>16 It is true, as the High Court said in Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118 at [31] , that a factual finding should, so far as possible, turn on the basis of "contemporary materials, objectively established facts and the apparent logic of events". Nevertheless, I do not see that a sufficient basis has been established to allow the issue of failure to complain to be explored in the manner proposed; nor do I consider that the observations of the High Court in MWJ v The Queen [2005] HCA 74 ; (2005) 222 ALR 436 at [39] - [40] on the application of the rule in Browne v Dunn assist in the resolution of this motion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Gassy (No 3) (2005) 93 SASR 454</tocase>
<text>7 The principles stated in Brown v Petranker (1991) 22 NSWLR 717 at 728-9 by Clarke JA (with whom Handley JA and Waddell AJA agreed) applied to an application by a party to recall a witness to give further evidence in chief. Nevertheless, in my opinion the overriding principle stated by Clarke JA seems to be the appropriate test. That is, the exercise of the court's discretion is dependent upon whether the interests of justice require leave to be granted or refused. Inquiry includes an examination of any prejudice to the other party; see also R v Gassy (No 3) (2005) 93 SASR 454 at [318].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Searle v Keayes (1994) 126 ALR 728</tocase>
<text>5 As Tamberlin J said in Searle v Keayes (1994) 126 ALR 728, the trial judge has a discretion whether to permit the recall of witnesses. His Honour pointed out at 729 that "[o]ne important consideration is that litigation must be resolved and not be the subject of continuous reopening and prolongation".</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>