<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kapitany v Commonwealth of Australia [2006] FCA 111 (17 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/111.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Skalkos v T &amp; S Recoveries Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 321 ; (2004) 141 FCR 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/321.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The respondent relies on evidence that the notice was posted in accordance with the requirements of s 29(1) , and the evidence recorded at [12] that it was received at the applicant's place of business on 30 June 2005. It relies on this last-mentioned evidence as proof to the contrary for the purposes of the concluding limb of s 29(1). The applicant did not contest this aspect of the "service" issue. If service by post (ie s 28A(1) of the AIA) was available to the respondent, its reliance on s 29(1) is made out. See Skalkos v T &amp; S Recoveries Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 321 ; (2004) 141 FCR 107 at [22] , [24]-[25].

16 The issue between the parties was whether service by post was available. The applicant contended that s 36 of the Act discloses a contrary intention for the purposes of s 28A(1) of the AIA. I cannot discern in s 36 any indication that service by post is not to be available in relation to a notice under sub-s (7) thereof.

17 The applicant relied on sub-s (8)(a), which speaks of notice having been "given" to a person under sub-s (7). Sub-section (7) requires the appropriate person to "serve" the notice. Sub-section (8)(b) speaks of a failure to bring an action within four months after "service" of the notice. It was said that the contrast between "serve" and "service" on the one hand and "given" on the other shows that "serve" in sub-s (7) requires personal service. In my view that contrast is too feeble to constitute a contrary intention. In any case, s 28A(1) of the AIA applies "whether the expression 'serve', 'give' or 'send' or any other expression is used".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Secretary, Department of Social Security v Garratt (1992) 109 ALR 149</tocase>
<text>18 The applicant also relied on the obiter observations of Gummow J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Garratt (1992) 109 ALR 149 at 157-158, approved in obiter by a Full Court in Secretary, Department of Social Security v O'Connell (1992) 38 FCR 540 at 551-554. In my view Garratt is readily distinguishable. The statutory scheme in s 168(3) and (4) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth) (the SSA) was entirely different from that in the Act. Section 168(4) dealt with the time at which a determination upon internal review would take place. If the person concerned had sought review within three months after "a notice was given to the person ... advising the person of the making of the previous decision", or if no such notice was given, the determination took effect on the date of the previous decision. Otherwise, the determination took effect on the date of the application for review.

20 Unlike the present case, there was no provision in the SSA that required a notice to be given of a cancellation decision. Although the Act implicitly permitted the Secretary to serve such a document, and to serve it in accordance with s 28A of the AIA, there was no statutory link between that document and the notice of the previous decision referred to in s 168(4)(a). Thus in O'Connell at 552, the question whether the Secretary was entitled to serve a notice of cancellation in accordance with s 28A was treated as separate from whether notice had in fact been given of the previous decision for the purposes of s 168(4)(a). By contrast, s 36(7) of the Act expressly requires a notice to be served, and sub-s (8) refers to the service of that notice. That is to say, the time period specified in sub-s (8) begins to run on "the service of the notice" under sub-s (7). This is not analogous to the legislative setting in Garratt , where the relevant provisions fixed a date which was "determinative of the right of persons in relation to pensions, benefits and claims under the Act": Garratt at 157.

21 It was submitted by the applicant, again by analogy with Garratt at 157, that a contrary intention was constituted by the fact that s 36(8) brought about the forfeiture of property. I do not think that constitutes a contrary intention. In Fancourt v Mercantile Credits Ltd [1983] HCA 25 ; (1983) 154 CLR 87 at 96, speaking of a Queensland provision in the same form as s 28A, the High Court said:
 
 "Paragraphs (b) and (c) of s 42(1) contemplate the possibility of something less than actual receipt by the person to be served. As was observed by Tindal CJ in Bishop v Helps in relation to a comparable provision, although leaving notices at a place of abode or sending them through the post involve the possibility of non-receipt by the intended recipient: 
 
 
 
 'It was probably considered that the public convenience would be promoted by the present provision, and that its advantages would greatly outweigh the inconvenience which, in some few cases, might possibly arise from it.' 
 
 
 
 Nevertheless, proof of the use of any one of the methods of service provided by s 42(1) constitutes proof of service for the purpose of the Hire Purchase Act ...."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Secretary, Department of Social Security v O'Connell (1992) 38 FCR 540</tocase>
<text>18 The applicant also relied on the obiter observations of Gummow J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Garratt (1992) 109 ALR 149 at 157-158, approved in obiter by a Full Court in Secretary, Department of Social Security v O'Connell (1992) 38 FCR 540 at 551-554. In my view Garratt is readily distinguishable. The statutory scheme in s 168(3) and (4) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth) (the SSA) was entirely different from that in the Act. Section 168(4) dealt with the time at which a determination upon internal review would take place. If the person concerned had sought review within three months after "a notice was given to the person ... advising the person of the making of the previous decision", or if no such notice was given, the determination took effect on the date of the previous decision. Otherwise, the determination took effect on the date of the application for review.

20 Unlike the present case, there was no provision in the SSA that required a notice to be given of a cancellation decision. Although the Act implicitly permitted the Secretary to serve such a document, and to serve it in accordance with s 28A of the AIA, there was no statutory link between that document and the notice of the previous decision referred to in s 168(4)(a). Thus in O'Connell at 552, the question whether the Secretary was entitled to serve a notice of cancellation in accordance with s 28A was treated as separate from whether notice had in fact been given of the previous decision for the purposes of s 168(4)(a). By contrast, s 36(7) of the Act expressly requires a notice to be served, and sub-s (8) refers to the service of that notice. That is to say, the time period specified in sub-s (8) begins to run on "the service of the notice" under sub-s (7). This is not analogous to the legislative setting in Garratt , where the relevant provisions fixed a date which was "determinative of the right of persons in relation to pensions, benefits and claims under the Act": Garratt at 157.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fancourt v Mercantile Credits Ltd [1983] HCA 25 ; (1983) 154 CLR 87</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/25.html</AustLII>
<text>21 It was submitted by the applicant, again by analogy with Garratt at 157, that a contrary intention was constituted by the fact that s 36(8) brought about the forfeiture of property. I do not think that constitutes a contrary intention. In Fancourt v Mercantile Credits Ltd [1983] HCA 25 ; (1983) 154 CLR 87 at 96, speaking of a Queensland provision in the same form as s 28A, the High Court said:
 
 "Paragraphs (b) and (c) of s 42(1) contemplate the possibility of something less than actual receipt by the person to be served. As was observed by Tindal CJ in Bishop v Helps in relation to a comparable provision, although leaving notices at a place of abode or sending them through the post involve the possibility of non-receipt by the intended recipient: 
 
 
 
 'It was probably considered that the public convenience would be promoted by the present provision, and that its advantages would greatly outweigh the inconvenience which, in some few cases, might possibly arise from it.' 
 
 
 
 Nevertheless, proof of the use of any one of the methods of service provided by s 42(1) constitutes proof of service for the purpose of the Hire Purchase Act ...."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Gordon (1990) 26 FCR 569</tocase>
<text>22 Repatriation Commission v Gordon (1990) 26 FCR 569 concerned a situation analogous to that in the present case. Service of a copy of a decision marked the commencement of the period within which an application for review could be made. Spender J held that the veterans' entitlements legislation did not evince an intention that service by post was not available. His Honour said at 577:
 
 "The object of service, in whatever form, is to bring the contents of the document or documents served to the attention of the person to be served. The mere fact that one might more confidently expect that aim to be achieved if personal service, as opposed to service by pre-paid post, is required, does not permit the conclusion that service by pre-paid post was intended to be excluded. Such a consideration would apply in every case. Accepting, as I do, that the veterans' entitlement legislation is benevolent in purpose, nonetheless in my view there is nothing in its provisions which manifests an intention to preclude service by pre-paid post of the documents that s 34(2) requires the Commission to cause to be served on the claimant or applicant."

23 My conclusions are that s 28A of the AIA was available to the respondent, the notice was served in accordance with s 29 , and was delivered on 30 June 2005.

24 In case it might be thought that the application of s 28A has produced a harsh result in this case, I note four matters. First, as I have said, the notice was delivered to the applicant's business premises on 30 June 2005. Second, it was received by him, in the sense that he read it, on 5 July 2005, which gave him almost four months in which to commence proceedings. The four month period did not expire until 31 October. Third, according to the applicant's statement of claim, on or about 29 June 2005 Mr Wohlers notified him that if he did not bring an action for recovery within four months of service of the notice, the objects would be forfeited. Fourth, the applicant's counsel contacted the Department on 20 October and was informed of the Department's view that the period expired on 31 October. The file note recording the conversation states that counsel responded that "they would contemplate (bringing the action) by the end of the following week [ie 28 October 2005]". Notwithstanding this, the proceeding was commenced out of time.

25 The action against the Commonwealth for which s 37 provides is available only if two conditions are satisfied. The first is that a protected object has been seized under the Act. The second is that the object has not been forfeited by s 36. The action that is authorised by s 37(1) is one to recover the object on the ground that it is not forfeited or liable to be forfeited. In a case such as the present, the ultimate task for the court is to decide whether the object is liable to forfeiture by virtue of s 14(1). That involves determining the three matters prescribed by s 14(1): whether a protected object has been exported from a foreign country, whether the export was prohibited by a law of that country relating to cultural property, and whether the object has been imported into Australia. Section 37(3) prescribes what the court is to do in certain events. If it determines that the object is liable to forfeiture under s 14(1), it is required to order that the object is forfeited. If it finds that the object is not liable to forfeiture, it may order its return.

26 There is an oddity in the drafting of ss 34 to 37. Section 34 confers power to seize a "protected object" where the relevant belief exists. Section 36(2) and (5) and s 37 also use these words. Although s 36(8) speaks of "an object" and "the object", it is clear from s 36(5) that what sub-s (8) calls an "object" is a "protected object". One of the questions for the Court under s 37(3) is whether what has been seized is a protected object. See par (b) and s 14(1)(a). Where the court finds that an object is not liable to forfeiture by virtue of s 14(1), it may order its return. This it may do if it is not liable to forfeiture because it is not a protected object within s 14(1)(a). Accordingly, it seems to me that "protected object" in s 37(1)(a) and "the object" in par (b) must include an object that is alleged to be a protected object. Similarly with s 34, which appears to contemplate that in some cases a seized object will not in fact be liable to be forfeited because, for example, it is not in fact a protected object within s 14(1)(a).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>