<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Slick v Westpac Banking Corporation (ACN 007 457 141)(No 2) [2006] FCA 1712 (8 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1712.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Allstate Life Insurance Co v ANZ Banking Group (No 15) (unreported, Lindgren J, 22 August 1995)</tocase>
<text>9 This passage and the principle which underlies it were referred to with approval by Lindgren J in Allstate Life Insurance Co v ANZ Banking Group Limited (No 15) (unreported, Lindgren J, 22 August 1995) at pages 5-6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1981) 48 FLR 292</tocase>
<text>6 The Court has power under O 15 r 8 of the Federal Court Rules to order particular discovery where there is a defect in compliance with an earlier order. The power conferred by O 15 r 8 is discretionary; see Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1981) 48 FLR 292 at 295.

7 The orders which are sought go beyond the power conferred by O 15 r 8. However, it seems to me that I have power to make the orders under s 23 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) if I consider it to be appropriate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BT Australasia Pty Limited v State of New South Wales (unreported, Sackville J, 9 April 1998)</tocase>
<text>10 In BT Australasia Pty Limited v State of New South Wales (unreported, Sackville J, 9 April 1998), his Honour ordered Telstra to discover emails and attachments from back-up computer tapes for certain identified persons. His Honour also directed Telstra to file a report setting out the steps taken to comply with that order.

11 In deciding to make orders for additional discovery, his Honour was satisfied that Telstra had failed to fully comply with its discovery obligations. His Honour was also satisfied that the tapes contained much material that was relevant to the issues in the proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Molnlycke AB v Procter &amp; Gamble Limited (No 3) [1990] RPC 498</tocase>
<text>8 In my view, the exercise of the power is informed by similar considerations to those which underlie the power conferred by O 15 r 8. Thus, the Court may refuse to make an order if it would be unduly oppressive to the other party. As Mummery J said in Molnlycke AB v Procter &amp; Gamble Limited (No 3) [1990] RPC 498 at 503:
 
 The Court takes account of such considerations as the value of the discovery to the person seeking it and the burden imposed on the party giving it, with a view to restricting the volume of documents and the labour and expense involved to that which is necessary for fairly disposing of the issues in the case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>NT Power Generation Pty Limited v Power &amp; Water Authority [1999] FCA 1669</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1669.html</AustLII>
<text>12 In NT Power Generation Pty Limited v Power &amp; Water Authority [1999] FCA 1669 , Mansfield J declined to limit discovery to email communications which existed in hard copy form at the time of the order. His Honour indicated at [2] that it would impose a very substantial burden on the respondents to restore and examine the back up tapes.

13 However, he was not satisfied that the material which might be recoverable electronically was sufficiently insubstantial to warrant the order sought by the Respondents limiting discovery to hard copy documents. His Honour said at [17]:
 
 As I have indicated, I am not persuaded that the e-mail communications retained only electronically are unlikely to contain any material communications which are discoverable in these proceedings. I have used the word "material" to indicate communications beyond those that are merely formal or insignificant. The applicant is entitled to discovery of them. I am not persuaded, in the interests of justice, that I should excuse the Respondents from giving discovery of that material notwithstanding the time, expense, and effort involved in doing so.

14 The evidence establishes that, as one would expect, both of the respondents used email at the relevant times. Nevertheless, very few emails have been discovered and those which have been discovered fall outside the critical time periods in the proceedings.

15 Most importantly, Quadrant has not discovered any emails from Mr Hadley or Mr Penklis for the whole of the year 2000 which is the most important year in the case. Nor has Quadrant discovered any emails from Mr Hadley or Mr Penklis for the first half of 2001 which is also an important time period in the proceedings. Moreover, Quadrant was able in February 2004 to generate electronic diaries for Mr Hadley and Mr Penklis from its computer systems.

16 Those diaries contain references to a number of important meetings but there are some significant gaps. Both diaries contain references to the meeting of 16 August 2000 between Mr Hadley, Mr Blom and Mr Seward. There is no reference to a meeting apparently planned on 17 or 18 September 2000 between Quadrant and Ms Addison nor is there any reference to the meeting which took place in Dallas on 25 September 2000.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>