<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 001 660715) v Global Gaming Supplies Pty Ltd (ACN 008 548 589) [2006] FCA 1707 (30 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1707.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Anton Piller KG v Manufacturing Process Ltd [1975] EWCA Civ 12 ; [1976] Ch 55</tocase>
<text>28 Moreover, it seems to me that the approach proposed by the respondents is not consistent with the usual practice which applies to search orders. The terms of O 25B of the Federal Court Rules are to be considered in light of the practice which evolved in the years following the decision in Anton Piller KG v Manufacturing Process Ltd [1975] EWCA Civ 12 ; [1976] Ch 55.

29 Prior to the advent of the computer era, the practice was for a physical search to be conducted at the premises. Questions of relevance were not an issue, although provision was always made for the protection of material claimed to be privileged or confidential. The computer imaging which now takes place seems to me to be the equivalent of what Mr Cobden SC for the applicants called the "flick through", which took place in the searched premises in the days when only hard copy documents and other physical materials were the subject of searches.

30 I accept that the effect of the modern regime of computer imaging as applied in the present case is to grant an applicant a far more leisurely period in which to examine the seized materials than was previously available. This will be a particular concern where the seized materials are obtained from a trade competitor as has happened in the present case. This emphasises the draconian and exceptional nature of the remedy.

31 However, in order to obtain a search order an applicant must satisfy the stringent conditions laid down in O 25B r 3. As I have already noted, Allsop J was satisfied that the necessary conditions were met. His Honour was also satisfied that the search should not be limited to the precise cause of action known to the applicants when the search order was obtained.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Home Office v Harman [1983] 1 AC 280</tocase>
<text>19 Order 14 provides for the respondents to file and serve affidavits setting out the nature and basis of any claim for privilege or confidentiality. Order 16 provides in effect for a complete release of the obligations arising from the principle in Home Office v Harman [1983] 1 AC 280.

20 On 16 October 2006 the computer experts prepared a report in accordance with Order 10. They stated that, in accordance with Order 7, they performed an independent analysis of the forensic images and extracted certain files from the images based upon the search regime. They stated that the results have been saved to a series of spreadsheets accompanying the report.

21 The computer experts' report was not provided to the solicitors for the respondents until 17 October 2006, and the relevant files ("Extracted Files") referred to therein were only made available for inspection on 8 November 2006. The solicitors inspected the Extracted Files and determined that there are approximately 284,000 electronic files in some 15,600 folders, and approximately 68,000 emails. Plainly the work involved in the search of that material to determine the existence of privileged or confidential material is significant.

34 With one exception, I am not satisfied that there are sufficient changed circumstances to warrant any amendments to the orders made on 7 September 2006. The exception is that the Home Office v Harman exemption, which is contained in Order 16, ought in my view to be deleted. In many instances such an exemption may be appropriate, but in the circumstances of the present case where the known infringement consisted of the sale of a limited number of gaming machines in Peru in 2000-2002 I do not think that the terms of Order 16 should be maintained. It seems to me to be contrary to the interests of justice in the case for them to remain as part of the court orders. It follows that I will make orders in terms of those that have been provided to me by senior counsel for the applicants.
 
 I certify that the preceding thirty-four (34) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson J. 

 Associate:

Dated: 30 November 2006

 Counsel for the Applicants: R Cobden SC with N Murray 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Baker &amp; McKenzie 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: J Ireland QC with M Green 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Paul Bard Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 27 November 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 November 2006 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1707.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>