<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rossetto v Meriton Apartments Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1290 (28 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1290.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/1.html</AustLII>
<text>It is well established that the power to strike out a pleading and to enter summary judgment must be exercised with great caution and only in very clear cases where the Court is satisfied that the cause of action cannot possibly succeed ( Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 at 91; General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 129).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Gates v The City Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [1986] HCA 3 ; (1986) 160 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/3.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Rossetto submits that the principles in Shepperd v The Council of the Municipality of Ryde [1952] HCA 9 ; (1952) 85 CLR 1 apply. He relies upon a clear common intention of the parties that, first, Mr Rossetto would rely upon the representations and, on that basis, proceed to contract to buy the premises. Secondly, the representations were ' presupposed as something antecedent upon which the purchaser might implicitly rely ' ( Shepperd at 13). Mr Rossetto submits that, as enunciated in Gates v The City Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [1986] HCA 3 ; (1986) 160 CLR 1, a collateral contract arises where the intention of the parties is clear and the terms of the collateral contract are not inconsistent with the main written agreement (at 5).

A collateral agreement inconsistent with the principal contract will not be enforced ( Maybury v Atlantic Union Oil Co Ltd [1953] HCA 89 ; (1953) 89 CLR 507 at 517; Gates at 5 per Gibbs CJ and at 11 per Mason, Wilson and Dawson JJ). The collateral contract as pleaded is inconsistent with at least clauses 56.2 (especially 56.2.2), 56.3 and 56.4.

Mr Rossetto is not entitled to damages for the loss of an expectation of rental or profits unless reliance on the representations deprived him of the opportunity to enter into a different contract resulting in greater rental or profits ( Havyn Pty Ltd v Webster (2005) 12 BPR 22,837 at [117(g)]; Gates at 13 to 15; Marks at [48]). There is no pleading or evidence that, had Mr Rossetto not relied on the representations, he would have entered into a different contract and thereby made a profit. However, Mr Rossetto asserts in his written submissions that the evidence will be adduced to establish an opportunity foregone by reason of reliance on the representation, for which he is entitled to damages. 
 Value of the premises</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>It is well established that the power to strike out a pleading and to enter summary judgment must be exercised with great caution and only in very clear cases where the Court is satisfied that the cause of action cannot possibly succeed ( Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 at 91; General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 129).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Havyn Pty Ltd v Webster (2005) 12 BPR 22,837</tocase>
<text>Mr Rossetto is not entitled to damages for the loss of an expectation of rental or profits unless reliance on the representations deprived him of the opportunity to enter into a different contract resulting in greater rental or profits ( Havyn Pty Ltd v Webster (2005) 12 BPR 22,837 at [117(g)]; Gates at 13 to 15; Marks at [48]). There is no pleading or evidence that, had Mr Rossetto not relied on the representations, he would have entered into a different contract and thereby made a profit. However, Mr Rossetto asserts in his written submissions that the evidence will be adduced to establish an opportunity foregone by reason of reliance on the representation, for which he is entitled to damages. 
 Value of the premises</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Henville v Walker [2001] HCA 52 ; (2001) 206 CLR 459</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/52.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 52 is directed at the making of the representation, not the failure to honour it. Where there is no obligation to honour the false representation, the measure of the loss is not determined by reference to what Mr Rossetto would have received if Meriton's representations had been true ( Henville v Walker [2001] HCA 52 ; (2001) 206 CLR 459 at [132] per McHugh J with whom Gummow J agreed). The representations were not warranties entitling Mr Rossetto to estimated rental or profits for the years in which the premises contained the only child care centre in the World Tower ( Warwick Entertainment at [148]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>I &amp; L Securities Pty Ltd v HTW Valuers (Brisbane) Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 41 ; (2002) 210 CLR 109</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/41.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 52 of the Act proscribes a corporation from engaging in trade or commerce in conduct that is misleading or deceptive or is likely to mislead or deceive. Mr Rossetto and Bimbee claim that they have suffered, or are likely to suffer, loss or damage ' by conduct of ' Meriton in contravention of s 52 and may recover that loss or damage pursuant to s 82 or s 87 of the Act. The words ' by conduct of ' in ss 82 and 87 impose a causal requirement that the loss or damage claimed must be sustained "by" the contravention of s 52 ( Marks v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [1998] HCA 69 ; (1998) 196 CLR 494 at [95] ; I &amp; L Securities Pty Ltd v HTW Valuers (Brisbane) Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 41 ; (2002) 210 CLR 109 at [50] and [54]).

Bimbee alleges that it relied on the representations. On the basis of this chronology and the pleadings, and in the absence of particularisation or explanation, Bimbee cannot establish that it entered the lease in reliance on the representations. To the contrary, Bimbee entered the lease with full knowledge there would be a second child care centre in the World Tower. The representations are not a cause of the loss or damage it is alleged to have suffered or is likely to suffer ( I &amp; L Securities at [57]). Bimbee does not have a reasonable cause of action against Meriton for past or future damages suffered by reason of a contravention of s 52 of the Act.

Mr Rossetto alleges that the representations were made to induce him to enter into the contract. He alleges that the representations were a promise made in consideration of him entering into the main contract, which he did. He pleads a collateral contract, formed on or before exchange. The allegation in the further amended statement of claim at [29] is: 
 
 'On or before 11 March 2002 [Mr Rossetto] and [Meriton] entered into an agreement (the collateral contract) pursuant to which in consideration of [Mr Rossetto] entering [the contract] , [Meriton] agreed to sell to [Mr Rossetto] the only child care centre in the World Tower.'

Mr Rossetto submits that, at the time the representations were made, Meriton intended to sell Mr Rossetto the only child care centre in the World Tower and Mr Rossetto was prepared to purchase the premises on the basis that it was the only child care centre. He says that the representations were warranties of the collateral contract, which were breached when the premises on level 11 of the World Tower were sold to a third party and approved as a child care centre. By reason of the breach of the collateral contract, Mr Rossetto alleges that he suffered damages, particularised as for the alleged contravention of s 52 of the Act and discussed at [24] to [36] below.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Janssen-Cilag Pty Ltd v Pfizer Pty Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 526</tocase>
<text>It is not pleaded that the representations were made to Bimbee. Bimbee relies on the fact that Meriton's conduct caused Mr Rossetto to act in a way that led to loss or damage to Bimbee. If so, the contravening conduct must still be a cause of the loss which must directly result from the conduct ( Janssen-Cilag Pty Ltd v Pfizer Pty Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 526 at 529 31 per Lockhart J). Bimbee was incorporated in March 2004. By that time, Mr Rossetto had been informed that the representations were untrue and had been offered rescission of the contract. Mr Rossetto was the sole director of Bimbee. Despite knowledge that there was to be another child care centre in the World Tower, Bimbee elected to take a lease of the premises. Bimbee was not misled at the time it took an interest in the premises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Marks v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [1998] HCA 69 ; (1998) 196 CLR 494</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/69.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 52 of the Act proscribes a corporation from engaging in trade or commerce in conduct that is misleading or deceptive or is likely to mislead or deceive. Mr Rossetto and Bimbee claim that they have suffered, or are likely to suffer, loss or damage ' by conduct of ' Meriton in contravention of s 52 and may recover that loss or damage pursuant to s 82 or s 87 of the Act. The words ' by conduct of ' in ss 82 and 87 impose a causal requirement that the loss or damage claimed must be sustained "by" the contravention of s 52 ( Marks v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [1998] HCA 69 ; (1998) 196 CLR 494 at [95] ; I &amp; L Securities Pty Ltd v HTW Valuers (Brisbane) Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 41 ; (2002) 210 CLR 109 at [50] and [54]).

Mr Rossetto is not entitled to damages for the loss of an expectation of rental or profits unless reliance on the representations deprived him of the opportunity to enter into a different contract resulting in greater rental or profits ( Havyn Pty Ltd v Webster (2005) 12 BPR 22,837 at [117(g)]; Gates at 13 to 15; Marks at [48]). There is no pleading or evidence that, had Mr Rossetto not relied on the representations, he would have entered into a different contract and thereby made a profit. However, Mr Rossetto asserts in his written submissions that the evidence will be adduced to establish an opportunity foregone by reason of reliance on the representation, for which he is entitled to damages. 
 Value of the premises

Mr Rossetto has suffered no loss with respect to the value of the premises because what he bought was worth what he paid for it ( Marks at 514-5 per McHugh, Hayne and Callinan JJ). There was no loss as a result of altering his position under the inducement of the misleading conduct ( Marks at 513-4).

The damages alleged to have been suffered by Bimbee are particularised as: 
 
 'The loss of income being the reduction in the net income caused by [Bimbee] not operating the only child care centre in the World Tower building as represented to [Mr Rossetto] '.

Bimbee's claim has been further particularised to include loss of income and goodwill. The former has been particularised as: 
 
 &#8226; past loss of income, calculated as profit expected less actual profit received; and
 &#8226; future loss of income, as expected income assuming no competitor and a daily charge of $120 per child.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maybury v Atlantic Union Oil Co Ltd [1953] HCA 89 ; (1953) 89 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1953/89.html</AustLII>
<text>A collateral agreement inconsistent with the principal contract will not be enforced ( Maybury v Atlantic Union Oil Co Ltd [1953] HCA 89 ; (1953) 89 CLR 507 at 517; Gates at 5 per Gibbs CJ and at 11 per Mason, Wilson and Dawson JJ). The collateral contract as pleaded is inconsistent with at least clauses 56.2 (especially 56.2.2), 56.3 and 56.4.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/3.html</AustLII>
<text>Loss or damage suffered by reason of a contravention of s 52 is not confined by reference to a form of claim under the general law and is not necessarily singular; it may be, for example, both loss of revenue and loss of capital and may be incurred at different times ( Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 at [44] , [49] [52]). However, the risk of loss is not itself a category of loss ( Murphy at [46] discussing Wardley Australia Ltd v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 at 526-7).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Shepperd v The Council of the Municipality of Ryde [1952] HCA 9 ; (1952) 85 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1952/9.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Rossetto submits that the principles in Shepperd v The Council of the Municipality of Ryde [1952] HCA 9 ; (1952) 85 CLR 1 apply. He relies upon a clear common intention of the parties that, first, Mr Rossetto would rely upon the representations and, on that basis, proceed to contract to buy the premises. Secondly, the representations were ' presupposed as something antecedent upon which the purchaser might implicitly rely ' ( Shepperd at 13). Mr Rossetto submits that, as enunciated in Gates v The City Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [1986] HCA 3 ; (1986) 160 CLR 1, a collateral contract arises where the intention of the parties is clear and the terms of the collateral contract are not inconsistent with the main written agreement (at 5).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wardley Australia Ltd v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/55.html</AustLII>
<text>Loss or damage suffered by reason of a contravention of s 52 is not confined by reference to a form of claim under the general law and is not necessarily singular; it may be, for example, both loss of revenue and loss of capital and may be incurred at different times ( Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 at [44] , [49] [52]). However, the risk of loss is not itself a category of loss ( Murphy at [46] discussing Wardley Australia Ltd v Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 at 526-7).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Warwick Entertainment Centre Pty Ltd v Alpine Holdings Pty Ltd (2005) 224 ALR 134</tocase>
<text>Accepting for the purposes of this application that Mr Rossetto entered into the contract in reliance on the misrepresentations and affirmed the contract after being told the true position, Mr Rossetto is not automatically precluded from a claim for damages pursuant to ss 82 and 87. The success of his claim may depend upon whether his decision to affirm the contract was reasonable ( Warwick Entertainment Centre Pty Ltd v Alpine Holdings Pty Ltd (2005) 224 ALR 134 at [72]). The affirmation of the contract alone does not result in an absence of a reasonable cause of action for damages pursuant to ss 82 and 87. There may be loss or damage after entry into the contract and prior to the decision to affirm the contract or prior to the completion of the contract. The decision may have been reasonable in light of evidence Mr Rossetto proposes to adduce concerning the time, energy and money he had already invested in the premises although no such evidence has been forthcoming to date. These are factual matters that will need to be determined.

Section 52 is directed at the making of the representation, not the failure to honour it. Where there is no obligation to honour the false representation, the measure of the loss is not determined by reference to what Mr Rossetto would have received if Meriton's representations had been true ( Henville v Walker [2001] HCA 52 ; (2001) 206 CLR 459 at [132] per McHugh J with whom Gummow J agreed). The representations were not warranties entitling Mr Rossetto to estimated rental or profits for the years in which the premises contained the only child care centre in the World Tower ( Warwick Entertainment at [148]).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>