<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wyong-Gosford Progressive Community Radio Incorporatedv Australian Communications Media Authority and Gosford Christian Broadcasters Limited [2006] FCA 1691 (20 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1691.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ansell v Wells and Others (1982) 63 FLR 127</tocase>
<text>38 In R v O'Sullivan; Ex parte Clarke [1967] WAR 168, the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia found that a delay in filing an application for a writ of certiorari, issued more than three months after the Court's decision, was regarded as substantial and ' an important factor in the exercise of the court's decision to refuse relief... ' In Ansell v Wells and Others (1982) 63 FLR 127 Lockhart J at page 156 said '[d]elay, coupled with prejudice to the defendant or a third party, may debar a plaintiff from discretionary relief. ' In Re David Smith and The West Australian Development Corporation; Ex parte Rundle and Others (1992) 5 WAR 295 Malcolm CJ, delivering the judgment of the Full Court observed in relation to the time limit prescribed by the Rules of the Supreme Court of Western Australia:
 
 'The time limit in O 65, r 11(1) of six months has its justification in the need to act promptly in relation to proceedings to quash the decision of an inferior court or tribunal. Great inconvenience could be caused by permitting the decision to stand and allowing people to act on the assumption that the decision was valid. The six months time limit was introduced in England in 1740 by the statute 13 GeoII, c 18 s 5 which provided that no certiorari should issue for the removal of orders made by justices of the peace after six months. The court had no discretion to extend time: see R v Anglesea Justices (1846) 10 Jur 817. The 1740 statute was repealed by the Statute Law Revision Act 1888 . The court has an express power to extend the time under the rule. In my opinion it is, at the least, extremely doubtful whether the rule applies to decisions of bodies or persons other than inferior courts or statutory tribunals. If it does not, the rule would not apply to a decision such as that made by the minister in the present case. Even if the rule does not apply, however, the nature of the remedy of certiorari is such that the court would require it to be sought promptly.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/33.html</AustLII>
<text>65 PCR claims that such finding was critical in the chain of reasoning which led to ABA's decision, and relies upon the decision of the Full Court in Curragh Queensland Mining Limited v Daniel and Others (1992) 34 FCR 212 (especially at 220-221). It submits that there was no evidence upon which ABA could have reached its decision and it is therefore invalid according to the principles referred to in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 and in Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Others [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24.

71 The approach to be adopted in cases of judicial review was also explained by the High Court of Australia in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others where the Court said at [341]:
 
 'The expression "judicial review", when applied to the traditional review functions of the superior courts in our system of justice, exercisable by means of the prerogative writs and the grant of declaratory relief and injunction, ordinarily does not extend to findings of fact as such. To expose all findings of fact, or the generality of them, to judicial review would expose the steps in administrative decision-making to comprehensive review by the courts and thus bring about a radical change in the relationship between the executive and judicial branches of government. Amongst other things, such a change would bring in its train difficult questions concerning the extent to which the courts should take account of policy considerations when reviewing the making of findings of fact and the drawing of inferences of fact.'

93 Mason CJ in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others referred to grounds of review in circumstances where there is no evidence to support a finding. He referred to the ' no sufficient evidence ' test in the context of judicial review of findings of fact and stated at page 356:
 
 'Thus, at common law, according to the Australian authorities, want of logic is not synonymous with error of law. So long as there is some basis for an inference in other words, the particular inference is reasonably open even if that inference appears to have been drawn as a result of their illogical reasoning, there is no place for judicial review because no error of law has taken place.'

94 Although some letters were written prior to the incorporation of GCB, and others were from persons who were legally still 'members' of NCB, I do not think that this fact leads to the conclusion that there was no evidence upon which the ABA could rely in relation to the letters. There was no legal requirement that only members of GCB could support GCB's application. The letters were provided by persons who wished to support the service, and whether they were actually 'members' of GCB was not a critical matter for determination.

95 I consider that the ABA was correct in considering that the letters that it had received indicated widespread support for GCB's proposed service. Accordingly, the ABA did not err as alleged by PCR.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brisbane South Regional Health Authority v Taylor [1996] HCA 25 ; (1996) 186 CLR 541</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/25.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The High Court in Brisbane South Regional Health Authority v Taylor [1996] HCA 25 ; (1996) 186 CLR 541 considered the Limitation of Actions Act 1974 (Qld) and held that where an applicant sought an extension of time in which to bring proceedings it was necessary to show that prejudice would not result to the other party. McHugh J referred to the need to limit the time in which actions should be brought (see 552-553). McHugh J observed at 555 that a plaintiff's claim is:
 
 '... seldom likely to be strong enough to warrant a Court reinstating a right of action against the defendant who, by reason of delay in commencing the action, is unable to fairly defend itself or is otherwise prejudiced in fact and who is not guilty of fraud, deception or concealment in respect of the existence of that action.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>72 If the Court is satisfied that the ABA has misdirected itself in law or has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider, or taken irrelevant matters into consideration, its decision will have miscarried: see Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 (at 118-119 per Gibbs J). However, the failure of a decision maker to take into account an insignificant matter may not warrant a Court setting aside the decision: see Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Anor v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Ors at 40. If the Court should conclude that there is inadequate factual material to support a finding by the ABA, it could lead to the inference that the Tribunal has applied a wrong test or has not otherwise satisfied the requisite matters which it was obliged to consider under s 84(2) of the Act: see The Queen v Australian Stevedoring Industry Board and Another: Ex parte Melbourne Stevedoring Company Proprietary Limited [1953] HCA 22 ; (1953) 88 CLR 100 at 120. In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajamanikkam and Another [2002] HCA 32 ; [2002] 210 CLR 222, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said at page 241:
 
 'Whether a decision would or would not have been made without a particular factual finding depends on indications to that effect in the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process. And unless it is possible to say on a proper analysis of the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process that, had a particular finding not been made, the decision in question would not have been reached, it is, in our view, impossible to say that the decision was based on that finding.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280</tocase>
<text>70 Upon reading the whole of the challenged decision, a Court must be satisfied that the Tribunal applied its mind to the correct issues, and decided those issues by findings based on evidence or material which was reasonable. In Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 the Court said at 287:
 
 'The Court will not be concerned with looseness in the language of the Tribunal nor with unhappy phrasing of the Tribunal's thoughts: Lennell v Repatriation Commission (1982) 4 ALN N 54 (Northrop and Sheppard JJ); Freeman v Defence Force Retirement and Death Benefits Authority (1985) 5 AAR 156 at 164 (Sheppard J); Repatriation Commission v Bushell (1991) 13 AAR 176 at 183 (Morling and Neaves JJ). The reasons for the decision under review are not to be construed minutely and finely with an eye keenly attuned to the perception of error: Politis v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) (1988) 16 ALD 707 at 708 (Lockhart J).'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Community Television Sydney Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Authority and Another [2004] FCA 443 ; (2004) 136 FCR 316</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/443.html</AustLII>
<text>33 Section 5 of the Act makes provision for the role of the ABA. In Community Television Sydney Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Authority and Another [2004] FCA 443 ; (2004) 136 FCR 316 Sackville J at [317] observed that s 5(1)(b)(i) of the Act:
 
 '... required the Authority to use its functions and powers in a manner which, in its opinion, "will produce regulatory arrangements that are stable and predictable."'

34 The ABA submits that judicial review proceedings under the ADJR Act are not ' at large ' in relation to the time in which an application must be brought. I consider that the time limits provided by the ADJR Act further the object of certainty and reliability of administrative decisions which are necessary for stable and predictable regulatory arrangements. As such, they contribute to the efficiency of the broadcasting industry.

35 The failure of PCR to communicate in any way with GCB for more than 12 months following the date of the grant of the licence or to warn it of an impending challenge has led GCB to believe that no challenge would be made after the 28 period had expired. Further, the reasons advanced by Mr Lindberg for the failure to lodge the application even within a reasonable time after 22 February 2005 (being the expiration of the 28 day period), is not satisfactorily explained. PCR approached the issue in a leisurely manner, not foreshadowing its possible challenge. There was nothing in the advice received by Mr Lindberg in February 2005 which suggested that an open ended period would be allowed and considered appropriate by the Court. Further he was aware that a time limit for the commencement of proceedings existed. The claimed lack of funds is inadequate to explain way at least a warning to GCB and the ABA of a possible challenge could not have been given.

55 PCR submits that most of the letters of support relied upon by GCB related to the service provided by NCB which the ABA found was different to that proposed by GCB, but that the ABA took all of the letters into account in its finding that GCB had 2080 letters of support for its proposed service within the licence area. Accordingly, GCB claims that the Decision was made on the erroneous premise that the ' support ' was for GCB, when it was support from members of NCB. This ground relies upon the premise that the term ' proposed service ' must refer to the particular programming proposed by a particular applicant for a licence as discussed by Sackville J in Community Television Sydney Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Authority at [50].

56 PCR claims that at common law, the ABA's misconstruction of the statute was an error of law and a jurisdictional error because it failed to take into account a relevant consideration. Additionally, PCR submits that there has been a breach of s 5(1)(d),(f),(j) of the ADJR Act.

79 I am satisfied that the particular programs proposed were those intended by GCB and that the ABA correctly directed itself to the requirements of s 84(2)(a) when it assessed the ' proposed service ' of GCB. Whilst Sackville J in Community Television Sydney Pty Ltd v ABA observed that the s 84(2) ' required the Authority to take the specified matters into account and give each of them weight as a fundamental element in making the determination. ' (see [5]), it would be wrong to construe the ABA's decision in relation to the proposed service as having been determined merely upon the letters of support. Accordingly I reject the first ground of challenge.

80 Section 3 of ABA Form 32 identifies the matters to be considered by the ABA in its assessment of the several matters under s 84 of the Act. One of those matters is membership and the extent to which the programming would be relevant to the community. Section 3 includes the following:
 
 'The reference to 'the community within the licence area' means the whole of the community within a licence area. That is, the reference is not limited to the community interest which the applicant proposes to serve. 
 This does not necessarily mean that an applicant which proposes to serve a specific community interest will be regarded as meeting the needs of the community to a lesser extent than an applicant which proposes to serve the general community. 
 The assessment of the extent to which the proposed service would meet the needs of the community will be affected by the nature and diversity of the interests of that community and the nature and diversity of the other broadcasting services available within the licence area catering to those interests.'

81 The ABA accepted that GCB had a relatively large membership base and specifically referred to the 2080 letters. The ABA was entitled to have regard to the fact that such significant support, although mainly based on the programs provided by NCB, was equally applicable to such programs in the Gosford area. The ABA was satisfied that ' a full-time Christian broadcasting service of the kind proposed by GCB will add to the diversity of services in the licence area and meet the needs of Christians in the licence area community not provided for by other broadcasters. '</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Curragh Queensland Mining Limited v Daniel and Others (1992) 34 FCR 212</tocase>
<text>65 PCR claims that such finding was critical in the chain of reasoning which led to ABA's decision, and relies upon the decision of the Full Court in Curragh Queensland Mining Limited v Daniel and Others (1992) 34 FCR 212 (especially at 220-221). It submits that there was no evidence upon which ABA could have reached its decision and it is therefore invalid according to the principles referred to in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 and in Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Others [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Doyle v Chief of General Staff (1982) 42 ALR 283</tocase>
<text>28 The merits of the substantive application are to be taken into consideration (see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349). In these proceedings, the Court considers that PCR's claims are arguable. However, PCR's application must be considered with reference to all parties who might be affected and the question of prejudice being occasioned to GCB is a matter for the Court's consideration: see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349; Doyle v Chief of General Staff (1982) 42 ALR 283 at 287; Lovett v Le Gall (1975) 10 SASR 479 at 485; Wedesweiller and Others v Cole and Others (1983) 47 ALR 528 at 533-534.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Elias v Commissioner of Taxation [2002] FCA 845 ; (2002) 123 FCR 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/845.html</AustLII>
<text>57 PCR submits that the approach by the ABA relating to ' needs' was erroneous. It submits that the brief analysis as to the extent to which ' needs' within the Gosford community would be met by the services proposed to be provided by GCB was meaningless and that no real consideration has been provided of the statutory requirement of s 84(2)(a) of the Act. PCR claims that the ABA mistakenly considered letters of support as being relevant to the concept of ' needs ', when in fact they did not address such issue. As such there is both common law jurisdictional error and a breach of s 5(1)(e) and 5(2)(b) of the ADJR Act. PCR relies upon the principles referred to in Elias v Commissioner of Taxation [2002] FCA 845 ; (2002) 123 FCR 499 at [62] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>F Hoffmann-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (1975) AC 295</tocase>
<text>39 In Re Refugee Review Tribunal and Another; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; [2000] 204 CLR 82 Gaudron and Gummow JJ referred to circumstances which might prevent the Court exercising its discretion in favour of granting prerogative relief and at [57] quoted Lord Denning in F Hoffmann-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (1975) AC 295 at 320 (CA) where His Lordship said of a plaintiff who delays commencing proceedings:
 
 'He may be debarred from relief if he has acquiesced in the invalidity or has waived it. If he does not come with due diligence and ask for it to be set aside, he may be sent away with nothing (145). If his conduct has been disgraceful and he has in fact suffered no injustice, he may be refused relief (146).'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gamaethige v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 565 ; (2001) 109 FCR 424</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/565.html</AustLII>
<text>69 In considering the approach to be taken by the Court to the Decision of the ABA, the Court must be satisfied that the ABA's Reasons considered the relevant factual matters required by s 84(2) of the Act, and that the ABA did not take into account irrelevant considerations. The Court must also be satisfied that the power provided to the ABA has been exercised reasonably: see Kruger and Others v Commonwealth of Australia [1997] HCA 27 ; (1997) 190 CLR 1 at 36 per Brennan CJ. The process adopted by the ABA in its application of s 84(2) must be logical. In Hill v Green [1999] NSWCA 477 ; (1999) 48 NSWLR 161, Spigelman CJ said (at 174-175):
 
 'In my opinion, where a statute or regulation makes provision for an administrative decision in terminology which does not confer an unfettered discretion on the decision-maker, the court should approach the construction of the statute or regulation with the presumption that the Parliament or the author of the regulation intended the decision-maker to reach a decision by a process of logical reasoning and a contrary interpretation would require clear and unambiguous words.' 

For similar observations, see Gamaethige v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 565 ; (2001) 109 FCR 424 at [28] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at [145] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hickey and Others v Australian Telecommunications Commission (1983) 72 FLR 291</tocase>
<text>22 The principles to be applied in relation to an application for extension of time are conveniently referred to in Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen (1984) 3 FCR 344 at 348-349 and in Hickey and Others v Australian Telecommunications Commission (1983) 72 FLR 291.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hill v Green [1999] NSWCA 477 ; (1999) 48 NSWLR 161</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/1999/477.html</AustLII>
<text>69 In considering the approach to be taken by the Court to the Decision of the ABA, the Court must be satisfied that the ABA's Reasons considered the relevant factual matters required by s 84(2) of the Act, and that the ABA did not take into account irrelevant considerations. The Court must also be satisfied that the power provided to the ABA has been exercised reasonably: see Kruger and Others v Commonwealth of Australia [1997] HCA 27 ; (1997) 190 CLR 1 at 36 per Brennan CJ. The process adopted by the ABA in its application of s 84(2) must be logical. In Hill v Green [1999] NSWCA 477 ; (1999) 48 NSWLR 161, Spigelman CJ said (at 174-175):
 
 'In my opinion, where a statute or regulation makes provision for an administrative decision in terminology which does not confer an unfettered discretion on the decision-maker, the court should approach the construction of the statute or regulation with the presumption that the Parliament or the author of the regulation intended the decision-maker to reach a decision by a process of logical reasoning and a contrary interpretation would require clear and unambiguous words.' 

For similar observations, see Gamaethige v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 565 ; (2001) 109 FCR 424 at [28] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at [145] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen (1984) 3 FCR 344</tocase>
<text>22 The principles to be applied in relation to an application for extension of time are conveniently referred to in Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen (1984) 3 FCR 344 at 348-349 and in Hickey and Others v Australian Telecommunications Commission (1983) 72 FLR 291.

28 The merits of the substantive application are to be taken into consideration (see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349). In these proceedings, the Court considers that PCR's claims are arguable. However, PCR's application must be considered with reference to all parties who might be affected and the question of prejudice being occasioned to GCB is a matter for the Court's consideration: see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349; Doyle v Chief of General Staff (1982) 42 ALR 283 at 287; Lovett v Le Gall (1975) 10 SASR 479 at 485; Wedesweiller and Others v Cole and Others (1983) 47 ALR 528 at 533-534.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kruger and Others v Commonwealth of Australia [1997] HCA 27 ; (1997) 190 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/27.html</AustLII>
<text>69 In considering the approach to be taken by the Court to the Decision of the ABA, the Court must be satisfied that the ABA's Reasons considered the relevant factual matters required by s 84(2) of the Act, and that the ABA did not take into account irrelevant considerations. The Court must also be satisfied that the power provided to the ABA has been exercised reasonably: see Kruger and Others v Commonwealth of Australia [1997] HCA 27 ; (1997) 190 CLR 1 at 36 per Brennan CJ. The process adopted by the ABA in its application of s 84(2) must be logical. In Hill v Green [1999] NSWCA 477 ; (1999) 48 NSWLR 161, Spigelman CJ said (at 174-175):
 
 'In my opinion, where a statute or regulation makes provision for an administrative decision in terminology which does not confer an unfettered discretion on the decision-maker, the court should approach the construction of the statute or regulation with the presumption that the Parliament or the author of the regulation intended the decision-maker to reach a decision by a process of logical reasoning and a contrary interpretation would require clear and unambiguous words.' 

For similar observations, see Gamaethige v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 565 ; (2001) 109 FCR 424 at [28] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at [145] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lovett v Le Gall (1975) 10 SASR 479</tocase>
<text>28 The merits of the substantive application are to be taken into consideration (see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349). In these proceedings, the Court considers that PCR's claims are arguable. However, PCR's application must be considered with reference to all parties who might be affected and the question of prejudice being occasioned to GCB is a matter for the Court's consideration: see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349; Doyle v Chief of General Staff (1982) 42 ALR 283 at 287; Lovett v Le Gall (1975) 10 SASR 479 at 485; Wedesweiller and Others v Cole and Others (1983) 47 ALR 528 at 533-534.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lucic v Nolan and Others (1982) 45 ALR 411</tocase>
<text>23 PCR asks the Court to exercise its discretion to grant an extension of time. In exercising its discretion, the Court must consider interests beyond those of an applicant. Whilst s 11 of the ADJR Act does not specifically impose a burden of proof upon an applicant for the extension of time, an applicant is required to show why ' in all the circumstances, the extension of time should be granted ': see Lucic v Nolan and Others (1982) 45 ALR 411 at 416. Further, the ' prescribed period ' of 28 days is not to be ignored: see Ralkon Agricultural Co Pty Ltd v Aboriginal Development Commission (1982) 43 ALR 535 at 550.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Others [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>65 PCR claims that such finding was critical in the chain of reasoning which led to ABA's decision, and relies upon the decision of the Full Court in Curragh Queensland Mining Limited v Daniel and Others (1992) 34 FCR 212 (especially at 220-221). It submits that there was no evidence upon which ABA could have reached its decision and it is therefore invalid according to the principles referred to in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond and Others [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 and in Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Others [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/21.html</AustLII>
<text>69 In considering the approach to be taken by the Court to the Decision of the ABA, the Court must be satisfied that the ABA's Reasons considered the relevant factual matters required by s 84(2) of the Act, and that the ABA did not take into account irrelevant considerations. The Court must also be satisfied that the power provided to the ABA has been exercised reasonably: see Kruger and Others v Commonwealth of Australia [1997] HCA 27 ; (1997) 190 CLR 1 at 36 per Brennan CJ. The process adopted by the ABA in its application of s 84(2) must be logical. In Hill v Green [1999] NSWCA 477 ; (1999) 48 NSWLR 161, Spigelman CJ said (at 174-175):
 
 'In my opinion, where a statute or regulation makes provision for an administrative decision in terminology which does not confer an unfettered discretion on the decision-maker, the court should approach the construction of the statute or regulation with the presumption that the Parliament or the author of the regulation intended the decision-maker to reach a decision by a process of logical reasoning and a contrary interpretation would require clear and unambiguous words.' 

For similar observations, see Gamaethige v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 565 ; (2001) 109 FCR 424 at [28] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at [145] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajamanikkam and Another [2002] HCA 32 ; (2002) 210 CLR 222</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/32.html</AustLII>
<text>72 If the Court is satisfied that the ABA has misdirected itself in law or has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider, or taken irrelevant matters into consideration, its decision will have miscarried: see Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 (at 118-119 per Gibbs J). However, the failure of a decision maker to take into account an insignificant matter may not warrant a Court setting aside the decision: see Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Anor v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Ors at 40. If the Court should conclude that there is inadequate factual material to support a finding by the ABA, it could lead to the inference that the Tribunal has applied a wrong test or has not otherwise satisfied the requisite matters which it was obliged to consider under s 84(2) of the Act: see The Queen v Australian Stevedoring Industry Board and Another: Ex parte Melbourne Stevedoring Company Proprietary Limited [1953] HCA 22 ; (1953) 88 CLR 100 at 120. In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajamanikkam and Another [2002] HCA 32 ; [2002] 210 CLR 222, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said at page 241:
 
 'Whether a decision would or would not have been made without a particular factual finding depends on indications to that effect in the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process. And unless it is possible to say on a proper analysis of the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process that, had a particular finding not been made, the decision in question would not have been reached, it is, in our view, impossible to say that the decision was based on that finding.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>73 Identifying a wrong issue or asking a wrong question may be indicative of jurisdictional error: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 351.

74 The above principles form the basis of the approach to be taken when considering challenges made under the ADJR Act and at common law.

75 The Reasons show that the ABA considered the type of service that would be provided by GCB. It found that some of the programs to be broadcast would be the same as those broadcast by NCB being programs directed at furthering Christian beliefs. As was explained in oral evidence by John Ian Marks, general manager of NCB, the term Rhema which is used in the trading names of both NCB and GCB, is derived from the Greek word meaning the s poken word and is used to connote the furtherance of the Christian religion. The ABA referred to the information provided by GCB that community needs would be met through a range of 'spoken word programming', such as broadcasts by a Christian psychologist on relevant issues, including raising children, building better marriages and ' hope for the seriously ill '. Accordingly, it was apparent that the type of programs broadcast by NCB trading as Rhema FM Newcastle would not be dissimilar to those proposed for GCB trading as Rhema Gosford. However, the ABA found that local content would be incorporated in GCB's programs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>R v O'Sullivan; Ex parte Clarke [1967] WAR 168</tocase>
<text>38 In R v O'Sullivan; Ex parte Clarke [1967] WAR 168, the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia found that a delay in filing an application for a writ of certiorari, issued more than three months after the Court's decision, was regarded as substantial and ' an important factor in the exercise of the court's decision to refuse relief... ' In Ansell v Wells and Others (1982) 63 FLR 127 Lockhart J at page 156 said '[d]elay, coupled with prejudice to the defendant or a third party, may debar a plaintiff from discretionary relief. ' In Re David Smith and The West Australian Development Corporation; Ex parte Rundle and Others (1992) 5 WAR 295 Malcolm CJ, delivering the judgment of the Full Court observed in relation to the time limit prescribed by the Rules of the Supreme Court of Western Australia:
 
 'The time limit in O 65, r 11(1) of six months has its justification in the need to act promptly in relation to proceedings to quash the decision of an inferior court or tribunal. Great inconvenience could be caused by permitting the decision to stand and allowing people to act on the assumption that the decision was valid. The six months time limit was introduced in England in 1740 by the statute 13 GeoII, c 18 s 5 which provided that no certiorari should issue for the removal of orders made by justices of the peace after six months. The court had no discretion to extend time: see R v Anglesea Justices (1846) 10 Jur 817. The 1740 statute was repealed by the Statute Law Revision Act 1888 . The court has an express power to extend the time under the rule. In my opinion it is, at the least, extremely doubtful whether the rule applies to decisions of bodies or persons other than inferior courts or statutory tribunals. If it does not, the rule would not apply to a decision such as that made by the minister in the present case. Even if the rule does not apply, however, the nature of the remedy of certiorari is such that the court would require it to be sought promptly.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ralkon Agricultural Co Pty Ltd v Aboriginal Development Commission (1982) 43 ALR 535</tocase>
<text>23 PCR asks the Court to exercise its discretion to grant an extension of time. In exercising its discretion, the Court must consider interests beyond those of an applicant. Whilst s 11 of the ADJR Act does not specifically impose a burden of proof upon an applicant for the extension of time, an applicant is required to show why ' in all the circumstances, the extension of time should be granted ': see Lucic v Nolan and Others (1982) 45 ALR 411 at 416. Further, the ' prescribed period ' of 28 days is not to be ignored: see Ralkon Agricultural Co Pty Ltd v Aboriginal Development Commission (1982) 43 ALR 535 at 550.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re David Smith and The West Australian Development Corporation; Ex parte Rundle and Others (1992) 5 WAR 295</tocase>
<text>38 In R v O'Sullivan; Ex parte Clarke [1967] WAR 168, the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Western Australia found that a delay in filing an application for a writ of certiorari, issued more than three months after the Court's decision, was regarded as substantial and ' an important factor in the exercise of the court's decision to refuse relief... ' In Ansell v Wells and Others (1982) 63 FLR 127 Lockhart J at page 156 said '[d]elay, coupled with prejudice to the defendant or a third party, may debar a plaintiff from discretionary relief. ' In Re David Smith and The West Australian Development Corporation; Ex parte Rundle and Others (1992) 5 WAR 295 Malcolm CJ, delivering the judgment of the Full Court observed in relation to the time limit prescribed by the Rules of the Supreme Court of Western Australia:
 
 'The time limit in O 65, r 11(1) of six months has its justification in the need to act promptly in relation to proceedings to quash the decision of an inferior court or tribunal. Great inconvenience could be caused by permitting the decision to stand and allowing people to act on the assumption that the decision was valid. The six months time limit was introduced in England in 1740 by the statute 13 GeoII, c 18 s 5 which provided that no certiorari should issue for the removal of orders made by justices of the peace after six months. The court had no discretion to extend time: see R v Anglesea Justices (1846) 10 Jur 817. The 1740 statute was repealed by the Statute Law Revision Act 1888 . The court has an express power to extend the time under the rule. In my opinion it is, at the least, extremely doubtful whether the rule applies to decisions of bodies or persons other than inferior courts or statutory tribunals. If it does not, the rule would not apply to a decision such as that made by the minister in the present case. Even if the rule does not apply, however, the nature of the remedy of certiorari is such that the court would require it to be sought promptly.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Refugee Review Tribunal and Another; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; [2000] 204 CLR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/57.html</AustLII>
<text>39 In Re Refugee Review Tribunal and Another; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; [2000] 204 CLR 82 Gaudron and Gummow JJ referred to circumstances which might prevent the Court exercising its discretion in favour of granting prerogative relief and at [57] quoted Lord Denning in F Hoffmann-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry (1975) AC 295 at 320 (CA) where His Lordship said of a plaintiff who delays commencing proceedings:
 
 'He may be debarred from relief if he has acquiesced in the invalidity or has waived it. If he does not come with due diligence and ask for it to be set aside, he may be sent away with nothing (145). If his conduct has been disgraceful and he has in fact suffered no injustice, he may be refused relief (146).'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Silkman v Kendall [1982] 1 NSWLR 133</tocase>
<text>58 PCR submits that community needs means ' the reasonable demands or expectations of the public '; see Silkman v Kendall [1982] 1 NSWLR 133 at 140; Toohey v Taylor [1983] 1 NSWLR 743 at 748-749. By analogy, it is submitted that such principle applies to the question of needs as contained in s 84(2)(a) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Telstra Corp Ltd v Hornsby Shire Council (2006) 146 LGERA 10</tocase>
<text>63 PCR submits that the assertion of the 2080 letters in support by GCB was in reality no more than speculation, and that what was required was evidence which logically showed the existence of the facts relevant to the issue to be determined: see Telstra Corp Ltd v Hornsby Shire Council (2006) 146 LGERA 10.

64 PCR submits that ABA's findings were based upon the number of members of GCB and that at the relevant time GCB did not have 1078 members as claimed. In fact, approximately 1000 of those members belonged to NCB. Accordingly, PCR claims that there was no probative value in the finding by the ABA relating to the number of members of GCB.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Queen v Australian Stevedoring Industry Board and Another: Ex parte Melbourne Stevedoring Company Proprietary Limited [1953] HCA 22 ; (1953) 88 CLR 100</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1953/22.html</AustLII>
<text>72 If the Court is satisfied that the ABA has misdirected itself in law or has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider, or taken irrelevant matters into consideration, its decision will have miscarried: see Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 (at 118-119 per Gibbs J). However, the failure of a decision maker to take into account an insignificant matter may not warrant a Court setting aside the decision: see Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Anor v Peko-Wallsend Limited and Ors at 40. If the Court should conclude that there is inadequate factual material to support a finding by the ABA, it could lead to the inference that the Tribunal has applied a wrong test or has not otherwise satisfied the requisite matters which it was obliged to consider under s 84(2) of the Act: see The Queen v Australian Stevedoring Industry Board and Another: Ex parte Melbourne Stevedoring Company Proprietary Limited [1953] HCA 22 ; (1953) 88 CLR 100 at 120. In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajamanikkam and Another [2002] HCA 32 ; [2002] 210 CLR 222, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said at page 241:
 
 'Whether a decision would or would not have been made without a particular factual finding depends on indications to that effect in the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process. And unless it is possible to say on a proper analysis of the decision, the reasons for decision or the decision making process that, had a particular finding not been made, the decision in question would not have been reached, it is, in our view, impossible to say that the decision was based on that finding.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Queen v The Australian Broadcasting Tribunal and Others; Ex parte Hardiman and Others [1980] HCA 13 ; (1980) 144 CLR 13</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/13.html</AustLII>
<text>31 The interests of the ABA are to be considered also. Consistent with the principles referred to in The Queen v The Australian Broadcasting Tribunal and Others; Ex parte Hardiman and Others [1980] HCA 13 ; (1980) 144 CLR 13, the ABA has adopted a neutral position in these proceedings. Nevertheless, in relation to the application for the extension of time it has raised matters relating to the public interest which the Court will consider.

32 The ABA refers to the statutory objects of the Act as contained in s 3 thereof. In summary, those objects included the provision of a regulatory environment 
 
 'that will facilitate the development of a broadcasting industry in Australia that is efficient, competitive and responsive to audience needs...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Toohey v Taylor [1983] 1 NSWLR 743</tocase>
<text>58 PCR submits that community needs means ' the reasonable demands or expectations of the public '; see Silkman v Kendall [1982] 1 NSWLR 133 at 140; Toohey v Taylor [1983] 1 NSWLR 743 at 748-749. By analogy, it is submitted that such principle applies to the question of needs as contained in s 84(2)(a) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wedesweiller and Others v Cole and Others (1983) 47 ALR 528</tocase>
<text>28 The merits of the substantive application are to be taken into consideration (see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349). In these proceedings, the Court considers that PCR's claims are arguable. However, PCR's application must be considered with reference to all parties who might be affected and the question of prejudice being occasioned to GCB is a matter for the Court's consideration: see Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd at 349; Doyle v Chief of General Staff (1982) 42 ALR 283 at 287; Lovett v Le Gall (1975) 10 SASR 479 at 485; Wedesweiller and Others v Cole and Others (1983) 47 ALR 528 at 533-534.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wyong-Gosford Progressive Community Radio Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority and Another [2003] FCA 33 ; [2003] 125 FCR 560</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/33.html</AustLII>
<text>7 On 23 December 2002 the licence was awarded by the ABA to GCB. PCR promptly challenged the decision of the ABA to grant the licence to GCB and brought proceedings under the ADJR Act in this Court. On 31 January 2003 Wilcox J determined that the award of the licence to GCB resulted from denial of natural justice and set aside the decision of the ABA: see Wyong-Gosford Progressive Community Radio Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority and Another [2003] FCA 33 ; [2003] 125 FCR 560.

8 On 19 March 2004 the ABA called for applications for the licence in respect of the licence area by advertisement published in the Central Coast Express, and by 16 April 2004 the ABA had received applications from three applicants, namely PCR, GCB and Radio Yesteryear.

9 On 6 May 2004 copies of each application was made available for public inspection on the ABA website and in hard copy at Gosford City Public Library. On 19 April 2004 the ABA wrote to each of the licence applicants advising them of the other applications and informing them that the general public was entitled to make submissions on the applications until 14 May 2004. The ABA duly received submissions and placed the submissions on its website for public inspection.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>