<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZBDW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1338 (13 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1338.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/33.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Magistrates Court exercised jurisdiction to judicially review the decision of the Tribunal. The appeal to this Court is to correct error in the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court. The ground of appeal sought to be relied upon does not relate to any such error. Furthermore, the ground involves a question of fact not raised before the Federal Magistrates Court. The application to amend is misconceived ( Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1). The application to amend is refused.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/264.html</AustLII>
<text>The consequence is that the case for the appellants stands or falls upon the use by the Tribunal of country information concerning document fraud in Bangladesh without having complied with s 424A in relation to that information. That basis was rejected by the learned Federal Magistrate, based upon Full Court authority in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572. Counsel for the Minister submits that authority since then has confirmed that position. It is sufficient to refer to QAAC of 2004 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2005] FCAFC 92 and VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>QAAC of 2004 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2005] FCAFC 92 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/92.html</AustLII>
<text>The consequence is that the case for the appellants stands or falls upon the use by the Tribunal of country information concerning document fraud in Bangladesh without having complied with s 424A in relation to that information. That basis was rejected by the learned Federal Magistrate, based upon Full Court authority in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572. Counsel for the Minister submits that authority since then has confirmed that position. It is sufficient to refer to QAAC of 2004 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2005] FCAFC 92 and VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZEEU &amp; Ors v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2006) 150 FCA 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/214.html</AustLII>
<text>I awaited the judgment of the Full Court in SZEEU &amp; Ors v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2006) 150 FCA 214 before coming to my decision and gave the parties the opportunity of making submissions in light of that judgment. Counsel for the appellants then sought leave to further amend the notice of appeal by taking one ground as follows: 
 
 
 '1. The Tribunal constructed a jurisdictional error when it failed to comply with s 424A of the M igration Act 1958 Cth 
 
 Particulars 
 
 
 
 (a) The Tribunal considered the following information was part of the reason for affirming the decision of the delegate to refuse the applicants protection visas: 
 
 
 
 (i) The applicant husbands education and employment history provided in the protection visa record. 
 
 
 
 (b) The Tribunal did not disclose the particulars of the information to the applicants in writing. 
 (c) The information was not exempted from disclosure by s 424A(3)(b). 
 (d) The information was specifically about the applicant husband.'

The amendment was opposed on two bases. Firstly an entirely new point should not be permitted to be raised at this stage of an appeal in judicial review proceedings. Secondly the proposed ground raises a question of fact, namely, what was provided by or on behalf of the appellants to the Tribunal for the purposes of s 424A(3)(b). Counsel for the appellants submitted that it can be deduced from a reading of the decision of the Tribunal, taken with the documents which were before the Tribunal, that it had relied upon material supplied only in the visa application. However, counsel for the Minister correctly points out that that conclusion cannot be drawn in the absence of a transcript of what took place before the Tribunal. If the issue had been raised in the Federal Magistrates Court, the factual issue could and would have been properly investigated.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/178.html</AustLII>
<text>The consequence is that the case for the appellants stands or falls upon the use by the Tribunal of country information concerning document fraud in Bangladesh without having complied with s 424A in relation to that information. That basis was rejected by the learned Federal Magistrate, based upon Full Court authority in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572. Counsel for the Minister submits that authority since then has confirmed that position. It is sufficient to refer to QAAC of 2004 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2005] FCAFC 92 and VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>