<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pfizer Corp v Commissioner of Patents (No 2) [2006] FCA 1176 (11 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1176.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler [1997] FCA 455</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1997/455.html</AustLII>
<text>An undertaking as to damages in support of a stay is required when it is necessary to protect against a perceived risk of loss ( Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495 at [8]; Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler [1997] FCA 455). Pfizer submits that the matters raised by the Commonwealth, such as a generic manufacturer who relies on the Patents Register and declines to take steps to be ready to enter the market in April 2007, are speculative and not sufficient reason to require the undertaking.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495</tocase>
<text>An undertaking as to damages in support of a stay is required when it is necessary to protect against a perceived risk of loss ( Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495 at [8]; Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler [1997] FCA 455). Pfizer submits that the matters raised by the Commonwealth, such as a generic manufacturer who relies on the Patents Register and declines to take steps to be ready to enter the market in April 2007, are speculative and not sufficient reason to require the undertaking.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>H Lundbeck A/S v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 163 ; (2006) 150 FCR 269</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/163.html</AustLII>
<text>The validity of reg 10.7(7) was considered by Lindgren J in H Lundbeck A/S v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 163 ; (2006) 150 FCR 269. His Honour held that reg 10.7(7) is not invalid. Pfizer makes a ' formal submission ' that reg 10.7(7) is invalid but limits its submissions to that contention. Pfizer relies upon the submissions presented by the applicant in Lundbeck as reflected in his Honour's reasons but does not repeat them or otherwise explain why reg 10.7(7) is invalid.

It is accepted by all parties that, for the purposes of this appeal, I will follow the Lundbeck decision that reg 10.7(7) is valid, prior to any determination to the contrary by the Full Court.



Section 70(3) provides that, as a condition for extension, goods containing at least one of the claimed pharmaceutical substances must be included in the Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods ('the ARTG') and the period beginning on the date of the patent and ending on ' the first regulatory approval date ' for the substance must be at least 5 years. Section 77 provides for the calculation of the term of extension by reference to the period beginning on the date of the Patent and ending on the earliest ' first regulatory approval date ' as defined in s 70, reduced by 5 years.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Newcastle City Council v GIO General Limited [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/53.html</AustLII>
<text>The words ' first inclusion in [the ARTG]' themselves are neither ambiguous nor obscure (see [ 31 ] above). This is acknowledged by Pfizer's submission that uncertainty arises ' not so much from the terms of s 70(5) itself but from the nature of the ARTG '. Accordingly, s 15AB(1)(b)(i) has no application ( Newcastle City Council v GIO General Limited [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85 at 112). Use of the extrinsic materials to confirm the ordinary meaning of the words does not assist Pfizer (s 15AB(1)(a)). Indeed, Pfizer did not rely on the extrinsic materials for this purpose.

Section 15AB(1)(b)(ii) is also not applicable. The ordinary meaning conveyed by the words ' first inclusion in [the ARTG]', taking into account their context and the purpose or object underlying the Act, does not lead to a ' manifestly absurd ' or ' unreasonable ' result ([ 65 ] below).

Pfizer submits that, independent of s 15AB of the Acts Interpretation Act , the extrinsic materials are part of the legal and historical context of the Act. For this reason, it submits that it is appropriate to consider the extrinsic materials at the outset to ascertain and give effect to the purpose of the Act, or ' the mischief which the statute was intended to cure ' ( Newcastle City Council at 99, 112-3).

In Newcastle City Council , the relevant Law Reform Commission Report on insurance contracts made the legislative objective plain (at 102). In the present case, it is difficult to detect any clear legislative purpose or intention with respect to the relevant entry in the ARTG. Although Pfizer points to the use of the words ' marketing in Australia ', ' the Australian market ' and ' first registration as a therapeutic good ', the extrinsic materials also refer to the time available to ' exploit ' the invention, the period during which patentees can ' earn a return ' and ' first inclusion in [the ARTG]'. To the extent that the policy of the IP Amendment Act is discussed, the discussion is equivocal as to whether the intention was to grant an extension from the date of an approval enabling marketing in Australia rather than the date of approval for a more limited form of exploitation such as manufacture for export.

This is not a case where a ' strained construction ' is necessary to give effect to the legislative purpose ( Newcastle City Council at 113). To the contrary, the extrinsic materials tend to confirm the clear, ordinary meaning of "first inclusion in the ARTG".

Pfizer applies for an order that the Commissioner of Patents be restrained from amending the Patents Register to reflect the shorter extended term of the Pfizer patents ('the stay order').

The Commonwealth filed a motion on 16 November 2005 seeking to intervene in relation to the stay order. The Commonwealth submits that, unless Pfizer can establish that no person could potentially suffer damage by the stay in rectification of the Patents Register, an undertaking as to damages should be required before a stay is granted. The undertaking is only sought in respect of one of the Pfizer patents, Australian Patent No 540769 in respect of the product NORVASC. Such potential damage would include, but not be limited to, damage to generic pharmaceutical companies which may wish to market NORVASC and damage to the Commonwealth in respect of the costs of the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pfizer Corp v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 67 IPR 646</tocase>
<text>Spirit Pharmaceuticals Pty Limited is an Australian pharmaceutical company with a commercial interest in the expiry date of at least one of the Pfizer patents. Spirit was joined as a respondent to this proceeding on 1 March 2006 ( Pfizer Corp v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 67 IPR 646).

Spirit seeks to adduce evidence of Dr Walters, a person experienced in matters relating to the ARTG, to establish the regulatory requirements of Listed Goods and the extent to which a patentee with an export only listing can exploit a patent. The evidence is said to answer Pfizer's contention that there is no requirement to lodge extensive data in support of an application for inclusion in the ARTG as Listed Goods, which is a requirement for goods to be Registered Goods. Spirit also wishes to respond to any suggestion that an export only listing does not allow exploitation of the patent which compensates for regulatory and product development delays. Such evidence was tendered by Pfizer before the Commissioner and was referred to in the decision. Pfizer now contends that the issue is one of statutory construction to which this evidence is not relevant.

Pfizer submits that all parties now accept that there can be different inclusions in the ARTG. Pfizer accepts that it is necessary to provide data in support of an application for Listed Goods and that an export only listing enables the patentee to exploit the invention, albeit on a less than "fully effective" basis. The point that Pfizer wishes to make is that the provision of data for Registered Goods is more onerous and extensive. This itself is said to result in regulatory delay before there can be marketing in Australia and full exploitation of the patent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>Re Pfizer Corporation (2005) 67 IPR 201</tocase>
<text>The Commissioner of Patents, by her delegate the Deputy Commissioner of Patents, decided that an amendment should be made to the Register of Patents ('the Patents Register') to correct the extension of term of four patents ('the Pfizer patents') in the name of the applicants (collectively 'Pfizer') ( Re Pfizer Corporation (2005) 67 IPR 201). This appeal by Pfizer from that decision raises two issues, which arise with respect to all four patents: 
 
 &#8226; The validity of reg 10.7(7) of the Patents Regulations 1991 (Cth) ('the Patents Regulations ').
 &#8226; The date from which an extension of term of a pharmaceutical patent is calculated.

</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment [2005] HCA 58 ; (2005) 221 ALR 448</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/58.html</AustLII>
<text>While no particular theory or rule of statutory interpretation obviates the need for close attention to the text and structure of the provision in question ( Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment [2005] HCA 58 ; (2005) 221 ALR 448 at [30] ), the extrinsic materials are part of the context of the Act and relevant in interpreting the meaning of ' first inclusion in [the ARTG]'.

The extrinsic materials, for whatever reason, do not give any clear indication of how the IP Amendment Act took its final form. That makes it difficult, if not impossible, to fix upon the references to ' marketing approval in Australia ' and ' bend ' the language of the Act to meet that purpose ( Stevens at [34]).

What is clear from the Response, which is given effect in the IP Amendment Act, is that the extension of term scheme was introduced in recognition of the need to compensate for the time before which a patentee of a pharmaceutical substance can exploit the invention.

Pfizer's submission that the relevant approval must be one which allows marketing in Australia in order to give effect to the policy of the IP Amendment Act ignores the fact that inclusion in the ARTG as Listed Goods permits the patentee to exploit the patent. This may not extend to marketing in Australia but it does enable a commercial return to the patentee. The consequence that this is less than full exploitation of the product in Australia is not contrary to the policy of the Act or the purpose of an extension to extend the "effective life" of the patent. The patentee's decision to obtain an early export only listing and thereby a shorter extended term is its choice and may have sound commercial reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 132</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/132.html</AustLII>
<text>Pfizer's concern is that, if the entry in the Patents Register is amended and Pfizer succeeds on any appeal, the Commissioner would have no power to re-amend the Register. Pfizer's concern arises because of potential problems once the Patents Register is rectified by amending the date of expiry of the patents to the earlier date. This was the subject of consideration by the Full Court in Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 52 ; (2006) 150 FCR 134 (' Woolworths No 1 ') and Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 132 ( 'Woolworths No 2 ') in the context of the Trade Marks Act 1995 (Cth). Sundberg and Bennett JJ in Woolworths No 1 at [52] and the Full Court in Woolworths No 2 at [149] were of the view that the Court has power to order the Register of Trade Marks to be rectified on appeal. No detailed submissions have been made as to the application of the Woolworths decisions in the context of the Act. Pfizer has not informed the Court whether it still seeks the stay order.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 52 ; (2006) 150 FCR 134</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/52.html</AustLII>
<text>Pfizer's concern is that, if the entry in the Patents Register is amended and Pfizer succeeds on any appeal, the Commissioner would have no power to re-amend the Register. Pfizer's concern arises because of potential problems once the Patents Register is rectified by amending the date of expiry of the patents to the earlier date. This was the subject of consideration by the Full Court in Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 52 ; (2006) 150 FCR 134 (' Woolworths No 1 ') and Woolworths Limited v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 132 ( 'Woolworths No 2 ') in the context of the Trade Marks Act 1995 (Cth). Sundberg and Bennett JJ in Woolworths No 1 at [52] and the Full Court in Woolworths No 2 at [149] were of the view that the Court has power to order the Register of Trade Marks to be rectified on appeal. No detailed submissions have been made as to the application of the Woolworths decisions in the context of the Act. Pfizer has not informed the Court whether it still seeks the stay order.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>