<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wen Bi Dai v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural&amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1819 (22 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1819.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cheng v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1028</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1028.html</AustLII>
<text>14 There is no basis for permitting the latest amendment and leave to amend should be refused. Apart from the general discretionary factors that would apply to an application to amend after the conclusion of the hearing, the applicant elected to seek merits review in the Tribunal of the Delegate's decision. The fact that such a review cured, in a legal sense, any defect in the hearing before the Delegate attributable to a denial of natural justice is now settled ( Zubair v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344; Uddin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 218 ; (2005) 149 FCR 1 (special leave to appeal refused); Humayun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 35 ; (2006) 149 FCR 558 at [30] ; Cheng v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1028 at [67] ). There is no reason to permit the applicant to amend to seek orders against the Delegate.

48 Further, in Mr Gormly's submission, Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314, Zubair , and Uddin have no application because the Tribunal in this case could not cure the denial of procedural fairness occasioned by the Notice. The Notice was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal. To the extent that existing authority of this Court suggests otherwise, Mr Gormly seeks to distinguish this case which, he says, raises matters not considered by the Full Court in Zhou and Zubair or by Siopis J in Cheng.

50 Mr Johnson makes six points in his submissions as to the alleged denial of procedural fairness:
 
 1. The Court is reviewing the decision of the Tribunal, which has no role to play in the processes of s 20 of the Students Act. 
 2. It is now settled by Zhou and Cheng that there is no legal interaction between the processes of s 20 of the Students Act and a cancellation under s 116 of the Act.
 3. It is not contended that the Notice did not comply with s 20 of the Students Act. In any event, Morsed does not say that there is a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal where a notice issued pursuant to s 20 of the Students Act is misleading.
 4. Even if it were misleading, the Notice did not affect the power of the Delegate to effect a visa cancellation under s 116 ( Humayun at [30]). Further, the Tribunal conducted a merits review and any defects in the decision of the Delegate were cured by that review ( Zubair ; Cheng at [67]).
 5. The question whether there could be a cure for any deficiency in the Notice that gave rise to a denial of natural justice could not affect the operation of s 116 of the Act. Such a denial could not result in jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal.
 6. No denial of natural justice or breach of statutory requirements can be established on the part of the Tribunal.

54 In Cheng , Siopis J addressed submissions that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error in failing to consider whether the Delegate had denied the applicant procedural fairness by reason of an allegedly misleading s 20 notice. As here, the alleged denial of procedural fairness was relevantly based on the failure of the applicant's expectation of being able to raise matters relating to her medical and personal circumstances as a means of preventing the cancellation of her visa, when there was an alternative course available where those circumstances could be raised as grounds for reinstating her visa (at [69]). His Honour applied Zhou and observed at [65] that '[i] t does not avail the applicant to impugn the procedural fairness of a process which is legally unrelated to the process which led to the impugned decision, namely, the cancellation of the visa under s 116 of the Act '. The processes are, as pointed out by his Honour at [72], ' legally separate '.

56 The decision under review in this case is that of the Tribunal. It is not suggested that the Tribunal failed to accord procedural fairness in its own procedures. Questions of procedural fairness must be considered by reference to the Tribunal's decision to affirm the Delegate's decision made under s 116 of the Act ( Cheng at [74]).

57 The Minister submits that, as the hearing before the Tribunal is a merits review, the Tribunal can, in a legal sense, "cure" any defects leading to the decision of the Delegate under review ( Zubair ; Ahmed ; Uddin ; Hamayun ). Mr Gormly submits, however, that the Tribunal cannot cure any defects in the Notice because it formed no part of the Tribunal's review of the decision to cancel made under s 116. He submits that this was not considered in Cheng and that this inability on the part of the Tribunal to cure the denial of procedural fairness invalidates the Tribunal decision.

58 This submission cannot be correct and ignores the reasoning in Zhou and Cheng . The Full Court in Zhou stated comprehensively at [39] that alleged defects in a s 20 notice are not material to an appeal from a decision of the Tribunal to affirm a cancellation decision under s 116 of the Act. Siopis J in Cheng specifically considered and rejected a submission that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error by failing to consider an alleged denial of procedural fairness on the part of the Delegate by reason of a s 20 notice being misleading. The s 20 notice has no role in the Tribunal decision. It is irrelevant to the Tribunal's review of the Minister's decision to cancel the visa under s 116, a decision with a different statutory basis. Once it is irrelevant and the question for this Court is jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal, the applicant cannot succeed on the basis of a denial of natural justice concerning the Notice.

60 Consistent with the decision in Zhou and Cheng , no jurisdictional error has been established on the part of the Tribunal in its review of the Minister's decision to cancel the applicant's visa pursuant to s 116 of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Conroy v Shire of Springvale and Noble Park (1959) VR 737</tocase>
<text>35 Mr Gormly argues that academic standards can never be fully objectified such that their application is a matter of mere administration. He points out that different institutions prescribe different rules and standards. The certification, he submits, is not merely administrative; it is not purely routine and non-discretionary. Mr Gormly submits that the education provider, by reason of its certification of an academic result "to be at least satisfactory" for the purposes of Condition 8202 and its issue of a s 20 notice under the Students Act, impermissibly performs a "migration function" without regard to the objects of the Act. Condition 8202(3)(b) is, he submits, ultra vires (cf Ellis v Dubowski (1921) 3 KB 621 at 625). It makes the education provider the decision maker on the terms of the visa condition and on a breach of that condition, resulting in automatic cancellation. Mr Gormly submits that the result is an invalid sub-delegation ( Conroy v Shire of Springvale and Noble Park (1959) VR 737).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ellis v Dubowski (1921) 3 KB 621</tocase>
<text>35 Mr Gormly argues that academic standards can never be fully objectified such that their application is a matter of mere administration. He points out that different institutions prescribe different rules and standards. The certification, he submits, is not merely administrative; it is not purely routine and non-discretionary. Mr Gormly submits that the education provider, by reason of its certification of an academic result "to be at least satisfactory" for the purposes of Condition 8202 and its issue of a s 20 notice under the Students Act, impermissibly performs a "migration function" without regard to the objects of the Act. Condition 8202(3)(b) is, he submits, ultra vires (cf Ellis v Dubowski (1921) 3 KB 621 at 625). It makes the education provider the decision maker on the terms of the visa condition and on a breach of that condition, resulting in automatic cancellation. Mr Gormly submits that the result is an invalid sub-delegation ( Conroy v Shire of Springvale and Noble Park (1959) VR 737).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Humayun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 35 ; (2006) 149 FCR 558 at [30]</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/35.html</AustLII>
<text>14 There is no basis for permitting the latest amendment and leave to amend should be refused. Apart from the general discretionary factors that would apply to an application to amend after the conclusion of the hearing, the applicant elected to seek merits review in the Tribunal of the Delegate's decision. The fact that such a review cured, in a legal sense, any defect in the hearing before the Delegate attributable to a denial of natural justice is now settled ( Zubair v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344; Uddin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 218 ; (2005) 149 FCR 1 (special leave to appeal refused); Humayun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 35 ; (2006) 149 FCR 558 at [30] ; Cheng v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1028 at [67] ). There is no reason to permit the applicant to amend to seek orders against the Delegate.

50 Mr Johnson makes six points in his submissions as to the alleged denial of procedural fairness:
 
 1. The Court is reviewing the decision of the Tribunal, which has no role to play in the processes of s 20 of the Students Act. 
 2. It is now settled by Zhou and Cheng that there is no legal interaction between the processes of s 20 of the Students Act and a cancellation under s 116 of the Act.
 3. It is not contended that the Notice did not comply with s 20 of the Students Act. In any event, Morsed does not say that there is a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal where a notice issued pursuant to s 20 of the Students Act is misleading.
 4. Even if it were misleading, the Notice did not affect the power of the Delegate to effect a visa cancellation under s 116 ( Humayun at [30]). Further, the Tribunal conducted a merits review and any defects in the decision of the Delegate were cured by that review ( Zubair ; Cheng at [67]).
 5. The question whether there could be a cure for any deficiency in the Notice that gave rise to a denial of natural justice could not affect the operation of s 116 of the Act. Such a denial could not result in jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal.
 6. No denial of natural justice or breach of statutory requirements can be established on the part of the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/58.html</AustLII>
<text>48 Further, in Mr Gormly's submission, Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314, Zubair , and Uddin have no application because the Tribunal in this case could not cure the denial of procedural fairness occasioned by the Notice. The Notice was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal. To the extent that existing authority of this Court suggests otherwise, Mr Gormly seeks to distinguish this case which, he says, raises matters not considered by the Full Court in Zhou and Zubair or by Siopis J in Cheng.

57 The Minister submits that, as the hearing before the Tribunal is a merits review, the Tribunal can, in a legal sense, "cure" any defects leading to the decision of the Delegate under review ( Zubair ; Ahmed ; Uddin ; Hamayun ). Mr Gormly submits, however, that the Tribunal cannot cure any defects in the Notice because it formed no part of the Tribunal's review of the decision to cancel made under s 116. He submits that this was not considered in Cheng and that this inability on the part of the Tribunal to cure the denial of procedural fairness invalidates the Tribunal decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>52 Mr Gormly adopts the characterisation of the defects in the s 20 notice in Morsed and relies upon the denial of procedural fairness resulting from that notice with its attendant effect on the opportunity for the applicant to rely on exceptional circumstances to avoid cancellation of her visa. He refers to Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at [34] and submits that, because of the consequences of compliance with the Notice, the contents of the Notice cannot be quarantined from the procedural fairness requirements of a cancellation under s 116(3) of the Act. The failure to accord procedural unfairness cannot, he says, be cured by merits review by the Tribunal because of the lack of discretion on the part of the Delegate and the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Zhou (2006) 125 FCR 115</tocase>
<text>8 By a further amended application filed in the Federal Magistrates Court under s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth), the applicant sought a declaration that Condition 8202(3)(b) of Sch 8 of the Regulations is invalid and a writ of certiorari to quash the Tribunal decision. This application to review the Tribunal's decision was referred to this Court by Emmett FM. A second further amended application was filed in this Court. The matter was then adjourned pending the anticipated judgment of the Full Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Zhou (2006) 125 FCR 115, which concerned one of the issues raised by the applicant in these proceedings.

9 Put shortly, the grounds of the second further amended application are based on the alleged invalidity of condition 8202(3)(b) and a denial of procedural fairness to the applicant. It is not in dispute that, if Condition 8202 is valid and there was no failure to accord procedural fairness, this application must fail.

10 In order to understand the alleged denial of procedural fairness, it is necessary to consider s 20 of the Students Act. Section 20(1) provides that a registered provider of overseas student courses must send the student a written notice if he or she has breached a student visa condition relating to attendance or satisfactory academic performance. That notice must state, inter alia, that the student is required to attend in person before an officer of the Department to explain the breach and set out the effects of s 137J and s 137K of the Act (s 20(4)(b) and (d) of the Students Act).

48 Further, in Mr Gormly's submission, Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314, Zubair , and Uddin have no application because the Tribunal in this case could not cure the denial of procedural fairness occasioned by the Notice. The Notice was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal. To the extent that existing authority of this Court suggests otherwise, Mr Gormly seeks to distinguish this case which, he says, raises matters not considered by the Full Court in Zhou and Zubair or by Siopis J in Cheng.

50 Mr Johnson makes six points in his submissions as to the alleged denial of procedural fairness:
 
 1. The Court is reviewing the decision of the Tribunal, which has no role to play in the processes of s 20 of the Students Act. 
 2. It is now settled by Zhou and Cheng that there is no legal interaction between the processes of s 20 of the Students Act and a cancellation under s 116 of the Act.
 3. It is not contended that the Notice did not comply with s 20 of the Students Act. In any event, Morsed does not say that there is a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal where a notice issued pursuant to s 20 of the Students Act is misleading.
 4. Even if it were misleading, the Notice did not affect the power of the Delegate to effect a visa cancellation under s 116 ( Humayun at [30]). Further, the Tribunal conducted a merits review and any defects in the decision of the Delegate were cured by that review ( Zubair ; Cheng at [67]).
 5. The question whether there could be a cure for any deficiency in the Notice that gave rise to a denial of natural justice could not affect the operation of s 116 of the Act. Such a denial could not result in jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal.
 6. No denial of natural justice or breach of statutory requirements can be established on the part of the Tribunal.

53 In Zhou , the applicant's visa was cancelled under s 116 of the Act on the grounds that she had breached Condition 8202 of her visa. The Full Court considered whether alleged defects in a s 20 notice under the Students Act are material to the resolution of an appeal from a decision of the Tribunal to affirm a cancellation decision under s 116 of the Act. The Full Court determined that, even where the s 20 notice and the response to it give rise to the delivery of the notice of intention to cancel the visa under s 119 of the Act (at [41] and [43]), there is no implied limitation on the operation of s 116 (at [42]) and no ' legal interaction ' between the s 20 notice under the Students Act and the exercise of power in s 116 of the Act. Invalidity of the s 20 notice can have no invalidating effect on the s 119 procedure (at [40]).

54 In Cheng , Siopis J addressed submissions that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error in failing to consider whether the Delegate had denied the applicant procedural fairness by reason of an allegedly misleading s 20 notice. As here, the alleged denial of procedural fairness was relevantly based on the failure of the applicant's expectation of being able to raise matters relating to her medical and personal circumstances as a means of preventing the cancellation of her visa, when there was an alternative course available where those circumstances could be raised as grounds for reinstating her visa (at [69]). His Honour applied Zhou and observed at [65] that '[i] t does not avail the applicant to impugn the procedural fairness of a process which is legally unrelated to the process which led to the impugned decision, namely, the cancellation of the visa under s 116 of the Act '. The processes are, as pointed out by his Honour at [72], ' legally separate '.

55 That conclusion follows from Zhou .

58 This submission cannot be correct and ignores the reasoning in Zhou and Cheng . The Full Court in Zhou stated comprehensively at [39] that alleged defects in a s 20 notice are not material to an appeal from a decision of the Tribunal to affirm a cancellation decision under s 116 of the Act. Siopis J in Cheng specifically considered and rejected a submission that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error by failing to consider an alleged denial of procedural fairness on the part of the Delegate by reason of a s 20 notice being misleading. The s 20 notice has no role in the Tribunal decision. It is irrelevant to the Tribunal's review of the Minister's decision to cancel the visa under s 116, a decision with a different statutory basis. Once it is irrelevant and the question for this Court is jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal, the applicant cannot succeed on the basis of a denial of natural justice concerning the Notice.

60 Consistent with the decision in Zhou and Cheng , no jurisdictional error has been established on the part of the Tribunal in its review of the Minister's decision to cancel the applicant's visa pursuant to s 116 of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Morsed v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 88 ALD 90</tocase>
<text>46 Mr Gormly places considerable reliance on Morsed v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 88 ALD 90 at [22] [24] where the Full Court observed that a s 20 notice in relevantly indistinguishable terms was, for this reason, misleading.

47 Mr Gormly acknowledges that the Act provides, by s 357A, for its procedures to be an exhaustive statement of the natural justice hearing rule before the Tribunal. He contends that as the Notice was not a notice served under the Act but under the Students Act and, as that notice did not apply to the substantive right considered by the Tribunal and its validity was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal, that section does not apply.

50 Mr Johnson makes six points in his submissions as to the alleged denial of procedural fairness:
 
 1. The Court is reviewing the decision of the Tribunal, which has no role to play in the processes of s 20 of the Students Act. 
 2. It is now settled by Zhou and Cheng that there is no legal interaction between the processes of s 20 of the Students Act and a cancellation under s 116 of the Act.
 3. It is not contended that the Notice did not comply with s 20 of the Students Act. In any event, Morsed does not say that there is a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal where a notice issued pursuant to s 20 of the Students Act is misleading.
 4. Even if it were misleading, the Notice did not affect the power of the Delegate to effect a visa cancellation under s 116 ( Humayun at [30]). Further, the Tribunal conducted a merits review and any defects in the decision of the Delegate were cured by that review ( Zubair ; Cheng at [67]).
 5. The question whether there could be a cure for any deficiency in the Notice that gave rise to a denial of natural justice could not affect the operation of s 116 of the Act. Such a denial could not result in jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal.
 6. No denial of natural justice or breach of statutory requirements can be established on the part of the Tribunal.

51 I agree, with respect, with the observations of the Full Court in Morsed at [21] that the Notice does not inform the recipient that, where the breach was due to exceptional circumstances beyond her control, the only way that a holder of a student visa who has breached Condition 8202 can avoid having their visa cancelled is not to comply with the Notice. The Notice is misleading for the reasons given in Morsed at [22] [25].

52 Mr Gormly adopts the characterisation of the defects in the s 20 notice in Morsed and relies upon the denial of procedural fairness resulting from that notice with its attendant effect on the opportunity for the applicant to rely on exceptional circumstances to avoid cancellation of her visa. He refers to Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at [34] and submits that, because of the consequences of compliance with the Notice, the contents of the Notice cannot be quarantined from the procedural fairness requirements of a cancellation under s 116(3) of the Act. The failure to accord procedural unfairness cannot, he says, be cured by merits review by the Tribunal because of the lack of discretion on the part of the Delegate and the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Racecourse Co-operative Sugar Association Ltd v Attorney-General of the State of Queensland [1979] HCA 50 ; (1979) 142 CLR 460</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1979/50.html</AustLII>
<text>42 On its proper construction, the Act permits the opinion or assessment of the education provider to be provided for in the regulations, to be provided to the Minister and had regard to and be considered correct in the decision making of the Minister (see discussion in Racecourse Co-operative Sugar Association Ltd v Attorney-General of the State of Queensland [1979] HCA 50 ; (1979) 142 CLR 460 at 481 per Gibbs J).

43 The fact that the scheme of the Act results in an absence of discretion in the cancellation of a visa where the Minister has decided that the requirements of Condition 8202 has not been satisfied under s 116 does not determine that there has been a delegation of the power to specify visa conditions to the education provider. It does not convert the specification by the Governor-General of conditions pursuant to s 41 into an impermissible delegation of the specification of the visa condition.

44 Mr Gormly emphasises the misleading nature of the Notice. Specifically, he contends that the Notice implies that there exists a discretion on the part of the Department, so that an explanation for the breach will be taken into account. It does not, he observes, inform the applicant that her visa will be cancelled if a breach of condition did occur and she attends to "explain" that breach in response to the Notice. The applicant was thereby deprived of the opportunity of not responding to the Notice, awaiting the automatic cancellation of her visa and then applying to the Minister under s 137K of the Act, where exceptional circumstances can be taken into consideration (s 137L(1)(b)). This represents the alleged practical unfairness of the denial of natural justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Turner v Owen (1990) 26 FCR 366</tocase>
<text>34 Mr Gormly relies upon the conclusion by French J in Turner v Owen (1990) 26 FCR 366 that delegating to the Minister the power to prohibit goods, which in his opinion ' are of a dangerous character and a menace to the community ' constituted an unlawful delegation because those words ' are not indicative of a factual criterion or class description limited by any intelligible boundary ' and were legislative in character (at 389). French J concluded that the regulations in that case impermissibly asked the Minister to prohibit, rather than the Governor-General.

37 Here, the delegation is not of the decision to decide whether a visa holder satisfies the criterion. Section 41 provides that the regulations may provide that visas are subject to specified conditions. Condition 8202 is such a condition specified in the Regulations. The Minister decides whether to grant a visa, subject to satisfaction that the criteria are satisfied (s 65). The Minister decides whether a visa holder satisfies the specified condition (s 116(1) of the Act, reg 2.43(2)(b)(ii) of the Regulations). Further, as a matter of reality, an academic result that, for a specified course, is "at least satisfactory" is limited ' by an intelligible boundary ' and is not legislative in character (cf Turner at [389]).

38 Section 505, which refers specifically to such matters for visa applicants, does not delegate the whole of power to decide whether an applicant for a visa satisfies the relevant criterion. The section provides for the making of regulations under which the Minister, when required to decide whether an applicant for a visa satisfies a specified criterion, may obtain the opinion, assessment, finding or decision of a specified person or organisation and have regard to it and to take it to be correct.

39 The sub-delegation in s 505 is not of a legislative but of an administrative character. It is not the delegation of a wide field of operation but, rather, a narrow question of fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Twinn v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 242 ; (2005) 147 FCR 490</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/242.html</AustLII>
<text>40 A sub-delegation under s 504 is of the same character. The Act does not reserve any of the delegated functions in Condition 8202 to the Governor-General. The Governor-General has exercised the power conferred by the Act to make regulations, within the limits laid down by the Act ( Twinn v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 242 ; (2005) 147 FCR 490 at [22] ). The authorisation given by s 504 encompasses the making of regulations by the Governor-General to allow administrative functions to be undertaken by the Minister for the purposes of the regulations ( Twinn at [23]). For the purposes of deciding whether an applicant for a visa satisfies the condition for a visa, the regulations may make provision for the Minister to have consideration of the matters enunciated in s 505 of the Act. The fact that this was particularised in s 505, "to avoid doubt", indicates a statutory acknowledgment that the power to make regulations in respect of those matters already existed by reason of s 504 and s 41(1) of the Act.

41 Once the Minister is satisfied that the condition has not been met, there is a mandatory cancellation by reason of s 116(3) but that does not convert the sub-delegation into an effective abdication of powers (see generally Pearce D and Argument S, Delegated Legislation in Australia (3 rd ed, Butterworths, 2005) Ch 23).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Uddin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 218 ; (2005) 149 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/218.html</AustLII>
<text>14 There is no basis for permitting the latest amendment and leave to amend should be refused. Apart from the general discretionary factors that would apply to an application to amend after the conclusion of the hearing, the applicant elected to seek merits review in the Tribunal of the Delegate's decision. The fact that such a review cured, in a legal sense, any defect in the hearing before the Delegate attributable to a denial of natural justice is now settled ( Zubair v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344; Uddin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 218 ; (2005) 149 FCR 1 (special leave to appeal refused); Humayun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 35 ; (2006) 149 FCR 558 at [30] ; Cheng v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1028 at [67] ). There is no reason to permit the applicant to amend to seek orders against the Delegate.

48 Further, in Mr Gormly's submission, Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314, Zubair , and Uddin have no application because the Tribunal in this case could not cure the denial of procedural fairness occasioned by the Notice. The Notice was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal. To the extent that existing authority of this Court suggests otherwise, Mr Gormly seeks to distinguish this case which, he says, raises matters not considered by the Full Court in Zhou and Zubair or by Siopis J in Cheng.

57 The Minister submits that, as the hearing before the Tribunal is a merits review, the Tribunal can, in a legal sense, "cure" any defects leading to the decision of the Delegate under review ( Zubair ; Ahmed ; Uddin ; Hamayun ). Mr Gormly submits, however, that the Tribunal cannot cure any defects in the Notice because it formed no part of the Tribunal's review of the decision to cancel made under s 116. He submits that this was not considered in Cheng and that this inability on the part of the Tribunal to cure the denial of procedural fairness invalidates the Tribunal decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Zubair v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/248.html</AustLII>
<text>14 There is no basis for permitting the latest amendment and leave to amend should be refused. Apart from the general discretionary factors that would apply to an application to amend after the conclusion of the hearing, the applicant elected to seek merits review in the Tribunal of the Delegate's decision. The fact that such a review cured, in a legal sense, any defect in the hearing before the Delegate attributable to a denial of natural justice is now settled ( Zubair v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344; Uddin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 218 ; (2005) 149 FCR 1 (special leave to appeal refused); Humayun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 35 ; (2006) 149 FCR 558 at [30] ; Cheng v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1028 at [67] ). There is no reason to permit the applicant to amend to seek orders against the Delegate.

48 Further, in Mr Gormly's submission, Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Ahmed [2005] FCAFC 58 ; (2005) 143 FCR 314, Zubair , and Uddin have no application because the Tribunal in this case could not cure the denial of procedural fairness occasioned by the Notice. The Notice was not part of the hearing before the Tribunal. To the extent that existing authority of this Court suggests otherwise, Mr Gormly seeks to distinguish this case which, he says, raises matters not considered by the Full Court in Zhou and Zubair or by Siopis J in Cheng.

50 Mr Johnson makes six points in his submissions as to the alleged denial of procedural fairness:
 
 1. The Court is reviewing the decision of the Tribunal, which has no role to play in the processes of s 20 of the Students Act. 
 2. It is now settled by Zhou and Cheng that there is no legal interaction between the processes of s 20 of the Students Act and a cancellation under s 116 of the Act.
 3. It is not contended that the Notice did not comply with s 20 of the Students Act. In any event, Morsed does not say that there is a breach of procedural fairness by the Tribunal where a notice issued pursuant to s 20 of the Students Act is misleading.
 4. Even if it were misleading, the Notice did not affect the power of the Delegate to effect a visa cancellation under s 116 ( Humayun at [30]). Further, the Tribunal conducted a merits review and any defects in the decision of the Delegate were cured by that review ( Zubair ; Cheng at [67]).
 5. The question whether there could be a cure for any deficiency in the Notice that gave rise to a denial of natural justice could not affect the operation of s 116 of the Act. Such a denial could not result in jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal.
 6. No denial of natural justice or breach of statutory requirements can be established on the part of the Tribunal.

57 The Minister submits that, as the hearing before the Tribunal is a merits review, the Tribunal can, in a legal sense, "cure" any defects leading to the decision of the Delegate under review ( Zubair ; Ahmed ; Uddin ; Hamayun ). Mr Gormly submits, however, that the Tribunal cannot cure any defects in the Notice because it formed no part of the Tribunal's review of the decision to cancel made under s 116. He submits that this was not considered in Cheng and that this inability on the part of the Tribunal to cure the denial of procedural fairness invalidates the Tribunal decision.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>