<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tepperova v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1147 (29 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1147.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Vans, Inc v Offprice.Com.Au Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 137</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/137.html</AustLII>
<text>While there is some level of uncertainty as to the burden of the "no reasonable prospect" formulae in s 31A: see e.g. Vans, Inc v Offprice.Com.Au Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 137 ; this is not a case in which it is necessary to explore that formula at any length. The claims made against the first and third respondents are doomed to failure as they disclose no reasonable causes of action in any event. The Amended Statement of Claim is itself embarrassing and must be struck out under O 11 r 16. As the applicant has been given every reasonable opportunity to replead and has been given adequate forewarning of what was needed and required, I will not give leave again to further amend the Amended Statement of Claim. Rather I will order the application be dismissed.

I will consider the claims made against each respondent in turn.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Racz v Home Office [1994] 2 AC 45</tocase>
<text>There are two bases on which relief was sought against the Minister. The first was that he was vicariously liable for the misfeasance tort of the second and third respondents. Accepting that an employer could be vicariously liable for such a tort: see Racz v Home Office [1994] 2 AC 45; Porter v OAMPS Ltd (2005) 215 ALR 327 at [108]; the applicant abandoned this claim when confronted with the constitutional reality in this country that public servants, such as the second and third respondents who are employed under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth), are employees of the Commonwealth, not of the relevant portfolio Minister.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Porter v OAMPS Ltd (2005) 215 ALR 327</tocase>
<text>There are two bases on which relief was sought against the Minister. The first was that he was vicariously liable for the misfeasance tort of the second and third respondents. Accepting that an employer could be vicariously liable for such a tort: see Racz v Home Office [1994] 2 AC 45; Porter v OAMPS Ltd (2005) 215 ALR 327 at [108]; the applicant abandoned this claim when confronted with the constitutional reality in this country that public servants, such as the second and third respondents who are employed under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth), are employees of the Commonwealth, not of the relevant portfolio Minister.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Sanders v Snell (No 2) [2003] FCAFC 150 ; (2003) 130 FCR 149</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/150.html</AustLII>
<text>As is now well accepted, the misfeasance tort can take either of two forms. In one form (that of "targeted malice") it must be shown that the public officer in question has acted as such with an actual intent to cause injury to a person or persons. In its alternate form it must be shown either that the officer has actual knowledge both that his or her action was beyond power and would cause or be likely to cause injury, or else that the officer has acted with reckless indifference both to the possibility his or her action was beyond power and to the possibility that that action would cause or be likely to cause injury: see generally Sanders v Snell (No 2) [2003] FCAFC 150 ; (2003) 130 FCR 149 at [95] - [100] . The essence of the tort in either of its forms is the "dishonest abuse of power": L (a child) v Reading Borough Council [2001] EWCA Civ 346 ; [2001] 1 WLR 1575 at 1588.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>L (a child) v Reading Borough Council [2001] EWCA Civ 346 ; [2001] 1 WLR 1575</tocase>
<text>As is now well accepted, the misfeasance tort can take either of two forms. In one form (that of "targeted malice") it must be shown that the public officer in question has acted as such with an actual intent to cause injury to a person or persons. In its alternate form it must be shown either that the officer has actual knowledge both that his or her action was beyond power and would cause or be likely to cause injury, or else that the officer has acted with reckless indifference both to the possibility his or her action was beyond power and to the possibility that that action would cause or be likely to cause injury: see generally Sanders v Snell (No 2) [2003] FCAFC 150 ; (2003) 130 FCR 149 at [95] - [100] . The essence of the tort in either of its forms is the "dishonest abuse of power": L (a child) v Reading Borough Council [2001] EWCA Civ 346 ; [2001] 1 WLR 1575 at 1588.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>