<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>VSAB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 239 (17 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/239.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Applicants in V 722 of 2000 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 1059</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/1059.html</AustLII>
<text>29 Mr Gibson noted that the Federal Magistrate had relied upon the judgment of Ryan J in Applicants in V 722 of 2000 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 1059 (" Applicants V 722 ") in dealing with the ascertainment of foreign law. His Honour's approach was approved, on appeal, by the Full Court in VHAJ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 186.

30 In substance, Ryan J held, at [32]-[33], that while findings relating to the law of a foreign country are questions of fact, and therefore susceptible to proof by expert evidence, it is not necessary to resort to such evidence to make "a finding as to the effect of a relevant law of a foreign country". He stated at [33]:
 
 "If, for example, the text of a presumably relevant statute of that country or an authoritative statement in a legal text book or other authority appears to suggest with sufficient precision the effect of the law in question, the court or tribunal is entitled, in the absence of contradictory expert evidence, to make a finding accordingly ( Evidence Act (Cth) 1995 s 174(1)). "

31 It should be noted that Ryan J did not stipulate that the only way in which foreign law can be proved is through one of the means set out above. These were examples, rather than an exhaustive statement of the methods of proof that were legally permissible.

32 In any event, Mr Gibson submitted that Ryan J's judgment needed to be understood in context. He contended that, to the extent that his Honour's reasoning might be thought to broaden the types of evidence upon which a finding as to foreign law could be made, Applicants V 722 was distinguishable from the present case on the following bases:
 
 
 "i) the issue requiring an examination of foreign law in that case was the entitlement of the applicants to remain in, or re-enter Italy 
 
 ii) this was a different issue to that of establishing nationality, and in any event, there were a number of evidentiary matters raising a presumption that they would not be precluded from returning to Italy i.e. long term residence coupled with possession of valid passports endorsed with Australian visitor's visas. The presumption was strengthened by their possession of unexpired Italian temporary residence permits and had pending applications for permanent residence permits. 
 
 iii) Raising a rebuttable presumption regarding the entitlement of a non-citizen to re-enter a foreign state is not the same thing as establishing that a person holds the nationality of a foreign state, and as the judgment shows a lesser evidentiary basis may suffice in the former situation. 
 
 iv) The case is otherwise distinguishable on its facts as it was accepted that the passport was valid. Here the First Appellant's case was that his passport and its renewal had been acquired by fraudulent means purchase through the agency of a corrupt policeman by payment of massive bribes without which he would not have been able to secure documentation ... In light of the basis on which his case was put, acceptance by the Tribunal ... that he may have paid some bribes without any further explanation (or rejection of any aspect of this story) totally undermines any prima facie presumption of nationally by reason of the issue and possession of a FYROM passport".

33 Mr Gibson then submitted that nothing said by Ryan J in Applicants V 722 detracted from his central proposition that the issue of nationality, and particularly nationality derivatively acquired, raised a question of fact, and had to be proved. He further submitted that it was no answer for the Minister to contend, as her counsel had, that it had been open to the husband to provide evidence of the relevant law governing nationality in FYROM. He submitted that before the Tribunal could properly make any finding on a critical issue of this nature, it was obliged to ensure that it had sufficient material before it to support such a finding.

34 With regard to the husband's possession of the FYROM passport, Mr Gibson submitted that the Tribunal had acknowledged, and accepted, the husband's account of how he had initially acquired that passport, and later had it renewed. It was always the husband's case that upon the expiry of his former Yugoslav passport, he had managed to purchase a FYROM passport through his contacts with a corrupt policeman. In other words, his claim, which it was submitted had been accepted by the Tribunal, was that he had obtained the passport only through the payment of bribes. It was submitted that whatever weight might ordinarily be given to the possession of a particular passport when considering the question of nationality, no weight could attach to that fact in circumstances where the passport had only been obtained through bribery.

35 Mr Gibson also criticised certain aspects of the reasoning of the Federal Magistrate. At one point, his Honour had put forward the hypothesis that even though the husband may have paid bribes in relation to the passport, it did not necessarily follow that the passport could not provide some evidence of nationality. His Honour's reasoning, implicitly at least, was that the husband may have been entitled to the issue of a FYROM passport, but paid a bribe in ignorance of that fact. Alternatively, the husband may have paid bribes simply in order to speed up the process of obtaining the passport to which he was, in fact, in any event entitled. Mr Gibson submitted that each of these hypotheses consisted of nothing more than speculation and conjecture. He further submitted that they indicated that the Federal Magistrate had failed to appreciate the fact that the case before the Tribunal had been put on a basis that did not admit of any such reasoning. That was because, implicit in that case, was the contention that the husband obtained his passport by bribery, and that he was not legally entitled to one.

36 Mr Gibson therefore submitted that, contrary to the Federal Magistrate's findings, the Tribunal had considered and evaluated the husband's claims against the wrong country. It ought to have carried out its statutory task by reference to Bosnia-Herzegovina, the country of which the husband was an acknowledged national, and not by reference to FYROM, a country in which he had only occasionally resided.

37 Mr Horan, counsel for the Minister, acknowledged that whether the husband was a national of FYROM did indeed raise a question of fact. He submitted that the Tribunal had determined that question of fact lawfully, and in an appropriate manner. It had identified the relevant issue correctly, and had properly concluded, on the basis of the material before it, that the husband was a national of FYROM.

38 Mr Horan submitted that there was, in fact, a substantial body of evidence and other material before the Tribunal to support that conclusion. This included, in particular, the various matters set out in the passage from the Tribunal's reasons for decision extracted above at [8]. He submitted that it could not be said that the Tribunal had failed to address any of the husband's claims, or that it had misconstrued, misunderstood or overlooked any relevant criteria for the grant of a visa. In classic terms, it could not be said that the Tribunal had identified a wrong issue, asked itself a wrong question, ignored relevant material or relied on irrelevant material.

39 Mr Horan submitted that, contrary to Mr Gibson's contention, there were no "irreducible minimum evidentiary requirements" to be satisfied in order to establish that the husband was a national of FYROM. Nor was there any "minimum standard of proof" that had to be met. He contended that Mr Gibson's submission, when properly understood, amounted to nothing more than a claim that there was insufficient evidence to support the Tribunal's finding. Even if that claim could be substantiated, it would not demonstrate the existence of jurisdictional error. The appellants would have to go further, and show that there was "no evidence" to support the Tribunal's finding. This they plainly could not do.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Joyce v Director of Public Prosecutions [1946] AC 347</tocase>
<text>54 It is at the next stage that the appellants' argument breaks down. In my view, the possession and regular use by the husband of a FYROM passport provided some evidence that he was, as the Tribunal found, a national of that country. At common law, the issue of a passport involved an exercise of the royal prerogative by which the protection of the Crown was extended to a citizen of the country in whose name the passport was issued who travelled abroad: see Joyce v Director of Public Prosecutions [1946] AC 347 at 369-70; and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Petrovski (1997) 73 FCR 303 at 307. Under ss 7 and 8 of the Australian Passports Act 2005 (Cth), an Australia passport can only be granted to an Australian citizen. The same appears to be generally true of other countries. The issue of a passport does not, of itself, amount to a grant of citizenship. It may not amount to conclusive evidence of nationality, but it seems to me to be at least some evidence of that fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Petrovski (1997) 73 FCR 303</tocase>
<text>54 It is at the next stage that the appellants' argument breaks down. In my view, the possession and regular use by the husband of a FYROM passport provided some evidence that he was, as the Tribunal found, a national of that country. At common law, the issue of a passport involved an exercise of the royal prerogative by which the protection of the Crown was extended to a citizen of the country in whose name the passport was issued who travelled abroad: see Joyce v Director of Public Prosecutions [1946] AC 347 at 369-70; and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Petrovski (1997) 73 FCR 303 at 307. Under ss 7 and 8 of the Australian Passports Act 2005 (Cth), an Australia passport can only be granted to an Australian citizen. The same appears to be generally true of other countries. The issue of a passport does not, of itself, amount to a grant of citizenship. It may not amount to conclusive evidence of nationality, but it seems to me to be at least some evidence of that fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nolan v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1988] HCA 45 ; (1988) 165 CLR 178</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/45.html</AustLII>
<text>51 Of course, while remaining constitutional monarchies, both Australia and the United Kingdom have by statute adopted the concept of "citizenship". See Nationality and Citizenship Act 1948 (Cth) (now titled the Australian Citizenship Act 1948 (Cth)), and see also the British Nationality Act 1981 (UK). The notions of citizenship and nationality were considered by the High Court in Nolan v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1988] HCA 45 ; (1988) 165 CLR 178 at 186, and in Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391 at 467 (per Gummow and Hayne JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nottebohm Case (Liechtenstein v Guatemala) (Second Phase) [1955] ICJ Rep 4</tocase>
<text>49 Questions of nationality are generally determined in accordance with the municipal laws of the State concerned: Convention on Certain Questions Relating to Nationality , opened for signature 12 April 1930, LNTS 179 89, arts 1 and 2 (entered into force 1 July 1937, ratified by Australia 10 November 1937) and Tji at 513-14. There are, however, limits on the extent to which such municipal laws will be recognised under international law: See Nottebohm Case (Liechtenstein v Guatemala) [1955] ICJ 4 at 20-23; R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 649 per Latham CJ, and 673 per Dixon J; and Sykes v Cleary [1992] HCA 60 ; (1992) 176 CLR 77 at 105-6 per Mason CJ, Toohey and McHugh JJ, 112 per Brennan J, 127 per Deane J, 131 per Dawson J, and 135 per Gaudron J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249</tocase>
<text>24 Mr Gibson, counsel for the appellants, developed these submissions in the course of a helpful argument. He contended that at common law, and under customary international law, a person's nationality had to be determined by the municipal law of the State in relation to which nationality was claimed. He cited Tji v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1998) 55 ALD 508 at 513-4 per Finkelstein J, and Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249 as authority for this proposition. He next submitted that a distinction should be drawn between what Finkelstein J in Tji referred to as "original acquisition of nationality", and what his Honour described as "derivative acquisition of nationality": see Tji at 516. In international law, generally speaking, original acquisition of nationality, that is nationality acquired at birth, was based on descent from a national, or birth within the territory of a State, or both. Derivative acquisition of nationality (which Mr Gibson contended was at issue in this case) could take place in one of only two ways. These were through naturalisation (in consequence of an application for citizenship), or by operation of law (for example, through the emergence of a new State, and principles of succession). See generally the discussion of these principles in Tji at 516.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/52.html</AustLII>
<text>49 Questions of nationality are generally determined in accordance with the municipal laws of the State concerned: Convention on Certain Questions Relating to Nationality , opened for signature 12 April 1930, LNTS 179 89, arts 1 and 2 (entered into force 1 July 1937, ratified by Australia 10 November 1937) and Tji at 513-14. There are, however, limits on the extent to which such municipal laws will be recognised under international law: See Nottebohm Case (Liechtenstein v Guatemala) [1955] ICJ 4 at 20-23; R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 649 per Latham CJ, and 673 per Dixon J; and Sykes v Cleary [1992] HCA 60 ; (1992) 176 CLR 77 at 105-6 per Mason CJ, Toohey and McHugh JJ, 112 per Brennan J, 127 per Deane J, 131 per Dawson J, and 135 per Gaudron J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/51.html</AustLII>
<text>51 Of course, while remaining constitutional monarchies, both Australia and the United Kingdom have by statute adopted the concept of "citizenship". See Nationality and Citizenship Act 1948 (Cth) (now titled the Australian Citizenship Act 1948 (Cth)), and see also the British Nationality Act 1981 (UK). The notions of citizenship and nationality were considered by the High Court in Nolan v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1988] HCA 45 ; (1988) 165 CLR 178 at 186, and in Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391 at 467 (per Gummow and Hayne JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SFGB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 231</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/231.html</AustLII>
<text>45 Mr Horan relied upon the following observation of the Full Court regarding the "no evidence ground" in SFGB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 231 at [20] :
 
 "On the other hand, if there is sufficient evidence or other information before the Tribunal on which it could reach the conclusion it did then it is for the Tribunal to determine what weight it gives to that evidence. Indeed, unless the relevant fact can be identified as a 'jurisdictional fact', there is no error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error, in the Tribunal making a wrong finding of fact: Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35-36. It is for the Tribunal to determine the merit of the claim. The line between merit review and jurisdictional error may not be a 'bright line', but it is nevertheless an essential one: Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272."

46 Mr Horan noted that Mr Gibson had not submitted that the question of the husband's nationality gave rise to a "jurisdictional fact". It was clear that it did not.

47 Mr Horan therefore submitted that the appellants' case, taken at its highest, amounted to nothing more than an assertion that the Tribunal's finding that the husband was a national of FYROM was factually incorrect. However, consistently with SFGB and numerous other authorities, even if factual error of that kind could be demonstrated, it would not give rise to jurisdictional error. And the second limb of Mr Gibson's argument, namely his submission that the Tribunal had been required to refer to direct evidence only of the relevant laws of FYROM, was unsupported by any authority, and could not be sustained.

48 It should be noted, at the outset, that the concept of "nationality", which is central to this appeal, is a term somewhat lacking in precision. It is generally used to signify the legal connection between an individual and a State. The primary relevance of nationality under international law is to provide a basis upon which a State can exercise jurisdiction over persons. However, the term is employed in different ways in international law, and domestic law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sykes v Cleary [1992] HCA 60 ; (1992) 176 CLR 77</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/60.html</AustLII>
<text>49 Questions of nationality are generally determined in accordance with the municipal laws of the State concerned: Convention on Certain Questions Relating to Nationality , opened for signature 12 April 1930, LNTS 179 89, arts 1 and 2 (entered into force 1 July 1937, ratified by Australia 10 November 1937) and Tji at 513-14. There are, however, limits on the extent to which such municipal laws will be recognised under international law: See Nottebohm Case (Liechtenstein v Guatemala) [1955] ICJ 4 at 20-23; R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 649 per Latham CJ, and 673 per Dixon J; and Sykes v Cleary [1992] HCA 60 ; (1992) 176 CLR 77 at 105-6 per Mason CJ, Toohey and McHugh JJ, 112 per Brennan J, 127 per Deane J, 131 per Dawson J, and 135 per Gaudron J.

50 One of the terms that is often used synonymously with "nationality" is "citizenship". It has become usual to employ the term "citizen" instead of "subject" in States that adopt a republican form of government. In Sykes v Cleary , Brennan J observed at 109, in relation to the expression "subject or citizen of a foreign power" in s 44(i) of the Commonwealth Constitution ,
 
 "subject being a term appropriate when the foreign power is a monarch of feudal origin; citizen when the foreign power is a republic."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tji v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1998) 55 ALD 508</tocase>
<text>24 Mr Gibson, counsel for the appellants, developed these submissions in the course of a helpful argument. He contended that at common law, and under customary international law, a person's nationality had to be determined by the municipal law of the State in relation to which nationality was claimed. He cited Tji v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1998) 55 ALD 508 at 513-4 per Finkelstein J, and Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249 as authority for this proposition. He next submitted that a distinction should be drawn between what Finkelstein J in Tji referred to as "original acquisition of nationality", and what his Honour described as "derivative acquisition of nationality": see Tji at 516. In international law, generally speaking, original acquisition of nationality, that is nationality acquired at birth, was based on descent from a national, or birth within the territory of a State, or both. Derivative acquisition of nationality (which Mr Gibson contended was at issue in this case) could take place in one of only two ways. These were through naturalisation (in consequence of an application for citizenship), or by operation of law (for example, through the emergence of a new State, and principles of succession). See generally the discussion of these principles in Tji at 516.

49 Questions of nationality are generally determined in accordance with the municipal laws of the State concerned: Convention on Certain Questions Relating to Nationality , opened for signature 12 April 1930, LNTS 179 89, arts 1 and 2 (entered into force 1 July 1937, ratified by Australia 10 November 1937) and Tji at 513-14. There are, however, limits on the extent to which such municipal laws will be recognised under international law: See Nottebohm Case (Liechtenstein v Guatemala) [1955] ICJ 4 at 20-23; R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 649 per Latham CJ, and 673 per Dixon J; and Sykes v Cleary [1992] HCA 60 ; (1992) 176 CLR 77 at 105-6 per Mason CJ, Toohey and McHugh JJ, 112 per Brennan J, 127 per Deane J, 131 per Dawson J, and 135 per Gaudron J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VHAJ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 186</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/186.html</AustLII>
<text>29 Mr Gibson noted that the Federal Magistrate had relied upon the judgment of Ryan J in Applicants in V 722 of 2000 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 1059 (" Applicants V 722 ") in dealing with the ascertainment of foreign law. His Honour's approach was approved, on appeal, by the Full Court in VHAJ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 186.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>