<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>AMP Services Ltd v Manning [2006] FCA 256 (24 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/256.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Aberdeen Railway Co v Blaikie Bros (1854) Macq 461</tocase>
<text>59 The claim that Ms Manning breached her duty not to make use of any business opportunity obtained during the course of her employment must also be rejected. This kind of claim cannot be brought against an employee in Ms Manning's position. It is reserved for those in "top management" such as directors or senior officers: Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley (1973) 40 DLR (3d) 371, 381-382. See also Aberdeen Railway Co v Blaikie Bros (1854) Macq 461, 472.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>American Financial Corporation v Computer Sciences Corporation , 558 FSupp 1182 (D.Del, 1983)</tocase>
<text>6 It will be noticed that the promisee under each employment contract is AMP Services. Yet it is Arrive that sues for the breach of each contract to recover its alleged loss of $4.3 million. The difficulty with such a course is obvious and was recognised by the plaintiffs. In their amended points of claim they allege that the benefit of the post-employment restraint and the benefit of other provisions of each contract are held on trust for Arrive. In the alternative they contend that each agreement was made by AMP Services as agent for Arrive. Those are the bases upon which Arrive asserts standing to sue. The allegation that several provisions of each contract are held on trust for Arrive has been admitted, although the defendants say that each post-employment restraint is "void and unenforceable". The admission makes it unnecessary to determine several tricky questions that would otherwise arise, including: (1) Whether each promise is capable of being held on trust; (2) Whether the intention to create the trust must be gathered from the contract itself or whether extrinsic evidence is admissible for this purpose: American Financial Corporation v Computer Sciences Corporation , 558 FSupp 1182 (D.Del, 1983); and (3) Whether the requisite intention must be that of both the promisor and the promisee: see the discussion in Restatement (Second) of Contracts SS302.

7 The principal service provided by Arrive to its clients was investment and superannuation planning advice. Its income was derived from fees charged for advice and commissions earned from the management of funds. The business was conducted from offices in most capital cities. The largest office was located in the PwC building in Melbourne where Ms Manning was in charge. The advisers in the Melbourne office were Ms Manning's group from PwC plus two additional advisers, Sam Gray and Andrew Walsh, who had been engaged in 2003.

8 Ms Manning was Arrive's most successful adviser. Yet, she was dissatisfied with several aspects of Arrive's business. I will only mention a few of them. In 2002 she was involved in a dispute with Mr Farrington about the quantum of bonus commission to be paid to herself and her group. The dispute was resolved, but not to Ms Manning's complete satisfaction. Another matter was the structure of the business. From the outset Ms Manning pressed for the introduction of a "self-employment" business model. Under this model clients would "belong" to an adviser and the income that was derived from that client would be split between the adviser and Arrive. Ms Manning was of the view that unless this model was instituted it would not be possible to retain quality advisers. The model was often discussed, but nothing was done. Another sticking point was Ms Manning's concern about the addition of AMP "products" to the range of investments that clients were encouraged to make. She did not believe they were suitable for Arrive's clients. This issue was never resolved.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSC/2004/248.html</AustLII>
<text>52 I can now deal with the claims. The claims in contract can be disposed of in short order. The plaintiffs contend that by engaging in certain conduct, especially the conversations with clients, Ms Manning acted in breach of the post-employment restraint. Even if I were to make the assumption, as is required by cl 11, that the purpose of each call was to entice away clients or disrupt their relationship with AMP Services, the claim is hopeless. I need do no more than briefly state my reasons. First, by its terms (which notwithstanding the trust remain unaltered) the restraint operates "after the cessation of [Ms Manning's] employment with AMP." I have already explained that her employment did not come to an end until 16 February. By then the damage had been done. Second, it is a condition of the operation of the clause that Ms Manning work for a competitor of "AMP". It is clear from the opening paragraph of the employment contract that "AMP" is a defined term: it is defined to mean "AMP Services Limited". So far as I know GSJBW is not a competitor of AMP Services. It is of course a competitor of Arrive, but that is a different company. Absent a rectification order it is not possible to read "Arrive" for "AMP". Third, the prohibition imposed by cl 11 is against an approach to any client "of AMP" for the purpose of enticing them away "from AMP". The clients that Ms Manning approached were clients of Arrive and not AMP Services. Finally, if it were possible to extend the restraint to Arrive it would be void for being in breach of the common law doctrine of restraint of trade, the modern formulation of which is stated by Lord McNaughton in Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535, 565 and accepted for Australia in Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353, 376. The unreasonableness of the restraint lies in the fact that it is wider than necessary, covering all Arrive clients, many of whom did not have any connection with Ms Manning: G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568. If the restraint had been limited to, say, clients of the Melbourne office it may have been lawful: see eg IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192 ; Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/71.html</AustLII>
<text>52 I can now deal with the claims. The claims in contract can be disposed of in short order. The plaintiffs contend that by engaging in certain conduct, especially the conversations with clients, Ms Manning acted in breach of the post-employment restraint. Even if I were to make the assumption, as is required by cl 11, that the purpose of each call was to entice away clients or disrupt their relationship with AMP Services, the claim is hopeless. I need do no more than briefly state my reasons. First, by its terms (which notwithstanding the trust remain unaltered) the restraint operates "after the cessation of [Ms Manning's] employment with AMP." I have already explained that her employment did not come to an end until 16 February. By then the damage had been done. Second, it is a condition of the operation of the clause that Ms Manning work for a competitor of "AMP". It is clear from the opening paragraph of the employment contract that "AMP" is a defined term: it is defined to mean "AMP Services Limited". So far as I know GSJBW is not a competitor of AMP Services. It is of course a competitor of Arrive, but that is a different company. Absent a rectification order it is not possible to read "Arrive" for "AMP". Third, the prohibition imposed by cl 11 is against an approach to any client "of AMP" for the purpose of enticing them away "from AMP". The clients that Ms Manning approached were clients of Arrive and not AMP Services. Finally, if it were possible to extend the restraint to Arrive it would be void for being in breach of the common law doctrine of restraint of trade, the modern formulation of which is stated by Lord McNaughton in Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535, 565 and accepted for Australia in Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353, 376. The unreasonableness of the restraint lies in the fact that it is wider than necessary, covering all Arrive clients, many of whom did not have any connection with Ms Manning: G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568. If the restraint had been limited to, say, clients of the Melbourne office it may have been lawful: see eg IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192 ; Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley (1973) 40 DLR (3d) 371</tocase>
<text>55 The next claim is for breach of fiduciary duty. The particular duties which are said to have been breached are the traditional duties owed by an employee to his employer. These were: (a) to act in all her dealings with clients in the best interests of Arrive; (b) to protect Arrive's business; (c) in the course of her employment, not to favour her own interests or the interests of any other party over the interests of Arrive; (d) not to induce, suggest or otherwise entice any client to take business away from Arrive; (e) to act in the course of all her dealings with other Arrive employees in the best interests of Arrive; and (f) not to induce, suggest or otherwise entice any employee of Arrive to leave his or her employment. It should be observed that the duties came to an end when Ms Manning's employment was terminated. Loyalty cannot be demanded of a former employee: Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley (1973) 40 DLR (3d) 371. As Ms Manning was not an employee of Arrive, the fiduciary duties could not arise out of her contract of employment. She was, however, retained by AMP Services to work for Arrive and so the usual conditions which would give rise to the fiduciary obligations claimed here do subsist. For example: Ms Manning was appointed as the head of Arrive's Victorian office and thus undertook to act in its interests; she was given powers which would affect the interests of Arrive; there was a relationship of trust and confidence between herself and Arrive. The absence of a contract of employment does not deny the fiduciary character of the relationship between Arrive and Ms Manning. In the end I do not think that this was seriously contested.

56 Having accepted the existence of the duties for which the plaintiffs contend the question is whether those duties were breached. Much of the conduct which I have found to have been engaged in by Ms Manning was not in breach of duty. For example, informing her group that she was going to leave, telling the group who to contact at GSJBW and even settling some of their terms of employment are not inconsistent with any duty owed to Arrive. Further, merely advising a client that she had resigned would not breach any duty. Nor would informing a client that she was proposing to leave Arrive and that she was going to join or had joined GSJBW.

57 It is true that in some circumstances the use of client contact details to solicit business can amount to a breach of duty if the client contact details are confidential. This is not, however, one of those cases. At the meeting on 21 January Ms Manning handed over her mobile telephone. However she asked that she be permitted to retain the SIM card on which all client details were stored. She explained that she wanted the SIM card to place into her new mobile telephone. The request was granted. Mr Furness removed the SIM card himself and handed it to Ms Manning. It is simply not possible for Arrive now to complain about the use of the information on the SIM card. Clearly Arrive did not regard client contact details as part of its confidential information.

59 The claim that Ms Manning breached her duty not to make use of any business opportunity obtained during the course of her employment must also be rejected. This kind of claim cannot be brought against an employee in Ms Manning's position. It is reserved for those in "top management" such as directors or senior officers: Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley (1973) 40 DLR (3d) 371, 381-382. See also Aberdeen Railway Co v Blaikie Bros (1854) Macq 461, 472.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129</tocase>
<text>66 To accept Arrive's argument is to accept the notion that a fiduciary breach effectively "stops the clock" at the time of breach for the purpose of determining what actual loss was suffered by a party and what the party's ultimate "position" would have been. This line of reasoning was rejected by the House of Lords in Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421. There, Lord Browne-Wilkinson said (at 439):
 
 "Equitable compensation for breach of trust is designed to achieve exactly what the word compensation suggests: to make good a loss in fact suffered by the beneficiaries and which, using hindsight and common sense, can be seen to have been caused by the breach." 


See also Re Dawson [1966] 2 NSWR 211; Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co . (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow &amp; Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The cases make clear that the court must take advantage of the "full benefit of hindsight" to ensure that "the losses made good are only those which, on a common sense view of causation, were caused by the breach": Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163.

69 Though the actual quantification of the claim will take place at a later point, it is necessary to say one final word about the method of calculating that loss. When dealing with equitable compensation a court is often faced with the challenge of placing a monetary value on an elusive loss such as a "loss of opportunity", a loss that defies precise measurement: O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262, 273, adopting Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163. To this end the court is permitted to use somewhat subjective "tools" in arriving at a valuation; tools such as common sense and general notions of justice and fairness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Charles Lo Presti Pty Ltd v Karabalios [2000] NSWSC 395</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2000/395.html</AustLII>
<text>68 The actual loss that Arrive has suffered is not the broad "total loss of clients" as Arrive would have it but the loss of the "value" of keeping those clients between 20 January and 16 February (being the day Ms Manning's employment terminated) together with, perhaps, the loss of the opportunity to take steps in that period to retain the lost clients: Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1, 12-15; Charles Lo Presti Pty Ltd v Karabalios [2000] NSWSC 395 , [31], [49], and [56]. On this latter aspect, however, given the history and the close relationship between Ms Manning and her clients, I am not at this point persuaded that "but for" her breach of fiduciary duty the clients would have remained with Arrive. On the contrary, the evidence so far suggests that regardless of Ms Manning's breach of duty the clients would have remained with Arrive only until her move to GSJBW and they would then have followed her.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Claremont Petroleum NL v Cummings (1992) 110 ALR 239</tocase>
<text>49 The conditions for the application of that rule are explained in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191, 201-202. Opinions have differed as regards whether these conditions can be satisfied when a witness is equally available to both parties. Some judges have said that in such circumstances no inference is available: see eg Claremont Petroleum NL v Cummings (1992) 110 ALR 239. This is not a universally accepted view. For example, in Earle v Castlemaine District Community Hospital [1974] VR 722, 728, a decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria, Little J, cites with approval the following passage from 2 Wigmore on Evidence (3 rd ed, 1940) SS288, 0"> 169- 171 : "The more logical view is that the failure [by both parties] to adduce is open to an inference against both parties, the particular strength of the inference against either depending on the circumstances. To prohibit the inference entirely is to reduce to an arbitrary rule of uniformity that which really depends on the varying significance of facts which cannot be so measured." The judge went on to say that it would be erroneous to lay down any "general rule" that if a witness was available to both parties no inference could be drawn against either and that it must depend on the facts and circumstances of a particular case. This, I think, is the correct view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Dawson, Re [1966] 2 NSWR 211</tocase>
<text>66 To accept Arrive's argument is to accept the notion that a fiduciary breach effectively "stops the clock" at the time of breach for the purpose of determining what actual loss was suffered by a party and what the party's ultimate "position" would have been. This line of reasoning was rejected by the House of Lords in Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421. There, Lord Browne-Wilkinson said (at 439):
 
 "Equitable compensation for breach of trust is designed to achieve exactly what the word compensation suggests: to make good a loss in fact suffered by the beneficiaries and which, using hindsight and common sense, can be seen to have been caused by the breach." 


See also Re Dawson [1966] 2 NSWR 211; Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co . (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow &amp; Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The cases make clear that the court must take advantage of the "full benefit of hindsight" to ensure that "the losses made good are only those which, on a common sense view of causation, were caused by the breach": Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Earle v Castlemaine District Community Hospital [1974] VR 722</tocase>
<text>49 The conditions for the application of that rule are explained in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191, 201-202. Opinions have differed as regards whether these conditions can be satisfied when a witness is equally available to both parties. Some judges have said that in such circumstances no inference is available: see eg Claremont Petroleum NL v Cummings (1992) 110 ALR 239. This is not a universally accepted view. For example, in Earle v Castlemaine District Community Hospital [1974] VR 722, 728, a decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria, Little J, cites with approval the following passage from 2 Wigmore on Evidence (3 rd ed, 1940) SS288, 0"> 169- 171 : "The more logical view is that the failure [by both parties] to adduce is open to an inference against both parties, the particular strength of the inference against either depending on the circumstances. To prohibit the inference entirely is to reduce to an arbitrary rule of uniformity that which really depends on the varying significance of facts which cannot be so measured." The judge went on to say that it would be erroneous to lay down any "general rule" that if a witness was available to both parties no inference could be drawn against either and that it must depend on the facts and circumstances of a particular case. This, I think, is the correct view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Enoch and Zaretzkey, Bock &amp; Co's Arbitration [1910] 1 KB 327</tocase>
<text>48 If it were possible, I would have called the clients myself in order to get to the truth of the matter. After all, the principal object of a court proceeding is to find the truth and arrive at the right result. Or at least that should be the object. Unfortunately, while the adversary system is touted as "the greatest legal engine ever invented for the discovery of truth" (5 Wigmore on Evidence (3 rd ed, 1940) SS1367) it often falls well short of the mark. The problem is that the system leaves it to the parties to shape the issues to be litigated and to call the evidence they feel will resolve those issues. And in a civil case it is not permissible for the judge to go behind the parties to call witnesses: Enoch and Zaretzkey, Bock &amp; Co's Arbitration [1910] 1 KB 327. Perhaps this will one day be reformed. But until that occurs all a judge is able to do when faced with a refusal by a party to call relevant evidence is, if appropriate, to apply the rule in Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Foran v Wight [1989] HCA 51 ; (1989) 168 CLR 385</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/51.html</AustLII>
<text>45 During the course of argument Ms Manning attempted to rely on two other incidents as a repudiation of the contract which justified her purported termination of it on 21 January. The first is steps taken around 23 January to revoke Ms Manning's status under the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) as an Authorised Representative of Arrive and the second is the instruction on 4 February to terminate Ms Manning's fortnightly salary payments. This conduct is not repudiatory. Even if it were, it would not assist Ms Manning. It is a well established rule of contract law that if a party gives an incorrect reason for terminating a contract this does not prevent him from later asserting a good reason, whether or not he was aware of the reason when he brought the contract to an end: Shepherd v Felt and Textiles of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 21 ; (1931) 45 CLR 359, 377-378. The rule is so well established it needs no elaboration. But the rule only applies if the unstated (and sometimes unknown) ground was available at the time the contract was brought to an end. If the repudiatory conduct occurs later it cannot be relied upon retrospectively but only as a trigger for a later acceptance, and there was none. Further, by the time the second of the events had occurred Ms Manning had begun to work for GSJBW although still an employee of AMP Services. For example, she attended GSJBW's office on most working days, she sat in on at least one interview with a client (and probably gave advice to the client during the course of the interview), she helped draft letters to clients of Arrive to assist them to transfer their business to GSJBW and she presented a paper at an in-house conference. This put her in breach of her employment contract (a breach not pleaded) and disentitled her from terminating the contract for repudiation: Foran v Wight [1989] HCA 51 ; (1989) 168 CLR 385.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568</tocase>
<text>52 I can now deal with the claims. The claims in contract can be disposed of in short order. The plaintiffs contend that by engaging in certain conduct, especially the conversations with clients, Ms Manning acted in breach of the post-employment restraint. Even if I were to make the assumption, as is required by cl 11, that the purpose of each call was to entice away clients or disrupt their relationship with AMP Services, the claim is hopeless. I need do no more than briefly state my reasons. First, by its terms (which notwithstanding the trust remain unaltered) the restraint operates "after the cessation of [Ms Manning's] employment with AMP." I have already explained that her employment did not come to an end until 16 February. By then the damage had been done. Second, it is a condition of the operation of the clause that Ms Manning work for a competitor of "AMP". It is clear from the opening paragraph of the employment contract that "AMP" is a defined term: it is defined to mean "AMP Services Limited". So far as I know GSJBW is not a competitor of AMP Services. It is of course a competitor of Arrive, but that is a different company. Absent a rectification order it is not possible to read "Arrive" for "AMP". Third, the prohibition imposed by cl 11 is against an approach to any client "of AMP" for the purpose of enticing them away "from AMP". The clients that Ms Manning approached were clients of Arrive and not AMP Services. Finally, if it were possible to extend the restraint to Arrive it would be void for being in breach of the common law doctrine of restraint of trade, the modern formulation of which is stated by Lord McNaughton in Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535, 565 and accepted for Australia in Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353, 376. The unreasonableness of the restraint lies in the fact that it is wider than necessary, covering all Arrive clients, many of whom did not have any connection with Ms Manning: G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568. If the restraint had been limited to, say, clients of the Melbourne office it may have been lawful: see eg IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192 ; Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSC/2003/192.html</AustLII>
<text>52 I can now deal with the claims. The claims in contract can be disposed of in short order. The plaintiffs contend that by engaging in certain conduct, especially the conversations with clients, Ms Manning acted in breach of the post-employment restraint. Even if I were to make the assumption, as is required by cl 11, that the purpose of each call was to entice away clients or disrupt their relationship with AMP Services, the claim is hopeless. I need do no more than briefly state my reasons. First, by its terms (which notwithstanding the trust remain unaltered) the restraint operates "after the cessation of [Ms Manning's] employment with AMP." I have already explained that her employment did not come to an end until 16 February. By then the damage had been done. Second, it is a condition of the operation of the clause that Ms Manning work for a competitor of "AMP". It is clear from the opening paragraph of the employment contract that "AMP" is a defined term: it is defined to mean "AMP Services Limited". So far as I know GSJBW is not a competitor of AMP Services. It is of course a competitor of Arrive, but that is a different company. Absent a rectification order it is not possible to read "Arrive" for "AMP". Third, the prohibition imposed by cl 11 is against an approach to any client "of AMP" for the purpose of enticing them away "from AMP". The clients that Ms Manning approached were clients of Arrive and not AMP Services. Finally, if it were possible to extend the restraint to Arrive it would be void for being in breach of the common law doctrine of restraint of trade, the modern formulation of which is stated by Lord McNaughton in Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535, 565 and accepted for Australia in Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353, 376. The unreasonableness of the restraint lies in the fact that it is wider than necessary, covering all Arrive clients, many of whom did not have any connection with Ms Manning: G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568. If the restraint had been limited to, say, clients of the Melbourne office it may have been lawful: see eg IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192 ; Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Industrial Equity Limited v Blackburn [1977] HCA 59 ; (1977) 137 CLR 567</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/59.html</AustLII>
<text>54 I can also dispose of the statutory claims without much ado. The amended points of claim assert that the duties imposed by ss 182 and 183 are owed to AMP Services. This is correct. In Walker v Winborne [1976] HCA 7 ; (1976) 137 CLR 1, 6-7, Mason J (as he then was) pointed out that because each company in a group is a "separate and independent legal entity" the officer of a company owes his duties to that company alone. See also Industrial Equity Limited v Blackburn [1977] HCA 59 ; (1977) 137 CLR 567. Here it is said that Ms Manning made "(1) improper use of her position to (a) gain an advantage for herself or someone else; or (b) cause detriment to [AMP Services]; (2) improper use of confidential information [vis name, contact details or financial position of clients] obtained in the course of her employment to (a) gain an advantage for herself or someone else; or (b) cause detriment to [AMP Services]." There is no evidence to support the first allegation and, if it matters, none of the conduct about which complaint is made (even if proven) is conduct engaged in by Ms Manning in her "position" with AMP Services. As to the second allegation, the evidence shows that the information (whether confidential or not) was not the property of Arrive but AMP Services. Sections 182 and 183 do not provide a cause of action for the misuse of confidential information which belongs to a related company and causes damage to the related company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/8.html</AustLII>
<text>48 If it were possible, I would have called the clients myself in order to get to the truth of the matter. After all, the principal object of a court proceeding is to find the truth and arrive at the right result. Or at least that should be the object. Unfortunately, while the adversary system is touted as "the greatest legal engine ever invented for the discovery of truth" (5 Wigmore on Evidence (3 rd ed, 1940) SS1367) it often falls well short of the mark. The problem is that the system leaves it to the parties to shape the issues to be litigated and to call the evidence they feel will resolve those issues. And in a civil case it is not permissible for the judge to go behind the parties to call witnesses: Enoch and Zaretzkey, Bock &amp; Co's Arbitration [1910] 1 KB 327. Perhaps this will one day be reformed. But until that occurs all a judge is able to do when faced with a refusal by a party to call relevant evidence is, if appropriate, to apply the rule in Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Nocton v Lord Ashburton [1914] AC 932</tocase>
<text>64 Arrive is entitled to compensation for Ms Manning's breach of duty. In equity, the object of compensation is to restore the person who has suffered loss to the position in which they would have been if there had been no breach of the equitable obligation: Nocton v Lord Ashburton [1914] AC 932; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The critical question to determine is in what position would Arrive have been had Ms Manning not breached her equitable obligation -- that is to say, what actual loss was suffered by Arrive due to the breach?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535</tocase>
<text>52 I can now deal with the claims. The claims in contract can be disposed of in short order. The plaintiffs contend that by engaging in certain conduct, especially the conversations with clients, Ms Manning acted in breach of the post-employment restraint. Even if I were to make the assumption, as is required by cl 11, that the purpose of each call was to entice away clients or disrupt their relationship with AMP Services, the claim is hopeless. I need do no more than briefly state my reasons. First, by its terms (which notwithstanding the trust remain unaltered) the restraint operates "after the cessation of [Ms Manning's] employment with AMP." I have already explained that her employment did not come to an end until 16 February. By then the damage had been done. Second, it is a condition of the operation of the clause that Ms Manning work for a competitor of "AMP". It is clear from the opening paragraph of the employment contract that "AMP" is a defined term: it is defined to mean "AMP Services Limited". So far as I know GSJBW is not a competitor of AMP Services. It is of course a competitor of Arrive, but that is a different company. Absent a rectification order it is not possible to read "Arrive" for "AMP". Third, the prohibition imposed by cl 11 is against an approach to any client "of AMP" for the purpose of enticing them away "from AMP". The clients that Ms Manning approached were clients of Arrive and not AMP Services. Finally, if it were possible to extend the restraint to Arrive it would be void for being in breach of the common law doctrine of restraint of trade, the modern formulation of which is stated by Lord McNaughton in Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535, 565 and accepted for Australia in Buckley v Tutty [1971] HCA 71 ; (1971) 125 CLR 353, 376. The unreasonableness of the restraint lies in the fact that it is wider than necessary, covering all Arrive clients, many of whom did not have any connection with Ms Manning: G W Ploughman &amp; Son Ltd v Ash [1964] 1 WLR 568. If the restraint had been limited to, say, clients of the Melbourne office it may have been lawful: see eg IF Asia Pacific Pty Ltd Galbally [2003] VSC 192 ; Brilliant Lighting (Aust) Pty Ltd v Baillieu [2004] VSC 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262</tocase>
<text>64 Arrive is entitled to compensation for Ms Manning's breach of duty. In equity, the object of compensation is to restore the person who has suffered loss to the position in which they would have been if there had been no breach of the equitable obligation: Nocton v Lord Ashburton [1914] AC 932; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The critical question to determine is in what position would Arrive have been had Ms Manning not breached her equitable obligation -- that is to say, what actual loss was suffered by Arrive due to the breach?

66 To accept Arrive's argument is to accept the notion that a fiduciary breach effectively "stops the clock" at the time of breach for the purpose of determining what actual loss was suffered by a party and what the party's ultimate "position" would have been. This line of reasoning was rejected by the House of Lords in Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421. There, Lord Browne-Wilkinson said (at 439):
 
 "Equitable compensation for breach of trust is designed to achieve exactly what the word compensation suggests: to make good a loss in fact suffered by the beneficiaries and which, using hindsight and common sense, can be seen to have been caused by the breach." 


See also Re Dawson [1966] 2 NSWR 211; Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co . (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow &amp; Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The cases make clear that the court must take advantage of the "full benefit of hindsight" to ensure that "the losses made good are only those which, on a common sense view of causation, were caused by the breach": Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163.

69 Though the actual quantification of the claim will take place at a later point, it is necessary to say one final word about the method of calculating that loss. When dealing with equitable compensation a court is often faced with the challenge of placing a monetary value on an elusive loss such as a "loss of opportunity", a loss that defies precise measurement: O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262, 273, adopting Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163. To this end the court is permitted to use somewhat subjective "tools" in arriving at a valuation; tools such as common sense and general notions of justice and fairness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191</tocase>
<text>49 The conditions for the application of that rule are explained in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191, 201-202. Opinions have differed as regards whether these conditions can be satisfied when a witness is equally available to both parties. Some judges have said that in such circumstances no inference is available: see eg Claremont Petroleum NL v Cummings (1992) 110 ALR 239. This is not a universally accepted view. For example, in Earle v Castlemaine District Community Hospital [1974] VR 722, 728, a decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria, Little J, cites with approval the following passage from 2 Wigmore on Evidence (3 rd ed, 1940) SS288, 0"> 169- 171 : "The more logical view is that the failure [by both parties] to adduce is open to an inference against both parties, the particular strength of the inference against either depending on the circumstances. To prohibit the inference entirely is to reduce to an arbitrary rule of uniformity that which really depends on the varying significance of facts which cannot be so measured." The judge went on to say that it would be erroneous to lay down any "general rule" that if a witness was available to both parties no inference could be drawn against either and that it must depend on the facts and circumstances of a particular case. This, I think, is the correct view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Shepherd v Felt and Textiles of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 21 ; (1931) 45 CLR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1931/21.html</AustLII>
<text>45 During the course of argument Ms Manning attempted to rely on two other incidents as a repudiation of the contract which justified her purported termination of it on 21 January. The first is steps taken around 23 January to revoke Ms Manning's status under the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) as an Authorised Representative of Arrive and the second is the instruction on 4 February to terminate Ms Manning's fortnightly salary payments. This conduct is not repudiatory. Even if it were, it would not assist Ms Manning. It is a well established rule of contract law that if a party gives an incorrect reason for terminating a contract this does not prevent him from later asserting a good reason, whether or not he was aware of the reason when he brought the contract to an end: Shepherd v Felt and Textiles of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 21 ; (1931) 45 CLR 359, 377-378. The rule is so well established it needs no elaboration. But the rule only applies if the unstated (and sometimes unknown) ground was available at the time the contract was brought to an end. If the repudiatory conduct occurs later it cannot be relied upon retrospectively but only as a trigger for a later acceptance, and there was none. Further, by the time the second of the events had occurred Ms Manning had begun to work for GSJBW although still an employee of AMP Services. For example, she attended GSJBW's office on most working days, she sat in on at least one interview with a client (and probably gave advice to the client during the course of the interview), she helped draft letters to clients of Arrive to assist them to transfer their business to GSJBW and she presented a paper at an in-house conference. This put her in breach of her employment contract (a breach not pleaded) and disentitled her from terminating the contract for repudiation: Foran v Wight [1989] HCA 51 ; (1989) 168 CLR 385.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1</tocase>
<text>64 Arrive is entitled to compensation for Ms Manning's breach of duty. In equity, the object of compensation is to restore the person who has suffered loss to the position in which they would have been if there had been no breach of the equitable obligation: Nocton v Lord Ashburton [1914] AC 932; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The critical question to determine is in what position would Arrive have been had Ms Manning not breached her equitable obligation -- that is to say, what actual loss was suffered by Arrive due to the breach?

66 To accept Arrive's argument is to accept the notion that a fiduciary breach effectively "stops the clock" at the time of breach for the purpose of determining what actual loss was suffered by a party and what the party's ultimate "position" would have been. This line of reasoning was rejected by the House of Lords in Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421. There, Lord Browne-Wilkinson said (at 439):
 
 "Equitable compensation for breach of trust is designed to achieve exactly what the word compensation suggests: to make good a loss in fact suffered by the beneficiaries and which, using hindsight and common sense, can be seen to have been caused by the breach." 


See also Re Dawson [1966] 2 NSWR 211; Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co . (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow &amp; Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The cases make clear that the court must take advantage of the "full benefit of hindsight" to ensure that "the losses made good are only those which, on a common sense view of causation, were caused by the breach": Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163.

68 The actual loss that Arrive has suffered is not the broad "total loss of clients" as Arrive would have it but the loss of the "value" of keeping those clients between 20 January and 16 February (being the day Ms Manning's employment terminated) together with, perhaps, the loss of the opportunity to take steps in that period to retain the lost clients: Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow and Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1, 12-15; Charles Lo Presti Pty Ltd v Karabalios [2000] NSWSC 395 , [31], [49], and [56]. On this latter aspect, however, given the history and the close relationship between Ms Manning and her clients, I am not at this point persuaded that "but for" her breach of fiduciary duty the clients would have remained with Arrive. On the contrary, the evidence so far suggests that regardless of Ms Manning's breach of duty the clients would have remained with Arrive only until her move to GSJBW and they would then have followed her.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421</tocase>
<text>66 To accept Arrive's argument is to accept the notion that a fiduciary breach effectively "stops the clock" at the time of breach for the purpose of determining what actual loss was suffered by a party and what the party's ultimate "position" would have been. This line of reasoning was rejected by the House of Lords in Target Holdings Ltd v Redferns (a firm) [1996] 1 AC 421. There, Lord Browne-Wilkinson said (at 439):
 
 "Equitable compensation for breach of trust is designed to achieve exactly what the word compensation suggests: to make good a loss in fact suffered by the beneficiaries and which, using hindsight and common sense, can be seen to have been caused by the breach." 


See also Re Dawson [1966] 2 NSWR 211; Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co . (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129; O'Halloran v RT Thomas &amp; Family Pty Ltd (1998) 45 NSWLR 262; Southern Real Estate Pty Ltd v Dellow &amp; Arnold (2003) 87 SASR 1. The cases make clear that the court must take advantage of the "full benefit of hindsight" to ensure that "the losses made good are only those which, on a common sense view of causation, were caused by the breach": Canson Enterprises Ltd v Boughton &amp; Co. (1991) 85 DLR (4th) 129, 163.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Walker v Winborne [1976] HCA 7 ; (1976) 137 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/7.html</AustLII>
<text>54 I can also dispose of the statutory claims without much ado. The amended points of claim assert that the duties imposed by ss 182 and 183 are owed to AMP Services. This is correct. In Walker v Winborne [1976] HCA 7 ; (1976) 137 CLR 1, 6-7, Mason J (as he then was) pointed out that because each company in a group is a "separate and independent legal entity" the officer of a company owes his duties to that company alone. See also Industrial Equity Limited v Blackburn [1977] HCA 59 ; (1977) 137 CLR 567. Here it is said that Ms Manning made "(1) improper use of her position to (a) gain an advantage for herself or someone else; or (b) cause detriment to [AMP Services]; (2) improper use of confidential information [vis name, contact details or financial position of clients] obtained in the course of her employment to (a) gain an advantage for herself or someone else; or (b) cause detriment to [AMP Services]." There is no evidence to support the first allegation and, if it matters, none of the conduct about which complaint is made (even if proven) is conduct engaged in by Ms Manning in her "position" with AMP Services. As to the second allegation, the evidence shows that the information (whether confidential or not) was not the property of Arrive but AMP Services. Sections 182 and 183 do not provide a cause of action for the misuse of confidential information which belongs to a related company and causes damage to the related company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>William Hill Organisation Ltd v Tucker [1999] ICR 291</tocase>
<text>43 Ms Manning accepts (correctly in my opinion) that upon giving notice she could be instructed to stay away from work during the notice period if there was an express term to that effect. On the other hand she says (also correctly in my opinion) that if there was no such term then AMP Services was obliged to provide work for Ms Manning because part of her remuneration was based on performance: see eg William Hill Organisation Ltd v Tucker [1999] ICR 291.

44 In this case the employment contract permitted the employer, AMP Services, to require Ms Manning not to attend work for some or all of the notice period while continuing to pay her wages. I have already set out cl 7 of the employment contract. It is convenient to repeat para 3 of that clause which provides: "AMP may elect to pay you salary in lieu of notice or require you to work during part or all of your notice period." What Ms Manning was told at the meeting on 20 January amounted to the exercise of the option conferred by that clause. The instruction was repeated at the meeting on 21 January, as well as in AMP Service's letters of 23 and 27 January to Ms Manning's solicitors. The instruction was not a repudiation of the employment contract. It was the exercise of a right conferred by the contract.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>