<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGGS v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 224 (1 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/224.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Applicant S1746 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1591</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1591.html</AustLII>
<text>3 On 25 August 2004 the Minister's solicitor filed an application for summary dismissal which was made returnable on 1 September 2004. However, the applicant on 31 August 2004 filed a notice of discontinuance. Undeterred, on 24 September 2004 he made an application to this court for an extension of time to file and serve a notice of appeal against Einfeld J's decision. On 9 December 2004, Bennett J dismissed that application saying that she was of the view that the applicant had no prospects of success in an appeal based on a new argument put forward, if it were a new argument, and had not demonstrated any special reasons for the exercise of a discretion to extend the time for filing a notice of appeal: Applicant S1746 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1591 [36].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Bienstein v Bienstein [2003] HCA 7 ; (2003) 195 ALR 225 at 231</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/7.html</AustLII>
<text>15 I do not have to form a final view about those matters because my function is to consider the application as an interlocutory application in which leave to appeal must be obtained. In Bienstein v Bienstein [2003] HCA 7 ; (2003) 195 ALR 225 at 231 it was said at paragraph [29]:
 
 'An applicant for leave must establish that the decision in question is attendant with sufficient doubt to warrant the grant of leave. He must also show that substantial injustice will result from refusal of leave to appeal.'

16 I am of the opinion that there is no sufficient doubt to warrant the grant of leave on the basis of the material in the application for leave to appeal or the applicant's affidavit of 12 December 2005, the draft notice of appeal, or the matters referred to in the judgment below. For those reasons the application is dismissed.

17 The Minister has applied for an order for costs fixed in the sum of $800. I note that in the court below, his Honour made an order that the applicant pay the costs on an indemnity basis. I am of the opinion that it is an appropriate case in which to make an order in the terms sought. 
 

 I certify that the preceding seventeen (17) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares. 


Associate:

Dated: 15 March 2006


 Applicant: In Person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: A Markus 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 1 March 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 1 March 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/224.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Walton v Gardiner [1992] HCA 12 ; (1993) 177 CLR 378</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/12.html</AustLII>
<text>8 His Honour concluded that the substantive application had no merit at all. I am of opinion that that is an unimpeachably correct finding. In Walton v Gardiner [1992] HCA 12 ; (1993) 177 CLR 378 at 392-393 Mason CJ, Deane and Dawson JJ said:
 
 'The inherent jurisdiction of a superior court to stay its proceedings on grounds of abuse of process extends to all those categories of cases in which the processes and procedures of the court, which exist to administer justice with fairness and impartiality, may be converted into instruments of injustice or unfairness. Thus, it has long been established that, regardless of the propriety of the purpose of the person responsible for their institution and maintenance, proceedings will constitute an abuse of process if they can be clearly seen to be foredoomed to fail (see e.g. Metropolitan Bank v Pooley (1885) 10 App Cas 210 at pp 220-221; General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways ( NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at pp 128-130). Again, proceedings within the jurisdiction of a court will be unjustifiably oppressive and vexatious of an objecting defendant, and will constitute an abuse of process, if that court is, in all the circumstances of the particular case, a clearly inappropriate forum to entertain them (see, generally, Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538). Yet again, proceedings before a court should be stayed as an abuse of process if, notwithstanding that the circumstances do not give rise to an estoppel, their continuance would be unjustifiably vexatious and oppressive for the reason that it is sought to litigate anew a case which has already been disposed of by earlier proceedings (see e.g. Reichel v Magrath (1889) 14 App Cas 665 at p 668; Connelly v Director of Public Prosecutions [1964] AC 1254 at pp 1361-1362). The jurisdiction of a superior court in such a case was correctly described by Lord Diplock in Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police ([1982] AC 529 at p 536) as the "the inherent power which any court of justice must possess to prevent misuse of its procedure in a way which, although not inconsistent with the literal application of its procedural rules, would nevertheless be manifestly unfair to a party to litigation before it, or would otherwise bring the administration of justice into disrepute among right-thinking people".'

9 The basis on which the applicant sought leave to appeal is set out in his affidavit sworn 12 December 2005 and the draft notice of appeal of the same date. Before I embarked on the hearing of this matter I had the matter called outside the court. The applicant was given notice in a letter from the court dated 23 February 2006 that the matter would be heard today. Mr Markus who appears for the Minister, informed me that he had received a copy of that letter in his office on 24 February. Mr Markus said no communication had been received from the applicant in relation to today's hearing and there is no record of the court of any such communication.

10 The notice of appeal asserts that the trial Judge in the Federal Magistrates Court erred in holding that the delegate of the Minister had not given a biased decision based or that the original decision was not full of unreasonable and illogical applications in the delegate's mind.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Wilson v Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs [1996] HCA 18 ; (1996) 189 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/18.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Zubair v Minister [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344 at 352-354 [28] - [32] a Full Court of this Court held that any error affecting the decision of a delegate, including one which may go to jurisdiction, could not be relied on to challenge the subsequent decision on a merits review before the Tribunal. That is because the function of the Tribunal on review is to arrive at the correct and preferable decision: see Wilson v Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs [1996] HCA 18 ; (1996) 189 CLR 1 at 18. Secondly, by electing to challenge the adverse decision by way of merits review an applicant invites the reviewer to apply to him or her a fair procedure in arriving at that correct and preferable decision. Therefore, one ignores the alleged errors attending the making of the original decision: see too: Twist v Randwick Municipal Council [1976] HCA 58 ; (1976) 136 CLR 106 at 116.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Twist v Randwick Municipal Council [1976] HCA 58 ; (1976) 136 CLR 106</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/58.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Zubair v Minister [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344 at 352-354 [28] - [32] a Full Court of this Court held that any error affecting the decision of a delegate, including one which may go to jurisdiction, could not be relied on to challenge the subsequent decision on a merits review before the Tribunal. That is because the function of the Tribunal on review is to arrive at the correct and preferable decision: see Wilson v Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs [1996] HCA 18 ; (1996) 189 CLR 1 at 18. Secondly, by electing to challenge the adverse decision by way of merits review an applicant invites the reviewer to apply to him or her a fair procedure in arriving at that correct and preferable decision. Therefore, one ignores the alleged errors attending the making of the original decision: see too: Twist v Randwick Municipal Council [1976] HCA 58 ; (1976) 136 CLR 106 at 116.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Zubair v Minister [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/248.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Zubair v Minister [2004] FCAFC 248 ; (2004) 139 FCR 344 at 352-354 [28] - [32] a Full Court of this Court held that any error affecting the decision of a delegate, including one which may go to jurisdiction, could not be relied on to challenge the subsequent decision on a merits review before the Tribunal. That is because the function of the Tribunal on review is to arrive at the correct and preferable decision: see Wilson v Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs [1996] HCA 18 ; (1996) 189 CLR 1 at 18. Secondly, by electing to challenge the adverse decision by way of merits review an applicant invites the reviewer to apply to him or her a fair procedure in arriving at that correct and preferable decision. Therefore, one ignores the alleged errors attending the making of the original decision: see too: Twist v Randwick Municipal Council [1976] HCA 58 ; (1976) 136 CLR 106 at 116.

14 Whether or not Zubair would otherwise apply to the present applicant, one has only to consider the persistent litigation brought by the applicant challenging the rejection of his claims by the Tribunal to see that his Honour was justified in coming to the conclusion that the proceedings below ought be dismissed.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>