<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231 (16 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/231.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 63 ALD 43</tocase>
<text>23 This Court has power to allow grounds to be argued on appeal that were not argued before the trial judge. The principles governing the exercise of this power have been considered by the Full Court on several occasions, and those principles are well settled: see H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 63 ALD 43 (Branson, Katz and Marshall JJ) (" H "); and VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168 (North, Merkel and Weinberg JJ) (" VAAC ").</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/74.html</AustLII>
<text>23 This Court has power to allow grounds to be argued on appeal that were not argued before the trial judge. The principles governing the exercise of this power have been considered by the Full Court on several occasions, and those principles are well settled: see H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2001) 63 ALD 43 (Branson, Katz and Marshall JJ) (" H "); and VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168 (North, Merkel and Weinberg JJ) (" VAAC ").

25 In VAAC at 177 [26], the Full Court identified factors which need to be considered in applying these principles: 
 "It is therefore necessary to consider whether it is expedient in the interests of justice to allow the new ground to be argued and determined. In the present case, the interests of justice require reference to a number of considerations, namely, the appellant's prospects of success on the appeal on the new argument, the explanation given by the appellant for failing to raise the argument before the primary judge, the prejudice to the respondent in allowing the appellant to raise the new argument, the potentially serious consequences to the appellant if leave to amend is refused, and the integrity of the appellate process."

26 The Full Court in VAAC also observed that determining the appellant's prospects of success on the appeal requires consideration of the merits of the proposed new ground. In this case, the convenient course was to hear full argument on the appeal, including the proposed new ground of appeal, without ruling on the application for leave. In taking this course I took the following matters into account: a determination of the leave application would require consideration of the merits of the new ground; it was common ground between the appellant and the first respondent that if the proposed new ground of appeal had been raised as a ground of review before Hartnett FM, it would not have involved the calling of additional evidence; the first respondent did not suggest that it would be prejudiced if leave were granted to add the proposed new ground of appeal; and the duration of the appeal would not be significantly affected by allowing the proposed new ground to be fully argued before ruling on the application for leave to amend. However, I would not wish it to be thought that the same course will always be followed. There may be occasions when it is more appropriate or convenient to rule on an application for leave to amend a notice of appeal before embarking on the substance of the appeal itself.

36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/24.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Counsel for the appellant submitted that their failure to raise the s 424A ground before the Federal Magistrates Court is explained by the fact that the decision of the High Court in SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 (" SAAP ") was handed down after Hartnett FM dismissed the appellant's application. In SAAP , the trial judge (Mansfield J) had held that, while there had been a failure to comply with s 424A , that failure had not deprived the appellant in that case of any opportunity to learn of material adverse to her claim or comment on it. In those circumstances, his Honour declined to grant relief: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 577. The Full Court (Heerey, Moore and Kiefel JJ) dismissed the initial appeal: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 411. However, the High Court took a different view and allowed the appeal.

31 In oral submissions in this Court, counsel for the appellant said that even if it be the case that the s 424A ground should have been raised before the Tribunal, its significance was brought into much sharper focus by the High Court's decision in SAAP . There is some force in this submission, particularly where there was a risk that any s 424A ground would fail at the same hurdle as that which proved decisive before Mansfield J and the Full Court in SAAP .

32 In all the circumstances, I consider that it is expedient in the interests of justice to grant leave to the appellant to amend the notice of appeal so as to raise the new ground. In reaching this conclusion, I have taken into account the potentially serious consequences to the appellant if leave to amend were to be refused and the lack of any prejudice to the respondents in allowing the appellant to raise the new argument. I also consider that the failure of the appellant to raise the argument before the Tribunal has been adequately explained. As to the prospects of success of the new ground, I consider that the ground is sufficiently arguable to warrant the grant of leave to amend.

33 Section 424A provides: 
 
 
 "(1) Subject to subsection (3), the Tribunal must: 
 
 
 (a) give to the applicant, in the way that the Tribunal considers appropriate in the circumstances, particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the decision that is under review; and 
 (b) ensure, as far as is reasonably practicable, that the applicant understands why it is relevant to the review; and 
 (c) invite the applicant to comment on it. 
 
 
 
 
 (2) The information and invitation must be given to the applicant: 
 
 
 (a) except where paragraph (b) applies--by one of the methods specified in section 441A; or 
 (b) if the applicant is in immigration detention--by a method prescribed for the purposes of giving documents to such a person. 
 
 
 
 
 (3) This section does not apply to information: 
 
 
 (a) that is not specifically about the applicant or another person and is just about a class of persons of which the applicant or other person is a member; or 
 (b) that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application; or 
 (c) that is non-disclosable information."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 577</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/577.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Counsel for the appellant submitted that their failure to raise the s 424A ground before the Federal Magistrates Court is explained by the fact that the decision of the High Court in SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 (" SAAP ") was handed down after Hartnett FM dismissed the appellant's application. In SAAP , the trial judge (Mansfield J) had held that, while there had been a failure to comply with s 424A , that failure had not deprived the appellant in that case of any opportunity to learn of material adverse to her claim or comment on it. In those circumstances, his Honour declined to grant relief: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 577. The Full Court (Heerey, Moore and Kiefel JJ) dismissed the initial appeal: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 411. However, the High Court took a different view and allowed the appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 411</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/411.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Counsel for the appellant submitted that their failure to raise the s 424A ground before the Federal Magistrates Court is explained by the fact that the decision of the High Court in SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 (" SAAP ") was handed down after Hartnett FM dismissed the appellant's application. In SAAP , the trial judge (Mansfield J) had held that, while there had been a failure to comply with s 424A , that failure had not deprived the appellant in that case of any opportunity to learn of material adverse to her claim or comment on it. In those circumstances, his Honour declined to grant relief: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 577. The Full Court (Heerey, Moore and Kiefel JJ) dismissed the initial appeal: see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 411. However, the High Court took a different view and allowed the appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471</tocase>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

40 In VAF , Finn and Stone JJ at 478 [33] said that, in applying s 424A, it is necessary to differentiate between the integral and inessential parts for the reasons for the Tribunal's decision. Ultimately, the test which Finn and Stone JJ applied in VAF (at 481 [41]) was whether the information in question was so integral to the reasoning process rejecting the appellant's claim as to require, as a matter of fairness, that the appellant be told that information and why it was relevant to the review.

44 In SZECF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1200 , the appeal arose from a Tribunal decision which had found that the applicant for a protection visa had fabricated his claim and various documents submitted in support of it. In reaching this conclusion, the Tribunal relied upon the fact that the applicant's written statement to the Department did not mention the claims of persecution that the Tribunal ultimately rejected. One of the issues that arose on the appeal to this Court was whether s 424A applied to the information contained in the applicant's original statement to the Department. After referring to VAF, Paul and WAGP , Allsop J at [26] and [34] held that it did: 
 "I have extracted earlier the places in the Tribunal's reasons where the prior statement is used. Having read the whole of the reasons of the Tribunal, it is clear that the comprehensive disbelief of the appellant and the finding that he had brought forward fraudulent documentation was largely, if not wholly, a product of the importance placed by the Tribunal on the form and content of his first statement. In short, the Tribunal found that if what he was saying were true, it would have been referred to earlier. The fact that it was not, demonstrated the falsity of his evidence to the Tribunal. 
 
 ... 
 
 In my view, here, the knowledge of the Tribunal of the content of the earlier statement, including the limits of its contents can be seen to be a part of the reason for the decision because its form and content were instrumental in the Tribunal reaching a conclusion that the oral evidence of the appellant was false and the documents he was propounding were fraudulent." 
 

In Allsop J's view, the case before him involved something more than what Finn and Stone JJ in VAF at 476-477 [24] had called 'identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity' in evidence given to the Tribunal, or what the Full Court in WAGP had described as a failure to mention something in evidence given to the Tribunal.

48 Moore J adopted and applied what had been said by Finn and Stone JJ in VAF : see SZEEU at [22] [25]. In his Honour's view, the flight information was not of sufficient significance to warrant a conclusion that it formed part of the Tribunal's reasons for affirming the decision of the Minister's delegate. This was because it was a subsidiary and peripheral reason which the Tribunal relied upon to reject the applicant's claim that charges were outstanding against him in Bangladesh. Other factors referred to by the Tribunal were of greater significance. As for the similar claims information, Moore J noted that the Tribunal only referred to this information after analysing and rejecting the applicant's central claims. In his Honour's view, the Tribunal therefore rejected the central claims of the appellant by a process of reasoning not dependent on the similar claims information: see SZEEU at [27]-[28].

50 Allsop J held that the test which had been advanced in Paul and VAF had to be reconsidered in the light of the High Court's decision in SAAP . His Honour said that, to the extent that Paul and VAF both include notions of fairness derived from the rules of procedural fairness as part of the analysis of whether something is part of the reason for affirming the decision, those decisions are in conflict with the approach of the majority of the High Court in SAAP . In consequence, his Honour set out what he thought that the approach to be adopted in the future should be at [215]:
 "In my view, in the light of SAAP , in circumstances where one is faced with a decision of the Tribunal with reasons and the complaint is a contravention of s 424A(1), the question to ask, by reference to the reasons of the Tribunal in the context in which one find them (as revealing what would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the decision immediately prior to the making of the decision), is whether the information in question was a part (that is any part) of the reason for affirming the decision. To the extent that the reasons of the relevant majorities in Paul and VAF can be seen to require that the relevant part of the reason have a stature or importance, or be of a character which would make it unfair not to invoke the procedures of s 424A, I think SAAP requires that such an approach be rejected. It is only necessary that the information be a part of the reason." 
 

The application of these principles by the majority in SZEEU necessarily led to the conclusion that both the flight information and the similar claims information fell squarely within s 424A. It was sufficient that both pieces of information were referred to and relied upon by the Tribunal as relevant and operative considerations, whether or not they could be described as a subsidiary or a minor part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision.

62 In applying s 424A , it is necessary to focus on matters that, viewed prospectively, would be the reason or a part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision, or viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's actual decision, can be seen to be the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. At the outset of the Tribunal hearing and prior to the appellant's evidence to the Tribunal, I doubt that the Keskin information could be characterised as information that the Tribunal then considered, or might consider, would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the delegate's decision. By itself, the Keskin information was not adverse to the appellant. Numerous cases suggest that s 424A is concerned with information that is adverse to the interests of the visa applicant: see SAAP per McHugh J at 175 [50]; VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAJR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 624 per French J at 637 [57]; and M17/2004 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 85 ALD 597 per Ryan J at 615-616 [79] [83]. The Keskin information was simply factual information that might assist in testing the extent of the appellant's knowledge of the activities of the HRA in Turkey and the veracity of her claims. The same picture is presented when the matter is viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's reasons. The Tribunal attached some significance to the fact that in her evidence to the Tribunal the appellant displayed a lack of knowledge of the Keskin information, amongst other matters. In my opinion, the Keskin information cannot be characterised as the reason, or as a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision under review.

70 There is, in my opinion, a valid distinction between the HRA letter and the Tribunal's subjective evaluation of the weight that should be attached to it in the light of the appellant's oral evidence to the Tribunal. Such a distinction is supported by VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAGP per Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ at 282-283 [26] [29]; Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 per Sackville J at [53] [54]; and Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120 per Carr, Moore and Marshall JJ. It is also consistent with the statutory purpose of s 424A , which (to paraphrase the language of Allsop J in Paul at [104]) is to ensure that the applicant is fairly informed of information adverse to his or her case so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, if possible, to meet it. By itself, the HRA letter was not the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the delegate's decision. Nor was there any point of time prior to the Tribunal's decision at which the Tribunal would have considered that the HRA letter might have constituted the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the delegate's decision. It follows that the HRA letter does not fall within the scope of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1196.html</AustLII>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

37 In Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 (" Paul ") at 428 [95], Allsop J, with whom Heerey J agreed, said:
 "... I agree with the distinction drawn by Sackville J in Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs that the information of which particulars must be provided is information or knowledge that has come to or been gained by the Tribunal and is not the subjective appraisal or thought process of the Tribunal ... However, the distinction can become very fine. If the subjective thought processes of the Tribunal are as they are because of the perceived importance of some piece of knowledge, those thought processes may merely reveal the relevance (for the purposes of s 424(A)(1)(b)) of information (for s 424A(1)(a)), requiring the Tribunal to give particulars of that information and to explain its relevance."

38 Allsop J also observed that some unbundling of the immediate reason for the Tribunal's affirmation may be required, and that in any given circumstance it may not be straightforward to identify from an expressed reasoning process whether information was the reason or a part of the reason for affirmation: see Paul at 428-429 [99]-[100].

39 In the result, Allsop J adopted the following approach at 432 [116]: 
 
 "The question as to whether information would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirmation is ultimately decided, in my view, by whether it can be characterised as sufficiently important to the reasoning process in the rejection of the appellant's claims, for fairness to warrant that the applicant be told if it is so that he or she can understand and be able to meet the integers or elements that make up the Tribunal's reasons or conclusion thus far reached (hence 'would') for finding adversely to the applicant."

41 Merkel J dissented. In the course of his Honour's reasons for judgment, he cautioned that it is impermissible to impose an additional criterion that the information must be an 'integral' or 'essential' reason for the decision in order for s 424A to apply. His Honour recognised that it may not be straightforward to identify from the reasons themselves whether the information in question was part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision. In discussing Paul , his Honour approved of the fact that Allsop J had eschewed a narrow view of what would constitute the reason or part of the reason for a decision to affirm the decision of the delegate. However, his Honour added the following cautionary words at 483 [54]-[55]:
 "His Honour's observations may provide guidance for assessing whether particular information was part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision where, as was the case in Paul , it may not be straightforward to identify from the reasons themselves whether the information in question was part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision. 
 
 However, his Honour should not be regarded as having intended to lay down an exhaustive test for the circumstances in which s 424A is to apply. If his Honour's observations (at FCR 432 [116]; ALD 320-1) were said to lay down such a test, that test would become a substitute for the words the legislature has used in the section itself. Thus in a case, of which Al Shamry is an example, where it is clear on the face of the reasons expressed by the Tribunal that the information in question was a part of the reason for the decision, Allsop J's observations cannot be employed to arrive at a different conclusion because to do so would be to impermissibly import into s 424A an additional criterion of 'sufficient importance'."

50 Allsop J held that the test which had been advanced in Paul and VAF had to be reconsidered in the light of the High Court's decision in SAAP . His Honour said that, to the extent that Paul and VAF both include notions of fairness derived from the rules of procedural fairness as part of the analysis of whether something is part of the reason for affirming the decision, those decisions are in conflict with the approach of the majority of the High Court in SAAP . In consequence, his Honour set out what he thought that the approach to be adopted in the future should be at [215]:
 "In my view, in the light of SAAP , in circumstances where one is faced with a decision of the Tribunal with reasons and the complaint is a contravention of s 424A(1), the question to ask, by reference to the reasons of the Tribunal in the context in which one find them (as revealing what would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the decision immediately prior to the making of the decision), is whether the information in question was a part (that is any part) of the reason for affirming the decision. To the extent that the reasons of the relevant majorities in Paul and VAF can be seen to require that the relevant part of the reason have a stature or importance, or be of a character which would make it unfair not to invoke the procedures of s 424A, I think SAAP requires that such an approach be rejected. It is only necessary that the information be a part of the reason." 
 

The application of these principles by the majority in SZEEU necessarily led to the conclusion that both the flight information and the similar claims information fell squarely within s 424A. It was sufficient that both pieces of information were referred to and relied upon by the Tribunal as relevant and operative considerations, whether or not they could be described as a subsidiary or a minor part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision.

52 I do, however, wish to make one observation. In my view, it does not follow from the decisions in SAAP and SZEEU that the statutory purpose of s 424A is irrelevant to its proper construction and application. In SAAP , McHugh J at 181 [73] said that s 424A is a statutory formulation of the obligation to accord procedural fairness in the conduct of a review, and endorsed statements in this Court to the same effect: see SAAP at 179 [66]. Hayne J emphasised the crucial role played by the language, scope and objects of s 424A in its construction and application: see SAAP at 211 [208]. In Paul , Allsop J construed and applied s 424A in the light of its purpose of 'ensuring that the claimant is fully informed of information adverse to his or her case (in the manner described by the section) so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, somehow, if possible, to meet it': see Paul at 429-430 [104]. In Al Shamr y at 40 [39], Merkel J said that s 424A enacts a basic principle of the common law rules of natural justice that a person whose interests are likely to be affected by an exercise of power be given an opportunity to deal with relevant matters adverse to his or her interests that the repository of the power proposes to take into account in deciding upon its exercise. Cases may arise in which it is appropriate to take account of the statutory purpose of s 424A in determining whether there is any information within the meaning of s 424A, or whether particular information is the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. I do not consider that there is anything to the contrary in SZEEU .

70 There is, in my opinion, a valid distinction between the HRA letter and the Tribunal's subjective evaluation of the weight that should be attached to it in the light of the appellant's oral evidence to the Tribunal. Such a distinction is supported by VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAGP per Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ at 282-283 [26] [29]; Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 per Sackville J at [53] [54]; and Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120 per Carr, Moore and Marshall JJ. It is also consistent with the statutory purpose of s 424A , which (to paraphrase the language of Allsop J in Paul at [104]) is to ensure that the applicant is fairly informed of information adverse to his or her case so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, if possible, to meet it. By itself, the HRA letter was not the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the delegate's decision. Nor was there any point of time prior to the Tribunal's decision at which the Tribunal would have considered that the HRA letter might have constituted the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the delegate's decision. It follows that the HRA letter does not fall within the scope of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>WAGP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/266.html</AustLII>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

42 In WAGP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 (" WAGP "), the Full Court (Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ) held that the word 'information' in s 424A(1) does not encompass a failure to mention a matter to the Tribunal. Their Honours said at 282 [26]:
 "It is inappropriate to speak of the RRT 'getting information' where the substance of that information is merely an observation that the appellant did not refer to a particular matter in his evidence. The fact that the appellant did not refer to a particular matter constitutes nothing more than an aspect of the RRT's reasoning concerning a deficiency in his evidence. That observation cannot meaningfully be described as 'information'. Moreover, the appellant's submission cannot be accepted as a matter of sound policy. To permit an applicant for review of a delegate's decision to comment on each deficiency in his or her evidence, as viewed by the RRT, has the potential to allow a protracted and almost never ending process of review, a result plainly not intended by the legislature."

43 The Full Court went on to distinguish Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212, where the Full Court (Whitlam, Tamberlin and Sackville JJ) held that the assertions of an informant which cast doubt on the applicant's version of events constituted information for the purposes of s 424A(1). The Full Court said that there was a material difference between assertions of an informant and observations or conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up aspects of the evidence of an applicant by reference to gaps or defects in that evidence: see WAGP at 282 [27].

44 In SZECF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1200 , the appeal arose from a Tribunal decision which had found that the applicant for a protection visa had fabricated his claim and various documents submitted in support of it. In reaching this conclusion, the Tribunal relied upon the fact that the applicant's written statement to the Department did not mention the claims of persecution that the Tribunal ultimately rejected. One of the issues that arose on the appeal to this Court was whether s 424A applied to the information contained in the applicant's original statement to the Department. After referring to VAF, Paul and WAGP , Allsop J at [26] and [34] held that it did: 
 "I have extracted earlier the places in the Tribunal's reasons where the prior statement is used. Having read the whole of the reasons of the Tribunal, it is clear that the comprehensive disbelief of the appellant and the finding that he had brought forward fraudulent documentation was largely, if not wholly, a product of the importance placed by the Tribunal on the form and content of his first statement. In short, the Tribunal found that if what he was saying were true, it would have been referred to earlier. The fact that it was not, demonstrated the falsity of his evidence to the Tribunal. 
 
 ... 
 
 In my view, here, the knowledge of the Tribunal of the content of the earlier statement, including the limits of its contents can be seen to be a part of the reason for the decision because its form and content were instrumental in the Tribunal reaching a conclusion that the oral evidence of the appellant was false and the documents he was propounding were fraudulent." 
 

In Allsop J's view, the case before him involved something more than what Finn and Stone JJ in VAF at 476-477 [24] had called 'identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity' in evidence given to the Tribunal, or what the Full Court in WAGP had described as a failure to mention something in evidence given to the Tribunal.

45 In the course of his reasons for judgment, Allsop J discussed the decision of Branson J in NAIH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 1010 ; (2002) 124 FCR 223 (" NAIH "), which had been cited with approval by the Full Court in WAGP . In NAIH at 226 [8], her Honour had doubted that an intention can be discerned in s 424A that the totality of the claims and assertions in a statement made by an applicant in support of his or her application, and the general impression of coherence or otherwise created by those claims and assertions, is information received by the Tribunal. Allsop J distinguished NAIH on several grounds. First, he thought that Branson J was not directing herself to a case where the very form and content of the applicant's original statement is central to the rejection of virtually all of the applicant's evidence. Secondly, while the Tribunal contrasted the applicant's evidence with the cohesive account in the earlier statement, Branson J found that the Tribunal based its decision on the unconvincing nature of the applicant's oral evidence before it.

70 There is, in my opinion, a valid distinction between the HRA letter and the Tribunal's subjective evaluation of the weight that should be attached to it in the light of the appellant's oral evidence to the Tribunal. Such a distinction is supported by VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAGP per Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ at 282-283 [26] [29]; Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 per Sackville J at [53] [54]; and Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120 per Carr, Moore and Marshall JJ. It is also consistent with the statutory purpose of s 424A , which (to paraphrase the language of Allsop J in Paul at [104]) is to ensure that the applicant is fairly informed of information adverse to his or her case so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, if possible, to meet it. By itself, the HRA letter was not the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the delegate's decision. Nor was there any point of time prior to the Tribunal's decision at which the Tribunal would have considered that the HRA letter might have constituted the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the delegate's decision. It follows that the HRA letter does not fall within the scope of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/56.html</AustLII>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

43 The Full Court went on to distinguish Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212, where the Full Court (Whitlam, Tamberlin and Sackville JJ) held that the assertions of an informant which cast doubt on the applicant's version of events constituted information for the purposes of s 424A(1). The Full Court said that there was a material difference between assertions of an informant and observations or conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up aspects of the evidence of an applicant by reference to gaps or defects in that evidence: see WAGP at 282 [27].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZECF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1200</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1200.html</AustLII>
<text>44 In SZECF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1200 , the appeal arose from a Tribunal decision which had found that the applicant for a protection visa had fabricated his claim and various documents submitted in support of it. In reaching this conclusion, the Tribunal relied upon the fact that the applicant's written statement to the Department did not mention the claims of persecution that the Tribunal ultimately rejected. One of the issues that arose on the appeal to this Court was whether s 424A applied to the information contained in the applicant's original statement to the Department. After referring to VAF, Paul and WAGP , Allsop J at [26] and [34] held that it did: 
 "I have extracted earlier the places in the Tribunal's reasons where the prior statement is used. Having read the whole of the reasons of the Tribunal, it is clear that the comprehensive disbelief of the appellant and the finding that he had brought forward fraudulent documentation was largely, if not wholly, a product of the importance placed by the Tribunal on the form and content of his first statement. In short, the Tribunal found that if what he was saying were true, it would have been referred to earlier. The fact that it was not, demonstrated the falsity of his evidence to the Tribunal. 
 
 ... 
 
 In my view, here, the knowledge of the Tribunal of the content of the earlier statement, including the limits of its contents can be seen to be a part of the reason for the decision because its form and content were instrumental in the Tribunal reaching a conclusion that the oral evidence of the appellant was false and the documents he was propounding were fraudulent." 
 

In Allsop J's view, the case before him involved something more than what Finn and Stone JJ in VAF at 476-477 [24] had called 'identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity' in evidence given to the Tribunal, or what the Full Court in WAGP had described as a failure to mention something in evidence given to the Tribunal.

47 In separate reasons for judgment, each member of the Full Court in SZEEU considered the application of s 424A(2) to information which the Tribunal had relied on to make adverse credibility findings. The first piece of information concerned a statement which the appellant had made in a document lodged in support of his protection visa application explaining the circumstances in which he had left Bangladesh. The members of the Full Court described this as 'the flight information'. The second piece of information was that the Tribunal had received essentially the same claims in the same words from several other applicants represented by the same migration agent. This was referred to as 'the similar claims information'. Both pieces of information were used by the Tribunal in making an adverse assessment of the appellant's credibility. Each member of the Full Court considered that the information constituted information within the meaning of s 424A(1). Allsop J expressly stated that he adhered to what he had said in SZECF . There was, however, a difference of view between Moore J on the one hand, and Weinberg and Allsop JJ on the other, concerning the approach which should be adopted to the question whether these pieces of information constituted a part of the reason for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision made by the Minister's delegate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>NAIH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 1010 ; (2002) 124 FCR 223</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/1010.html</AustLII>
<text>45 In the course of his reasons for judgment, Allsop J discussed the decision of Branson J in NAIH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 1010 ; (2002) 124 FCR 223 (" NAIH "), which had been cited with approval by the Full Court in WAGP . In NAIH at 226 [8], her Honour had doubted that an intention can be discerned in s 424A that the totality of the claims and assertions in a statement made by an applicant in support of his or her application, and the general impression of coherence or otherwise created by those claims and assertions, is information received by the Tribunal. Allsop J distinguished NAIH on several grounds. First, he thought that Branson J was not directing herself to a case where the very form and content of the applicant's original statement is central to the rejection of virtually all of the applicant's evidence. Secondly, while the Tribunal contrasted the applicant's evidence with the cohesive account in the earlier statement, Branson J found that the Tribunal based its decision on the unconvincing nature of the applicant's oral evidence before it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>46 After argument concluded in this appeal, the Full Court (Moore, Weinberg and Allsop JJ) handed down its decision in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 (" SZEEU ") which incorporates four related appeals. The main issue addressed by the Full Court was whether the authority of Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Al Shamry [2001] FCA 919 ; (2001) 110 FCR 27 (" Al Shamry ") should be reconsidered. The Court held unanimously that it should follow the construction of s 424A(3)(d) adopted in Al Shamry .

47 In separate reasons for judgment, each member of the Full Court in SZEEU considered the application of s 424A(2) to information which the Tribunal had relied on to make adverse credibility findings. The first piece of information concerned a statement which the appellant had made in a document lodged in support of his protection visa application explaining the circumstances in which he had left Bangladesh. The members of the Full Court described this as 'the flight information'. The second piece of information was that the Tribunal had received essentially the same claims in the same words from several other applicants represented by the same migration agent. This was referred to as 'the similar claims information'. Both pieces of information were used by the Tribunal in making an adverse assessment of the appellant's credibility. Each member of the Full Court considered that the information constituted information within the meaning of s 424A(1). Allsop J expressly stated that he adhered to what he had said in SZECF . There was, however, a difference of view between Moore J on the one hand, and Weinberg and Allsop JJ on the other, concerning the approach which should be adopted to the question whether these pieces of information constituted a part of the reason for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision made by the Minister's delegate.

48 Moore J adopted and applied what had been said by Finn and Stone JJ in VAF : see SZEEU at [22] [25]. In his Honour's view, the flight information was not of sufficient significance to warrant a conclusion that it formed part of the Tribunal's reasons for affirming the decision of the Minister's delegate. This was because it was a subsidiary and peripheral reason which the Tribunal relied upon to reject the applicant's claim that charges were outstanding against him in Bangladesh. Other factors referred to by the Tribunal were of greater significance. As for the similar claims information, Moore J noted that the Tribunal only referred to this information after analysing and rejecting the applicant's central claims. In his Honour's view, the Tribunal therefore rejected the central claims of the appellant by a process of reasoning not dependent on the similar claims information: see SZEEU at [27]-[28].

50 Allsop J held that the test which had been advanced in Paul and VAF had to be reconsidered in the light of the High Court's decision in SAAP . His Honour said that, to the extent that Paul and VAF both include notions of fairness derived from the rules of procedural fairness as part of the analysis of whether something is part of the reason for affirming the decision, those decisions are in conflict with the approach of the majority of the High Court in SAAP . In consequence, his Honour set out what he thought that the approach to be adopted in the future should be at [215]:
 "In my view, in the light of SAAP , in circumstances where one is faced with a decision of the Tribunal with reasons and the complaint is a contravention of s 424A(1), the question to ask, by reference to the reasons of the Tribunal in the context in which one find them (as revealing what would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the decision immediately prior to the making of the decision), is whether the information in question was a part (that is any part) of the reason for affirming the decision. To the extent that the reasons of the relevant majorities in Paul and VAF can be seen to require that the relevant part of the reason have a stature or importance, or be of a character which would make it unfair not to invoke the procedures of s 424A, I think SAAP requires that such an approach be rejected. It is only necessary that the information be a part of the reason." 
 

The application of these principles by the majority in SZEEU necessarily led to the conclusion that both the flight information and the similar claims information fell squarely within s 424A. It was sufficient that both pieces of information were referred to and relied upon by the Tribunal as relevant and operative considerations, whether or not they could be described as a subsidiary or a minor part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision.

51 On the question whether the Keskin information and the HRA letter were a part of the reason for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision made by the Minister's delegate, I consider that I am bound by, and ought to follow, SZEEU as the most recent considered statement of principle by the Full Court.

52 I do, however, wish to make one observation. In my view, it does not follow from the decisions in SAAP and SZEEU that the statutory purpose of s 424A is irrelevant to its proper construction and application. In SAAP , McHugh J at 181 [73] said that s 424A is a statutory formulation of the obligation to accord procedural fairness in the conduct of a review, and endorsed statements in this Court to the same effect: see SAAP at 179 [66]. Hayne J emphasised the crucial role played by the language, scope and objects of s 424A in its construction and application: see SAAP at 211 [208]. In Paul , Allsop J construed and applied s 424A in the light of its purpose of 'ensuring that the claimant is fully informed of information adverse to his or her case (in the manner described by the section) so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, somehow, if possible, to meet it': see Paul at 429-430 [104]. In Al Shamr y at 40 [39], Merkel J said that s 424A enacts a basic principle of the common law rules of natural justice that a person whose interests are likely to be affected by an exercise of power be given an opportunity to deal with relevant matters adverse to his or her interests that the repository of the power proposes to take into account in deciding upon its exercise. Cases may arise in which it is appropriate to take account of the statutory purpose of s 424A in determining whether there is any information within the meaning of s 424A, or whether particular information is the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. I do not consider that there is anything to the contrary in SZEEU .

64 The HRA letter was provided to the Department in connection with the appellant's application for a protection visa; it was not given to the Tribunal for the purposes of the review application. In these circumstances, the exception in s 424A(3)(b) is inapplicable. It only applies to information that is given for the purposes of the review application before the Tribunal: see Al Shamry per Ryan and Conti JJ at 33-34 [17]-[20] and per Merkel J at 38-39 [35]; and SZEEU per Moore J at [9], per Weinberg J at [154] and per Allsop J at [199]. The first respondent did not contend that the exception applied, or dispute the appellant's submission that it was inapplicable.

69 Does the HRA letter constitute information to which s 424A applies? The first respondent advanced two reasons why s 424A did not apply. First, it was argued that the Tribunal's subjective appraisal of the HRA letter, in weighing it against the appellant's oral statements and explanations to the delegate and to the Tribunal, did not constitute information for the purposes of s 424A. Secondly, the first respondent argued that any reservations which the Tribunal had about the letter could not be considered integral to, nor an important aspect of, the Tribunal's reasoning process so as to enliven the Tribunal's obligations under s 424A. The second argument must be rejected having regard to the Full Court's decision in SZEEU . The first argument has more substance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Al Shamry [2001] FCA 919 ; (2001) 110 FCR 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/919.html</AustLII>
<text>46 After argument concluded in this appeal, the Full Court (Moore, Weinberg and Allsop JJ) handed down its decision in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 (" SZEEU ") which incorporates four related appeals. The main issue addressed by the Full Court was whether the authority of Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Al Shamry [2001] FCA 919 ; (2001) 110 FCR 27 (" Al Shamry ") should be reconsidered. The Court held unanimously that it should follow the construction of s 424A(3)(d) adopted in Al Shamry .

52 I do, however, wish to make one observation. In my view, it does not follow from the decisions in SAAP and SZEEU that the statutory purpose of s 424A is irrelevant to its proper construction and application. In SAAP , McHugh J at 181 [73] said that s 424A is a statutory formulation of the obligation to accord procedural fairness in the conduct of a review, and endorsed statements in this Court to the same effect: see SAAP at 179 [66]. Hayne J emphasised the crucial role played by the language, scope and objects of s 424A in its construction and application: see SAAP at 211 [208]. In Paul , Allsop J construed and applied s 424A in the light of its purpose of 'ensuring that the claimant is fully informed of information adverse to his or her case (in the manner described by the section) so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, somehow, if possible, to meet it': see Paul at 429-430 [104]. In Al Shamr y at 40 [39], Merkel J said that s 424A enacts a basic principle of the common law rules of natural justice that a person whose interests are likely to be affected by an exercise of power be given an opportunity to deal with relevant matters adverse to his or her interests that the repository of the power proposes to take into account in deciding upon its exercise. Cases may arise in which it is appropriate to take account of the statutory purpose of s 424A in determining whether there is any information within the meaning of s 424A, or whether particular information is the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. I do not consider that there is anything to the contrary in SZEEU .

64 The HRA letter was provided to the Department in connection with the appellant's application for a protection visa; it was not given to the Tribunal for the purposes of the review application. In these circumstances, the exception in s 424A(3)(b) is inapplicable. It only applies to information that is given for the purposes of the review application before the Tribunal: see Al Shamry per Ryan and Conti JJ at 33-34 [17]-[20] and per Merkel J at 38-39 [35]; and SZEEU per Moore J at [9], per Weinberg J at [154] and per Allsop J at [199]. The first respondent did not contend that the exception applied, or dispute the appellant's submission that it was inapplicable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>WAJR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 624</tocase>
<text>62 In applying s 424A , it is necessary to focus on matters that, viewed prospectively, would be the reason or a part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision, or viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's actual decision, can be seen to be the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. At the outset of the Tribunal hearing and prior to the appellant's evidence to the Tribunal, I doubt that the Keskin information could be characterised as information that the Tribunal then considered, or might consider, would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the delegate's decision. By itself, the Keskin information was not adverse to the appellant. Numerous cases suggest that s 424A is concerned with information that is adverse to the interests of the visa applicant: see SAAP per McHugh J at 175 [50]; VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAJR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 624 per French J at 637 [57]; and M17/2004 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 85 ALD 597 per Ryan J at 615-616 [79] [83]. The Keskin information was simply factual information that might assist in testing the extent of the appellant's knowledge of the activities of the HRA in Turkey and the veracity of her claims. The same picture is presented when the matter is viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's reasons. The Tribunal attached some significance to the fact that in her evidence to the Tribunal the appellant displayed a lack of knowledge of the Keskin information, amongst other matters. In my opinion, the Keskin information cannot be characterised as the reason, or as a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision under review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>M17/2004 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 85 ALD 597</tocase>
<text>62 In applying s 424A , it is necessary to focus on matters that, viewed prospectively, would be the reason or a part of the reason for the Tribunal's decision, or viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's actual decision, can be seen to be the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's decision. At the outset of the Tribunal hearing and prior to the appellant's evidence to the Tribunal, I doubt that the Keskin information could be characterised as information that the Tribunal then considered, or might consider, would be the reason or a part of the reason for affirming the delegate's decision. By itself, the Keskin information was not adverse to the appellant. Numerous cases suggest that s 424A is concerned with information that is adverse to the interests of the visa applicant: see SAAP per McHugh J at 175 [50]; VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAJR v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 624 per French J at 637 [57]; and M17/2004 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2005) 85 ALD 597 per Ryan J at 615-616 [79] [83]. The Keskin information was simply factual information that might assist in testing the extent of the appellant's knowledge of the activities of the HRA in Turkey and the veracity of her claims. The same picture is presented when the matter is viewed retrospectively in the light of the Tribunal's reasons. The Tribunal attached some significance to the fact that in her evidence to the Tribunal the appellant displayed a lack of knowledge of the Keskin information, amongst other matters. In my opinion, the Keskin information cannot be characterised as the reason, or as a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the decision under review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1109.html</AustLII>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

37 In Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 (" Paul ") at 428 [95], Allsop J, with whom Heerey J agreed, said:
 "... I agree with the distinction drawn by Sackville J in Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs that the information of which particulars must be provided is information or knowledge that has come to or been gained by the Tribunal and is not the subjective appraisal or thought process of the Tribunal ... However, the distinction can become very fine. If the subjective thought processes of the Tribunal are as they are because of the perceived importance of some piece of knowledge, those thought processes may merely reveal the relevance (for the purposes of s 424(A)(1)(b)) of information (for s 424A(1)(a)), requiring the Tribunal to give particulars of that information and to explain its relevance."

70 There is, in my opinion, a valid distinction between the HRA letter and the Tribunal's subjective evaluation of the weight that should be attached to it in the light of the appellant's oral evidence to the Tribunal. Such a distinction is supported by VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAGP per Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ at 282-283 [26] [29]; Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 per Sackville J at [53] [54]; and Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120 per Carr, Moore and Marshall JJ. It is also consistent with the statutory purpose of s 424A , which (to paraphrase the language of Allsop J in Paul at [104]) is to ensure that the applicant is fairly informed of information adverse to his or her case so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, if possible, to meet it. By itself, the HRA letter was not the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the delegate's decision. Nor was there any point of time prior to the Tribunal's decision at which the Tribunal would have considered that the HRA letter might have constituted the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the delegate's decision. It follows that the HRA letter does not fall within the scope of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/120.html</AustLII>
<text>36 There is no reason to doubt that 'information' in s 424A(1) is used in its ordinary sense of knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance. In VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 (" VAF ") at 476-477 [24], Finn and Stone JJ set out the following propositions about the meaning of the term 'information' in its s 424A(1) setting: 
 
 
 "(i) the purpose of s 424A is to provide in part a statutory procedural analogue to the common law of procedural fairness: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 429-30 [104] ; [2001] FCA 1196 ; 64 ALD 289 at 318. However the obligation imposed is not coextensive with that which might be imposed by the common law to avoid practical injustice: VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; BC200301782; 
 
 (ii) the word 'information' in s 424A(1) has the same meaning as in s 424; Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212 at 218 [20] ; and in this setting it refers to knowledge of relevant facts or circumstances communicated to or received by the Tribunal: Tin v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 ; BC200004607 at [3]; irrespective of whether it is reliable or has a sound factual basis: Win , at 217-18 [19]-[22]; and 
 
 (iii) the word does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations: Tin at [54]; Paul at FCR 428 [95]; ALD 317; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1679 ; BC200107472 at [25]; approved [2002] FCAFC 120 ; BC200203793; nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc: WAGP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 266 ; (2002) 124 FCR 276 at 282-4 [26] - [29] ." 
 
 
 

The third proposition has not been doubted but its application has produced some fine distinctions.

70 There is, in my opinion, a valid distinction between the HRA letter and the Tribunal's subjective evaluation of the weight that should be attached to it in the light of the appellant's oral evidence to the Tribunal. Such a distinction is supported by VAF per Finn and Stone JJ at 476-477 [24]; WAGP per Marshall, Weinberg and Jacobson JJ at 282-283 [26] [29]; Tin v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 per Sackville J at [53] [54]; and Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 120 per Carr, Moore and Marshall JJ. It is also consistent with the statutory purpose of s 424A , which (to paraphrase the language of Allsop J in Paul at [104]) is to ensure that the applicant is fairly informed of information adverse to his or her case so that investigation may be made, and steps may be taken, if possible, to meet it. By itself, the HRA letter was not the reason, or a part of the reason, for the Tribunal's affirmation of the delegate's decision. Nor was there any point of time prior to the Tribunal's decision at which the Tribunal would have considered that the HRA letter might have constituted the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the delegate's decision. It follows that the HRA letter does not fall within the scope of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59</tocase>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.

78 The appellant submitted that the decision in Appellant S106/2002 shows that McHugh and Gummow JJ (at 67 and 71) were prepared to consider a challenge to a Tribunal decision based on the grounds that it was illogical, irrational or lacking a basis in findings or inferences of fact. The first of these passages merely describes the argument and is purely introductory. In the second passage, their Honours were directing themselves to a case where the decision itself was illogical or irrational; not a case where particular findings of fact or findings about credibility are impugned as illogical or lacking in probative support.

79 Far from assisting the appellant, the decision in Appellant S106/2002 illustrates the difficulties of contending that the Tribunal's evaluation of the credibility of a witness, or the plausibility of particular pieces of evidence, involved jurisdictional error. The essence of the complaint in Appellant S106/2002 was that the Tribunal failed to consider the evidence as a whole, but first considered and disbelieved the evidence of the applicant without taking account of corroborating evidence, and then considered and rejected the corroboration because of the rejection of the applicant's evidence. Gleeson CJ said at 63 [12]-[13]:
 "In my view, all that the member was saying was that, for reasons already given at length, she found the applicant/appellant's story implausible, and in some important respects unbelievable, and that she also rejected the evidence of the corroborating witness, even though she had no separate reason to doubt his credibility other than the reasons that she had already given for rejecting the claim she was considering. The member could have expressed herself more clearly. It is not necessarily irrational, or illogical, for a finder of fact, who is convinced that a principal witness is fabricating a story, which is considered to be inherently implausible, to reject corroborative evidence, even though there is no separate or independent ground for its rejection, apart from the reasons given for disbelieving the principal witness. 
 
 Upon analysis, the complaint is that the Tribunal member did not have regard to the whole of the evidence before deciding whether she believed the applicant/appellant, and did not properly assess the significance of the evidence of the corroborating witness. I am not persuaded that this criticism is justified." 


See also McHugh and Gummow JJ at 70 [49] and 71 [51] [52].

80 Here, the statements by the Tribunal which are attacked as illogical form part of the Tribunal's overall assessment of the appellant's evidence, including her credibility and the plausibility of her claims to have a well-founded fear of persecution. That assessment was supported by other considerations which are not impugned as illogical, such as the Tribunal's reference to the appellant's vague and unconvincing identification of those who threatened or harassed her as right wing militants and/or religious extremists.

81 Hartnett FM concluded that none of the impugned findings was illogical, or indicated that the Tribunal had failed to properly exercise its jurisdiction. As Gleeson CJ pointed out in Appellant S106/2002 , the description of reasoning as illogical or irrational may merely be an emphatic way of expressing disagreement with it. It is not enough that another Tribunal might not have made the impugned findings, or attached the same weight to them. As the Full Court (Heerey, Sundberg and Crennan JJ) said in NATC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 52 at [27] , opinions can vary about what is inherently improbable or unacceptable as evidence of the fact, or what evidence makes sense, that is whether evidence is probative in relation to a particular fact. In the absence of perversity or manifest error, sufficient in each case to give rise to jurisdictional error, the Court cannot intervene.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/33.html</AustLII>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402</tocase>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/235.html</AustLII>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/255.html</AustLII>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/286.html</AustLII>
<text>77 The immediate obstacle confronting this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal is the finder of fact. Mere errors in fact-finding will not constitute an error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error: see Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 per Brennan J at 35-36; and Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 198 ALR 59 (" Appellant S106/2002 ") per Gleeson CJ at 61 62 [5] [9] and per Kirby J at 85 86 [116] [120]. Even if a factual finding is illogical or unsupported by evidence, it would only be capable of constituting a jurisdictional error if it constituted a critical step in the Tribunal's ultimate conclusion or demonstrated that there had been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of power: see Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1990) 170 CLR 321 per Mason CJ at 355-357; SFGB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 77 ALD 402 per Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ at 407-408 [19] [20]; and NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 (" NACB ") at [29]. In NACB , the Full Court (Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ) affirmed a line of authorities to the effect that illogical reasoning does not of itself constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error, or necessarily indicate that there had only been a purported exercise of power. In W404/01A of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 255 at [35] , Lee and Carr JJ, with whom French J agreed, said that even though the Tribunal's reasoning could be regarded as illogical, this did not in itself show a ground of review although it may on occasion manifest other reviewable error. In VWST v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [18] , the Full Court (Kiefel, Marshall and Dowsett JJ) reviewed the authorities and concluded that want of logic in the reasons of the Tribunal is not an available ground of review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NATC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 52</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>81 Hartnett FM concluded that none of the impugned findings was illogical, or indicated that the Tribunal had failed to properly exercise its jurisdiction. As Gleeson CJ pointed out in Appellant S106/2002 , the description of reasoning as illogical or irrational may merely be an emphatic way of expressing disagreement with it. It is not enough that another Tribunal might not have made the impugned findings, or attached the same weight to them. As the Full Court (Heerey, Sundberg and Crennan JJ) said in NATC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 52 at [27] , opinions can vary about what is inherently improbable or unacceptable as evidence of the fact, or what evidence makes sense, that is whether evidence is probative in relation to a particular fact. In the absence of perversity or manifest error, sufficient in each case to give rise to jurisdictional error, the Court cannot intervene.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>