<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZAIX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 3 (10 January 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/3.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Khawar [2002] HCA 14 ; (2002) 210 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/14.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The appellant submitted that, even if, upon analysis, she feared persecution only by a non-State actor for non-Convention reasons, the Tribunal erred by failing to consider whether there had been a failure by the Indonesian authorities, for Convention reasons, to provide protection to her. The appellant relied on the observation in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Respondents S152/2003 (2004) 205 ALR 487 (' S152 ') that a state's inability to control the conduct of its police force may amount to a sufficient reason for a person to be unwilling to avail herself of the protection of her country of nationality once outside the country. That, however, assumes that a Convention reason is implicated. In oral submissions, the appellant submitted that, had the Tribunal applied the correct test, it would have been open to it to conclude that the failure by the authorities to protect the appellant was for a Convention reason: the High Court's decision in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Khawar [2002] HCA 14 ; (2002) 210 CLR 1 (' Khawar ') is authority for the proposition that criminal activity committed by a private individual, which is tolerated or condoned by the State because it systematically discriminates on Convention grounds, may amount to persecution.

40 More specifically and authoritatively, in Khawar it was recognised that, as Gleeson CJ put it (at [30] [31]):
 
 'The references in the authorities to state agents of persecution and non-state agents of persecution should not be understood as constructing a strict dichotomy. Persecution may also result from the combined effect of the conduct of private individuals and the state or its agents; and a relevant form of state conduct may be tolerance or condonation of the inflicting of serious harm in circumstances where the state has a duty to provide protection against such harm. As was noted earlier, this is not a case in which it is necessary to deal with mere inability to provide protection; this is a case of alleged tolerance and condonation. In Ex parte Shah , Lord Hoffmann, in giving the example of the Jewish shopkeeper set upon with impunity by business rivals in Nazi Germany, referred to the failure of the authorities to provide protection, based upon race, as an "element in the persecution". The same expression was used by Lord Hope of Craighead in the passage from Horvath quoted above. 
 
 Where persecution consists of two elements, the criminal conduct of private citizens, and the toleration or condonation of such conduct by the state or agents of the state, resulting in the withholding of protection which the victims are entitled to expect, then the requirement that the persecution be by reason of one of the Convention grounds may be satisfied by the motivation of either the criminals or the state. In relation to the case which Ms Khawar seeks to make out, the decision in Ex parte Shah in this respect is directly in point. If her contentions, as to which no findings have yet been made, are correct, then Ms Khawar was being abused by her husband and his relatives for personal reasons, but her likely subjection to further abuse without state protection is by reason of her membership of a particular social group , if it be the case that women in Pakistan may be so described.' (Footnotes omitted, emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

 See also Khawar at [79]-[80], [87] and [114] ff.

41 S152 effected no modification of Khawar .

43 The Tribunal had before it material from the appellant's father which she and her father had wished to have considered by the relevant Australian authorities. Her father suggested that he was treated differently and less favourably, when he complained, by the local police, Muslims, because he was Chinese. It was elsewhere asserted in the materials relied on by the appellant that all the police are Muslims. The Refugee Advice and Casework Service (Australia) Inc ('RACS') had submitted on behalf of the appellant that she 'fears that the police and authorities in Indonesia will not protect her because of the fact she is a Christian Chinese...'. Her solicitor had also submitted that the appellant's father had provided a statement detailing his experience with the police: 'He reported the matter to the police who took no action, he opined that it was due to the fact that he and his daughter were Chinese whereas the police and the rapist were Muslim.' The appellant's solicitor, citing Khawar (at [29]), submitted that '[o]n its face, this is a further case of persecution. Even if the original rape was not for a convention reason, the failure of the authorities to investigate and take action in respect of the rape can amount to persecution if such inaction was motivated by questions of race.' The Tribunal Member who first heard the appellant's case recorded that the appellant had 'also stated that her father and brother had reported the assault to the police but they took no action. The Indonesian authorities were not interested in protecting her.' The Tribunal Member asked the appellant 'how, in her view, the police could have done anything without more information.' According to the Member, the appellant did not respond to that question, but 'reiterated that the complaint was ignored because she was of Chinese descent so was ignored. There were fights between Muslims and Chinese Christians.'

44 The Tribunal appears to have accepted the appellant's claim that her attacker was a threat to her on account of her complaint to the police. It was also apparently accepted, at least, that the appellant had been raped; that this had been reported to the police; that they had, at best, done nothing useful directed towards apprehending the rapist, and that she had been raped again by the same man on account of the complaint to the police.

45 In such circumstances, it behoved the Tribunal, in light of the several ways in which the appellant put her case, to examine whether the appellant might qualify for refugee status. There is nothing abstruse or indirect in the proposition, which readily springs to mind, that despite anti-racist sentiments expressed and progress initiated at the highest levels of government, these may have had little effect at local police level.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Respondents S152/2003 (2004) 205 ALR 487</tocase>
<text>30 The appellant submitted that, even if, upon analysis, she feared persecution only by a non-State actor for non-Convention reasons, the Tribunal erred by failing to consider whether there had been a failure by the Indonesian authorities, for Convention reasons, to provide protection to her. The appellant relied on the observation in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Respondents S152/2003 (2004) 205 ALR 487 (' S152 ') that a state's inability to control the conduct of its police force may amount to a sufficient reason for a person to be unwilling to avail herself of the protection of her country of nationality once outside the country. That, however, assumes that a Convention reason is implicated. In oral submissions, the appellant submitted that, had the Tribunal applied the correct test, it would have been open to it to conclude that the failure by the authorities to protect the appellant was for a Convention reason: the High Court's decision in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Khawar [2002] HCA 14 ; (2002) 210 CLR 1 (' Khawar ') is authority for the proposition that criminal activity committed by a private individual, which is tolerated or condoned by the State because it systematically discriminates on Convention grounds, may amount to persecution.

31 In considering whether effective state protection was available, the appellant submitted that the Tribunal was required to consider whether there was a reasonably effective and impartial police force and a reasonably impartial system of justice: see S152 at [26]. The appellant argued that the Tribunal's reasoning reveals no consideration of whether effective state protection was available to the appellant 'on the ground' or at a 'micro' level, as was required: the question was, what would be available as a practical matter to a woman in the position of the appellant?

32 The appellant submitted that, had the Tribunal really questioned whether there was an effective and impartial police force and a reasonably impartial system of justice, as required by S152 , it would have dealt with the suggestion by the appellant's father that the police had not responded to his complaint of his daughter's rape because she is Chinese, and that the appellant was raped again after the complaint.

34 The Minister further argued that in a case of persecution by non-state agents the question of state protection may be relevant at three stages of the inquiry: whether the fear is well-founded; whether the conduct giving rise to the fear is persecution, and; whether the appellant is unable, or, owing to fear of persecution, unwilling, to avail herself of the protection of her state: S152 per Gleeson CJ, Hayne and Heydon JJ at [21]. It was for this reason that the High Court allowed an appeal from the judgment of the Full Court of the Federal Court in S152 that turned on a finding, similar to the appellant's argument in this appeal, that the Tribunal erred in failing to determine whether there was protection available 'in a practical sense'.

35 However, while the 'ability of the state to discharge its obligation to protect its citizens', may , as counsel for the Minister submitted, be relevant at three stages of the inquiry, it is here, in my view, relevant to the second question identified by Gleeson CJ, Hayne and Heydon JJ, viz 'whether the conduct giving rise to the fear is persecution' (at [21]). If the state, despite the good intentions of its leaders, is not able, at what might be called the operational or grass-roots level, to have its operatives provide an acceptable level of protection against serious harm, and the dereliction of those operatives has as its basis their discrimination of a Convention kind against the appellant, that situation, as Hale LJ put it in Horvath v Secretary of State for the Home Department [2000] 1 NLR 15, 'may turn the acts of others [ie non-state actors] into persecution for a Convention reason' (at 52 and quoted with approval by Lord Hope of Craighead in the appeal to the House of Lords (see [2000] UKHL 37 ; [2001] 1 AC 489 at 497)).

36 So much was uncontroversial in S152 . S152 was a case where harm had been inflicted by non-state actors for Convention reasons. The majority in the High Court took the view that (at [26]):
 
 ' [n] o country can guarantee that its citizens will at all times, and in all circumstances, be safe from violence. Day by day, Australian courts deal with criminal cases involving violent attacks on person or property. Some of them may occur for reasons of racial or religious intolerance. The religious activities in which the first respondent engaged ... evidently aroused the anger of some other people. Their response was unlawful. The Ukrainian state was obliged to take reasonable measures to protect the lives and safety of its citizens, and those measures would include an appropriate criminal law, and the provision of a reasonably effective and impartial police force and justice system. None of the country information before the tribunal justified a conclusion that there was a failure on the part of Ukraine to conform to its obligations in that respect.'

37 In the present case, by contrast, (if the matter were sufficiently raised by the appellant), although the serious harm done to her by a non-state agent was not itself inflicted for a Convention reason, she might nevertheless be refugee if, for Convention reasons, namely, anti-Chinese racism merging into antipathy for Chinese women considered as a social group exhibited by the local police, the State failed, to provide a 'reasonably effective and impartial police force' (cf S152 at [26]) at a grass-roots level. That is, the State's weakness or incompetence, whatever its leaders' good intention, in having its norms carried out, might have permitted the local police to engage in Convention persecution themselves, by failure (for Convention reasons) to prevent and act against those who would cause the appellant serious harm.

38 As I read S152 , nothing in it, or otherwise in principle, denies that such a claim, if made out, may constitute the appellant a refugee. She would be in her predicament because of the risk of serious harm coming to her for a Convention reason. As the Convention definition puts it (see Article 1(A)(2)), she would be: 
 
 '...owing to well-founded fear of being persecuted for [Convention reasons] ... outside the country of [her] nationality and ... , owing to such fear ... unwilling to avail [herself] of the protection of that country'.

39 As the 'Michigan Guidelines', developed by Professor Hathaway and others, put it:
 
 'The causal link between the applicant's predicament and a Convention ground will be revealed by evidence of the reasons which led either to the infliction or threat of a relevant harm, or which cause the applicant's country of origin to withhold effective protection in the face of a privately inflicted risk. Attribution of the Convention ground to the applicant by the state or non-governmental agent of persecution is sufficient to establish the required causal connection.' (See: Hathaway, 'The Michigan Guidelines on Nexus to a Convention Ground', Michigan Journal of International Law (2002) vol 23, pp 211-222 at 215.)

41 S152 effected no modification of Khawar .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>63 If a matter is not mentioned in a Tribunal's findings, this entitles a court to infer that the matter was not considered by the Tribunal to be material ( Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 per McHugh, Gummow, Hayne JJ (with whom Gleeson CJ agreed) at [69]). That the Tribunal Member engaged in no discussion of questions of those kinds suggests that the psychological aspects of the practical realities facing the appellant were not present to his mind. Given the strangeness of such matters not having been mentioned if they were considered, in my view it is appropriate to draw the inference that they were not considered. I do not wish to seem overcritical. The appellant's case was not a simple one. She had, according to the Tribunal, embroidered some facts and the Tribunal Member thought that a friend who gave evidence was suggesting that, even in the Australian context, she was less robust a person than the Tribunal considered her to be. Nevertheless, it is notorious that in the last 20 years or so the high potential for sexual assault, let alone repeated instances of it, to cause the victim serious psychological difficulties, has become widely accepted. I think that the kinds of potential difficulties to which I have referred were overlooked. There has in my opinion been, as in NAIZ , a failure by the Tribunal to ask itself (as Branson J put it) 'the right questions'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>NABE v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 219 ALR 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/263.html</AustLII>
<text>50 The unexamined question was, in my opinion, sufficiently clearly an integer of her case to require consideration. If it was not clearly and expressly so asserted in the ways referred to at [44] above, in my view it clearly arose on the materials before the Tribunal. In NABE v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 219 ALR 27 (' NABE ') the Full Court said (at [61]): 
 
 'We are of the view that the observations by Merkel J in Paramananthan , by the Full Courts in Sellamuthu and Sarrazola (No 2) and by Cooper J in SDAQ are consistent with the proposition that the tribunal is not required to consider a case that is not expressly made or does not arise clearly on the materials before it. The tribunal's obligation is not limited to procedural fairness in responding to expressly articulated claims but, as is apparent from Dranichnikov , extends to reviewing the delegate's decision on the basis of all the materials before it.'

51 Earlier the Full Court had approved (at [60]) some pertinent observations by Selway J in SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364 at [17]-[18] : 
 
 '...But this does not mean that the application is to be treated as an exercise in nineteenth century pleading. ... 
 The question, ultimately, is whether the case put by the appellant before the tribunal has sufficiently raised the relevant issue that the tribunal should have dealt with it.' 


It would be strange if a claimant of refugee status were to be denied a right to have the substance of her claim considered, including the different ways in which the Convention might apply to her, because she had failed clearly to analyse those ways in her application and supporting material, although she had clearly enough delineated facts that might attract the salvation of the Convention. It is not likely that the Full Court in NABE intended such a thing. The Full Court was absolving the Tribunal from any duty to engage in subtle teasing out of hypotheses that only abstrusely arise from an applicant's account of the circumstances that have led to the claim of refugee status. That is not the position here.

52 In my opinion, nothing in NABE was intended to deny, nor can it be denied, that to determine whether a claim 'clearly arises' on the material before a decision-maker, the decision-maker must fully understand the claim being made. That, in turn, may in some cases make it necessary for the decision-maker to analyse what the appellant has said in terms of possible Convention categories. That was the position here.

53 In my opinion, failure to consider this matter constituted a constructive failure to exercise the Tribunal's jurisdiction.

54 Nevertheless, whether such error ultimately has the effect of invalidating the Tribunal's decision depends on whether there was otherwise an independent, jurisdictionally robust basis, among those found by the Tribunal, for denying the appellant's claim. In particular, the finding that the appellant feared persecution at the hands of one local man and that the appellant could avoid such threat as he might pose by relocating elsewhere in Indonesia is of potential significance here.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAIZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 37</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/37.html</AustLII>
<text>60 In NAIZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 37 (' NAIZ ') at [22], Branson J (with whom North J agreed) found jurisdictional error on the part of a Tribunal Member who, though acknowledging that internal relocation should be 'reasonable' in the circumstances:
 
 '...did not, as ... Randhawa [at] [16] ... requires, give consideration to the practical realities facing the appellant [a widow of advancing years] with respect to accommodation and care should she seek to relocate within Fiji ... the Tribunal was required to give consideration to how, in a practical sense, the appellant could be expected to relocate within Fiji.'

61 Here, the appellant was a Chinese Christian widow with young children who had been twice raped and who had never lived in Indonesia outside Jakarta. True it is that she was enterprising and employable. But on the material accepted by the Tribunal, anti-Chinese sentiment runs deep in Indonesia and the vulnerability of women to rape appears, from the Tribunal's findings, to be high.

62 It requires little empathy to understand that, although the appellant's precise fear of persecution as identified by the Tribunal relates to one man in Jakarta, she may well now suffer profound psychological difficulty in readjusting to Indonesian society and adjusting to a new place of residence in Indonesia at some place where, ex hypothesi , she appears likely to have no close family support. To observe that she had suffered an 'ordeal', yet appeared capable in Australia, where the social environment is entirely different and she has family support, is simply not to acknowledge the major difficulty in the 'practical realities', both psychological and physical, that now would confront her if returned to Indonesia. Who would befriend her? What support, if any, would be available? Would she be able to speak freely about her troubles (there is a suggestion in her materials, unexplored by the Tribunal, that even in Chinese-Indonesian circles shame attaches to a sexually assaulted woman)? Is a Chinese widow on her own in Indonesia especially apt to attract unwelcome sexual advances?

63 If a matter is not mentioned in a Tribunal's findings, this entitles a court to infer that the matter was not considered by the Tribunal to be material ( Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 per McHugh, Gummow, Hayne JJ (with whom Gleeson CJ agreed) at [69]). That the Tribunal Member engaged in no discussion of questions of those kinds suggests that the psychological aspects of the practical realities facing the appellant were not present to his mind. Given the strangeness of such matters not having been mentioned if they were considered, in my view it is appropriate to draw the inference that they were not considered. I do not wish to seem overcritical. The appellant's case was not a simple one. She had, according to the Tribunal, embroidered some facts and the Tribunal Member thought that a friend who gave evidence was suggesting that, even in the Australian context, she was less robust a person than the Tribunal considered her to be. Nevertheless, it is notorious that in the last 20 years or so the high potential for sexual assault, let alone repeated instances of it, to cause the victim serious psychological difficulties, has become widely accepted. I think that the kinds of potential difficulties to which I have referred were overlooked. There has in my opinion been, as in NAIZ , a failure by the Tribunal to ask itself (as Branson J put it) 'the right questions'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>NAJT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/134.html</AustLII>
<text>11 In NAJT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 I gave my views as follows (at [162]-[166]), Conti J generally agreeing:
 
 'Quite apart from a power to receive new evidence, what is the position of an appellate court rehearing a matter as to questions of law available on the materials before the trial judge but not raised at first instance? An appellant wishing to raise fresh legal questions cannot, in the first place, be in a worse position than one seeking to augment the evidence itself. Secondly, a party victorious at first instance is, in any case, liable to be defeated by a change in the law occurring before the appeal is heard; that, indeed, is conventionally given as the main practical difference between a "strict" appeal and one by way of rehearing. The result of a new legal point being successfully raised is no harder for the litigant thereby defeated than if the defeat follows from some legal point newly raised. Thirdly, however, there is undoubtedly great, general value in considerations of finality of litigation acting as a brake on appellate intervention, thereby preserving the integrity of the trial as the normal arena for final disposition of that case. As a general statement of principle there is no conflict between what the Full Court approved in Branir and the approach in the cases next referred to. 
 
 In my respectful view, the correct approach, and the one generally adopted in practice in this Court, is that succinctly expressed in VUAX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158 (" VUAX ") by Kiefel, Weinberg and Stone JJ (at [46] [48]): 
 
 
 
 
 "Leave to argue a ground of appeal not raised before the primary judge should only be granted if it is expedient in the interests of justice to do so: O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310; H v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs ; and Branir ... at [20]-[24] and [38]. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 In Coulton ..., Gibbs CJ, Wilson, Brennan and Dawson JJ observed, in their joint judgment, at 7 : 
 
 
 
 
 
 'It is fundamental to the due administration of justice that the substantial issues between the parties are ordinarily settled at the trial. If it were not so the main arena for the settlement of disputes would move from the court of first instance to the appellate court, tending to reduce the proceedings in the former court to little more than a preliminary skirmish.' 
 
 
 
 
 
 The practice of raising arguments for the first time before the Full Court has been particularly prevalent in appeals relating to migration matters. The Court may grant leave if some point that was not taken below, but which clearly has merit, is advanced, and there is no real prejudice to the respondent in permitting it to be agitated. Where, however, there is no adequate explanation for the failure to take the point, and it seems to be of doubtful merit, leave should generally be refused." (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 
 To similar effect, in Iyer ... Heerey, Moore and Goldberg JJ said (at [22] [24]): 
 
 
 
 
 
 "... We recognise that there is a particular sensitivity in refugee cases where an adverse decision may have very serious consequences for an applicant. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Although it is in the interests of justice that decisions be made on the true merits of the case sought to be argued, the structure and integrity of the appellate process must also be taken into consideration. It is incumbent upon parties bringing applications to the Court to review decisions of tribunals such as the [Tribunal] to make it clear from the outset what are the substantive grounds of review relied upon .... 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 However, in order to determine whether it is expedient and in the interests of justice that leave be given to argue new grounds it is necessary to give some consideration to the merits of the grounds raised . That does not mean that an appellate court should enter upon a full consideration of the grounds. To do so would make the requirement for leave meaningless. It is sufficient to determine whether the grounds sought to be raised have a reasonable prospect of success. We also consider it appropriate to take into account whether the appellant had the benefit of legal representation at the hearing before the primary judge ." (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 
 ... 
 
 Thus, relevant questions include: 
 
 
 
 
 1) Do the new legal arguments have a reasonable prospect of success? 
 
 2) Is there an acceptable explanation of why they were not raised below? 
 
 3) How much dislocation to the Court and efficient use of judicial sitting time is really involved? 
 
 
 
 
 4) What is at stake in the case for the appellant? 
 
 
 
 
 5) Will the resolution of the issues raised have any importance beyond the case at hand? 
 
 6) Is there any actual prejudice, not viewing the notion of prejudice narrowly, to the respondent? 
 
 
 
 
 7) If so, can it be justly and practicably cured? 
 
 
 
 
 8) If not, where, in all the circumstances, do the interests of justice lie?' (Original emphasis).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NALZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 320 ; (2004) 140 FCR 270</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/320.html</AustLII>
<text>56 The present and well-entrenched state of Full Federal Court authority is that a claim to refugee status is not established by those who could reasonably avail themselves of the real protection of the country of nationality elsewhere within their country of nationality: Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437 (' Randhawa' ) per Black CJ at 440 (cf my remarks in dissent in NALZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 320 ; (2004) 140 FCR 270 at [8] ). The question is whether the person can relocate to another area of the country, and, it is said, whether he or she could reasonably be expected to do so. However, answering this question is influenced by the principle that: 
 
 'notwithstanding that real protection from persecution may be available elsewhere within the country of nationality, a person's fear of persecution in relation to that country will remain well-founded with respect to the country as a whole if, as a practical matter, the part of the country in which protection is available is not reasonably accessible to that person' (per Black CJ in Randhawa at 442).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Queensland v J L Holdings Pty Limited [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/1.html</AustLII>
<text>10 At the hearing, counsel for the appellant relied on Queensland v J L Holdings Pty Limited [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146, suggesting that it is authority for the principle that the requirements of case management are relevant considerations, but they cannot be used to prevent a party from arguing a ground that is fairly arguable. Further, counsel suggested that there is a level of disagreement in this Court regarding the approach to be taken to this issue. In doing so, counsel referred to the judgment of Allsop J in Branir v Owston Nominees (No 2) [2001] FCA 1833 ; (2001) 117 FCR 424 at 440, in which his Honour expressly declined to comment on the approach taken by Branson and Katz JJ in H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2000) 63 ALD 43. In that case, their Honours gave consideration to the merits of the new grounds to be raised. On this point, counsel also referred to the discussion in VUAX at [48] where, it appears, the Full Court accepted that the merits of the new grounds are to be given consideration. The appellant argued that a party should be permitted to raise an arguable case provided any prejudice to other parties could be compensated by costs. In addition, the appellant referred to the judgment of R D Nicholson J in Jones , where his Honour stated (at 48) that whether or not the Immigration Review Tribunal had complied with its statutory duty 'raises a point of law in the interests of justice which supports and outweighs, in all the circumstances, the public interest in the finality of litigation in these particular circumstances'. Jenkinson J (with whom Carr J agreed) similarly stated (at 37) that the '[o]bservance of such [statutory] requirements by a tribunal administering important and publicly scrutinised immigration laws should be encouraged by this Court. A determination whether...the Tribunal satisfied those requirements is in my opinion expedient and in the interests of justice.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437</tocase>
<text>56 The present and well-entrenched state of Full Federal Court authority is that a claim to refugee status is not established by those who could reasonably avail themselves of the real protection of the country of nationality elsewhere within their country of nationality: Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437 (' Randhawa' ) per Black CJ at 440 (cf my remarks in dissent in NALZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 320 ; (2004) 140 FCR 270 at [8] ). The question is whether the person can relocate to another area of the country, and, it is said, whether he or she could reasonably be expected to do so. However, answering this question is influenced by the principle that: 
 
 'notwithstanding that real protection from persecution may be available elsewhere within the country of nationality, a person's fear of persecution in relation to that country will remain well-founded with respect to the country as a whole if, as a practical matter, the part of the country in which protection is available is not reasonably accessible to that person' (per Black CJ in Randhawa at 442).

57 The appellant submitted that the Tribunal incorrectly took a general approach that there must be a safe haven somewhere in Indonesia, and did not consider, as a matter of practical reality, the issues raised by the appellant as required ( Randhawa at 443). The appellant submitted that the specific issues which the Tribunal was obliged, but failed to consider were:
 
 
 
 1. the psychological difficulties of continuing to live anywhere within a country and culture in which the appellant had experienced rape on two occasions;
 2. the appellant's need, as a single mother (her husband having died in January 2001), for the support of her family;
 3. the appellant may face discrimination and/or harm living as a single woman with children without any family protection;
 4. the appellant has never lived outside Cenkarang (apparently a suburb of Jakarta) in Indonesia as a single woman; and
 5. the only family the appellant has who are outside Cenkarang live in Australia. The Tribunal did not advert to the fact that all of the appellant's relatives living in Indonesia live in Cenkarang.

58 The Tribunal also failed to take into account its finding that the incidence of rape of women in Indonesia generally is a problem and the fact of a general social prejudice against ethnic Chinese Indonesians. These are probable issues for the appellant, who would effectively be without family support. In oral submissions counsel added that the Tribunal did not take into account that the appellant may have her children with her if she relocates, unlike her experience in Australia, which had encouraged the Tribunal to regard her as a relatively resilient person.

59 The Minister denied the claim that the Tribunal merely assumed there was a safe haven within Indonesia, and argued that it is for the Tribunal to determine the significant issues in assessing the matter of relocation. It cannot be assumed that, because the Tribunal has failed to refer expressly to an issue, it has failed to consider it. The proper inference is that the issues referred to by counsel for the appellant were not considered by the Tribunal to be as significant as those the Tribunal mentioned. Also, of the issues listed by the appellant's counsel, factors (1) and (3) go to whether the appellant would want to live in Indonesia at all, rather than to whether she could relocate. Issues (2) and (5) concern the appellant's wish to have family support, which was acknowledged by the Tribunal, and issue (4) could properly be considered not to carry great weight, given that the appellant had successfully made her way in the unfamiliar cultural environment in Australia. The brevity, it was submitted, of the Tribunal's reasons on this matter 'does not detract from the breadth of the consideration'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364</tocase>
<text>51 Earlier the Full Court had approved (at [60]) some pertinent observations by Selway J in SGBB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 364 at [17]-[18] : 
 
 '...But this does not mean that the application is to be treated as an exercise in nineteenth century pleading. ... 
 The question, ultimately, is whether the case put by the appellant before the tribunal has sufficiently raised the relevant issue that the tribunal should have dealt with it.' 


It would be strange if a claimant of refugee status were to be denied a right to have the substance of her claim considered, including the different ways in which the Convention might apply to her, because she had failed clearly to analyse those ways in her application and supporting material, although she had clearly enough delineated facts that might attract the salvation of the Convention. It is not likely that the Full Court in NABE intended such a thing. The Full Court was absolving the Tribunal from any duty to engage in subtle teasing out of hypotheses that only abstrusely arise from an applicant's account of the circumstances that have led to the claim of refugee status. That is not the position here.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VUAX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/158.html</AustLII>
<text>6. Did the Tribunal fail to apply the correct legal test, or fail to take relevant considerations into account, on the question of the availability of State protection, in relation to future protection by the police? 
 
 

6 The appellant was legally represented at the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court, but submitted in this Court that the new grounds were not raised there in circumstances where her solicitor's grasp of the legal complexities appeared to be less than fully adequate. The appellant submitted, and the first respondent ('Minister') agreed, that where it is expedient and in the interests of justice to grant leave to raise new grounds on appeal, the Court should do so. The appellant cited VUAX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158 at [46] (' VUAX' ) (and the cases there cited) in support of her request for leave.

10 At the hearing, counsel for the appellant relied on Queensland v J L Holdings Pty Limited [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146, suggesting that it is authority for the principle that the requirements of case management are relevant considerations, but they cannot be used to prevent a party from arguing a ground that is fairly arguable. Further, counsel suggested that there is a level of disagreement in this Court regarding the approach to be taken to this issue. In doing so, counsel referred to the judgment of Allsop J in Branir v Owston Nominees (No 2) [2001] FCA 1833 ; (2001) 117 FCR 424 at 440, in which his Honour expressly declined to comment on the approach taken by Branson and Katz JJ in H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2000) 63 ALD 43. In that case, their Honours gave consideration to the merits of the new grounds to be raised. On this point, counsel also referred to the discussion in VUAX at [48] where, it appears, the Full Court accepted that the merits of the new grounds are to be given consideration. The appellant argued that a party should be permitted to raise an arguable case provided any prejudice to other parties could be compensated by costs. In addition, the appellant referred to the judgment of R D Nicholson J in Jones , where his Honour stated (at 48) that whether or not the Immigration Review Tribunal had complied with its statutory duty 'raises a point of law in the interests of justice which supports and outweighs, in all the circumstances, the public interest in the finality of litigation in these particular circumstances'. Jenkinson J (with whom Carr J agreed) similarly stated (at 37) that the '[o]bservance of such [statutory] requirements by a tribunal administering important and publicly scrutinised immigration laws should be encouraged by this Court. A determination whether...the Tribunal satisfied those requirements is in my opinion expedient and in the interests of justice.'

11 In NAJT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 I gave my views as follows (at [162]-[166]), Conti J generally agreeing:
 
 'Quite apart from a power to receive new evidence, what is the position of an appellate court rehearing a matter as to questions of law available on the materials before the trial judge but not raised at first instance? An appellant wishing to raise fresh legal questions cannot, in the first place, be in a worse position than one seeking to augment the evidence itself. Secondly, a party victorious at first instance is, in any case, liable to be defeated by a change in the law occurring before the appeal is heard; that, indeed, is conventionally given as the main practical difference between a "strict" appeal and one by way of rehearing. The result of a new legal point being successfully raised is no harder for the litigant thereby defeated than if the defeat follows from some legal point newly raised. Thirdly, however, there is undoubtedly great, general value in considerations of finality of litigation acting as a brake on appellate intervention, thereby preserving the integrity of the trial as the normal arena for final disposition of that case. As a general statement of principle there is no conflict between what the Full Court approved in Branir and the approach in the cases next referred to. 
 
 In my respectful view, the correct approach, and the one generally adopted in practice in this Court, is that succinctly expressed in VUAX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158 (" VUAX ") by Kiefel, Weinberg and Stone JJ (at [46] [48]): 
 
 
 
 
 "Leave to argue a ground of appeal not raised before the primary judge should only be granted if it is expedient in the interests of justice to do so: O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310; H v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs ; and Branir ... at [20]-[24] and [38]. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 In Coulton ..., Gibbs CJ, Wilson, Brennan and Dawson JJ observed, in their joint judgment, at 7 : 
 
 
 
 
 
 'It is fundamental to the due administration of justice that the substantial issues between the parties are ordinarily settled at the trial. If it were not so the main arena for the settlement of disputes would move from the court of first instance to the appellate court, tending to reduce the proceedings in the former court to little more than a preliminary skirmish.' 
 
 
 
 
 
 The practice of raising arguments for the first time before the Full Court has been particularly prevalent in appeals relating to migration matters. The Court may grant leave if some point that was not taken below, but which clearly has merit, is advanced, and there is no real prejudice to the respondent in permitting it to be agitated. Where, however, there is no adequate explanation for the failure to take the point, and it seems to be of doubtful merit, leave should generally be refused." (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 
 To similar effect, in Iyer ... Heerey, Moore and Goldberg JJ said (at [22] [24]): 
 
 
 
 
 
 "... We recognise that there is a particular sensitivity in refugee cases where an adverse decision may have very serious consequences for an applicant. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Although it is in the interests of justice that decisions be made on the true merits of the case sought to be argued, the structure and integrity of the appellate process must also be taken into consideration. It is incumbent upon parties bringing applications to the Court to review decisions of tribunals such as the [Tribunal] to make it clear from the outset what are the substantive grounds of review relied upon .... 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 However, in order to determine whether it is expedient and in the interests of justice that leave be given to argue new grounds it is necessary to give some consideration to the merits of the grounds raised . That does not mean that an appellate court should enter upon a full consideration of the grounds. To do so would make the requirement for leave meaningless. It is sufficient to determine whether the grounds sought to be raised have a reasonable prospect of success. We also consider it appropriate to take into account whether the appellant had the benefit of legal representation at the hearing before the primary judge ." (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 
 ... 
 
 Thus, relevant questions include: 
 
 
 
 
 1) Do the new legal arguments have a reasonable prospect of success? 
 
 2) Is there an acceptable explanation of why they were not raised below? 
 
 3) How much dislocation to the Court and efficient use of judicial sitting time is really involved? 
 
 
 
 
 4) What is at stake in the case for the appellant? 
 
 
 
 
 5) Will the resolution of the issues raised have any importance beyond the case at hand? 
 
 6) Is there any actual prejudice, not viewing the notion of prejudice narrowly, to the respondent? 
 
 
 
 
 7) If so, can it be justly and practicably cured? 
 
 
 
 
 8) If not, where, in all the circumstances, do the interests of justice lie?' (Original emphasis).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>