<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hassan v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 379 (9 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/379.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/22.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Minister for Immigration; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 the High Court held, when dealing with ss 52 to 63 of the Act , that there was no intention to exclude the operation of common law rules of procedural fairness. In Nais v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 77 (" Nais" ), Gleeson CJ referred to Bastarache J whom, for the majority in Blencoe v British Columbia (Human Rights Commission) [2000] 2 SCR 307 at 367 [102], said that it was "accepted that the principles of natural justice and the duty of fairness include the right to a fair hearing and that undue delay in the processing of an administrative proceeding that impairs the fairness of the hearing can be remedied". There was, however, no infringement of this principle in this case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nais v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 77</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/77.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In Minister for Immigration; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 the High Court held, when dealing with ss 52 to 63 of the Act , that there was no intention to exclude the operation of common law rules of procedural fairness. In Nais v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 77 (" Nais" ), Gleeson CJ referred to Bastarache J whom, for the majority in Blencoe v British Columbia (Human Rights Commission) [2000] 2 SCR 307 at 367 [102], said that it was "accepted that the principles of natural justice and the duty of fairness include the right to a fair hearing and that undue delay in the processing of an administrative proceeding that impairs the fairness of the hearing can be remedied". There was, however, no infringement of this principle in this case.

14 Much of the delay in this case can be attributed to the Department's efforts to allow Mr Hassan an opportunity to respond to Ms Kurami's letter of 14 April 2004. Also, the delay must be considered within the context of an application for a spousal visa. Marriage is intended to be a life-long commitment. Thus, a delay of a few months should not prejudice an applicant for a spouse visa. The delay in this case was significantly less than that considered in Nais (41/2 years) where the High Court did find a breach of procedural fairness. In all the circumstances, I do not find that the delay in this case involved a denial of procedural fairness.

15 As the appellant has identified no error in the decisions of the Tribunal or the Federal Magistrate, I would dismiss the appeal with costs.

16 It is open to the appellant to make application to the Minister pursuant to s 351 of the Act , which enables the Minister to make a more favourable decision notwithstanding the decision of the Tribunal. There would be no impediment to him so doing. His would appear to be an appropriate case for making such an application. 
 

 I certify that the preceding sixteen (16) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Kenny. 


Associate:

Dated: 6 April 2006


 
 
 
 
 Applicant appeared in person 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr C Symons 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 9 March 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 9 March 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/379.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Blencoe v British Columbia (Human Rights Commission) [2000] 2 SCR 307</tocase>
<text>13 In Minister for Immigration; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 the High Court held, when dealing with ss 52 to 63 of the Act , that there was no intention to exclude the operation of common law rules of procedural fairness. In Nais v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 77 (" Nais" ), Gleeson CJ referred to Bastarache J whom, for the majority in Blencoe v British Columbia (Human Rights Commission) [2000] 2 SCR 307 at 367 [102], said that it was "accepted that the principles of natural justice and the duty of fairness include the right to a fair hearing and that undue delay in the processing of an administrative proceeding that impairs the fairness of the hearing can be remedied". There was, however, no infringement of this principle in this case.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>