<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Delta Metallics v Hawley-Jacobs T/A Fightboi Health &amp; Fitness Centre [2006] FCA 334 (31 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/334.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Banque Commerciale SA (In Liquidation) v Akhil Holdings Ltd [1990] HCA 11 ; (1990) 169 CLR 279</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/11.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Without providing an exhaustive list of defects, it is sufficient to state that the challenged portions of the respondent's Defence and Cross-Claim do not comply with the Rules. For example, paragraphs 6, 7, 9 and 21 all allege that AAB acted "falsely and recklessly" in some regard. This allegation appears akin to one of fraud, and as such must be further particularised pursuant to O 12 r 2: see Banque Commerciale SA (In Liquidation) v Akhil Holdings Ltd [1990] HCA 11 ; (1990) 169 CLR 279 at 285 per Mason CJ and Gaudron J. Even if it is not intended as an allegation of fraud (or misrepresentation or wilful default), O 12 r 3 obliges the respondent to particularise the facts relied upon for his allegations that AAB had such a condition of mind.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Johnson Tiles Pty Ltd v Esso Australia [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2001) ATPR 41-794</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1572.html</AustLII>
<text>7 Also, the respondent must provide particulars of AAB's alleged breach of s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth): see Johnson Tiles Pty Ltd v Esso Australia [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2001) ATPR 41-794 at 42,547-42,548, [63] - [66] per French J with whom Beaumont and Finkelstein JJ agreed (outlining the detailed requirements for pleading a claim under s 52 of the TPA).

8 Furthermore, pursuant to O 11 r 10 the respondent must plead specifically the provisions of the TMA he claims AAB has violated. Amongst other things, O 11 r 10 requires a party to plead specifically any matter of fact or point of law that, if not specifically pleaded, might take the other party by surprise. It is insufficient to specify provisions in the prayer for relief. It must be borne in mind that no relief can be granted unless justified by what has been pleaded in the body of the pleadings.

9 If the deficiencies in the pleading could be cured by the provision of further and better particulars, I would order that such particulars be provided. There is, however, a basic problem that the provision of particulars will not overcome. It is a fundamental rule of pleading that a respondent must state in his defence the material facts essential to any affirmative case he wants to make in answer to the applicant's claim. These facts (and not the evidence for them) are to be stated in a summary form according to the pleading rules. As far as convenient, each material fact or other matter is to be put into a separate paragraph, with paragraphs numbered consecutively (O 11, r 1 and r 2). Proper particulars are required of the relevant allegations (see, e.g., [6]-[8] above). Paragraphs 6, 7, 9 and 21 of the defence and cross-claim do not comply with these requirements.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (No 2) (1996) 72 FCR 151</tocase>
<text>11 By its notice of motion, the applicant sought its costs of the motion on an indemnity basis. Counsel properly did not press this application today. It is true that the applicant sough to put the respondent on notice that there were problems with his pleading late last year when it wrote its letter of 22 December 2005. Ordinarily, however, costs in this court are awarded on a party and party basis. The respondent has made a good faith effort to respond to the allegations against him. In Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (No 2) (1996) 72 FCR 151 (" Re Wilcox ") at 156-157, Cooper and Merkel JJ said that: (a) the court ought not to depart from the usual party and party basis for costs unless this was warranted by the circumstances of the case; and (b) these circumstances arise "as and when the justice of the case so requires or where there may be some special or unusual feature in the case to justify the court in departing from the usual course". I do not find that the circumstances of this case warrant a departure from the usual course.

12 Nevertheless, the applicant has been successful in its motion and, notwithstanding the respondent's opposition, costs should follow the event. I propose to order that the respondent pay the costs of the motion on a party and party basis.

13 I also propose to direct that the parties file and serve submissions on the following two questions: whether or not the proceeding should be transferred to the Queensland District Registry; and (2) whether or not the proceeding should be referred to mediation under O 72 of the Federal Court Rules. I have already raised these matters with the parties in the course of the recent directions hearing. I would also make a further direction in the terms discussed in court today in relation to matters presently the subject of a confidentiality order.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>