<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Original Mama*s Pizza and Ribs Pty Ltd (ACN 093 465 046) [2006] FCA 302 (21 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/302.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hughes Motor Service Pty Ltd v Wang Computer Pty Ltd (1978) 35 FLR 346</tocase>
<text>14 The relevant power of the Court to control its own proceedings has been considered in Hughes Motor Service Pty Ltd v Wang Computer Pty Ltd (1978) 35 FLR 346 (' Wang ') at 351 to 354, and Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v The Boots Company (Australia) Pty Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 287 (' Sterling Pharmaceuticals '). As McClelland CJ in Equity said in Tamas v Silver Beach Resort Pty Ltd (unreported, NSWSC, 13 July 1994): 'a party bringing proceedings is entitled to have them dealt with and heard in the ordinary course of the Court's business unless some strong countervailing consideration can be demonstrated'.

16 In Wang , Bowen CJ stressed that, where a public regulator is seeking an injunction to restrain conduct which might mislead or deceive members of the public generally (and, I would interpolate, a relevant section or sections of the public, even if numerically small), 'the weight of public interest in the scales in favour of rejecting an application for a stay would be very heavy.'

17 There are legitimate public interest considerations to be ventilated, and possibly vindicated, in these proceedings and, while not overlooking the inconvenience for the respondents of having to fight on a number of fronts, and the expense and difficulty of so doing, it seems to me that the justification for a stay has not, on a balance of relevant factors, been made out.

18 Accordingly, I reject the application for a stay with costs.
 

 I certify that the preceding eighteen (18) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Madgwick. 


Associate:

Dated: 29 March 2006


 Counsel for the Applicants: Ms N Sharp 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Ramrakha Jenkins 
 
 Date of Hearing: 21 March 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 March 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/302.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v The Boots Company (Australia) Pty Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 287</tocase>
<text>14 The relevant power of the Court to control its own proceedings has been considered in Hughes Motor Service Pty Ltd v Wang Computer Pty Ltd (1978) 35 FLR 346 (' Wang ') at 351 to 354, and Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v The Boots Company (Australia) Pty Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 287 (' Sterling Pharmaceuticals '). As McClelland CJ in Equity said in Tamas v Silver Beach Resort Pty Ltd (unreported, NSWSC, 13 July 1994): 'a party bringing proceedings is entitled to have them dealt with and heard in the ordinary course of the Court's business unless some strong countervailing consideration can be demonstrated'.

15 In Sterling Pharmaceuticals at 291, Lockhart J sought to provide something of a check-list of matters that might be considered. These included the priority in point of time of the institution of the different proceedings; whether the termination of one proceeding was likely to have a material effect on the other; the public interest; the undesirability of waste of time and effort; and of course, costs, if substantially the same issues were to be ventilated in actions in different courts; the general policy of the law discouraging multiplicity of proceedings in relation to similar issues; and, as his Honour said, '[g]enerally balancing the advantages and disadvantages to each party'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Tamas v Silver Beach Resort Pty Ltd (unreported, NSWSC, 13 July 1994)</tocase>
<text>14 The relevant power of the Court to control its own proceedings has been considered in Hughes Motor Service Pty Ltd v Wang Computer Pty Ltd (1978) 35 FLR 346 (' Wang ') at 351 to 354, and Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v The Boots Company (Australia) Pty Ltd (1992) 34 FCR 287 (' Sterling Pharmaceuticals '). As McClelland CJ in Equity said in Tamas v Silver Beach Resort Pty Ltd (unreported, NSWSC, 13 July 1994): 'a party bringing proceedings is entitled to have them dealt with and heard in the ordinary course of the Court's business unless some strong countervailing consideration can be demonstrated'.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>