<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Duncan v Lipscombe Child Care Services Inc [2006] FCA 458 (28 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/458.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1948) 78 CLR 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/1.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Plainly s 31A was introduced to establish a lower standard for strikeouts (either of claims or defences) than that previously laid down by the High Court's decisions in Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1948) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 130, namely that the allegations are "so clearly untenable that [they] cannot possibly succeed".

32 The application of the Concrete Constructions principle to conduct concerning contracts of employment has resulted in a divergence of Federal Court authority. In Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389 Wilcox J held that information supplied to an employee in the course of negotiating a variation to his contract of employment was "in trade or commerce". In Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501, a case concerning negotiations for a new contract of employment, Finkelstein J came to the same view. Both these cases were strikeout applications and thus were governed at the time they were decided by the Dey and General Steel authorities; their Honours could only strike out the claim if it was hopeless or bound to fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; 1964 112 CLR 125 at 130</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Plainly s 31A was introduced to establish a lower standard for strikeouts (either of claims or defences) than that previously laid down by the High Court's decisions in Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1948) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 130, namely that the allegations are "so clearly untenable that [they] cannot possibly succeed".

32 The application of the Concrete Constructions principle to conduct concerning contracts of employment has resulted in a divergence of Federal Court authority. In Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389 Wilcox J held that information supplied to an employee in the course of negotiating a variation to his contract of employment was "in trade or commerce". In Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501, a case concerning negotiations for a new contract of employment, Finkelstein J came to the same view. Both these cases were strikeout applications and thus were governed at the time they were decided by the Dey and General Steel authorities; their Honours could only strike out the claim if it was hopeless or bound to fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Rodway v The Queen [1990] HCA 19 ; (1990) 169 CLR 515</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/19.html</AustLII>
<text>8 In my opinion, s 31A applies to the present strikeout application. The provision is of a procedural rather than substantive nature. In Rodway v The Queen [1990] HCA 19 ; (1990) 169 CLR 515 the High Court was concerned with the appellant's convictions for certain sexual offences. At the time of the alleged offences the Criminal Code (Tas) required corroboration of the evidence of the complainant but by the time of the trial that requirement had been repealed. The High Court upheld the ruling of the trial judge (Neasey J) and the Court of Criminal Appeal that the repealed provision did not apply. After citing the statement of Dixon CJ in Maxwell v Murphy [1957] HCA 7 ; (1957) 96 CLR 261 at 267, Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said at 521:
 
 'But ordinarily an amendment to the practice and procedure of a court, including the admissibility of evidence and the effect to be given to evidence, will not operate retrospectively so as to impair any existing right. It may govern the way in which the right is to be enforced or vindicated, but that does not bring it within the presumption against retrospectivity."

9 In the present case the language of the provision clearly directs attention to the time at which the strikeout application is made (where the party "is defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding"). The substantive rights of Ms Duncan which came into existence in October 2005, eg her right to damages for any breach of contract, have not been affected. The present case is not in principle distinguishable from Rodway .

10 The statement of claim alleges in par 1 that Ms Duncan was responsible for the day to day management of the Service and had been its Director since appointment by the first respondent on or about 24 September 2001. It is said that at all material times Lipscombe Child Care was engaged in trade or commerce by conducting the business of a child care service.

11 Paragraph 5 alleges a contract of employment (the Contract) made on 24 September 2001 whereby Lipscombe Child Care retained the applicant as Director of the Service. In par 6 a number of terms of the Contract are pleaded, including: 
 
 "(d) That in the event of a grievance, a grievance procedure set forth in a document entitled Grievance Policy would be followed. The Grievance Policy formed part of the Contract of Employment and provided, inter alia : 
 
 
 (i) That the grievances should be, if possible, resolved informally with respect for other employees being maintained at all times; 
 (ii) Confidentiality would be maintained at all times and formal and informal discussions with respect to the employee would be conducted in strict confidence; 
 (iii) Disclosure information relating to the grievance would be limited to those people legitimately involved in the process, namely the Complainant and the Respondent or its Delegate: 
 (iv) If the grievance could not be resolved on an informal level a moderator would be involved and where appropriate such moderator would be drawn from the Lipscombe Child Care Service Board of Directors: 
 (v) At the conclusion of the formal grievance procedure, the processes and outcomes would be recorded in separate and confidential grievance files."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Maxwell v Murphy [1957] HCA 7 ; (1957) 96 CLR 261 at 267</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1957/7.html</AustLII>
<text>8 In my opinion, s 31A applies to the present strikeout application. The provision is of a procedural rather than substantive nature. In Rodway v The Queen [1990] HCA 19 ; (1990) 169 CLR 515 the High Court was concerned with the appellant's convictions for certain sexual offences. At the time of the alleged offences the Criminal Code (Tas) required corroboration of the evidence of the complainant but by the time of the trial that requirement had been repealed. The High Court upheld the ruling of the trial judge (Neasey J) and the Court of Criminal Appeal that the repealed provision did not apply. After citing the statement of Dixon CJ in Maxwell v Murphy [1957] HCA 7 ; (1957) 96 CLR 261 at 267, Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said at 521:
 
 'But ordinarily an amendment to the practice and procedure of a court, including the admissibility of evidence and the effect to be given to evidence, will not operate retrospectively so as to impair any existing right. It may govern the way in which the right is to be enforced or vindicated, but that does not bring it within the presumption against retrospectivity."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brambles Holdings Pty Ltd v Bathurst City Council [2001] NSWCA 61 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 153 at 177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2001/61.html</AustLII>
<text>26 On its face, the Grievance Procedure came into existence long after the Contract. There is before the Court a formal document headed "Contract of Employment" signed by Ms Duncan and the President of the Management Committee to which is attached a "Position Description and the Staff Policy". Included in the latter is a requirement for the Director to
 
 "Be responsible for human resources management in the Service, including staff appointments, supervision, evaluation, support and training, and OH&amp;S." 


Sometimes it can be difficult to locate an offer and acceptance and, in an ongoing relationship, it is not always easy to point to the precise moment when the legal criteria of a contract have been fulfilled: Brambles Holdings Pty Ltd v Bathurst City Council [2001] NSWCA 61 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 153 at 177, Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corporation (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11,110 at 11,1178. However, the present case is one where there is a formal, written contract of employment, quite detailed and complete in itself, entered into at the commencement of Ms Duncan's employment. The Grievance Procedure was not part of the Contract when it was formed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corporation (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11,110 at 11,1178</tocase>
<text>26 On its face, the Grievance Procedure came into existence long after the Contract. There is before the Court a formal document headed "Contract of Employment" signed by Ms Duncan and the President of the Management Committee to which is attached a "Position Description and the Staff Policy". Included in the latter is a requirement for the Director to
 
 "Be responsible for human resources management in the Service, including staff appointments, supervision, evaluation, support and training, and OH&amp;S." 


Sometimes it can be difficult to locate an offer and acceptance and, in an ongoing relationship, it is not always easy to point to the precise moment when the legal criteria of a contract have been fulfilled: Brambles Holdings Pty Ltd v Bathurst City Council [2001] NSWCA 61 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 153 at 177, Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corporation (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11,110 at 11,1178. However, the present case is one where there is a formal, written contract of employment, quite detailed and complete in itself, entered into at the commencement of Ms Duncan's employment. The Grievance Procedure was not part of the Contract when it was formed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Concrete Constructions (NSW) Pty Ltd v Nelson [1990] HCA 17 ; (1990) 169 CLR 594</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/17.html</AustLII>
<text>31 The respondents submit that the conduct alleged was not in trade or commerce. In Concrete Constructions (NSW) Pty Ltd v Nelson [1990] HCA 17 ; (1990) 169 CLR 594 a worker was injured as a result of his foreman wrongly telling him that grates in an air-conditioning shaft were secured by bolts. He brought a s 52 claim based on misleading and deceptive conduct by the foreman, for which the employer was vicariously liable. In the view of the majority (Mason CJ, Dawson, Deane and Gaudron JJ) at 604-605, the foreman's statement was not made in the course of, or for the purposes of, some trading or commercial dealing between the corporation and the particular employee. The conduct of the foreman "consisted of an internal communication by one employee to another employee in the course of their ordinary activities in and about the construction of a building".

32 The application of the Concrete Constructions principle to conduct concerning contracts of employment has resulted in a divergence of Federal Court authority. In Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389 Wilcox J held that information supplied to an employee in the course of negotiating a variation to his contract of employment was "in trade or commerce". In Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501, a case concerning negotiations for a new contract of employment, Finkelstein J came to the same view. Both these cases were strikeout applications and thus were governed at the time they were decided by the Dey and General Steel authorities; their Honours could only strike out the claim if it was hopeless or bound to fail.

34 Had this question arisen under the former strikeout standard, it would be very difficult to say this part of the case was hopeless, given the divergence of authority. However, s 31A is a clear, and different, command. I am still of the view that the application of Concrete Constructions in Martin was correct and that, accordingly, Ms Duncan has no reasonable prospect of success. Paragraphs 29, 30, 31 and 34 will be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389</tocase>
<text>32 The application of the Concrete Constructions principle to conduct concerning contracts of employment has resulted in a divergence of Federal Court authority. In Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389 Wilcox J held that information supplied to an employee in the course of negotiating a variation to his contract of employment was "in trade or commerce". In Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501, a case concerning negotiations for a new contract of employment, Finkelstein J came to the same view. Both these cases were strikeout applications and thus were governed at the time they were decided by the Dey and General Steel authorities; their Honours could only strike out the claim if it was hopeless or bound to fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501</tocase>
<text>32 The application of the Concrete Constructions principle to conduct concerning contracts of employment has resulted in a divergence of Federal Court authority. In Barto v GPR Management Services Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 389 Wilcox J held that information supplied to an employee in the course of negotiating a variation to his contract of employment was "in trade or commerce". In Stoelwinder v Southern Health Care Network (2000) 177 ALR 501, a case concerning negotiations for a new contract of employment, Finkelstein J came to the same view. Both these cases were strikeout applications and thus were governed at the time they were decided by the Dey and General Steel authorities; their Honours could only strike out the claim if it was hopeless or bound to fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Martin v Tasmania Development and Resources (1999) 163 ALR 79</tocase>
<text>33 In Martin v Tasmania Development and Resources (1999) 163 ALR 79, Mr Martin claimed that a letter stating that his termination was necessary on the basis of "operational requirements" was misleading and deceptive and contravened s 52. At the trial of the action I found that there were in fact "operational requirements" within the meaning of that term in the contract of employment: 163 ALR at [55]-[67]. Mr Martin succeeded on other grounds, not relevant for present purposes. However, I held that if the representations as to operational requirements were misleading and deceptive, they would not have been made in trade or commerce. In expressing disagreement with Wilcox J, I said (at [77]):
 
 "The majority in (Concrete Constructions) clearly rejected the wider construction of 'in trade or commerce', which would extend to virtually any activity of a corporation. It is true that a building company could not earn income unless it had workers who received instructions from foremen. But that was not enough to bring the alleged misrepresentation within the concept of 'trade or commerce'. Similarly, TDR could not carry out its activities of promoting Tasmanian trade and development (which activities themselves I assume for present purposes to be in trade or commerce) unless it engaged staff. Nevertheless such engagements and the necessary associated incidental negotiations, however necessary, are not in themselves of a trading or commercial nature. They are internal affairs of TDR." 


In Mulcahy v Hydro-Electric Commission (1998) 85 FCR 170 at 212-213, another final hearing, a case concerning alleged misrepresentations by an employer to employees about superannuation entitlements, I took the same view.

34 Had this question arisen under the former strikeout standard, it would be very difficult to say this part of the case was hopeless, given the divergence of authority. However, s 31A is a clear, and different, command. I am still of the view that the application of Concrete Constructions in Martin was correct and that, accordingly, Ms Duncan has no reasonable prospect of success. Paragraphs 29, 30, 31 and 34 will be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Mulcahy v Hydro-Electric Commission (1998) 85 FCR 170 at 212-213</tocase>
<text>33 In Martin v Tasmania Development and Resources (1999) 163 ALR 79, Mr Martin claimed that a letter stating that his termination was necessary on the basis of "operational requirements" was misleading and deceptive and contravened s 52. At the trial of the action I found that there were in fact "operational requirements" within the meaning of that term in the contract of employment: 163 ALR at [55]-[67]. Mr Martin succeeded on other grounds, not relevant for present purposes. However, I held that if the representations as to operational requirements were misleading and deceptive, they would not have been made in trade or commerce. In expressing disagreement with Wilcox J, I said (at [77]):
 
 "The majority in (Concrete Constructions) clearly rejected the wider construction of 'in trade or commerce', which would extend to virtually any activity of a corporation. It is true that a building company could not earn income unless it had workers who received instructions from foremen. But that was not enough to bring the alleged misrepresentation within the concept of 'trade or commerce'. Similarly, TDR could not carry out its activities of promoting Tasmanian trade and development (which activities themselves I assume for present purposes to be in trade or commerce) unless it engaged staff. Nevertheless such engagements and the necessary associated incidental negotiations, however necessary, are not in themselves of a trading or commercial nature. They are internal affairs of TDR." 


In Mulcahy v Hydro-Electric Commission (1998) 85 FCR 170 at 212-213, another final hearing, a case concerning alleged misrepresentations by an employer to employees about superannuation entitlements, I took the same view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at [6] - [8] , [42]-[46]</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/18.html</AustLII>
<text>37 In any event, unconscionable in s 51AA does not mean unfair or reprehensible in a colloquial sense. Rather, as explained in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at [6] - [8] , [42]-[46], it refers to the equitable doctrine, the meaning of which has been expounded in High Court cases such as Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 and Commercial Bank of Australia Ltd v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 457. In the present case there is no complaint that the respondents exploited any special disadvantage of Ms Lipscombe in respect of the formation of the Contract and her engagement as Director. If the respondents' termination of the Contract amounted to a breach, the ordinary contractual remedies would be available. If the publication of the termination letter amounted to defamation, she will have, as she alleges, a good cause of action.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 and Commercial Bank of Australia Ltd v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 457</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1954/79.html</AustLII>
<text>37 In any event, unconscionable in s 51AA does not mean unfair or reprehensible in a colloquial sense. Rather, as explained in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at [6] - [8] , [42]-[46], it refers to the equitable doctrine, the meaning of which has been expounded in High Court cases such as Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 and Commercial Bank of Australia Ltd v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 457. In the present case there is no complaint that the respondents exploited any special disadvantage of Ms Lipscombe in respect of the formation of the Contract and her engagement as Director. If the respondents' termination of the Contract amounted to a breach, the ordinary contractual remedies would be available. If the publication of the termination letter amounted to defamation, she will have, as she alleges, a good cause of action.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commercial Bank of Australia Ltd v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 457</tocase>
<text>37 In any event, unconscionable in s 51AA does not mean unfair or reprehensible in a colloquial sense. Rather, as explained in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at [6] - [8] , [42]-[46], it refers to the equitable doctrine, the meaning of which has been expounded in High Court cases such as Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 and Commercial Bank of Australia Ltd v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 457. In the present case there is no complaint that the respondents exploited any special disadvantage of Ms Lipscombe in respect of the formation of the Contract and her engagement as Director. If the respondents' termination of the Contract amounted to a breach, the ordinary contractual remedies would be available. If the publication of the termination letter amounted to defamation, she will have, as she alleges, a good cause of action.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Burgundy Royale Investments Pty Ltd v Westpac Banking Corporation (1987) 18 FCR 212 at 219</tocase>
<text>40 But even if the federal claims are struck out, this Court will not be deprived of jurisdiction over the non-federal claims unless it can be shown that the former were "colourable", that is they were made for the improper purpose of fabricating jurisdiction: Burgundy Royale Investments Pty Ltd v Westpac Banking Corporation (1987) 18 FCR 212 at 219. This is a serious allegation. I did not understand it to have been put by the respondents. In any case, there is no basis for it. In particular, the s 52 claims would have appeared to have had some support from first instance judgements, at least in the light of the strikeout standard which applied when the proceeding was commenced.

41 Paragraphs 23-34 of the statement of claim will be struck out. The respondents will have leave to file and serve an amended defence on or before 12 May 2006. The directions hearing is adjourned to 6 June 2006 at 9.30 am. The applicant is to pay the respondents' costs of the strikeout application.
 

 I certify that the preceding forty one (41) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey . 


Associate:

Dated: 


 Counsel for the Applicant: W A Ayliffe 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Jo Matthews 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: R E Hudson 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondents: Butler McIntyre &amp; Butler 
 
 Date of Hearing: 17 March 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 28 April 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/458.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>