<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Enano v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 426 (21 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/426.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Xiang v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 64</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/64.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The appellant noted the Federal Magistrate's comment (at [16]) that it was not clear that any error would have affected the MRT's decision because the appellant was required to continue to satisfy the requirements of the visa at the time of decision. Referring to Xiang v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 64 (" Xiang "), the appellant submitted that his Honour was in error in this regard.

14 In support of her second ground of appeal, the appellant argued that the MRT wrongly failed to have regard to the subjective aspect of the relevant regulation. Counsel cited Biyiksiz v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 814 (" Biyiksiz ") and Xiang . In Biyiksiz , Gray J held (at [20]) that "the words 'cannot reasonably be obtained' must be construed by reference to the reasonableness from the point of view of the person requiring assistance, and not only by reference to the reasonable availability of the assistance from other sources." The appellant submitted that the MRT and the learned Federal Magistrate erred by failing to consider whether other sources of assistance were reasonably available from the point of view of the nominator.

18 First, I reject the appellant's submission that the MRT failed to have regard to the subjective element of the regulation. In particular, fairly read, the MRT's decision is consistent with the reasoning of Gray J in Biyiksiz and the Full Court's decision in Xiang .

21 The facts of this case can be distinguished from those in Biyiksiz and there is nothing in Xiang that would suggest error here. In this case, the MRT focussed on the availability of assistance from other family members. Importantly, the MRT noted that, at the time of application, the nominator was living with one of her other children and other children lived nearby. The appellant did not hold a driver's licence and thus another child transported the nominator by car. Also, one of the nominator's other daughters had recently sponsored him for an aged parent visa. In these circumstances, it was plainly open to the MRT not to be satisfied that the requisite assistance could not reasonably be obtained from one or more of his other children in Australia or public services.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Biyiksiz v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 814</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/814.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In support of her second ground of appeal, the appellant argued that the MRT wrongly failed to have regard to the subjective aspect of the relevant regulation. Counsel cited Biyiksiz v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 814 (" Biyiksiz ") and Xiang . In Biyiksiz , Gray J held (at [20]) that "the words 'cannot reasonably be obtained' must be construed by reference to the reasonableness from the point of view of the person requiring assistance, and not only by reference to the reasonable availability of the assistance from other sources." The appellant submitted that the MRT and the learned Federal Magistrate erred by failing to consider whether other sources of assistance were reasonably available from the point of view of the nominator.

18 First, I reject the appellant's submission that the MRT failed to have regard to the subjective element of the regulation. In particular, fairly read, the MRT's decision is consistent with the reasoning of Gray J in Biyiksiz and the Full Court's decision in Xiang .

19 In Biyiksiz , the nominator was an elderly woman of a Kurdish Alevi background. She spoke no English, speaking Kurdish and a rare dialect of Turkish. The visa applicant had raised the concern that, if her mother was placed in a nursing home, her mother would be unable to communicate with the staff or other residents. The MRT had found that, regardless of these potential difficulties, places were available in nursing home facilities: see Biyiksiz at [14].

20 Gray J found (at [22]) that the MRT fell into error because it "considered the question whether assistance could reasonably be obtained from welfare, hospital, nursing or community services from the point of view of the availability of assistance from those services, and did not consider whether the assistance was reasonably obtainable by the applicant's mother from those services". His Honour noted (at [17]) that, in Australia health and welfare services are highly developed. As a result, if the mere availability of assistance from those services meant that assistance was reasonably obtainable, then "there would be very few, if any, [special need] visas granted". Accordingly, Gray J held that the MRT should consider not simply whether other sources of assistance were available, but whether it was reasonable for the nominator to obtain such assistance.

21 The facts of this case can be distinguished from those in Biyiksiz and there is nothing in Xiang that would suggest error here. In this case, the MRT focussed on the availability of assistance from other family members. Importantly, the MRT noted that, at the time of application, the nominator was living with one of her other children and other children lived nearby. The appellant did not hold a driver's licence and thus another child transported the nominator by car. Also, one of the nominator's other daughters had recently sponsored him for an aged parent visa. In these circumstances, it was plainly open to the MRT not to be satisfied that the requisite assistance could not reasonably be obtained from one or more of his other children in Australia or public services.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Truong v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1035</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/1035.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The first respondent submitted that, contrary to the appellant's submission, the appellant had to make out both grounds of appeal in order to have the MRT's decision set aside. Referring to Truong v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1035 , the first respondent submitted that it was legitimate for the MRT to take into account evidence of events subsequent to the time of application if that evidence is probative of the relevant facts at the earlier time. The first respondent argued that, even if such evidence were not relevant, the MRT's error would, at most, be an error of fact. The first respondent also submitted that it was open to the MRT to regard the appellant's subsequent employment as relevant to her ability to provide continuing as well as substantial assistance as at the date of application. Further, the first respondent contended that, when regard was had to the context of the contested findings, it was clear that the MRT was referring to the correct date, which was the date of application.

16 With respect to the second ground of appeal, the first respondent submitted that there is no indication that the MRT did not consider the "reasonable obtainability" of assistance by the nominator as opposed to the "reasonable availability" of such assistance. Further, the MRT's conclusion was plainly open to it on the factual findings that it had made.

23 Further, I reject the appellant's submission that the MRT relevantly erred when it relied on her subsequent employment history as probative, as at the date of application, of a need to work and her ability to provide the requisite continuing (and substantial) assistance. There is no reason why subsequent events cannot shed light on the circumstances as they existed at an earlier time. For example, "medical reports, later in time to earlier medical reports concerning the same person, may serve the evidentiary function of establishing the pre-existence of illnesses, disabilities or other physical or metaphysical conditions, for which there may or may not have been symptoms already manifest at the time of earlier reports": Koulaxazov v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 75 at [38] per Conti J; also Truong at [40] per Weinberg J. Moreover, a logical error in reasoning does not amount to jurisdictional error: see, e.g., VWST v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [14] - [18] per Kiefel, Marshall and Downes JJ. I find that the MRT made no logical or legal error when it considered subsequent events as probative of earlier facts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Zahid v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 670</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/670.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In order to succeed on this appeal, the appellant must succeed on both the grounds that she advanced. This is because the appellant must satisfy each requirement of the visa to be eligible: see, e.g, Zahid v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 670 at [29] per Sackville J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>22 It would be wrong to find error simply because the MRT failed to note explicitly that it was not just considering whether other sources of assistance were available but was directing its attention to whether the nominator could reasonably obtain such assistance. A reviewing court should not read the MRT's decision overly finely with an eye attuned to the perception of error: see Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 271-272 and 291 per Kirby J. Taking the reasons as a whole, there are no grounds to conclude that the MRT failed to address the correct question when it considered whether other forms of assistance could be reasonably obtained by the nominator. In fact, it is clear that the MRT did address the correct question and made its finding consonant with it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Koulaxazov v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 75</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/75.html</AustLII>
<text>23 Further, I reject the appellant's submission that the MRT relevantly erred when it relied on her subsequent employment history as probative, as at the date of application, of a need to work and her ability to provide the requisite continuing (and substantial) assistance. There is no reason why subsequent events cannot shed light on the circumstances as they existed at an earlier time. For example, "medical reports, later in time to earlier medical reports concerning the same person, may serve the evidentiary function of establishing the pre-existence of illnesses, disabilities or other physical or metaphysical conditions, for which there may or may not have been symptoms already manifest at the time of earlier reports": Koulaxazov v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 75 at [38] per Conti J; also Truong at [40] per Weinberg J. Moreover, a logical error in reasoning does not amount to jurisdictional error: see, e.g., VWST v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [14] - [18] per Kiefel, Marshall and Downes JJ. I find that the MRT made no logical or legal error when it considered subsequent events as probative of earlier facts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>VWST v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/286.html</AustLII>
<text>23 Further, I reject the appellant's submission that the MRT relevantly erred when it relied on her subsequent employment history as probative, as at the date of application, of a need to work and her ability to provide the requisite continuing (and substantial) assistance. There is no reason why subsequent events cannot shed light on the circumstances as they existed at an earlier time. For example, "medical reports, later in time to earlier medical reports concerning the same person, may serve the evidentiary function of establishing the pre-existence of illnesses, disabilities or other physical or metaphysical conditions, for which there may or may not have been symptoms already manifest at the time of earlier reports": Koulaxazov v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 75 at [38] per Conti J; also Truong at [40] per Weinberg J. Moreover, a logical error in reasoning does not amount to jurisdictional error: see, e.g., VWST v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 286 at [14] - [18] per Kiefel, Marshall and Downes JJ. I find that the MRT made no logical or legal error when it considered subsequent events as probative of earlier facts.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>