<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Spalla v St George Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 416 (18 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/416.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2001) 205 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/63.html</AustLII>
<text>5 Mr Spalla argued that, considered together, these factors would suggest to a reasonable lay observer that I had prejudged his credibility and the issues in this case. He suggested that, under the test established in Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2001) 205 CLR 337 (" Ebner ") and Johnson v Johnson [2000] HCA 48 ; (2000) 201 CLR 488 (" Johnson "), I should disqualify myself from the further hearing in the case.

7 The governing principle in determining whether a judge is disqualified on the ground of apprehended bias is "whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question the judge is required to decide": Johnson at 492 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ. The focus of this test is whether an observer might conclude that the judge would decide a case "other than on its legal and factual merits": Ebner at 345 per Gleason CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ.

8 The High Court has emphasised that judges should not be overly hasty in acceding to motions to disqualify. This is because judges "have a duty to exercise their judicial functions when ... they are assigned to cases in accordance with the practice which prevails in the court to which they belong": Ebner at 348. This ensures that litigants do not have the opportunity to select their judges (and that judges do not select their cases).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Johnson v Johnson [2000] HCA 48 ; (2000) 201 CLR 488</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/48.html</AustLII>
<text>5 Mr Spalla argued that, considered together, these factors would suggest to a reasonable lay observer that I had prejudged his credibility and the issues in this case. He suggested that, under the test established in Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2001) 205 CLR 337 (" Ebner ") and Johnson v Johnson [2000] HCA 48 ; (2000) 201 CLR 488 (" Johnson "), I should disqualify myself from the further hearing in the case.

7 The governing principle in determining whether a judge is disqualified on the ground of apprehended bias is "whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question the judge is required to decide": Johnson at 492 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ. The focus of this test is whether an observer might conclude that the judge would decide a case "other than on its legal and factual merits": Ebner at 345 per Gleason CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ.

9 In this matter, the applicant has identified no factors which, considered individually or cumulatively, warrant my disqualification. The High Court has stressed that the reasonableness of any complaint of apprehended bias is "to be considered in the context of ordinary judicial practice": Johnson at 493. Thus, events occurring within the ordinary course of litigation will not give rise to an apprehension of bias. As the High Court has explained, "modern judges, responding to a need for more active case management, intervene in the conduct of cases to an extent that may surprise a person who came to court expecting a judge to remain, until the moment of pronouncement of judgment, as inscrutable as the Sphinx": Johnson at 493. As a case progresses, a judge may make rulings, as needs be, on adjournment applications, the admissibility of evidence, the amendment of pleadings and the like but the fact that the ruling may suit the immediate interests of one side rather than the other does not mean that the judge has formed any concluded view about the ultimate merits of the case. From time to time, a judge may also indicate to counsel that she or he is taking some necessarily tentative view on an issue. The reason for this is most often to allow counsel an opportunity to deal with the problem that the judge perceives, whether rightly or wrongly, to lie in counsel's way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Antoun v The Queen [2006] HCA 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>10 As the High Court's judgment in Antoun v The Queen [2006] HCA 2 indicates, there remain limits on the manner in which a judge may conduct a case even allowing for modern case management practices. In the present case, however, the applicant has identified what are for the most part rulings that are commonplace in many trials.

11 Mr Spalla first raised the issue of my decision to continue with the hearing despite the illness of his senior counsel. As the respondents noted, this was a qualified decision. After a colloquy with the applicant's junior counsel (who has apparently over ten year's experience at the bar) I ruled that the hearing should continue in order that the applicant might present his evidence in chief notwithstanding the absence of senior counsel. The applicant's counsel apparently conceded that he could cope with the presentation of evidence in chief although not cross-examination. I ruled that I would adjourn the hearing, if needs be, to allow the applicant the benefit of senior counsel in the cross-examination of the respondents' witnesses. A date was nominated, which was available to the Court, and, on the information before me at that time, gave the applicant a sufficient opportunity to order his affairs. The respondents opposed any adjournment. My decision favoured neither party. It was a straightforward example of case management, which took account of the interests of all parties, as well as broader interests in the timely progression of cases in order that other litigants might also be heard. Decisions such as these are routine and are not proper bases for disqualifying the trial judge.

12 Similar considerations apply to Mr Spalla's complaints about my rulings concerning the admissibility of his affidavit of 1 June 2005 and his application for leave to amend further his notice of motion. The rulings have not been as Mr Spalla wanted.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>