<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2006] FCA 460 (28 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/460.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/34.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The respondents nevertheless submitted that the facts necessary to induce the state of mind (reasonable grounds) must be established on the balance of probabilities. However, as soon as evidence is adduced that shows that on the balance of probabilities there was not a serious and imminent risk to air safety, then the evidentiary burden shifts back to the applicant. The respondents also submitted that the well-known principles in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 (' Briginshaw ') at 361-3 are applicable.

24 Although in the present case there was time for a full investigation to take place, ordinarily the legislature's evident contemplation was that the Court will have the task of forming its judgment on incomplete materials. Thus a reasonably sanguine view must be taken of the way in which reasonable people might differ in their approach to matters. So, even if the Court took the view that a serious and imminent risk to air safety were not affirmatively proven on the balance of probabilities, in my opinion the Court nevertheless should be cautious, if there be some evidence of relevant matters for concern, before concluding that there is no reasonable ground for belief.

62 As to the ease with which the Court should be satisfied of matters adverse to them, the respondents submitted that, given the seriousness of the consequences for their reputation and livelihood of adverse findings, the evidentiary principles in Briginshaw at 361-3 are applicable. I disagree. The proceedings are primarily protective of the public, notwithstanding that fairness to impugned authorisation holders is an important part of the process. Further, any adverse finding that the Court might make is provisional only: it would merely assert that there are reasonable grounds for believing that some conduct had been in contravention of the statutory requirement. It would be inconsistent with the statutory commands to the Court to consider 'reasonable grounds to believe' and to give safety the primary emphasis to require that the Court only act on proofs which are not 'inexact', testimony which is not 'indefinite' and inferences which are not 'indirect' (see Briginshaw at 362).

63 Mr Boatman was in his sixties, and an extremely well-qualified and experienced pilot in relation to bush flying, including in relation to the use of narrow and curved runways. He had over 12 000 hours of flying experience, mostly in light single-engine aircraft such as Cessnas, accumulated over a period of 40-odd years. He had been to Innamincka and other like remote places before. He had many years, and thousands of hours of experience in instructing trainee pilots and licensed pilots in advanced safe handling techniques. For 14 years he had conducted an advanced safe handling course, training pilots in relation to using airstrips with difficult approaches, upslopes, downslopes and undulations, including landings and take-offs on curved strips, and using strips narrower than the road at Innamincka. He had, among other things, at the request of a Papua New Guinea commercial airline operator, trained some 50 pilots for operations in the notoriously difficult airstrips and conditions there.

64 Mr Boatman had also trained Ms Kennedy in such specialised techniques including take-offs and landings into strips much more difficult, in Mr Boatman's opinion, than would be the road at Innamincka. Ms Kennedy had some four years' flying experience, including 'reasonable experience flying in the outback and in respect of operations from unmade surfaces and marginal areas'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 336 ; (2004) 139 FCR 444</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/336.html</AustLII>
<text>9 However, this matter has followed a much more protracted course. Prior to the substantive issue being heard, the matter was twice before a Full Federal Court, first in relation to the validity of s 30DE of the Act, the validity of the section being upheld: Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 165 (' CASA No 1 '); and secondly, in relation to confusion over consent orders that are not relevant to the present proceedings: Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 336 ; (2004) 139 FCR 444 (' CASA No 2 ').</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/165.html</AustLII>
<text>9 However, this matter has followed a much more protracted course. Prior to the substantive issue being heard, the matter was twice before a Full Federal Court, first in relation to the validity of s 30DE of the Act, the validity of the section being upheld: Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 165 (' CASA No 1 '); and secondly, in relation to confusion over consent orders that are not relevant to the present proceedings: Civil Aviation Safety Authority v Boatman [2004] FCAFC 336 ; (2004) 139 FCR 444 (' CASA No 2 ').</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fleming v Hutchinson (1991) 66 ALJR 211</tocase>
<text>33 In relation to the third factor of potential consequences, the applicant contended that the 'word "serious" imports a test which is relative to the range of possible risks'. It is a question of degree: see Fleming v Hutchinson (1991) 66 ALJR 211 at 211 per Mason CJ, Brennan and Dawson JJ, albeit in a different context, where it was said by McGarvie J that 'elements of fact, degree and judgement are involved'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>George v Rockett (1990) 170 CLR 140</tocase>
<text>19 The applicant further relied on George v Rockett [1990] HCA 26 ; (1990) 170 CLR 104 (' Rockett ') at 116:
 
 'The objective circumstances sufficient to show a reason to believe something need to point more clearly to the subject matter of the belief, but that is not to say that the objective circumstances must establish on the balance of probabilities that the subject matter in fact occurred or exists: the assent of belief is given on more slender evidence than proof. Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting, a proposition and the grounds which can reasonably induce that inclination of the mind may, depending on the circumstances, leave something to surmise or conjecture.'

20 CASA submitted that, in deciding whether grounds are 'reasonable', emphasis is to be given to the primacy of the maintenance, enhancement and promotion of air safety, with particular emphasis on prevention of accidents and incidents. The applicant further contended that the establishment of those grounds, though objective, contemplates a reasonable person in the position of CASA, as is apparent from the reference in s 30DE(3) to ss 3A and 9A(1).

21 The principal proposition advanced by the respondents is that it cannot be the case that all that is required is 'reasonable grounds to believe' without taking account of any rebuttal evidence, as such a test would result in CASA's application being successful every time.

22 As to what is involved in 'reasonable grounds for a belief', the passage cited from Rockett is obiter as to belief because that case concerned suspicion. In any case, the respondents said that the High Court really decided in Rockett that 'reasonable grounds for believing' '[r]equires the existence of facts sufficient to induce' an actual belief (at 112-3), so that, to discharge its legal onus, while the applicant does not need to prove on the balance of probabilities that the take-offs at Innamincka constituted a serious and imminent risk to air safety, it must nevertheless prove facts sufficient to induce a belief in that proposition.

25 I do not accept that the establishment of the reasonable grounds for the necessary belief necessarily contemplates a reasonable person in the position of CASA . The point of the requisite approach to the Court is clearly to enable the Court to decide on all the materials before it, whether, objectively, there are reasonable grounds for the requisite belief. The Court is to adjudicate that matter, not CASA. It is not a mere question of considering whether CASA's view was such that no reasonable person could hold it. The Court is to form its own view of what are reasonable grounds for belief. So, the question is: regardless of whether or not there was in fact a serious and imminent risk to air safety, are reasonable grounds shown to the Court's satisfaction to induce an actual belief that there was such a risk? As the High Court said in Rockett (at [116]): 
 
 'Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting, a proposition and the grounds which can reasonably induce that inclination of the mind may, depending on the circumstances, leave something to surmise or conjecture.'

26 Whereas the fact of such a risk need not be established, it will not, on the other hand, be sufficient to show reasonable grounds for a mere suspicion, even a serious suspicion, that there was a risk of the relevant kind.

27 If the judge is moved by all the evidence to conclude that there was in fact such a risk, it will follow that there were reasonable grounds for that belief. If not, the judge must consider whether, nevertheless, there are, in the judge's opinion, reasonable grounds for so believing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Kennelly v Incitec Ltd [1998] FCA 1470</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1998/1470.html</AustLII>
<text>34 Further, the applicant drew an analogy with Kennelly v Incitec Ltd [1998] FCA 1470 (' Kennelly '). In that case, Mr Kennelly was an experienced 'versatile operator' of an elevator used to transport fertilizer to the top of a tower approximately five storeys high. He was dismissed for conduct said to be such as to cause 'imminent and serious risk' to the 'safety, of a person' within the meaning of reg 30CA of the Workplace Relations Regulations 1989 (Cth). The central feature of the impugned conduct of Mr Kennelly was the removal of a 'danger tag' on the head roller of the elevator without ensuring by inspection that it was safe to commence the operation of the elevator. Spender J said (at 15-16):
 
 '...in my opinion, it remains plain that his failure to ensure that the machinery, which the danger tag indicated had been the subject of fitter repairs, was in a position properly to be started, is an act that involved the risk of very serious injury to any person working on or in the vicinity of the machine at the time of it start up. The failure to inspect the machine was a serious breach of Mr Kennelly's obligations in the operation of the systems dealing with safety in the workplace. Such visual inspection as he performed was wholly insufficient to discharge his responsibilities in the circumstances, and the fact that fortunately no person was injured or killed as a result of the operation of the elevator on that morning cannot affect the conclusion that the start up in the circumstances involved a serious risk of injury . 
 
 "Risk" is defined in the Macquarie Dictionary to include "exposure to the chance of injury or loss; a hazard or dangerous chance; to expose to the chance of injury or loss, or hazard". It is clear on the evidence that Mr Kennelly exposed employees and maintenance workers to the chance of injury or loss in removing the danger tag and operating the elevator without performing the physical inspection of the head roller on the morning of 8 September 1997, and satisfying himself that it was safe to remove the danger tag and operate the elevator. There was the possibility that such persons might be working on, or in the vicinity of, the head roller, when Mr Kennelly removed the danger tag and commenced the operation of the head roller.' (emphasis added)

35 The applicant said the following can be taken from this case:
 
 (i) it is the risk that must be imminent, not the actuality of the occurrence; and
 (ii) the occasioning of the means by which the risk may be manifested (that is, the operation of an aircraft) affects the imminence of the risk.

36 The respondents submitted that both 'serious' and 'imminent' import the notion, in their context, of a high probability of a risk being realised, whether or not it is in fact realized. Where that high probability is missing (as in the present case, on the respondents' submission), no matter how catastrophic the potential consequences, a risk cannot be characterized as a serious and imminent risk to air safety.

37 The respondents submitted that the meaning of the phrase 'serious and imminent risk to air safety' should be determined by reference to its context in Division 3A of the Act. Given the scope of reg 269 of the CAR (see para [11] above), Division 3A should be confined to the hopefully exceptional circumstance of serious and imminent risk to air safety.

38 The respondents submit that the notion of 'serious risk' has two limbs to it.
 
 (i) The seriousness of the risk is principally, but not solely, related to the probability of the risk being realised; and (ii) In the context of s 30DB, it must also relate to the significance of the consequence: a high chance of quite minor harm occurring is not what the section is aimed at.

39 As to 'imminent', this necessarily entails not only that there is a high probability of the risk being realised, but that that risk is one that may be realised in a short time frame, that is, very soon.

40 The respondents submitted that the case of the applicant focused on the magnitude of the potential consequences, and not on the probabilities of such consequences being realised. In the present case, the respondents cast no doubt upon the potential seriousness of the consequences, but said that there was only an 'outside' (to use a word discussed in argument) or remote chance that such consequences would materialize. Therefore there was not a 'serious risk'.

41 The respondents say that if there were a strong chance of some quite minor harm, that is not what the section is concerned with. Neither, if there were a miniscule chance of major harm, is such the concern of the section. All flying involves a degree of risk. A really significant chance of significant harm occurring is what the section contemplates.

42 In CASA No 1 , Sundberg J observed at [15]: 'The power conferred by s 30DE is no different in its nature from that routinely exercised by a court of determining whether a motor vehicle is being driven dangerously, recklessly or negligently' .

56 In Kennelly a danger tag was attached to grain-elevating machinery having the capacity, if it malfunctioned, to threaten safety. The purpose of the tag was to indicate that a danger existed if the machinery were started before a competent person had indicated that it was safe to do so. A supervising employee removed the tag without ensuring by inspection that it was safe to put the equipment into operation. Thus, in the face of a clear indication that a dangerous situation might exist, a person responsible for making an inspection to see whether that dangerous situation did exist, failed to do so. His Honour's finding that this was conduct that caused 'imminent, and serious, risk' to safety commands respect.

57 That case is different from the present. In Kennelly there was no doubt that a dangerous situation existed. The worker did not take a readily available step to confirm or dispel the warning offered by the danger tag. Here, the question is whether there are reasonable grounds to believe that such elevation of the risks in taking-off as occurred was in the actual circumstances prevailing, 'serious' and whether, the steps taken to recognise and avert any such risks were sufficient to render the risks, in their context, less than 'serious'. As will appear, in my view, reasonable grounds do not exist to believe that the elevation of the risks given the steps taken by the experienced pilots in the interests of their own and their passengers' safety constituted a serious risk to air safety.

58 The respondents submitted: 
 
 'Realisation of a risk which was no more than an "outside chance" would not necessarily be caught by section 30DB. For example: 
 
 a) consider a landing aircraft which collided with an aircraft which was positioned adjacent to the runway at a holding point but which unexpectedly moved forward on to the runway into the path of the landing aircraft. Notwithstanding the seriousness (in the sense of significance) of the consequences, this circumstance would not necessarily be conduct that constitutes, contributes to or results in a serious and imminent risk to air safety, in respect of the landing aircraft. The relevant conduct is proceeding with the landing with an aircraft adjacent to the runway (a common occurrence). There is plainly a possibility that the parked aircraft will infringe the runway. But despite that remote possibility occurring, landing an aircraft in that circumstances does not constitute, contribute to or result in encountering a serious and imminent risk to air safety. It entails encountering a remote possibility, which against the odds, materialised. 
 b) consider a single engine aircraft flying over the sea, beyond gliding distance of land. Despite the reliability of aircraft engines, they can and do fail. To undertake such a flight with a normally functioning well maintained engine, is acceptable and lawful conduct not caught by section 30DB, because to undertake such a flight is to encounter merely a remote risk to air safety, not a serious and imminent risk to air safety. This is so whether or not the engine actually fails over the water and the aircraft is forced to ditch with serious consequences.' (original emphasis)

59 While there may be less stark examples than those given of flying which constitutes a serious and imminent risk to air safety, I agree with the general thrust of the distinctions drawn.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Magdulski (1989) 40 A Crim R 154</tocase>
<text>18 CASA submitted that the requirement to establish 'reasonable grounds to believe' falls well short of a requirement to satisfy the Court that the respondents did in fact engage in conduct of the requisite character. It requires only that the Court be persuaded that, upon the evidence before it, there are grounds upon which a belief may be based that the respondent had engaged in such conduct (or is likely to engage in it). The presence of grounds to believe the contrary is not inconsistent with the presence of grounds that satisfy the test: R v Magdulski (1989) 40 A Crim R 154.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>