<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SYWB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 402 (18 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/402.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd (No 1) [1980] HCA 41 ; (1981) 147 CLR 35</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/41.html</AustLII>
<text>34 In Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd (No 1) [1980] HCA 41 ; (1981) 147 CLR 35 (' Anshun (No 1) '), the Court was concerned with an appeal from the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria which had upheld an order of McGarvie J staying forever an action by the Port of Melbourne Authority in relation to a claim by way of indemnity. His Honour had ordered a stay because he thought that it was an abuse of process to raise in subsequent proceedings matters which could and reasonably should have been litigated in earlier proceedings.

36 Gibbs J, with whom Mason and Murphy JJ agreed, said at 38:
 
 ' In support of the objection to competency before us, Mr. Griffith naturally relied upon the decision of the Privy Council in Tampion v. Anderson (1973) 48 A.L.J.R. 11; 3 A.L.R. 414, where it was held that an order staying an action on the ground that it is frivolous, vexatious and an abuse of the process of the court is an interlocutory judgment. Their Lordships in the course of their reasons refer to a number of authorities, but none of those authorities was a case in which a stay had been granted on the ground that there was an estoppel of the kind which McGarvie J. found to have been raised in the present case. 
 
 If the view expressed in Licul v. Corney (1976) 50 A.L.J.R., at p. 444 is correct, and the true test of finality is whether the judgment or order, as made, finally disposes of the rights of the parties, it would seem clear that the order made in the present case was a final judgment. It is not necessary to consider whether the view expressed in Tampion v. Anderson is one which is consistent with the view taken in the Australian authorities. There may well be a difference between a case in which the action is frivolous or vexatious in the ordinary sense, or in which the proceedings disclose no reasonable cause of action, and a case in which the abuse of process lies in an attempt to litigate an issue which is res judicata, and Tampion v. Anderson has nothing to say about a case of the latter kind.'

41 Kenny J said:
 
 '6 The distinction between an interlocutory and final judgment is not always a clear one. In this case, however, the decision of the High Court in Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd (No 1) [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35 (" Anshun (No 1) ") provides an authoritative answer. In Anshun (No 1) , the High Court unanimously held that an order that a proceeding be stayed as an abuse of process on the grounds of estoppel and res judicata was a final judgment, for the purposes of appeal. The approach of the High Court in Anshun (No 1) is equally applicable in relation to applications for leave to appeal in this Court: see, e.g., The Lardil Peoples v State of Queensland [2001] FCA 414 ; (2001) 108 FCR 453 at 480 [85] - [86] per Dowsett J. Anshun (No 1) applies with even stronger force in this case than in case of The Lardil Peoples , because the proceeding from which the current appeal is brought was dismissed on the same bases as in Anshun (No 1) .'

43 The disagreement amongst judges was adverted to by Selway J in S1000 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 285 where he said:
 
 '2 The original application made by the applicant was by Notice of Appeal. There may be some disagreement in the cases as to whether an order dismissing an action on the basis that it is vexatious and or an abuse of process is an interlocutory order, contrast Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at 4, [9] , and Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35. As the decision of the High Court in Re Luck is the most recent, I should follow it. This is consistent with other recent practice in this court. I refer, for example, to the decisions of the Full Court of this Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 , Lindsey v Philip Morris Limited [2004] FCAFC 40 , and in Johnson Tiles Pty Limited v Esso Australia Pty Limited [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2000) 104 FCR 564, [43].'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/70.html</AustLII>
<text>37 In a later decision of the High Court, Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 (' Luck '), Gleeson CJ had refused Ms Luck leave to issue a writ of summons and statement of claim which had been the subject of a direction made by Callinan J pursuant to O 58 r 4(3) of the High Court Rules. The question before the Court was whether Gleeson CJ's order was final or interlocutory.

38 The Court in Luck , after referring with approval to the dicta of Lord Evershed in Hunt v Allied Bakeries Ltd (1956) 3 All ER 513 at 514, said at [9]:
 
 'Given the long-established English rule, the decision in Tampion and our decisions in Pye, Hall, Carr and Bienstein, we see no valid reason for departing from the rule laid down in Tampion . An order is an interlocutory order, therefore, when it stays or dismisses an action or refuses leave to commence or proceed with an action because the action is frivolous, vexatious, an abuse of the process of the court or does not disclose a reasonable cause of action.'

39 Their Honours did not refer to Anshun (No 1) in Luck .

43 The disagreement amongst judges was adverted to by Selway J in S1000 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 285 where he said:
 
 '2 The original application made by the applicant was by Notice of Appeal. There may be some disagreement in the cases as to whether an order dismissing an action on the basis that it is vexatious and or an abuse of process is an interlocutory order, contrast Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at 4, [9] , and Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35. As the decision of the High Court in Re Luck is the most recent, I should follow it. This is consistent with other recent practice in this court. I refer, for example, to the decisions of the Full Court of this Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 , Lindsey v Philip Morris Limited [2004] FCAFC 40 , and in Johnson Tiles Pty Limited v Esso Australia Pty Limited [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2000) 104 FCR 564, [43].'

44 Branson J followed that decision in SZDEG v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 748 and said:
 
 '8 It does not appear that either the Full Court of this Court or the High Court has given express consideration to the present status of Anshun No 1 . I am thus placed in the difficult position of deciding which of the above decisions of my colleagues I should follow. With some hesitation, and with great respect to Kenny J, I have concluded that the view adopted by Selway J is the preferable view. The unqualified nature of the statement in Re Luck at [9] which is highlighted in [4] above seems to me to carry considerable weight as it was made in a case decided after Anshun No 1. Additionally, I note that the Full Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 placed reliance on Re Luck at [9] and made no reference to Anshun No 1.
 
 9 I conclude that the judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court in respect of which the notice of appeal was filed is an interlocutory judgment. As mentioned above, s 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) operates to prevent an appeal being brought from an interlocutory judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court unless the Court or a judge gives leave.'

45 The respondent, on this application, has urged me to follow the decisions which followed Luck rather than Anshun (No 1) . In Lashansky v Bruvecchis Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 64 , the Full Court of the Federal Court, of which I was a member (Madgwick, Lander and Crennan JJ), considered the decision of the High Court in Luck , the earlier decision of the Privy Council in Tampion v Anderson , and the earlier decision of the English Court of Appeal in Hunt v Allied Bakeries Ltd , and concluded that an order dismissing an action because it does not disclose a reasonable cause of action was interlocutory. In that case, the decision in Anshun (No 1) was not cited to the Court.

47 The High Court said in Luck at 2:
 
 'That question is answered by determining whether the legal effect of the judgment is final or not. If the legal effect of the judgment is final, it is a final order; otherwise, it is an interlocutory order.' (Footnote omitted.)

49 In those circumstances, I am disposed to follow the decisions which have followed Luck and proceed upon the basis that leave to appeal is required.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>MZWHW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 466</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/466.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In MZWHW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 466 , Kenny J was concerned with a notice of appeal and an application for leave to appeal filed in the same matter against an order of a Federal Magistrate dismissing an application for judicial review on the ground that it raised the same cause of action considered in previous proceedings for reason of res judicata or issue estoppel.

41 Kenny J said:
 
 '6 The distinction between an interlocutory and final judgment is not always a clear one. In this case, however, the decision of the High Court in Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd (No 1) [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35 (" Anshun (No 1) ") provides an authoritative answer. In Anshun (No 1) , the High Court unanimously held that an order that a proceeding be stayed as an abuse of process on the grounds of estoppel and res judicata was a final judgment, for the purposes of appeal. The approach of the High Court in Anshun (No 1) is equally applicable in relation to applications for leave to appeal in this Court: see, e.g., The Lardil Peoples v State of Queensland [2001] FCA 414 ; (2001) 108 FCR 453 at 480 [85] - [86] per Dowsett J. Anshun (No 1) applies with even stronger force in this case than in case of The Lardil Peoples , because the proceeding from which the current appeal is brought was dismissed on the same bases as in Anshun (No 1) .'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/546.html</AustLII>
<text>42 That decision was followed by Tamberlin J in SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 and Graham J in NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/975.html</AustLII>
<text>42 That decision was followed by Tamberlin J in SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 and Graham J in NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>S1000 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 285</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/285.html</AustLII>
<text>43 The disagreement amongst judges was adverted to by Selway J in S1000 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 285 where he said:
 
 '2 The original application made by the applicant was by Notice of Appeal. There may be some disagreement in the cases as to whether an order dismissing an action on the basis that it is vexatious and or an abuse of process is an interlocutory order, contrast Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at 4, [9] , and Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35. As the decision of the High Court in Re Luck is the most recent, I should follow it. This is consistent with other recent practice in this court. I refer, for example, to the decisions of the Full Court of this Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 , Lindsey v Philip Morris Limited [2004] FCAFC 40 , and in Johnson Tiles Pty Limited v Esso Australia Pty Limited [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2000) 104 FCR 564, [43].'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZDEG v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 748</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/748.html</AustLII>
<text>44 Branson J followed that decision in SZDEG v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 748 and said:
 
 '8 It does not appear that either the Full Court of this Court or the High Court has given express consideration to the present status of Anshun No 1 . I am thus placed in the difficult position of deciding which of the above decisions of my colleagues I should follow. With some hesitation, and with great respect to Kenny J, I have concluded that the view adopted by Selway J is the preferable view. The unqualified nature of the statement in Re Luck at [9] which is highlighted in [4] above seems to me to carry considerable weight as it was made in a case decided after Anshun No 1. Additionally, I note that the Full Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 placed reliance on Re Luck at [9] and made no reference to Anshun No 1.
 
 9 I conclude that the judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court in respect of which the notice of appeal was filed is an interlocutory judgment. As mentioned above, s 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) operates to prevent an appeal being brought from an interlocutory judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court unless the Court or a judge gives leave.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lashansky v Bruvecchis Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 64</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/64.html</AustLII>
<text>45 The respondent, on this application, has urged me to follow the decisions which followed Luck rather than Anshun (No 1) . In Lashansky v Bruvecchis Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 64 , the Full Court of the Federal Court, of which I was a member (Madgwick, Lander and Crennan JJ), considered the decision of the High Court in Luck , the earlier decision of the Privy Council in Tampion v Anderson , and the earlier decision of the English Court of Appeal in Hunt v Allied Bakeries Ltd , and concluded that an order dismissing an action because it does not disclose a reasonable cause of action was interlocutory. In that case, the decision in Anshun (No 1) was not cited to the Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bienstein v Bienstein [2003] HCA 7 ; (2003) 195 ALR 225</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/7.html</AustLII>
<text>37 In a later decision of the High Court, Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 (' Luck '), Gleeson CJ had refused Ms Luck leave to issue a writ of summons and statement of claim which had been the subject of a direction made by Callinan J pursuant to O 58 r 4(3) of the High Court Rules. The question before the Court was whether Gleeson CJ's order was final or interlocutory.

43 The disagreement amongst judges was adverted to by Selway J in S1000 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 285 where he said:
 
 '2 The original application made by the applicant was by Notice of Appeal. There may be some disagreement in the cases as to whether an order dismissing an action on the basis that it is vexatious and or an abuse of process is an interlocutory order, contrast Re Luck [2003] HCA 70 ; (2003) 203 ALR 1 at 4, [9] , and Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun [1980] HCA 41 ; (1980) 147 CLR 35. As the decision of the High Court in Re Luck is the most recent, I should follow it. This is consistent with other recent practice in this court. I refer, for example, to the decisions of the Full Court of this Court in Wride v Schulze [2004] FCAFC 216 , Lindsey v Philip Morris Limited [2004] FCAFC 40 , and in Johnson Tiles Pty Limited v Esso Australia Pty Limited [2000] FCA 1572 ; (2000) 104 FCR 564, [43].'

46 Of course, as the High Court has said in Bienstein v Bienstein [2003] HCA 7 ; (2003) 195 ALR 225 at 230, the test for whether an order is final or interlocutory is whether the order made finally determines the rights of the parties in the principal action before the Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MZWHN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 491</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/491.html</AustLII>
<text>48 In my opinion, the Court can have regard to the jurisdiction which was exercised by the Court below in determining whether the effect of the order which was sought is to finally determine the issues between the parties. Where the Court is exercising its summary jurisdiction to dispose of the matter without proceeding to examine the matter on its merits it is more likely that the order made is not a final order but an interlocutory order because the order does not usually finally determine the legal rights of the parties: MZWHN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 491 per Crennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>50 The tests that have to be considered in an application for leave to appeal are well know: D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries (1991) 33 FCR 397. On an application such as this, an applicant must establish that the decision is attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered by the Court of Appeal. If so, the applicant must also satisfy the Court considering the question of leave that substantial injustice would result if leave were refused. Of course, the two tests are not considered independently of each other but are interrelated.

51 In my opinion, there can be no doubt that the applicant has failed to satisfy the Court that the decision is attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being re considered by the Full Court. Except for the claim of bias, the grounds which gave rise to the order dismissing the application were in substance the same grounds which had previously been ventilated before Smith FM in the Federal Magistrates Court and on appeal to this Court, and in the application for special leave to the High Court.

52 The Magistrate was right to conclude that the application was in that respect an abuse of process.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>