<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v McDougall [2006] FCA 427 (20 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/427.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Pegasus Leveraged Options Group Pty Ltd (2002) 41 ACSR 561</tocase>
<text>34 In Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Pegasus Leveraged Options Group Pty Ltd (2002) 41 ACSR 561 at 574 (" Pegasus "), Davies AJ addressed the question whether the sole director of the company which promoted and operated a managed investment scheme should also be considered to be a person operating the scheme. His Honour said at [55]-[57]:
 
 "The word 'operate' is an ordinary word of the English language and, in the context, should be given its meaning in ordinary parlance. The term is not used to refer to ownership or proprietorship but rather to the acts which constitute the management of or the carrying out of the activities which constitute the managed investment scheme. The Oxford English Dictionary gives these relevant meanings: 
 
 5. To effect or produce by action or the exertion of force or influence; to bring about, accomplish, work. 
 6. To cause or actuate the working of; to work (a machine, etc). Chiefly U.S. 
 7. To direct the working of; to manage, conduct, work (a railway, business, etc); to carry out or through, direct to an end (a principle, an undertaking, etc) orig. U.S. 
 
 
 I have concluded that Mr McKim operated the managed investment scheme. He was the living person who formulated and directed the scheme and he was actively involved in its day to day operations. He supervised others in their performance. 
 
 I have also concluded that Mr McKim is not exempted by s601ED(6). He did not 'merely' act as agent or employee of Pegasus. He was the directing mind and will of Pegasus and of the scheme."

35 Mansfield J reached a similar conclusion in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v McNamara (2002) 42 ACSR 488. In that case, the individual in question was one of the directors of the company managing the scheme. His Honour found that the person in question formulated and directed the scheme, and was actively involved in its day to day operations as the directing mind and will of the company managing the scheme. Accordingly, he was operating the scheme in contravention of s 601EB(5). In making these findings, Mansfield J approved the passage in Pegasus to which I have referred.

55 Since Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW ) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121, esp at 125, the courts have recognised that the grant of declaratory relief on the application of a statutory body such as ASIC may serve important law enforcement purposes: see Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) NSWLR 596 at 603; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114 at [30] - [31] ; and Pegasus at 571. ASIC is charged with the administration and enforcement of the Act , and there will be many cases where it is in the public interest for the courts to make a declaration on ASIC's application that the Act has been contravened in specified respects. The making of such a declaration does not simply record the outcome of enforcement proceedings; it may also be an appropriate way of marking the court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: see Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80 at 97-99, 106 and 110.

77 ASIC does not seek an order that BTS be wound up, even though there is some evidence that it might be insolvent. In many cases, it may be appropriate, and it may further investor protection, to make winding up orders in respect of both the unregistered managed investment scheme and the company which administered the scheme: see Pegasus at 579-580, at [95] [98]. Indeed, in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Chase Capital Management Pty Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 778 at 796, Owen J said at [93] that if an unregistered scheme is to be wound up, the case for a liquidation of the company that conducted it is compelling.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v McNamara (2002) 42 ACSR 488</tocase>
<text>35 Mansfield J reached a similar conclusion in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v McNamara (2002) 42 ACSR 488. In that case, the individual in question was one of the directors of the company managing the scheme. His Honour found that the person in question formulated and directed the scheme, and was actively involved in its day to day operations as the directing mind and will of the company managing the scheme. Accordingly, he was operating the scheme in contravention of s 601EB(5). In making these findings, Mansfield J approved the passage in Pegasus to which I have referred.

74 In ASIC v Takaran Pty Ltd (No 2) (2003) 194 ALR 743 at 747-748, at [15], Barrett J made the following observation, with which I agree:
 
 "The fact that a scheme is being operated by its existing operators in contravention of statute activates a public interest in favour of not only its being wound up under s 601EE ( Australian Securities and Investments Commission v McNamara (2002) 42 ACSR 488) but also 'ensuring the transparency of the winding up process and the safeguarding of the rights of the contributories' by committing the winding up to an independent party ( Bells Securities Pty Ltd v LPG Mourant [2002] QSC 156 ; BC200202989 per Wilson J; see also Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Product Management Group Pty Ltd (2002) 42 ACSR 343)."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Giann &amp; Giann Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 81 ; (2005) 141 FCR 278</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/81.html</AustLII>
<text>51 Numerous cases have held that s 911A of the Act extends to a company director who conducts or is involved in a company's carrying on of a financial services business without an Australian financial services licence: see Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Giann &amp; Giann Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 81 ; (2005) 141 FCR 278; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Manito Pty Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 56; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Drury Management Pty Ltd [2004] QSC 68.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Manito Pty Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 56</tocase>
<text>51 Numerous cases have held that s 911A of the Act extends to a company director who conducts or is involved in a company's carrying on of a financial services business without an Australian financial services licence: see Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Giann &amp; Giann Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 81 ; (2005) 141 FCR 278; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Manito Pty Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 56; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Drury Management Pty Ltd [2004] QSC 68.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Drury Management Pty Ltd [2004] QSC 68</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2004/68.html</AustLII>
<text>51 Numerous cases have held that s 911A of the Act extends to a company director who conducts or is involved in a company's carrying on of a financial services business without an Australian financial services licence: see Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Giann &amp; Giann Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 81 ; (2005) 141 FCR 278; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Manito Pty Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 56; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Drury Management Pty Ltd [2004] QSC 68.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>54 In Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564, at 581-582, Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey and Gaudron JJ said that superior courts have inherent power to grant declaratory relief. Their Honours added that it is a discretionary power which it is neither possible nor desirable to fetter by laying down rules as to the manner of its exercise, although it must be recognised that it is a power confined by the considerations which mark out the boundaries of judicial power. In the same case, Brennan J emphasised that the making of a declaration, and the terms in which it is to be made, are in the court's discretion: at 596.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/49.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Since Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW ) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121, esp at 125, the courts have recognised that the grant of declaratory relief on the application of a statutory body such as ASIC may serve important law enforcement purposes: see Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) NSWLR 596 at 603; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114 at [30] - [31] ; and Pegasus at 571. ASIC is charged with the administration and enforcement of the Act , and there will be many cases where it is in the public interest for the courts to make a declaration on ASIC's application that the Act has been contravened in specified respects. The making of such a declaration does not simply record the outcome of enforcement proceedings; it may also be an appropriate way of marking the court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: see Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80 at 97-99, 106 and 110.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 596</tocase>
<text>55 Since Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW ) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121, esp at 125, the courts have recognised that the grant of declaratory relief on the application of a statutory body such as ASIC may serve important law enforcement purposes: see Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) NSWLR 596 at 603; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114 at [30] - [31] ; and Pegasus at 571. ASIC is charged with the administration and enforcement of the Act , and there will be many cases where it is in the public interest for the courts to make a declaration on ASIC's application that the Act has been contravened in specified respects. The making of such a declaration does not simply record the outcome of enforcement proceedings; it may also be an appropriate way of marking the court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: see Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80 at 97-99, 106 and 110.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/114.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Since Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW ) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121, esp at 125, the courts have recognised that the grant of declaratory relief on the application of a statutory body such as ASIC may serve important law enforcement purposes: see Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) NSWLR 596 at 603; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114 at [30] - [31] ; and Pegasus at 571. ASIC is charged with the administration and enforcement of the Act , and there will be many cases where it is in the public interest for the courts to make a declaration on ASIC's application that the Act has been contravened in specified respects. The making of such a declaration does not simply record the outcome of enforcement proceedings; it may also be an appropriate way of marking the court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: see Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80 at 97-99, 106 and 110.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80</tocase>
<text>55 Since Australian Softwood Forest Pty Ltd v Attorney-General (NSW ) [1981] HCA 49 ; (1981) 148 CLR 121, esp at 125, the courts have recognised that the grant of declaratory relief on the application of a statutory body such as ASIC may serve important law enforcement purposes: see Corporate Affairs Commission (NSW) v Transphere Pty Ltd (1988) NSWLR 596 at 603; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sweeney [2001] NSWSC 114 at [30] - [31] ; and Pegasus at 571. ASIC is charged with the administration and enforcement of the Act , and there will be many cases where it is in the public interest for the courts to make a declaration on ASIC's application that the Act has been contravened in specified respects. The making of such a declaration does not simply record the outcome of enforcement proceedings; it may also be an appropriate way of marking the court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: see Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 80 at 97-99, 106 and 110.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>OD Transport Pty Ltd v WA Government Railways Commission (1987) 13 FCR 500</tocase>
<text>64 Section 1324 permits the Court to grant an injunction "on such terms as the court thinks appropriate". These words echo the concluding words of s 80(1) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 ("TPA") which state that the Court may grant an injunction in such terms as the Court determines to be appropriate. These words were introduced into s 80(1) by a 1983 amendment to the TPA, which, to adapt the language used by French J in OD Transport Pty Ltd v WA Government Railways Commission (1987) 13 FCR 500 at 508, freed the power conferred by s 80 from the previous constraint that the injunction granted under it must restrain a person from engaging in conduct that constitutes or would constitute a contravention of Part IV of Part V of the TPA or one of the species of accessorial participation there listed.

67 French J said that s 80 was a widely drawn remedial provision which was available to restrain conduct which may infringe upon the public interest by contravening the provisions of the TPA in Part IV and Part V. His Honour added at 268:
 
 "There is room within the statutory framework and the policy that underlies it for an injunction which is intended not to restrain an apprehended repetition of contravening conduct but to deter an offender from repeating the offence. That deterrence is effected by attaching to the repetition of the contravention the range of sanctions available for contempt of court. The possibility remains open, by virtue of s 80(3) , that after a suitable period unmarked by further contravention the party restrained may apply to the court to rescind the order. 
 
 The remedy is flexible and may be applied in service of a variety of functions to support the policy of the Act . This was a proper case for the grant of that relief."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>ICI Australia Operations Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248</tocase>
<text>65 The operation of s 80(1) of the TPA was canvassed by the Full Court of this Court in ICI Australia Operations Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248 (" ICI "). Lockhart J described s 80(1) as a public interest provision which attracts special considerations; it represents a primary means of ensuring compliance with commercial regulation legislation: at 254-255. After referring to subss 80(4) and (5), Lockhart J said: 
 
 "Injunctions are traditionally employed to restrain repetition of conduct. A statutory provision that enables an injunction to be granted to prevent the commission of conduct that has never been done before and is not likely to be done again is a statutory enlargement of traditional equitable principles. But this is because traditional doctrine surrounding the grant of injunctive relief was developed primarily for the protection of private proprietary rights. Public interest injunctions are different. Parts IV and V of the Act involve matters of high public policy. Parts IV and V relate to practices and conduct that legislatures throughout the world in different forms and to different degrees, have decided are contrary to the public interest (contracts, arrangements or understandings affecting competition adversely (s 45)), the misuse of market power (s 46) , the practice of exclusive dealing (s 47) , resale price maintenance (s 48) , price discrimination (s 49) , anti-competitive mergers (s 50) and unfair practices with respect to consumers (Pt V). These are legislative enactments of matters vital to the presence of free competition and enterprise and a just society." 
 

In his Honour's view, the section would in an appropriate case authorise the Court to grant an injunction against a respondent preventing him in engaging in conduct which is similar to the conduct which constituted, or would constitute, a contravention of the Act : at 261. Lockhart J also agreed (at 261) with the reasoning of Barwick CJ in Mikasa (NSW) Pty Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617 at 632 that in an appropriate case the court may grant an injunction to restrain the respondent from engaging in the practice of resale price maintenance notwithstanding that only some of the acts falling within s 96(3) were found to have been so committed.

68 In ACCC v Z-Tek Computer Pty Ltd (1997) 78 FCR 197 at 202 at [D]-[E], after referring to these passages in ICI , Merkel J said:
 
 "The width of the power conferred by s 80 and its public interest character obviously give the Court great amplitude in determining appropriate injunctive orders in a particular case. However there are limitations on the Court's power under the section. Confinement of the power by reference to the scope and purpose of the TPA, and in particular s 80 , is one limitation on the power. However, there are at least two further limitations. The power to make orders under s 80 is only enlivened in a proceeding which alleges that there has been a contravention of a provision of Pt IV , IVA or V of the TPA. As was said by Gummow J in ICI at 267, the terms of an injunction granted under s 80 must, on their face, operate upon a range of conduct which has 'the relationship required by s 80 with contravention of the Act . Irrespective of whether the injunction is sought or granted under s 80(1) or 80 (1AA) there must be a nexus between the conduct alleged or found to constitute the relevant contraventions and the injunctions granted."

70 Most recently, in Foster v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2006] FCAFC 21 , a Full Court (comprising Ryan, Finn and Allsop JJ) noted the apparent tension between the view expressed by Lockhart and Gummow JJ in ICI . Their Honours said at [30]-[31]:
 
 "His Honour's reference to terms having 'an operation outside the boundaries of s 80 ' is no more than a paraphrase of the actual words of the subsection 'such terms as the Court determines to be appropriate.' That paraphrase, we consider with respect, does not illuminate the amplitude which should be given, as a matter of construction, to the grant of power. In our view, a more helpful guide to resolving the question of construction is afforded by this observation, also from ICI v Trade Practices Commission , of Lockhart J (with whom French J agreed) at 256; 
 
 
 'In my opinion subss (4) and (5) are designed to ensure that once the condition precedent to the exercise of injunctive relief has been satisfied (ie contraventions or proposed contraventions of Pt IV or V of the Act ), the court should be given the widest possible injunctive powers, devoid of traditional constraints, though the power must be exercised judicially and sensibly.' 
 
 
 
 This approach of Lochkhart J accords with the view often expressed by the High Court that discretions or powers entrusted to Courts should be read liberally for the relevant statutory purpose, without making implications or imposing limitations not found in the express words: Australian Memory Pty Ltd v Brien [2000] HCA 30 ; (2000) 200 CLR 270 at [77] and see generally for the cases Hewlett Packard v GE Capital [2003] FCAFC 256 ; (2003) 203 ALR 51 at [187] ." 
 

Thus, the Full Court preferred the wider view described by Lockhart and French JJ in ICI to the narrower view which the appellant in Foster sought to found upon the judgment of Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mikasa (NSW) Pty Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/69.html</AustLII>
<text>65 The operation of s 80(1) of the TPA was canvassed by the Full Court of this Court in ICI Australia Operations Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248 (" ICI "). Lockhart J described s 80(1) as a public interest provision which attracts special considerations; it represents a primary means of ensuring compliance with commercial regulation legislation: at 254-255. After referring to subss 80(4) and (5), Lockhart J said: 
 
 "Injunctions are traditionally employed to restrain repetition of conduct. A statutory provision that enables an injunction to be granted to prevent the commission of conduct that has never been done before and is not likely to be done again is a statutory enlargement of traditional equitable principles. But this is because traditional doctrine surrounding the grant of injunctive relief was developed primarily for the protection of private proprietary rights. Public interest injunctions are different. Parts IV and V of the Act involve matters of high public policy. Parts IV and V relate to practices and conduct that legislatures throughout the world in different forms and to different degrees, have decided are contrary to the public interest (contracts, arrangements or understandings affecting competition adversely (s 45)), the misuse of market power (s 46) , the practice of exclusive dealing (s 47) , resale price maintenance (s 48) , price discrimination (s 49) , anti-competitive mergers (s 50) and unfair practices with respect to consumers (Pt V). These are legislative enactments of matters vital to the presence of free competition and enterprise and a just society." 
 

In his Honour's view, the section would in an appropriate case authorise the Court to grant an injunction against a respondent preventing him in engaging in conduct which is similar to the conduct which constituted, or would constitute, a contravention of the Act : at 261. Lockhart J also agreed (at 261) with the reasoning of Barwick CJ in Mikasa (NSW) Pty Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617 at 632 that in an appropriate case the court may grant an injunction to restrain the respondent from engaging in the practice of resale price maintenance notwithstanding that only some of the acts falling within s 96(3) were found to have been so committed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ACCC v Z-Tek Computer Pty Ltd (1997) 78 FCR 197 at 202</tocase>
<text>68 In ACCC v Z-Tek Computer Pty Ltd (1997) 78 FCR 197 at 202 at [D]-[E], after referring to these passages in ICI , Merkel J said:
 
 "The width of the power conferred by s 80 and its public interest character obviously give the Court great amplitude in determining appropriate injunctive orders in a particular case. However there are limitations on the Court's power under the section. Confinement of the power by reference to the scope and purpose of the TPA, and in particular s 80 , is one limitation on the power. However, there are at least two further limitations. The power to make orders under s 80 is only enlivened in a proceeding which alleges that there has been a contravention of a provision of Pt IV , IVA or V of the TPA. As was said by Gummow J in ICI at 267, the terms of an injunction granted under s 80 must, on their face, operate upon a range of conduct which has 'the relationship required by s 80 with contravention of the Act . Irrespective of whether the injunction is sought or granted under s 80(1) or 80 (1AA) there must be a nexus between the conduct alleged or found to constitute the relevant contraventions and the injunctions granted."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ACCC v Real Estate Institute (WA) [1999] FCA 1387 ; (1999) 95 FCR 114</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1387.html</AustLII>
<text>69 It is implicit in Merkel J's judgment that an injunction under s 80 may extend beyond the specific conduct proven to constitute a contravention by s 80 and may, in appropriate cases, extend to conduct of the same kind or class. There must, however, be a sufficient nexus or relationship between the conduct that is the subject of the restraint and the conduct that was alleged to constitute a contravention of the Act . As French J pointed out in ACCC v Real Estate Institute (WA) [1999] FCA 1387 ; (1999) 95 FCR 114 at 131, the question whether there is a sufficient nexus between the orders sought and the contraventions alleged involves an evaluative judgment by the Court which will depend heavily upon the circumstances of the particular case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Foster v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2006] FCAFC 21</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/21.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Most recently, in Foster v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2006] FCAFC 21 , a Full Court (comprising Ryan, Finn and Allsop JJ) noted the apparent tension between the view expressed by Lockhart and Gummow JJ in ICI . Their Honours said at [30]-[31]:
 
 "His Honour's reference to terms having 'an operation outside the boundaries of s 80 ' is no more than a paraphrase of the actual words of the subsection 'such terms as the Court determines to be appropriate.' That paraphrase, we consider with respect, does not illuminate the amplitude which should be given, as a matter of construction, to the grant of power. In our view, a more helpful guide to resolving the question of construction is afforded by this observation, also from ICI v Trade Practices Commission , of Lockhart J (with whom French J agreed) at 256; 
 
 
 'In my opinion subss (4) and (5) are designed to ensure that once the condition precedent to the exercise of injunctive relief has been satisfied (ie contraventions or proposed contraventions of Pt IV or V of the Act ), the court should be given the widest possible injunctive powers, devoid of traditional constraints, though the power must be exercised judicially and sensibly.' 
 
 
 
 This approach of Lochkhart J accords with the view often expressed by the High Court that discretions or powers entrusted to Courts should be read liberally for the relevant statutory purpose, without making implications or imposing limitations not found in the express words: Australian Memory Pty Ltd v Brien [2000] HCA 30 ; (2000) 200 CLR 270 at [77] and see generally for the cases Hewlett Packard v GE Capital [2003] FCAFC 256 ; (2003) 203 ALR 51 at [187] ." 
 

Thus, the Full Court preferred the wider view described by Lockhart and French JJ in ICI to the narrower view which the appellant in Foster sought to found upon the judgment of Gummow J.

71 The issue in Foster was whether an injunction that restrained the fourth respondent from being directly or indirectly knowingly concerned in the promotion or conduct of a business of a specified kind for a period of five years went beyond the power conferred by s 80 of the TPA. As the Full Court explained, this turned on the existence of a sufficient nexus between a contravention that enlivened the Court's power under s 80 and the conduct that was restrained by the injunction:
 
 "In our view, the need, suggested by the authorities, for a nexus between the contravention of the Act which the Court has found and the terms of the restraint which it then decides to impose is a specific reflection of Lockhart J's insistence that the power be exercised 'judicially and sensibly'. It goes to the appropriateness of the relief contemplated by the concluding words of s 80(1) , not to the extent of the power to grant it. If the Court considers that a complete prohibition, whether permanently or for a specified period, on a respondent's engaging in a particular field of commercial activity or industry is required to protect the public from conduct of the kind which constituted the contravention, s 80 is wide enough to support such a prohibition as a matter of power. This analysis of s 80 conforms, we consider, with that recently undertaken by Goldberg J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Dermalogica Pty Ltd (2005) 215 ALR 482 at 504 [110]." 
 

The Full Court held that there was an appropriate nexus, as the evidence and the trial judge's findings at first instance gave rise to a real fear that the fourth respondent would, unless restrained, commit further conduct of the same general kind. In these circumstances, it was appropriate to cast the injunction more widely in order to catch conduct which was similar to the established contravention: at [34] and [38].

72 In the present case, I consider that the wider form of injunctive relief is appropriate, especially given the evidence that McDougall attempted to resuscitate the Scheme in another form. The evidence demonstrates, in my view, that the defendants are susceptible to repeating their contraventions of the managed investment provisions of the Act . There is, in my opinion, a sufficient nexus between the wider form of injunctive order sought by ASIC in par 5 of the draft orders, and the contraventions of the Act which were established by the evidence in this case. The wider form of injunction is consented to by the defendants. In all the circumstances, I consider that the wider form of injunction is warranted, and that it will serve the public interest.

73 ASIC seeks orders that the Scheme be wound up pursuant to s 601EE(1) of the Act . A number of ancillary orders are sought, including an order appointing the existing Court appointed receivers as joint and several liquidators of the Scheme. The defendants consent to these orders being made. I have made two minor alterations to the form of the draft orders for the winding up of the Scheme. The first alteration, in par 7, identifies Adrian Lawrence Brown and James Henry Stewart as the receivers appointed by order of Merkel J on 25 October 2005. The second alteration clarifies that the receivers referred to in par 9 are the individuals identified in the above par 7 of the orders.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Takaran Pty Ltd (No 2) (2003) 194 ALR 743</tocase>
<text>74 In ASIC v Takaran Pty Ltd (No 2) (2003) 194 ALR 743 at 747-748, at [15], Barrett J made the following observation, with which I agree:
 
 "The fact that a scheme is being operated by its existing operators in contravention of statute activates a public interest in favour of not only its being wound up under s 601EE ( Australian Securities and Investments Commission v McNamara (2002) 42 ACSR 488) but also 'ensuring the transparency of the winding up process and the safeguarding of the rights of the contributories' by committing the winding up to an independent party ( Bells Securities Pty Ltd v LPG Mourant [2002] QSC 156 ; BC200202989 per Wilson J; see also Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Product Management Group Pty Ltd (2002) 42 ACSR 343)."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Chase Capital Management Pty Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 778</tocase>
<text>77 ASIC does not seek an order that BTS be wound up, even though there is some evidence that it might be insolvent. In many cases, it may be appropriate, and it may further investor protection, to make winding up orders in respect of both the unregistered managed investment scheme and the company which administered the scheme: see Pegasus at 579-580, at [95] [98]. Indeed, in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Chase Capital Management Pty Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 778 at 796, Owen J said at [93] that if an unregistered scheme is to be wound up, the case for a liquidation of the company that conducted it is compelling.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>