<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Applicant M20/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 539 (28 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/539.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>M20 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2005] FMCA 902 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2005/902.html</AustLII>
<text>1 This appeal is from a judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court, published as M20 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2005] FMCA 902. The federal magistrate dismissed an application by the appellant, seeking relief in respect of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal ('the Tribunal'), dated 30 August 2001 and handed down on 21 September 2001. The proceeding before the Federal Magistrates Court had been remitted from the High Court of Australia to this Court, and from this Court to the Federal Magistrates Court.

2 The appellant is a citizen of India, who arrived in Australia on 12 September 1996 in possession of a student visa. After a renewal of that student visa in 1998, the appellant applied for a protection visa on 26 June 2000. A delegate of the first respondent, then the Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs, and subsequently the Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs, and now again the Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (in all cases, 'the Minister') refused the application for a protection visa. The appellant sought review of that decision by the Tribunal. The Tribunal conducted a hearing, at which the appellant gave evidence to it. Its decision was that the Tribunal was not satisfied that the appellant was a refugee, and the Tribunal affirmed the decision not to grant a protection visa.

3 After some significant delay, the appellant applied to the High Court, seeking to set aside the Tribunal's decision and to have the matter reheard by the Tribunal, differently constituted. Once the matter had been remitted via this Court to the Federal Magistrates Court, the appellant filed an amended application, seeking relief in the exercise of the jurisdiction conferred on that court by s 483A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ('the Migration Act '). In relation to matters arising under the Migration Act , that jurisdiction is identical to that conferred on this Court by s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).

4 In that amended application, the appellant made it fairly clear that he wished to assert that some of the factual conclusions of the Tribunal were incorrect.

5 The federal magistrate took the view that, in reality, the appellant's challenge to the Tribunal's decision was based on issues of fact, and that the Federal Magistrates Court had no jurisdiction to review the decision on the merits. In substance, this constituted the reasons of the federal magistrate for dismissing the amended application.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>