<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>A &amp; D Douglas Pty Ltd ACN 008 404 180 v Lawyers Private Mortgages Pty Ltd ACN 010 556 751 (with Corrigendum dated 15 May 2006 [2006] FCA 520 (12 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/520.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hungerfords v Walker [1989] HCA 8 ; (1988-1989) 171 CLR 125 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/8.html</AustLII>
<text>570. The applicants seek compound interest. They submit that the decision of the High Court in Hungerfords v Walker [1989] HCA 8 ; (1988-1989) 171 CLR 125 is authority for the proposition that compound interest may be awarded by way of damages. The decision is certainly authority for that proposition. Such an award is distinct from an award of interest pursuant to the statutory power conferred upon this Court by s 51A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) (the "Federal Court Act"). It is clear from the reasons of Mason CJ and Wilson J at 149 (Brennan and Deane JJ concurring) that an award of compound interest must be for 'a foreseeable loss, necessarily within the contemplation of the parties, which is directly related to the defendant's breach of contract or tort' . In that case, the plaintiff conducted a business and had borrowed substantial amounts for that purpose. The award was designed to compensate the plaintiff for specifically identifiable losses. Compound interest was not allowed by way of damages on amounts which would have been spent for private purposes.

571. As far as I am aware, none of the applicants has asserted a case of the kind considered in Hungerfords . Given the relatively small amounts of most investments and the personal circumstances of many of the applicants, it is likely that many would have expended any interest on living expenses and other private outgoings. The loss of interest may have caused them a degree of hardship or discomfort, but they cannot be compensated for that in dollar terms. It is not appropriate, in this case, to award compound interest as damages.

572. As to the rate at which the awards should bear interest pursuant to s 51A, ex 74 contains information as to bank deposit rates for the period from July 1999 until September 2004. The table shows monthly fluctuations in interest rates for various types of deposit and for various periods. Given that the applicants have been out of their funds since 23 July 2000 it seems appropriate to adopt the rate payable for the longest available term which is five years. The average rate over the period from 23 July 2000 until September 2004 is 4.9 per cent. The awards will bear interest at that rate from 23 July 2000 until the date of judgment. To this sum will be added, in the case of each applicant, interest at the same rate on the amount of the first distribution for the period of 2.75 years and on the amount of the second distribution for 3.8 years. There may have to be further adjustments in the cases of the thirty-eighth and thirty-ninth applicants. I will hear further submissions after publication of these reasons.

573. It might be thought that this approach involves the award of interest upon interest, which approach is not permitted by s 51A. I refer to my inclusion of an amount for interest in calculating the award of damages and then allowing interest on the amount of the award. However I do not understand s 51A to regulate the calculation of damages. It rather addresses the award of interest after such calculation. It does not authorize compound interest on an award.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Gilmour v AMP General Insurance (1997) 9 ANZIC 61-372 </tocase>
<text>610. MDRN seeks to narrow the construction of cl 5(e)(v) of the St Paul policy, submitting that it does not operate to deprive an innocent partner of indemnity where loss is the result of the dishonest or fraudulent act of an employee. The point is clearly unarguable. Clause 5(e)(v) specifically excludes indemnity where the loss occurs in those circumstances. The argument would result in the clause having no effect whatsoever. MDRN sought to rely upon the decision of the Full Court of South Australia in Gilmour v AMP General Insurance (1997) 9 ANZIC 61-372. However it is relatively clear that the case did not involve a clause such as cl 5(e)(v). There is nothing in this argument.

611. As I understand it, my findings lead to the conclusion that St Paul is obliged to indemnify MDRN only in the amount of Mr Bengston's claim. However I will invite the parties to make further submissions should they wish to do so.

612. One other matter requires comment. St Paul submits that the fees charged by Mr Jessup are not recoverable by the applicants. The applicants do not claim them as damages. However they were deducted from moneys received by Mr Jessup and so the amount thereof was not passed on to investors. The amount of each claim has been increased as a result of such deduction.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Moloney &amp; Anor v Bells Securities Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] QSC 013</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2005/013.html</AustLII>
<text>617. The reference to 'Bells case' is to the decision of Chesterman J in Moloney &amp; Anor v Bells Securities Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2005] QSC 013. In that case his Honour declined to allow as damages the costs of a liquidator appointed in circumstances similar to those in the present case. St Paul's argument seems to be that as the period of the ASIC exemption was to expire on 31 October 2001, a liquidator would have been appointed in any event. It is said to follow that the costs incurred by Mr Jessup were not a consequence, or perhaps a foreseeable consequence, of any conduct on the part of the respondents, particularly MDRN. The applicants did not take this point in argument, but it addresses the measure of damages in their claims against MDRN.

618. In causes of action for misleading and deceptive conduct and negligent misstatement, the relevant measure of damages is designed to put the applicant in the position in which he or she would have been, had the relevant conduct not occurred. That is often achieved by awarding the difference between the value of the property acquired as a result of the relevant conduct and the price paid for it. However there are limits upon the extent of permissible recovery. I accept that for present purposes, the test of reasonable foreseeability provides such limit. Had Project Results discharged its obligation, the loan would have been repaid in 2000. At the time of the relevant conduct it was reasonably foreseeable that the applicants would suffer loss as a result of Project Results failing to meet such obligations. It was also reasonably foreseeable that in that event, the applicants would have to resort to available securities, including Mr Rivett's guarantee, in order to recover their investments and interest. It was similarly foreseeable that, as a result of their conduct, MDRN and the trustee company would be unable to attend to such realization, and that somebody else would have to do so. That was likely to cost money.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Overseas Tankship (UK) Ltd v Morts Dock &amp; Engineering Co Ltd (The Wagon Mound) [1961] AC 388</tocase>
<text>491. Paragraph 12 of the statement of claim pleads that:
 
 'The [investment summary] represented and contained advice that the application from Rivett for an advance on specified security referred to in the [investment summary] had been approved by the Respondents under its loan application assessment programme, that being in accordance with the procedure referred to in paragraph 10.'

492. Paragraph 10 pleads representations in the brochure and newsletters concerning steps taken in assessing loan applications. Thus it is claimed on behalf of those applicants who received the brochure and/or either or both of the newsletters that they understood the investment summary as referring to one or more of those other documents. See par 39 of the applicants' written submissions. As I understood the applicants' final submissions only those applicants who received the autumn 1999 newsletter now rely on this alleged misrepresentation in the investment summary. It will be convenient to deal with this aspect after I have dealt with the other, more commonly shared, complaints.

493. On pp 3 and 5 of the investment summary there are statements which suggest that all units (ex 54A) or all units in Stage 1 (ex 54B) have been sold. I have previously set out relevant passages from pp 2, 3, 4 and 5 and given my reasons for concluding that a reader would take the statements in ex 54A as referring to pre-sale of all units in Stage 1. See [38]-[46]. The difference in wording between ex 54A and ex 54B is of no consequence in this regard.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mount Isa Mines Ltd v Pusey [1970] HCA 60 ; (1970) 125 CLR 383</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1970/60.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>South Australia v Johnson (1982) 42 ALR 161</tocase>
<text>619. In my view it was reasonably foreseeable that as a result of the conduct of the trustee company and MDRN, additional costs would be incurred in realizing the securities. That is sufficient to permit recovery by the applicants from MDRN of the reasonable costs so incurred. See South Australia v Johnson (1982) 42 ALR 161. The prospective expiry of the ASIC exemption played no causal role in the incurrence by the applicants of their costs, nor did it render them too remote to be recoverable in these proceedings.

620. MDRN pleads professional indemnity policies with QBE for the periods from 6 September 1998 to 6 September 1999 (the "1998 policy"), 6 September 1999 to 6 September 2000 (the "1999 policy") and 6 September 2000 to 6 September 2001 (the "2000 policy"). Clause 1.1 of each policy provided:
 
 'QBE agrees to indemnify the insured against legal liability for any Claim for compensation first made against the Insured during the Period of Cover and which is notified to QBE during the Period of Cover, in respect of any civil liability whatsoever and howsoever incurred in the conduct of the Professional Business Practice.'

621. Pursuant to cl 5.1 the period for notification of a claim was extended to include the period of 28 days after the end of the period of cover. Clause 5.2 provided:
 
 'If during the Period of Cover the Insured becomes aware of any fact or circumstance that might give rise to a Claim under this Policy and elects to give notice in writing to QBE of such fact or circumstance, then any Claim which may subsequently arise out of such fact or circumstance shall be deemed to be a Claim made during the Period of Cover PROVIDED ALWAYS THAT such written notice is given to QBE during the same period of cover or within 28 days after its expiry.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>FAI General Insurance Co Limited v Australian Hospital Care Pty Limited [2001] HCA 38 ; (2001) 204 CLR 641 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/38.html</AustLII>
<text>641. The decision of the High Court in FAI General Insurance Co Limited v Australian Hospital Care Pty Limited [2001] HCA 38 ; (2001) 204 CLR 641 at [40] [46] (per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ) demonstrates that QBE is not entitled to avoid payment pursuant to the policy upon the basis of MDRN's failure to notify this claim during the period of cover, save to the extent permitted by s 54. Although MDRN's pleading does not say so, the relevant "act" for the purposes of s 54 is that failure. It may be that the decision in FAI v Australian Hospital Care can be distinguished for present purposes. I say that in view of the language of "election" contained in cl 5.2 of the present policy. The language of the policy in that case seems not to have contained that concept. It may be arguable that the High Court was not addressing a situation in which the parties had stipulated for an election, and that an election may not accurately be described as an "omission". However the contrary is also arguable. In any event, I proceed upon the basis that the decision is relevant to MDRN's claim to indemnity under the 1998 policy.

642. The cross-claim was amended to add the claim under the 1998 policy and reliance on s 54. The amendment was provoked by QBE's plea of non-disclosure and misrepresentation in connection with the 1999 policy. Paragraph 18 of the cross-claim asserts:
 
 'If the matters alleged by QBE in its amended defence do constitute non-disclosure or misrepresentation in respect of the 1999 policy, then those matters, or certain of them, would constitute a fact or circumstance that might give rise to a claim for the purpose of cl 5.2 of the previous year policy.'

643. This method of pleading is unsatisfactory. The matters so alleged by QBE are numerous. They relate to MDRN's system for loan approval and particular aspects of its conduct concerning the Yandina project, in particular, compilation of the investment summary. It would have been helpful had MDRN specified the precise matters which it claims to have omitted to notify. In any event, QBE denies that such matters could have given rise to a claim under the 1998 policy. It also denies that during the term of that policy, MDRN became aware of such matters. It is said to follow that MDRN 'are not, and were not during the term of the (1998) policy, entitled to give notice' of such matters, and that cl 5.2 of the 1998 policy therefore does not apply so as to deem there to be a claim under that policy, regardless of any question of late notification. As it is MDRN's primary position that it is entitled to indemnity pursuant to the 1999 policy, it will be best to leave consideration of the argument concerning the 1998 policy and the application of s 54 until the issue of liability under the 1999 policy has been determined.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Permanent Trustee Australia &amp; Anor v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 186</tocase>
<text>722. The question, then, is whether any of the three matters mentioned above was known to MDRN, and if so, whether it knew that any such matter was relevant to QBE's decision to accept the proposal, or whether a reasonable person, in the circumstances, could have been expected to know that such matter was relevant. It is appropriate to consider the meaning of each of the words "known", "knows" and "know" in s 21. Two questions arise for consideration. The first is whether the required knowledge must be actual, or whether it is sufficient that it can be inferred from other matters known to the insured. The second is the extent to which the knowledge of some person other than the insured is to be imputed to him or her. The Insurance Contracts Act seems not to deal with either question other than in the bald terms of s 21. However the cases establish, with respect to the first question, that it is actual knowledge which must be disclosed. Thus in Permanent Trustee Australia &amp; Anor v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 186 at 247, Hodgson CJ in Equity (as his Honour then was) said:
 
 'In my opinion, "known" in s 21(1) means more than "suspected" or "believed". What is required is that the matter should be the subject of a true belief, held with sufficient assurance to justify the term "known". However, it must be remembered that a belief may sometimes itself be a matter relevant to the decision of an insurer. An insured may know that it has a particular belief, and know that its having that belief is relevant to the decision of an insurer, in which case that belief itself is a matter which must be disclosed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Permanent Trustee Australia Co Ltd &amp; Anor v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd [2001] NSWCA 20 ; (2001) 50 NSWLR 679 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2001/20.html</AustLII>
<text>723. On appeal (at [2001] NSWCA 20 ; (2001) 50 NSWLR 679) Handley JA said at [45] et seq (Meagher and Powell JJA concurring):
 
 
 '45. The problem of defining, for legal purposes, the boundary between belief and knowledge did not arise for the first time in this case. The problem has been considered in a number of legal contexts, and in general it may be said that, for legal purposes, our knowledge includes the facts, apart from matters of religious faith, that we believe to be true. 
 
 46. Thus out of court admissions are receivable in evidence against a party if they disclose an intention to affirm or acknowledge the existence of a fact whatever the party's source of information or belief; see Lustre Hosiery Ltd v York [1935] HCA 71 ; (1935) 54 CLR 134 at 143. However, as the Court said (at 144): 
 
 
 
 
 "If it appears that [the party] had no knowledge, or that, although he had some means of knowledge, he had formed no certain or considered belief and indicated nothing amounting to a personal judgment or conclusion of his own, the probative force of the admission may be so small that a jury ought not to be allowed to act upon it alone, or in preference to opposing evidence." 
 
 
 
 
 ... 
 
 
 
 54. ... When a person, on the basis of some information, holds a belief on which that person is prepared to act in the world of practical affairs, he or she knows that fact for most legal purposes, and certainly for the purposes of s 21. '</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Midaz Pty Ltd v Peter McCarthy Insurance Brokers Pty Ltd (1999) 1 Qd R 279 </tocase>
<text>724. In Midaz Pty Ltd v Peter McCarthy Insurance Brokers Pty Ltd [1999] 1 Qd R 279, the Court of Appeal of Queensland addressed the question of whether a person who was aware of certain facts should be taken to have knowledge of a reasonably available inference from those facts. Of that proposition Pincus JA said at 283-4 (Moynihan SPJ and Byrne J concurring):
 
 'Acceptance of that argument must depend on adoption of a construction of section 21(1) which is rather generous to insurers: that the section means that if an insured knows matter A which is not in itself relevant to insurance, but the insured should reasonably infer from matter A a further matter B which is so relevant, then the duty to disclose matters A and B arises. This construction is in practical terms little different from reading the introductory part of section 21(1) as if it included the expression "... every matter that is known to or should be inferred by the insured". 
 
 I have found no authority which supports such a reading, nor does it appear to be one which must be adopted to give section 21(1) a sensible operation.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Advance (NSW) Insurance Agencies Pty Ltd v Matthews (1987) 4 ANZ Ins Cas 60-813 </tocase>
<text>725. As to imputed knowledge, in Advance (NSW) Insurance Agencies Pty Ltd v Matthews (1987) 4 ANZ Ins Cas 60-813, Young J said at 74,998:
 
 'Although the language of section 21 is awkward, in my view it means that if a reasonable person in the circumstances could be expected to know that a matter is relevant it must be disclosed and whether that be the case or not, if the insured actually knows the relevant thing, that is enough. However, the insured must have actual knowledge of the thing, the mere fact that he ought in the ordinary course of business to have known is insufficient.'

726. Nonetheless, in some cases, knowledge of an agent will be imputed to the principal. In Peter MacDonald Eggers, Simon Picken and Patrick Foss, Good Faith and Insurance Contracts (2 nd ed), Insurance Law Library, London, 2004, the authors assert at par 13.49:
 
 'The agents whose knowledge principally is imputed to the assured are those agents who are concerned with the custody, care or status of the subject matter insured, general agents who are so placed with respect to the assured that they may be said to make decisions for the assured generally and agents who are charged with arranging the insurance.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lindsay v CIC Insurance Ltd (1989) 16 NSWLR 673 </tocase>
<text>727. The authors of MacGillivray on Insurance Law (10 th ed) say at par 1812:
 
 'It is not all agents whose knowledge is imputed in that way for purposes of non-disclosure but only those agents who are "agents to know" that is to say, are responsible for keeping the assured informed about the subject matter of the insurance, either because they are responsible for placing the insurance or because they have the management of it for the assured. If such an agent owes a duty to communicate information which is relevant to the insurance, but fails to do so, the assured is deemed to know what in the ordinary routine of his business he should have been told if the agent had performed his duty, but he will not be deemed to know facts which, whether or not owing to the deficient organization of the business, no agent was responsible for communicating to him.' 
 

See also Lindsay v CIC Insurance Ltd (1989) 16 NSWLR 673 and Ayoub v Lombard Insurance Co (Aust) Pty Ltd (1989) 5 ANZ Ins Cas 60-933.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ayoub v Lombard Insurance Co (Aust) Pty Ltd (1989) 5 ANZ Ins Cas 60-933 </tocase>
<text>727. The authors of MacGillivray on Insurance Law (10 th ed) say at par 1812:
 
 'It is not all agents whose knowledge is imputed in that way for purposes of non-disclosure but only those agents who are "agents to know" that is to say, are responsible for keeping the assured informed about the subject matter of the insurance, either because they are responsible for placing the insurance or because they have the management of it for the assured. If such an agent owes a duty to communicate information which is relevant to the insurance, but fails to do so, the assured is deemed to know what in the ordinary routine of his business he should have been told if the agent had performed his duty, but he will not be deemed to know facts which, whether or not owing to the deficient organization of the business, no agent was responsible for communicating to him.' 
 

See also Lindsay v CIC Insurance Ltd (1989) 16 NSWLR 673 and Ayoub v Lombard Insurance Co (Aust) Pty Ltd (1989) 5 ANZ Ins Cas 60-933.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australia and New Zealand Bank Limited v Colonial and Eagles Wharves Limited (1960) 2 Lloyd's Rep. 241 </tocase>
<text>728. McNair J discussed the matter at length in Australia and New Zealand Bank Limited v Colonial and Eagles Wharves Limited (1960) 2 Lloyd's Rep. 241. In that case his Lordship assumed that at common law, rules derived from the Marine Insurance Act 1906 (Imp) applied to non-marine insurance. After reference to the authorities, his Lordship observed at 254:
 
 'These judgments make it clear to my mind that it is not the knowledge of all agents or servants that is imputed to the proposer of any marine insurance, but only the knowledge of quite a limited class, namely, the broker who actually places the insurance, the master or the ship agent, or, to use Lord Halsbury's phrase, "his general agent for the management of his shipping business." On the facts of the present case, Henderson was not within that limited class. Though, in a sense, the key man in the sense that a mistake by him would mean the failure of the system his duties were almost entirely clerical; it was not established that he had any discretion or executive authority; he was not superior to the head clerks in the warehouses but co-ordinate with them. He was not, in my judgment, a person within the class of those who were under a duty to report to the company.' 
 

See also Sutton's Insurance Law in Australia (3 rd ed) at pars 3.183 and 3.184, and Tarr's Australian Insurance Law at 104-105. It seems to be generally accepted that the position under the Insurance Contracts Act reflects the common law position.

731. The general principles to which I have referred are subject to a critical qualification. In ANZ Bank v Colonial Wharves (supra) McNair J said at 254:
 
 'There is, however, another answer in law to the third party's contention on this point, namely, that assuming that he was within the class of persons who were under a duty to report so that his knowledge was to be imputed to his principal, he, on the principle stated in Bell &amp; Anor v Lever Bros Ltd &amp; Ors [1931] UKHL 2 ; [1932] A.C. 161, and J C Houghton &amp; Co v Nothard, Lowe &amp; Wills Ltd [1928] A.C. 1 ... was under no duty to report his own dereliction of duty, and his knowledge of that dereliction is not to be imputed to his principals.' Lord Atkin ([1932] A.C. 6, at p 228) puts the matter succinctly in the following passage: 
 "... The servant owes a duty not to steal, but, having stolen, is there super-added a duty to confess that he has stolen? I am satisfied that to imply such a duty would be a departure from the well established usage of mankind and would be to create obligations entirely outside the contemplation of the parties concerned ...".'

732. Sutton observes, concerning that decision, at 339:
 
 'What had to be considered was what an honest and competent agent would have communicated to the assured in the ordinary course of business, and such an agent would not have had any dishonesty to reveal.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Insurance Law Commercial Union Assurance Co of Australia Ltd v Beard (2000) 11 ANZ Ins Cas 61-458 </tocase>
<text>728. McNair J discussed the matter at length in Australia and New Zealand Bank Limited v Colonial and Eagles Wharves Limited (1960) 2 Lloyd's Rep. 241. In that case his Lordship assumed that at common law, rules derived from the Marine Insurance Act 1906 (Imp) applied to non-marine insurance. After reference to the authorities, his Lordship observed at 254:
 
 'These judgments make it clear to my mind that it is not the knowledge of all agents or servants that is imputed to the proposer of any marine insurance, but only the knowledge of quite a limited class, namely, the broker who actually places the insurance, the master or the ship agent, or, to use Lord Halsbury's phrase, "his general agent for the management of his shipping business." On the facts of the present case, Henderson was not within that limited class. Though, in a sense, the key man in the sense that a mistake by him would mean the failure of the system his duties were almost entirely clerical; it was not established that he had any discretion or executive authority; he was not superior to the head clerks in the warehouses but co-ordinate with them. He was not, in my judgment, a person within the class of those who were under a duty to report to the company.' 
 

See also Sutton's Insurance Law in Australia (3 rd ed) at pars 3.183 and 3.184, and Tarr's Australian Insurance Law at 104-105. It seems to be generally accepted that the position under the Insurance Contracts Act reflects the common law position.

734. As the duty to disclose extends only to matters which the insured knows, only matters actually known to a relevant agent will be imputed to him or her. In Commercial Union Assurance Co of Australia Ltd v Beard (2000) 11 ANZ Ins Cas 61-458, Davies AJA (Meagher JA and Foster AJA concurring) said at 75-259:
 
 'The terms "known" and "knows" are used in their common law sense. Their primary denotation refers to that which is actually known; but it would be wrong to import the word "actually" into a provision such as section 21. The section does not use it. The terms "known" and "knows" are used in their ordinary sense. Whether a matter is known is a question of fact for the judge or jury.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hammer Waste Pty Ltd v QBE Mutual Ltd [2002] NSWSC 1006</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2002/1006.html</AustLII>
<text>735. In Hammer Waste Pty Ltd v QBE Mutual Ltd [2002] NSWSC 1006 , Palmer J referred to that decision and said:
 
 '... (I)n s 21(1) ... the word "know" is used in its ordinary sense; it implies actual, not constructive, knowledge both on the part of the insured and on the part of any agent or employee of the insured whose "knowledge" is to be imputed to the insured. The obligation to disclose something "known" can attach only to something which, at the time for disclosure, a person actually has in his or her consciousness or else something which exists in some record or other source of information which the person actually knows about and to which the person has access. So, for example, I "know" my driving licence number for the purposes of s 21(1) ... even though I cannot recite it off hand because I actually know that it is to be found in the plastic card in my wallet.'

736. I return to the three matters which may have required disclosure. I am satisfied that a reasonable person, in the circumstances, could be expected to know that each of those matters would be relevant to QBE's decision. I have indicated with respect to the third of those matters, divergence between contents of the newsletters and actual practice, that I am not satisfied that there was any significant divergence. However, for reasons which appear below, it is not necessary finally to decide that question.

737. QBE asserts that Mr Ryan was familiar with the content of the investment summary and knew that Mr Blackadder did not carry out detailed checks of the asset positions of applicants for loans as allegedly asserted in the newsletters, or credit checks against guarantors as asserted in the winter 1999 newsletter. It is said to follow that he had knowledge which should have been disclosed. In my view unless asked, Mr Ryan had no duty to disclose either the content of the newsletters or the actual practice which was adopted. At least for present purposes, neither matter, by itself, exposed either MDRN or QBE to risk. The relevant matter was the alleged divergence between the two. As I have said, I do not necessarily accept that there was a significant divergence. It is at least arguable that the practice as described by Mr Blackadder and Mr Ryan was a form of checking in the sense in which the term was used in the newsletters. Potential investors may have understood the newsletters to imply something more, but for present purposes we are looking at the subjective states of mind of Mr Blackadder and Mr Ryan.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>