<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXEF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (with Corrigendum dated 2 June 2006) [2006] FCA 507 (8 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/507.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>M18/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1289</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/1289.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The matter was remitted to the Federal Court and heard as proceeding VID 676 of 2002. Following a direction by a Registrar of the Court, on 29 November 2002 the appellants filed an amended application under s 475A of the Migration Act 1958 ("the Act ") and s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 . That application, which was heard in the first instance by Sundberg J, alleged that the RRT fell into jurisdictional error by considering out-of-date country information. The appellants' written contentions of fact and law repeated this claim. By a decision delivered 12 November 2003, Sundberg J dismissed the application for review. His Honour said, in M18/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1289 , at [13] and [16]:
 
 "As can be seen, when the Tribunal was considering the applicant's claims as to what happened to her in 1994 and thereafter, it considered information contemporaneous with the times. It would have been irrelevant to consider current information about Sri Lanka in assessing the state of the country after the events were said to have occurred. When it was considering the real chance of persecution on return, it had regard to current information about the country. 
 ... 
 It is to be remembered that the weight to be attributed to country information is a matter for the Tribunal, not for the Court."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>M18/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 127</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/127.html</AustLII>
<text>5 The appellants appealed to a Full Court of this Court. The Full Court said, in M18/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 127 , at [10]-[11], as follows:
 
 "In a notice of appeal filed on 1 December 2003, the appellant effectively repeated the ground raised before the primary judge. That is, it was alleged that the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error by considering dated and not recent country information and the primary judge erred in not concluding that the Tribunal had fallen into jurisdictional error. 
 
 For the reasons given by the primary judge, this contention is without substance."

6 The Full Court also discussed the appellants' additional submissions, which sought to raise the 'medically unfit' ground mentioned in the draft order nisi filed in the High Court. The Court said, at [12]-[19]:
 
 "In written submissions, the [first] appellant raised a number of additional issues. They included that she had been denied procedural fairness because she had been required to attend the hearing before the Tribunal at a time when she was medically unfit. The appellant also contended, in effect, that the Tribunal failed to take into account her mental state when assessing her evidence and, in particular, when considering the significance of her inability to name the Tamil boarders she claimed to have taken in during 1999. 
 
 It is apparent from the Tribunal's reasons that the hearing was delayed for three months at the appellant's request because of a psychologist's report concerning the mental health of the appellant. That report recommended that the appellant should receive treatment for her condition in the interim. After the three months had passed, the Tribunal asked the appellant to attend a hearing on 25 May 2001 but, at the appellant's request (made on 24 May 2001) delayed that hearing until 31 May 2001. The Tribunal refused to delay the hearing for a longer period. It did so on the ground that the psychologist, although stating that the appellant still suffered from the same condition, reported that the appellant had not sought the recommended treatment. The appellant attended the delayed hearing with her legal representative. 
 
 The appellant's amended application and written submissions before the primary Judge were prepared by counsel. That application and those submissions appear to have abandoned a complaint made in the draft order nisi that the appellant was denied procedural fairness (and that the Tribunal failed to follow procedures required by [the Act ] and misconceived its duty) because the hearing before the Tribunal took place when she was suffering from a mental disability. It may well be that the matter was not pursued in either the application or submissions because those advising the appellant considered a denial of procedural fairness was not a ground available under the then legislative regime. 
 
 The allegation of denial of procedural fairness is not raised in the notice of appeal. However it is relatively clear the notice was prepared by the appellant without legal assistance. 
 
 A full investigation of the consequences of any mental illness the appellant might have suffered at the time of the hearings before the Tribunal, would almost certainly have involved evidence being led before the primary judge. It was not."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>MZXEF v Minister for Immigration [2006] FMCA 187</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/187.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The learned Federal Magistrate found ( MZXEF v Minister for Immigration [2006] FMCA 187 at [14] ):
 
"[T] here is little doubt that in this case the issues now sought to be agitated ... are substantially the same as the issues which had been initially before the primary judge in the first application and in any event, which had been considered by the Full Court of the Federal Court on appeal from that decision. "
 
Accordingly, his Honour found that the doctrine of res judicata applied and that the review application should be summarily dismissed. The Federal Magistrate held, in the alternative, that the application constituted an abuse of process and could also be dismissed on that basis.

12 The notice of appeal was broad and unparticularised. It was, however, accompanied by an affidavit sworn by the first appellant on 17 February 2006. The principal grounds of appeal raised by the appellants appear in this affidavit and in the appellants' written submissions filed on 25 April 2006. These grounds were: (1) that the first appellant was medically unfit to give evidence in support of her application before the RRT and was therefore denied procedural fairness and her rights under s 425 of the Act ; and (2) that the RRT failed to consider up-to-date country information.

13 On the hearing of the appeal, the first appellant reiterated both grounds and gave the Court copies of a document containing recent information on the situation in Sri Lanka.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>MZWHW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 466</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/466.html</AustLII>
<text>15 This is the second occasion in which the appellants have instituted proceedings for the judicial review of the RRT's decision in January 2002. The grounds or proposed grounds were (1) the RRT's reliance on out-of-date country information and (2) save before Sundberg J, the first appellant's medical condition at the time of the hearing. At first instance and on appeal, the appellants were unsuccessful. The RRT's reliance on country information was the subject of Sundberg J's and the Full Court's consideration. The appellants seek to raise again the very same ground. I accept the first respondent's submission that there is no error shown in his Honour's conclusion that res judicata applied to preclude the appellants from pursuing a second judicial review application on this ground. Res judicata can operate as a bar to a judicial review application in these circumstances: see MZWHW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 466 (" MZWHW ") at [11] referring to Re Wong v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 722 (" Wong ") at [71].

18 The Federal Magistrate's decision was, so it seems to me, a final decision: see MZWHW at [6]; also SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 at [8] - [11] ; NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975 at [29] ; and MZWZL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1475 at [11] . Accordingly, the appellant did not require leave to appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Wong v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 722</tocase>
<text>15 This is the second occasion in which the appellants have instituted proceedings for the judicial review of the RRT's decision in January 2002. The grounds or proposed grounds were (1) the RRT's reliance on out-of-date country information and (2) save before Sundberg J, the first appellant's medical condition at the time of the hearing. At first instance and on appeal, the appellants were unsuccessful. The RRT's reliance on country information was the subject of Sundberg J's and the Full Court's consideration. The appellants seek to raise again the very same ground. I accept the first respondent's submission that there is no error shown in his Honour's conclusion that res judicata applied to preclude the appellants from pursuing a second judicial review application on this ground. Res judicata can operate as a bar to a judicial review application in these circumstances: see MZWHW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 466 (" MZWHW ") at [11] referring to Re Wong v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 204 ALR 722 (" Wong ") at [71].

16 The issue concerning the first appellant's medical condition formed part of the appellants' application in the High Court and a ground, or proposed ground, of appeal in the Full Court. The Full Court gave detailed consideration to the 'medically unfit' ground in determining whether, if an application to adduce further evidence were made, there would be any basis for the grant of leave. In substance, the Court held that there was no basis for the grant because the proposed ground was untenable in light of what had occurred at the RRT hearing. Even if this were insufficient to attract res judicata because directed to a different issue (namely, whether there was any basis to grant leave to adduce further evidence) from that which arises here, the history of the various proceedings instituted by the appellants discloses that his Honour correctly held the proceeding in the Federal Magistrates Court constituted an abuse of process. This is because, to the extent the appellants relied on the 'medically unfit' ground, these second judicial review proceedings would attract an Anshun estoppel: see Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589. Such an estoppel bars a party from raising any point which properly belonged to the subject of earlier litigation that the party, exercising reasonable diligence, might have brought forward at the time of the earlier proceeding. Plainly enough, the 'medically unfit' ground might have been brought forward for Sundberg J's consideration. Nothing has been established that would attract the discretion that forms part of the Anshun estoppel doctrine: see generally Wong at [49], [61]-[64], [149].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/45.html</AustLII>
<text>16 The issue concerning the first appellant's medical condition formed part of the appellants' application in the High Court and a ground, or proposed ground, of appeal in the Full Court. The Full Court gave detailed consideration to the 'medically unfit' ground in determining whether, if an application to adduce further evidence were made, there would be any basis for the grant of leave. In substance, the Court held that there was no basis for the grant because the proposed ground was untenable in light of what had occurred at the RRT hearing. Even if this were insufficient to attract res judicata because directed to a different issue (namely, whether there was any basis to grant leave to adduce further evidence) from that which arises here, the history of the various proceedings instituted by the appellants discloses that his Honour correctly held the proceeding in the Federal Magistrates Court constituted an abuse of process. This is because, to the extent the appellants relied on the 'medically unfit' ground, these second judicial review proceedings would attract an Anshun estoppel: see Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589. Such an estoppel bars a party from raising any point which properly belonged to the subject of earlier litigation that the party, exercising reasonable diligence, might have brought forward at the time of the earlier proceeding. Plainly enough, the 'medically unfit' ground might have been brought forward for Sundberg J's consideration. Nothing has been established that would attract the discretion that forms part of the Anshun estoppel doctrine: see generally Wong at [49], [61]-[64], [149].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/1.html</AustLII>
<text>17 As the Federal Magistrate noted, the relevant standard for assessing an application for summary dismissal is well established: see, e.g., in Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62. Although it must be very clear that summary dismissal is appropriate, no error is shown in his Honour's decision that this standard was met in this case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/546.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The Federal Magistrate's decision was, so it seems to me, a final decision: see MZWHW at [6]; also SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 at [8] - [11] ; NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975 at [29] ; and MZWZL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1475 at [11] . Accordingly, the appellant did not require leave to appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/975.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The Federal Magistrate's decision was, so it seems to me, a final decision: see MZWHW at [6]; also SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 at [8] - [11] ; NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975 at [29] ; and MZWZL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1475 at [11] . Accordingly, the appellant did not require leave to appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MZWZL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1475</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1475.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The Federal Magistrate's decision was, so it seems to me, a final decision: see MZWHW at [6]; also SZEEO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 546 at [8] - [11] ; NADZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 975 at [29] ; and MZWZL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1475 at [11] . Accordingly, the appellant did not require leave to appeal.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>