<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Matrix Film Investment One Pty Limited v Alameda Films LLC [2006] FCA 591 (19 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/591.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>St George Bank v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147</tocase>
<text>14 The relevant principles in relation to preliminary discovery were summarised by Hely J in St George Bank v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 at [153]-[154]. These indicate that O 15A r 6 is to be beneficially construed and given the fullest scope that its language will reasonably allow, with the proper brake on any excesses lying in the discretion of the Court in the light of the specific circumstances. Each of the elements in sub-paragraphs (a) to (c) of r 6 must be established. The test for determining whether the applicant has "reasonable cause to believe" as required by r 6(a) is an objective one. There is no requirement for the applicant to make out a prima facie case, but a mere assertion that there may be a right to obtain relief is not sufficient. There must be more than suspicion or conjecture. If there is no reasonable cause to believe that one of the necessary elements of a potential cause of action exists, that would dispose of the application in so far as it is based on that cause of action.

15 In relation to r 6(b), the authorities indicate that the question is whether an applicant has sufficient information for the limited purpose of making a decision as to whether to commence proceedings in the Court. It is permissible for an applicant to obtain discovery to determine what defences are available to the respondent, and the possible strength of these defences, but discovery is not available to an applicant so that it may exhaust every possible line of defence. The question as to whether sufficient information is available requires an objective assessment to be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2005) FCA 801</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/801.html</AustLII>
<text>16 The relevant principles were also considered by Lindgren J in Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2005) FCA 801. In that case, his Honour indicated that the measure of preliminary discovery is the extent of information that is necessary, but no more than that which is reasonably necessary, in order to overcome the insufficiency of information already possessed by the applicant after it has made all reasonable inquiries to enable it to make a decision as to whether to commence proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] (unreported, No. NG 351 of 1996)</tocase>
<text>17 In Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] (unreported, No. NG 351 of 1996), Lindgren J stated at [41]:
 
 'The fact that a particular applicant genuinely feels unable, because of a lack of information, to decide to commence a proceeding does not, without more, satisfy para 6 (b); the objective aspect of the paragraph requires it to be shown as an objective fact that the applicant lacks "sufficient information to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding."'

18 At [50], his Honour said:
 
 'Having regard to the extensive scientific research which has been carried out by or on behalf of Alphapharm and its strong prima facie case, it is difficult to avoid the conclusion that in seeking re-action discovery, it is seeking to eliminate a possibility, rather than to obtain key information without which it is not able to commence a proceeding. No doubt inspection of the documents referred to in Alphapharm's application would assist it in taking that decision, but I am of the view that it already has reasonably sufficient information to enable it to decide. Another way of expressing the matter is to say that Alphapharm has not, after making all reasonable inquiries, come up against an obstacle consisting of the lack of key information which it reasonably needs to enable it to decide whether to commence a proceeding; rather, it hopes to be comforted in taking the decision which it already has sufficient information to enable it to take .' (Emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>C7 Pty Limited v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1864.html</AustLII>
<text>19 These remarks, particularly at [50], are apposite to the present case. It is necessary for an applicant to show more than a mere assertion that there is a case against a prospective respondent: see C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864 at [39] . The purpose of preliminary discovery is not to produce material which will strengthen or enhance a decision to commence proceedings but rather to provide what is reasonably necessary to enable the decision to be made.

20 The respondents resist the application and submit that the application must fail because essential elements which must be established under r 6(a) to (c) in order to found jurisdiction in the Federal Court have not been made out. In addition, the respondents submit that as a matter of discretion, the Court should refuse to grant the discovery sought on the basis that it is oppressive and so broadly cast as to encompass what are likely to be a substantial number of irrelevant documents.

21 In relation to r 6(a), the respondents submit that, objectively approached, there is no reasonable cause to believe that the applicant may have a right to obtain relief in the Federal Court. This is because the elements of the prospective cause of action advanced by the applicants which might attract federal jurisdiction, namely, a claim for misleading and deceptive conduct under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), are not present on the evidence. It is said that as an objective conclusion, it has not been established that the elements of such an action can be made out. For present purposes the respondents do not dispute that there may be a cause of action in contract, but say this is not sufficient to ground jurisdiction for the grant of preliminary discovery because it lacks the necessary federal element to satisfy r 6(a) so that there is a right to relief in the Federal Court. Unless there is reasonable cause to believe there is a federal cause of action, it is said that the preliminary discovery application must be refused for want of jurisdiction.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>