<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 642 (29 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/642.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Croker v Deputy Registrar of the High Court of Australia [2003] FCA 681</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/681.html</AustLII>
<text>4 In this matter, I am satisfied that it is appropriate for me to consider the question of security and not refer the matter to a Full Court. The relevant principles were discussed by Hely J in Croker v Deputy Registrar of the High Court of Australia [2003] FCA 681 at [10] - [11] . In that case, his Honour did not consider it appropriate to convene and refer the application for security for costs to a Full Court. Nor did Spender J in Dranichnikov v Centrelink [2002] FCA 1622 , where his Honour took a similar course.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Centrelink [2002] FCA 1622</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/1622.html</AustLII>
<text>4 In this matter, I am satisfied that it is appropriate for me to consider the question of security and not refer the matter to a Full Court. The relevant principles were discussed by Hely J in Croker v Deputy Registrar of the High Court of Australia [2003] FCA 681 at [10] - [11] . In that case, his Honour did not consider it appropriate to convene and refer the application for security for costs to a Full Court. Nor did Spender J in Dranichnikov v Centrelink [2002] FCA 1622 , where his Honour took a similar course.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Endormer Pty Ltd (in liquidation) v Australian Guarantee Corporation Ltd [2001] FCA 510</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/510.html</AustLII>
<text>5 Both these decisions considered a contrary approach to that expressed by Beaumont J in Endormer Pty Ltd (in liquidation) v Australian Guarantee Corporation Ltd [2001] FCA 510 , in which his Honour held that the jurisdiction to order security for costs of an appeal should more properly be exercised by a Full Court.

6 In my view, a single Judge has jurisdiction to hear an application and, in the present case, it is appropriate to do so rather than convene a Full Court to hear the application for security for costs. Moreover, having heard the matter over several days, I am familiar with the background of the matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Keating v Morris &amp; Ors (Moynihan J, Supreme Court of Queensland, 1 September 2005 unreported)</tocase>
<text>7 It was submitted by Mr Anthony Morris QC for Mr Cooper that, as I had previously expressed adverse views as to the credit of some witnesses in the matter, there may be a perception of apprehended bias and I should therefore consider disqualifying myself from hearing the application for security for costs. I have considered the principles set forth in the decision in Keating v Morris &amp; Ors (Moynihan J, Supreme Court of Queensland, 1 September 2005 unreported) at [32] - [47]. It does not follow simply from my rejection of certain evidence and preference for other evidence that, without more, there is any basis for a perception by a reasonable informed observer that I may be perceived to be affected by apprehended bias on this application for security for costs. Therefore, I reject this submission.

8 The record companies have filed an affidavit by Mr Michael Williams, solicitor for the record companies, dated 22 March 2006. The file number on the copy of this affidavit on the Court file does not refer to the number assigned to the particular appeals, but to the number assigned to the matter at first instance. In my view, nothing turns on this, as the affidavit was accompanied by two notices of motion, one in NSD 61 of 2006 and the other in NSD 150 of 2006 in identical terms. I mention these matters because counsel for E-Talk and Mr Bal has contended that it is inappropriate, without a Court order, that evidence on one application for security for costs should be evidence on the other. I do not accept this submission and I make an order that, since the evidence relates to both applications, it may be used in each.

9 Counsel for E-Talk and Mr Bal also submits that evidence in the affidavit of Mr Williams which does not pertain to the circumstances of E-Talk and Mr Bal should be rejected as against them. I accept this submission, and I have read and used the affidavit only in relation to the particular appellants in question. The form of the affidavit makes it clear which paragraphs relate to each of the appeals and which relate to common matters.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cowell v Taylor (1885) 31 Ch D 34</tocase>
<text>11 The Court has a wide discretion in relation to the grant of security for costs. There is no general rule because each case depends upon its own circumstances. In relation to an appeal, Courts have given weight to the injustice that might be caused to a successful litigant if the litigant is compelled to contest the matter for a second time without the probability of obtaining the costs if ultimately successful: Cowell v Taylor (1885) 31 Ch D 34 at 38. In Equity Access v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972, Hill J at 50,635 listed some of the relevant matters to be considered when deciding whether security for costs ought to be awarded:
 
 
 &#8226; the prosects of success;
 &#8226; the quantum of risk that a costs order will not be satisfied;
 &#8226; whether the making of an order would be oppressive in that it would stifle the reasonably arguable claim;
 &#8226; whether any impecuniosity of the appellants arises out of the conduct complained of;
 &#8226; whether there are aspects of public interest which weigh in the balance against such an order;
 &#8226; whether there are any particular discretionary matters peculiar to the circumstances of the case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Equity Access v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972</tocase>
<text>11 The Court has a wide discretion in relation to the grant of security for costs. There is no general rule because each case depends upon its own circumstances. In relation to an appeal, Courts have given weight to the injustice that might be caused to a successful litigant if the litigant is compelled to contest the matter for a second time without the probability of obtaining the costs if ultimately successful: Cowell v Taylor (1885) 31 Ch D 34 at 38. In Equity Access v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972, Hill J at 50,635 listed some of the relevant matters to be considered when deciding whether security for costs ought to be awarded:
 
 
 &#8226; the prosects of success;
 &#8226; the quantum of risk that a costs order will not be satisfied;
 &#8226; whether the making of an order would be oppressive in that it would stifle the reasonably arguable claim;
 &#8226; whether any impecuniosity of the appellants arises out of the conduct complained of;
 &#8226; whether there are aspects of public interest which weigh in the balance against such an order;
 &#8226; whether there are any particular discretionary matters peculiar to the circumstances of the case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 56 FCR 189</tocase>
<text>13 Other relevant considerations affecting the discretion to award costs are also set out in KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 56 FCR 189 per Beazley J; Paton v Campbell Ltd [1993] FCA 449 per Burchett J; Carey-Hazell v Getz Bros (Aust) Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1334 per French J at [28]-[31].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Paton v Campbell Ltd [1993] FCA 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1993/449.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Other relevant considerations affecting the discretion to award costs are also set out in KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 56 FCR 189 per Beazley J; Paton v Campbell Ltd [1993] FCA 449 per Burchett J; Carey-Hazell v Getz Bros (Aust) Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1334 per French J at [28]-[31].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Carey-Hazell v Getz Bros (Aust) Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1334</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1334.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Other relevant considerations affecting the discretion to award costs are also set out in KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 56 FCR 189 per Beazley J; Paton v Campbell Ltd [1993] FCA 449 per Burchett J; Carey-Hazell v Getz Bros (Aust) Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1334 per French J at [28]-[31].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>