<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHFE v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2006] FCA 648 (24 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/648.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAGP v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 709</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/709.html</AustLII>
<text>7 I am satisfied that the appellant has given a satisfactory explanation for his delay. However, the exercise of my discretion to set aside the orders depends not only upon the sufficiency of the explanation but also on whether I come to the view that the appellant has a properly arguable case to go to a hearing of the appeal, see NAGP v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 709 at [3] - [4] ; NALO v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 113 ; NADF v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 71 at [16] - [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NALO v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 113</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/113.html</AustLII>
<text>7 I am satisfied that the appellant has given a satisfactory explanation for his delay. However, the exercise of my discretion to set aside the orders depends not only upon the sufficiency of the explanation but also on whether I come to the view that the appellant has a properly arguable case to go to a hearing of the appeal, see NAGP v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 709 at [3] - [4] ; NALO v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 113 ; NADF v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 71 at [16] - [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NADF v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 71</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/71.html</AustLII>
<text>7 I am satisfied that the appellant has given a satisfactory explanation for his delay. However, the exercise of my discretion to set aside the orders depends not only upon the sufficiency of the explanation but also on whether I come to the view that the appellant has a properly arguable case to go to a hearing of the appeal, see NAGP v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 709 at [3] - [4] ; NALO v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 113 ; NADF v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 71 at [16] - [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yevad Products Pty Limited v Brookfield [2005] FCAFC 263</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/263.html</AustLII>
<text>4 Nevertheless, I am satisfied that I have power to set aside the order on either of two bases; the first is order 35 rule 7(1) if the motion was filed before entry of the order. The second is an implied power under section 23 of the Act to overcome the court's failure to provide a party with a hearing; see Yevad Products Pty Limited v Brookfield [2005] FCAFC 263 at [26] - [33] and the authorities there cited; see also DJL v Central Authority [2000] HCA 17 ; (2000) 201 CLR 226 at [189] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>DJL v Central Authority [2000] HCA 17 ; (2000) 201 CLR 226</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/17.html</AustLII>
<text>4 Nevertheless, I am satisfied that I have power to set aside the order on either of two bases; the first is order 35 rule 7(1) if the motion was filed before entry of the order. The second is an implied power under section 23 of the Act to overcome the court's failure to provide a party with a hearing; see Yevad Products Pty Limited v Brookfield [2005] FCAFC 263 at [26] - [33] and the authorities there cited; see also DJL v Central Authority [2000] HCA 17 ; (2000) 201 CLR 226 at [189] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The Minister fairly raises another issue which was not addressed by the appellant. The issue is the question of whether section 424A was breached. The Minister concedes that in light of a decision of a Full Court in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 (" SZEEU") , the Federal Magistrate's finding that a protection visa application had been adopted in writing was no longer sustainable the Minister concedes that the information contained in the appellant's protection visa application was not "information" falling within the exception contained in section 424A(3)(b) of the Act .

33 However, it seems to me to be clear that the observations of Allsop J in SZEEU at [206] and [207] are applicable. That is to say, "information" does not encompass the RRT's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations nor does it encompass gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the RRT in weighing the evidence by reference to those gaps.

34 Thus, applying the approach adopted by Allsop J at [216] of SZEEU, the RRTs reasons in the present case went to the appellant's manner of giving evidence and the vague and generalised claims which he made it was those factors which informed the RRTs decision and not the information in the protection visa application itself.

35 I am satisfied on a careful reading of the decision of the RRT and the decision of the Federal Magistrate that there is no fairly arguable case that the appellant could succeed on an appeal. I therefore decline to exercise my discretion to set aside the orders which I made on 11 April 2006.

36 The order I will make is that the notice of motion be dismissed with costs.
 


 I certify that the preceding thirty six (36) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson. 

Associate:

Dated: 31 May 2006


 
 The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 24 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 24 May 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/648.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>