<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHIB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 611 (8 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/611.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZHIB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 137</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/137.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The bases of the appellant's claims to be entitled to a protection visa are set out in detail in the reasons for decision of the Tribunal. They are also summarised in the decision of Scarlett FM: see SZHIB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 137.

5 The appellant claims to have been a driver for senior leaders of the Chengbei Industry General Corporation from 1995. In the course of those duties, he became privy to certain views and actions to be taken concerning Mr Guo, a politically active farmer. The appellant became aware that Mr Guo had been or would be falsely incriminated, and consequently the appellant wrote to the People's Court and Procuratorate to let them know the truth. As a result of his actions, the appellant claims to have dismissed from the Chengbei Industry General Corporation in September 1999. He subsequently became a freelance driver after purchasing a second-hand truck.

6 The appellant claims that in January 2003 he became involved in a farmers' union at the behest of Mr Guo and another person by the name of Mr Cong. The farmers' union was known as the Farmer's Self-Supported Association ('the Association'). The appellant says that Mr Guo and Mr Cong requested him to be the public face of the Association because the other men had ongoing problems with the authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>M55 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 131</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/131.html</AustLII>
<text>23 There is, moreover, a second reason for rejecting the appellant's arguments based on s 424A. In my opinion, if any material in the protection visa application was relied upon by the Tribunal as a basis for its findings concerning inconsistencies in the appellant's evidence and its adverse finding on his credibility, that material was republished by the letter accompanying the application to the Tribunal. I have already referred to the content of that letter. The appellant's letter incorporates, in my view, the substantive claims made in the appellant's statutory declaration which supported his application for a protection visa. It follows that the information in the protection visa application became information given by the appellant to the Tribunal within the meaning of subs (3)(b) of s 424A. This view is supported by the authorities: see M55 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 131 ; VUAV v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1271 ; and SZDMJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1034.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VUAV v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1271</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1271.html</AustLII>
<text>23 There is, moreover, a second reason for rejecting the appellant's arguments based on s 424A. In my opinion, if any material in the protection visa application was relied upon by the Tribunal as a basis for its findings concerning inconsistencies in the appellant's evidence and its adverse finding on his credibility, that material was republished by the letter accompanying the application to the Tribunal. I have already referred to the content of that letter. The appellant's letter incorporates, in my view, the substantive claims made in the appellant's statutory declaration which supported his application for a protection visa. It follows that the information in the protection visa application became information given by the appellant to the Tribunal within the meaning of subs (3)(b) of s 424A. This view is supported by the authorities: see M55 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 131 ; VUAV v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1271 ; and SZDMJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1034.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZDMJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1034</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1034.html</AustLII>
<text>23 There is, moreover, a second reason for rejecting the appellant's arguments based on s 424A. In my opinion, if any material in the protection visa application was relied upon by the Tribunal as a basis for its findings concerning inconsistencies in the appellant's evidence and its adverse finding on his credibility, that material was republished by the letter accompanying the application to the Tribunal. I have already referred to the content of that letter. The appellant's letter incorporates, in my view, the substantive claims made in the appellant's statutory declaration which supported his application for a protection visa. It follows that the information in the protection visa application became information given by the appellant to the Tribunal within the meaning of subs (3)(b) of s 424A. This view is supported by the authorities: see M55 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 131 ; VUAV v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1271 ; and SZDMJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1034.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>24 Scarlett FM relied upon a third basis for rejecting the appellant's argument based on s 424A. The third basis was that the inconsistencies identified by the Tribunal did not, in his Honour's opinion, constitute 'information' within the meaning of s 424A(1). The first respondent submitted that this ground must now be viewed as incorrect, having regard to the decision of the Full Court in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2. For the purposes of this appeal, I need do no more than assume that the first respondent is correct in submitting that the third ground can no longer be correctly advanced, having regard to the decision of the Full Court. It does not follow that Scarlett FM's decision is rendered invalid or erroneous by virtue of a reliance on this third ground. The decision was capable of standing independently on one or other of the two grounds that I have earlier discussed.

25 I turn to consider the appellant's claims based on s 425 of the Act. Section 425 provides that the Tribunal must invite the applicant to appear before the Tribunal to give evidence and present arguments relating to the issues in relation to the decision under review.

26 The appellant appeared to make essentially two points in relation to s 425. The first point was that he was not given a proper opportunity to make oral submissions and set out his entire case in full; rather, he was constantly interrupted by questions from the Tribunal. As a result, the appellant says that he did not get the chance to give his oral evidence completely, and became confused and lost as a result of the Tribunal's questioning. Having carefully read the Tribunal's reasons, I have concluded that the Tribunal did not conduct its proceedings in a way which involved any contravention of s 425. The Tribunal invited the appellant to appear before it to give evidence and present arguments, and the appellant had the opportunity of doing precisely that. Section 425 is not infringed by virtue of the fact that the Tribunal asked many questions of the appellant. In any event, it is clear from the Tribunal's reasons that the appellant was invited to make any submission or argument that he wished at the hearing, having regard to the questions that had been posed by the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/1.html</AustLII>
<text>29 More generally, I should observe that the application before the Tribunal failed essentially because the Tribunal did not accept the appellant's claims, having regard to the findings which it made concerning his credibility. Credibility findings are the function of the primary decision-maker, par excellence, as McHugh J said in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 423 [67] . On appeal from a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court, this Court is not required to embark upon a re-hearing of the facts or the evidence heard by the Tribunal: see Abeyesinghe v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1558 at [4] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Abeyesinghe v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1558</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1558.html</AustLII>
<text>29 More generally, I should observe that the application before the Tribunal failed essentially because the Tribunal did not accept the appellant's claims, having regard to the findings which it made concerning his credibility. Credibility findings are the function of the primary decision-maker, par excellence, as McHugh J said in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 423 [67] . On appeal from a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court, this Court is not required to embark upon a re-hearing of the facts or the evidence heard by the Tribunal: see Abeyesinghe v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1558 at [4] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>