<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bayer Bioscience NV v Deltapine Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 68 (10 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/68.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd v Guina Developments Pty Ltd [1996] 2 VR 34 at 38</tocase>
<text>19 Consistently with Dr Cusick's approach, Deltapine's argument centred around the possible redaction of material said not to be relevant to this proceeding. It seems to me with respect however that this rather misses the point. If a document is relevant to the issues in the present proceeding, that does not exclude the risk that disclosure to Professor Adang may lead (without any subjective bad faith on his part) to commercial damage to Bayer. On the contrary, the more relevant the document to this proceeding, the more sensitive and potentially damaging it would be to Bayer. Knowledge once acquired cannot be isolated within the mind behind some internal Chinese wall: see Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd v Guina Developments Pty Ltd [1996] 2 VR 34 at 38.

20 I think Bayer have made out a case for refusing disclosure. The hard fact is that Professor Adang is a direct commercial competitor in the field of the Patent. The documents in question are admitted to be confidential.

21 It is not clear whether refusal of disclosure to Professor Adang means that he will not be giving evidence for Deltapine. Deltapine did not assert as much before me. However, I accept that at the very least his value as a witness would be substantially affected. But I am confident that no substantial injustice will be caused to Deltapine because they propose to lead evidence from three other experts, Professor Richard Roush, Director of the Statewide IPM Program at the University of California at Davis, Professor Sarjeet Gill, Chair of the Department of Cell Biology and Neuroscience, University of California at Riverside and Dr Paul Ebert of the School of Life Sciences, University of Queensland, all of whom appear to be eminently qualified. Bayer has consented to Deltapine providing its confidential documents to both Professor Gill and Dr Ebert. Deltapine does not wish to disclose Bayer's confidential documents to Professor Roush.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>