<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investment Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 5) [2006] FCA 684 (1 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/684.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission , In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 3) [2006] FCA 433</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/433.html</AustLII>
<text>2 For reasons published on 20 April 2006 orders were made appointing receivers to the property of the four individuals and three of the corporations being the fifth, sixth and eighth defendants Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 3) [2006] FCA 433. A separate order, by way of a Mareva injunction, was made against the seventh defendant, Bowesco Pty Ltd, which was already in receivership under the terms of securities over its assets. Similar orders were made in relation to Keypoint Developments on 26 May 2006 - Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 4) [2006] FCA 644.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 4) [2006] FCA 644</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/644.html</AustLII>
<text>2 For reasons published on 20 April 2006 orders were made appointing receivers to the property of the four individuals and three of the corporations being the fifth, sixth and eighth defendants Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 3) [2006] FCA 433. A separate order, by way of a Mareva injunction, was made against the seventh defendant, Bowesco Pty Ltd, which was already in receivership under the terms of securities over its assets. Similar orders were made in relation to Keypoint Developments on 26 May 2006 - Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd (ACN 099 071 968) v Carey (No 4) [2006] FCA 644.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Burke [2000] NSWSC 694</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2000/694.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In accordance with the authorities relating to the application of s 1323 and its predecessors there was no requirement on ASIC to demonstrate a prime facie case of liability on the part of the defendants or that they had contravened any law or even that their assets had been or were about to be dissipated. There was therefore a need for restraint in the formulation of orders made under the section. The appointment of a receiver is 'an extraordinary step' Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Burke [2000] NSWSC 694 at [8] (Austin J). In the present case the interlocutory character and protective purposes of the orders made were considered in defining the limits of the receivers' powers. The powers so defined were a moderated and qualified version of those initially sought by ASIC.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson (1984) 3 NSWLR 547</tocase>
<text>18 The provisional character of the judgments upon which the orders for the appointment of the receivers were based informs consideration of the question whether the receivers' costs of discharging their functions under those orders should be borne by the defendants. It is not the object of the orders made under s 1323 to punish the defendants. Their object is to preserve their assets and thereby protect the interests of persons to whom they may have a liability. A secondary object is to ascertain the extent of the assets. This understanding of the purpose of such orders is well established in case law relating to s 1323 and its predecessors. In Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson (1984) 3 NSWLR 547, Waddell J said of the like provisions of s 573 of the Companies (New South Wales) Code (at 553):
 
 '... the purpose of appointing a receiver is to provide security for the moneys which the relevant person is, or may become, liable to pay.' 
 

See also Corporate Affairs Commission v Transphere (1988) 15 NSWLR 596 at 611; Corporate Affairs Commission v ASC Timber Pty Ltd (1992) 10 ACSR 525 at 531.

21 The point was well made by Waddell J in Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson in which the appointment of receivers under s 573 of the Corporations (New South Wales) Code was considered. The section was, in the relevant parts, similar to s 1323. Waddell J pointed to the 'severe effects' that the appointment of a receiver might have upon a defendant noting that the court was precluded from requiring the Commission to give an undertaking as to damages as a condition of appointing a receiver. Unjustified and irrecoverable damage could be suffered where the relevant person was subject to the appointment of receivers as security for claims which might not be made out. Waddell J further said (at 556): 
 
 'If a receiver is appointed on terms which permit him to take his remuneration out of the assets received by him, the unjustified damage caused to the relevant person would be so much greater. It should not be thought that in every case the property of a relevant person may be taken over by a receiver and his financial affairs investigated in order to provide security for claims against him, which may or may not succeed, on the basis that in any event the relevant person will have to pay the receiver's remuneration. It may well be that in a particular case, in order to avoid such a consequence, no order should be made permitting the receiver to take his remuneration out of the assets received, thus leaving it to the Commissioner to be responsible for such remuneration pending a determination of the liability of the relevant person.' 
 

In Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 194, Hill J cited the passage from the judgment of Waddell J including that quoted above, and said (at 204): 
 
 'I am in complete agreement with what is said by Waddell J.'

56 In my opinion the Court has the power to order the examination of a party on the adequacy of a disclosure affidavit provided pursuant to an order of the Court under s 1323 of the Corporations Act . In Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson, Waddell J said (at 554): 
 
 'What then can be done to enforce an order made under s 573 for the appointment of a receiver of all of the property of a relevant person? Such an order should, I think, ordinarily be accompanied by an order having the effect of requiring the relevant person to file in court an affidavit listing all his property and a further order having the effect of requiring him to transfer or deliver all of it to the receiver. If the relevant person fails to comply with such orders proceedings could be taken against him for contempt of court or, in my opinion, an order could be made under the Supreme Court Rules 1970 , Pt 43 , r 1, for him to attend before an officer of the court and be orally examined on such questions concerning or in aid of the enforcement of the order as may be specified in the order for examination. Under that rule he can also be required to produce documents.'

57 The Court may make such ancillary orders in support of its disclosure requirements as are necessary to enable the receivers it has appointed properly to discharge their functions. The power to do so derives from s 23 of the Federal Court Act , if from no other source. That power may well have a wider application than the power to make orders ancillary to a Mareva or other injunction in proceedings between private parties. The Court could, as an incident of its power to appoint receivers, require a relevant person to present himself or herself for examination by the receivers or ASIC before a Registrar in order to ascertain the extent and nature of the person's assets. The use of a disclosure affidavit is not required in every case. It is simply a mechanism to the same end. The Court is not confined to directing the filing of a disclosure affidavit and only if that is inadequate directing oral examination of the deponent.

58 In my opinion there is a real possibility that the disclosure affidavits sworn by Mr Carey have failed to disclose the full extent of assets and property owned or controlled by him or in relation to which he has an interest. The term 'control' used in Order 4 is to be interpreted according to its ordinary meaning and not limited to property in which he has a legal or beneficial interest.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Corporate Affairs Commission v Transphere (1988) 15 NSWLR 596</tocase>
<text>18 The provisional character of the judgments upon which the orders for the appointment of the receivers were based informs consideration of the question whether the receivers' costs of discharging their functions under those orders should be borne by the defendants. It is not the object of the orders made under s 1323 to punish the defendants. Their object is to preserve their assets and thereby protect the interests of persons to whom they may have a liability. A secondary object is to ascertain the extent of the assets. This understanding of the purpose of such orders is well established in case law relating to s 1323 and its predecessors. In Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson (1984) 3 NSWLR 547, Waddell J said of the like provisions of s 573 of the Companies (New South Wales) Code (at 553):
 
 '... the purpose of appointing a receiver is to provide security for the moneys which the relevant person is, or may become, liable to pay.' 
 

See also Corporate Affairs Commission v Transphere (1988) 15 NSWLR 596 at 611; Corporate Affairs Commission v ASC Timber Pty Ltd (1992) 10 ACSR 525 at 531.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Corporate Affairs Commission v ASC Timber Pty Ltd (1992) 10 ACSR 525</tocase>
<text>18 The provisional character of the judgments upon which the orders for the appointment of the receivers were based informs consideration of the question whether the receivers' costs of discharging their functions under those orders should be borne by the defendants. It is not the object of the orders made under s 1323 to punish the defendants. Their object is to preserve their assets and thereby protect the interests of persons to whom they may have a liability. A secondary object is to ascertain the extent of the assets. This understanding of the purpose of such orders is well established in case law relating to s 1323 and its predecessors. In Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson (1984) 3 NSWLR 547, Waddell J said of the like provisions of s 573 of the Companies (New South Wales) Code (at 553):
 
 '... the purpose of appointing a receiver is to provide security for the moneys which the relevant person is, or may become, liable to pay.' 
 

See also Corporate Affairs Commission v Transphere (1988) 15 NSWLR 596 at 611; Corporate Affairs Commission v ASC Timber Pty Ltd (1992) 10 ACSR 525 at 531.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jackson v Sterling Industries Ltd [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/23.html</AustLII>
<text>19 The Corporations Act does not expressly authorise the Court to make an order that the persons or companies who are the subject of the orders appointing receivers to their property pay the costs of those receivers in discharging their function. The Court may confer upon the receivers 'such powers as the Court orders'. Such powers necessarily relate to the ways in which the receivers can deal with a relevant person's property. The imposition of a costs liability by the Court is not readily accommodated by words authorising it to confer powers on the receivers. Absent any express power in the Corporations Act the relevant provision can be found in s 23 of the Federal Court Act or in the implied incidental power Jackson v Sterling Industries Ltd [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612.

20 Although, in my opinion, the existence of a power to impose a liability to pay receivers' remuneration out of the defendants' assets can be found in s 23 as an incident of the powers conferred on the Court by s 1323 of the Corporations Act , it is not lightly to be exercised.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 194</tocase>
<text>21 The point was well made by Waddell J in Corporate Affairs Commission v Smithson in which the appointment of receivers under s 573 of the Corporations (New South Wales) Code was considered. The section was, in the relevant parts, similar to s 1323. Waddell J pointed to the 'severe effects' that the appointment of a receiver might have upon a defendant noting that the court was precluded from requiring the Commission to give an undertaking as to damages as a condition of appointing a receiver. Unjustified and irrecoverable damage could be suffered where the relevant person was subject to the appointment of receivers as security for claims which might not be made out. Waddell J further said (at 556): 
 
 'If a receiver is appointed on terms which permit him to take his remuneration out of the assets received by him, the unjustified damage caused to the relevant person would be so much greater. It should not be thought that in every case the property of a relevant person may be taken over by a receiver and his financial affairs investigated in order to provide security for claims against him, which may or may not succeed, on the basis that in any event the relevant person will have to pay the receiver's remuneration. It may well be that in a particular case, in order to avoid such a consequence, no order should be made permitting the receiver to take his remuneration out of the assets received, thus leaving it to the Commissioner to be responsible for such remuneration pending a determination of the liability of the relevant person.' 
 

In Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 194, Hill J cited the passage from the judgment of Waddell J including that quoted above, and said (at 204): 
 
 'I am in complete agreement with what is said by Waddell J.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Berona Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 18 ACSR 772</tocase>
<text>22 In Australian Securities Commission v Berona Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 18 ACSR 772, Cooper J held that the conduct of the respondents and their controllers had resulted in the appointment of the receivers and that there was therefore no need to depart from 'the ordinary rule that the respondents be liable for the costs of the receiver appointed by the Court'. In so concluding, Cooper J cited a judgment of McPherson J in Rosanove v O'Rourke (1987) 1 Qd R 275. The question in that case was whether receivers appointed in the equitable jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of Queensland, to a partnership in dispute, should be able to recover against the partners personally for their remuneration where partnership assets were not sufficient. McPherson J answered the question in the affirmative but was reversed in the Full Court in Rosanove v O'Rourke (1988) 1 Qd R 171. It was not in dispute that the receivers could recover their remuneration out of the assets of the partnership. Connolly J said (at 174):
 
 'Trustees and receivers are, generally speaking, in a similar position in at least two respects. First, both are permanently liable on their contracts and second, both have a right of indemnity out of the property or estate.' 
 

That similarity did not extend to the trustee's right to recover from a beneficiary personally the amount expended by them (174). In my opinion the position of a receiver appointed in the exercise of equitable jurisdiction differs from that of a receiver appointed in the exercise of the statutory power conferred by s 1323. There is no entitlement, that goes with the appointment, to recover remuneration from the assets of the relevant person. The appointment under s 1323 when made on the application of ASIC and based on an ongoing investigation, aids the public regulatory and protective functions conferred upon ASIC by the Corporations Act and by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission Act 2001 (Cth) . That is a foundation for such an appointment which differs from that which underpins the private equitable remedy.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rosanove v O'Rourke (1988) 1 Qd R 171</tocase>
<text>22 In Australian Securities Commission v Berona Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 18 ACSR 772, Cooper J held that the conduct of the respondents and their controllers had resulted in the appointment of the receivers and that there was therefore no need to depart from 'the ordinary rule that the respondents be liable for the costs of the receiver appointed by the Court'. In so concluding, Cooper J cited a judgment of McPherson J in Rosanove v O'Rourke (1987) 1 Qd R 275. The question in that case was whether receivers appointed in the equitable jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of Queensland, to a partnership in dispute, should be able to recover against the partners personally for their remuneration where partnership assets were not sufficient. McPherson J answered the question in the affirmative but was reversed in the Full Court in Rosanove v O'Rourke (1988) 1 Qd R 171. It was not in dispute that the receivers could recover their remuneration out of the assets of the partnership. Connolly J said (at 174):
 
 'Trustees and receivers are, generally speaking, in a similar position in at least two respects. First, both are permanently liable on their contracts and second, both have a right of indemnity out of the property or estate.' 
 

That similarity did not extend to the trustee's right to recover from a beneficiary personally the amount expended by them (174). In my opinion the position of a receiver appointed in the exercise of equitable jurisdiction differs from that of a receiver appointed in the exercise of the statutory power conferred by s 1323. There is no entitlement, that goes with the appointment, to recover remuneration from the assets of the relevant person. The appointment under s 1323 when made on the application of ASIC and based on an ongoing investigation, aids the public regulatory and protective functions conferred upon ASIC by the Corporations Act and by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission Act 2001 (Cth) . That is a foundation for such an appointment which differs from that which underpins the private equitable remedy.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Cooke (1996) 22 ACSR 580</tocase>
<text>23 In Australian Securities Commission v Cooke (1996) 22 ACSR 580, Nicholson J made an order for receiver's costs under s 1323 to recover remuneration out of the estate of the relevant person. There were, however, no reasons given to explain that order and it does not appear that it was the subject of any argument before his Honour.

24 I do not consider at this stage that, absent agreement, I should order that the receivers recover the costs and remuneration out of the assets of the defendants. While there are serious concerns about the conduct of the defendants, these are based on provisional judgments about the facts. No liability has been ascertained. I am prepared to make an order in respect of the third and fourth defendants because they have consented to that course no doubt on the basis that they are insulated from the risk of having to contribute to the costs of the receiverships over other defendants. ASIC will have liberty to apply again for the orders it seeks as circumstances change. It may also seek an order at or before the end of the receivership that it be indemnified out of the assets of the defendants (other than the third and fourth defendants) for any payments made by it to the receivers in relation to the discharge of their functions.

25 In the orders made on 20 April 2006 there was included, as against Mr Carey and other individual defendants, an order in the following terms: 
 
 
 4. Except to the extent that a claim of privilege against self incrimination or exposure to civil penalty is made by any of the First, Second, Third and Fourth Defendants, each of the First, Second, Third and Fourth Defendants shall, by 5.00pm on Thursday 4 May 2006, deliver or cause to be delivered to the Plaintiff and the Individual Receivers full and detailed affidavits sworn by each of them, setting out: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 4.1 the name and address of any bank, building society or other financial institution at which there is an account in the name of or under the control of the respective Defendant, together with the number of such account, the name of such account and the balance of that account at the date of this Order; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 4.2 the name and address of any person or persons indebted to the respective Defendant at the date of this Order and the amount of the indebtedness; 
 
 4.3 an itemised inventory of the respective Defendant's assets and liabilities; 
 
 4.4 an itemised inventory of any and all property whether real or personal; 
 
 
 
 
 4.4.1 owned by the respective Defendant; 
 4.4.2 controlled by the respective Defendant; and 
 4.4.3 in which the respective Defendant has an interest, 
 
 and which includes details of the location of that property;...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kodak (Australasia) Pty Ltd v Cochran (unreported Supreme Court of New South Wales, Equity Division, Brownie J, 4 April 1996)</tocase>
<text>49 As a primary position, Mr Carey argued that the Court should not be required to look beyond the affidavits which he had filed. It was submitted that cross-examination of a deponent of a disclosure affidavit will not normally be ordered. An order for cross-examination should only be made when such an order is the only just and convenient way of ensuring the deponent would not deal with his assets so as to deprive a plaintiff of the fruits of a judgment. Reference was made to Kodak (Australasia) Pty Ltd v Cochran (unreported Supreme Court of New South Wales, Equity Division, Brownie J, 4 April 1996); House of Spring Gardens v Waite (1985) FSR 173. It was also submitted that it may not be appropriate to make an order for cross-examination when a deponent is prepared to provide a further affidavit. He cited Planet International Ltd v Garcia (No 2) [1991] 1 Qd R 426.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>House of Spring Gardens v Waite (1985) FSR 173</tocase>
<text>49 As a primary position, Mr Carey argued that the Court should not be required to look beyond the affidavits which he had filed. It was submitted that cross-examination of a deponent of a disclosure affidavit will not normally be ordered. An order for cross-examination should only be made when such an order is the only just and convenient way of ensuring the deponent would not deal with his assets so as to deprive a plaintiff of the fruits of a judgment. Reference was made to Kodak (Australasia) Pty Ltd v Cochran (unreported Supreme Court of New South Wales, Equity Division, Brownie J, 4 April 1996); House of Spring Gardens v Waite (1985) FSR 173. It was also submitted that it may not be appropriate to make an order for cross-examination when a deponent is prepared to provide a further affidavit. He cited Planet International Ltd v Garcia (No 2) [1991] 1 Qd R 426.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Planet International Ltd v Garcia (No 2) [1991] 1 QD R 426</tocase>
<text>49 As a primary position, Mr Carey argued that the Court should not be required to look beyond the affidavits which he had filed. It was submitted that cross-examination of a deponent of a disclosure affidavit will not normally be ordered. An order for cross-examination should only be made when such an order is the only just and convenient way of ensuring the deponent would not deal with his assets so as to deprive a plaintiff of the fruits of a judgment. Reference was made to Kodak (Australasia) Pty Ltd v Cochran (unreported Supreme Court of New South Wales, Equity Division, Brownie J, 4 April 1996); House of Spring Gardens v Waite (1985) FSR 173. It was also submitted that it may not be appropriate to make an order for cross-examination when a deponent is prepared to provide a further affidavit. He cited Planet International Ltd v Garcia (No 2) [1991] 1 Qd R 426.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>