<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Adams v Lambert [2006] FCA 623 (25 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/623.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Adams v Lambert [2004] FCA 928 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/928.html</AustLII>
<text>2 On 1 July 2004 I made the following orders in this proceeding ( Adams v Lambert [2004] FCA 928): 
 
 '(1) The petition be dismissed. 
 
 
 (2) The applicant petitioner is to pay the respondent debtor's costs (including any reserved costs).'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Adams v Lambert [2006] HCA 10 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/10.html</AustLII>
<text>3 On 4 April 2006 the High Court, inter alia, made the following orders ( Adams v Lambert [2006] HCA 10): 
 
 '2. ... 
 
 
 
 (b) the orders of Gyles J made on 1 July 2004 be set aside. 
 
 
 
 
 3. Remit the matter to a Judge of the Federal Court of Australia for further hearing in accordance with the reasons of this Court.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne (1984) 4 FCR 156 </tocase>
<text>7 It is submitted by counsel for the applicant creditor that the case falls squarely within the proviso to s 52(4) as the petition was dismissed. It is submitted that the reasoning of the Full Court in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne (1984) 4 FCR 156, particularly per Toohey and Wilcox JJ at 158, confirms that conclusion.

8 The orders of the High Court and the passage of the judgment which relates to them contemplate that the matter will proceed to a hearing of the case, although there is no indication that the present issue was present to the minds of the Court. As pointed out in the passage from the judgment of Toohey and Wilcox JJ in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne (above) somewhat anomalous results occur whichever view is taken where a petition comes on for hearing nearly two years from its date. In Rangott v Marshall [2004] FCA 961 ; (2004) 139 FCR 14 at [24] I said:
 
 'It seems that the Act does not expressly address the imposition of an appellate regime upon the provisions in relation to sequestration and bankruptcy. That may be an accident of history.' 
 

However, as I held in that case, there is an appellate regime which applies to sequestration orders, the critical provision of which is s 28 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).

10 In my opinion, the section should not be read in that fashion as it would, in many cases, frustrate the appeal provisions. As this case illustrates, it takes time to dispose of appeals. An order extending a petition which has been dismissed could hardly be made in the meantime. It is, no doubt, for this reason that that point was not taken up either by the Full Court of this Court or by the High Court, notwithstanding invitations to do so by counsel for the applicant creditor. That conclusion is consistent with the reasoning of the Full Court in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne . In other words, in my opinion, 'dismissal' in s 52(4) means dismissal in fact, whether or not subsequently set aside (cf Yilmaz v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 906 ; (2000) 100 FCR 495).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Elyard Corporation Pty Ltd v DDB Needham Sydney Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 385 </tocase>
<text>6 It is submitted on behalf of the debtor that, as no order has been made pursuant to subsection (5), the petition lapsed at the expiration of the period of 12 months commencing on the date of the presentation of the petition. It is submitted that there is now no power to extend the period relying upon the decision of the Full Court in Re Young; Ex parte Smith (1985) 5 FCR 204. It is submitted that there could be no use of the slip rule to cure the problem such as occurred in Elyard Corporation Pty Ltd v DDB Needham Sydney Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 385, applied in circumstances such as these in Re Howell; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 261.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>MacDonald v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2001] FCA 140 ; (2001) 107 FCR 72</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/140.html</AustLII>
<text>12 In my opinion, an amendment should be allowed having in mind authorities such as MacDonald v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2001] FCA 140 ; (2001) 107 FCR 72 and Re Pinkerton; Ex parte BG Textiles Pty Ltd (in liq) (1984) 4 FCR 64. The amendments are to deal with the debateable result of the effect of the Regulations upon undisputed primary facts as to service. The amended petition would plainly refer to precisely the same set of events as did the original petition. There is no room for misunderstanding or misleading the respondent debtor. There is no evidence led on behalf of the respondent debtor or any suggestion made on his behalf that any prejudice flows from the amendment. The amendment, however, should not include the words in parenthesis starting with 'or on' down to 'in this paragraph'. There being no prejudice, I would order that the amended petition need not be served again.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rangott v Marshall [2004] FCA 961 ; (2004) 139 FCR 14</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/961.html</AustLII>
<text>8 The orders of the High Court and the passage of the judgment which relates to them contemplate that the matter will proceed to a hearing of the case, although there is no indication that the present issue was present to the minds of the Court. As pointed out in the passage from the judgment of Toohey and Wilcox JJ in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne (above) somewhat anomalous results occur whichever view is taken where a petition comes on for hearing nearly two years from its date. In Rangott v Marshall [2004] FCA 961 ; (2004) 139 FCR 14 at [24] I said:
 
 'It seems that the Act does not expressly address the imposition of an appellate regime upon the provisions in relation to sequestration and bankruptcy. That may be an accident of history.' 
 

However, as I held in that case, there is an appellate regime which applies to sequestration orders, the critical provision of which is s 28 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).

9 I have no difficulty in agreeing with the submission of counsel for the applicant creditor that the decision of the Full Court in Re Young; Ex parte Smith (above) is not in point. It did not deal with the problem occasioned by the dismissal of a petition, when that dismissal is subsequently set aside on appeal. Nonetheless, the question remains as to the effect of the order of the High Court setting aside the dismissal. On one view, it is as if the dismissal had never occurred (cf Rangott v Marshall (above) at [29]). Thus, there is an argument that, as the dismissal never occurred, the proviso to s 52(4) was not met and the petition has lapsed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Re Howell; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 261 </tocase>
<text>6 It is submitted on behalf of the debtor that, as no order has been made pursuant to subsection (5), the petition lapsed at the expiration of the period of 12 months commencing on the date of the presentation of the petition. It is submitted that there is now no power to extend the period relying upon the decision of the Full Court in Re Young; Ex parte Smith (1985) 5 FCR 204. It is submitted that there could be no use of the slip rule to cure the problem such as occurred in Elyard Corporation Pty Ltd v DDB Needham Sydney Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 385, applied in circumstances such as these in Re Howell; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 261.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Re Young; Ex parte Smith (1985) 5 FCR 204 </tocase>
<text>6 It is submitted on behalf of the debtor that, as no order has been made pursuant to subsection (5), the petition lapsed at the expiration of the period of 12 months commencing on the date of the presentation of the petition. It is submitted that there is now no power to extend the period relying upon the decision of the Full Court in Re Young; Ex parte Smith (1985) 5 FCR 204. It is submitted that there could be no use of the slip rule to cure the problem such as occurred in Elyard Corporation Pty Ltd v DDB Needham Sydney Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 385, applied in circumstances such as these in Re Howell; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 261.

9 I have no difficulty in agreeing with the submission of counsel for the applicant creditor that the decision of the Full Court in Re Young; Ex parte Smith (above) is not in point. It did not deal with the problem occasioned by the dismissal of a petition, when that dismissal is subsequently set aside on appeal. Nonetheless, the question remains as to the effect of the order of the High Court setting aside the dismissal. On one view, it is as if the dismissal had never occurred (cf Rangott v Marshall (above) at [29]). Thus, there is an argument that, as the dismissal never occurred, the proviso to s 52(4) was not met and the petition has lapsed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re Pinkerton; Ex parte BG Textiles Pty Ltd (in liq) (1984) 4 FCR 64</tocase>
<text>12 In my opinion, an amendment should be allowed having in mind authorities such as MacDonald v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2001] FCA 140 ; (2001) 107 FCR 72 and Re Pinkerton; Ex parte BG Textiles Pty Ltd (in liq) (1984) 4 FCR 64. The amendments are to deal with the debateable result of the effect of the Regulations upon undisputed primary facts as to service. The amended petition would plainly refer to precisely the same set of events as did the original petition. There is no room for misunderstanding or misleading the respondent debtor. There is no evidence led on behalf of the respondent debtor or any suggestion made on his behalf that any prejudice flows from the amendment. The amendment, however, should not include the words in parenthesis starting with 'or on' down to 'in this paragraph'. There being no prejudice, I would order that the amended petition need not be served again.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yilmaz v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 906 ; (2000) 100 FCR 495</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/906.html</AustLII>
<text>10 In my opinion, the section should not be read in that fashion as it would, in many cases, frustrate the appeal provisions. As this case illustrates, it takes time to dispose of appeals. An order extending a petition which has been dismissed could hardly be made in the meantime. It is, no doubt, for this reason that that point was not taken up either by the Full Court of this Court or by the High Court, notwithstanding invitations to do so by counsel for the applicant creditor. That conclusion is consistent with the reasoning of the Full Court in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Clyne . In other words, in my opinion, 'dismissal' in s 52(4) means dismissal in fact, whether or not subsequently set aside (cf Yilmaz v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 906 ; (2000) 100 FCR 495).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>