<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Commonwealth Bank of Australia v Jeans, in the matterof Jeans [2006] FCA 693 (10 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/693.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ling v Enrobook Pty Limited (1997) 74 FCR 19</tocase>
<text>11 The prejudice to the bank of not my making a sequestration order today is that it may be affected by a dissipation of assets by the debtor after today including a dissipation in the pursuit of the litigation against Mr Cleary. I have been referred to the decision of the Full Court of this court in Ling v Enrobook Pty Limited (1997) 74 FCR 19 and in particular the court's statement of the test to be applied for the purposes of determining whether, pursuant to s 52(2) of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth), I could be satisfied by the debtor that 'for other sufficient cause a sequestration order ought not to be made' and that therefore I might in my discretion dismiss the petition. The court said (74 FCR at 26D-E):
 
 'The authorities also show that satisfaction that the debtor is well advanced with litigation likely to result in the debtor being in a position to pay his or her debts may well provide a basis for a finding that there is a " sufficient cause " for a sequestration order not to be made (see, for example, Maddestra v Penfolds Wines Pty Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 303 ). But the authorities do not suggest that it is in the public interest to allow insolvent debtors to prosecute litigation generally. They only recognise that it is not in the public interest for a debtor to be forced into bankruptcy by reason of a state of insolvency likely to be of only short duration'

12 Mr Ireland QC, who appears for the debtor, has asked for an adjournment to permit, if it is at all possible, that the consideration of whether sufficient cause has been made out occur once the outcome of the Supreme Court proceedings is known. Mr Bell points out that if the petition remains undetermined prior to its expiry on 9 July 2006 the bank will lose the benefit of any relation back period based on the occurrence of the act of bankruptcy which founds the petition. If I were to grant an adjournment there would be a very tight time frame within which, ultimately, a Supreme Court judge would have to give a reasoned final judgment, if that were to happen prior to the expiry date of the petition.

13 On the other hand if I were to refuse to grant an adjournment of the petition, a case which clearly has a triable issue as found by the Court of Appeal, and which has a number of very difficult factual and legal issues may never be able to be determined since the overwhelming quantum of the debtor's creditors consist of the bank by reason of the size of the judgment debt.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>