<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nyangatjatjara Aboriginal Corporation v Registrar of Aboriginal Corporations (No 2) [2006] FCA 675 (1 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/675.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Perkins v Cuthill (1981) 34 ALR 669</tocase>
<text>35 The other formulation of the appropriate test is that an order may be made under s 15(1) of the ADJR Act if the applicant satisfies the Court that it is just in all the circumstances to make such an order. That was the approach suggested by Keely J in Perkins v Cuthill (1981) 34 ALR 669 at 671 and favoured by French J in Snow v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1987) 14 FCR 119 at 131.

37 In Snow v Deputy Commission of Taxation (supra), French J said that there may be cases where an order under s 15 of the ADJR Act will not be made, even though the test for the granting of an interlocutory injunction is satisfied. His Honour said (at 129):
 
 'In my opinion however there may be cases where, for reasons peculiar to the administration of the Judicial Review Act and the particular legislative scheme on which it is operating, the establishment of a "serious question" to be tried and a balance of convenience in favour of an applicant, ordinarily sufficient to justify the grant of an interlocutory injunction, will be insufficient to warrant the making of an order under s 15. 
 
 It is unnecessary for present purposes to attempt an exhaustive definition of the boundaries within which the powers conferred by the two sections may operate.' 


Allowing for that possibility, French J said that it would be preferable to adopt the test formulated by Keely J in Perkins v Cuthill (supra).

38 In many cases, including the present, the application of the test for an interlocutory injunction is the proper test to be applied on an application under s 15(1). Both parties to this application argued the application on the basis that the two requirements for an interlocutory injunction were both necessary and sufficient and I will proceed on that same basis.

39 I turn to consider whether there is a serious question to be tried.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Snow v Deputy Federal Commissioner of Taxation (WA) (1987) 70 ALR 672</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Faingold v Zammit (1984) 1 FCR 87</tocase>
<text>36 In Faingold v Zammit (1984) 1 FCR 87 the Full Court of this Court considered the two formulations and said that, in practical terms, there may be very little difference between them. It held that the trial judge in that case had not erred in applying the test appropriate on the application for an interlocutory injunction.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>43 To successfully challenge the Registrar's decision, the applicants must make out one of the above grounds in the context of a power the exercise of which is conditioned on the Registrar being satisfied of one of the grounds in s 71(2) of the Act. The question of the limits that this fact places on the scope of a challenge to a decision has been considered in a number of authorities, but it is unnecessary to pause on this point on this application: Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110; Darling Casino Ltd v NSW Casino Control Authority [1997] HCA 11 ; (1997) 191 CLR 602 per Gaudron and Gummow JJ at 628-629.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Darling Casino Ltd v NSW Casino Control Authority [1997] HCA 11 ; (1997) 191 CLR 602</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/11.html</AustLII>
<text>43 To successfully challenge the Registrar's decision, the applicants must make out one of the above grounds in the context of a power the exercise of which is conditioned on the Registrar being satisfied of one of the grounds in s 71(2) of the Act. The question of the limits that this fact places on the scope of a challenge to a decision has been considered in a number of authorities, but it is unnecessary to pause on this point on this application: Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110; Darling Casino Ltd v NSW Casino Control Authority [1997] HCA 11 ; (1997) 191 CLR 602 per Gaudron and Gummow JJ at 628-629.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jameson v Guri Wa Ngundagar Aboriginal Corporation [2001] FCA 1104</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1104.html</AustLII>
<text>46 The Registrar authorised the preparation of the examination report pursuant to s 60. The examiner spoke to certain persons for the purposes of preparing the examination report. The applicants contend that there were persons the examiner should have spoken to, to whom he did not speak. The notice to show cause is based on the findings of the examiner, as set out in his report. As I have said, it seems that the delegate of the Registrar had a copy of the examination report before preparing the notice to show cause, but the examination report was marked 'Draft'. It was not until some time after the service of the notice to show cause that the delegate was told the examination report marked 'Draft' was in fact the final report. There is evidence before me that the delegate was told this some time in late February 2006. The conclusions of the delegate for the purposes of his decision to appoint an administrator were based on the findings of the examiner. The applicants asked for a copy of the examination report before responding to the notice to show cause, but it was not provided. I doubt that the failure to provide the examination report amounts to a breach of the rules of natural justice: see Jameson v Guri Wa Ngundagar Aboriginal Corporation [2001] FCA 1104. The applicants pointed to the fact that the Registrar did not raise any further concerns that she had despite their invitation by letter dated 5 April 2006 to do so.

47 It is not clear to me that there is a serious question to be tried. Had the fate of this application turned on that issue, I would have been disposed to allow the applicants to make further submissions on the issue. Although they have already had an adequate opportunity to do so, the decision is an important one from the applicants' point of view. As it is, I have reached the conclusion that the balance of convenience clearly favours the refusal of the application and it is unnecessary to pursue the issue of whether there is a serious question to be tried any further.

48 I turn now to consider the balance of convenience.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>