<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Traxon Industries Pty Ltd ACN 009 318 987 v Emerson Electric Co (No 2) [2006] FCA 630 (26 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/630.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Traxon Industries Pty Ltd v Emerson Electric Co [2006] FCA 450</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/450.html</AustLII>
<text>1 Traxon Industries Pty Ltd (Traxon) applied to the Court by motion dated 18 April 2006 for leave to serve proceedings on Emerson Electric Co (Emerson) in the United States of America (USA). The proceedings arose out of a dispute between Traxon and Emerson connected with the performance of a Confidentiality Agreement and a Distributorship Agreement relating to the marketing and sale, in the USA, of oil level control devices manufactured by Traxon. Traxon's causes of action against Emerson were for misleading or deceptive conduct in contravention of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), breach of contract, breach of duty of confidence and breach of fiduciary duty. For reasons published on 26 April 2006 the motion was adjourned and Traxon given leave to amend its statement of claim and to file further affidavit evidence in support of its application Traxon Industries Pty Ltd v Emerson Electric Co [2006] FCA 450. The principal reason for the decision not to accede to Traxon's motion was its inclusion in the application and statement of claim of the causes of action arising out of breach of confidence and breach of fiduciary duty. These causes of action were based entirely on conduct allegedly committed by Emerson in the United States. They did not otherwise fall within any of the categories of causes of action to which the relevant rule of Court, O 8, authorising service out of the jurisdiction, applies.

2 Traxon has now filed a proposed amended application and proposed amended statement of claim together with a proposed further amended application and further amended statement of claim. It has also filed additional affidavit material. In its proposed amended application and amended statement of claim Traxon seeks to join Traxon International Ltd (Traxon International) as a second applicant. It abandons the claim for breach of duty of confidence but maintains the claim based on breach of fiduciary duty. As an alternative position, it relies upon a further amended application and further amended statement of claim which would also omit the cause of action for breach of fiduciary duty.

3 For the reasons which I now publish, I am prepared to grant leave to serve an application and statement of claim on Emerson in the United States in the form set out in the further amended application and further amended statement of claim. So that Emerson may also be served with a reasonably self contained set of reasons for that decision these reasons repeat elements of those published on 26 April 2006 adapted to take account of the amendments to the pleadings and the additional evidence which has been filed.

4 Traxon, on 18 April 2006, commenced proceedings in this Court against Emerson. It claimed damages for misleading or deceptive conduct in contravention of the Trade Practices Act , at common law for breach of contract and, alternatively, in equity for breach of confidence and breach of fiduciary duty. Traxon is an Australian company which carries on the business of manufacturing, marketing and selling oil level control devices, one of which is known as the TraxOil Management System (the TraxOil Device). Emerson is incorporated in Missouri and currently trades under the business name Emerson Climate Technologies. It used to trade as Alco Controls.

5 By a notice of motion filed on 18 April 2006, Traxon sought leave to serve its application, statement of claim and supporting affidavits on Emerson in the USA. Its motion was filed pursuant to O 8 of the Federal Court Rules .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Delco Australia Pty Ltd v Equipment Enterprises Incorporated trading as Kukla Trenchers [2000] FCA 821</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/821.html</AustLII>
<text>76 The cause of action in breach of fiduciary duty is based on conduct engaged in in the United States. Even though the duty pleaded depends upon conduct in Australia that does not mean that its breach by acts outside Australia give rise to a cause of action 'arising in the Commonwealth' under O 8 r 1(a). As von Doussa J observed in Delco Australia Pty Ltd v Equipment Enterprises Incorporated trading as Kukla Trenchers [2000] FCA 821 , the authorities establish that 'cause of action' within the meaning of O 8 r 1(a) does not refer to all the elements of the cause of action. It refers rather to the act on the part of the defendant which gave the plaintiff his cause for complaint. In Distillers Co (Biochemicals) v Thompson [1971] AC 458 at 467, Lord Pearson said (at 468):
 
 It is not the right approach to say that, because there was no complete tort until the damage occurred, therefore the cause of action arose wherever the damage happened to occur. The right approach is, when the tort is complete, to look back over the series of events constituting it and ask the question, where in substance did this cause of action arise? 
 
 Theory no (iii) is that the cause of action arose within the jurisdiction if the act on the part of the defendant, which gives the plaintiff his cause of complaint has occurred within the jurisdiction. That is the rule laid down in Jackson v Spittal (1870) LR 5CP 542, which is an authoritative case, and the rule is inherently reasonable, as the defendant is called upon to answer for his wrong in the courts of the country where he did the wrong.' 
 

Counsel for the applicants contends that the cause of action for breach of fiduciary duty falls within O 8 r 1(ab)(ii). That is to say the proceeding, in so far as it seeks relief for breach of fiduciary duty is one which 'otherwise affects a contract'. In my respectful opinion that contention is unsustainable. While it may rightly be said that the fiduciary obligation, as pleaded, arises out of the asserted contractual relationship, the proceeding based upon breach of fiduciary duty does not of itself affect the contract. In my opinion, therefore, the cause of action for breach of fiduciary duty is not one to which O 8 r 1 applies.

77 As I concluded in the reasons published on 26 April 2006, the fact that the causes of action in misleading or deceptive conduct and breach of contract are within O 8 r 1, would be insufficient to satisfy the requirement that the rule 'applies to the proceeding' within the meaning of O 8 r 2(2)(b) for so long as the claim for breach of fiduciary duty is included. As von Doussa J said in Delco Australia [at 35]:
 
 'In this Court r 1(n) makes express provision for a proceeding where a proceeding does not fall squarely within one of the heads enumerated in the earlier paragraphs. In my opinion r 1(n) makes it clear that an originating process to be served out of the Commonwealth must be confined to causes of action that fall wholly within one or several of the heads in r 1. An originating process that includes a claim that does not fall within one or more of the heads is not an originating process that meets the description of r 1, in that it is not one "in" any of the cases described in the rule. It is not a "proceeding to which rule 1 applies" so as to meet the requirement of r 2(2)(c)(b). A similar conclusion was expressed by Wilcox J in Tycoon Holdings Ltd v Tencor Jetco Inc (1992) 34 FCR 31 at 35.'

78 In the circumstances, because of the inclusion of the claim for breach of fiduciary duty, it is not possible to conclude that 'the proceeding' reflected in the amended application and the amended statement of claim is one to which O 8 r 1 applies. However the minute of further amended statement of claim which is proposed would omit the claim for breach of fiduciary duty and, on that basis, would transform the action into a proceeding to which O 8 r 1 applies. I am therefore prepared to make an order for service on Emerson in the United States of America of an application and statement of claim in terms of the further amended application and further amended statement of claim filed on 24 May 2006. A minute of proposed orders has been filed also to take account of that contingency. I will make orders in terms of the minute. 
 

 I certify that the preceding seventy eight (78) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice French. 


Associate:

Dated: 26 May 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr D Solomon 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Solomon Brothers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 18 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 26 May 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/630.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Distillers Co (Biochemicals) v Thompson [1971] AC 458</tocase>
<text>76 The cause of action in breach of fiduciary duty is based on conduct engaged in in the United States. Even though the duty pleaded depends upon conduct in Australia that does not mean that its breach by acts outside Australia give rise to a cause of action 'arising in the Commonwealth' under O 8 r 1(a). As von Doussa J observed in Delco Australia Pty Ltd v Equipment Enterprises Incorporated trading as Kukla Trenchers [2000] FCA 821 , the authorities establish that 'cause of action' within the meaning of O 8 r 1(a) does not refer to all the elements of the cause of action. It refers rather to the act on the part of the defendant which gave the plaintiff his cause for complaint. In Distillers Co (Biochemicals) v Thompson [1971] AC 458 at 467, Lord Pearson said (at 468):
 
 It is not the right approach to say that, because there was no complete tort until the damage occurred, therefore the cause of action arose wherever the damage happened to occur. The right approach is, when the tort is complete, to look back over the series of events constituting it and ask the question, where in substance did this cause of action arise? 
 
 Theory no (iii) is that the cause of action arose within the jurisdiction if the act on the part of the defendant, which gives the plaintiff his cause of complaint has occurred within the jurisdiction. That is the rule laid down in Jackson v Spittal (1870) LR 5CP 542, which is an authoritative case, and the rule is inherently reasonable, as the defendant is called upon to answer for his wrong in the courts of the country where he did the wrong.' 
 

Counsel for the applicants contends that the cause of action for breach of fiduciary duty falls within O 8 r 1(ab)(ii). That is to say the proceeding, in so far as it seeks relief for breach of fiduciary duty is one which 'otherwise affects a contract'. In my respectful opinion that contention is unsustainable. While it may rightly be said that the fiduciary obligation, as pleaded, arises out of the asserted contractual relationship, the proceeding based upon breach of fiduciary duty does not of itself affect the contract. In my opinion, therefore, the cause of action for breach of fiduciary duty is not one to which O 8 r 1 applies.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>