<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>VWDC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 728 (2 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/728.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 16</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/16.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Finally, I wish to say a brief word about an authority cited by the appellant during the hearing. Appearing on her own behalf, the appellant referred to one case in support of her argument. The case, Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 16 , is one where the Full Court allowed an appeal on multiple grounds, including failure of the tribunal to comply with the requirements of s 424A. Unfortunately for the appellant, the case does not significantly advance her claims in the matter before me now.

14 In M164 , the tribunal had noted and relied on inconsistencies between direct oral testimony of the applicant and conflicting testimony by the applicant's husband. Though the husband's testimony was given at the hearing and in the presence of the applicant, the Full Court found that, under a strict reading of s 424A , the applicant was to be given notice, in writing, of the tribunal's intended reliance on discrepancies between the husband's testimony and the applicant's testimony: Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 16 at [97] - [100] .

15 In the instant case, the hearing-testimony relied upon by the tribunal came directly from the appellant, herself, and was therefore exempted under s 424A(3)(b) as information that "the applicant gave." There was no third party testimony cited or relied upon by the tribunal in reaching its decision.

16 The appeal will be dismissed with costs.
 
I certify that the preceding sixteen (16) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Finkelstein. 


Associate:

Dated: 2 June 2006


 First appellant in person. 
 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Ms S Burchell 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 3 May 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 2 June 2006 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/728.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/24.html</AustLII>
<text>5 In fact it is not the appellant but the first respondent who has raised the possibility that the tribunal decision may have been based on information not provided to the appellant under s 424A. The first respondent's counsel referred to decisions in the High Court to the effect that the tribunal must strictly comply with s 424A (see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162). Thus, any finding that information was not properly provided would be a jurisdictional error and the tribunal's decision would necessarily be vacated by this Court.

6 The first instance involves the dates on which the Sri Lanka Provincial Council elections occurred. The tribunal states in its Findings and Reasons:
 
 
 "[t]he applicant had submitted in her protection visa application lodged in July 1999 that she had been recently involved in the Provincial Council election campaigns but stated at the hearing that she assisted with the 1996 Provincial Council elections. There were, however, no such elections in 1996; rather these occurred in 1999, in the months before her departure for Australia."
 
 

The tribunal then went on to explain that this inconsistency was one consideration that led the tribunal to doubt the truth of the appellant's story.

12 Since I have determined that the "information" in question all qualifies under the statutory exemption in s 424A(3) , it is not necessary to examine the specifics of whether and how the information was relayed to the appellant. I do note, however, that the High Court's ruling in SAAP makes it clear that any information required under s 424A must be given to an applicant in writing : see SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 at 183 per McHugh J; at 196 per Gummow J; at 205 per Hayne J. This would be necessary even in a situation where the tribunal discusses adverse information with an applicant during the hearing and gives the applicant an opportunity to comment. Thus, were any of the information at issue in this case not subject to exemption under s 424A(3) , the appellant might very well have succeeded in her appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>7 At first blush, it might appear that the tribunal was comparing written information from the appellant's visa application with the appellant's testimony at the hearing. In its reasons, however, the tribunal explained that the appellant's visa application was merely the medium that raised the issue for the tribunal: see eg SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 at [49] - [50] per Moore J; at [244] per Allsop J. The inconsistency itself arose between the appellant's testimony that she participated in 1996 Provincial Council elections, and the independent country information stating that the scheduled 1996 elections never occurred and were, instead, postponed until nearly 1999: see ibid. Thus, the information which is relevant for the purposes of s 424A is the independent country information and the appellant's hearing testimony.

8 Section 424A(3)(b) provides that information given by an applicant for the purpose of the application is exempted from the disclosure requirements of s 424A. While some cases might call into question when, specifically, information is given "for the purpose of the application", I think it is beyond question that testimony given by an applicant in a statutory hearing pursuant to s 425 of the Migration Act is given in support of, and therefore "for the purpose of", the application.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/74.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Similarly, with regard to independent country information, s 424A(3)(a) exempts such general information from the requirements of s 424A when it is not specifically about the applicant or another person. This is established by numerous Full Court authorities: see VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178 ; VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) ALD 559 at 562-563 per Gyles and Conti JJ, at 564 per Allsop J; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168. Thus, with regard to the first instance of possible error, I find no violation of s 424A by the tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) ALD 559</tocase>
<text>9 Similarly, with regard to independent country information, s 424A(3)(a) exempts such general information from the requirements of s 424A when it is not specifically about the applicant or another person. This is established by numerous Full Court authorities: see VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178 ; VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) ALD 559 at 562-563 per Gyles and Conti JJ, at 564 per Allsop J; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168. Thus, with regard to the first instance of possible error, I find no violation of s 424A by the tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/178.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Similarly, with regard to independent country information, s 424A(3)(a) exempts such general information from the requirements of s 424A when it is not specifically about the applicant or another person. This is established by numerous Full Court authorities: see VJAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 178 ; VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) ALD 559 at 562-563 per Gyles and Conti JJ, at 564 per Allsop J; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168. Thus, with regard to the first instance of possible error, I find no violation of s 424A by the tribunal.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>