<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZWMF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 780 (20 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/780.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>MZWMF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FMCA 513</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2005/513.html</AustLII>
<text>1 This is an appeal from a judgment of O'Dwyer FM dismissing an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the Tribunal"): MZWMF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FMCA 513. By that decision, the Tribunal affirmed the decision of a delegate of the respondent Minister refusing to grant the appellant a class XA protection visa.

2 The appellant, a national of India, is Muslim. He arrived in Australia on 13 September 2003 on a travel visa issued in Delhi. On 8 October 2003, he applied for a protection visa. A criterion for the grant of a protection visa, pursuant to s 36 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ("the Act "), is that the person bringing the application is a non-citizen of Australia to whom Australia owes protection obligations under the Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees as amended. Article 1A(2) of the Convention provides that a refugee is a person who:
 
 "owing to well-founded fear of being persecuted for reasons of race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular social group or political opinion, is outside the country of his nationality and is unable or, owing to such fear, is unwilling to avail himself of the protection of that country; or who, not having a nationality and being outside the country of his former habitual residence, is unable or, owing to such fear, is unwilling to return to it."

3 The appellant's claims in support of his application for a protection visa were somewhat vague. He claimed to have been a member of the "Muslim League" living in the Coimbatore district of Tamil Nadu, a southern state of India. He said that both his father and his brother had been heavily involved in Muslim politics. In November 1997, his father and mother were killed during religious rioting in the district. Fearing for his life, he moved to the Chennai district. He established a clothing business there. He maintained his involvement with the Muslim League. He claimed that he donated money, was involved in political rallies and that he sought to recruit new party members. He claimed that political opponents became aware of his activities and that he was threatened and "physically attacked" by these people. Nonetheless, he continued his active involvement with the Muslim League. He supported the party financially, and this may have led to a further attack upon him by his political opponents. However, he was spared any serious physical injury because of the presence, on this occasion, of a number of Muslim supporters.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/22.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The Tribunal referred to several cases in support of these propositions. These included Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559, Nagalingam v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1992) 38 FCR 191 and Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155 . The Tribunal did not err in relying upon these cases, or in its formulation of the relevant legal principles. Moreover, the appellant's contention must fail by reason of the principles stated by the Full Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v VSAF of 2003 [2005] FCAFC 73 at [20] [24].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nagalingam v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1992) 38 FCR 191</tocase>
<text>11 The Tribunal referred to several cases in support of these propositions. These included Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559, Nagalingam v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1992) 38 FCR 191 and Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155 . The Tribunal did not err in relying upon these cases, or in its formulation of the relevant legal principles. Moreover, the appellant's contention must fail by reason of the principles stated by the Full Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v VSAF of 2003 [2005] FCAFC 73 at [20] [24].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155</tocase>
<text>11 The Tribunal referred to several cases in support of these propositions. These included Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559, Nagalingam v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1992) 38 FCR 191 and Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155 . The Tribunal did not err in relying upon these cases, or in its formulation of the relevant legal principles. Moreover, the appellant's contention must fail by reason of the principles stated by the Full Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v VSAF of 2003 [2005] FCAFC 73 at [20] [24].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v VSAF of 2003 [2005] FCAFC 73</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/73.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The Tribunal referred to several cases in support of these propositions. These included Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559, Nagalingam v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1992) 38 FCR 191 and Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155 . The Tribunal did not err in relying upon these cases, or in its formulation of the relevant legal principles. Moreover, the appellant's contention must fail by reason of the principles stated by the Full Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v VSAF of 2003 [2005] FCAFC 73 at [20] [24].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>