<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Fleming*s Nurseries Pty Ltd v Siciliano [2006] FCA 757 (22 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/757.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner of Railways ( NSW ) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The standard to be applied before a pleading is struck out is that the claim must be 'so clearly untenable that it cannot possibly succeed': General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner of Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 130. I am conscious that this is an early stage of the proceeding. Bearing in mind what the Amended Statement of Claim states concerning the relationship between the brothers and their companies, I am not prepared to conclude at this stage that the claim of wrongful interference with contractual rights is so untenable that it cannot possibly succeed.

10 As to the question whether or not the claim is properly pleaded, in my view there is no deficiency in the pleading: the material facts are pleaded and particulars are provided in support of the claim. It is simply a question of whether the facts alleged and the particulars provided make out a tenable claim. I am satisfied that the claim is sufficiently arguable that it should not be struck out.

11 I turn to deal with the causes of action concerning the allegation that the third applicant's plant breeder's rights have been infringed. The attack on this part of the pleading was based on submissions which, at least to some extent, involved a misapprehension of what is required by the rules of pleading and the authorities. In the first place, the respondents submitted (by reference to the paragraph concerning the Rich Lady plant breeder's rights allegations) that allegations in paragraphs 34 to 38 were in the nature of conclusions of law. In my opinion, that characterisation is not apposite. Paragraphs 34 to 38 make allegations of material fact, and are expressed in language which reflects the facts required to be established under ss 3, 11 and 53(1)(a) of the PBR Act, in order to establish an infringement of plant breeder's rights. That does not mean that what is alleged is a conclusion of law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/70.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Order 11 r 2(a) of the Federal Court Rules ('the Rules') requires that a pleading shall contain only 'a statement in summary form of the material facts on which the party relies, but not the evidence by which those facts are to be proved'. The purpose of pleadings is to define the issues and to inform the other parties of the case that they must meet: Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658 at 664. In distinguishing between material facts and evidence, the pleader must choose an appropriate level of generality in which to express the material facts that is consistent with the purposes to be achieved by the pleadings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Scott v Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd (unreported, Burchett J, 14 December 1996)</tocase>
<text>14 The Rules do not compel the pleader to adopt so detailed an approach to the identification of material facts that it would unduly lengthen or complicate a pleading, or, to use the language of Burchett J in Scott v Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd (unreported, Burchett J, 14 December 1996), throw up 'an impenetrable forest of detail'. A statement of claim is not defective merely because it pleads what might be said to be conclusions of fact at a higher level of generality than the primary facts that must be proved by evidence. So much clearly appears from the decision of French J in Kernel Holdings Pty Ltd v Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 217 ALR 171 at 173; see also BWK Elders Australia Pty Ltd v Westgate Wool Co Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] ATPR 41-860 at 44,748 [15] per Mansfield J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kernel Holdings Pty Ltd v Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 217 ALR 171</tocase>
<text>14 The Rules do not compel the pleader to adopt so detailed an approach to the identification of material facts that it would unduly lengthen or complicate a pleading, or, to use the language of Burchett J in Scott v Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd (unreported, Burchett J, 14 December 1996), throw up 'an impenetrable forest of detail'. A statement of claim is not defective merely because it pleads what might be said to be conclusions of fact at a higher level of generality than the primary facts that must be proved by evidence. So much clearly appears from the decision of French J in Kernel Holdings Pty Ltd v Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 217 ALR 171 at 173; see also BWK Elders Australia Pty Ltd v Westgate Wool Co Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] ATPR 41-860 at 44,748 [15] per Mansfield J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>BWK Elders Australia Pty Ltd v Westgate Wool Co Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] ATPR 41-860</tocase>
<text>14 The Rules do not compel the pleader to adopt so detailed an approach to the identification of material facts that it would unduly lengthen or complicate a pleading, or, to use the language of Burchett J in Scott v Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd (unreported, Burchett J, 14 December 1996), throw up 'an impenetrable forest of detail'. A statement of claim is not defective merely because it pleads what might be said to be conclusions of fact at a higher level of generality than the primary facts that must be proved by evidence. So much clearly appears from the decision of French J in Kernel Holdings Pty Ltd v Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 217 ALR 171 at 173; see also BWK Elders Australia Pty Ltd v Westgate Wool Co Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] ATPR 41-860 at 44,748 [15] per Mansfield J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Dart Industries Inc v David Jones Ltd [1990] AIPC 90-689</tocase>
<text>23 Mr Caine, senior counsel for the applicants, referred me to several authorities dealing with a like provision to O 58 r 27(1) concerning patent pleadings: see s 117 of the Patents Act 1990 (Cth) and Dart Industries Inc v David Jones Ltd [1990] AIPC 90-689 (' Dart v David Jones' ); and Dart Industries Inc v Grace Bros Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 87 (' Dart v Grace Bros' ).

24 In Dart v David Jones , King J considered the sufficiency of a pleading and particulars of patent infringement which alleged that the plaintiff retailer had possessed for sale, offered for sale, offered for supply, sold or supplied certain press type sealed containers. His Honour referred to the equivalent provision of the Industrial Property Rules (Vic) and concluded that the particulars were adequate, having regard to the pre-discovery stage of the proceedings: at 36,412-36,413. His Honour concluded that the particulars were sufficient to apprise the other side of the nature of the case they had to meet. King J added that, on the face of it, a marketing company such as David Jones should know what it has sold, or should have access to records from which such information may be ascertained: at 36,414.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Dart Industries Inc v Grace Bros Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 87</tocase>
<text>23 Mr Caine, senior counsel for the applicants, referred me to several authorities dealing with a like provision to O 58 r 27(1) concerning patent pleadings: see s 117 of the Patents Act 1990 (Cth) and Dart Industries Inc v David Jones Ltd [1990] AIPC 90-689 (' Dart v David Jones' ); and Dart Industries Inc v Grace Bros Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 87 (' Dart v Grace Bros' ).

25 In Dart v Grace Bros, another case involving a retailer, the defendants argued that the particulars alleging the instances of sales of goods were inadequate. Marks J held that it was appropriate, given the early stage of the pleading, to accept the adequacy of the particulars that had been given. In reaching this conclusion, his Honour referred to the fact that more detailed information was not in the possession of the plaintiff, but it was clearly within the possession of the manufacturers and retailers of the products. In addition, Marks J observed that defendants failed to put on affidavit that they did not deal in the subject goods at the relevant time. His Honour noted that defendants were well aware that 'they and they alone hold the key to the solution of the problem whether they deal in these goods or not': at 89.

26 In my view, there are distinctions between the above authorities and the present case. The principal allegation against the respondents is that they have grown trees of the relevant varieties in the course of their orchard and wholesale fruit business and that they have sold fruit of the relevant variety. The facts particularised go no further than raising a case of that kind. While the relevant particulars can support (at least to the necessary threshold stage in a pleading) the allegations in, for instance paragraphs 34(a), (b) and (e), they do not lend any support to the allegations in paragraphs 34(c) and (d). Accordingly, I propose to strike out the unsupported subparagraphs (c) and (d) in paragraphs 34 to 52 of the Amended Statement of Claim.

27 Mr Hess, senior counsel for the respondents, argued that the other allegations of infringement of plant breeder's rights were not supported by material facts. It was argued that the particulars merely identify that trees have been found in existence at the properties and, in the case of Arctic Star and Earliqueen, provide some factual material indicating sales. In my view, a sufficient case is raised by the allegations that have been pleaded and the facts that have been particularised. The respondents' attack on the other aspects of the pleadings concerning contravention of plant breeder's rights therefore fails.

28 The respondents criticised other minor aspects of the pleading in argument. The respondents argued that some illogicality or inconsistency arose because paragraphs 4, 5 and 8 of the Amended Statement of Claim allege that each of Fred, Bruno and Tony are and were at all relevant times in effective control of fourth and fifth respondents. Mr Caine submitted that there was no logical inconsistency in alleging that each of the brothers was in effective control of the two companies. Be that as it may, Mr Caine indicated that if pleading requires some attention, it would be appropriate to address this matter by adding some words to paragraphs 4(f), 5(e) and 8(e) of the Amended Statement of Claim, to the effect that the relevant individual was in effective control 'either alone or in conjunction with his brothers'. I consider that the additional words suggested by Mr Caine may assist the clarity of the pleading; however I decline to make a specific finding that the pleading as it stands is illogical or inconsistent in this regard.

29 It was also submitted that there were deficiencies or pleading inadequacies in relation to the allegations of breach of contract in the Amended Statement of Claim. I do not accept these submissions. The breach of contract claims are pleaded at an appropriate level of generality, and the particulars are capable of supporting the allegations.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>