<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Restom v Battenberg, in the matter of Battenberg [2006] FCA 781 (22 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/781.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/66.html</AustLII>
<text>5 The disclosure of the contents of the letter of 3 March 2005 in the Notice of Appeal signed by the debtor is inconsistent with the maintenance of confidentiality. The only apparent purpose of the reference to the letter is to summarise the content of the letter and indicate that it supported the assertion that the debtor was domiciled in Australia. The reference to the letter in the Notice of Appeal cannot be linked to the Tribunal's alleged error since the letter is dated 3 March 2005 and, according to the Notice of Appeal, the Tribunal's decision was made on 11 March 2005. In my view it constitutes waiver of legal privilege in accordance with the principle expressed in Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 at 13 and for that reason I decline to set aside paragraph 4 of the subpoena.

6 This subpoena was not referred to in the interim application; however it was raised at the hearing. As the documents sought under this subpoena are the same as those sought under the subpoena already discussed, the debtor's objections can be dealt with expeditiously. The documents produced in response to the above subpoena are also responsive to paragraphs 1 and 2 of this subpoena and there are no documents falling within paragraph 3. The only issue is the legal professional privilege issue discussed above and my conclusion is the same as that expressed above, for the same reasons.

7 The notice seeks documents in eight categories. I was informed that there are not any documents in six of the categories. The remaining categories are in paragraphs 4 and 5:
 
 '4. Trust account and general account statements of account from Salvatore Russo, solicitor for the period 1 January 2005 to 30 December 2005 issued with respect to the Union Club litigation in the Supreme Court of New South Wales Equity Division; Supreme Court of New South Wales defamation list; Administrative Decisions Tribunal; the Supreme Court of New South Wales Court of Appeal and the Applicant's litigation before Gyles J in the Federal Court and Full Court of the Federal Court. 
 5. Statements of account and/or memorandum of fees from Murray Aldridge SC and James Dupree for the period 1 January 2005 to 30 December 2005 and records by way of cheque butts, direct deposit and bank statements to show payment of same.'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>