<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pan Australia Shipping Pty Ltd v The Ship *Comandate* [2006] FCA 881 (22 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/881.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Limited [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90</tocase>
<text>7 Exhibit A before me is the judgment of Thomas J in Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Limited [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90. In that case his Lordship concluded that Peoples Insurance had not submitted to the jurisdiction of the courts of New South Wales. He held that the judgment of the High Court of Australia ( Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Ltd [1996] HCA 39 ; (1996) 188 CLR 418) was not one that was recognised as giving rise to a decision binding on Peoples Insurance in accordance with the rules of private international law operative in England. He concluded that because the parties had freely bargained for the English choice of law and jurisdiction clauses, that bargain should be upheld, unless there were strong reasons for not doing so and should not as a matter of comity give effect to the decision of the High Court of Australia which overrode that bargain and that choice ([1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep at 100). The effect of allowing the Australian proceedings to proceed, his Lordship held, would deprive Peoples Insurance of the results of that bargain by imposing a set of statutory provisions which made the contract much less favourable to the insurer than English law provided.

18 I am of opinion that those threats clearly conveyed that on the basis of English law as evidenced in Akai Pty Ltd v People's Insurance Co Ltd [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90, the owners would seek to enjoin the further progress of these proceedings and the issue of any statement of claim pursuant to r 22 of the Admiralty Rules .

19 The basis on which the plaintiff seeks an injunction is, in effect, to preserve the subject matter of such rights as the plaintiff may have, having regularly invoked, as the concession of the unconditional appearance demonstrates, the jurisdiction of this court to decide the in rem proceedings.

20 The power of the court to protect its own processes is one that is not susceptible of definition in closed categories. The purpose for which the court, as a superior court of record, has inherent powers is to protect its processes is so that, inter alia, all persons may approach the court and so that its jurisdiction may be not merely invoked but exercised where it exists.

31 If the defendant were permitted to bring injunctive proceedings in London then on the evidence before me, which is uncontested, it is highly likely that the Commercial List Judge would grant an injunction on the basis and for similar reasons to that granted by Thomas J in Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Ltd [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90. If that were to happen then these proceedings would be unable to be pursued by the plaintiff at all and such rights as the plaintiff may have under the laws passed by the Parliament of the Commonwealth, and which the public policy of this nation regards as being ones which ought to be able to be availed of by persons who come before courts in this country, will be set at nought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Ltd [1996] HCA 39 ; (1996) 188 CLR 418</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/39.html</AustLII>
<text>7 Exhibit A before me is the judgment of Thomas J in Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Limited [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90. In that case his Lordship concluded that Peoples Insurance had not submitted to the jurisdiction of the courts of New South Wales. He held that the judgment of the High Court of Australia ( Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Ltd [1996] HCA 39 ; (1996) 188 CLR 418) was not one that was recognised as giving rise to a decision binding on Peoples Insurance in accordance with the rules of private international law operative in England. He concluded that because the parties had freely bargained for the English choice of law and jurisdiction clauses, that bargain should be upheld, unless there were strong reasons for not doing so and should not as a matter of comity give effect to the decision of the High Court of Australia which overrode that bargain and that choice ([1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep at 100). The effect of allowing the Australian proceedings to proceed, his Lordship held, would deprive Peoples Insurance of the results of that bargain by imposing a set of statutory provisions which made the contract much less favourable to the insurer than English law provided.

31 If the defendant were permitted to bring injunctive proceedings in London then on the evidence before me, which is uncontested, it is highly likely that the Commercial List Judge would grant an injunction on the basis and for similar reasons to that granted by Thomas J in Akai Pty Ltd v Peoples Insurance Co Ltd [1998] 1 Lloyd's Rep 90. If that were to happen then these proceedings would be unable to be pursued by the plaintiff at all and such rights as the plaintiff may have under the laws passed by the Parliament of the Commonwealth, and which the public policy of this nation regards as being ones which ought to be able to be availed of by persons who come before courts in this country, will be set at nought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority of New South Wales [2006] HCA 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/27.html</AustLII>
<text>22 In Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority of New South Wales [2006] HCA 27 Gleeson CJ and Gummow, Hayne and Crennan JJ said at [9]:
 
 'What amounts to abuse of court process is insusceptible of a formulation comprising closed categories. Development continues. One example is the line of authority dealing with the stay of proceedings instituted in a second forum where there are pending proceedings in another forum and the continuance of the second proceedings would be an abuse of the process of the first forum ( Logan v Bank of Scotland (No 2) [1906] 1 KB 141; Maritime Insurance Co Ltd v Geelong Harbor Trust Commissioners [1908] HCA 37 ; (1908) 6 CLR 194; Oceanic Sun Line Special Shipping Company Inc v Fay [1988] HCA 32 ; (1988) 165 CLR 197; Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538). Again, in Cardile v LED Builders Pty Ltd ((1999) [1999] HCA 18 ; 198 CLR 380 at 393 [25] ), Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Callinan JJ referred to the passage in the joint judgment in CSR Ltd v Cigna Insurance Australia Ltd ((1997) [1997] HCA 33 ; 189 CLR 345 at 391) where it was said of the grant of an anti-suit injunction that the counterpart of the power of a court to prevent the abuse of its processes was the power of the court to protect the integrity of those processes once set in motion.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>CSR Limited v Cigna Insurance Australia Limited [1997] HCA 33 ; (1997) 189 CLR 345</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/33.html</AustLII>
<text>21 In CSR Limited v Cigna Insurance Australia Limited [1997] HCA 33 ; (1997) 189 CLR 345 at 391-392 Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Kirby JJ said:
 
 'The counterpart of a court's power to prevent its processes being abused is its power to protect the integrity of those processes once set in motion (see, eg, with respect to the power to grant a Mareva injunction, Jackson v Sterling Industries Ltd [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612 at 619, 621, 639; Witham v Holloway [1995] HCA 3 ; (1995) 183 CLR 525 at 535. See also Ridgeway v The Queen [1994] HCA 33 ; (1995) 184 CLR 19 at 60). And in some cases, it is that counterpart power of protection that authorises the grant of anti-suit injunctions. Thus, for example, if "an estate is being administered ... or a petition in bankruptcy has been presented ... or winding up proceedings have been commenced ... an injunction [may be] granted to restrain a person from seeking, by foreign proceedings, to obtain the sole benefit of certain foreign assets" ( Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Nationale Industrielle Aerospatiale v Lee Kui Jak [1987] AC 871 at 892. See also Bank of Tokyo Ltd v Karoon [1987] AC 45 at 60, per Robert Goff LJ, and the cases there cited; Allstate Ltd v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [No 1] (1996) 64 FCR 1 at 26, and the cases there cited). Similarly, as Gummow J pointed out in National Mutual Holdings Pty Ltd v Sentry Corporation ((1989) 22 FCR 209 at 232. See also, eg, Laker Airways Ltd v Sabena, Belgian World Airlines (1984) 731 F 2d 909 at 927; Re Siromath Pty Ltd [No 3] (1991) 25 NSWLR 25 at 29-30), a court may grant an injunction to restrain a person from commencing or continuing foreign proceedings if they, the foreign proceedings, interfere with or have a tendency to interfere with proceedings pending in that court. 
 
 The inherent power to grant anti-suit injunctions is not confined to the examples just given. As with other aspects of that power, it is not to be restricted to defined and closed categories 112 . Rather, it is to be exercised when the administration of justice so demands or, in the context of anti-suit injunctions, when necessary for the protection of the court's own proceedings or processes.'

22 In Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority of New South Wales [2006] HCA 27 Gleeson CJ and Gummow, Hayne and Crennan JJ said at [9]:
 
 'What amounts to abuse of court process is insusceptible of a formulation comprising closed categories. Development continues. One example is the line of authority dealing with the stay of proceedings instituted in a second forum where there are pending proceedings in another forum and the continuance of the second proceedings would be an abuse of the process of the first forum ( Logan v Bank of Scotland (No 2) [1906] 1 KB 141; Maritime Insurance Co Ltd v Geelong Harbor Trust Commissioners [1908] HCA 37 ; (1908) 6 CLR 194; Oceanic Sun Line Special Shipping Company Inc v Fay [1988] HCA 32 ; (1988) 165 CLR 197; Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538). Again, in Cardile v LED Builders Pty Ltd ((1999) [1999] HCA 18 ; 198 CLR 380 at 393 [25] ), Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Callinan JJ referred to the passage in the joint judgment in CSR Ltd v Cigna Insurance Australia Ltd ((1997) [1997] HCA 33 ; 189 CLR 345 at 391) where it was said of the grant of an anti-suit injunction that the counterpart of the power of a court to prevent the abuse of its processes was the power of the court to protect the integrity of those processes once set in motion.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hi-Fert Pty Ltd v Kiukiang Maritime Carriers Inc (No 5) (1998) 90 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>39 This court has recognised that rights granted to parties under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) are important considerations in determining whether or not stays should be granted under s 7 of the International Arbitration Act 1974 (Cth) and under contractual arrangements for arbitrations or choice of law or jurisdiction in other jurisdictional areas. Allsop J recently affirmed these matters in Walter Rau Neusser Oel und Fett AG v Cross Pacific Trading Limited [2005] FCA 1102 at [73] ; see also at [71]-[74] and [110]-[111]; Hi-Fert Pty Ltd v Kiukiang Maritime Carriers Inc (No 5) (1998) 90 FCR 1 at 7 and 23-24.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Queensland v JL Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/1.html</AustLII>
<text>34 The proceedings were brought on quickly and the ship was arrested just immediately before its detention by the authorities was about to cease. Since then the solicitors have concentrated on the agitation of the inter-jurisdictional dispute. In Queensland v JL Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146 at 152-155, 164-165, the High Court made it quite clear that the pleadings and the rules were not the masters but were the servants of the interests of justice. If by oversight, or because of pressure of time, or otherwise the plaintiff has not hitherto been able clearly to articulate a formulated cause of action which could be maintained in this court but may not be able to be maintained in English courts, there should be some recognition that this court should allow its procedures to be invoked in a regular way and in a way in which rights, that do exist under Australian law, can be articulated and recognised.

35 I was of opinion that in order to protect the processes of this court and its ability to hear and determine what appears to me to be a bona fide dispute between these parties that the injunctive relief that I granted earlier this afternoon was appropriate. While ordinarily one would expect to see the precise definition of the issues in dispute and the controversy for the purposes of identifying the relevant constitutional matter under Chapter III of the Constitution of the Commonwealth in pleadings, r 22 of the Admiralty Rules recognises that indeed such a course is likely not to occur necessarily immediately the writ is issued. That is why there is a provision for time to be given to a plaintiff, after the writ in rem has issued, and after the defendant has appeared to it, to put on a statement of claim in personam.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Raymond v Honey [1981] UKHL 8 ; [1983] 1 AC 1</tocase>
<text>23 Just as the court can protect the efficacy of execution in proceedings which it has not yet decided, it can also protect the ability of persons to approach the court who seek the regular invocation and exercise of its jurisdiction. The law of contempt both in England and Australia enables courts to grant injunctions to protect the administration of justice by protecting them from interferences by outside influences. So, in Raymond v Honey [1981] UKHL 8 ; [1983] 1 AC 1 at 10D Lord Wilberforce said:
 
 '... any act which is calculated to obstruct or interfere with the due course of justice, or the lawful process of the court is a contempt of court.'

24 His Lordship held ([1983] 1 AC at 13C) that the actions of prison officers in interfering with the plaintiff's mail by stopping him applying to the High Court in England even though it was only a temporary interference was a contempt.

25 In my opinion it is part of the court's inherent power to protect the efficacy of proceedings already on foot which the Admiralty Rules contemplate can be supplemented by the pleading of a statement of claim. That may include in personam claims and other claims outside those contemplated under the Admiralty Act 1988 (Cth). These proceedings, which have been regularly instituted should not be interfered with peremptorily by the threats which the defendant has made to enjoin the plaintiff from proceeding with its rights to invoke and have the court exercise its judicial power.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/27.html</AustLII>
<text>36 In Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585 [139] Gummow and Hayne JJ with whom, Gleeson CJ and Gaudron J, expressly agreed (198 CLR at 546 [25], [26]) said that:
 
 'The central task was to identify the justiciable controversy. In civil proceedings that will ordinarily require close attention to the pleadings (if any) and to the factual basis of each claim.'

37 Having regard to the facts articulated in the evidence before me, the factual basis of the claims demonstrate that there is the potential for a controversy that will invoke or be capable of invoking relief under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) at the very least, in addition to whatever contractual remedies might be available. In my opinion, the plaintiff ought to have a reasonable opportunity in order to do so.

38 No serious opposition was made by the defendant to the application of the plaintiff that it should be allowed till 5 July 2006 in order to put on a statement of claim were I otherwise to grant an interim injunction. I took the view that the interim injunction that I was minded to grant was one to preserve a particular subject matter, namely, the ability of the plaintiff to invoke and have the court exercise jurisdiction under Acts of the Commonwealth that would not be recognised in English proceedings and which it would then be prevented from being able to litigate. Inter alia, there was the potential, as adverted to by counsel for the plaintiff, of involving brokers as third parties or defendants to the proceedings in personam and that was another consideration that I had in mind when granting the order.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Walter Rau Neusser Oel und Fett AG v Cross Pacific Trading Limited [2005] FCA 1102</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1102.html</AustLII>
<text>39 This court has recognised that rights granted to parties under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) are important considerations in determining whether or not stays should be granted under s 7 of the International Arbitration Act 1974 (Cth) and under contractual arrangements for arbitrations or choice of law or jurisdiction in other jurisdictional areas. Allsop J recently affirmed these matters in Walter Rau Neusser Oel und Fett AG v Cross Pacific Trading Limited [2005] FCA 1102 at [73] ; see also at [71]-[74] and [110]-[111]; Hi-Fert Pty Ltd v Kiukiang Maritime Carriers Inc (No 5) (1998) 90 FCR 1 at 7 and 23-24.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>