<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rana v Australian Federal Police [2006] FCA 890 (13 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/890.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Chu v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2005] FCA 1730 ; (2005) 147 FCR 505</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1730.html</AustLII>
<text>8 I pause at this point to note that the condition in s 24A(a) is not expressed in terms of the agency or Minister being satisfied that reasonable steps have been taken, and that raises a question as to whether the condition involves a jurisdictional fact. That question was addressed by Finn J in Chu v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2005] FCA 1730 ; (2005) 147 FCR 505 and, for the reasons his Honour gives (with which I respectfully agree), the judgment as to the requirement in s 24A(a) is for the agency or Minister in question and, upon review, for the Tribunal, and not ultimately for the Court.

9 Under s 55 of the FIO Act, the applicant sought a review of the decision by the Tribunal. As I have said, the Tribunal affirmed the decision under review.

10 On 17 August 2005, the applicant limited his application to the Tribunal to his request for documents said to have been provided by him to the respondent in 1991. His description of the documents is as follows:
 
 '... documents [that] were given to me by the Queensland Police after I had complained to the Fitzgerald Inquiry. Australian Federal Police wanted to know about my involvement with Operation Maitita an undercover role that I had played to trap some members of the Ananda Marga sect implicated allegedly in the 1978 Hilton Hotel bombings in Sydney. 
 
 ("1991 Documents")'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>McLeod v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2002] HCA 37 ; (2002) 211 CLR 287</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/37.html</AustLII>
<text>19 As to the second submission, this could be rejected on a number of grounds. It is sufficient for me to say that the State Act does not apply to the applicant's request for access according to its terms and is not 'picked up' by s 79 of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth), because the Commonwealth has 'otherwise provided' in the FIO Act: see McLeod v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2002] HCA 37 ; (2002) 211 CLR 287 at 302 [44] .

20 The application must be dismissed and the applicant must pay the respondent's costs.
 

 I certify that the preceding twenty (20) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko. 


Associate:

Dated: 13 July 2006


 The Applicant: The Applicant appeared in person. 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms E Reed 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 30 June 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 13 July 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/890.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pancontinental Mining Ltd v Burns (1994) 52 FCR 454</tocase>
<text>2 The applicant's challenge is made by way of an application under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) ('the ADJR Act'). It seems that the applicant had a right of appeal on a question of law from the decision of the Tribunal under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) ('the AAT Act'), but he has not exercised that right. Although the respondent accepts that the decision falls within the terms of the ADJR Act (see, eg, Pancontinental Mining Ltd v Burns (1994) 52 FCR 454 at 462-464 per von Doussa J), it submits that because the applicant had a right of appeal on a question of law under the AAT Act, I have a discretion not to entertain the application under the ADJR Act. However, the respondent has asked me not to exercise the discretion to decline to entertain the application, because it submits that it is in the interests of justice that the application be determined as expeditiously as possible. I am prepared to proceed in this way because, irrespective of the form of the challenge, the applicant must show a breach of the rules of natural justice or an error of law and I am satisfied that he is unable to do this.

3 The applicant represented himself both in this Court and in the Tribunal. He believes that the respondent has certain documents and, as will become clear, his attempts to obtain those documents have a long history.

4 On 18 February 2005, the applicant made a request of the respondent under s 15 of the FIO Act for certain documents. The documents sought were as follows:
 
 'Seeking freedom of information between 1978 to 2005 about myself ... I seek all materials and including a Queensland Police file (including the Special Branch files) that I provided you in 1990.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sullivan v Department of Transport (1978) 20 ALR 323</tocase>
<text>17 Section 33(1)(b) of the AAT Act provides that a proceeding before the Tribunal shall be conducted with as little formality and technicality, and with as much expedition, as the requirements of that Act and of every other relevant enactment and a proper consideration of the matters before the Tribunal permit. The Tribunal has a duty to act judicially. Ordinarily, it is for the parties to define the issues in the proceedings and to decide how they wish to conduct their respective cases. As Deane J (with whom Fisher J agreed) noted in Sullivan v Department of Transport (1978) 20 ALR 323 (at 343), undue interference by the Tribunal with how the parties conduct their cases may prove counter-productive. At the same time, there may be cases where the Tribunal's duty to act judicially may require it to advise a party of his or her ability to seek an adjournment, or even to adjourn a hearing of its own motion. It is not possible to catalogue the circumstances in which either of these courses may be appropriate. They are likely to be rare and to involve a party who does not have legal representation.

18 In this case, the applicant was aware before the hearing that the respondent was asserting that the documents could not be found or did not exist. There is nothing in what occurred before the Tribunal to suggest that it would have been appropriate for the Tribunal to intervene in some way so as to enable the applicant to launch what is even now an unparticularised challenge to the evidence of the searches conducted of the electronic databases of the respondent. I reject the first submission.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>