<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 810 (30 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/810.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Citrix Systems Inc v Telesystems Learning Pty Ltd (in liq) (1998) 28 ACSR 529</tocase>
<text>14 In Citrix Systems Inc v Telesystems Learning Pty Ltd (in liq) (1998) 28 ACSR 529, Moore J made an order that a company be wound up in insolvency in circumstances where it was being wound up voluntarily, and there was no suggestion that an order terminating the voluntary winding up was necessary.

18 In the authorities, various reasons for making an order in such circumstances have been put forward and held to be sufficient. One reason which has commonly been put forward is that a change of liquidator is desirable. That reason will be sufficient if the liquidator has not given the appearance of being independent: Citrix Systems Inc v Telesystems Learning Pty Ltd (in liq) (supra) per Moore J at 535-537, but, on the other hand, a mere desire to replace a liquidator is not sufficient: Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra). The fact that an insurance policy responding to claims for insolvent trading by directors may cover such claims only if the liquidator is appointed by the court may be a sufficient reason: Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra), as may the fact that a charge or certain dispositions of property may only be challenged if the court has ordered the company to be wound up under s 459A: Carter (as liq of New Tel Ltd (in liq)) v New Tel Ltd (in liq) (supra).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (2004) 52 ACSR 452</tocase>
<text>15 In Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq) (2004) 52 ACSR 452, Barrett J made an order that the company be wound up in insolvency in circumstances where it was the subject of a creditors' voluntary winding up arising from a voluntary administration under Pt 5.3A and there was no suggestion that an order terminating the voluntary winding up was necessary.

16 In the circumstances, the Registrar's lack of power to make orders under s 482 is no obstacle to her power to make an order winding up the company in insolvency.

17 A court will not make an order winding up a company in insolvency in circumstances in which the company is already the subject of creditors' voluntary winding up unless there is good reason to do so: Carter (as liq of New Tel Ltd (in liq)) v New Tel Ltd (in liq) (2003) 44 ACSR 661 per Austin J at 663(5); Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra) per Barrett J at 453 [5]. The reason for this is that, in the ordinary case, there is little practical difference between a creditors' voluntary winding up and a form of winding up imposed by order of the court.

18 In the authorities, various reasons for making an order in such circumstances have been put forward and held to be sufficient. One reason which has commonly been put forward is that a change of liquidator is desirable. That reason will be sufficient if the liquidator has not given the appearance of being independent: Citrix Systems Inc v Telesystems Learning Pty Ltd (in liq) (supra) per Moore J at 535-537, but, on the other hand, a mere desire to replace a liquidator is not sufficient: Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra). The fact that an insurance policy responding to claims for insolvent trading by directors may cover such claims only if the liquidator is appointed by the court may be a sufficient reason: Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra), as may the fact that a charge or certain dispositions of property may only be challenged if the court has ordered the company to be wound up under s 459A: Carter (as liq of New Tel Ltd (in liq)) v New Tel Ltd (in liq) (supra).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Carter (as liq of New Tel Ltd (in liq) v New Tel Ltd (in liq) (2003) 44 ACSR 661</tocase>
<text>17 A court will not make an order winding up a company in insolvency in circumstances in which the company is already the subject of creditors' voluntary winding up unless there is good reason to do so: Carter (as liq of New Tel Ltd (in liq)) v New Tel Ltd (in liq) (2003) 44 ACSR 661 per Austin J at 663(5); Re Green (as liq of Australian Resources Ltd (in liq)) (supra) per Barrett J at 453 [5]. The reason for this is that, in the ordinary case, there is little practical difference between a creditors' voluntary winding up and a form of winding up imposed by order of the court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>