<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SBNC v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 843 (5 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/843.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>14 The leading authority on the circumstances in which an extension of time may be granted under O 52 r 15 is Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187. In that case, the Court (Lockhart, Sheppard and Burchett JJ) said at 195:
 
 'What is needed to justify an extension of time is indicated in r 15(2) by the words "for special reasons". It is that there be shown a special reason why the appeal should be permitted to proceed, though filed after the expiry of 21 days. In that context, the expression "special reasons" is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is 21 days. But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in a particular case. Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary. We do not think the use of the expression "for special reasons" implies something narrower than this. 
 
 ... 
 
 It should not be overlooked that r 15(2) enables leave to be given "at any time"; the "special reasons" relevant to such a power cannot but describe an elastic test, suitable for application across a wide range of situations, from an oversight of a day to a neglect persisted in during a prolonged period. It would require something very persuasive indeed to justify a grant of leave after, for example, a year; equally, it may be said, something much less significant might justify leave where a party is a few days late. "Special reasons" must be understood in a sense capable of accommodating both types of situation. It is an expression describing a flexible discretionary power, but one requiring a case to be made upon grounds sufficient to justify a departure, in the particular circumstances, from the ordinary rule prescribing a period within which an appeal must be filed and served.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Howard v Australian Electoral Commission [2000] FCA 1767</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1767.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Considerations relevant to the exercise of the power are discussed in Howard v Australian Electoral Commission [2000] FCA 1767 and Ariaee v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1627.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ariaee v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1627</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1627.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Considerations relevant to the exercise of the power are discussed in Howard v Australian Electoral Commission [2000] FCA 1767 and Ariaee v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1627.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>