<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Boyapati v Rockefeller Management Corporation [2006] FCA 897 (10 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/897.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/7.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles that govern associated or accrued jurisdiction have been discussed by the High Court of Australia in a number of decisions, including Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457 at 474-5, Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 (" Fencott ") at 607-8, Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261 at 294, Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585-6, and Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559 at 585-6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/12.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles that govern associated or accrued jurisdiction have been discussed by the High Court of Australia in a number of decisions, including Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457 at 474-5, Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 (" Fencott ") at 607-8, Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261 at 294, Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585-6, and Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559 at 585-6.

10 In Fencott , Mason, Murphy, Brennan and Deane JJ, in a joint judgment, sought to clarify what would be considered a "separate and disparate" matter. At 607-608, their Honours said: 
 
 "Perhaps it is not possible to devise so precise a formula that its application to the facts of any controversy would determine accurately what claims are disparate and what claims are not. Whatever formula be adopted as a guide - and the formula of 'common transactions and facts' is a sound guide for the purpose - it must result in leaving outside the ambit of a matter a 'completely disparate claim constituting in substance a separate proceeding', a non-federal matter which is 'completely separate and distinct from the matter which attracted federal jurisdiction', or 'some distinct and unrelated non-federal claim'" (Citations omitted) 


Their Honours continued at 608:
 
 "The scope of a controversy which constitutes a matter is not ascertained merely by reference to the proceedings which a party may institute, but may be illuminated by the conduct of those proceedings and especially by the pleadings in which the issues in controversy are defined and the claims for relief are set out. But in the end, it is a matter of impression and of practical judgment whether a non-federal claim and a federal claim joined in a proceeding are within the scope of one controversy and thus within the ambit of a matter." 
 

In short, this Court will have jurisdiction to hear and determine the cross-claim in so far as it concerns the claimed sixth publication defamation, even though the claim raises no federal claim, if it shares a "common substratum of facts" with the principal proceeding, or if the claims are related in the sense that the determination of one is essential for the determination of the other.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/36.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles that govern associated or accrued jurisdiction have been discussed by the High Court of Australia in a number of decisions, including Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457 at 474-5, Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 (" Fencott ") at 607-8, Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261 at 294, Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585-6, and Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559 at 585-6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/27.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles that govern associated or accrued jurisdiction have been discussed by the High Court of Australia in a number of decisions, including Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457 at 474-5, Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 (" Fencott ") at 607-8, Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261 at 294, Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585-6, and Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559 at 585-6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/1.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles that govern associated or accrued jurisdiction have been discussed by the High Court of Australia in a number of decisions, including Philip Morris Inc v Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 7 ; (1981) 148 CLR 457 at 474-5, Fencott v Muller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 (" Fencott ") at 607-8, Stack v Coast Securities (No 9) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 36 ; (1983) 154 CLR 261 at 294, Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 at 585-6, and Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Edensor Nominees Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 1 ; (2001) 204 CLR 559 at 585-6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Hunt Australia Pty Ltd v Davidson's Arnhemland Safaris (2000) 179 ALR 738</tocase>
<text>11 The respondents relied on Hunt Australia Pty Ltd v Davidson's Arnhemland Safaris (2000) 179 ALR 738 (" Hunt ") in support of the proposition that this proposed claim fell within the associated jurisdiction. In Hunt , a Full Court held that, on the facts of that case, a defamation claim was not completely separate and distinct from a claim under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) and therefore the court had jurisdiction to decide it. The circumstances of Hunt , though different, are not completely dissimilar to the present case. The parties in Hunt were competitors and the dominant purpose of the defamatory publication was, so the court at first instance found, to injure the other party. The Court held that there was a common substratum of facts even though the publication that gave rise to the misleading and deceptive conduct claim was separate from the publication that gave rise to the defamation claim: see Hunt at 746 [30].

12 I accept that the alleged sixth publication forms part of the one controversy and, for the reasons I am about to give, can be said to arise out of the same substratum of facts. The respondents' case is that the applicants have waged a campaign of defamatory conduct against them as part of the applicants' attempt to seize market share from the respondents. The cause of action with respect to the sixth publication is related to the other defamation claims pleaded by them. Similar factual and legal issues arise in respect of all the respondents' defamation claims. The applicants conceded that at least some of the respondents' defamation claims arise out of the same circumstances as the federal matters pleaded by them. In any case, as already noted, the applicants no longer contest the court's jurisdiction over the first to fifth defamation claims. I can discern no relevant distinction between the claim with respect to the sixth publication and the other claims. It is to be borne in mind that there is an issue as to whether the applicants were motivated by express malice in making the first publication; and there is a common temporal connection with respect to all the defamation claims and the remaining issues in the proceeding.

13 Accordingly, I would grant leave to the respondents to amend their pleading in the manner they have sought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/718.html</AustLII>
<text>14 As noted earlier, the applicants also sought an order for the separate determination of certain questions under O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules . The principles that govern the circumstances in which an order of this kind may be made are well established. They are discussed by Branson J in Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 at [7] and [8] and by French J in Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651 at [7] . In discussion in court today, the parties agreed upon what I consider, in accordance with these principles, to be an appropriate separation of the questions that arise for determination in the proceeding. Accordingly, I would make the order sought in the terms discussed in court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/651.html</AustLII>
<text>14 As noted earlier, the applicants also sought an order for the separate determination of certain questions under O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules . The principles that govern the circumstances in which an order of this kind may be made are well established. They are discussed by Branson J in Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 at [7] and [8] and by French J in Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651 at [7] . In discussion in court today, the parties agreed upon what I consider, in accordance with these principles, to be an appropriate separation of the questions that arise for determination in the proceeding. Accordingly, I would make the order sought in the terms discussed in court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>