<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rubibi Community v State of Western Australia (No 6) (Corrigenda dated 15 February 2006 and 10 May 2006) [2006] FCA 82 (13 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/82.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v State of Western Australia (No 5) [2005] FCA 1025</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1025.html</AustLII>
<text>1. Introduction 2
 (a) The Yawuru community ([366]) 2 - 3
 (b) Traditional laws and customs ([367]-[369]) 3 - 4
 (c) Possession of native title rights and interests ([370]-[376]) 4 - 5
 (d) The Walman Yawuru claim 5
 (e) The remaining issues 5 - 6
2. The native title determination area 6 - 31
 (a) Introduction 6
 (b) The southern area 7
 (c) The northern area 7 - 31
 (i) Introduction 7 - 11
 (ii) The Djugan 'tribe' 11 - 13
 (iii) Yawuru 'country' 13 - 16
 (iv) Practice of the northern and southern traditions in
 Yawuru 'country' 16 - 18
 (v) Yawuru language in Yawuru 'country' 18 - 22
 (vi) The contemporary Yawuru community 22 - 25
 (vii) The native title holding community for Yawuru 'country' 25 - 27
 (viii) Succession 27 - 30
 (ix) Connection 30 - 31
 (x) Conclusion 31
3. Membership of the native title holding community 31 - 35
4. The nature and extent of native title 35 - 38
 
 
 1. Introduction 
 In interim reasons for judgment ( Rubibi Community v State of Western Australia (No 5) [2005] FCA 1025) ('the interim reasons') I determined that:

The key findings in the interim reasons that are relevant for present purposes may be summarised as follows.

The present Yawuru community, as generally defined in the genealogies before the Court, is a recognisable body of persons who are likely to be descendants, on an ambilineal or cognatic basis, of members of the Yawuru community at the time of colonial contact and therefore at the time of sovereignty. The genealogies before the Court support an inference of continuity of the Yawuru community that existed at the time of sovereignty through to the present time. As the definition of the Yawuru community, based on ambilineal or cognatic descent, is in accordance with the traditional laws and customs of the Yawuru community, it follows that the present Yawuru community is one whose members are descended from the members of the Yawuru community at sovereignty in accordance with traditional laws and customs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia [2001] FCA 607</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/607.html</AustLII>
<text>In Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia [2001] FCA 607 (' Rubibi '), which concerned the Yawuru community's claim to the law ground at Kunin, the evidence concerning the Djugan led me to conclude (at [99]) that 'at least in relation to their traditional connection to Kunin, the Djugan people are a subgroup of the Yawuru people'. At the hearing in this proceeding, which related to the establishment of native title in the Yawuru claim area, a considerably greater body of evidence was adduced in relation to the Djugan. An aspect of that evidence was that, unlike the Yawuru who practiced the southern tradition, the Djugan practiced the northern tradition. In the interim reasons I made certain observations (at [55]-[61] and [79]) about the two traditions practiced in the claim area: 
 '55. Two legal traditions, which lay down "the law", are claimed to be applicable in Yawuru country. Each of the traditions involves the creation of the world by mythological creatures or heroes who gave the people their "law", waterholes (soaks or jilas ), "law grounds", songs, "skin sections" and languages. Patrick Dodson outlined the path of the southern tradition in the Yawuru claim area in a restricted exhibit. The southern tradition is "the law" that is generally practiced by the Yawuru, Karajarri, Nyangumarta, Nygina and Mangala people. The northern tradition is generally practiced by the Bardi, Nyul Nyul, Jabirrr Jabirrr and Nyambal people. The southern tradition (southern law) may be referred to in Yawuru country as the Yawuru law. The northern tradition is often called Bardi law. The "law bosses" for the southern tradition in Yawuru country are Felix Edgar, Frank Sebastian (Gajai), Francis Djiagween (Lulga), Joseph "Nipper" Roe and Patrick Dodson. The "law bosses" for the northern tradition in Yawuru country were said to be Joseph Roe, Richard Hunter and Phillip Hunter. 
 
 The two traditions are kept separate. Joseph Roe said that the laws sit side by side without overlapping because "Bugarrigarra make them like that, we're just following Bugarrigarra." 
 While the Bugarrigarra and many of the basic rituals, customs and laws it prescribes are common to the northern and southern traditions, the two mytho-ritual traditions differ in their origin, being the journeys and undertakings of the mythological creators of the respective traditions. However, support for the claim of the Yawuru claimants that both traditions were observed in the same country is to be found in R Piddington's article, which contains observations about the initiation ceremonies under both traditions in the country of the Karajarri people, which is to the south of the Yawuru claim area. (R Piddington, "Karadjeri Initiation", Oceania , vol 3, no 1, 1932, p 46) 
 Men can go through both northern and southern law. Gajai said "[i]t has always been okay for a man to go through more than one law...The two laws don't mix but they are respected in this country." Patrick Dodson said "[i]t's not a unusual thing for a Yawuru man to go through northern law." Yawuru community members who have been through both laws include Lulga and Patrick Dodson's grandson (by "skin" and nephew by blood), Sooty Pigram. Several men who are now deceased, have also been through both laws, namely Paddy Djiagween, Bandak Bernard, Peter Kajit, Johnny Peters, and Stanley Djiagween, as well as Lulu and Paul Sampi. 
 Paul Sampi, a senior Bardi "law man", described how the northern tradition of "law" travels along two paths. The first path, Ungui , which is the first stage of "law", travels down from Bardi country along the east coast of the Dampier Peninsula from Swan Point to the mouth of the Fitzroy River at Langey Crossing, then west to Garawan and then to Willie Creek. From there, it travels back to the east to Garawan and then north to La Djardarr Bay. The other part, Ululong , the second stage of "law", travels down along the west coast of the Dampier Peninsula from Swan Point through to Wapunu in Karajarri country. Paul's evidence was that, after World War Two, Bardi men, who were living and working in Broome and wanted to be able to practice Bardi law in Yawuru country, asked permission of the Yawuru "law men" to start Ululong at Four Mile. Paul was living in Broome in 1949 and, as he had been through Ungui , was able to go through the second stage of the southern law. He says that "[i]n those days people went through both law[s]." 
 There is also a third tradition, which starts at Bilinnguru (Hidden Valley) in Yawuru country and goes out into the desert. This tradition is like a "song line" and is known as the Wanji or Dingarri . Peter Clancy, a Mangala man who gave evidence about the Wanji , stated that it speaks "Yawuru language in Yawuru country, Karajarri language in Karajarri country, and Mangala language in Mangala country. I know the songs for the Wanji right through." 
 There was some confusion as to how the Yawuru claimants relied upon the northern tradition in making out their case. Ultimately, they accepted that the normative system upon which they relied was the southern tradition, but they claimed that under that tradition there was a recognition and acceptance of the overlapping role played by the northern tradition in the Yawuru claim area. 
 
 ... 
 
 ... The evidence referred to above establishes that, on balance, "the law" is still acknowledged and observed, notwithstanding that many of the rituals of "the law" are no longer practiced. Fundamentally, "the law", as laid down by the southern tradition, remains "the law" that is acknowledged and accepted by the Yawuru community as governing all aspects of its traditional life.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Northern Territory of Australia v Alyawarr, Kaytetye, Warumungu, Wakaya Native Title Claim Group [2005] FCAFC 135 ; (2005) 145 FCR 442</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/135.html</AustLII>
<text>In Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia [2001] FCA 607 (' Rubibi '), which concerned the Yawuru community's claim to the law ground at Kunin, the evidence concerning the Djugan led me to conclude (at [99]) that 'at least in relation to their traditional connection to Kunin, the Djugan people are a subgroup of the Yawuru people'. At the hearing in this proceeding, which related to the establishment of native title in the Yawuru claim area, a considerably greater body of evidence was adduced in relation to the Djugan. An aspect of that evidence was that, unlike the Yawuru who practiced the southern tradition, the Djugan practiced the northern tradition. In the interim reasons I made certain observations (at [55]-[61] and [79]) about the two traditions practiced in the claim area: 
 '55. Two legal traditions, which lay down "the law", are claimed to be applicable in Yawuru country. Each of the traditions involves the creation of the world by mythological creatures or heroes who gave the people their "law", waterholes (soaks or jilas ), "law grounds", songs, "skin sections" and languages. Patrick Dodson outlined the path of the southern tradition in the Yawuru claim area in a restricted exhibit. The southern tradition is "the law" that is generally practiced by the Yawuru, Karajarri, Nyangumarta, Nygina and Mangala people. The northern tradition is generally practiced by the Bardi, Nyul Nyul, Jabirrr Jabirrr and Nyambal people. The southern tradition (southern law) may be referred to in Yawuru country as the Yawuru law. The northern tradition is often called Bardi law. The "law bosses" for the southern tradition in Yawuru country are Felix Edgar, Frank Sebastian (Gajai), Francis Djiagween (Lulga), Joseph "Nipper" Roe and Patrick Dodson. The "law bosses" for the northern tradition in Yawuru country were said to be Joseph Roe, Richard Hunter and Phillip Hunter. 
 
 The two traditions are kept separate. Joseph Roe said that the laws sit side by side without overlapping because "Bugarrigarra make them like that, we're just following Bugarrigarra." 
 While the Bugarrigarra and many of the basic rituals, customs and laws it prescribes are common to the northern and southern traditions, the two mytho-ritual traditions differ in their origin, being the journeys and undertakings of the mythological creators of the respective traditions. However, support for the claim of the Yawuru claimants that both traditions were observed in the same country is to be found in R Piddington's article, which contains observations about the initiation ceremonies under both traditions in the country of the Karajarri people, which is to the south of the Yawuru claim area. (R Piddington, "Karadjeri Initiation", Oceania , vol 3, no 1, 1932, p 46) 
 Men can go through both northern and southern law. Gajai said "[i]t has always been okay for a man to go through more than one law...The two laws don't mix but they are respected in this country." Patrick Dodson said "[i]t's not a unusual thing for a Yawuru man to go through northern law." Yawuru community members who have been through both laws include Lulga and Patrick Dodson's grandson (by "skin" and nephew by blood), Sooty Pigram. Several men who are now deceased, have also been through both laws, namely Paddy Djiagween, Bandak Bernard, Peter Kajit, Johnny Peters, and Stanley Djiagween, as well as Lulu and Paul Sampi. 
 Paul Sampi, a senior Bardi "law man", described how the northern tradition of "law" travels along two paths. The first path, Ungui , which is the first stage of "law", travels down from Bardi country along the east coast of the Dampier Peninsula from Swan Point to the mouth of the Fitzroy River at Langey Crossing, then west to Garawan and then to Willie Creek. From there, it travels back to the east to Garawan and then north to La Djardarr Bay. The other part, Ululong , the second stage of "law", travels down along the west coast of the Dampier Peninsula from Swan Point through to Wapunu in Karajarri country. Paul's evidence was that, after World War Two, Bardi men, who were living and working in Broome and wanted to be able to practice Bardi law in Yawuru country, asked permission of the Yawuru "law men" to start Ululong at Four Mile. Paul was living in Broome in 1949 and, as he had been through Ungui , was able to go through the second stage of the southern law. He says that "[i]n those days people went through both law[s]." 
 There is also a third tradition, which starts at Bilinnguru (Hidden Valley) in Yawuru country and goes out into the desert. This tradition is like a "song line" and is known as the Wanji or Dingarri . Peter Clancy, a Mangala man who gave evidence about the Wanji , stated that it speaks "Yawuru language in Yawuru country, Karajarri language in Karajarri country, and Mangala language in Mangala country. I know the songs for the Wanji right through." 
 There was some confusion as to how the Yawuru claimants relied upon the northern tradition in making out their case. Ultimately, they accepted that the normative system upon which they relied was the southern tradition, but they claimed that under that tradition there was a recognition and acceptance of the overlapping role played by the northern tradition in the Yawuru claim area. 
 
 ... 
 
 ... The evidence referred to above establishes that, on balance, "the law" is still acknowledged and observed, notwithstanding that many of the rituals of "the law" are no longer practiced. Fundamentally, "the law", as laid down by the southern tradition, remains "the law" that is acknowledged and accepted by the Yawuru community as governing all aspects of its traditional life.'

However, it does not follow that the Djugan and the Yawuru each possessed their own discrete communal native title rights and interests at and since sovereignty in respect of the northern and southern areas respectively. The entitlement of different groups to communal native title was considered by the Full Court in Northern Territory of Australia v Alyawarr, Kaytetye, Warumungu, Wakaya Native Title Claim Group [2005] FCAFC 135 ; (2005) 145 FCR 442 (' Alyawarr ') at 466-475 [78]-[112]. The Full Court, after citing a number of cases, observed that members of a 'community' may possess communal native title rights and interests, albeit that they are 'intramurally allocated' to different groups or subsets of the community. Although each of the cases cited by the Full Court turns on its own facts, their Honours (at 475 [112]) accepted that the evidence of 'extensive connections' across the claimant groups supported the primary judge's characterisation of those groups as 'one native title holding community' that had the necessary connection with the land in the claim area 'at a communal or claim group level'.

Accordingly, it is necessary to consider the totality of the evidence concerning the Djugan and the Yawuru in order to determine whether, notwithstanding their cultural and other differences at and since sovereignty, the Djugan and the Yawuru are one native title holding community that had the necessary connection with Yawuru 'country' at a communal level.

Extensive evidence was adduced to the effect that Yawuru 'country' included the northern area. The evidence, which included the views of senior law men and women, was not seriously challenged. The evidence of senior law men from 'country' adjacent to the claim area and the evidence adduced as to the views of senior Yawuru law men and women was that Yawuru 'country' consisted of the southern and the northern areas. Peter Clancy, a senior Mangala law man regarded the northern area as being within 'Yawuru Country because the old people told me'. A senior Nyangumarta law man stated that the shared law that comes from the Bugarrigarra included 'the whole lot of that country up to Willie Creek'. Evidence adduced as part of the Walman Yawuru case was also to the effect that 'Mimi', a senior Yawuru law woman who lived in Broome up to the 1950s, had claimed that Yawuru country included Broome and extended up to Willie Creek.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sampi on behalf of the Bardi and Jawi People v Western Australia [2005] FCA 777</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/777.html</AustLII>
<text>Subject to the possible exception referred to above, I am satisfied that, generally, the evidence supports the inference contended for by the Yawuru claimants of exclusive possession and occupation of the Yawuru claim area (excluding the intertidal zone) where there has been no extinguishment. However, for the reasons given by French J in Sampi on behalf of the Bardi and Jawi People v Western Australia [2005] FCA 777 at [1072] , the right should be limited to exclusive possession and occupation and should not extend to the broader concepts of 'use and enjoyment'. I also agree with his Honour that the right claimed to 'speak for' the land and to make decisions about its use and enjoyment by others is also subsumed in the global right of exclusive possession and occupation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sampi v Western Australia (No 3) [2005] FCA 1716</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1716.html</AustLII>
<text>In conclusion, the evidence and findings to which I have referred support a finding of the existence of the rights claimed by the Yawuru claimants as set out in [111] save that the references to use and enjoyment are to be deleted. Also, the proposed determination of the Yawuru claimants does not state the purposes for which the resources of the land and waters in the claim area, including the intertidal areas, may be accessed and used: cf Sampi v Western Australia (No 3) [2005] FCA 1716. I doubt that it is contended that the purposes are to be unlimited or are to extend to a general right of commercial exploitation. In the circumstances, it is desirable that the Yawuru claimants address that issue.

I would add that, apart from the fact that the rights claimed in the intertidal zone are not exclusive and are necessarily more limited than the rights claimed in the land areas, I see no proper basis for otherwise distinguishing between the native title rights and interests in that zone and in the land. No such distinction was drawn in the evidence or in the traditional laws and customs acknowledged and observed by the Yawuru community.

As there will be some issues as to how the final determination should reflect my findings and conclusions, I propose to afford the parties an opportunity of making further submissions on that matter. There also remains for determination the issues the parties still propose to press in relation to extinguishment, as well as any issues arising out of these reasons. I propose to give directions for an early determination of all of those issues.
 I certify that the preceding one hundred and twenty one (121) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Merkel. 
 
Associate:
 
 
Dated: 13 February 2006
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: Mr K Bell QC with
Mr G Irving and
Mr A Firth 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Mr I Irving of the Kimberley Land Council 
 
 Counsel for the State of Western Australia: Ms R Webb QC with
Mr B King 
 
 Solicitors for the State of Western Australia: Crown Solicitor for the State of Western Australia 
 
 Counsel for the Commonwealth of Australia: Mr P Quinlan with
Mr A Rorrison 
 
 Solicitors for the Commonwealth of Australia: Australian Government Solicitors 
 
 Counsel for the Western Australian Fishing Industry Council (Inc): Mr G Hiley QC with
Mr M McKenna 
 
 Solicitors for the Western Australian Fishing Industry Council (Inc): Hunt and Humphrey 
 
 Counsel for the Walman Yawuru Respondents: Mr I Viner QC 
 
 Appearing as a representative of the Walman Yawuru Respondents: Ms R Hanigan 
 
 Solicitor for Shire of Broome: Mr P Wittkuhn of McLeods 
 
 Dates of hearing: 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 May 2003;
3, 4, 5, 6, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13 June 2003;
27, 28, 29, 30, 31 October 2003;
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14 November 2003;
14, 15, 16, 17, 18 June 2004;
27, 28, 29, 30 September 2004; and
1, 4, 5, 6, 7 October 2004. 
 
 Date of Interim Reasons: 29 July 2005 
 
 Date of these further Reasons: 13 February 2006 
 SCHEDULE 
 
 
 APPLICANTS: 
CORPUS, Michael 
DJIAGWEEN, Cecilia
DJIAGWEEN, Francis
DODSON, Patrick
EDGAR, Elsie
EDGAR, Felix
HUNTER, Richard
ROE, Joseph
ROE, Joseph 'Nipper'
ROE, Teresa
SADDLER, Thelma
SEBASTIAN, Frank
 
 
 RESPONDENTS: 
 
 
 01 Government Interests State of Western Australia 
Aboriginal Affairs Department
Aboriginal Lands Trust
Commissioner of Main Roads
Electricity Corporation
Minister for Aboriginal Affairs
Minister for Energy
Minister for Fisheries
Minister for Lands
Minister for Mines
Minister for Transport
Minister for Water Resources
State of Western Australia
 
 
 02 Government Interests Commonwealth of Australia 
Airservices Australia
 
 
 02A Government Interests Commonwealth of Australia 
Commonwealth of Australia
 
 
 02A Government Interests Local Government 
Shire of Broome
 
 
 04 Indigenous Interests 
Bilgungurr Aboriginal Corporation
Kimberley Land Council
MATSUMOTO, Peter
ROBINSON, Margaret Mary
ROE, Edward Leonard
 
 
 05 Mining Interests 
CONNOLLY, Peter Scott
COUNTY, Brian Stanley
Maple Oil Exploration NL (Administrators Appointed) (Receivers and Managers Appointed)
 
 
 06 Pastoral Interests 
CROOK, Reginald D
Thangoo Pty Ltd (Thangoo Station)
 
 
 07 Telecommunications Industry Interests 
Telstra Corporation Limited
 
 
 08 Tourism Interests 
Broome Crocodile Park
Cable Beach Jet Boat Charter
Dampier Creek Boat Tours
Kimberley Birdwatching
The Kimberley Connection Pty Ltd
 
 
 09 Fishing Interests 
Australian Ocean Exporters Pty Ltd
BLATCHFORD, Kevin
Broometime Charters
CANNEY, Pam
FRASER, Alan John
IGNOTI, Les
IGNOTI, Peter
IGNOTI, Russell
Kimberley Fish and Ice Supplies
Lenden Nominees Pty Ltd
Leveque Wilderness Fishing Charters
LEW, Ian
LITTLETON, Kyran R
MOORE, Gary
NEWTON, Ross
Pearl Coast Charters
Pearl Sea Coastal Cruises
WEIR, Neville
 
 
 09A Fishing Interests 
Western Australian Fishing Industry Council (Inc)
 
 
 10 Pearling Interests 
Australian Sea Pearls Pty Ltd
Broome Pearls Pty Ltd
Cygnet Bay Pearls
Paspaley Pearling Company Pty Ltd
Pearls Pty Ltd
Roebuck Pearl Producers Pty Ltd
Willie Creek Pearl Farm and Broome Coachlines
 
 
 11 Petroleum Interests 
E-Com Multi Limited
 
 
 12 Non Party (For Information Only) 
National Native Title Tribunal
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/82.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>