<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>David Lambourne Yacht Rigging v Perry Catamarans (Receivers and Managers Appointed) [2006] FCA 887 (10 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/887.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Creevey v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 19 ACSR 456</tocase>
<text>8 In Creevey v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 19 ACSR 456, McPherson JA (with whom Davies and Pincus JJA agreed) observed at 457:
 
 'The question of whether an administration should continue, rather than that there be a winding-up, is obviously closely related to the further question of whether the creditors could hope to get more by way of payment of their debts from one form of process or administration than from the other. In order to satisfy the court of the matter referred to in s 440A(2) of the Corporations Law, one would expect that there would have to be some persuasive evidence to enable it to be seen that there were assets which, if realised under one form of administration rather than the other, would produce a larger dividend , or at least an accelerated dividend for the creditors.' [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/830.html</AustLII>
<text>9 That formulation of the approach to s 440A(2) has provided the jurisprudential foundation for the continuing assessment of the requirements of the section. (See TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830 per Hamilton J; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629 per Santow J; Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194 per Santow J). In TCS Management , Hamilton J at [15] embraced the observation of Young J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589 at [18] that, 'There must be a sufficient possibility , as distinct from mere optimistic speculation , that such a deferment for the envisaged time is in the interests of creditors' .[emphasis added] That view is consistent with the remarks of Santow J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615 at [8] and [9], in these terms:
 
 
 '8. The authorities on s 440A(2) require, in my view, more than a mere speculative possibility of a higher return to creditors if a winding-up application was to be adjourned, here in favour of the prospect of the Deed of Company Arrangement. ... 
 
 9. In my view, there must be a real prospect of benefit from the adjournment. But it is too simplistic to say that that prospect must necessarily be, at this point, a comfortable satisfaction that a Deed of Company Arrangement will yield a greater amount than winding-up. Of course, in some cases that may already be safely apparent whilst in others the company is so evidently a basket case that further delay of the inevitable would simply add to costs; see, for example, Yates v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation.' [emphasis added]

49 In TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd (supra) Hamilton J ultimately concluded [18] that the onus on the applicant for an adjournment of the winding-up application is one of establishing 'a good case that there will be a greater or more accelerated return from the course proposed' under the deed of company arrangement. It seems to me that the quality of the case made out must be one which demonstrates that the interests of all creditors are accommodated to a greater degree or with greater acceleration than they would otherwise be in the course of a winding-up.

50 Notwithstanding the assessment of the three scenarios contained in the report of the Administrators and an acceptance of the basis for those scenarios, I cannot be satisfied that it is in the interests of all creditors that the application for a winding-up order be adjourned.

51 Accordingly, I would dismiss the application for adjournment and make a winding-up order.
 
 
 I certify that the preceding fifty-one (51) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood. 


Associate:


Dated: 10 July 2006

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr Paul Freeburn SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: James Conomos Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr Stephen Lee 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Gadens Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 7 July 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 10 July 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/887.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629</tocase>
<text>9 That formulation of the approach to s 440A(2) has provided the jurisprudential foundation for the continuing assessment of the requirements of the section. (See TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830 per Hamilton J; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629 per Santow J; Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194 per Santow J). In TCS Management , Hamilton J at [15] embraced the observation of Young J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589 at [18] that, 'There must be a sufficient possibility , as distinct from mere optimistic speculation , that such a deferment for the envisaged time is in the interests of creditors' .[emphasis added] That view is consistent with the remarks of Santow J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615 at [8] and [9], in these terms:
 
 
 '8. The authorities on s 440A(2) require, in my view, more than a mere speculative possibility of a higher return to creditors if a winding-up application was to be adjourned, here in favour of the prospect of the Deed of Company Arrangement. ... 
 
 9. In my view, there must be a real prospect of benefit from the adjournment. But it is too simplistic to say that that prospect must necessarily be, at this point, a comfortable satisfaction that a Deed of Company Arrangement will yield a greater amount than winding-up. Of course, in some cases that may already be safely apparent whilst in others the company is so evidently a basket case that further delay of the inevitable would simply add to costs; see, for example, Yates v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation.' [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194</tocase>
<text>9 That formulation of the approach to s 440A(2) has provided the jurisprudential foundation for the continuing assessment of the requirements of the section. (See TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830 per Hamilton J; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629 per Santow J; Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194 per Santow J). In TCS Management , Hamilton J at [15] embraced the observation of Young J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589 at [18] that, 'There must be a sufficient possibility , as distinct from mere optimistic speculation , that such a deferment for the envisaged time is in the interests of creditors' .[emphasis added] That view is consistent with the remarks of Santow J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615 at [8] and [9], in these terms:
 
 
 '8. The authorities on s 440A(2) require, in my view, more than a mere speculative possibility of a higher return to creditors if a winding-up application was to be adjourned, here in favour of the prospect of the Deed of Company Arrangement. ... 
 
 9. In my view, there must be a real prospect of benefit from the adjournment. But it is too simplistic to say that that prospect must necessarily be, at this point, a comfortable satisfaction that a Deed of Company Arrangement will yield a greater amount than winding-up. Of course, in some cases that may already be safely apparent whilst in others the company is so evidently a basket case that further delay of the inevitable would simply add to costs; see, for example, Yates v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation.' [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/1999/589.html</AustLII>
<text>9 That formulation of the approach to s 440A(2) has provided the jurisprudential foundation for the continuing assessment of the requirements of the section. (See TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830 per Hamilton J; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629 per Santow J; Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194 per Santow J). In TCS Management , Hamilton J at [15] embraced the observation of Young J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589 at [18] that, 'There must be a sufficient possibility , as distinct from mere optimistic speculation , that such a deferment for the envisaged time is in the interests of creditors' .[emphasis added] That view is consistent with the remarks of Santow J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615 at [8] and [9], in these terms:
 
 
 '8. The authorities on s 440A(2) require, in my view, more than a mere speculative possibility of a higher return to creditors if a winding-up application was to be adjourned, here in favour of the prospect of the Deed of Company Arrangement. ... 
 
 9. In my view, there must be a real prospect of benefit from the adjournment. But it is too simplistic to say that that prospect must necessarily be, at this point, a comfortable satisfaction that a Deed of Company Arrangement will yield a greater amount than winding-up. Of course, in some cases that may already be safely apparent whilst in others the company is so evidently a basket case that further delay of the inevitable would simply add to costs; see, for example, Yates v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation.' [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615</tocase>
<text>9 That formulation of the approach to s 440A(2) has provided the jurisprudential foundation for the continuing assessment of the requirements of the section. (See TCS Management Pty Ltd v CTTI Solutions Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 830 per Hamilton J; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Yates Security Services Pty Ltd (1997) 26 ACSR 629 per Santow J; Waste Recycling and Processing Services of NSW v Local Government Recycling Co-Operative (1999) 32 ACSR 194 per Santow J). In TCS Management , Hamilton J at [15] embraced the observation of Young J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Choice Design Homes Pty Ltd [1999] NSWSC 589 at [18] that, 'There must be a sufficient possibility , as distinct from mere optimistic speculation , that such a deferment for the envisaged time is in the interests of creditors' .[emphasis added] That view is consistent with the remarks of Santow J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v First Netcom Pty Ltd (2000) 35 ACSR 615 at [8] and [9], in these terms:
 
 
 '8. The authorities on s 440A(2) require, in my view, more than a mere speculative possibility of a higher return to creditors if a winding-up application was to be adjourned, here in favour of the prospect of the Deed of Company Arrangement. ... 
 
 9. In my view, there must be a real prospect of benefit from the adjournment. But it is too simplistic to say that that prospect must necessarily be, at this point, a comfortable satisfaction that a Deed of Company Arrangement will yield a greater amount than winding-up. Of course, in some cases that may already be safely apparent whilst in others the company is so evidently a basket case that further delay of the inevitable would simply add to costs; see, for example, Yates v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation.' [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Lewis (as liq) of Doran Constructions Pty Ltd (in liq) and Anor v Doran &amp; Ors [2005] NSWCA 243</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2005/243.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The Administrators in their report express the view that it can not be said that the company was insolvent until the moment in time on 22 April 2006 when the secured creditors made an election not to continue to support the company. That view rests upon the assessment by the administrators of the observations of their Honours, Giles, Hodgson and McColl JJA in Lewis (as liq) of Doran Constructions Pty Ltd (in liq) and Anor v Doran &amp; Ors [2005] NSWCA 243. In particular, in determining whether a company is solvent for the purposes of s 95A of the Act, regard must be had to the commercial or practical realities of inter-group financing. At [109] their Honours said:
 
 'Particularly when the limiting words [from its own resources] are no longer part of a test, there is no compelling reason to exclude from consideration funds which can be gained from borrowings secured on assets of third parties, or even unsecured borrowings. If the company can borrow without security, it will have funds to pay its debts as they fall due and will be solvent ...'

22 However, their Honours also noted an important proviso in these terms:
 
 '... provided of course that the borrowing is on deferred payment terms or otherwise such that the lender itself is not a creditor whose debt can not be repaid as and when it becomes due and payable . It comes down to a question of fact, in which the key concept is ability to pay the company's debts as and when they become due and payable'.

23 In considering the question of whether the relevant transactions under consideration in Lewis v Doran (supra) were insolvent transactions their Honours noted (per Giles JA (with whom Hodgson and McColl JJA agreed)) at 113, 'Importantly, I do not think it was suggested that the funds made available apparently repayable on demand, were to be regarded as immediately repayable so that holdings itself (the lender) was a creditor whose debt could not be repaid as and when it was due and payable'.

24 The Administrators take the view that because the respondent company had access to funds from Perry Holdings and Farallon, and continued to enjoy that access until 22 April 2006 when support was withdrawn, the respondent company became insolvent only on 22 April 2006. Accordingly, when the respondent company incurred an obligation to pay creditors for the value of goods supplied, it did not do so in circumstances of insolvency and, more particularly, it did not do so in circumstances which would give rise to a claim against either Mr Nunn or Perry Holdings or Farallon under the Act. Accordingly, such a claim is not, properly considered, an asset which might be recovered in a winding-up. Alternatively, the pursuit of such a claim would require a liquidator to conduct an oral examination of a number of individuals including Mr Nunn, senior management of the respondent company, senior staff (including the CFO) of Perry Holdings and Farallon and other stakeholders of Perry Holdings and Farallon. Since the insolvency arose only on 22 April 2006, only those debts incurred after that date would be the subject of such a claim.

25 The fixed and floating charges secure monies payable upon an 'event of default' should the mortgagee elect to make demand for the immediate repayment of the secured money or exercise other rights and powers conferred by the security. A proof of debt has been lodged in the administration for the full amount of the secured debt of $6,937,873.00 although the shortfall will be approximately $5M. Although it may well be true that at the moment in time that debts to unrelated third parties were incurred, no demand had been made and therefore the secured monies were not then immediately due and payable, there is a reasonable basis for inferring that when a number of the debts to unsecured creditors were incurred (particularly in March and April 2006 but also earlier) Mr Nunn must have known that a demand he might choose to make wearing his Perry Holdings' hat could never be satisfied by the respondent company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v K J Consulting Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1827</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1827.html</AustLII>
<text>40 The respondents to the adjournment further rely upon the observations of Gyles J in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v K J Consulting Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1827. The factors that Gyles J suggests are influential against adjourning an application for a winding-up order are these. Firstly, the fact that the company is not trading; secondly, the undoubted insolvency of the company; thirdly, the composition and attitude of the creditors; and fourthly the recognition that a liquidator has more ability to follow potential breaches of the law than administrators. All of these factors are said to be made out in the present case and suggest strongly that the application for the winding-up order ought not to be adjourned.

41 It seems to me that each of these matters must contextually be considered against the background of whether there is, on the present material, a real prospect of a better outcome under the Deed than in a winding-up or, if the measure of the dividend is similar, whether the dividend can be achieved more quickly under the Deed. Although it seems to me that the circumstances of the relationship between the three entities and the role of Mr Nunn in each of them gives rise to a basis for suggesting that as a practical reality, a circumstance of insolvency may well have arisen earlier than the administrators contend for, there is no doubt that Perry Holdings and Farallon provided loan monies and financial accommodation of substance and that in a winding-up those related party transactions would rank for distribution. If an assumption is made that the full amount of the unrelated, unsecured creditor claims ($1.4M) might be recovered from Mr Nunn or from Perry Holdings or Farallon under s 588V (and assuming no set-off operates), the dividend will be 15.5 cents. Since the dividend under the deed is likely to be 17.9 cents without contest or the need to establish causes of action, the assessment by the administrators is more than 'a mere speculative possibility of a higher return'.

42 The opponents of the adjournment also say that the proposal to establish a deed fund of $300,000.00 should be viewed with scepticism because there is no obvious commercial purpose for establishing the fund and an inference should be drawn that the fund is proposed for the purpose of foreclosing any analysis or scrutiny of the conduct of Mr Nunn, Perry Holdings and Farallon.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>