<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lakshmanan v Janarthanan (No 2) [2006] FCA 832 (8 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/832.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hamilton v Whitehead [1988] HCA 65 ; (1988) 166 CLR 121</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/65.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Lastly, it was put that there was no evidence of reliance on the fifth respondent because of Dr Lakshmanan's lack of knowledge of its existence and that in order to enable the applicants to succeed they had to know of the existence of that corporation. I put to Mr Wood examples where courts have held, such as in Hamilton v Whitehead [1988] HCA 65 ; (1988) 166 CLR 121 at 127, that the act of an individual was the act of the corporation. If, here, it could be found, and I make no finding about this, that Mr Spratt was acting on behalf of the fifth respondent then his acts could be, I do not say they would be, found to be the fifth respondent's acts and likewise his omissions its omissions.

12 This application was made without notice, by only one of the respondents. The other respondents do not ask me to dismiss the case against them and the factual and legal issues which I have recounted above suggest that in order to resolve the matter at this point would require me to reserve judgment, analyse in some detail the evidence and then deliver a judgment at a later time, thereby interrupting the flow of the evidence. I do not believe that that would be in the interests of justice in a case in which fraud is alleged and where I have just had the benefit, as a trial judge, of observing two of the principal witnesses giving evidence as to the circumstances in which it is alleged that fraud or misleading conduct occurred.

13 The other basis on which Mr Wood submitted that I should dismiss the proceedings was that the allegation of fraud itself was so serious that there being the legal and evidentiary weaknesses to which he pointed in respect of the s 52 counts I should dismiss the case rather than require his client to be faced in litigation with the prospect of an adverse finding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hummerstone v Leary [1921] 2 KB 664</tocase>
<text>15 In James v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (1985) 9 FCR 448, Toohey J considered a similar situation and (at 9 FCR at 453) his Honour referred to decisions of the English Divisional Court in Hummerstone v Leary [1921] 2 KB 664, and of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Menzies v Australian Iron and Steel Limited (1952) 52 NSWSR 62. In the latter case, at the close of the plaintiff's case, counsel for the employer applied for a verdict by direction. The trial judge said that the application was premature but that it might be renewed later and that counsel could call and not call evidence as he thought fit. Toohey J said that a practice had been approved by the Full Court, which also gave its endorsement to Hummerstone v Leary and to the passage in Glanville Williams on Joint Torts and Contributory Negligence , at 59, in the following terms:
 
 'In actions against concurrent tortfeasors there is a further rule that if a plaintiff shows that prima facie one if not both of the defendants was negligent, the judge should not at the close of the plaintiff's evidence non suit him against one defendant only, but should hear the whole case before coming to a decision.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>James v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (1985) 9 FCR 448</tocase>
<text>15 In James v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (1985) 9 FCR 448, Toohey J considered a similar situation and (at 9 FCR at 453) his Honour referred to decisions of the English Divisional Court in Hummerstone v Leary [1921] 2 KB 664, and of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Menzies v Australian Iron and Steel Limited (1952) 52 NSWSR 62. In the latter case, at the close of the plaintiff's case, counsel for the employer applied for a verdict by direction. The trial judge said that the application was premature but that it might be renewed later and that counsel could call and not call evidence as he thought fit. Toohey J said that a practice had been approved by the Full Court, which also gave its endorsement to Hummerstone v Leary and to the passage in Glanville Williams on Joint Torts and Contributory Negligence , at 59, in the following terms:
 
 'In actions against concurrent tortfeasors there is a further rule that if a plaintiff shows that prima facie one if not both of the defendants was negligent, the judge should not at the close of the plaintiff's evidence non suit him against one defendant only, but should hear the whole case before coming to a decision.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/8.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In Rasomen v Shell Company of Australia Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 216 at 226C-E the Full Court of this Court said:
 
 'The cases referred to concern civil trials before a judge and jury, and the statements of principles in the judgment must be understood in that context where the trial judge is the arbiter of the law and not of the facts. In civil trials conducted before a judge alone the judge is arbiter both of the law and the facts, and the principles require modification to reflect that different considerations apply. In Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 at 330-331 Windeyer J said: 
 
 When there is no jury, the proposition " no case" to answer may obviously mean far more than " is there evidence on which a jury could find for the plaintiff? It may mean would you, the judge, on the evidence given find for the plaintiff?" '

20 And a reference was then given to Jones v Dunkel (101 CLR at 330-331).

21 In my opinion, if I were to approach the case on the basis of deciding whether or not I would find for the fifth respondent as the judge on the evidence given I would become involved in an adjudication of facts arising out of circumstances in which there were common elements and common alleged admissions to which the other respondents participating in the trial were party. I would run the risk of expressing a view which may mean that my continued ability to conduct the trial could be prejudiced by having in one way or another decided a matter of fact. It would involve me reviewing the evidence, analysing it in circumstances where there is a deal of evidence already, not all of it wholly consistent, and forming a view about what parts of it I should accept as being what I was told was: ' ...the applicant's case at its highest... '.

22 Ms Williams addressed that last consideration, in part, by pointing to a passage in the evidence in chief of Dr Lakshmanan in which in effect, he said that he would not have gone into the investment had he not been told that it was a good business. On the evidence thus far at its highest, all of the relevant corporate respondents and the human beings who were directors or associated with them were present during the visit to the factory on 6 March 1999 at that moment, including Mr Spratt, a then director of the fifth respondent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Menzies v Australian Iron and Steel Limited (1952) 52 NSWSR 62</tocase>
<text>15 In James v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (1985) 9 FCR 448, Toohey J considered a similar situation and (at 9 FCR at 453) his Honour referred to decisions of the English Divisional Court in Hummerstone v Leary [1921] 2 KB 664, and of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Menzies v Australian Iron and Steel Limited (1952) 52 NSWSR 62. In the latter case, at the close of the plaintiff's case, counsel for the employer applied for a verdict by direction. The trial judge said that the application was premature but that it might be renewed later and that counsel could call and not call evidence as he thought fit. Toohey J said that a practice had been approved by the Full Court, which also gave its endorsement to Hummerstone v Leary and to the passage in Glanville Williams on Joint Torts and Contributory Negligence , at 59, in the following terms:
 
 'In actions against concurrent tortfeasors there is a further rule that if a plaintiff shows that prima facie one if not both of the defendants was negligent, the judge should not at the close of the plaintiff's evidence non suit him against one defendant only, but should hear the whole case before coming to a decision.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Rasomen v Shell Company of Australia Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 216</tocase>
<text>17 In Rasomen v Shell Company of Australia Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 216 at 226C-E the Full Court of this Court said:
 
 'The cases referred to concern civil trials before a judge and jury, and the statements of principles in the judgment must be understood in that context where the trial judge is the arbiter of the law and not of the facts. In civil trials conducted before a judge alone the judge is arbiter both of the law and the facts, and the principles require modification to reflect that different considerations apply. In Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 at 330-331 Windeyer J said: 
 
 When there is no jury, the proposition " no case" to answer may obviously mean far more than " is there evidence on which a jury could find for the plaintiff? It may mean would you, the judge, on the evidence given find for the plaintiff?" '</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Winterton Constructions Pty Ltd v Hambros Australia Limited (1992) 39 FCR 97</tocase>
<text>7 It was put that silence itself could not be misleading and that, as Hill J had said in Winterton Constructions Pty Ltd v Hambros Australia Limited (1992) 39 FCR 97 at 114:
 
 '... it is difficult to see how mere silence could, of itself, constitute conduct which was misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive.'

8 His Honour, however, went on there to say:
 
 'However, if the circumstances are such that a person is entitled to believe that a relevant matter affecting him or her adversely would, if it existed, be communicated, then the failure to so communicate it may constitute conduct which is misleading or deceptive because the person who ultimately may act to his or her detriment is entitled to infer from the silence that no danger of the detriment existed. Thus, where a duty to speak is imposed, silence may constitute misleading and deceptive conduct. 
 
 Whether such a duty exists would clearly depend upon all the circumstances of the case.' 
 
 I agree.

9 Ms Williams said that a lack of the knowledge of the existence of the corporate party with whom Mr Spratt, in this circumstance, was connected, was irrelevant and that indeed, there can be situations where one is dealing, as commonly happens, with a business name that is quite dissimilar to the actual name of the corporate actor. A member of the public dealing with the business name would not have any idea whether or not it was an incorporated company, a partnership or an individual with whom he or she was trading yet it may well be that there is a responsibility able to be made out at the end of the day against the entity which ran whatever business it carried on under or through the business name.

10 Moreover, there is a further difficulty here that Ms Williams submitted and Mr Wood did not suggest to the contrary. At this stage there is no evidence that Mr Bayliss knew anything that he said was incorrect, whereas there is some evidence that representatives of the corporate entities with whom the fifth respondent was associated, namely, Furniture Australia and the fifth respondent itself through Mr Spratt, had knowledge of a different factual position of Furniture Australia from that the subject of the alleged representations.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>