<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Consort Express Lines Limited (ARBN 065 374 183) v J-Mac Pty Limited (ACN 055 284 270) (No 2) [2006] FCA 833 (3 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/833.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Admiralty Commissioners v SS Susquehanna [1926] AC 655</tocase>
<text>87 In the Hebridean Coast [1961] AC 545 at 576-578, Lord Reid applied there principles to a case where a government corporation claimed damages for the detention of a nonprofitearning vessel while she was being repaired. His Lordship distinguished this from the case of a profit-earning ship where the plaintiff had to prove '... the probability that she would have earned so much money if her owner could have used her' ([1961] AC at 577). With a nonprofit-earning ship, if no harm were proved apart from the mere fact that the owner is deprived of her services during the period of repairs, the Court awards damages based on interest and depreciation on the value of the ship ([1961] AC at 578 per Lord Reid, 580 per Lords Morton of Henryton and Tucker, 583 per Lord Morris of Borth-y-Gest; The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596). In Admiralty Commissioners v SS Susquehanna [1926] AC 655 at 664, Lord Sumner said that in such an assessment 'the practice of treating the injured ship, by a sort of personification, as a separate claimant is too inveterate to be disturbed now.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Anthanasopoulos v Moseley [2001] NSWCA 266 ; (2001) 52 NSWLR 262</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2001/266.html</AustLII>
<text>88 And in Anthanasopoulos v Moseley [2001] NSWCA 266 ; (2001) 52 NSWLR 262 the Court of Appeal of the Supreme Court of New South Wales allowed car owners (or their insurer) who were deprived of the use of their vehicles to recover the cost of hire of a substitute vehicle while theirs underwent repair even though they were not out of pocket for that hire. That Court applied The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596 on the basis that injury to non income producing property which deprives a party of the use of the property is compensable and held that the claim was for general, not special damages (see 52 NSWLR at 276 [76] per Ipp A-JA; see too at 273 [54], 274 [58] per Beazley JA).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Banco de Portugal v Waterlow &amp; Sons Ltd [1932] UKHL 1 ; [1932] AC 452</tocase>
<text>109 In Banco de Portugal v Waterlow &amp; Sons Ltd [1932] UKHL 1 ; [1932] AC 452 at 506 Lord Macmillan held that where the sufferer from a breach of contract finds itself in consequence of that breach placed in a position of embarrassment, the measures it may be driven to adopt in order to extricate itself ought not to be weighed in nice scales at the instance of the party whose breach of contract had occasioned the difficulty. His Lordship continued:
 
 'It is often easy after an emergency has passed to criticize the steps which have been taken to meet it, but such criticism does not come well from those who have themselves created the emergency. The law is satisfied if the party placed in a difficult situation by reason of the breach of a duty owed to him has acted reasonably in the adoption of remedial measures, and he will not be held disentitled to recover the cost of such measures merely because the party in breach can suggest that other measures less burdensome to him might have been taken.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292</tocase>
<text>86 The principle applicable to the right of a shipowner to recover from a wrongdoer the cost of hiring a substitute vessel while its own vessel is being repaired as a result of the tort, was stated by Viscount Sumner in SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196 at 205 (Lord Buckmaster agreeing at 205 and Lord Warrington of Clyffe gave a concurring speech at 211-212: see too per Scrutton LJ in The York [1929] P 178 at 184; The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n; 166 ER 155; cp: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 240-241 [1062] -1067] per Finn J; Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 300-302, 306, 313) thus:
 
 'If... the [plaintiff's] case is to be that the delay upset the general current of their trade, which had to be maintained in spite of it, I think that the extent and cost of this upset must be proved and must be causally connected with the collision in accordance with the ordinary rules of law as to damage. A ship's day is not like a unit of currency, always good for so many shillings. It has to be proved that, in doing the shipowner the wrong of laying his ship idle at the time in question, work, which she would otherwise have done during the time, went undone to his measurable loss or was only done by resorting to other expedients at a measurable outlay.'

89 I am satisfied that it was necessary for Consort to charter the Noumea Express as a substitute vessel in July and August 2000 while the Gazelle Coast underwent the extensive repairs and restoration work then undertaken. I am of opinion that the claim for the hire of the Noumea Express is reasonable. Mr McInnes noted that some repairs carried out at this time were not referable to any purchase defect. I have considered those items and they appear to me, based on their description, to be of a relatively minor or routine nature and to be of a kind that could be undertaken concurrently with the major work. A shipowner can have other work performed while its vessel is undergoing repairs caused by a wrongdoer without being obliged to account, as it were, for extra costs incurred: see Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 302-304 where Viscount Jowitt accurately summarizes the authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Czarnikow Ltd v Koufos [1967] UKHL 4 ; [1969] 1 AC 350</tocase>
<text>63 In assessing damages for breach of contract the Court seeks to place the party who sustains a loss by reason of the breach in a position, so far as money can do it, which is the same as if the contract had been performed: Robinson v Harman (1848) 1 Ex 850 at 855 [154 ER 363 at 365]; Burns v M.A.N. Automotive (Aust) Pty Limited [1986] HCA 81 ; (1986) 161 CLR 653 at 658, 667, 672-673. Wilson, Deane and Dawson JJ explained that this general principle is limited by a rule laid down by the Court of Exchequor in Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Ex 341 at 354 [156 ER 145 at 151] (161 CLR at 667). That rule held that the damages recoverable from a breach of contract were such as might fairly and reasonably be considered either arising naturally, that is, according to the usual course of things, from such a breach of contract itself, as may be reasonably supposed to have been in the contemplation of both parties at the time they made the contract, as the probable result of the breach of it. Their Honours went on to say that these principles had been discussed by Gibbs J in Wenham v Ella [1972] HCA 43 ; (1972) 127 CLR 454 at 471-472 where he approved the following exposition of Lord Reid ( Czarnikow Ltd v Koufos [1967] UKHL 4 ; [1969] 1 AC 350 at 385):
 
 'The crucial question is whether, on the information available to the defendant when the contract was made, he should, or the reasonable man in his position would, have realized that such loss was sufficiently likely to result from the breach of contract to make it proper to hold that the loss flowed naturally from the breach or that loss of that kind should have been within his contemplation.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1</tocase>
<text>67 In The London Corporation [1935] P 70 at 77, Greer LJ, with whom Slesser LJ and Eve J agreed, said: 
 
 'Prima facie, the damage occasioned to a vessel is the cost of repairs - the cost of putting the vessel in the same condition as she was in before the collision, and to restore her in the hands of the owners to the same value as she would have had if the damage had never been done; and prima facie, the value of a damaged vessel is less by the cost of repairs than the value it would have if undamaged, though it is true that evidence may establish that the value of the vessel undamaged is exactly the same as her value after she had been damaged.' 
 
 (see too Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 3 per McPherson J, Andrews ACJ agreeing (at 1), 12 per Derrington J; Mackinnon McErlane Booker Pty Ltd v P&amp;O Australia Ltd [1988] VR 534 at 544 per Murphy J, Gray and JH Phillips JJ agreeing; Gardiner v Metcalf [1994] 2 NZLR 8 at 14 per Hardie Boys J; see too McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) [32-003], [32-007].)

73 In Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 9, McPherson J (Andrews ACJ agreeing) held that the time, trouble, expense and risks of repair and sale were ordinarily to be borne by a defendant. That principle is also of longstanding in cases in Admiralty. Dr Lushington said in The Gazelle (1844) 2 W. Rob (Adm) 279 at 281; 166 ER 759 at 760 that in cases of collision the suffering party is entitled to indemnification which is co-extensive with the damage, that is, to restitutio in integrum . He continued, in a passage part of which is cited in McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) at [32-006] as authoritative on the common law of assessment of the cost of repair (and see too The Munster (1896) 12 TLR 264 at 265-266 per Jeune P; Port Kembla Coal Terminal Ltd v Braverus Maritime Inc [2004] FCA 1211 ; (2004) 140 FCR 445 at 542 [487] and see too at 542-543 [484]-[488] per Hely J):
 
 'If the settlement of the indemnification be attended with any difficulty (and in those cases difficulties must and will frequently occur), the party in fault must bear the inconvenience. He has no right to fix this inconvenience upon the injured party; and if that party derives incidentally a greater benefit than mere indemnification, it arises only from the impossibility of otherwise effecting such indemnification without exposing him to some loss or burden, which the law will not place upon him.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Gardiner v Metcalf [1994] 2 NZLR 8</tocase>
<text>67 In The London Corporation [1935] P 70 at 77, Greer LJ, with whom Slesser LJ and Eve J agreed, said: 
 
 'Prima facie, the damage occasioned to a vessel is the cost of repairs - the cost of putting the vessel in the same condition as she was in before the collision, and to restore her in the hands of the owners to the same value as she would have had if the damage had never been done; and prima facie, the value of a damaged vessel is less by the cost of repairs than the value it would have if undamaged, though it is true that evidence may establish that the value of the vessel undamaged is exactly the same as her value after she had been damaged.' 
 
 (see too Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 3 per McPherson J, Andrews ACJ agreeing (at 1), 12 per Derrington J; Mackinnon McErlane Booker Pty Ltd v P&amp;O Australia Ltd [1988] VR 534 at 544 per Murphy J, Gray and JH Phillips JJ agreeing; Gardiner v Metcalf [1994] 2 NZLR 8 at 14 per Hardie Boys J; see too McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) [32-003], [32-007].)

72 Coole P remarked that whatever verbal formulations courts employed '...[i]n truth damages are in the end always a question of fact dependent on the particular circumstances' ( Gardiner v Metcalf [1994] 2 NZLR at 12).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/50.html</AustLII>
<text>86 The principle applicable to the right of a shipowner to recover from a wrongdoer the cost of hiring a substitute vessel while its own vessel is being repaired as a result of the tort, was stated by Viscount Sumner in SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196 at 205 (Lord Buckmaster agreeing at 205 and Lord Warrington of Clyffe gave a concurring speech at 211-212: see too per Scrutton LJ in The York [1929] P 178 at 184; The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n; 166 ER 155; cp: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 240-241 [1062] -1067] per Finn J; Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 300-302, 306, 313) thus:
 
 'If... the [plaintiff's] case is to be that the delay upset the general current of their trade, which had to be maintained in spite of it, I think that the extent and cost of this upset must be proved and must be causally connected with the collision in accordance with the ordinary rules of law as to damage. A ship's day is not like a unit of currency, always good for so many shillings. It has to be proved that, in doing the shipowner the wrong of laying his ship idle at the time in question, work, which she would otherwise have done during the time, went undone to his measurable loss or was only done by resorting to other expedients at a measurable outlay.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/75.html</AustLII>
<text>99 Because Consort did not become the legal or beneficial owner of the ship at the time at which the purchase money of USD 3.5m was paid to the vendor, the usual measure of damages in tort, being a comparison between the price paid and the value received, cannot be applied: Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215 at 223 per Gibbs CJ; see too at 232 per Murphy J, 245-246 per Wilson J, 253-255 per Brennan J.

100 I am of opinion that, for the same reasons, damages for any claim in contract in the circumstances of a case like the present cannot be assessed on that comparative basis. This is because J-Mac's contract obliged it to provide a prepurchase survey report which was prepared with reasonable care. It could be expected, as I have held, that Consort would either itself, or through a subsidiary, enter into a contract to purchase the ship. The damage which was in the reasonable contemplation of the parties at the time the prepuchase survey contract was entered into must have been the loss that would flow to whomever was the purchaser. If that were not Consort, then Consort could only have been contemplated to be able to recover a different loss that it suffered itself.

101 In Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215, Mr and Mrs Gould were the guarantors of their company, Gould Holdings Pty Limited. The Goulds had entered into a contract to buy property induced by fraudulent misrepresentations made by the vendor. The contract provided for the purchaser to be a company to be incorporated, which, in the event, became Gould Holdings. By the time of the trial, Gould Holdings was in liquidation. The liquidator gave evidence that he had no funds and there was no substantive prospect of the company bringing an action to recover damages for the deceit caused by the vendor. The High Court made it clear that it was not open to the Goulds, as shareholders, to sue for the loss which their company had suffered by purchasing the property at a price much greater than its true value. However, the Court held that the Goulds could recover damages for the loss which they personally had suffered and which was separate and distinct from the loss suffered by the company (157 CLR at 220, 228 per Gibbs CJ, 231-232 per Murphy J, 245-246 per Wilson J, 253-255 per Brennan J).

102 Even though the basis for recovery under s 82 of the Act is not governed by common law rules of causation or remoteness or by the measures of damages in contract or tort, I am of opinion that in the present case it is still necessary to identify whether Consort has suffered some loss distinct and separate from that of its wholly owned subsidiary, Rho Beta 7, by entering into and completing the contract of the purchase of the vessel.

103 Consort itself paid for all of the repairs both before January 2001, and after that time when it had assumed the legal and beneficial ownership of the ship. Accordingly, Consort claimed that it suffered the damage in respect of the cost of repairs and restoration as well as the charter hire of the substitute vessels.

104 Having regard to the evidence of the nature and extent of the corrosion and other damaged condition of the ship at the time of purchase, it is clear that if the vessel were to be operated satisfactorily and to be maintained in class, it would have been necessary for extensive repairs and restoration work to be undertaken immediately or in the foreseeable future following completion of the purchase. And, likewise, it would have been necessary for the vessel to be taken out of service while the majority of that work was undertaken so that a substitute vessel or vessels would need to be hired to take the Gazelle Coast's place in Consort's business operations.

113 While it may have been true that just as in Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215, the subsidiary (Rho Beta 7) may have had a right of action against the wrongdoer (J-Mac) the fact is that without the financial support of the parent, Consort, the right of action could not be realized. In the meantime, Consort had a business to run and needed the ship back in service to do so. Consort's ability to recover its loan, being the purchase price of the vessel, from Rho Beta 7 was substantively diminished by at least the loss in the value of the ship that had to be recognized in Rho Beta 7's books. That loss, may have been offset by the contingent asset of Rho Beta 7's cause of action against J-Mac but, as I have said, the exercise of that right depended upon Consort causing it to occur. Perhaps, that would have been a legally correct and advisable course, but, for the reasons given by Lord Macmillan, the course embarked on by Consort was also reasonably open to it.

114 The purpose for which Consort had engaged J-Mac's services was to receive advice as to the condition of the vessel so that it could be employed in Consort's business. Whether it was employed directly or through one of Consort's subsidiaries mattered not. Once the vessel required, in order to maintain class and efficacy as a trading vessel, the repairs and restoration work, they had to be effected if it were to be available in Consort's business. And, Consort had to spend directly or indirectly the money for those repairs or else it would have lost the whole of the investment made.

115 The position here is similar to that which Gibbs CJ pointed out in Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215 at 225:
 
 'However it would be quite unreal to determine the extent of the Goulds' loss on the basis that Gould Holdings would recover damages for deceit immediately after the date of settlement of the contract of sale. There was not the least likelihood that such an event would occur. Moreover, there was not the slightest intention that the amount owing by Gould Holdings should be repaid to the Goulds until the company had been trading profitably for some time.'

116 Gibbs CJ went on to say that the fact that the company might have had rights against the wrongdoer, did not mean that the Goulds were precluded from enforcing their own personal rights (157 CLR at 229). His Honour had held that the direct consequence of buying the resort was that Gould Holdings had to procure, in that case, the necessary funds to enable the business to carry on and for that purpose to obtain the necessary guarantees from the Goulds. It was foreseeable that that would occur and therefore it was not unreasonable for the Goulds to have given the guarantees.

117 The situation here is stronger in Consort's favour since it itself was the principal debtor to ANZ, and Rho Beta 7 was, in effect, a surety for the repayment by Consort of the loan.

118 Mr McInnes said that in January 2001 ownership of the vessel was transferred back to Consort and the loan and security documentation was amended. He did not elaborate on precisely how that amendment occurred but I infer that the amendments were to reflect the fact that Rho Beta 7 no longer had any part in the arrangements between Consort and ANZ for the provision of funds with which to first, acquire and, secondly, repair and restore the vessel. He said:
 
 'Effectively no money changed hands between Consort and Rho Beta 7. Rho Beta 7 now has no assets.'

120 There is, of course, in a situation such as the present, a danger that by awarding Consort the damages claimed, J-Mac could be put in the position of having to pay Rho Beta 7 the same damages at a later time if other proceedings had been taken by Rho Beta 7. But, Mr McInnes swore that Rho Beta 7 had no assets. I must therefore infer that the asset comprised in its right of action against J-Mac was no longer available to Rho Beta 7 at 21 July 2005 when he swore his affidavit. Again, the evidence is not in the most satisfactory state, but I am of opinion that even if Rho Beta 7 retained at that time the causes of action it may have had against J-Mac for its prepurchase survey reports, in Rho Beta 7's hands that right of action was as valueless as Gould Holdings' right of action was in Gould v Vaggelas [1985] HCA 75 ; (1984) 157 CLR 215 at 228, 232, 258. The likelihood of Consort recovering anything from Rho Beta 7 in respect of the losses Consort has sustained is, on the evidence before me, negligible.

121 It follows, that Consort has established that it has suffered loss and damage in the sum claimed because any cause of action it may have against Rho Beta 7 is valueless and it, Consort, suffered the loss and damage of the cost of repairs, restoration and the hire of substitute vessels itself. Accordingly, judgment should be entered for the full amount claimed together with interest on the basis which I have indicated.

122 The amount for which judgment will be entered is based on the following calculations as to interest and currency conversion in a calculation prepared by the solicitors for Consort:
 
 (a) expenditure in the schedule in Australian dollars $ 2,547,384.34
 (b) expenditure in the schedule of USD 297,143 
 converted at the respective dates of payment to
 the Australian dollar equivalent $ 495,743.14
 
 
 
 (c) interest item by item from repair payment date
 to today $ 1,287,112.73 
 
 $ 4,330,240.21 
 
 
 


 I certify that the preceding one hundred and twenty-two (122) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares. 


Associate: 

Dated: 3 July 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr GA Thompson SC with T Sullivan 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Thynne &amp; Macartney 
 
 Respondent: No Appearance 
 
 Date of Hearing: 13 June 2006 and 16 June 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 July 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/833.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Ex 341</tocase>
<text>63 In assessing damages for breach of contract the Court seeks to place the party who sustains a loss by reason of the breach in a position, so far as money can do it, which is the same as if the contract had been performed: Robinson v Harman (1848) 1 Ex 850 at 855 [154 ER 363 at 365]; Burns v M.A.N. Automotive (Aust) Pty Limited [1986] HCA 81 ; (1986) 161 CLR 653 at 658, 667, 672-673. Wilson, Deane and Dawson JJ explained that this general principle is limited by a rule laid down by the Court of Exchequor in Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Ex 341 at 354 [156 ER 145 at 151] (161 CLR at 667). That rule held that the damages recoverable from a breach of contract were such as might fairly and reasonably be considered either arising naturally, that is, according to the usual course of things, from such a breach of contract itself, as may be reasonably supposed to have been in the contemplation of both parties at the time they made the contract, as the probable result of the breach of it. Their Honours went on to say that these principles had been discussed by Gibbs J in Wenham v Ella [1972] HCA 43 ; (1972) 127 CLR 454 at 471-472 where he approved the following exposition of Lord Reid ( Czarnikow Ltd v Koufos [1967] UKHL 4 ; [1969] 1 AC 350 at 385):
 
 'The crucial question is whether, on the information available to the defendant when the contract was made, he should, or the reasonable man in his position would, have realized that such loss was sufficiently likely to result from the breach of contract to make it proper to hold that the loss flowed naturally from the breach or that loss of that kind should have been within his contemplation.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Haines v Bendall [1991] HCA 15 ; (1991) 172 CLR 60</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/15.html</AustLII>
<text>64 The settled principle governing the assessment of compensatory damages, whether in actions of tort or contract, is that the injured party should receive compensation in a sum which, so far as money can do, will put that party in the same position as it would have been in if the tort had not been committed or the contract had been performed: Haines v Bendall [1991] HCA 15 ; (1991) 172 CLR 60 at 63 per Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey and Gaudron JJ. As their Honours noted, compensation is the cardinal principle and the 'universal' rule is that a plaintiff cannot recover more than it has lost (172 CLR at 63).

65 I find that when the prepurchase survey contract was made it was in the contemplation of the parties, and of a reasonable person in the position of J-Mac, that Consort would be likely to suffer loss if the survey results were reported negligently. Consort's loss would be that it had purchased the vessel at a price that was far greater than its true value or alternatively would have to pay for the cost of repair and restoration so that it would be brought to a condition conformable with that in the advice given by J-Mac. And, I find that a reasonable person in the position of J-Mac would have realized that Consort would be likely to be exposed to such losses either directly, were it to acquire ownership of the vessel itself, or indirectly by causing the vessel to be acquired by a wholly owned subsidiary using Consort's financial support or resources to make the purchase.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Hebridean Coast [1961] AC 545</tocase>
<text>87 In the Hebridean Coast [1961] AC 545 at 576-578, Lord Reid applied there principles to a case where a government corporation claimed damages for the detention of a nonprofitearning vessel while she was being repaired. His Lordship distinguished this from the case of a profit-earning ship where the plaintiff had to prove '... the probability that she would have earned so much money if her owner could have used her' ([1961] AC at 577). With a nonprofit-earning ship, if no harm were proved apart from the mere fact that the owner is deprived of her services during the period of repairs, the Court awards damages based on interest and depreciation on the value of the ship ([1961] AC at 578 per Lord Reid, 580 per Lords Morton of Henryton and Tucker, 583 per Lord Morris of Borth-y-Gest; The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596). In Admiralty Commissioners v SS Susquehanna [1926] AC 655 at 664, Lord Sumner said that in such an assessment 'the practice of treating the injured ship, by a sort of personification, as a separate claimant is too inveterate to be disturbed now.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astonland Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/54.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In tort, the measure of damages is that sum which would be sufficient to place the innocent party in the position it would have had had the tort not been committed. Frequently, in a case like the present where there is no contractual expectation loss ( Gates v City Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [1986] HCA 3 ; (1986) 160 CLR 1 at 12) courts take a similar approach to determining the loss or damage as I have just taken on the contractual measure which is appropriate in this case, namely the difference between the price and the true value: see Potts v Miller [1940] HCA 43 ; (1940) 64 CLR 282. However, that measure of damages is treated by the courts as a flexible rule of practice, which may not be appropriate to the quantification of damage in each case ( HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astonland Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640 at 656-658 [35] - [37] ).

96 The ultimate award, including interest, could, of course, be discounted back to reflect it as at 29 July 1999 when loss was incurred on completion of the purchase. I am of opinion that such a method would accurately reflect the damage, excluding interest, suffered by the purchaser. But, since I have evidence of the actual incurring of expenses and the appropriate quantum of interest to be awarded, it is sufficient to make the award as I propose ( HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astoland [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640 at 658-659 [38] - [40] , [47]). Doing the best I can, I find that such an award provides a just measure of compensation.

105 Upon purchase, Rho Beta 7 acquired an immediate right to sue J-Mac for the whole of those damages because the vessel at that time needed the repairs and restoration work to be done. There was no hidden contingency of the kind found in Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 at 401-402 [26] where someone else's discretion might in the future be exercised to change the purchaser's position. The damage to the vessel was not hidden and the need to repair and restore it was ineluctable ( HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astonland Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640 at 655 [30] ). Rho Beta 7 had been induced by J-Mac's negligence and misleading conduct, to pay the purchase price to the French vendor. And, when in early 2001 Consort chose to become the legal and beneficial owner of the Gazelle Coast , it knew the vessel's true value and accurately its then state of repair.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kenny &amp; Good Pty Limited v MGICA (1992) Ltd [1999] HCA 25 ; (1999) 199 CLR 413</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/25.html</AustLII>
<text>58 I find that had J-Mac properly reported in a prepurchase survey to Consort that the vessel had the deficiencies or a number of them which have been admitted as existing in the defence, Consort would not have purchased the vessel. In arriving at these findings I have also had regard to the evidence in the affidavits of Messrs Pasma, Woodall and Barrie as well as to so much of the affidavits of Messrs Perrott, Bleasdale, Dowell and McInnes and Capt Adhikari as was read. Accordingly, Consort's claim for damages is to be approached upon the basis that the cases have described as a 'no transaction' case ( Kenny &amp; Good Pty Limited v MGICA (1992) Ltd [1999] HCA 25 ; (1999) 199 CLR 413).

59 Thus, in Kenny &amp; Good Pty Limited v MGICA (1992) Ltd [1999] HCA 25 ; (1999) 199 CLR 413 at 457-458 [119] - [120] Kirby and Callinan JJ held that if a correct valuation had been given, there would have been no loss suffered by the mortgage insurer because it would not have provided mortgage insurance at all. They said that this approach gave content to, or defined, the contractual obligation to exercise reasonable care and the tortuous duty of care. It did this by having regard to the kind of loss or damage in respect of which the contract breaker or tortfeasor was required to exercise reasonable care.

60 In that case the valuation included a representation that the property was a suitable investment for trust funds, on the basis of the valuation, for a term of 3-5 years. Kirby and Callinan JJ said that the valuer had an obligation and a duty in giving the valuation to exercise reasonable care to enable the mortgage insurer to decide whether to enter into an insurance transaction at all. The obligation or duty was breached if an accurate representation would have suggested that the mortgage insurer should not have entered the transaction (the other justices took a similar approach: 199 CLR at 425-426 [19]-[21] per Gaudron J, 447 [83] and 449 [92] per Gummow J; but see per McHugh J at 431 [35]). The valuer was held liable for the whole of the loss which the mortgage insurer suffered, some of which resulted from a later fall in the property market.

61 Here, the advice sought from the professional surveyor related to the condition of the ship and its appropriateness for purchase by Consort. It was clearly within the contemplation of Consort and J-Mac at the time their contract was entered into that Consort would expose itself to financial loss if it acted on J-Mac's advice and J-Mac's prepurchase survey were inaccuracte. Such loss could occur if Consort purchased the ship itself or caused, as is usual in such commercial transactions, a subsidiary to be incorporated for the purposes of acquiring and holding the asset and the ship turned out not to be sound in respects the subject of the opinion provided by J-Mac.

62 The loss could be suffered by reason that, first, the price paid for the ship might be greater than its true worth or secondly, the cost to repair the ship, so as to bring it to the condition where it might operate and possess the characteristics the subject of the negligent opinion, was substantial. Who suffered that loss is a fundamental issue in this matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>distinguished</class>
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/3.html</AustLII>
<text>66 Immediately upon entry into the contract of purchase, Consort was exposed to a risk of loss. But risk of loss is not a category of loss ( Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 at 405-406 [37] ). By entering the purchase contract which permitted Consort to nominate the buyer, Consort did not then suffer damage. Damage would be suffered by whomever was the buyer i.e. Consort or its nominee, in the event Rho Beta 7 on completion, when the purchase price was paid.

105 Upon purchase, Rho Beta 7 acquired an immediate right to sue J-Mac for the whole of those damages because the vessel at that time needed the repairs and restoration work to be done. There was no hidden contingency of the kind found in Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 at 401-402 [26] where someone else's discretion might in the future be exercised to change the purchaser's position. The damage to the vessel was not hidden and the need to repair and restore it was ineluctable ( HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astonland Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640 at 655 [30] ). Rho Beta 7 had been induced by J-Mac's negligence and misleading conduct, to pay the purchase price to the French vendor. And, when in early 2001 Consort chose to become the legal and beneficial owner of the Gazelle Coast , it knew the vessel's true value and accurately its then state of repair.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Port Kembla Coal Terminal Ltd v Braverus Maritime Inc [2004] FCA 1211 ; (2004) 140 FCR 445</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1211.html</AustLII>
<text>73 In Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 9, McPherson J (Andrews ACJ agreeing) held that the time, trouble, expense and risks of repair and sale were ordinarily to be borne by a defendant. That principle is also of longstanding in cases in Admiralty. Dr Lushington said in The Gazelle (1844) 2 W. Rob (Adm) 279 at 281; 166 ER 759 at 760 that in cases of collision the suffering party is entitled to indemnification which is co-extensive with the damage, that is, to restitutio in integrum . He continued, in a passage part of which is cited in McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) at [32-006] as authoritative on the common law of assessment of the cost of repair (and see too The Munster (1896) 12 TLR 264 at 265-266 per Jeune P; Port Kembla Coal Terminal Ltd v Braverus Maritime Inc [2004] FCA 1211 ; (2004) 140 FCR 445 at 542 [487] and see too at 542-543 [484]-[488] per Hely J):
 
 'If the settlement of the indemnification be attended with any difficulty (and in those cases difficulties must and will frequently occur), the party in fault must bear the inconvenience. He has no right to fix this inconvenience upon the injured party; and if that party derives incidentally a greater benefit than mere indemnification, it arises only from the impossibility of otherwise effecting such indemnification without exposing him to some loss or burden, which the law will not place upon him.'

74 The principle identified by these authorities establishes that a tortfeasor must bear the cost of replacement or repair of the plaintiff's property where that has been damaged or destroyed by the tortfeasor's negligence. And the quantum of that cost is not diminished by any betterment of the plaintiff's property as a result of the repairs which the plaintiff achieves provided that the plaintiff does not act extravagantly: Port Kembla Coal Terminal Ltd v Braverus Maritime Inc [2004] FCA 1211 ; (2004) 140 FCR 445 at 542 [485] - [486] per Hely J.

75 The third basis upon which damages fall to be assessed in the present case is that provided pursuant to s 82 of the Act. That measure is one which is flexible so as to be appropriately adapted to the circumstances of compensating a person who suffers loss or damage by conduct of another person that was done in contravention of s 52 of the Act.

76 Here, Consort argues that it suffered loss by reason of J-Mac's contravention of s 52 because it was exposed to being in default under its financing arrangements with ANZ. It had caused its subsidiary to acquire the ship at a price far greater than its true worth. Rho Beta 7 had no assets other than the ship itself with which to repay the loan provided by Consort. Accordingly, Rho Beta 7 had a loan of USD 3.5m and its only asset was worth only half of that amount. Consort was obliged to maintain the asset value of its subsidiary so as to remain within its own covenants to ANZ. Thus, Consort argued that since it wished to run the ship in connection with its business, and not be in default under its loan facility it was necessary for Consort to pay for the repairs and restoration work and hire of substitute vessels. The ship had to be in a condition where it could keep its class certificates and registrations. And, it needed to be repaired and restored so as to be able to operate with appropriate efficiency in the conduct of Consort's business for which it had been purchased. Thus, Consort was exposed to the necessity of either itself paying those costs or alternatively of financing them.

77 I am satisfied that the repairs performed to the hydraulics of the vessel's cranes by Perrott Engineering Pty Limited in November 1999 were necessary and the sum claimed for them is reasonable.

78 In the period between July 2000 and September 2000 major repairs and restoration work were undertaken when the ship was at the Tropical Reef Shipyard. Further repairs were carried out in 2004. I accept Mr McInnes' evidence as to the circumstances in which the various repairs of the vessel were undertaken between 1999 and 2004 in respect of which damages are claimed in the schedule. I am of opinion that his evidence establishes that Consort acted reasonably in the way in which it went about arranging for and paying for the repairs and the hire of substitute vessels. Consort paid hire for a replacement vessels during that period.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Potts v Miller [1940] HCA 43 ; (1940) 64 CLR 282</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1940/43.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In tort, the measure of damages is that sum which would be sufficient to place the innocent party in the position it would have had had the tort not been committed. Frequently, in a case like the present where there is no contractual expectation loss ( Gates v City Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [1986] HCA 3 ; (1986) 160 CLR 1 at 12) courts take a similar approach to determining the loss or damage as I have just taken on the contractual measure which is appropriate in this case, namely the difference between the price and the true value: see Potts v Miller [1940] HCA 43 ; (1940) 64 CLR 282. However, that measure of damages is treated by the courts as a flexible rule of practice, which may not be appropriate to the quantification of damage in each case ( HTW Valuers (Central Qld) Pty Ltd v Astonland Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 54 ; (2004) 217 CLR 640 at 656-658 [35] - [37] ).

92 Consort claims damages on two alternate bases. First, it says that the total amount claimed is the equivalent of the damage suffered at the time of purchase, being the difference between the price and the true value of the Gazelle Coast ( Potts v Miller [1940] HCA 43 ; (1940) 64 CLR 282). Thus, it seeks interest on that sum from 29 July 1999. Secondly, Consort says that the amounts are claimed as damages being the expense to which it has been put in restoring the Gazelle Coast to the condition she ought to have been in had she been as J-Mac's survey report had represented.

93 The problem with the first basis is that it uses the actual costs of repair and restoration work, together with charter hire incurred at various times over the five years succeeding the purchase. No evidence has been given that repair costs remained constant in that period. And the evidence shows that charter rates were different: in mid 2000 they were USD 4600 per day while in late 2003, when the CEC Light was fixed, they were USD 5000. There is no evidence of the rates at July 1999. Nor has Consort given evidence of the net present value at July 1999 of the damages claimed.

94 If Consort were to receive an award calculated on the first basis, it would be likely to achieve more than the true measure of its loss if interest were then awarded from July 1999. Charter rates were different and the market for those rates varies over time. Mr Dowell identified an average fixing rate in the June quarter of 2000 at USD 4130, albeit that he deemed USD 4600 as a realistic rate for a replacement ship.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196</tocase>
<text>86 The principle applicable to the right of a shipowner to recover from a wrongdoer the cost of hiring a substitute vessel while its own vessel is being repaired as a result of the tort, was stated by Viscount Sumner in SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196 at 205 (Lord Buckmaster agreeing at 205 and Lord Warrington of Clyffe gave a concurring speech at 211-212: see too per Scrutton LJ in The York [1929] P 178 at 184; The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n; 166 ER 155; cp: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 240-241 [1062] -1067] per Finn J; Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 300-302, 306, 313) thus:
 
 'If... the [plaintiff's] case is to be that the delay upset the general current of their trade, which had to be maintained in spite of it, I think that the extent and cost of this upset must be proved and must be causally connected with the collision in accordance with the ordinary rules of law as to damage. A ship's day is not like a unit of currency, always good for so many shillings. It has to be proved that, in doing the shipowner the wrong of laying his ship idle at the time in question, work, which she would otherwise have done during the time, went undone to his measurable loss or was only done by resorting to other expedients at a measurable outlay.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>The Gazelle (1844) 2 W. Rob (Adm) 279 at 281</tocase>
<text>73 In Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 9, McPherson J (Andrews ACJ agreeing) held that the time, trouble, expense and risks of repair and sale were ordinarily to be borne by a defendant. That principle is also of longstanding in cases in Admiralty. Dr Lushington said in The Gazelle (1844) 2 W. Rob (Adm) 279 at 281; 166 ER 759 at 760 that in cases of collision the suffering party is entitled to indemnification which is co-extensive with the damage, that is, to restitutio in integrum . He continued, in a passage part of which is cited in McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) at [32-006] as authoritative on the common law of assessment of the cost of repair (and see too The Munster (1896) 12 TLR 264 at 265-266 per Jeune P; Port Kembla Coal Terminal Ltd v Braverus Maritime Inc [2004] FCA 1211 ; (2004) 140 FCR 445 at 542 [487] and see too at 542-543 [484]-[488] per Hely J):
 
 'If the settlement of the indemnification be attended with any difficulty (and in those cases difficulties must and will frequently occur), the party in fault must bear the inconvenience. He has no right to fix this inconvenience upon the injured party; and if that party derives incidentally a greater benefit than mere indemnification, it arises only from the impossibility of otherwise effecting such indemnification without exposing him to some loss or burden, which the law will not place upon him.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596</tocase>
<text>87 In the Hebridean Coast [1961] AC 545 at 576-578, Lord Reid applied there principles to a case where a government corporation claimed damages for the detention of a nonprofitearning vessel while she was being repaired. His Lordship distinguished this from the case of a profit-earning ship where the plaintiff had to prove '... the probability that she would have earned so much money if her owner could have used her' ([1961] AC at 577). With a nonprofit-earning ship, if no harm were proved apart from the mere fact that the owner is deprived of her services during the period of repairs, the Court awards damages based on interest and depreciation on the value of the ship ([1961] AC at 578 per Lord Reid, 580 per Lords Morton of Henryton and Tucker, 583 per Lord Morris of Borth-y-Gest; The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596). In Admiralty Commissioners v SS Susquehanna [1926] AC 655 at 664, Lord Sumner said that in such an assessment 'the practice of treating the injured ship, by a sort of personification, as a separate claimant is too inveterate to be disturbed now.'

88 And in Anthanasopoulos v Moseley [2001] NSWCA 266 ; (2001) 52 NSWLR 262 the Court of Appeal of the Supreme Court of New South Wales allowed car owners (or their insurer) who were deprived of the use of their vehicles to recover the cost of hire of a substitute vehicle while theirs underwent repair even though they were not out of pocket for that hire. That Court applied The Greta Holme [1897] AC 596 on the basis that injury to non income producing property which deprives a party of the use of the property is compensable and held that the claim was for general, not special damages (see 52 NSWLR at 276 [76] per Ipp A-JA; see too at 273 [54], 274 [58] per Beazley JA).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>The London Corporation [1935] P 70</tocase>
<text>67 In The London Corporation [1935] P 70 at 77, Greer LJ, with whom Slesser LJ and Eve J agreed, said: 
 
 'Prima facie, the damage occasioned to a vessel is the cost of repairs - the cost of putting the vessel in the same condition as she was in before the collision, and to restore her in the hands of the owners to the same value as she would have had if the damage had never been done; and prima facie, the value of a damaged vessel is less by the cost of repairs than the value it would have if undamaged, though it is true that evidence may establish that the value of the vessel undamaged is exactly the same as her value after she had been damaged.' 
 
 (see too Davidson v JS Gilbert Fabrications Pty Ltd [1986] 1 Qd R 1 at 3 per McPherson J, Andrews ACJ agreeing (at 1), 12 per Derrington J; Mackinnon McErlane Booker Pty Ltd v P&amp;O Australia Ltd [1988] VR 534 at 544 per Murphy J, Gray and JH Phillips JJ agreeing; Gardiner v Metcalf [1994] 2 NZLR 8 at 14 per Hardie Boys J; see too McGregor on Damages (17 th edn) [32-003], [32-007].)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>The York [1929] P 178</tocase>
<text>68 Because, the cost of repair is adopted as being equivalent to the diminution in the ship's value, it is immaterial that the repairs themselves are never executed: The York [1929] P 178 at 184-185 per Scrutton LJ with whom Greer LJ agreed at 187.

69 For the purchaser of the Gazelle Coast , that loss was the difference between the price paid and the actual value of the ship. Mr Dowell, an expert shipbroker, has assessed that difference at around USD 1.75m (i.e. that the vessel was really worth, at the time of its purchase, half of the purchase price). He arrived at that valuation on the basis that the cost of repairs, restoration work and substitute vessel hire actually incurred by Consort were necessary to bring the vessel to the standard at which it would have been worth the purchase price of USD 3.5m accounted for the difference in value. He considered that the purchase price was a proper reflection of market value for the vessel had it been in the sound condition which J-Mac's reports erroneously said it was.

70 There is, however, in this scenario the complication to which I referred earlier, namely that although Consort entered into the contract of purchase, and was liable for the price, it exercised its right to nominate Rho Beta 7 as the purchaser. Thus, when title to the vessel passed to Rho Beta 7, as I will discuss below, it, rather than Consort, suffered the loss of USD 1.75m.

86 The principle applicable to the right of a shipowner to recover from a wrongdoer the cost of hiring a substitute vessel while its own vessel is being repaired as a result of the tort, was stated by Viscount Sumner in SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196 at 205 (Lord Buckmaster agreeing at 205 and Lord Warrington of Clyffe gave a concurring speech at 211-212: see too per Scrutton LJ in The York [1929] P 178 at 184; The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n; 166 ER 155; cp: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 240-241 [1062] -1067] per Finn J; Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 300-302, 306, 313) thus:
 
 'If... the [plaintiff's] case is to be that the delay upset the general current of their trade, which had to be maintained in spite of it, I think that the extent and cost of this upset must be proved and must be causally connected with the collision in accordance with the ordinary rules of law as to damage. A ship's day is not like a unit of currency, always good for so many shillings. It has to be proved that, in doing the shipowner the wrong of laying his ship idle at the time in question, work, which she would otherwise have done during the time, went undone to his measurable loss or was only done by resorting to other expedients at a measurable outlay.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n</tocase>
<text>86 The principle applicable to the right of a shipowner to recover from a wrongdoer the cost of hiring a substitute vessel while its own vessel is being repaired as a result of the tort, was stated by Viscount Sumner in SS Strathfillan v SS Ikala [1929] AC 196 at 205 (Lord Buckmaster agreeing at 205 and Lord Warrington of Clyffe gave a concurring speech at 211-212: see too per Scrutton LJ in The York [1929] P 178 at 184; The Yorkshireman (1827) 2 Hagg Adm 30n; 166 ER 155; cp: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 240-241 [1062] -1067] per Finn J; Carslogie Steamship Co Ltd v Royal Norwegian Government [1951] UKHL 4 ; [1952] AC 292 at 300-302, 306, 313) thus:
 
 'If... the [plaintiff's] case is to be that the delay upset the general current of their trade, which had to be maintained in spite of it, I think that the extent and cost of this upset must be proved and must be causally connected with the collision in accordance with the ordinary rules of law as to damage. A ship's day is not like a unit of currency, always good for so many shillings. It has to be proved that, in doing the shipowner the wrong of laying his ship idle at the time in question, work, which she would otherwise have done during the time, went undone to his measurable loss or was only done by resorting to other expedients at a measurable outlay.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Unity Insurance Brokers Pty Ltd v Rocco Pezzano Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 38 ; (1998) 192 CLR 603</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/38.html</AustLII>
<text>110 In Unity Insurance Brokers Pty Ltd v Rocco Pezzano Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 38 ; (1998) 192 CLR 603 at 617-618 [36] - [41] per McHugh J, 638 [97(2)] per Kirby J and 654 [134] per Hayne J, this principle was applied to a case of negligent advice in contract or tort.

111 Here, Consort would not have undertaken the borrowing from ANZ or engaged in the whole exercise of procuring the acquisition of the Gazelle Coast if J-Mac had given accurate prepurchase survey reports to it. By the time the inaccuracy of J-Mac's reports became known, Consort was in the invidious position of being obligated to ANZ to maintain the value of the ship and Rho Beta 7. Not only that, Consort needed the ship for the purposes of its own business; after all that was the very purpose of the acquisition in the first place. Rho Beta 7 had no money or resources other than as may have been able to be provided by Consort.

112 As a matter of commonsense, without Consort's financial support, Rho Beta 7 could not have raised any money on the security of the ship with which to effect the repairs and restoration work which were needed. That is because the ship was worth about half of what Rho Beta 7 owed to Consort on the loan of the purchase price. The ship was mortgaged to ANZ and Rho Beta 7 had given a fixed and floating charge to ANZ. Its borrowing capacity against its only substantive asset was non existent. That is because Rho Beta 7's net asset position was one in which its liabilities exceeded its assets by about 100%, once the value of the ship was written down to half the purchase price. As a consequence, if repairs and restoration work were to be effected, they could only be by Consort using its financial resources to borrow the money and thereafter seeking to recoup itself from the wrongdoer who had place it into that position, namely J-Mac.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wenham v Ella [1972] HCA 43 ; (1972) 127 CLR 454</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/43.html</AustLII>
<text>63 In assessing damages for breach of contract the Court seeks to place the party who sustains a loss by reason of the breach in a position, so far as money can do it, which is the same as if the contract had been performed: Robinson v Harman (1848) 1 Ex 850 at 855 [154 ER 363 at 365]; Burns v M.A.N. Automotive (Aust) Pty Limited [1986] HCA 81 ; (1986) 161 CLR 653 at 658, 667, 672-673. Wilson, Deane and Dawson JJ explained that this general principle is limited by a rule laid down by the Court of Exchequor in Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Ex 341 at 354 [156 ER 145 at 151] (161 CLR at 667). That rule held that the damages recoverable from a breach of contract were such as might fairly and reasonably be considered either arising naturally, that is, according to the usual course of things, from such a breach of contract itself, as may be reasonably supposed to have been in the contemplation of both parties at the time they made the contract, as the probable result of the breach of it. Their Honours went on to say that these principles had been discussed by Gibbs J in Wenham v Ella [1972] HCA 43 ; (1972) 127 CLR 454 at 471-472 where he approved the following exposition of Lord Reid ( Czarnikow Ltd v Koufos [1967] UKHL 4 ; [1969] 1 AC 350 at 385):
 
 'The crucial question is whether, on the information available to the defendant when the contract was made, he should, or the reasonable man in his position would, have realized that such loss was sufficiently likely to result from the breach of contract to make it proper to hold that the loss flowed naturally from the breach or that loss of that kind should have been within his contemplation.'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>