<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Elias v Pascoe (Trustee), in the matter of Milad Elias (Bankrupt) [2006] FCA 802 (27 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/802.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 194</tocase>
<text>9 The principles which ordinarily govern the exercise of the Court's discretion to award costs pursuant to s 43 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) where an applicant no longer wishes to proceed were identified in Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Ltd (1993) 44 FCR 194 at 201. Those principles, so far as presently relevant, may be summarised as follows. First, the Court should be ready to facilitate the conclusion of the proceeding by making a costs order. Secondly, although the Court will not ordinarily seek to determine the likely outcome of a hypothetical trial, it may be more ready to do so where the issues are simple and issues of credit do not arise. Thirdly, it will ordinarily be appropriate for the Court to consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the parties in instituting and defending the proceedings and it may be appropriate for the Court to consider whether unreasonable conduct of the respondent precipitated the commencement of the proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Byron v Southern Star Group Pty Ltd (1997) 73 FCR 264</tocase>
<text>14 The Bankruptcy Act recognises that the Court may extend the time for compliance with a bankruptcy notice where proceedings to set aside the judgment in respect of which the notice was issued have been instituted by the debtor (s 41(6A)(a)). The power to extend time for compliance is in aid of the power to set aside the notice itself should the judgment ultimately be set aside ( Byron v Southern Star Group Pty Ltd (1997) 73 FCR 264 at 268). The judgment upon which the bankruptcy notice was founded has now been set aside. I conclude that Mr George Elias acted reasonably in instituting this proceeding.

15 The trustee was entitled to serve the bankruptcy notice as no stay of execution of the District Court judgment had been sought (s 40(1)(g) of the Bankruptcy Act ). I am not satisfied that he acted unreasonably in doing so. However, he must be assumed to have understood that, if the judgment were set aside on appeal, the judgment debt on which the bankruptcy notice was founded would no longer exist and the notice would be liable to be set aside.

16 The judgment of the Court of Appeal setting aside the judgment of the District Court was unanimous. One member of the Court of Appeal was implicitly critical of the conduct of the trustee in opposing a stay of proceedings in the District Court to allow the s 139ZQ notice to be challenged in the Federal Magistrates Court (Giles JA at [51]). Another member of the Court of Appeal considered that there was 'some plausibility' in the contention that the District Court proceeding should have been stayed but found it unnecessary to consider the issue (Santow JA at [111]). The third member (Bryson JA) of the Court of Appeal also found it unnecessary to consider the issue. However, all members of the Court of Appeal concluded that the District Court erred in entering summary judgment against Mr George Elias. I infer that the District Court adopted this course at the invitation of the trustee. I incline to the view that, in this sense, unreasonable conduct of the trustee precipitated the events that led to the institution of this proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Elias v Pascoe [2006] NSWCA 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2006/110.html</AustLII>
<text>8 On 9 May 2006 the New South Wales Court of Appeal granted Mr George Elias leave to appeal against the judgment of the District Court, allowed the appeal and set aside the judgment ( Elias v Pascoe [2006] NSWCA 110).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Principal Strategic Options Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 664</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/664.html</AustLII>
<text>10 In my view, the above principles also ordinarily guide the exercise of the Court's discretion in comparable circumstances to award costs pursuant to s 32 of the Bankruptcy Act . As I observed in Principal Strategic Options Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 664 at [17] - [18] , s 32 gives the Court a very wide discretion with respect to orders for costs, albeit that the discretion must be exercised judicially.

11 Mr George Elias submitted that the trustee should pay his costs of this proceeding because the trustee had acted precipitously in serving the bankruptcy notice. He argued that, once the holding summons for leave to appeal had been filed, it was inherently risky to serve the bankruptcy notice; the risk having eventuated, the trustee should pay the costs reasonably incurred by him with respect to the bankruptcy notice.

12 The trustee submitted that as no stay of the judgment of the District Court had been obtained, or indeed sought, he had acted reasonably and properly in serving the bankruptcy notice and in respect of the conduct of this proceeding.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>