<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Thirteenth Corp Pty Ltd v State (with Addendum dated 2 August) [2006] FCA 979 (2 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/979.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729</tocase>
<text>33 By contrast, there is no res judicata nor, as I understand the law, Anshun estoppel, when the earlier proceedings have been discontinued. In relation to res judicata at least, the same conclusion applies when the earlier proceedings have been dismissed on account of default in compliance with orders for discovery ( Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729), on account of default in the provision of particulars ( Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115) or for want of prosecution ( Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291; Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255). The question with which these cases do not deal, however, is whether, notwithstanding that there would be no res judicata , it might nonetheless be regarded as vexatious, and in that sense as an abuse of process, for a moving party, by his or her own default, to allow proceedings to be terminated, without adjudication, to his or her disadvantage, and then to bring new proceedings seeking the same remedy on closely related grounds.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Bell Wholesale Co Pty Ltd v Gates Export Corporation (No 2) (1984) 2 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>47 I turn then to the respondents' application for security for costs. The power to order security arises under s 56(1) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), the discretionary exercise of which is not limited to the particular circumstances set out in O 28 r 3(1) of the Rules of Court: Bell Wholesale Co Pty Ltd v Gates Export Corporation (No 2) (1984) 2 FCR 1, 2-3. Mr Frenkel drew my attention to the list of considerations referred to in Equity Access Limited v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972. Those matters are the applicant's chances of success, whether the order would shut out the applicant from pursuing its claim, whether the applicant's impecuniosity arose out of the breaches alleged against the respondent, the public interest, discretionary matters peculiar to the present case and the risk that the applicant would not be able to satisfy an order for costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Clout v Klein [2001] QSC 401</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2001/401.html</AustLII>
<text>35 The proposition that the later proceedings in Deangrove might have been regarded as an abuse of process not in the sense of demonstrating contumely but in the sense of an attempt to relitigate a matter which had previously been the subject of a final order disposing of identical proceedings appears not to have been the way the matter was put to Sackville J. That proposition was put to Holmes J in Clout v Klein [2001] QSC 401. There the earlier proceeding had been terminated not by a self-executing order but by a direct order of a Judge of the court. The ground which sustained the order, however, was that the plaintiffs in that proceeding had failed to comply with an order for security for costs. His Honour referred (at [44]) to some cases in which the application of the Anshun principle to situations in which there had been no adjudication had been doubted; doubts which, in my respectful view, would almost always be regarded as well-founded. However, on the facts, his Honour held that it was not unreasonable for the plaintiff which was common to both proceedings not to have raised the relevant claim in the earlier proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Deangrove Pty Ltd (Rec &amp; Mgrs Aptd) v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2001] FCA 173 ; (2001) 108 FCR 77</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/173.html</AustLII>
<text>34 I think the answer to that question is: not necessarily. In Deangrove Pty Ltd (Rec &amp; Mgrs Aptd) v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2001] FCA 173 ; (2001) 108 FCR 77, one of a number of points which Sackville J had to decide arose from the circumstance that the applicants had, in a previous proceeding, several times failed to comply with an order that they file a Statement of Claim, in consequence of which that proceeding was dismissed. A few months later, the instant proceeding was commenced by the same applicants against the same respondent as had been parties to the earlier proceeding. Identical relief was claimed. Sackville J dealt with the argument that the later proceeding amounted to an abuse of process as follows (108 FCR at 82-83):
 
 
 "[21] Mr Bell relied on a line of English authority in holding that it is an abuse of process for a litigant to commence fresh proceedings founded on the same cause of action as previous proceedings, where the previous proceedings have been terminated in consequence of the litigant's failure to comply with self-executing orders (which are known as "unless orders" in England). Mr Bell relied particularly on Janov v Morris [1981] 3 All ER 780. In that case, an action for damages for breach of contract was dismissed in consequence of an order that, unless the plaintiff issued and served a summons for directions by a particular date, the action would be dismissed for want of prosecution. Three months later, the plaintiff brought a second action against the defendant founded on the same cause of action. The master struck out the second action as an abuse of process but, on appeal, a judge in chambers allowed the appeal and rescinded the master's order. 
 
 [22] A further appeal to the Court of Appeal was allowed. Dunn LJ, with whom Watkins LJ agreed, said this (at 785): 
 
 
 
 
 'The court then has to consider whether, in the exercise of its discretion under Ord 18, r 19, [the] second action should be struck out. In my view, the court should be cautious in allowing the second action to continue and should have due regard to the necessity of maintaining the principle that orders are made to be complied with and not to be ignored...
 
 I regard it as a matter of discretion to be exercised having regard to the circumstances of the particular case. In this case there had, from first to last, been no explanation whatever by the plaintiff why there was the 10-month delay before the application to strike out the first action.... There was no explanation at all why he failed to comply with the 'unless' order [that is, the self-executing order] , and there has been no indication in this present action that he intends to comply with the orders of the court any more than he did in the first action. Indeed, he is still in contempt of court.'
 
 
 
 
 
 [23] An important factor in the reasoning of the Court of Appeal in Janov v Morris was the absence of any explanation for the failure to comply with the self-executing order. A similar approach has been taken in later English cases. In Re Jokai Tea Holdings Ltd [1993] 1 All ER 630, Browne-Wilkinson V-C observed (at 637) that the basis of the decision in Janov v Morris 
 
 
 
 
 'was that the failure to comply with the peremptory order was contumacious.... It is clear that the court, in reaching the conclusion that the conduct was contumacious, placed much reliance on the fact that no explanation or excuse being given by the plaintiff for his disobedience to the order. 
 
 


 
 
 
 In my judgment, in cases in which the court has to decide what are the consequences of a failure to comply with an 'unless' order, the relevant question is whether such failure is intentional and contumelious. The court should not be astute to find excuses for such failure since obedience to orders of the court is the foundation on which its authority is founded. But, if a party can clearly demonstrate that there was no intention to ignore or flout the order and that the failure to obey was due to extraneous circumstances, such failure to obey is not to be treated as contumelious and therefore does not disentitle the litigant to rights which he would otherwise have enjoyed.' 
 
 
 
 
 See also Grand Metropolitan Nominee (No 2) Co Ltd v Evans [1993] 1 All ER 642 (CA)". 


In Deangrove , the applicants' solicitor gave evidence that counsel had advised that their cause of action was not then complete, in consequence of which a Statement of Claim could not be drawn. Counsel advised that the applicants should allow the self-executing order to take effect. Sackville J accepted this evidence, and observed that it demonstrated that the applicants' behaviour had not been contumacious or such as to reflect wilful disobedience to the orders of the court.

35 The proposition that the later proceedings in Deangrove might have been regarded as an abuse of process not in the sense of demonstrating contumely but in the sense of an attempt to relitigate a matter which had previously been the subject of a final order disposing of identical proceedings appears not to have been the way the matter was put to Sackville J. That proposition was put to Holmes J in Clout v Klein [2001] QSC 401. There the earlier proceeding had been terminated not by a self-executing order but by a direct order of a Judge of the court. The ground which sustained the order, however, was that the plaintiffs in that proceeding had failed to comply with an order for security for costs. His Honour referred (at [44]) to some cases in which the application of the Anshun principle to situations in which there had been no adjudication had been doubted; doubts which, in my respectful view, would almost always be regarded as well-founded. However, on the facts, his Honour held that it was not unreasonable for the plaintiff which was common to both proceedings not to have raised the relevant claim in the earlier proceeding.

44 I do not believe that I would, on the facts of the present case, be justified in finding contumely on the part of the applicant apropos the self-executing order in the Victorian proceeding. Mr Frenkel did not put his case on this basis, at least explicitly, but he did urge me to find that the applicant's purpose in commencing the present proceeding was to "avoid" the operation and consequences of that order. In a sense it was, but in another sense so to conclude is to do no more than to beg the question. Although the applicant appears to remain in breach of so much of the order of Mandie J as required it provide security (a matter which is not for me to decide), it has suffered the adverse consequences of the self-executing part of that order. On one view, the respondents have achieved more from this sequence of events than they could have hoped for had security been provided and the Victorian proceeding continued. As in Deangrove , I think that the correct approach is to treat the applicant as, prima facie at least, entitled to allow the Victorian self-executing order to operate to its own disadvantage without holding that such conduct involves contumely.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Equity Access Limited v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972</tocase>
<text>47 I turn then to the respondents' application for security for costs. The power to order security arises under s 56(1) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), the discretionary exercise of which is not limited to the particular circumstances set out in O 28 r 3(1) of the Rules of Court: Bell Wholesale Co Pty Ltd v Gates Export Corporation (No 2) (1984) 2 FCR 1, 2-3. Mr Frenkel drew my attention to the list of considerations referred to in Equity Access Limited v Westpac Banking Corp (1989) ATPR 40-972. Those matters are the applicant's chances of success, whether the order would shut out the applicant from pursuing its claim, whether the applicant's impecuniosity arose out of the breaches alleged against the respondent, the public interest, discretionary matters peculiar to the present case and the risk that the applicant would not be able to satisfy an order for costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404</tocase>
<text>32 There is, of course, no shortage of authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process for a party to seek to contest, in later proceedings, a point which it has lost, or substantially lost, in earlier proceedings, even where there may not be complete overlap between all facts, parties, and causes of action: see eg Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529; Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404; Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 ; Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198; However, these authorities, like Anshun , speak only of situations in which the earlier point was actually decided by the court concerned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291</tocase>
<text>33 By contrast, there is no res judicata nor, as I understand the law, Anshun estoppel, when the earlier proceedings have been discontinued. In relation to res judicata at least, the same conclusion applies when the earlier proceedings have been dismissed on account of default in compliance with orders for discovery ( Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729), on account of default in the provision of particulars ( Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115) or for want of prosecution ( Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291; Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255). The question with which these cases do not deal, however, is whether, notwithstanding that there would be no res judicata , it might nonetheless be regarded as vexatious, and in that sense as an abuse of process, for a moving party, by his or her own default, to allow proceedings to be terminated, without adjudication, to his or her disadvantage, and then to bring new proceedings seeking the same remedy on closely related grounds.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529</tocase>
<text>32 There is, of course, no shortage of authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process for a party to seek to contest, in later proceedings, a point which it has lost, or substantially lost, in earlier proceedings, even where there may not be complete overlap between all facts, parties, and causes of action: see eg Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529; Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404; Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 ; Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198; However, these authorities, like Anshun , speak only of situations in which the earlier point was actually decided by the court concerned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Moore v Inglis (1976) 9 ALR 509</tocase>
<text>37 In the facts leading to the judgment of Mason J in Moore v Inglis (1976) 9 ALR 509, the plaintiff had commenced a proceeding in the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory alleging conspiracy, and seeking damages. While those proceedings were pending, the plaintiff commenced a proceeding in the original jurisdiction of the High Court alleging, in a reformulated way, what was essentially the same conspiracy, or series of conspiracies. In the High Court, the plaintiff sought declarations and injunctions only, not damages. The parties in the two actions were different. Mason J granted the defendants a perpetual stay upon the principle that it was prima facie vexatious to sue concurrently in different courts for the same thing, relying in this regard upon Logan v Bank of Scotland (No 2) [1906] 1 KB 141, 150; Slough Estates Ltd v Slough Borough Council [1968] Ch 299, 314-5; and Re Christiansborg (1885) 10 PD 141, 148. His Honour considered it inconsequential that the plaintiff sought different kinds of relief in the two proceedings: the Supreme Court of the ACT had jurisdiction to grant relief by way of declarations and injunctions, should the plaintiff choose to seek that, either in substitution for, or in addition to, her existing claim for damages (9 ALR at 514-5). Mason J continued at 515:
 
 "Any difficulty which the plaintiff may encounter in securing appropriate amendments to the proceedings in the Supreme Court will stem, not from jurisdictional limitations, but from the manner in which the plaintiff has presented her case to date and from the insufficiency of the matters upon which she relies to ground the relief which she claims. However, these difficulties do not provide a reason for allowing the plaintiff to maintain a second proceeding in this Court relating to the subject matter already in course of litigation in the Supreme Court." 
 

On the subject of different parties, Mason J noted that, if a proper case were made out, the Supreme Court proceeding could be amended so as to add or remove parties. With respect to this and other potential amendments, his Honour said (at 515):
 
 "Although I acknowledge that the plaintiff may not secure all the amendments which she desires it is neither just nor fair that she should, after commencing one action which is about to come to issue on the pleadings, bring another action on the same subject matter, making minor alterations only to the substantive allegations and to the parties. She must make up her mind once and for all as to how she is going to present her case." 
 

His Honour held that the commencement and continuation of the action in the High Court was vexatious and oppressive, and constituted an abuse of the process of the Court.

38 Turning to the motion before the Court, it is necessary to examine the applicant's respective causes of action in the Victorian proceeding, and here. In the Victorian proceeding, aside from the defences that the respondents raised, the applicant would have been required to establish that 
 
 &#8226; the respondents were directors of Mactec at the time it incurred the debt to the applicant; &#8226; Mactec was insolvent at that time, or became insolvent by incurring the debt; &#8226; there were reasonable grounds for suspecting that Mactec was insolvent, or would become insolvent by incurring the debt; &#8226; the respondents were aware, or a reasonable person in a like position in a company in Mactec's circumstances would have been aware, that there were reasonable grounds for so suspecting; &#8226; the respondents failed to prevent Mactec from incurring the debt; &#8226; because of Mactec's insolvency, the applicant suffered loss or damage; &#8226; the debt was wholly or partly unsecured; and &#8226; Mactec was being wound up. 


In the present proceeding (as pleaded by the applicant, and again putting aside any defences that might be raised), the applicant would be required to establish that 
 
 &#8226; Mactec was a trading corporation; &#8226; Mactec represented to the applicant, at or prior to entering into the loan agreement, that the waste supply agreement was executed and in place and/or that Mactec could repay the $500,000 loan before 23 May 2000; &#8226; the representations were misleading or deceptive either in fact (ie, as the case requires, that the waste supply agreement was not executed or in place or that Mactec could not repay the $500,000 loan before 23 May 2000) or in the statutory sense that, when made, its maker or makers had no reasonable grounds for believing that Mactec could repay the loan, on account of Mactec's insolvency; &#8226; the applicant relied on the representations in advancing the amount of the loan to Mactec; &#8226; the respondents were involved in the making of the representations within the meaning of s 75B of the Trade Practices Act ; and &#8226; the applicant suffered loss or damage.

39 There are several obvious differences between the causes of action, and the factual elements that would be required to be established, as between the Victorian proceeding and this proceeding. Section 588M of the Corporations Act involves no element of conduct by company directors: it is concerned with their knowledge, or constructive knowledge, as to the state of the company's solvency; and, of course, with the objective fact of solvency. Under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act , by contrast, conduct is everything, whereas the company's condition of solvency or otherwise is not, at least directly, relevant; and the respondents' ignorance of the falsity of the representations made by Mactec may not be fatal to the applicant's case. The waste supply agreement, and the questions of whether it was executed at the relevant time, of what representations were made about it, and the like, will constitute very significant elements of the applicant's case in the present proceeding, whereas, it does not appear that such matters would have been agitated in the Victorian proceeding.

41 The cases to which I have most recently referred above, especially Moore v Inglis , show that the question whether a later proceeding is an abuse of process because of similarity with an earlier, extant, proceeding is not concluded in the negative merely because the parties, the causes of action, the specific relief sought, or even the forensic issues which may arise, are not identical. In that case Mason J held that the later proceeding was abusive notwithstanding that, to accommodate all its elements, some amendments to the earlier proceeding might be required. The important, perhaps critical, point was that the court in which the earlier proceeding was commenced had jurisdiction to deal with everything raised in the later proceeding and there was no reasonable justification, based on legitimate considerations of convenience, cost or the like, for commencing the second proceeding rather than seeking to amend the earlier. One sees the same underlying values as to the requirements of a fair and efficient system for the administration of justice here as are to be seen, in a different but analogous context, in Anshun .

42 In the present case, were it not for one factor to which I shall turn next, I would consider that the commencement of the present proceeding was an abuse of process in the sense of being a course preferred by the applicant over what I would regard as the more obvious, more convenient, less costly and less vexing expedient of seeking to make the necessary amendments to the pleadings in the Victorian proceeding. The applicant was, as plaintiff in the Victorian proceeding, suing to achieve compensation for the very loss around which this proceeding is constructed. It was suing the same parties as are respondents here. Broadly speaking, it was putting the same series of transactions in 2000 into controversy. Had the Victorian proceeding still been on foot when this proceeding was commenced, I would have regarded the present case as covered by Williams v Hunt and Moore v Inglis .

43 However, the Victorian proceeding was dismissed on 9 February 2006 the very day on which the present proceeding was commenced as a result of the operation of the self-executing order which Mandie J had made in September 2005. This takes the present situation, in my view, out of the Moore v Inglis line of authority. The evil with which the principle in such cases is concerned arises where a plaintiff tries to have a foot in each camp, as it were, by keeping more than one proceeding alive at the same time. I am not aware of any instance in which the same or an analogous principle has been applied to a situation of successive, rather than concurrent, proceedings. In the case of successive proceedings, it may be that the plaintiff in the later proceeding will be met by a successful plea of res judicata or of Anshun estoppel; or it may be shown, on the facts, that the commencement of the later proceeding revealed a contumacious disregard for the authority of the court, or of another court. But, absent any of these situations, there is no established basis upon which I should regard the commencement of a later proceeding making the same or similar claims as those previously, or even contemporaneously, disposed of in an earlier proceeding by a self-executing order as necessarily amounting to an abuse of process.

45 The circumstances before Hargrave J on 3 March 2006 were, of course, different from those now confronting me. His Honour had before him an application which, if granted, would have kept alive two proceedings covering essentially the same things. It was a conventional Moore v Inglis situation. His Honour, quite correctly in my respectful view, recognised the objective of the then plaintiff as involving an abuse of process. He would not allow it. He refused to keep the Victorian proceeding alive, the result of which is that that proceeding was finally terminated on 9 February 2006 and the present proceeding remains the only relevant one which the respondents are obliged to defend.

46 For the above reasons I shall dismiss so much of the respondents' motion as seeks that the proceeding be dismissed or stayed as an abuse of process.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255</tocase>
<text>33 By contrast, there is no res judicata nor, as I understand the law, Anshun estoppel, when the earlier proceedings have been discontinued. In relation to res judicata at least, the same conclusion applies when the earlier proceedings have been dismissed on account of default in compliance with orders for discovery ( Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729), on account of default in the provision of particulars ( Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115) or for want of prosecution ( Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291; Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255). The question with which these cases do not deal, however, is whether, notwithstanding that there would be no res judicata , it might nonetheless be regarded as vexatious, and in that sense as an abuse of process, for a moving party, by his or her own default, to allow proceedings to be terminated, without adjudication, to his or her disadvantage, and then to bring new proceedings seeking the same remedy on closely related grounds.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/45.html</AustLII>
<text>31 Mr Frenkel relied upon the judgment of the High Court in Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589. But Anshun estoppel, as the principle for which that case stands is sometimes called, is concerned with the ability of a party in later proceedings to rely upon a point of claim or defence which was so relevant to the matters adjudicated upon in earlier proceedings to which that party was also a party that it would have been unreasonable not then to have relied on it. As is apparent from the statement in Henderson v Henderson (1843) 3 Hare 100, 115 which the High Court regarded as stating the law, the principle applies only where there has been an adjudication by the Court in the earlier proceedings. Anshun does not stand as authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process to make a claim in a later proceeding that could have been made in an earlier proceeding, where the earlier proceeding has been stayed or dismissed without adjudication.

32 There is, of course, no shortage of authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process for a party to seek to contest, in later proceedings, a point which it has lost, or substantially lost, in earlier proceedings, even where there may not be complete overlap between all facts, parties, and causes of action: see eg Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529; Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404; Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 ; Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198; However, these authorities, like Anshun , speak only of situations in which the earlier point was actually decided by the court concerned.

33 By contrast, there is no res judicata nor, as I understand the law, Anshun estoppel, when the earlier proceedings have been discontinued. In relation to res judicata at least, the same conclusion applies when the earlier proceedings have been dismissed on account of default in compliance with orders for discovery ( Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729), on account of default in the provision of particulars ( Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115) or for want of prosecution ( Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291; Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255). The question with which these cases do not deal, however, is whether, notwithstanding that there would be no res judicata , it might nonetheless be regarded as vexatious, and in that sense as an abuse of process, for a moving party, by his or her own default, to allow proceedings to be terminated, without adjudication, to his or her disadvantage, and then to bring new proceedings seeking the same remedy on closely related grounds.

35 The proposition that the later proceedings in Deangrove might have been regarded as an abuse of process not in the sense of demonstrating contumely but in the sense of an attempt to relitigate a matter which had previously been the subject of a final order disposing of identical proceedings appears not to have been the way the matter was put to Sackville J. That proposition was put to Holmes J in Clout v Klein [2001] QSC 401. There the earlier proceeding had been terminated not by a self-executing order but by a direct order of a Judge of the court. The ground which sustained the order, however, was that the plaintiffs in that proceeding had failed to comply with an order for security for costs. His Honour referred (at [44]) to some cases in which the application of the Anshun principle to situations in which there had been no adjudication had been doubted; doubts which, in my respectful view, would almost always be regarded as well-founded. However, on the facts, his Honour held that it was not unreasonable for the plaintiff which was common to both proceedings not to have raised the relevant claim in the earlier proceeding.

41 The cases to which I have most recently referred above, especially Moore v Inglis , show that the question whether a later proceeding is an abuse of process because of similarity with an earlier, extant, proceeding is not concluded in the negative merely because the parties, the causes of action, the specific relief sought, or even the forensic issues which may arise, are not identical. In that case Mason J held that the later proceeding was abusive notwithstanding that, to accommodate all its elements, some amendments to the earlier proceeding might be required. The important, perhaps critical, point was that the court in which the earlier proceeding was commenced had jurisdiction to deal with everything raised in the later proceeding and there was no reasonable justification, based on legitimate considerations of convenience, cost or the like, for commencing the second proceeding rather than seeking to amend the earlier. One sees the same underlying values as to the requirements of a fair and efficient system for the administration of justice here as are to be seen, in a different but analogous context, in Anshun .

43 However, the Victorian proceeding was dismissed on 9 February 2006 the very day on which the present proceeding was commenced as a result of the operation of the self-executing order which Mandie J had made in September 2005. This takes the present situation, in my view, out of the Moore v Inglis line of authority. The evil with which the principle in such cases is concerned arises where a plaintiff tries to have a foot in each camp, as it were, by keeping more than one proceeding alive at the same time. I am not aware of any instance in which the same or an analogous principle has been applied to a situation of successive, rather than concurrent, proceedings. In the case of successive proceedings, it may be that the plaintiff in the later proceeding will be met by a successful plea of res judicata or of Anshun estoppel; or it may be shown, on the facts, that the commencement of the later proceeding revealed a contumacious disregard for the authority of the court, or of another court. But, absent any of these situations, there is no established basis upon which I should regard the commencement of a later proceeding making the same or similar claims as those previously, or even contemporaneously, disposed of in an earlier proceeding by a self-executing order as necessarily amounting to an abuse of process.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2001/142.html</AustLII>
<text>32 There is, of course, no shortage of authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process for a party to seek to contest, in later proceedings, a point which it has lost, or substantially lost, in earlier proceedings, even where there may not be complete overlap between all facts, parties, and causes of action: see eg Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529; Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404; Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 ; Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198; However, these authorities, like Anshun , speak only of situations in which the earlier point was actually decided by the court concerned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115</tocase>
<text>33 By contrast, there is no res judicata nor, as I understand the law, Anshun estoppel, when the earlier proceedings have been discontinued. In relation to res judicata at least, the same conclusion applies when the earlier proceedings have been dismissed on account of default in compliance with orders for discovery ( Baines v State Bank of NSW (1985) 2 NSWLR 729), on account of default in the provision of particulars ( Samuels v Linzi Dresses Ltd [1981] QB 115) or for want of prosecution ( Hart v Hall &amp; Pickles Ltd [1969] 3 All ER 291; Pople v Evans [1969] 2 Ch 255). The question with which these cases do not deal, however, is whether, notwithstanding that there would be no res judicata , it might nonetheless be regarded as vexatious, and in that sense as an abuse of process, for a moving party, by his or her own default, to allow proceedings to be terminated, without adjudication, to his or her disadvantage, and then to bring new proceedings seeking the same remedy on closely related grounds.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sea Culture International Pty Ltd v Scoles (1991) 32 FCR 275</tocase>
<text>29 The finding which I have just made does not, however, mean that the respondents succeed on their abuse of process arguments. Their difficulty, as Mr Frenkel frankly acknowledged, was that the present circumstances do not fit neatly within any recognised category of abuse. Mr Frenkel referred me to the statement by French J in Sea Culture International Pty Ltd v Scoles (1991) 32 FCR 275, 279 that "the possible varieties of abuse of process are only limited by human ingenuity and the categories are not closed." With respect, I agree; but I cannot, as at present advised, envisage the circumstances in which I, sitting as a single Judge, would take it upon myself to create a new category, and I do not understand Mr Frenkel to have submitted that I should. Rather, while accepting that the facts of the present case were not on all fours with those of any binding or persuasive authority, he submitted that the principles which informed the decided cases should likewise lead to the conclusion that the applicant's conduct in commencing the present proceeding constituted an abuse of process.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Williams v Hunt [1905] 1 KB 512</tocase>
<text>36 Moving to a somewhat different line of authority, it is at least regarded prima facie as an abuse of process for a moving party to vex his or her opponent by instituting multiple proceedings to right a single wrong. In Williams v Hunt [1905] 1 KB 512, the Court of Appeal restored the order of a master in the Kings Bench Division to stay an action on a specially indorsed writ claiming principal and interest under a covenant in a mortgage deed, when there was waiting for trial in the Chancery Division an earlier proceeding in which the same plaintiff claimed, in relation to the same mortgage, an account, payment of the sum found to be due, and in default, sale or foreclosure. Collins MR said (at 514):
 
 "Where two separate remedies are possible, and a start is made by putting in force one of those remedies by a writ which would entitle the plaintiff to the relief he subsequently desires, he cannot by deliberately leaving that out of his claim reserve his right to ask for it in another proceeding. Where proceedings have been started, it is an abuse of the process of the Court to divide the remedy where there is a complete remedy in the Court where the suit was first started." 
 

Stirling LJ was of the same opinion (at 515).

42 In the present case, were it not for one factor to which I shall turn next, I would consider that the commencement of the present proceeding was an abuse of process in the sense of being a course preferred by the applicant over what I would regard as the more obvious, more convenient, less costly and less vexing expedient of seeking to make the necessary amendments to the pleadings in the Victorian proceeding. The applicant was, as plaintiff in the Victorian proceeding, suing to achieve compensation for the very loss around which this proceeding is constructed. It was suing the same parties as are respondents here. Broadly speaking, it was putting the same series of transactions in 2000 into controversy. Had the Victorian proceeding still been on foot when this proceeding was commenced, I would have regarded the present case as covered by Williams v Hunt and Moore v Inglis .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/34.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The judgment of the High Court in Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509 is often regarded as the leading Australian authority on abuse of process. The particular concept of abuse with which that judgment was concerned, however, was that of commencing and prosecuting proceedings for a purpose collateral to that for which the proceedings were designed: 174 CLR at 526-527. The Court was there concerned with the kind of case in which court proceedings are used as an instrument of oppression in the sense of seeking to achieve some collateral end rather than to vindicate the moving party's legitimate legal rights for which proceedings of the relevant kind were intended. A ready answer to the present problem is not provided by Williams v Spautz . It could not be suggested that the applicant had any purpose collateral to that achievable under s 52 of the Trade Practices Act in mind when the present proceeding was commenced. It is true that, as I have held, it was commenced as a separate proceeding because the more obvious expedient of seeking to amend the Victorian proceeding was unattractive. But on no view could it be asserted that the applicant is seeking to achieve some object extraneous to the rights and protections which it claims to have under the Trade Practices Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1308.html</AustLII>
<text>32 There is, of course, no shortage of authority for the proposition that it is an abuse of process for a party to seek to contest, in later proceedings, a point which it has lost, or substantially lost, in earlier proceedings, even where there may not be complete overlap between all facts, parties, and causes of action: see eg Hunter v Chief Constable of the West Midlands Police [1982] AC 529; Haines v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (1995) 43 NSWLR 404; Wilson v Commonwealth of Australia [1999] FCA 1308 ; Rippon v Chilcotin Pty Ltd [2001] NSWCA 142 ; (2001) 53 NSWLR 198; However, these authorities, like Anshun , speak only of situations in which the earlier point was actually decided by the court concerned.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>