<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZWTH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 997 (4 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/997.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/61.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Plainly the Magistrate was saying that the appellant's natural justice claim had to be measured against the provisions of Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act 1958 , and so measured did not fall within the scope of the modified natural justice requirements contained therein, as is indeed the case. The complaint that his Honour failed to explain how those provisions answered the appellant's natural justice claim is baseless. The appellant was making a common law claim that was not replicated in the modified regime. See Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61 at [64] - [70] and SZCIJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 62 at [5] - [8] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZCIJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/62.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Plainly the Magistrate was saying that the appellant's natural justice claim had to be measured against the provisions of Div 4 of Pt 7 of the Migration Act 1958 , and so measured did not fall within the scope of the modified natural justice requirements contained therein, as is indeed the case. The complaint that his Honour failed to explain how those provisions answered the appellant's natural justice claim is baseless. The appellant was making a common law claim that was not replicated in the modified regime. See Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Lay Lat [2006] FCAFC 61 at [64] - [70] and SZCIJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 62 at [5] - [8] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 123</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/123.html</AustLII>
<text>10 The fourth ground of appeal is also predicated upon the first. However, the essential complaint is that the Magistrate failed to accept that the Tribunal erred in not giving the appellant "required notice that it was rejecting her evidence, which evidence was the reason or part of the reason for the refusal of her application". It does not appear that this precise point was put to the Magistrate, although it is clear that the appellant did rely on s 424A of the Migration Act before his Honour. The Magistrate said:
 
 "The applicant also contends that the Tribunal failed to put inconsistencies to the applicant. However, the identification of inconsistencies is a matter of the Tribunal's evaluation of the evidence put forward by the applicant. It is not 'information' within the meaning of s 424A of the Act as suggested by the applicant. This issue has been authoritatively settled by the Full Federal Court in VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 123 at [24] ." 
 

Had the present complaint been put to the Magistrate, it would have been rejected for the reason contained in that passage. The Tribunal, having read the appellant's material and heard what she said at the hearing, decided as part of its evaluation of her evidence not to accept parts of it. That decision is not "information" within s 424A. See VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 123 at [24] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>