<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>McColm v Strudwicks Sportsworld Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 961 (27 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/961.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>American Cynamid v Ethicon Limited [1975] UKHL 1 ; (1975) AC 396</tocase>
<text>The Federal Court is empowered to make interlocutory orders by s 23 Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The principles which govern the exercise of that power were set out recently by Stone J in Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218 at [17] , namely: 1. That there is a serious question to be tried or a prima facie case such that if the evidence remains the same there is a probability that at a final hearing it will be entitled to relief. 2. That it will suffer irreparable harm for which damages will not be an adequate compensation, unless an injunction is granted. 3. That the balance of convenience favours the granting of an injunction. 

(See also Pharmacia Italia SPA v Pfizer (Perth) Pty Ltd v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) FCA 1675 per Sundberg J at [9]; Castlemaine Tooheys v State of South Australia [1986] HCA 58 ; (1986) 161 CLR 148 per Mason ACJ at [153]; and American Cynamid v Ethicon Limited [1975] UKHL 1 ; (1975) AC 396 per Lord Diplock at [406]-[407].)

 1. Serious Question to be Tried</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Castlemaine Tooheys v State of South Australia [1986] HCA 58 ; (1986) 161 CLR 148</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/58.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Court is empowered to make interlocutory orders by s 23 Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The principles which govern the exercise of that power were set out recently by Stone J in Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218 at [17] , namely: 1. That there is a serious question to be tried or a prima facie case such that if the evidence remains the same there is a probability that at a final hearing it will be entitled to relief. 2. That it will suffer irreparable harm for which damages will not be an adequate compensation, unless an injunction is granted. 3. That the balance of convenience favours the granting of an injunction. 

(See also Pharmacia Italia SPA v Pfizer (Perth) Pty Ltd v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) FCA 1675 per Sundberg J at [9]; Castlemaine Tooheys v State of South Australia [1986] HCA 58 ; (1986) 161 CLR 148 per Mason ACJ at [153]; and American Cynamid v Ethicon Limited [1975] UKHL 1 ; (1975) AC 396 per Lord Diplock at [406]-[407].)

 1. Serious Question to be Tried</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1218.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Court is empowered to make interlocutory orders by s 23 Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The principles which govern the exercise of that power were set out recently by Stone J in Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218 at [17] , namely: 1. That there is a serious question to be tried or a prima facie case such that if the evidence remains the same there is a probability that at a final hearing it will be entitled to relief. 2. That it will suffer irreparable harm for which damages will not be an adequate compensation, unless an injunction is granted. 3. That the balance of convenience favours the granting of an injunction. 

(See also Pharmacia Italia SPA v Pfizer (Perth) Pty Ltd v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) FCA 1675 per Sundberg J at [9]; Castlemaine Tooheys v State of South Australia [1986] HCA 58 ; (1986) 161 CLR 148 per Mason ACJ at [153]; and American Cynamid v Ethicon Limited [1975] UKHL 1 ; (1975) AC 396 per Lord Diplock at [406]-[407].)

 1. Serious Question to be Tried</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Outdoor Power Products Pty Ltd v Silvan Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1696</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1696.html</AustLII>
<text>A similar case concerning backpack style containers used for spot-spraying pests and weeds was heard before Finkelstein J in Outdoor Power Products Pty Ltd v Silvan Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1696. In that case, Finkelstein J considered an application for an interlocutory injunction to restrain an infringement of a trade mark over the 'Solo Sprayer'. His injunction considered the elements of the claimed passing off action and found it to be made out sufficiently for the purposes of an interlocutory application. His Honour held that in a case where it was clear that the offending product was interfering with the applicant's goodwill, damages would not be an adequate remedy.

As I indicated earlier, I have been provided in Court this morning with the football kicking tee as sold by the first respondent which I have referred to as the infringing kicking tee, and a 'Sharp Shooter' football kicking tee. I am in no doubt that the general appearance of each is extremely similar. I agree with Finkelstein J that in circumstances where it is clear that an infringement of the Registered Design by the respondents is being used to interfere with the goodwill of the applicants and being used to erode the applicants' market share in breach of the applicants' monopoly rights pursuant to the Registered Design, damages would not be an adequate remedy. 
 3. Balance of convenience

As I have already indicated, there is evidence that: o the respondents are selling infringing kicking tees which may infringe the applicants' registered design o there is a history of communication between these parties, including it appears undertakings by the respondents not to continue to sell kicking tees which infringe the applicants' Registered Design o the infringing kicking tees which the respondents are selling bear a very strong similarity to the applicants' kicking tees.

Again, it is unfortunate that the respondents did not appear today. However, the factors I have listed above, in particular the history of this matter as presented to me by the applicants, persuade me that it would be appropriate to grant the applicants interlocutory relief as they seek. Further, as evidenced by the email and letter exhibited to the affidavit of Mr Philp, the respondents had already indicated that they would not be selling kicking tees which infringe the applicants' Registered Design. An order restraining them from selling the infringing kicking tees appears to be compatible with undertakings it seems they made in 2005.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Pharmacia Italia SPA v Pfizer (Perth) Pty Ltd v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) FCA 1675</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1675.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Court is empowered to make interlocutory orders by s 23 Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The principles which govern the exercise of that power were set out recently by Stone J in Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218 at [17] , namely: 1. That there is a serious question to be tried or a prima facie case such that if the evidence remains the same there is a probability that at a final hearing it will be entitled to relief. 2. That it will suffer irreparable harm for which damages will not be an adequate compensation, unless an injunction is granted. 3. That the balance of convenience favours the granting of an injunction. 

(See also Pharmacia Italia SPA v Pfizer (Perth) Pty Ltd v Interpharma Pty Ltd (2005) FCA 1675 per Sundberg J at [9]; Castlemaine Tooheys v State of South Australia [1986] HCA 58 ; (1986) 161 CLR 148 per Mason ACJ at [153]; and American Cynamid v Ethicon Limited [1975] UKHL 1 ; (1975) AC 396 per Lord Diplock at [406]-[407].)

 1. Serious Question to be Tried</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wanem Pty Ltd v John Tekiela (1990) 19 IPR 435</tocase>
<text>Unfortunately the Court has not had the benefit of submissions from the respondents on these points. However, the visual similarity in the tees is clear. Gummow J in Wanem Pty Ltd v John Tekiela (1990) 19 IPR 435 at 15 said 'the design applies to the appearance of the article as a whole and issues of infringement are to be approached with that in mind'. Prima facie , there is a case that the tees sold by the first respondent infringe the Registered Design of the applicants under the Designs Act 1906 (Cth).

Further, there is affidavit evidence from the applicants that at least some infringing kicking tees are being sold in stores operated by the first respondents. Finally, there is evidence before the Court, including correspondence from the respondents, which supports the third contention of the applicants in relation to the conduct of the respondents. In my view, these issues indicate that there is a serious question to be tried. 
 2. Damages insufficient

In their written submissions and in oral submissions this morning the applicants submitted that whilst an account of profits or damages in respect of the infringements to date are sought in the eventual trial, long term damage to the market for kicking tees to which their Registered Design has been legitimately applied is of most concern.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>