<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEXQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 927 (21 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/927.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Al Shamry [2001] FCA 919 ; (2001) 110 FCR 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/919.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The appellant submits that the above conclusion is partly derived from information contained in the statement accompanying the appellant's application for a protection visa relating to the political activities of the appellant's family. The appellant's application for a protection visa was not provided to the Tribunal by the applicant and accordingly, s 424A(1) applied to that statement: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Al Shamry [2001] FCA 919 ; (2001) 110 FCR 27 .

14 The respondent submits that the reasons for decision suggest that the appellant provided this information to the Tribunal. The respondent points in particular to the Tribunal's comments that:
 
 'At the hearing before me the Applicant repeated that all his family had been involved in the PPP.'

15 The respondent also refers to the following paragraph:
 
 'The Applicant said that as a member of the students' union and the PPP he had been engaged in welfare work, helping poor people and poor students with books and money. He said that he had campaigned for the PPP in the general election which the PPP had won (in 1993, although the Applicant could not remember the year) and in the general election in 1997 which the PPP lost to the PML. He said that his local MNA had been from the PPP between 1993 and 1996 but that at the election in 1997 the PML candidate had been elected. The Applicant said that he himself had stood in the election for local bodies in the late 19990s, which he said had been held on a non-party basis. He said, however, that he had not been elected because the PML was in power.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam and Ors [1999] FCA 719 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/719.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The appellant submits that the Tribunal erred in failing to consider that elections were to be held in October 2002 in which the PML might have been successful, in which case the appellant may have faced a real chance of future persecution. The appellant submits that the word 'suggest' in Tribunal's statement that ' the Applicant did not leave Pakistan until the late 1990s, which does not suggest that he was being persecuted by reason of his involvement in the intervening period ' is indicative of a tentative finding by the Tribunal. The appellant relies upon a passage in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam and Ors [1999] FCA 719 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220 at [55] - [56] in which Sackville J states:
 
 'It can be seen from this passage that if the RRT finds that it is only slightly more probable than not that an alleged relevant event had not occurred, it must take into account the chance that it did occur when determining whether there was a well-founded fear of persecution ... 
 
 If, on the other hand, it appears that the RRT had no "real doubt" that its findings were correct, it is not bound to consider whether those findings might be wrong.' [original emphasis]

33 The appellant says that since the Tribunal observed that the PML had been ousted in a coup in 1999 in determining that there was no real chance that the appellant would be persecuted if he were to return to Pakistan now or in the reasonably foreseeable future, it was obliged to consider the possible changed circumstances following the election.

35 I do not consider that the word ' suggest ', in its context, shows that the Tribunal was ambivalent in its conclusion that the appellant had been persecuted between 1997 and the time when he left Pakistan by reason of his involvement in the PPP. I am satisfied that its finding was not attended by any significant doubt. Accordingly, I reject the submission of the appellant that the Tribunal should have adopted the approach referred to in Rajalingam .

40 With respect to the second ground (the Rajalingam argument), I am not satisfied that leave should be granted. The law relating to this ground was not uncertain at the time of the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court, and the appellant was represented at that hearing. This point should have been taken before the Federal Magistrates Court if the appellant wished to challenge the Tribunal's finding on this ground. Further, for the reasons expressed above, I do not consider there is any merit in this ground of appeal. Accordingly, I refuse leave to rely upon the second ground in the amended notice of appeal.

41 It follows from the above that the appellant succeeds on the first ground of the amended notice of appeal. Accordingly I will remit the matter to the Tribunal for reconsideration, and award costs to the appellant in these proceedings.
 

 I certify that the preceding forty-one (41) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Cowdroy. 


Associate:

Dated: 21 July 2006


 Counsel for the Applicant: B Zipser 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: J Mitchell 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 10 July 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 July 2006 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/927.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 219 ALR 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/263.html</AustLII>
<text>34 The respondent says that the appellant did not argue before the Tribunal that the result of the election might lead to a greater risk of persecution in the future and that it would be an unreasonable standard to require the Tribunal to consider this claim in the absence of argument. The respondent refers to NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 219 ALR 27 at [58] - [63] which sets out the extent of the obligation upon a Tribunal to consider unarticulated claims. At [58] the Court observed that:
 
 'It has been suggested that the unarticulated claim must be raised "squarely" on the material available to the tribunal before it has a statutory duty to consider it: SDAQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 129 FCR 137; 199 ALR 265; [2003] FCAFC 120 at [19] per Cooper J. The use of the adverb "squarely" does not convey any precise standard but it indicates that a claim not expressly advanced will attract the review obligation of the tribunal when it is apparent on the face of the material before the tribunal. Such a claim will not depend for its exposure on constructive or creative activity by the tribunal.' 

The respondent says that the significance of the forthcoming election was not raised squarely as an issue by the material before the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>NAOA v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 241</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/241.html</AustLII>
<text>25 This raises the question whether, in these circumstances, the appellant was required to prove conclusively, by tendering the transcript, that he did not provide information orally to the Tribunal from which it could have gleaned his approximate departure date. The respondent says that, in the absence of a transcript, the Court cannot conclude that such information was not provided by the appellant to the Tribunal at the hearing. The respondent says that the onus lies upon the appellant to provide the transcript as proof that the information was not provided to the Tribunal orally, and in the absence of the transcript, it is not open to the Court to infer that the information was not provided: see NAOA v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 241 at [21] per Beaumont, Merkel and Hely JJ.

26 The Full Court in NAOA was dealing with a claim of procedural unfairness, based upon the fact that certain matters had not been put to the appellant at the Tribunal hearing. The Full Court observed at [21]: 
 
 'For one thing, as the respondent submitted, the appellant's case is premised upon an assumption (that was also made by the learned Magistrate, albeit on a tentative basis), namely, that the Tribunal had not raised the issue of the authenticity of certain documents with the appellant at the hearing. However, his Honour did not make a finding in relation to this matter. Driver FM observed that this "appeared" to be the case "from the record of the [Tribunal] decision". On the evidence before his Honour, it was not open to him to have made a finding that this issue had not been canvassed. His Honour had no transcript. (As mentioned, the tape is before us and we refer to it below.) The appellant had not given any evidence (in affidavit form or orally) to the effect that this issue had not been raised. There was simply no basis upon which his Honour could properly have made this finding. His reasons should not be read as if he did so. In the absence of evidence about what occurred at the hearing, the appellant has no sufficient evidential basis for the grounds he seeks to raise, thus he has not, in our opinion, established that the Tribunal did not comply with the rules of natural justice.'

27 The situation in the present case is different from the position in NAOA . In NAOA , the Court found that there was no evidence which indicated whether the matter had been raised with the appellant by the Tribunal. In the present case, however, the Tribunal's reasons for decision clearly record that the appellant was questioned with respect to his departure date but was unable to provide that information to the Tribunal orally. The reasons specifically refer to information contained in the application form. The Tribunal's reasons themselves are evidence which suggests that the Tribunal did not receive the evidence orally from the appellant, but instead relied upon a document to which obligations under s 424A(1) and (2) applied.

28 I consider that the appellant was entitled to rely upon the reasons as evidence that the information had not been provided under s 424A(3)(b). The reasons directly touched upon the subject under dispute. If the transcript indicated a different position, then it was open to the respondent to tender it. However, in the absence of the transcript, the reasons of the Tribunal themselves provide, in my opinion, sufficient evidence for me to arrive at a conclusion that the information had not been provided to the Tribunal by the appellant as contemplated by s 424A(3)(b).

29 This is not to say that in all, or even most cases, it will be sufficient for the appellant to rely upon the reasons for the Tribunal alone. It is not the obligation of the Tribunal to refer in its reasons to the source of each part of the information upon which it relies. The present appeal is a rare case in which the Tribunal has specifically referred in its reasons to the very source of the information under consideration. Where the Court is unable directly to draw a conclusion from a Tribunal's reasons as to the source of the Tribunal's information, it is ultimately the responsibility of an appellant to ensure the transcript is provided if he or she wishes to argue that the information could only have been sourced from documents to which obligations under s 424A(1) and (2) applied.

30 Nonetheless, the Tribunal's reasons for decision themselves should not be ignored as evidence of the source of the Tribunal's information. The Full Court in NAOA , in noting that the appellant had not provided oral or affidavit evidence on the issue, explicitly recognised that there were forms of evidence other than the transcript which might enable a conclusion to be drawn about the oral evidence given at the Tribunal hearing. Since it may not always be clear when a conclusion can be reached upon the reasons alone, I consider it would be prudent to tender the transcript in all cases where a breach of s 424A is relied upon, or to incorporate the transcript into the appeal book where such a ground is raised.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SAAP and Anor v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/24.html</AustLII>
<text>36 The appellant acknowledges that he was represented by Counsel in the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court, and that the points now sought to be raised by the amended notice of appeal were not raised before that Court. However, the appellant argues that the effect of s 424A of the Migration Act was uncertain at the time of the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court. The appellant says when the Federal Magistrates Court hearing took place, no decision of the Federal Court had been given which upheld a challenge under s 424A based upon the combined effects of the decision in SAAP and Anor v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 and the decision in Al-Shamry . Further, the appellant says that leave was granted in a similar situation in each of the five appeals under consideration in SZEEU.

37 Counsel for the respondent says that the law was not uncertain at the time of the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court. Al-Shamry was handed down in July 2001 and SAAP was handed down in May 2005, well before the hearing in the Federal Magistrates Court in August 2005. He submits that the Court is limited under s 24 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) to hear appeals on the ground of errors in a judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>31 In this case, however, the reasons themselves directly point to the conclusion that the Tribunal relied upon information from the application form, in circumstances where that information had not been provided by the appellant orally at the hearing. The Tribunal did not provide this information to the appellant in writing as required by s 424A(2)(a) and s 441A of the Migration Act . It follows that, in accordance with the decision in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 , the Tribunal did not comply with the requirements of s 424A.

36 The appellant acknowledges that he was represented by Counsel in the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court, and that the points now sought to be raised by the amended notice of appeal were not raised before that Court. However, the appellant argues that the effect of s 424A of the Migration Act was uncertain at the time of the hearing before the Federal Magistrates Court. The appellant says when the Federal Magistrates Court hearing took place, no decision of the Federal Court had been given which upheld a challenge under s 424A based upon the combined effects of the decision in SAAP and Anor v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 and the decision in Al-Shamry . Further, the appellant says that leave was granted in a similar situation in each of the five appeals under consideration in SZEEU.

38 I am satisfied that the law relating to s 424A of the Migration Act had not been settled when the hearing in the Federal Magistrates Court took place. Since the hearing, the law has been clarified by the decision in SZEEU . The first issue relied upon by the appellant in the amended notice of appeal relies specifically upon the law as decided in SZEEU . I accept there would be some prejudice to the respondent by reason of the continuation of the proceedings if leave were granted. However if leave were not granted, the prejudice to the appellant, who would face removal to Pakistan without having had his application for asylum determined according to correct legal principles, would be greater.

39 For the reasons given above, I consider that one aspect of the appellant's claim under s 424A would succeed if leave were granted. Accordingly, I consider that leave with respect to the first ground of appeal in the amended notice of appeal should be granted.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>