<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Commissioner of Taxation v Slade Bloodstock Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 188 (23 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/188.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hope v Bathurst City Council [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/16.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The appeal under s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act is only available on a question of law. Counsel for the Company argued that this was not so in the present case. However, the present case is squarely within the proposition stated by the High Court in Hope v Bathurst City Council [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7 that 
 
 
 "the question whether facts fully found fall within the provisions of a statutory enactment properly construed is a question of law." 
 
 
 
 See also Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 286-287.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 286-287</tocase>
<text>15 The appeal under s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act is only available on a question of law. Counsel for the Company argued that this was not so in the present case. However, the present case is squarely within the proposition stated by the High Court in Hope v Bathurst City Council [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7 that 
 
 
 "the question whether facts fully found fall within the provisions of a statutory enactment properly construed is a question of law." 
 
 
 
 See also Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 286-287.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>J &amp; G Knowles &amp; Associates Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2000] FCA 196 ; (2000) 96 FCR 402 at [27]</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/196.html</AustLII>
<text>18 Moreover, the terms of the written agreement quoted at [6] above explicitly contemplate that one of the reasons Mr and Mrs Slade are to get repayment of their loans is for the discharge of their own personal obligations such as mortgages and school fees. There was here something more than a mere causal relationship between the employment and the payment: J &amp; G Knowles &amp; Associates Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2000] FCA 196 ; (2000) 96 FCR 402 at [27] . One cannot say that the Mr and Mrs Slade were employees who just happened to get repayments of a loan. Their position may be contrasted with the hypothetical example of an employee of a large public company who invests in publicly listed debentures of the company which are in due course repaid. In such a case the repayment would have nothing to do with the employment.

19 The appeal of the Commissioner should be allowed. It is not necessary to consider the alternative argument, which was confined to the car and entertainment payments. There will be orders that the decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal made 31 July 2006 be set aside and that the decision under review therein be affirmed. No order as to costs is sought. 


 I certify that the preceding nineteen (19) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 23 February 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: P Sest 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicant: Legal Services Branch, Australian Taxation Office 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: A Athanasiou 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondent: Rigby Cooke 
 
 Date of Hearing: 9 February 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 23 February 2007 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/188.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>Slade Bloodstock Pty Ltd and Commissioner of Taxation [2006] AATA 666</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/AATA/2006/666.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The Administrative Appeals Tribunal allowed the appeal of the Company: Slade Bloodstock Pty Ltd and Commissioner of Taxation [2006] AATA 660 . The commissioner now appeals to this Court under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth).

3 It is now not in dispute that by reason of the repayments Mr and Mrs Slade received a "benefit" and that they were "employees" of the Company. The only remaining issue is whether the Commissioner has shown that the Tribunal made an error of law in concluding that the repayments were not "in respect of the employment of an employee" within the meaning of s 5B and thus liable to tax under s 66(1).

4 Mr Slade is an accountant by profession. He has long held a passionate interest in the breeding of racehorses. In 2000 he and Mrs Slade set up the Company with its associated trust structure and commenced the business of acquiring yearlings and syndicating them to investors. Mr and Mrs Slade were the only persons involved in the business. Initially they operated it part time but as its success grew they became increasingly involved.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>