<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Mokbel v Attorney-General for the Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 1536 (5 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1536.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General in and for the United Kingdom v Heinemann Publishers Australia Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/25.html</AustLII>
<text>59 The courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory. This principle of non-adjudication is consistent with the international rule of comity which refers to the respect or courtesy accorded by a country to the laws and institutions of another. This was made clear in Attorney-General in and for the United Kingdom v Heinemann Publishers Australia Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40-41:
 
 
 "The rule is associated with a related principle of international law, which has long been recognized, namely that, in general, courts will not adjudicate upon the validity of acts and transactions of a foreign sovereign State within that sovereign's own territory. The statement of Fuller C.J. in Underhill v Hernandez [(1897) 168 U.S. 250, at 252] that "the courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory" has been repeated with approval in the House of Lords ( Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C. 888, at 933]) and the Supreme Court of the United States: Banco Nacional de Cuba v Sabbatino [(1964) 376 U.S. 398, at 416]. So, in Oetjen v Central Leather Co . [(1918) 246 U.S. 297, at 304] the Supreme Court said: 
 
 
 
 
 
 "To permit the validity of the acts of one sovereign State to be re-examined and perhaps condemned by the courts of another would very certainly 'imperil the amicable relations between governments and vex the peace of nations'." 
 
 
 
 
 
 As Lord Wilberforce observed in Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C., at 931-932], in the context of considering the United States decisions, the principle is one of "judicial restraint or abstention" and is "inherent in the very nature of the judicial process". 
 
 
 

See also Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 559 (Mason CJ, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [27] [30] (North J) and Gamogab v Akiba (2007) 159 FCR 578 at [32] (Kiefel J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/81.html</AustLII>
<text>28 Section 143(1)(c) of the Evidence Act permits the Court to take judicial notice of each instrument, without proof, as an order of the Governor-General in Council made under ss 64 and 65 of the Constitution : Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582 at [35] . Each instrument is signed by the Governor-General, sealed with the Great Seal of Australia and counter-signed by the Prime Minister of Australia. In accordance with ss 150(3) and (4) of the Evidence Act , it is to be presumed that each instrument was properly attested and, when read with cl 8 in Pt 2 of the Dictionary of the Evidence Act , it is to be presumed that the reproduction of the instrument before the Court is a true copy of the original. There is no evidence to the contrary. Each instrument is admissible and its contents proven under ss 143(1)(c) and ss 150(3) and (4) of the Evidence Act .

29 As a result, the Attorney-General and the Justice Minister are each Ministers of State, members of the Federal Executive Council and directed and appointed by the Governor-General to administer the Attorney-General's Department. The legislation administered by that department includes the Extradition Act , including s 40.

30 The dual administration of the Attorney-General's Department (and therefore the Extradition Act ) is consistent not only with the exercise of executive power as prescribed by the Constitution but is expressly provided for by s 19A of the AI Act .

34 Secondly, the executive and administrative arrangements expressly provide that the Justice Minister is one of two Ministers to administer the Extradition Act (including s 40), being arrangements necessary in the interests of efficient government administration: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582 at [37] and [42] and Zoeller v Attorney-General for the Commonwealth &amp; Ors (1987) 16 FCR 153 at 165.

37 As noted earlier, ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended after the decision of Spender J and before the decision on appeal: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. Parliament amended ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act in 1998 (see Acts Interpretation Amendment Act 1998 (Cth)), because of the " serious implications for government administration " which resulted from the decision of Spender J: Explanatory Memorandum, Acts Interpretation Amendment Bill 1998 (Cth) at 1.

38 By the 1998 amendments ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended as follows:
 
 (1) the phrase "unless the contrary intention appears" was deleted from s 19 ; and
 
 (2) s 19A(1) was amended to provide that a reference to a Minister, whether specific or generic, was taken to be a reference to all Ministers appointed to administer a particular department.

39 The amendments were explained in the Explanatory Memorandum, Acts Interpretation Amendment Bill 1998 (Cth) in the following terms:
 
 
 "Item 3 Section 19 
 
 
 
 
 
 13. The phrase 'unless the contrary intention appears' has created problems in relation to Acts that provide for a Minister to delegate his or her powers, one view being that the existence of a power to delegate may evince a relevant contrary intention. Item 3 amends section 19 by deleting the reference to contrary intention to ensure that these problems are not perpetuated. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 14. In the Foster decision Spender J recognised that both Cabinet and the Prime Minister have traditionally been able to appoint a Minister or member of the Executive Council to exercise a statutory power vested in another Minister for and on behalf of that other Minister. In particular, His Honour noted that Cabinet or the Prime Minister may make an appointment of that kind where the other Minister is unable to exercise the relevant power through illness, absence or more generally. Section 19 of the Act is being retained to ensure that Cabinet and the Prime Minister retain the powers of appointment recognised in the Foster decision. 
 
 
 
 
 
 Item 4 Subsection 19A(1) 
 
 
 
 
 
 15. Item 4 amends subsection 19A(1) to provide that a reference to a Minister, whether specific or generic, is taken to be a reference to all Ministers appointed to administer a particular department, that is, all Ministers within the one portfolio. This will allow all Ministers within a portfolio to exercise relevant statutory powers of the portfolio Minister, where appropriate. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 16. The reference to 'contrary intention' has been retained in section 19A as there is no question of a power of delegation giving rise to a contrary intention for the purposes of that provision."

40 Against that background, it is apparent that s 19A of the AI Act was amended to ensure that the reference in a provision to a Minister (specific or generic) is taken to be a reference to " all Ministers appointed to administer a particular department, that is, all Ministers within the one portfolio ." Section 19A(1) of the AI Act expressly acknowledges not only that the joint administration of the Attorney-General's department is possible but, as the Explanatory Memorandum makes clear, the " serious implications for government administration " if such a situation were not permitted.

41 After ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended, the decision of Spender J went on appeal and was overturned: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. The Full Court dealt with s 19 of the AI Act before it was amended and held that: 
 
 (1) s 19 of the AI Act was not merely one in aid of interpretation of legislation but had a substantive effect: at [36];
 (2) efficient government administration requires that in many circumstances a Minister act through another, and not personally discharge all powers and functions bestowed on the office by statutes: at [37] citing Staughton LJ in R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 at 194 (adopted on appeal in the House of Lords: ([1994] 1 AC 531 at 566) and O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 11;
 (3) the appointment of two Ministers to administer the Department of State of the Attorney-General, and the Administrative Arrangements Order that the Extradition Act be administered by " a Minister of State administering " that Department, is itself a sufficient indication that the Executive Council contemplated that the exercise of powers vested in the Attorney-General by the Act would devolve to the Minister for Justice: at [40];
 (4) ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act do not indicate a contrary intention which excludes the operation of s 19 of the AI Act in respect of the exercise of power vested in the Attorney-General: at [42];
 (5) in determining whether a statute requires the power to be exercised personally by the person designated depends on the nature of the power and all the other circumstances of the case: at [42] citing Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 at 93 and O'Reilly at 11.

44 Finally, the fact that the Law Officers Act 1964 (Cth) gives to the Attorney-General a general power to delegate to the Solicitor-General (s 17(1)) or to the Secretary of the Attorney-General's Department or " to the person for the time being holding or performing the duties of the office specified in the instrument of delegation " (s 17(2)) all or any of his or her powers and functions under all or any of the laws of the Commonwealth, is further evidence that s 40 of the Extradition Act did not evince a contrary intention. As the Full Court said in Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582 at [43] :
 
 
 "That the laws of the Commonwealth permit the delegation of the powers reposed in the Attorney-General under the Extradition Act to others who are not directly answerable to Parliament, lends weight to the conclusion that the nature of the powers reposed in the Attorney-General under the Act need not be exercised personally by the holder of that office."

45 Although Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582 was concerned with ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act and the language of s 40 of the Extradition Act is different, the decision of the Full Court and the principles established by it are directly contrary to the Applicant's contentions. As explained above, there is nothing to suggest that s 40 of the Extradition Act evinces a contrary intention for the purposes of s 19A of the AI Act . To adopt the Applicant's construction of the two sections read together would require me to ignore the history and express words of s 19A of the AI Act and the observations of the Full Court in Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. There is no occasion to do so.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1974/20.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The argument proceeded as follows:
 
 (1) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act had its origins in the decision of Barwick CJ in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477. That case concerned s 21 of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 (Cth) ("the 1966 Act") which provided that " the Attorney-General may make a requisition to [a foreign state] for the surrender of the person ." Barwick CJ stated that the Crown prerogative to seek and accept the surrender of a fugitive from a treaty state to which the 1966 Act applied had been wholly displaced and that the " only power " to requisition a treaty state for the surrender of a fugitive was that of the Attorney-General: at 487. In other words, if a treaty exists between Australia and a foreign state regulating the surrender and requests for surrender of fugitives, then the Extradition Act wholly replaced the prerogative power to make a request for the return of a fugitive to Australia: Barwick CJ in Barton at 487;
 (2) the Extradition Act was enacted in 1988. Its principal objectives are stated in s 3 to be: 
 
 
 
 "(a) to codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia to extradition countries and New Zealand and, in particular, to provide for proceedings by which courts may determine whether a person is to be, or is eligible to be, extradited, without determining the guilt or innocence of the person of an offence; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) to facilitate the making of requests for extradition by Australia to other countries; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) to enable Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties." 
 
 
 
 
 (3) consistent with the language adopted by Barwick CJ in Barton , s 40 of the Extradition Act states that: 
 
 
 "A request by Australia for the surrender of a person from a country ... in relation to an offence against a law of Australia of which the person is accused or of which the person has been convicted shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ." 
 
 (Emphasis added.)
 
 
 
 (4) the Replacement Explanatory Memorandum to the Extradition Bill 1987 supports the contention that any request is only to be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. In relation to what became s 40 of the Extradition Act , the Explanatory Memorandum states at 41: 
 
 
 "This clause makes it clear that the only way in which extradition can be requested by Australia ...is by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ...." 
 
 
 
 (5) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act are clear and unambiguous and mean what they say: Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297 at 305 (per Gibbs CJ);
 (6) the Extradition Act involves the liberty of the subject and where statutory authority is given to interfere with that liberty, such interference can be effected only in accordance with the terms and conditions of that grant: Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [126] to [134];
 (7) the following passage of the unanimous decision of the High Court in Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496 at [39] that considered a request for extradition to Poland signed by the Attorney-General under s 40 of the Extradition Act explains the correct way in which a request to a foreign state is to be made and raises the question why the Request in relation to the Applicant was not signed by the Attorney-General: 
 
 
 "Section 40 of the Act is not expressed as a source of power to make requests for extradition. The power to make a request is vested in the Executive Government. Section 40 assumes the existence of the power, and regulates its exercise by providing that a request shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. The request in the present case complied with that provision. " 
 
 (Emphasis added.)

18 The Executive Government is established by Ch 2 of the Constitution . By virtue of s 61 of the Constitution , the executive power of the Commonwealth extends to the " execution and maintenance of [the] Constitution , and of the laws of the Commonwealth. " As Latham CJ said in R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 643 644 cited by Mason J in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 at 498:
 
 
 "The execution and maintenance of the Constitution , particularly when considered in relation to other countries, involves ... the establishment of relations at any time with other countries, including the acquisition of rights and obligations upon the international plane."

19 A request to a foreign state for the surrender of a person convicted of, or alleged to have committed, an offence against the laws of Australia is within the sphere of executive power: Barton at 484 - 485 (Barwick CJ), at 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), at 498 (Mason J) and at 505 (Jacobs J). While it is now accepted that legislative power has abrogated executive power in respect of the extradition of persons from Australia (see s 3(a) of the Extradition Act which purports to " codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia... "), requests for the return of fugitives to Australia remains an exercise of executive power. This power cannot be displaced except by a clear and unambiguous legislative provision to the contrary. Part IV of the Extradition Act does not displace or even attempt to displace the executive power to seek the return of fugitives to Australia: Oates at [32] to [35], [38] and [39] (Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ) and Barton at 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), at 501 (Mason J) and at 508 (Jacobs J); cf Barton at 488 (Barwick CJ).

20 Consistent with that principle, s 40 of the Extradition Act is not expressed as a source of power. It properly assumes that the power to make a request to a foreign state is vested in the executive: see Truong v R [2004] HCA 10 ; (2004) 223 CLR 122 at [80] ; Oates at [29] and [39]; Barton at 484 (Barwick CJ), 490 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), 498 499 (Mason J), 505 508 (Jacobs J); see also Replacement Explanatory Memorandum, Extradition Bill 1987 (Cth) at 41.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 </tocase>
<text>13 The argument proceeded as follows:
 
 (1) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act had its origins in the decision of Barwick CJ in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477. That case concerned s 21 of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 (Cth) ("the 1966 Act") which provided that " the Attorney-General may make a requisition to [a foreign state] for the surrender of the person ." Barwick CJ stated that the Crown prerogative to seek and accept the surrender of a fugitive from a treaty state to which the 1966 Act applied had been wholly displaced and that the " only power " to requisition a treaty state for the surrender of a fugitive was that of the Attorney-General: at 487. In other words, if a treaty exists between Australia and a foreign state regulating the surrender and requests for surrender of fugitives, then the Extradition Act wholly replaced the prerogative power to make a request for the return of a fugitive to Australia: Barwick CJ in Barton at 487;
 (2) the Extradition Act was enacted in 1988. Its principal objectives are stated in s 3 to be: 
 
 
 
 "(a) to codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia to extradition countries and New Zealand and, in particular, to provide for proceedings by which courts may determine whether a person is to be, or is eligible to be, extradited, without determining the guilt or innocence of the person of an offence; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) to facilitate the making of requests for extradition by Australia to other countries; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) to enable Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties." 
 
 
 
 
 (3) consistent with the language adopted by Barwick CJ in Barton , s 40 of the Extradition Act states that: 
 
 
 "A request by Australia for the surrender of a person from a country ... in relation to an offence against a law of Australia of which the person is accused or of which the person has been convicted shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ." 
 
 (Emphasis added.)
 
 
 
 (4) the Replacement Explanatory Memorandum to the Extradition Bill 1987 supports the contention that any request is only to be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. In relation to what became s 40 of the Extradition Act , the Explanatory Memorandum states at 41: 
 
 
 "This clause makes it clear that the only way in which extradition can be requested by Australia ...is by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ...." 
 
 
 
 (5) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act are clear and unambiguous and mean what they say: Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297 at 305 (per Gibbs CJ);
 (6) the Extradition Act involves the liberty of the subject and where statutory authority is given to interfere with that liberty, such interference can be effected only in accordance with the terms and conditions of that grant: Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [126] to [134];
 (7) the following passage of the unanimous decision of the High Court in Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496 at [39] that considered a request for extradition to Poland signed by the Attorney-General under s 40 of the Extradition Act explains the correct way in which a request to a foreign state is to be made and raises the question why the Request in relation to the Applicant was not signed by the Attorney-General: 
 
 
 "Section 40 of the Act is not expressed as a source of power to make requests for extradition. The power to make a request is vested in the Executive Government. Section 40 assumes the existence of the power, and regulates its exercise by providing that a request shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. The request in the present case complied with that provision. " 
 
 (Emphasis added.)

60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Carltona Ltd v Commissioners of Works [1943] 2 All ER 560 </tocase>
<text>43 Thirdly, it could not have been expected by Parliament that the Attorney-General personally would exercise each of the powers reposed in the Attorney-General under the Extradition Act in each and every case where extradition is sought from Australia or to Australia: see Lord Greene MR in Carltona Ltd v Commissioners of Works [1943] 2 All ER 560 at 563.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/26.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The argument proceeded as follows:
 
 (1) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act had its origins in the decision of Barwick CJ in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477. That case concerned s 21 of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 (Cth) ("the 1966 Act") which provided that " the Attorney-General may make a requisition to [a foreign state] for the surrender of the person ." Barwick CJ stated that the Crown prerogative to seek and accept the surrender of a fugitive from a treaty state to which the 1966 Act applied had been wholly displaced and that the " only power " to requisition a treaty state for the surrender of a fugitive was that of the Attorney-General: at 487. In other words, if a treaty exists between Australia and a foreign state regulating the surrender and requests for surrender of fugitives, then the Extradition Act wholly replaced the prerogative power to make a request for the return of a fugitive to Australia: Barwick CJ in Barton at 487;
 (2) the Extradition Act was enacted in 1988. Its principal objectives are stated in s 3 to be: 
 
 
 
 "(a) to codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia to extradition countries and New Zealand and, in particular, to provide for proceedings by which courts may determine whether a person is to be, or is eligible to be, extradited, without determining the guilt or innocence of the person of an offence; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) to facilitate the making of requests for extradition by Australia to other countries; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) to enable Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties." 
 
 
 
 
 (3) consistent with the language adopted by Barwick CJ in Barton , s 40 of the Extradition Act states that: 
 
 
 "A request by Australia for the surrender of a person from a country ... in relation to an offence against a law of Australia of which the person is accused or of which the person has been convicted shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ." 
 
 (Emphasis added.)
 
 
 
 (4) the Replacement Explanatory Memorandum to the Extradition Bill 1987 supports the contention that any request is only to be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. In relation to what became s 40 of the Extradition Act , the Explanatory Memorandum states at 41: 
 
 
 "This clause makes it clear that the only way in which extradition can be requested by Australia ...is by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ...." 
 
 
 
 (5) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act are clear and unambiguous and mean what they say: Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297 at 305 (per Gibbs CJ);
 (6) the Extradition Act involves the liberty of the subject and where statutory authority is given to interfere with that liberty, such interference can be effected only in accordance with the terms and conditions of that grant: Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [126] to [134];
 (7) the following passage of the unanimous decision of the High Court in Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496 at [39] that considered a request for extradition to Poland signed by the Attorney-General under s 40 of the Extradition Act explains the correct way in which a request to a foreign state is to be made and raises the question why the Request in relation to the Applicant was not signed by the Attorney-General: 
 
 
 "Section 40 of the Act is not expressed as a source of power to make requests for extradition. The power to make a request is vested in the Executive Government. Section 40 assumes the existence of the power, and regulates its exercise by providing that a request shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. The request in the present case complied with that provision. " 
 
 (Emphasis added.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Foster v Attorney-General (1998) 158 ALR 394</tocase>
<text>35 Thirdly, the history of s 19A(1) of the AI Act does not support the Applicant's contention. Section 19A(1) of the AI Act , in its current form, was enacted following the decision of Spender J in Foster v Attorney-General (1998) 158 ALR 394. That case concerned s 19 of the AI Act which, at that time, read:
 
 
 "Where in an Act any Minister is referred to, such reference shall unless the contrary intention appears, be deemed to include any Minister or member of the Executive Council for the time being acting for or on behalf of such Minister." 
 
 

Foster sought to challenge a warrant for his surrender which had been issued by the Justice Minister under s 23 of the Extradition Act on the ground, inter alia, that the warrant was a nullity because the discretion in s 22(2) of the Extradition Act could only be lawfully exercised by the Attorney-General and not the Justice Minister.

36 Spender J held that s 22(2) of the Extradition Act required the surrender of a person be determined by the Attorney-General or, by application of s 19 of the AI Act , by a Minister or member of the Executive Council validly authorized to act for the time being on behalf of the Attorney-General. At a practical level, Spender J held that s 19 of the AI Act was an interpretation section which was confined in its operation to cases of temporary absence, for example when a Minister was on holiday or was sick, and that the authorisation for another Minister to perform had to be by the Prime Minister or Cabinet rather than by the authorising Minister: Foster v Attorney-General (1998) 158 ALR 394 at 408.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gamogab v Akiba (2007) 159 FCR 578 </tocase>
<text>59 The courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory. This principle of non-adjudication is consistent with the international rule of comity which refers to the respect or courtesy accorded by a country to the laws and institutions of another. This was made clear in Attorney-General in and for the United Kingdom v Heinemann Publishers Australia Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40-41:
 
 
 "The rule is associated with a related principle of international law, which has long been recognized, namely that, in general, courts will not adjudicate upon the validity of acts and transactions of a foreign sovereign State within that sovereign's own territory. The statement of Fuller C.J. in Underhill v Hernandez [(1897) 168 U.S. 250, at 252] that "the courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory" has been repeated with approval in the House of Lords ( Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C. 888, at 933]) and the Supreme Court of the United States: Banco Nacional de Cuba v Sabbatino [(1964) 376 U.S. 398, at 416]. So, in Oetjen v Central Leather Co . [(1918) 246 U.S. 297, at 304] the Supreme Court said: 
 
 
 
 
 
 "To permit the validity of the acts of one sovereign State to be re-examined and perhaps condemned by the courts of another would very certainly 'imperil the amicable relations between governments and vex the peace of nations'." 
 
 
 
 
 
 As Lord Wilberforce observed in Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C., at 931-932], in the context of considering the United States decisions, the principle is one of "judicial restraint or abstention" and is "inherent in the very nature of the judicial process". 
 
 
 

See also Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 559 (Mason CJ, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [27] [30] (North J) and Gamogab v Akiba (2007) 159 FCR 578 at [32] (Kiefel J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 </tocase>
<text>59 The courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory. This principle of non-adjudication is consistent with the international rule of comity which refers to the respect or courtesy accorded by a country to the laws and institutions of another. This was made clear in Attorney-General in and for the United Kingdom v Heinemann Publishers Australia Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40-41:
 
 
 "The rule is associated with a related principle of international law, which has long been recognized, namely that, in general, courts will not adjudicate upon the validity of acts and transactions of a foreign sovereign State within that sovereign's own territory. The statement of Fuller C.J. in Underhill v Hernandez [(1897) 168 U.S. 250, at 252] that "the courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory" has been repeated with approval in the House of Lords ( Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C. 888, at 933]) and the Supreme Court of the United States: Banco Nacional de Cuba v Sabbatino [(1964) 376 U.S. 398, at 416]. So, in Oetjen v Central Leather Co . [(1918) 246 U.S. 297, at 304] the Supreme Court said: 
 
 
 
 
 
 "To permit the validity of the acts of one sovereign State to be re-examined and perhaps condemned by the courts of another would very certainly 'imperil the amicable relations between governments and vex the peace of nations'." 
 
 
 
 
 
 As Lord Wilberforce observed in Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C., at 931-932], in the context of considering the United States decisions, the principle is one of "judicial restraint or abstention" and is "inherent in the very nature of the judicial process". 
 
 
 

See also Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 559 (Mason CJ, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [27] [30] (North J) and Gamogab v Akiba (2007) 159 FCR 578 at [32] (Kiefel J).

60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/21.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The argument proceeded as follows:
 
 (1) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act had its origins in the decision of Barwick CJ in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477. That case concerned s 21 of the Extradition (Foreign States) Act 1966 (Cth) ("the 1966 Act") which provided that " the Attorney-General may make a requisition to [a foreign state] for the surrender of the person ." Barwick CJ stated that the Crown prerogative to seek and accept the surrender of a fugitive from a treaty state to which the 1966 Act applied had been wholly displaced and that the " only power " to requisition a treaty state for the surrender of a fugitive was that of the Attorney-General: at 487. In other words, if a treaty exists between Australia and a foreign state regulating the surrender and requests for surrender of fugitives, then the Extradition Act wholly replaced the prerogative power to make a request for the return of a fugitive to Australia: Barwick CJ in Barton at 487;
 (2) the Extradition Act was enacted in 1988. Its principal objectives are stated in s 3 to be: 
 
 
 
 "(a) to codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia to extradition countries and New Zealand and, in particular, to provide for proceedings by which courts may determine whether a person is to be, or is eligible to be, extradited, without determining the guilt or innocence of the person of an offence; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) to facilitate the making of requests for extradition by Australia to other countries; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) to enable Australia to carry out its obligations under extradition treaties." 
 
 
 
 
 (3) consistent with the language adopted by Barwick CJ in Barton , s 40 of the Extradition Act states that: 
 
 
 "A request by Australia for the surrender of a person from a country ... in relation to an offence against a law of Australia of which the person is accused or of which the person has been convicted shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ." 
 
 (Emphasis added.)
 
 
 
 (4) the Replacement Explanatory Memorandum to the Extradition Bill 1987 supports the contention that any request is only to be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. In relation to what became s 40 of the Extradition Act , the Explanatory Memorandum states at 41: 
 
 
 "This clause makes it clear that the only way in which extradition can be requested by Australia ...is by or with the authority of the Attorney-General ...." 
 
 
 
 (5) the express words of s 40 of the Extradition Act are clear and unambiguous and mean what they say: Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297 at 305 (per Gibbs CJ);
 (6) the Extradition Act involves the liberty of the subject and where statutory authority is given to interfere with that liberty, such interference can be effected only in accordance with the terms and conditions of that grant: Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [126] to [134];
 (7) the following passage of the unanimous decision of the High Court in Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496 at [39] that considered a request for extradition to Poland signed by the Attorney-General under s 40 of the Extradition Act explains the correct way in which a request to a foreign state is to be made and raises the question why the Request in relation to the Applicant was not signed by the Attorney-General: 
 
 
 "Section 40 of the Act is not expressed as a source of power to make requests for extradition. The power to make a request is vested in the Executive Government. Section 40 assumes the existence of the power, and regulates its exercise by providing that a request shall only be made by or with the authority of the Attorney-General. The request in the present case complied with that provision. " 
 
 (Emphasis added.)

17 The object of Part IV of the Extradition Act entitled " Extradition to Australia from Other Countries " (of which s 40 forms part) is " to facilitate the making of requests for extradition by Australia to other countries" : s 3(b) of the Extradition Act . It is not a code: Oates v Attorney-General (Cth) [2003] HCA 21 ; (2003) 214 CLR 496 at [38] (per Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ). A request to a foreign state for the return of a fugitive to Australia remains an exercise of executive power.

19 A request to a foreign state for the surrender of a person convicted of, or alleged to have committed, an offence against the laws of Australia is within the sphere of executive power: Barton at 484 - 485 (Barwick CJ), at 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), at 498 (Mason J) and at 505 (Jacobs J). While it is now accepted that legislative power has abrogated executive power in respect of the extradition of persons from Australia (see s 3(a) of the Extradition Act which purports to " codify the law relating to the extradition of persons from Australia... "), requests for the return of fugitives to Australia remains an exercise of executive power. This power cannot be displaced except by a clear and unambiguous legislative provision to the contrary. Part IV of the Extradition Act does not displace or even attempt to displace the executive power to seek the return of fugitives to Australia: Oates at [32] to [35], [38] and [39] (Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ) and Barton at 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), at 501 (Mason J) and at 508 (Jacobs J); cf Barton at 488 (Barwick CJ).

20 Consistent with that principle, s 40 of the Extradition Act is not expressed as a source of power. It properly assumes that the power to make a request to a foreign state is vested in the executive: see Truong v R [2004] HCA 10 ; (2004) 223 CLR 122 at [80] ; Oates at [29] and [39]; Barton at 484 (Barwick CJ), 490 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), 498 499 (Mason J), 505 508 (Jacobs J); see also Replacement Explanatory Memorandum, Extradition Bill 1987 (Cth) at 41.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/74.html</AustLII>
<text>41 After ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended, the decision of Spender J went on appeal and was overturned: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. The Full Court dealt with s 19 of the AI Act before it was amended and held that: 
 
 (1) s 19 of the AI Act was not merely one in aid of interpretation of legislation but had a substantive effect: at [36];
 (2) efficient government administration requires that in many circumstances a Minister act through another, and not personally discharge all powers and functions bestowed on the office by statutes: at [37] citing Staughton LJ in R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 at 194 (adopted on appeal in the House of Lords: ([1994] 1 AC 531 at 566) and O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 11;
 (3) the appointment of two Ministers to administer the Department of State of the Attorney-General, and the Administrative Arrangements Order that the Extradition Act be administered by " a Minister of State administering " that Department, is itself a sufficient indication that the Executive Council contemplated that the exercise of powers vested in the Attorney-General by the Act would devolve to the Minister for Justice: at [40];
 (4) ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act do not indicate a contrary intention which excludes the operation of s 19 of the AI Act in respect of the exercise of power vested in the Attorney-General: at [42];
 (5) in determining whether a statute requires the power to be exercised personally by the person designated depends on the nature of the power and all the other circumstances of the case: at [42] citing Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 at 93 and O'Reilly at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/52.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The Executive Government is established by Ch 2 of the Constitution . By virtue of s 61 of the Constitution , the executive power of the Commonwealth extends to the " execution and maintenance of [the] Constitution , and of the laws of the Commonwealth. " As Latham CJ said in R v Burgess; ex parte Henry [1936] HCA 52 ; (1936) 55 CLR 608 at 643 644 cited by Mason J in Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 at 498:
 
 
 "The execution and maintenance of the Constitution , particularly when considered in relation to other countries, involves ... the establishment of relations at any time with other countries, including the acquisition of rights and obligations upon the international plane."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 </tocase>
<text>41 After ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended, the decision of Spender J went on appeal and was overturned: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. The Full Court dealt with s 19 of the AI Act before it was amended and held that: 
 
 (1) s 19 of the AI Act was not merely one in aid of interpretation of legislation but had a substantive effect: at [36];
 (2) efficient government administration requires that in many circumstances a Minister act through another, and not personally discharge all powers and functions bestowed on the office by statutes: at [37] citing Staughton LJ in R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 at 194 (adopted on appeal in the House of Lords: ([1994] 1 AC 531 at 566) and O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 11;
 (3) the appointment of two Ministers to administer the Department of State of the Attorney-General, and the Administrative Arrangements Order that the Extradition Act be administered by " a Minister of State administering " that Department, is itself a sufficient indication that the Executive Council contemplated that the exercise of powers vested in the Attorney-General by the Act would devolve to the Minister for Justice: at [40];
 (4) ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act do not indicate a contrary intention which excludes the operation of s 19 of the AI Act in respect of the exercise of power vested in the Attorney-General: at [42];
 (5) in determining whether a statute requires the power to be exercised personally by the person designated depends on the nature of the power and all the other circumstances of the case: at [42] citing Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 at 93 and O'Reilly at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] UKHL 8 ; [1994] 1 AC 531</tocase>
<text>41 After ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended, the decision of Spender J went on appeal and was overturned: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. The Full Court dealt with s 19 of the AI Act before it was amended and held that: 
 
 (1) s 19 of the AI Act was not merely one in aid of interpretation of legislation but had a substantive effect: at [36];
 (2) efficient government administration requires that in many circumstances a Minister act through another, and not personally discharge all powers and functions bestowed on the office by statutes: at [37] citing Staughton LJ in R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 at 194 (adopted on appeal in the House of Lords: ([1994] 1 AC 531 at 566) and O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 11;
 (3) the appointment of two Ministers to administer the Department of State of the Attorney-General, and the Administrative Arrangements Order that the Extradition Act be administered by " a Minister of State administering " that Department, is itself a sufficient indication that the Executive Council contemplated that the exercise of powers vested in the Attorney-General by the Act would devolve to the Minister for Justice: at [40];
 (4) ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act do not indicate a contrary intention which excludes the operation of s 19 of the AI Act in respect of the exercise of power vested in the Attorney-General: at [42];
 (5) in determining whether a statute requires the power to be exercised personally by the person designated depends on the nature of the power and all the other circumstances of the case: at [42] citing Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 at 93 and O'Reilly at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>considered</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/51.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Consistent with that view, the Applicant does not dispute that the High Court in Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391 established, in the context of s 501 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ("the Migration Act ") read with s 19A of the AI Act , that the combined use of the words "only" with the word "personally" in referring to one minister did not prevent one of two ministers administering the Act exercising the power in question. However, the Applicant sought to distinguish Re Patterson on the grounds that it was concerned with the Migration Act , not the Extradition Act , and s 40 of the Extradition Act was in wholly different terms to s 501 of the Migration Act .

16 The Applicant's construction of s 40 of the Extradition Act should be rejected. First, it proceeds from a misunderstanding about the source of power to request extradition of a fugitive from a foreign State to Australia. Secondly, it ignores the relevant executive and administrative arrangements made by the Governor-General pursuant to ss 61 , 64 and 65 of the Constitution . Thirdly, it is contrary to the express words and history of s 19A of the AI Act , is contrary to authority and, if adopted, would not facilitate " efficient and effective government administration ": see Re Patterson at [15].

46 Finally, the Applicant's contentions are contrary to the decision of the High Court in Re Patterson; ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 207 CLR 391. In that case, the combined use of the words "only" with the word "personally" in referring to one Minister in s 501 of the Migration Act , read with s 19A of the AI Act , did not prevent the other of the two Ministers administering the Act exercising the power in question. Although that case was concerned with the Migration Act , not the Extradition Act , and s 40 of the Extradition Act was in wholly different terms to s 501 of the Migration Act , having regard to the nature and express words of each provision, a generally similar analysis should be made leading to the same result.

47 As noted earlier, after the decision of Spender J in Foster , s 19 of the AI Act was also amended. The Respondents contend that s 19 of the AI Act is an alternative to s 40 of the Extradition Act which provides an independent and separate justification for the Justice Minister to sign the Request because the administrative arrangements are sufficient to constitute an authorisation of the Justice Minister to act for the Attorney-General.

48 Given the conclusions I have reached about s 19A of the AI Act , it is unnecessary to resolve the application of s 19 of the AI Act . Sections 19 and 19A of the AI Act overlap. Where and how they overlap is neither necessary nor appropriate to resolve in this case. It is sufficient to note that, consistent with the decision of the Full Court in Foster , if for the purposes of s 19 of the AI Act (in its pre-amended form) the Attorney-General can write out an authorisation for another Minister authorising that Minister to exercise the power under ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act , there can be no doubt that the Governor-General, in this case on the advice of the Prime Minister, can provide such an authorisation exercising his power under s 64 of the Constitution .

49 This ground of review should be dismissed.

50 The Applicant's contention in relation to this ground is not supported by the facts and is contrary to fundamental principles of public international law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 </tocase>
<text>41 After ss 19 and 19A of the AI Act were amended, the decision of Spender J went on appeal and was overturned: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582. The Full Court dealt with s 19 of the AI Act before it was amended and held that: 
 
 (1) s 19 of the AI Act was not merely one in aid of interpretation of legislation but had a substantive effect: at [36];
 (2) efficient government administration requires that in many circumstances a Minister act through another, and not personally discharge all powers and functions bestowed on the office by statutes: at [37] citing Staughton LJ in R v Secretary of State for the Home Department, ex parte Doody [1993] QB 157 at 194 (adopted on appeal in the House of Lords: ([1994] 1 AC 531 at 566) and O'Reilly v Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1982] HCA 74 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 11;
 (3) the appointment of two Ministers to administer the Department of State of the Attorney-General, and the Administrative Arrangements Order that the Extradition Act be administered by " a Minister of State administering " that Department, is itself a sufficient indication that the Executive Council contemplated that the exercise of powers vested in the Attorney-General by the Act would devolve to the Minister for Justice: at [40];
 (4) ss 22(2) and 23 of the Extradition Act do not indicate a contrary intention which excludes the operation of s 19 of the AI Act in respect of the exercise of power vested in the Attorney-General: at [42];
 (5) in determining whether a statute requires the power to be exercised personally by the person designated depends on the nature of the power and all the other circumstances of the case: at [42] citing Re Reference under Ombudsman Act 1976 (1979) 2 ALD 86 at 93 and O'Reilly at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.)</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 </tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Truong v R [2004] HCA 10 ; (2004) 223 CLR 122</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/10.html</AustLII>
<text>20 Consistent with that principle, s 40 of the Extradition Act is not expressed as a source of power. It properly assumes that the power to make a request to a foreign state is vested in the executive: see Truong v R [2004] HCA 10 ; (2004) 223 CLR 122 at [80] ; Oates at [29] and [39]; Barton at 484 (Barwick CJ), 490 491 (McTiernan and Menzies JJ), 498 499 (Mason J), 505 508 (Jacobs J); see also Replacement Explanatory Memorandum, Extradition Bill 1987 (Cth) at 41.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.)</tocase>
<text>60 French J made the following observations on the application of non-adjudication to extradition cases in Cabal v United Mexican States (No. 3) (2000) 186 ALR 188 at [104]:
 
 
 "[I]t is important to bear in mind that the general functioning of the judicial system of an extradition country is not a matter for this court. Such judgments, no doubt, have a part to play in the decision of the executive government in entering into the treaty. They may also, at least in theory, have a bearing upon the legislative decision whether or not to disallow particular treaty regulations and in the ultimate decision of an Attorney-General whether or not to surrender a requested person. The acceptability to Australia of the system of criminal justice in an extradition country is an issue "...to be determined by the Government of the Commonwealth when deciding to extend the application of the Extradition Act to the State in question, whether by treaty or regulation, and, in a given case, perhaps before ordering the surrender of the fugitive ... in exercise of the discretion ... given the Attorney-General": Wiest v Director of Public Prosecutions (1988) 23 FCR 472 at 514; 86 ALR 464 per Gummow J. That is not to say that governments and judicial systems of requesting countries may not have changed significantly since a treaty of extradition was entered into. But the continuance of the treaty and ultimate surrender decisions are still matters for the executive and not for the courts. " 
 
 
 
 (Emphasis added.) 
 
 
 
 

See also Todhunter v Attorney-General (Cth) (1994) 52 FCR 228 at 250 251; Sun Lau v Australia [1999] BCJ No 2971 at [73] [77] citing United States of America v McVey (1992) 77 C.C.C. (3d) 1 (S.C.C.) at 40 and Schmidt v the Queen (1987) 33 C.C.C. (3d) 193 (S.C.C.); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [33] [36] citing R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Johnson [1998] 4 All ER 635 at 644, Royal Government of Greece v Governor of Brixton Prison [1971] AC 250 at 280 and Republic of Argentina v Mellino [1987] 1 SCR 536 at 554; R v Secretary of State for the Home Department; ex parte Hill [1999] QB 886 at 905.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/55.html</AustLII>
<text>59 The courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory. This principle of non-adjudication is consistent with the international rule of comity which refers to the respect or courtesy accorded by a country to the laws and institutions of another. This was made clear in Attorney-General in and for the United Kingdom v Heinemann Publishers Australia Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40-41:
 
 
 "The rule is associated with a related principle of international law, which has long been recognized, namely that, in general, courts will not adjudicate upon the validity of acts and transactions of a foreign sovereign State within that sovereign's own territory. The statement of Fuller C.J. in Underhill v Hernandez [(1897) 168 U.S. 250, at 252] that "the courts of one country will not sit in judgment on the acts of the government of another done within its own territory" has been repeated with approval in the House of Lords ( Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C. 888, at 933]) and the Supreme Court of the United States: Banco Nacional de Cuba v Sabbatino [(1964) 376 U.S. 398, at 416]. So, in Oetjen v Central Leather Co . [(1918) 246 U.S. 297, at 304] the Supreme Court said: 
 
 
 
 
 
 "To permit the validity of the acts of one sovereign State to be re-examined and perhaps condemned by the courts of another would very certainly 'imperil the amicable relations between governments and vex the peace of nations'." 
 
 
 
 
 
 As Lord Wilberforce observed in Buttes Gas v Hammer [[1982] A.C., at 931-932], in the context of considering the United States decisions, the principle is one of "judicial restraint or abstention" and is "inherent in the very nature of the judicial process". 
 
 
 

See also Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 559 (Mason CJ, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ); McCrea v Minister for Customs and Justice (2004) 212 ALR 297 at [27] [30] (North J) and Gamogab v Akiba (2007) 159 FCR 578 at [32] (Kiefel J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Zoeller v Attorney-General for the Commonwealth &amp; Ors (1987) 16 FCR 153 </tocase>
<text>34 Secondly, the executive and administrative arrangements expressly provide that the Justice Minister is one of two Ministers to administer the Extradition Act (including s 40), being arrangements necessary in the interests of efficient government administration: Attorney-General v Foster [1999] FCA 81 ; (1999) 84 FCR 582 at [37] and [42] and Zoeller v Attorney-General for the Commonwealth &amp; Ors (1987) 16 FCR 153 at 165.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>