<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Highstoke Pty Ltd v Hayes Knight GTO Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 13 (16 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/13.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hayes Knight GTO Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2005] FCA 1509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1509.html</AustLII>
<text>22 On 26 October 2005 Siopis J dismissed Hayes Knight's interlocutory application in the Judicial Review Proceedings seeking the provision by ASIC of reasons for its decisions of 3 August 2005. His Honour did, however, make an order that ASIC give discovery of documents relating to its decision: Hayes Knight GTO Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2005] FCA 1509.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gould v Brown [1998] HCA 6 ; (1998) 193 CLR 346</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/6.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The applications by Hayes Knight in the Examination Proceedings and the Judicial Review Proceedings came on for hearing on 18 November 2005. In opening, counsel for Hayes Knight, Mr Donaldson SC, drew the Court's attention to a passage from the judgment of Gaudron J in Gould v Brown [1998] HCA 6 ; (1998) 193 CLR 346 at 405 in which her Honour said: 
 
 '... to the extent that the power conferred by Ch 5, Pt 5.9 is not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of the corporation, it is not properly characterised as judicial power.' 
 

Counsel submitted that there was a question whether Pt 5.9 went beyond the judicial power of the Commonwealth to the extent that it authorised examination unrelated to a matter, such as the winding up of a corporation. Discussion ensued about the possibility of transferring the matter to the Supreme Court of Western Australia but, as was pointed out by counsel for Hayes Knight, that did not cure the difficulty as the Supreme Court would still be asked to exercise federal jurisdiction and so confined by the constraints of Ch III of the Constitution . In the event, the hearings were adjourned to enable the parties to consider their positions. Ultimately Notices of a Constitutional Matter were given under s 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) to the Attorneys-General of the Commonwealth and the States.

24 On 8 February 2006 ASIC filed a notice of intervention in the Examination Proceedings in relation to the Hayes Knight application to discharge the examination summons. Both applications were subsequently relisted for hearing on 24 and 25 May 2006.

25 In the Examination Proceedings a "Minute of Proposed Amended Interlocutory Process" was filed on 3 November 2005. On 7 November 2005 Siopis J directed that it stand as the amended interlocutory processes of Hayes Knight and Mr O'Brien. That is the document that can be regarded as the initiating document in the discharge application brought by Hayes Knight and Mr O'Brien.

71 The cross vesting arrangements under the Corporations Law were challenged in Gould v Brown as an element of a challenge to the exercise of the examinations power under ss 596A and 596B by the Federal Court. The High Court divided evenly on the challenge to the cross vesting scheme which was therefore upheld as it had been in the Full Federal Court below. It was, however, only a matter of time before the validity of the cross vesting arrangements would come up again for consideration by the High Court. They did so and were held by a majority in Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 to be invalid to the extent that the State Corporations Laws purported to confer jurisdiction on the Federal Court.

99 In Gould v Brown summonses for examination issued by the Federal Court under ss 596A and 596B of the Corporations Law were challenged on the basis that the Court had no jurisdiction to issue them or conduct examinations. The first basis of the challenge, which failed, on the evenly divided vote of the Court, was that the State Parliaments had no power to invest in the Federal Court jurisdiction in matters arising under the Corporations Laws of the States. The second basis, relevant here, was that the examination function conferred on the Federal Court by the State laws did not involve the exercise of judicial power.

102 Gaudron J held that Ch III would preclude conferral on the Federal Court of a non-judicial examinations power "not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of corporations" (405). However there was nothing to prevent the Commonwealth from conferring power of that kind on the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory (405). Reference should be made in that regard to the developing jurisprudence about the interaction of Ch III and the Territories' power in Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226; Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591; Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171 and in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Hely J in North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204 at [106] [133].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Greys Brewery Company (1883) 2 Ch D 400</tocase>
<text>46 Statutory powers of examination of persons in connection with the affairs of bankrupts predated the creation of such powers with respect to the affairs of companies. What has been called the first bankruptcy statute in England, the 1842 Act, 34 and 35 Hen VIII c 4, provided for the examination of third persons about a debtor's estate. The earliest such provision in the companies laws of the United Kingdom was s 15 of the Joint Stock Companies Winding Up Act 1844 (UK) (7 and 8 Vict 111). Of that provision it is said in the 5 th Edition of McPherson's Law of Company Liquidation (Thomson, at 15.500):
 
 'It empowered the court to summon and examine persons who were thought to be capable of giving information about the property and past transactions of the company. But the primary purpose of examinations of this kind was to assist the liquidator in locating the assets.' 
 

Like powers were conferred by s 115 of the Companies Act 1862 (UK) (25 and 26 Vict c 89). By that section the court was given power to summon before it any person whom it might deem capable of giving information concerning the trade dealings, estate, or effects of the company. The examination was in private. It was referred to by Chitty J as the "Star Chamber" clause: Re Greys Brewery Company (1883) 25 Ch D 400 at 408. It was analogous to s 120 of the Bankruptcy Law Consolidation Act 1849 (UK) (12 &amp; 13 Vict 106) which was in force when the 1862 Act was passed. Sir George Jessell MR in Re Gold Company (1879) 12 Ch D 77 at 85 said: 
 
 
 'In fact the whole object of the section is to assimilate the practice in winding-up to the practice in bankruptcy, which was established in order to enable assignees, who are now called trustees, in bankruptcy to find out facts before they brought an action, so as to avoid incurring the expense of some hundreds of pounds in bringing an unsuccessful action, when they might, by examining a witness or two, have discovered at a trifling expense that an action could not succeed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Gold Company (1879) 12 Ch D 77</tocase>
<text>46 Statutory powers of examination of persons in connection with the affairs of bankrupts predated the creation of such powers with respect to the affairs of companies. What has been called the first bankruptcy statute in England, the 1842 Act, 34 and 35 Hen VIII c 4, provided for the examination of third persons about a debtor's estate. The earliest such provision in the companies laws of the United Kingdom was s 15 of the Joint Stock Companies Winding Up Act 1844 (UK) (7 and 8 Vict 111). Of that provision it is said in the 5 th Edition of McPherson's Law of Company Liquidation (Thomson, at 15.500):
 
 'It empowered the court to summon and examine persons who were thought to be capable of giving information about the property and past transactions of the company. But the primary purpose of examinations of this kind was to assist the liquidator in locating the assets.' 
 

Like powers were conferred by s 115 of the Companies Act 1862 (UK) (25 and 26 Vict c 89). By that section the court was given power to summon before it any person whom it might deem capable of giving information concerning the trade dealings, estate, or effects of the company. The examination was in private. It was referred to by Chitty J as the "Star Chamber" clause: Re Greys Brewery Company (1883) 25 Ch D 400 at 408. It was analogous to s 120 of the Bankruptcy Law Consolidation Act 1849 (UK) (12 &amp; 13 Vict 106) which was in force when the 1862 Act was passed. Sir George Jessell MR in Re Gold Company (1879) 12 Ch D 77 at 85 said: 
 
 
 'In fact the whole object of the section is to assimilate the practice in winding-up to the practice in bankruptcy, which was established in order to enable assignees, who are now called trustees, in bankruptcy to find out facts before they brought an action, so as to avoid incurring the expense of some hundreds of pounds in bringing an unsuccessful action, when they might, by examining a witness or two, have discovered at a trifling expense that an action could not succeed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Csidei; Ex parte Andrew (1979) 39 FLR 387</tocase>
<text>47 The connection between examination under bankruptcy and winding up laws has been recognised over more than 125 years that have passed since Jessell MR made his comments. The position historically is no different in Australia. As Lockhart J said in Re Csidei; Ex parte Andrew (1979) 39 FLR 387 at 390: 
 
 '... the process of examining persons in the winding up of companies has been borrowed from the law of bankruptcy and the purpose of the inquisitorial powers conferred by bankruptcy and company legislation is much the same.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ex parte Barnes (1896) AC 146</tocase>
<text>48 Section 8 of the Companies (Winding Up) Act 1890 (UK) provided for the examination by the court of promoters, officers and other persons who had past connections with the company following upon a report to the court by the official receiver. Unlike s 115 of the 1862 Act, which remained in force, s 8 provided for public examinations: See Ex parte Barnes (1896) AC 146. Its introduction in England in 1890 is described in McPherson as "... part of the general policy in England at the time assimilating liquidations with bankruptcy" (at 15-500). The Australian colonies prior to federation enacted companies statutes based on the Companies Act 1862 (UK).

49 In the first half of the twentieth century the laws of the United Kingdom relating to companies were reviewed at 20 year intervals by a Departmental Committee appointed by the Board of Trade. This resulted in consolidations of the Companies Act in 1908, 1929 and 1948: Gower Principles of Modern Company Law (6 th edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, 1997) at 48-49. Although the Companies Acts of the Australian States were based on the UK models differences developed over time between them. The inconveniences caused by these differences led to the development, by agreement between the States and the Commonwealth, of a Uniform Companies Bill based on the Companies Act 1958 (Vic). In 1961 and 1962 the States each passed a Companies Act based on the Bill. The Commonwealth made Companies Ordinances in like terms for the Australian Capital Territory, the Northern Territory and what was the then Territory of Papua New Guinea: Fords Principles of Corporations Law (12 th Edition, Butterworths, 2005) at [2-170], see also Ford HAJ, Principles of Company Law (Butterworths, 1974) at [111].

50 The powers of examination of persons in connection with the court ordered winding up of companies were found in ss 249 and 250 of the Companies Act 1961 . The two sections were located in Div 2 of Pt 10 entitled "Winding up by the Court". They were based on ss 268 and 270 of the Companies Act 1948 (UK). Section 249 conferred power on the court to "summon before it any officer of the company or person known or suspected to have in his possession any property of the company or supposed to be indebted to the company, or any person whom the court deems capable of giving information concerning the promotion, formation, trade dealings, affairs or property of the company" (s 249(1)). Such an examination could be held, if the court so directed, before a magistrate (s 249(4)). The section was silent on whether such examinations were to be held in public. Section 250 conferred power on the court to order a public examination of persons or officers of the company where the liquidator had made a report to the court alleging the commission of a fraud or the concealment of any material fact by a promoter or officer of the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Rolls Razor Ltd [1968] 3 All ER 698</tocase>
<text>51 The purpose of s 268 of the Companies Act 1948 (UK) on which s 249 was based was described by Buckley J in Re Rolls Razor Ltd [1968] 3 All ER 698 thus (at 700): 
 
 'The powers conferred by s 268 are powers directed to enabling the court to help a liquidator to discover the truth of the circumstances connected with the affairs of the company, information of trading, dealings and so forth, in order that the liquidator may be able, as effectively as possible and I think, with as little expense as possible and with as much expedition as possible, to complete his function as liquidator, to put the affairs of the company in order and to carry out the liquidation in all its various aspects, including of course the getting in of any assets of the company available in the liquidation.'

52 There has been debate in Australian and English authorities about whether the examination power permits "fishing" questions: See: Keay AR, " Gone Fishing!" Is it Legitimate in an Examination Under Section 597 of the Corporations Law? 1991, 9 C &amp; SLJ 70. The authorities and the issues discussed in that article revolved around the difficulties facing liquidators trying to obtain information about the affairs of a company in often chaotic circumstances following its winding up.

53 A broader power of examination was introduced into the Companies Act 1961 by the Companies Act Amendment Act 1969 (WA) which enacted s 367A. That section provided, in subs (1): 
 
 'Where it appears to the Attorney General that any officer or former officer of a company to which this section applies has conducted himself in such a way that the officer or former officer has rendered himself liable to action by the company in relation to the performance of his duties as an officer of the company, the Attorney General, or any person who is authorised in that behalf by the Attorney General, may apply ex parte to the Court for an order that the officer or former officer shall attend before the Court on a day to be appointed by the Court to be examined as to his conduct and dealings as an officer of the company.' (emphasis added) 


Section 367A(2) provided that any examination under that section should not be held in open court unless the court otherwise ordered. The range of companies encompassed by the term "a company to which this section applies" in s 367A was limited by s 367C(1) to companies which were in the course of being wound up or were under official management, companies in respect of which an inspector had been appointed and companies in respect of which a receiver and manager had been appointed either by the court or under an instrument. It also extended to any company which had ceased to carry on business or was unable to pay its debts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/21.html</AustLII>
<text>57 The operation of s 541 was discussed by the High Court in Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486 in the context of its effect upon the privilege of self incrimination. Mason CJ, in the leading majority judgment, described the section as creating "a system of discovery". It gave to the liquidator rights not possessed by an ordinary litigant. The Chief Justice quoted with approval from the judgment of Street J in Re Hugh J Roberts Pty Ltd (1970) 91 WN (NSW) 537 at 541 when he said that it must be accepted that the section applies equally to proceedings which a liquidator: 
 
 '.. might be able to bring, proceedings he contemplates bringing, proceedings he has decided to bring, and proceedings he has already brought." 
 

See also: Rothwells Ltd (No 2) (1989) 7 ACLC 576 at 588 (Nicholson J) in which authorities relevant to the scope of the inquiry which may be undertaken under compulsory examination were collected. In that judgment Nicholson J acknowledged a difference of approach between Australian and English authorities the latter holding, as a general rule, that a liquidator could not undertake such an examination when a firm decision had been taken to commence proceedings to which the proposed examination was relevant. The Australian approach to that point merely required the court to treat the liquidator's application with greater caution (588).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Hugh J Roberts Pty Ltd (1970) 91 WN (NSW) 537</tocase>
<text>57 The operation of s 541 was discussed by the High Court in Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486 in the context of its effect upon the privilege of self incrimination. Mason CJ, in the leading majority judgment, described the section as creating "a system of discovery". It gave to the liquidator rights not possessed by an ordinary litigant. The Chief Justice quoted with approval from the judgment of Street J in Re Hugh J Roberts Pty Ltd (1970) 91 WN (NSW) 537 at 541 when he said that it must be accepted that the section applies equally to proceedings which a liquidator: 
 
 '.. might be able to bring, proceedings he contemplates bringing, proceedings he has decided to bring, and proceedings he has already brought." 
 

See also: Rothwells Ltd (No 2) (1989) 7 ACLC 576 at 588 (Nicholson J) in which authorities relevant to the scope of the inquiry which may be undertaken under compulsory examination were collected. In that judgment Nicholson J acknowledged a difference of approach between Australian and English authorities the latter holding, as a general rule, that a liquidator could not undertake such an examination when a firm decision had been taken to commence proceedings to which the proposed examination was relevant. The Australian approach to that point merely required the court to treat the liquidator's application with greater caution (588).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rothwells Ltd (No 2) (1989) 7 ACLC 576</tocase>
<text>57 The operation of s 541 was discussed by the High Court in Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486 in the context of its effect upon the privilege of self incrimination. Mason CJ, in the leading majority judgment, described the section as creating "a system of discovery". It gave to the liquidator rights not possessed by an ordinary litigant. The Chief Justice quoted with approval from the judgment of Street J in Re Hugh J Roberts Pty Ltd (1970) 91 WN (NSW) 537 at 541 when he said that it must be accepted that the section applies equally to proceedings which a liquidator: 
 
 '.. might be able to bring, proceedings he contemplates bringing, proceedings he has decided to bring, and proceedings he has already brought." 
 

See also: Rothwells Ltd (No 2) (1989) 7 ACLC 576 at 588 (Nicholson J) in which authorities relevant to the scope of the inquiry which may be undertaken under compulsory examination were collected. In that judgment Nicholson J acknowledged a difference of approach between Australian and English authorities the latter holding, as a general rule, that a liquidator could not undertake such an examination when a firm decision had been taken to commence proceedings to which the proposed examination was relevant. The Australian approach to that point merely required the court to treat the liquidator's application with greater caution (588).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>New South Wales v Commonwealth [1990] HCA 2 ; (1990) 169 CLR 482</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/2.html</AustLII>
<text>58 In 1989 the Commonwealth, in reliance upon the Corporations power in s 51(xx) of the Commonwealth Constitution , passed the Corporations Act 1989 (Cth) imposing a national scheme of corporate regulation. It also established the Australian Securities Commission. However in New South Wales v Commonwealth [1990] HCA 2 ; (1990) 169 CLR 482 the High Court held that the Commonwealth did not have power to make laws about the incorporation of companies. This led to the introduction of the 1991 Cooperative Scheme. The Commonwealth Parliament enacted the Corporations Act 1989 as a law of the Government of the Australian Capital Territory pursuant to s 122 of the Constitution . Each of the States then passed its own Corporations Act applying the Corporations Law set out in the Corporations Act 1989 and the Australian Securities Commission Act 1989 as laws of the State. Each State conferred jurisdiction on the Federal Court "with respect to civil matters arising under the Corporations Law of [the State]". Like jurisdiction was conferred by each State Act on the Supreme Court of the State and the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory. The scheme reflected the more general provisions of the reciprocal Federal and State cross vesting legislation which had been introduced in 1987. It provided a special purpose cross vesting arrangement. It operated from 1 January 1991.

59 Section 597 of the Corporations Act 1989 and the Corporations Law of each State reflected s 541 of the former Companies Codes. As the Explanatory Memorandum for the Corporations Bill 1988 succinctly stated:
 
 'This provision is based on CA s 541. ' 
 

The examination power conferred by s 597 was subsequently described as: 
 
 
 'In many respects a conflation of the powers of examination in ss 249, 250 and 367A of the Uniform Companies Act 1961." 

AR Keay , op cit at 70.

Conflation as confusion was the view of the new provisions advanced by Parker G in Liquidator's Examinations (1993) 10 Aust Bar Rev 25. He found it hard to escape the conclusion that most of the changes made in 1981 were accidental (at 29): 
 
 
 'The Explanatory Memoranda betrayed no awareness of the separate origins and purposes of the examination provisions which were being fused together. Not all the changes made to the previous law were identified. No reasons were given for those that were identified.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 446</tocase>
<text>60 The legislative antecedents of s 597 were discussed by Lockhart J (Beaumont and Gummow JJ concurring) in Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 446 at 452-453. His Honour referred to the "long history" of the section in companies legislation and noted that neither s 597 nor its predecessor, s 541 of the Companies Code, had been confined to companies in the course of being wound up. He referred also to the "close correspondence" between the "inquisitorial provisions" under the companies legislation and the equivalent provisions with respect to individuals under bankruptcy legislation. He said (at 453): 
 
 'Like its predecessors, s 597 plays an important role in the administration of companies in liquidation, other administrations in insolvency and "external administrations" generally:...' 
 

He contrasted such provisions with those which relate to the investigation of the affairs of companies (whether or not in the course of being wound up) by government regulatory authorities and the making of reports by those authorities. The Compass case was concerned with the effect of s 597 upon legal professional privilege.

89 In my respectful opinion, the weight of authority, to the extent that it has considered the matter tends to support the proposition that ss 596A and 596B and their predecessors have been seen as provisions applicable to companies in one or other form of administration and not as applicable to companies at large. So much appears from the judgment of the Full Court in Re Compass Airlines and the Court of Appeal of New South Wales in HongKong Bank. New Zealand Steel also appears to be consistent with the views expressed by Gleeson J that the statutory context of s 597 was that of "external administration". It follows, that I would not, with respect, agree with the obiter observations at [84] of the Wainter judgment which would see the application of ss 596A and 596B extended to solvent corporations not under any form of external administration.

103 Neither McHugh J nor Gummow J who held the cross vesting of jurisdiction to be invalid made any comment on the characterisation of the examination process. Kirby J who held the cross vesting provisions to be valid, said that the examination function was "... a necessary and usual step in the process of the judicial winding up of a company". He acknowledged that it was a more difficult question whether the extension of the power to other "eligible applicants" such as the Australian Securities Commission and the inclusion of other inquisitorial powers contaminated the legislative provisions in such a way that they could not be severed to uphold permissible provisions and exercise the impermissible. As to that he agreed with the reasons of Brennan CJ and Toohey J (500).

104 Spinks v Prentice (1998) 87 FCR 89 was one of a group of appeals decided in conjunction with Re Wakim . It was an appeal from the Full Court of the Federal Court with respect to an order for examination of former officers of a company in liquidation. The company was taken to be incorporated in the Australian Capital Territory. The Full Court held that the Corporations Act 1989 (Cth), which applied the Corporations Law to the ACT, validly conferred jurisdiction on the Federal Court to entertain the application for an examination summons. The examination orders were also challenged before the Full Court on the basis that they did not involve an exercise of judicial power. As to that the Court said (at 96):
 
 'It is true that, although there is no challenge to the winding up order made here, s 596A would permit an examination where there has been no winding up. But given the long history of courts exercising such powers, we can see nothing foreign to the exercise of judicial power in this aspect of s 596A.' 
 

They referred to the Compass Airlines and Grosvenor Hall cases. It is not clear, given the absence of any long history of judicial examination of corporations at large unrelated to winding up or other judicial procedures, whether their Honours were saying that applications under s 596A when there was no winding up order or pending court proceedings were an exercise of judicial power. To the extent that they were so saying, their observations were dicta.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Murphy (1992) 28 NSWLR 512</tocase>
<text>61 The extension of the examination power to companies under external administration, not limited to winding up, was noted by Gleeson CJ (Mahoney and Priestley JJA agreeing) in HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Murphy (1992) 28 NSWLR 512 at 521. His Honour said: 
 
 'The statutory context of " external administration ", in which s 597 has its place, throws light on the purposes for which the power to order examinations (or to authorise persons to apply for examination orders) is conferred. Those purposes include the protection of shareholders and creditors and of interested members of the public. They are not however confined to the need for such protection in the case of winding up. Winding up is only one form of external administration. The scope of s 597 is wider.' 
 

The company whose officers were the subject of examination in that case was the former trustee of unit trusts known as the Estate Mortgage Trust. The trustee itself was in liquidation. The question whether s 597 was limited to companies in liquidation was relevant because s 601 of the Corporations Law stated that its provisions with respect to winding up did not apply to any body corporate, the winding up of which was started before the commencement of the chapter. The section was held not to apply to s 597 because that section was not a law with respect to winding up.

62 The Corporations Law was amended by the Corporate Law Reform Act 1992 (Cth) which introduced a new Div 1 in Pt 5.9. That Division was entitled "Examining a person about a corporation". It comprised ss 596A to 596F inclusive. Section 597 was reduced to its present form as a provision about the way in which examinations authorised under ss 596A and 596B are to be conducted.

63 The 1992 amendments implemented the Report of the Australian Law Reform Commission in its General Insolvency Inquiry Report No 45 (The Harmer Report). In par 584 of that Report the chief purposes of inquisitorial examinations in bankruptcy and company insolvency law were described thus: 
 
 '... to facilitate the recovery of property, to discover whether conduct of the insolvent led to the insolvency and to investigate possible causes of action against third parties.' 
 

The Commission recommended that company law be brought into closer alignment with bankruptcy law by allowing examination without court order of any person who had been a relevant company officer within two years before winding up commenced (par 586). It also recommended the retention of the requirement for a court order for examination of persons other than officers of the company who might nevertheless be able to provide information relating to the company's affairs. The Commission recommended as wide a definition of "examinable affairs" as applied to bankrupts under recent amendments. It agreed with the observation by Lockhart J in re Csidei that "the very nature and breadth of the inquisitorial power ... requires the exercise by the Court or Registrar of considerable care before it is invoked". On that basis it recommended that applications to the Court for examination orders be supported by affidavit.

68 In New Zealand Steel (Australia) Pty Ltd v Burton (1994) 13 ACSR 610 Hayne J, in the Supreme Court of Victoria, quoted and evidently adopted for the purposes of s 596B of the Corporations Law, what Gleeson CJ had said in HongKong Bank v Murphy . His Honour did so in aid of the proposition that (at 616): 
 
 '... no longer are the examination provisions of the companies legislation to be regarded as restricted to cases in which the company has been wound up and it therefore follows that the provisions are not to be limited to cases in which the examination will be for the purpose of a winding up and the benefit of those interested in that winding up.' 
 

In New Zealand Steel the company whose examinable affairs were in issue had a receiver and manager appointed. The question before the court was whether the examination proposed was an abuse of process because it was directed to obtaining a private forensic advantage in pending litigation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>New Zealand Steel (Australia) Pty Ltd v Burton (1994) 13 ACSR 610</tocase>
<text>68 In New Zealand Steel (Australia) Pty Ltd v Burton (1994) 13 ACSR 610 Hayne J, in the Supreme Court of Victoria, quoted and evidently adopted for the purposes of s 596B of the Corporations Law, what Gleeson CJ had said in HongKong Bank v Murphy . His Honour did so in aid of the proposition that (at 616): 
 
 '... no longer are the examination provisions of the companies legislation to be regarded as restricted to cases in which the company has been wound up and it therefore follows that the provisions are not to be limited to cases in which the examination will be for the purpose of a winding up and the benefit of those interested in that winding up.' 
 

In New Zealand Steel the company whose examinable affairs were in issue had a receiver and manager appointed. The question before the court was whether the examination proposed was an abuse of process because it was directed to obtaining a private forensic advantage in pending litigation.

77 Lander J made some observations relevant to the question now before the Court on whether Pt 5.9 is limited in its application to the examinable affairs of corporations under external administration. At one point he said of s 596A (at [84]): 
 
 'The corporation may be in administration, subject to a deed of company arrangement, or being wound up. However, that is not essential. ASIC, or a person authorised by ASIC, could apply to summon an examinable officer about the corporation's examinable affairs even where the company is solvent and still trading provided that the person is an examinable officer at the time of the application: s 596A(b)(iv).' 
 

That observation was, with respect, obiter as the case before the Court concerned the examinable affairs of a company in liquidation. And later in the reasons for judgment his Honour agreed with the observations of Hayne J in New Zealand Steel , and said (at [245]):
 
 
 'In my opinion, the procedure in Pt 5.9 of the Law and the Act is to aid persons who have the responsibility of the external administration of the company in carrying out their duties.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Grosvenor Hill (Qld) Pty Ltd v Barber (1994) 48 FCR 301</tocase>
<text>69 A broad view of "examinable affairs" was adopted by the Full Federal Court in Grosvenor Hill (Qld) Pty Ltd v Barber (1994) 48 FCR 301. In that case the challenged orders had been made under s 596B and had required a valuer employed by Grosvenor Hill to be examined to determine whether the liquidators of a second company, Interchase Corporation Ltd (In Liq), had a good cause of action for damages against Grosvenor Hill in respect of valuation advice which the individuals had provided. In holding that the inquiry was within the examinable affairs of Interchase, their Honours said (at 305 - 306): 
 
 'In accordance with the settled course of authority ... information with respect to the probability or otherwise of success in litigation contemplated by the corporation would be information with respect to the "examinable affairs" of the corporation in question. This information would be "relevant", that is to say, it would bear upon or be connected with, the question whether the corporation possessed a cause of action, that is, a chose in action, as its property. It is not, and could not be, seriously disputed that an inquiry as to the existence, and value, of any property that the corporation may possess would be a "relevant" inquiry for the purposes of s 597(9).' 
 

The "examinable affairs" in that case were those of the company which was the subject of a winding up order albeit it was an officer of another company that was to be examined about them. The Court also referred to the special position of the liquidator as an officer of the Court under a duty and responsibility to get in and maximise the assets of the company for distribution for the benefit of the creditors. The limited knowledge of the company's assets and business affairs possessed by a liquidator had been recognised by the legislature in the enactment of the examination provisions of the Corporations Law and its predecessors.

70 The Full Court said that the language of s 597B, having regard to the definition of "examinable affairs" in s 9, had a broader operation than its statutory ancestor, s 115 of the Companies Act 1862 (UK) (at 308 - 309): 
 
 'The fact that the examination of a person under s 596B of the Law is not a proceeding inter partes is a circumstance in favour of a broad and generous construction of the section having regard to its statutory purpose, subject to the power of the Court not to allow the provision to be used oppressively to the private interests of the examinee.' 
 

The Court also held that the power could be used to order the production of relevant documents including insurance policies to ascertain whether or not the person against whom action might be taken by the liquidator had an enforceable right to indemnity from an insurer or other person (at 311): 
 
 
 'Realisation of the chose in action is an "examinable affair" within the meaning of ss 596B(1)(6)(ii) and 9 of the Law. Any policy of professional indemnity insurance containing the terms of the indemnity, including any exclusions and excesses and the amount of cover is, we think, a document "relevant to matters to which the examination relates or will relate" (s 597(9) of the Law)."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/27.html</AustLII>
<text>71 The cross vesting arrangements under the Corporations Law were challenged in Gould v Brown as an element of a challenge to the exercise of the examinations power under ss 596A and 596B by the Federal Court. The High Court divided evenly on the challenge to the cross vesting scheme which was therefore upheld as it had been in the Full Federal Court below. It was, however, only a matter of time before the validity of the cross vesting arrangements would come up again for consideration by the High Court. They did so and were held by a majority in Re Wakim; Ex parte McNally [1999] HCA 27 ; (1999) 198 CLR 511 to be invalid to the extent that the State Corporations Laws purported to confer jurisdiction on the Federal Court.

104 Spinks v Prentice (1998) 87 FCR 89 was one of a group of appeals decided in conjunction with Re Wakim . It was an appeal from the Full Court of the Federal Court with respect to an order for examination of former officers of a company in liquidation. The company was taken to be incorporated in the Australian Capital Territory. The Full Court held that the Corporations Act 1989 (Cth), which applied the Corporations Law to the ACT, validly conferred jurisdiction on the Federal Court to entertain the application for an examination summons. The examination orders were also challenged before the Full Court on the basis that they did not involve an exercise of judicial power. As to that the Court said (at 96):
 
 'It is true that, although there is no challenge to the winding up order made here, s 596A would permit an examination where there has been no winding up. But given the long history of courts exercising such powers, we can see nothing foreign to the exercise of judicial power in this aspect of s 596A.' 
 

They referred to the Compass Airlines and Grosvenor Hall cases. It is not clear, given the absence of any long history of judicial examination of corporations at large unrelated to winding up or other judicial procedures, whether their Honours were saying that applications under s 596A when there was no winding up order or pending court proceedings were an exercise of judicial power. To the extent that they were so saying, their observations were dicta.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans v Wainter Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 114 ; (2005) 145 FCR 176</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/114.html</AustLII>
<text>73 The operation of the examination powers was given comprehensive consideration by Lander J who wrote the principal judgment in the Full Court of the Federal Court in Evans v Wainter Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 114 ; (2005) 145 FCR 176. The case involved the issue of summonses under ss 596A and 596B for the examination of persons in relation to the examinable affairs of New Tel Ltd (in liq). An interlocutory application to discharge the summonses was refused and an appeal by leave taken to the Full Court, which appeal was ultimately dismissed. The appellants contended that the sole purpose of the examinations was to elicit evidence in relation to causes of action said to have arisen out of representations made by them to the company Wainter Pty Ltd in relation to New Tel. The Full Court held that New Tel stood to benefit from any action brought by Wainter against the appellants as recovery by Wainter against the appellants would reduce its claim against New Tel.

74 Lander J reviewed the history and authorities relevant to the examination powers and identified their legislative purposes in terms which may be paraphrased as follows (at [252]): 
 
 3.1 To enable an eligible applicant to gather information to assist the eligible applicant in the administration of the corporation. 
 3.2 To assist the corporation's administrators to identify the corporation's assets, both tangible and intangible, and to allow its liabilities to be identified.
 3.3 To protect the interests of the corporation's creditors. 
 3.4 To enable evidence and information to be obtained to support the bringing of proceedings against examinable officers and other persons in connection with the examinable affairs of the corporation. 
 3.5 To assist in the regulation of corporations by providing a public forum for the examination of examinable officers of corporations. 


With respect, the last mentioned purpose must be regarded with some reserve in terms of its compatibility with the exercise of judicial power. This is, however, subsumed in the discussion that follows about the characterisation of the examination power, for purposes of assessing constitutional validity, as judicial or administrative.

75 His Honour also advanced the following propositions about the exercise of the examinations power which he said emerged from the legislation and the authorities (at [252]):
 
 
 '4. If an eligible applicant applies for an order for examination of a person for a purpose unconnected with the purposes authorised by the legislation that will be an abuse of process and the order, if obtained, will be set aside. 
 
 5. The procedure may not be used to allow a party to obtain a forensic advantage and, if it is, any order obtained will be set aside. 
 
 6. The procedure may not be used as a dress rehearsal for the cross- examination of a person in a pending or subsequent action. However, it is not improper to seek an order of the Court to summon a person for examination whilst litigation is pending against that person or entities connected with that person. 
 
 7. The question whether in any particular case the applicant has used the procedure abusively will depend upon the applicant's purpose in seeking the order and all of the surrounding circumstances. It will not be an abuse unless an offensive purpose is at least the predominant purpose. 
 
 8. It will be an offensive purpose if the application cannot be characterised as being for the benefit of the corporation, its contributories or creditors. 
 
 9. A creditor may, if first authorised by ASIC, apply to the Court for an order to summon for examination a person for the purpose of obtaining information in relation to a debt owed to the creditor if such an examination would be in the interests of the corporation or its creditors as a whole. 
 
 10. A creditor may not use the procedure for the purpose of obtaining a forensic advantage which would not have been available to the creditor if the corporation had not gone into administration.'

76 Ryan and Crennan JJ generally agreed with Lander J subject to certain expressed qualifications. Lander J did not accept the correctness of the opinions of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria in Flanders v Beatty (1995) 16 ACSR 324 and the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia in Sandhurst Trustees Ltd v Harvey (2004) 88 SASR 519, that the scope of the examination process had been greatly expanded by the 1992 amendments ([187] and [206]). Ryan and Crennan JJ both held it unnecessary to reflect upon those views for the purpose of dealing with the appeal before them.

78 In Meteyard v Love [2005] NSWCA 444 ; (2005) 224 ALR 588 summonses for examination had issued to the insurer of a company in receivership on the application of its creditors. Basten JA, who wrote the principal judgment, dealt with questions of oppression, abuse of process and the effect of the examination power on legal professional privilege. Santow JA, who agreed with Basten JA, noted that the particular purpose of the examinations in that case was not to expose misconduct but to provide information that would advance the external administration of the company under receivership. His Honour considered that the limitations upon the examination power, in that context, were as articulated by Lander J in Wainter in [245] [251] (at [7]). There is nothing in that judgment supportive of the application of the power in respect of examinable affairs of companies not under external administration.

79 This case concerns in part the scope of the following statutory powers and obligations: 
(i) The power of ASIC to authorise a person to make an application under Pt 5.9.
 
 (ii) The obligation and associated power of the Court, under s 596A, to summon a person for examination about a corporation's examinable affairs and the power under s 597 to examine a person so summoned.

89 In my respectful opinion, the weight of authority, to the extent that it has considered the matter tends to support the proposition that ss 596A and 596B and their predecessors have been seen as provisions applicable to companies in one or other form of administration and not as applicable to companies at large. So much appears from the judgment of the Full Court in Re Compass Airlines and the Court of Appeal of New South Wales in HongKong Bank. New Zealand Steel also appears to be consistent with the views expressed by Gleeson J that the statutory context of s 597 was that of "external administration". It follows, that I would not, with respect, agree with the obiter observations at [84] of the Wainter judgment which would see the application of ss 596A and 596B extended to solvent corporations not under any form of external administration.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flanders v Beatty (1995) 16 ACSR 324</tocase>
<text>76 Ryan and Crennan JJ generally agreed with Lander J subject to certain expressed qualifications. Lander J did not accept the correctness of the opinions of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria in Flanders v Beatty (1995) 16 ACSR 324 and the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia in Sandhurst Trustees Ltd v Harvey (2004) 88 SASR 519, that the scope of the examination process had been greatly expanded by the 1992 amendments ([187] and [206]). Ryan and Crennan JJ both held it unnecessary to reflect upon those views for the purpose of dealing with the appeal before them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sandhurst Trustees Ltd v Harvey (2004) 88 SASR 519</tocase>
<text>76 Ryan and Crennan JJ generally agreed with Lander J subject to certain expressed qualifications. Lander J did not accept the correctness of the opinions of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria in Flanders v Beatty (1995) 16 ACSR 324 and the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia in Sandhurst Trustees Ltd v Harvey (2004) 88 SASR 519, that the scope of the examination process had been greatly expanded by the 1992 amendments ([187] and [206]). Ryan and Crennan JJ both held it unnecessary to reflect upon those views for the purpose of dealing with the appeal before them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1992) 40 FCR 402</tocase>
<text>80 The Corporations Act makes no express provision for ASIC to authorise a person to make an application under Pt 5.9. Its function in that respect is identified in the definition of "eligible applicant". The function so identified is picked up by the general provisions of s 11(1) of the ASIC Act. The power to do whatever is necessary for the performance of its functions is conferred upon ASIC by s 11(4). Section 11(4) is therefore the source of ASIC's power to authorise a person as an "eligible applicant". That has been so held in respect of analogous provisions of the Corporations Law in three decisions of the Full Court: HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1992) 40 FCR 402; Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 40 FCR 409 and Re Excel; Worthley v England (1994) 52 FCR 69. The Court of Appeal of New South Wales in Burns Philp &amp; Co Ltd v Murphy (1993) 29 NSWLR 723 held that the power was located in the definitional provision of s 597(1) of the Corporations Law, reflected in the definition of "eligible applicant" in s 9 of the Corporations Act . I will, with respect, follow and apply the analysis and conclusions of the Full Court of the Federal Court in the three decisions mentioned. They are helpfully discussed in Zumbo F, Liquidator's Power of Examination under the Corporations Law: The State of Play (1994) 12 C &amp; SLJ 504. The precise location of the statutory power to authorise a person to make application for an examination summons was relevant, in those cases, to the availability of administrative review by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal. The decisions of the Full Court of the Federal Court had the consequence that such review was not available. No such limitation applies in respect of judicial review of the ASIC decision whether under the ADJR Act or the provisions of s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 40 FCR 409</tocase>
<text>80 The Corporations Act makes no express provision for ASIC to authorise a person to make an application under Pt 5.9. Its function in that respect is identified in the definition of "eligible applicant". The function so identified is picked up by the general provisions of s 11(1) of the ASIC Act. The power to do whatever is necessary for the performance of its functions is conferred upon ASIC by s 11(4). Section 11(4) is therefore the source of ASIC's power to authorise a person as an "eligible applicant". That has been so held in respect of analogous provisions of the Corporations Law in three decisions of the Full Court: HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1992) 40 FCR 402; Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 40 FCR 409 and Re Excel; Worthley v England (1994) 52 FCR 69. The Court of Appeal of New South Wales in Burns Philp &amp; Co Ltd v Murphy (1993) 29 NSWLR 723 held that the power was located in the definitional provision of s 597(1) of the Corporations Law, reflected in the definition of "eligible applicant" in s 9 of the Corporations Act . I will, with respect, follow and apply the analysis and conclusions of the Full Court of the Federal Court in the three decisions mentioned. They are helpfully discussed in Zumbo F, Liquidator's Power of Examination under the Corporations Law: The State of Play (1994) 12 C &amp; SLJ 504. The precise location of the statutory power to authorise a person to make application for an examination summons was relevant, in those cases, to the availability of administrative review by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal. The decisions of the Full Court of the Federal Court had the consequence that such review was not available. No such limitation applies in respect of judicial review of the ASIC decision whether under the ADJR Act or the provisions of s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Excel; Worthley v England (1994) 52 FCR 69</tocase>
<text>80 The Corporations Act makes no express provision for ASIC to authorise a person to make an application under Pt 5.9. Its function in that respect is identified in the definition of "eligible applicant". The function so identified is picked up by the general provisions of s 11(1) of the ASIC Act. The power to do whatever is necessary for the performance of its functions is conferred upon ASIC by s 11(4). Section 11(4) is therefore the source of ASIC's power to authorise a person as an "eligible applicant". That has been so held in respect of analogous provisions of the Corporations Law in three decisions of the Full Court: HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1992) 40 FCR 402; Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 40 FCR 409 and Re Excel; Worthley v England (1994) 52 FCR 69. The Court of Appeal of New South Wales in Burns Philp &amp; Co Ltd v Murphy (1993) 29 NSWLR 723 held that the power was located in the definitional provision of s 597(1) of the Corporations Law, reflected in the definition of "eligible applicant" in s 9 of the Corporations Act . I will, with respect, follow and apply the analysis and conclusions of the Full Court of the Federal Court in the three decisions mentioned. They are helpfully discussed in Zumbo F, Liquidator's Power of Examination under the Corporations Law: The State of Play (1994) 12 C &amp; SLJ 504. The precise location of the statutory power to authorise a person to make application for an examination summons was relevant, in those cases, to the availability of administrative review by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal. The decisions of the Full Court of the Federal Court had the consequence that such review was not available. No such limitation applies in respect of judicial review of the ASIC decision whether under the ADJR Act or the provisions of s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Burns Philp &amp; Co Ltd v Murphy (1993) 29 NSWLR 7232</tocase>
<text>80 The Corporations Act makes no express provision for ASIC to authorise a person to make an application under Pt 5.9. Its function in that respect is identified in the definition of "eligible applicant". The function so identified is picked up by the general provisions of s 11(1) of the ASIC Act. The power to do whatever is necessary for the performance of its functions is conferred upon ASIC by s 11(4). Section 11(4) is therefore the source of ASIC's power to authorise a person as an "eligible applicant". That has been so held in respect of analogous provisions of the Corporations Law in three decisions of the Full Court: HongKong Bank of Australia Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1992) 40 FCR 402; Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 40 FCR 409 and Re Excel; Worthley v England (1994) 52 FCR 69. The Court of Appeal of New South Wales in Burns Philp &amp; Co Ltd v Murphy (1993) 29 NSWLR 723 held that the power was located in the definitional provision of s 597(1) of the Corporations Law, reflected in the definition of "eligible applicant" in s 9 of the Corporations Act . I will, with respect, follow and apply the analysis and conclusions of the Full Court of the Federal Court in the three decisions mentioned. They are helpfully discussed in Zumbo F, Liquidator's Power of Examination under the Corporations Law: The State of Play (1994) 12 C &amp; SLJ 504. The precise location of the statutory power to authorise a person to make application for an examination summons was relevant, in those cases, to the availability of administrative review by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal. The decisions of the Full Court of the Federal Court had the consequence that such review was not available. No such limitation applies in respect of judicial review of the ASIC decision whether under the ADJR Act or the provisions of s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Huddart Parker &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Moorehead [1909] HCA 36 ; (1909) 8 CLR 330</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1909/36.html</AustLII>
<text>94 The limits of the judicial power of the Commonwealth are not easily defined. At its heart is "the power which any sovereign authority must of necessity have to decide controversies between its subjects, or between itself and its subjects, whether the rights relate to life, liberty or property": Huddart Parker &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Moorehead [1909] HCA 36 ; (1909) 8 CLR 330 at 357 (Griffith CJ). But as was pointed out in R v Davison [1954] HCA 46 ; (1954) 90 CLR 353, the elements of controversy between subjects and the determination of existing rights and liabilities were "entirely lacking from many proceedings falling within the jurisdiction of various courts of justice in English law" (per Dixon CJ and McTiernan J at 368). Examples given included directions as to the administration of trusts, orders relating to the maintenance and guardianship of infants and declarations of legitimacy. Their Honours also referred to incidental administrative functions such as the issue of warrants of execution and said (at 368): 
 
 'But to say that a thing may be done in the course of the exercise of judicial power is not to say that it may be done without the exercise of judicial power.' 
 

Their Honours recognised that some functions are treated as judicial because they have long been so treated (at 369):
 
 
 'The truth is that the ascertainment of existing rights by the judicial determination of issues of fact or law falls exclusively within judicial power so that the Parliament cannot confide the function to any person or body but a court constituted under ss 71 and 72 of the Constitution and this may be true also of some duties or powers hitherto invariably discharged by courts under our system of jurisprudence but not exactly of the foregoing description.'

97 When a regulatory body or authority such as ASIC or the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission or the Commissioner of Taxation is given such a power it is a power to investigate not to decide in the sense that a court decides when it gives judgment upon a matter before it: Huddart Parker &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Moorehead at 358 (Griffiths CJ), 380 (O'Connor J), 384 (Isaacs J), 418 (Higgins J); Pioneer Concrete (Vic) Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1982] HCA 65 ; (1982) 152 CLR 460. The latter case concerned s 155 of the Trade Practices Act conferring power on the Chairman of the Trade Practices Commission to orally examine persons or require production of documents relevant to possible contraventions of the Act. The Court held that s 155 did not purport to confer judicial power on the Commission. Mason J made some observations relevant to the distinction between the exercise of an investigative power which may lead to subsequent judicial proceedings but nevertheless remains administrative and the exercise of an administrative power as an incident of judicial power. He said (at 471 - 472): 
 
 'The absence in s 155 of any power to decide or determine a dispute between parties the central element in the exercise of judicial power might be thought to be an overwhelming answer to the argument that there is an attempt to confer judicial power on the Commission. 
 
 However, it is suggested that if the Commission requires information to be given for the purpose of obtaining evidence in a matter before the Court then it is exercising judicial power. According to Holmes J in Prentis v Atlantic Coastline [(1908) 211 US 210 at p 227], "The nature of the final act determines the nature of the previous inquiry". But this does not mean that because the determination ultimately made by the Federal Court in proceedings in respect of a contravention of the Act is an exercise of judicial power the issue and service of the notices is itself such an exercise. Holmes J was merely saying that the character of the order or final decision made by a tribunal will determine the character of the inquiry which precedes its decision, so that if its determination is a judicial order then its inquiry will constitute an exercise of judicial power. R v Davison [(1954) [1954] HCA 46 ; 90 CLR 353] was just such a case. This is not to say that it is legitimate to characterize the nature of the power exercised by the Commission under s 155 by reference to the judicial power which the Court exercises when it hears proceedings for a penalty under the Act. What the Commission does will produce information which may be presented in evidence by a party in proceedings in respect of a contravention under the Act, but this is no basis for saying that there is an exercise of judicial power on the part of the Commission. The exercise of a power to compel the provision of information is not inherently such an exercise. It may constitute an element in the exercise of judicial power when the power is part of the proceedings of the court, its object being to aid the court or the parties to obtain and present evidence in those proceedings. Then the exercise of the power by the court or the parties in proceedings in the court is for the purpose of enabling the court to hear and determine the lis and is, accordingly, incidental to, if not an element in, the exercise of judicial power.' 
 

See also Kluver and Woellner , Powers of Investigation in Revenue, Companies and Trade Practices Law (Butterworths, 1983, [102] - [103])

108 The above passage states no new principle and indeed refers generally in a footnote to the discussion by Dixon CJ and McTiernan J in R v Davison. But to say that the courts have historically exercised investigative functions does not mean that all investigative functions conferred on a court, absent relevant historical antecedents or analogues, are to be regarded as judicial if not otherwise incidental to the exercise of judicial power. Without some limitation of that kind investigative obligations may be imposed by statute upon courts exercising federal jurisdiction on any subject within the legislative competence of the Commonwealth Parliament.

109 The question in this case is where there is any historical basis for characterising the examination power as now propounded as judicial in character. Its purported extension to corporations which are not being wound up or otherwise subject to judicial processes is an event of recent and certainly post-federation history. Nor can its characterisation as judicial be treated as analogous to such processes as preliminary discovery or bills of discovery in equity which have, in any event, a narrower field of operation than that which is proposed for s 596A. In so saying it is necessary to bear in mind that the validity of s 596A in its general application to solvent corporations not under any form of administration or judicial process is not to be judged by reference to this particular application in respect of such a corporation. The examination power cannot be justified on the basis that there is a damages claim pending against the company being examined. The construction of s 596A relied upon and necessary to support the issue of the examination summons in this case does not depend upon the existence of the damages claim but upon the status of Hayes Knight as a corporation.

110 In my opinion if the construction of s 596A for which Highstoke contends is the correct construction, then s 596A purports to confer on the Court a power which is not capable of characterisation as judicial and which, in its present application, is not incidental to the exercise of judicial power. To that extent, s 596A would exceed the legislative power of the Commonwealth. It may be that, by virtue of s 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act s 596A can be read down to yield the construction which, in my opinion, is in any event the correct one. The outcome is the same. The summons must be discharged.

111 The disposition of the Judicial Review Proceedings is effectively governed by the conclusions in respect of the Examination Proceedings. It was at the very least a mandatory relevant consideration to be taken into account by the ASIC delegate, if not a factor defining the limits of the delegate's power that Hayes Knight was not under any form of external administration of the kind referred to in Ch 5 of the Act or otherwise amenable to the provisions of the Act. The stated purpose for which authorisation was sought was for an application which, on the proper construction of the relevant provisions, would be beyond the power of the Court. The authorisation decision should be quashed. There is no point in remitting the matter for reconsideration by ASIC as the quashing of the authorisation decision depends upon the proposition that, having regard to the purpose for which the application for authorisation was made, authorisation could not properly have been granted.

112 The question whether the issue of the summons was for an improper purpose because it was related to an examination not for the benefit of Hayes Knight falls away.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Kirby; Ex parte Boilermakers' Society of Australia [1956] HCA 10 ; (1956) 94 CLR 254</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1956/10.html</AustLII>
<text>95 Non-judicial functions may be conferred as an incident of judicial power. As was said in R v Kirby; Ex parte Boilermakers' Society of Australia [1956] HCA 10 ; (1956) 94 CLR 254 at 278:
 
 '... it must not be forgotten that s 51(xxxix) expressly empowers the Parliament to make laws with respect to matters incidental to the execution of any power vested by the Constitution in the federal judicature. What belongs to the judicial power or is incidental or ancillary to it cannot be determined except by ascertaining if it has a sufficient relation to the principal or judicial function or purpose to which it may be thought to be accessory.' 
 

More recently in Re Tracey; Ex parte Ryan [1989] HCA 12 ; (1989) 166 CLR 518 Deane J observed (at 580):
 
 
 'The Executive Government cannot absorb or be amalgamated with the judicature by the conferral of non-ancillary executive functions upon the courts.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Tracey; Ex parte Ryan [1989] HCA 12 ; (1989) 166 CLR 518</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/12.html</AustLII>
<text>95 Non-judicial functions may be conferred as an incident of judicial power. As was said in R v Kirby; Ex parte Boilermakers' Society of Australia [1956] HCA 10 ; (1956) 94 CLR 254 at 278:
 
 '... it must not be forgotten that s 51(xxxix) expressly empowers the Parliament to make laws with respect to matters incidental to the execution of any power vested by the Constitution in the federal judicature. What belongs to the judicial power or is incidental or ancillary to it cannot be determined except by ascertaining if it has a sufficient relation to the principal or judicial function or purpose to which it may be thought to be accessory.' 
 

More recently in Re Tracey; Ex parte Ryan [1989] HCA 12 ; (1989) 166 CLR 518 Deane J observed (at 580):
 
 
 'The Executive Government cannot absorb or be amalgamated with the judicature by the conferral of non-ancillary executive functions upon the courts.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pioneer Concrete (Vic) Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1982] HCA 65 ; (1982) 152 CLR 460</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/65.html</AustLII>
<text>97 When a regulatory body or authority such as ASIC or the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission or the Commissioner of Taxation is given such a power it is a power to investigate not to decide in the sense that a court decides when it gives judgment upon a matter before it: Huddart Parker &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Moorehead at 358 (Griffiths CJ), 380 (O'Connor J), 384 (Isaacs J), 418 (Higgins J); Pioneer Concrete (Vic) Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1982] HCA 65 ; (1982) 152 CLR 460. The latter case concerned s 155 of the Trade Practices Act conferring power on the Chairman of the Trade Practices Commission to orally examine persons or require production of documents relevant to possible contraventions of the Act. The Court held that s 155 did not purport to confer judicial power on the Commission. Mason J made some observations relevant to the distinction between the exercise of an investigative power which may lead to subsequent judicial proceedings but nevertheless remains administrative and the exercise of an administrative power as an incident of judicial power. He said (at 471 - 472): 
 
 'The absence in s 155 of any power to decide or determine a dispute between parties the central element in the exercise of judicial power might be thought to be an overwhelming answer to the argument that there is an attempt to confer judicial power on the Commission. 
 
 However, it is suggested that if the Commission requires information to be given for the purpose of obtaining evidence in a matter before the Court then it is exercising judicial power. According to Holmes J in Prentis v Atlantic Coastline [(1908) 211 US 210 at p 227], "The nature of the final act determines the nature of the previous inquiry". But this does not mean that because the determination ultimately made by the Federal Court in proceedings in respect of a contravention of the Act is an exercise of judicial power the issue and service of the notices is itself such an exercise. Holmes J was merely saying that the character of the order or final decision made by a tribunal will determine the character of the inquiry which precedes its decision, so that if its determination is a judicial order then its inquiry will constitute an exercise of judicial power. R v Davison [(1954) [1954] HCA 46 ; 90 CLR 353] was just such a case. This is not to say that it is legitimate to characterize the nature of the power exercised by the Commission under s 155 by reference to the judicial power which the Court exercises when it hears proceedings for a penalty under the Act. What the Commission does will produce information which may be presented in evidence by a party in proceedings in respect of a contravention under the Act, but this is no basis for saying that there is an exercise of judicial power on the part of the Commission. The exercise of a power to compel the provision of information is not inherently such an exercise. It may constitute an element in the exercise of judicial power when the power is part of the proceedings of the court, its object being to aid the court or the parties to obtain and present evidence in those proceedings. Then the exercise of the power by the court or the parties in proceedings in the court is for the purpose of enabling the court to hear and determine the lis and is, accordingly, incidental to, if not an element in, the exercise of judicial power.' 
 

See also Kluver and Woellner , Powers of Investigation in Revenue, Companies and Trade Practices Law (Butterworths, 1983, [102] - [103])</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Monadelphous Engineering Associates (NZ) Ltd (in liq); ex parte McDonald and Watson (1989) 7 ACLC 220</tocase>
<text>98 In Re Monadelphous Engineering Associates (NZ) Ltd (in liq) ; ex parte McDonald and Watson (1989) 7 ACLC 220 Northrop J referred to the investigative character of the examination procedure under s 541 of the Companies (Victoria) Code and said it was "inappropriate" for a judge of the Federal Court to conduct such a process (at 225-226): 
 
 '... examination is not a court hearing in the true sense. It is not the exercise of judicial power. It is part of an investigative procedure ... In my opinion it would not be appropriate for a Judge of the Federal Court to conduct examinations of an investigatory nature, and not truly judicial.' 
 

He transferred the matter, which was an application by a liquidator, to the Supreme Court of Victoria. The same characterisation of the examination process was made by the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria in Friedrich v Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd [1990] VR 995 at 1003: 
 
 '... essentially this procedure is administrative and does not result in judicial decisions as to any parties' rights, except decisions as to the manner in which the examination itself should be conducted.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Friedrich v Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd [1990] VR 995</tocase>
<text>98 In Re Monadelphous Engineering Associates (NZ) Ltd (in liq) ; ex parte McDonald and Watson (1989) 7 ACLC 220 Northrop J referred to the investigative character of the examination procedure under s 541 of the Companies (Victoria) Code and said it was "inappropriate" for a judge of the Federal Court to conduct such a process (at 225-226): 
 
 '... examination is not a court hearing in the true sense. It is not the exercise of judicial power. It is part of an investigative procedure ... In my opinion it would not be appropriate for a Judge of the Federal Court to conduct examinations of an investigatory nature, and not truly judicial.' 
 

He transferred the matter, which was an application by a liquidator, to the Supreme Court of Victoria. The same characterisation of the examination process was made by the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Victoria in Friedrich v Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd [1990] VR 995 at 1003: 
 
 '... essentially this procedure is administrative and does not result in judicial decisions as to any parties' rights, except decisions as to the manner in which the examination itself should be conducted.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1965/66.html</AustLII>
<text>102 Gaudron J held that Ch III would preclude conferral on the Federal Court of a non-judicial examinations power "not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of corporations" (405). However there was nothing to prevent the Commonwealth from conferring power of that kind on the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory (405). Reference should be made in that regard to the developing jurisprudence about the interaction of Ch III and the Territories' power in Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226; Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591; Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171 and in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Hely J in North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204 at [106] [133].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/10.html</AustLII>
<text>102 Gaudron J held that Ch III would preclude conferral on the Federal Court of a non-judicial examinations power "not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of corporations" (405). However there was nothing to prevent the Commonwealth from conferring power of that kind on the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory (405). Reference should be made in that regard to the developing jurisprudence about the interaction of Ch III and the Territories' power in Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226; Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591; Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171 and in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Hely J in North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204 at [106] [133].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spinks v Prentice (1998) 87 FCR 89</tocase>
<text>104 Spinks v Prentice (1998) 87 FCR 89 was one of a group of appeals decided in conjunction with Re Wakim . It was an appeal from the Full Court of the Federal Court with respect to an order for examination of former officers of a company in liquidation. The company was taken to be incorporated in the Australian Capital Territory. The Full Court held that the Corporations Act 1989 (Cth), which applied the Corporations Law to the ACT, validly conferred jurisdiction on the Federal Court to entertain the application for an examination summons. The examination orders were also challenged before the Full Court on the basis that they did not involve an exercise of judicial power. As to that the Court said (at 96):
 
 'It is true that, although there is no challenge to the winding up order made here, s 596A would permit an examination where there has been no winding up. But given the long history of courts exercising such powers, we can see nothing foreign to the exercise of judicial power in this aspect of s 596A.' 
 

They referred to the Compass Airlines and Grosvenor Hall cases. It is not clear, given the absence of any long history of judicial examination of corporations at large unrelated to winding up or other judicial procedures, whether their Honours were saying that applications under s 596A when there was no winding up order or pending court proceedings were an exercise of judicial power. To the extent that they were so saying, their observations were dicta.

105 In the High Court, on appeal from the Full Federal Court in Spinks v Prentice , Gummow and Hayne JJ noted that it had not been contended that the power to order the examination of witnesses and the production of documents for the purposes of a winding up and to supervise the conduct of the examination was otherwise than in the exercise of a function incidental to the exercise of judicial power. Their Honours did not think it appropriate to express any view on the validity of provisions conferring jurisdiction on the Federal Court to make orders under Pt 5.9 save for those immediately in question. On that point Kirby J agreed with them (619).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/44.html</AustLII>
<text>102 Gaudron J held that Ch III would preclude conferral on the Federal Court of a non-judicial examinations power "not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of corporations" (405). However there was nothing to prevent the Commonwealth from conferring power of that kind on the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory (405). Reference should be made in that regard to the developing jurisprudence about the interaction of Ch III and the Territories' power in Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226; Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591; Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171 and in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Hely J in North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204 at [106] [133].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/297.html</AustLII>
<text>102 Gaudron J held that Ch III would preclude conferral on the Federal Court of a non-judicial examinations power "not confined to examination by a court which has exercised or is exercising jurisdiction to make an order for the winding up of corporations" (405). However there was nothing to prevent the Commonwealth from conferring power of that kind on the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory (405). Reference should be made in that regard to the developing jurisprudence about the interaction of Ch III and the Territories' power in Spratt v Hermes [1965] HCA 66 ; (1965) 114 CLR 226; Capital TV and Appliances Pty Ltd v Falconer [1971] HCA 10 ; (1971) 125 CLR 591; Re Governor, Goulburn Correctional Centre; Ex parte Eastman [1999] HCA 44 ; (1999) 165 ALR 171 and in the joint judgment of Black CJ and Hely J in North Australian Aboriginal Legal Aid Service Inc v Bradley [2002] FCAFC 297 ; (2002) 122 FCR 204 at [106] [133].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Munro [1926] HCA 58 ; (1926) 38 CLR 153</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1926/58.html</AustLII>
<text>106 Divorced from association with a judicial proceeding nothing about the examination power under the Corporations Act marks it as judicial in character. It lacks the core elements of the judicial process such as the finding of facts, the making of value judgments and binding determinations as to legal rights and obligations. There are of course, functions, which can be viewed as administrative or judicial depending upon the body that discharges them: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Munro [1926] HCA 58 ; (1926) 38 CLR 153 at 175-179; Cominos v Cominos [1972] HCA 54 ; (1972) 127 CLR 588 at 599, 605 and 606; R v Quinn ; Ex parte Consolidated Foods Corporation [1977] HCA 62 ; (1977) 138 CLR 1 at 6. It is nevertheless a necessary condition of the attribution of this "chameleon" status to a particular function that it be capable of constituting an exercise of judicial power.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cominos v Cominos [1972] HCA 54 ; (1972) 127 CLR 588</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/54.html</AustLII>
<text>106 Divorced from association with a judicial proceeding nothing about the examination power under the Corporations Act marks it as judicial in character. It lacks the core elements of the judicial process such as the finding of facts, the making of value judgments and binding determinations as to legal rights and obligations. There are of course, functions, which can be viewed as administrative or judicial depending upon the body that discharges them: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Munro [1926] HCA 58 ; (1926) 38 CLR 153 at 175-179; Cominos v Cominos [1972] HCA 54 ; (1972) 127 CLR 588 at 599, 605 and 606; R v Quinn ; Ex parte Consolidated Foods Corporation [1977] HCA 62 ; (1977) 138 CLR 1 at 6. It is nevertheless a necessary condition of the attribution of this "chameleon" status to a particular function that it be capable of constituting an exercise of judicial power.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Quinn; Ex parte Consolidated Foods Corporation [1977] HCA 62 ; (1977) 138 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/62.html</AustLII>
<text>106 Divorced from association with a judicial proceeding nothing about the examination power under the Corporations Act marks it as judicial in character. It lacks the core elements of the judicial process such as the finding of facts, the making of value judgments and binding determinations as to legal rights and obligations. There are of course, functions, which can be viewed as administrative or judicial depending upon the body that discharges them: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Munro [1926] HCA 58 ; (1926) 38 CLR 153 at 175-179; Cominos v Cominos [1972] HCA 54 ; (1972) 127 CLR 588 at 599, 605 and 606; R v Quinn ; Ex parte Consolidated Foods Corporation [1977] HCA 62 ; (1977) 138 CLR 1 at 6. It is nevertheless a necessary condition of the attribution of this "chameleon" status to a particular function that it be capable of constituting an exercise of judicial power.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dalton v New South Wales Crime Commission [2006] HCA 17 ; (2006) 226 ALR 570</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/17.html</AustLII>
<text>107 The examination power taken alone, in the sense used above, is not an exercise of judicial power nor, taken alone, is it judicial when exercised by a court. It can only be accommodated within the exercise of judicial power if incidental to it or justified by historical usage. An examination ordered in aid of the implementation of a winding up order made by a court can be seen as incidental to the exercise of judicial power and has long been accepted as such, at least implicitly if not explicitly, on that basis. On the other hand an examination which is "free standing" in the sense that it is exercised without reference to any pending proceeding does not fall within the scope of the judicial power unless it can be characterised as judicial on the basis that it is a function which courts have long carried out. The historical incidence of investigative functions exercised by courts was referred to in Dalton v New South Wales Crime Commission [2006] HCA 17 ; (2006) 226 ALR 570. That case concerned the validity of s 76 of the Service and Execution of Process Act 1992 (Cth). The section empowers the Supreme Court of a State, in which a subpoena is issued by a tribunal for a person to give evidence before the tribunal, to give leave to serve the subpoena out of the State. It was submitted in the High Court that the exercise by the Courts of investigative functions did not occasion or support the issue and service of process under s 51(xxiv) of the Constitution . There was therefore said to be no foundation for an analogical extension in respect of the investigative functions of tribunals. To the extent that this argument involved a denial of the investigative function of courts it was rejected in the joint judgment of Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ. Their Honours said (at [45]):
 
 'From a time well before federation, the courts of the Australian colonies, like those in England and elsewhere in the Empire, exercised a range of administrative and investigative functions. Provisions for the examination of judgment debtors, bankrupts, and officers of failed corporations are in point. In Cheney v Spooner [(1929) [1929] HCA 12 ; 41 CLR 532] this court upheld the application of the 1901 Act to an order by the Supreme Court of New South Wales under ss 123 and 124 of the Companies Act 1899 (NSW) which gave leave to the liquidator of a company in voluntary liquidation to summons a number of persons to attend for examination by the Master in Equity. The equity jurisdiction of the Supreme Courts with respect to bills of discovery (or preliminary discovery in more recent parlance) provides another instance of an investigative procedure. So also the courts of marine inquiry established in the Australian colonies. Likewise the next of kin inquiry in an administration suit, conducted in New South Wales by the master in equity. Further, the 1901 Act, as King CJ pointed out in [ Alliance Petroleum Australia NL v Australian Gaslight Co (1983) 34 SASR 215 at 236], applied to subpoenas and summonses issued by coroners.'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>