<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Barrett Property Group Pty Ltd v Metricon Homes Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1509 (28 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1509.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Adelaide Corporation v Australia Performing Right Association Ltd [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1928/10.html</AustLII>
<text>261 While the Court must take these matters into account, they are not the only matters that may be taken into account: Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 at [13] per Branson J; [135] per Kenny J, French J agreeing (concerning the construction and application of s 101(1A) of the Act which corresponds in terms to s 36(1A), in the context of infringement of copyright in sound recordings, films and the like). Both these sections are premised on the concept of "authorisation" developed by the High Court in University of New South Wales v Moorhouse [1975] HCA 26 ; (1975) 133 CLR 1; Cooper at [136]. The word "authorise" in the cases has been given its dictionary meaning of "sanction, approve or countenance": Falcon v Famous Players Film Company [1926] 2 KB 474; Adelaide City Corporation v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481; Moorhouse at 12 (Gibbs J), 20-21 (Jacobs J); WEA International Inc v Hanimex Corp Ltd (1987) 17 FCR 274, 285-286 (Gummow J); Cooper at [20] per Branson J, French J agreeing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd v Hooker Homes Pty Ltd [1971] 2 NSWLR 278</tocase>
<text>28 While the above considerations are, typically, considered in a cumulative sense, I will address each of them in turn. Ultimately, however, whether the Alleged Infringing Works are, in each case, sufficiently similar to the Copyright Works such as to amount to a reproduction of a substantial part of these or any of these, is for the Court to determine and the Court will be assisted by expert evidence which "is of value in exposing the facets of the ultimate question to which the expert opinion evidence is directed": Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd v Hooker Homes Pty Ltd [1971] 2 NSWLR 278 at 286.

29 The question is whether the alfresco quadrant in each of the Seattle 31 and Memphis 33 plans and homes constitutes a substantial part of each plan and home in the Alleged Infringing Works within the meaning of s 14 of the Act. The applicants submitted that this is the case for a number of reasons.

30 First, the applicants asserted that the alfresco quadrant was the main communal living area of the home hence the design was of qualitative significance. As a corollary, it was submitted that the orientation of the kitchen was important, being at the "hub" of the design, which could be viewed from all rooms within the alfresco quadrant.

54 Consistent with the above analysis, it has been suggested that where subjective copying is found, the task of proving objective similarities of what was taken was a "substantial part" of the protected work becomes "easier" to find: see Eagle Homes and Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd at 289.

55 My findings below of subjective copying have enabled me more readily to find objective similarities between the Alleged Infringing Works and the Copyright Works.

115 Where objective similarities are so close that it is open to the Court to draw an inference of copying, then such an inference may be rebutted by the respondents by evidence which explains the provenance of the similarities other than as the result of copying the applicants' copyright works: Pacific Gaming at [19] citing Ibcos Computers Ltd v Barclays Mercantile Highland Finance Ltd [1994] FSR 275, at 296-297; Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd at 284; Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Jain (1990) 26 FCR 53</tocase>
<text>262 It is a question of fact in each case, as to what inferences may be drawn from the conduct of the person said to have authorised the act of which complaint is made: Winstone v Wurlitzer Automatic Phonograph Co of Australia Pty Ltd [1946] VLR 338. This was referred to with apparent approval by the Full Court in Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Jain (1990) 26 FCR 53 at 59.

266 However it is not necessary here to do so. The case against Palazzesi and Popple is not that they are liable for the tort of Metricon, but rather that each was liable for infringement by authorisation under s 36(1A) of the Act. The applicants refer to Australasian Performing Right Association v Jain (1990) 26 FCR 53. No reliance was placed by the applicants upon the Performing Right Society test or the Mentmore test.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Autodesk Inc v Dyason (No 2) [1993] HCA 6 ; (1993) 176 CLR 300</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/6.html</AustLII>
<text>22 Emphasis on quality rather than quantity is further exemplified in more recent Australian authorities. In Data Access Corp v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [32] , a majority of the High Court endorsed the views expressed by Mason CJ in dissent in Autodesk Inc v Dyason (No 2) [1993] HCA 6 ; (1993) 176 CLR 300 at 305. In that case, Mason CJ, citing Ladbroke (Football) Ltd v William Hill (Football) Ltd [1964] 1 WLR 273 stated:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected. For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that 'there is no copyright' in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright.
 
 As this statement makes clear, in determining whether the quality of what is taken makes it a 'substantial part' of the copyright work, it is important to inquire into the importance which the taken portion bears in relation to the work as a whole: is it an 'essential' or 'material' part of the work? 
 
 ...in the context of copyright law, where emphasis is to be placed upon the 'originality' of the work's expression, the essential or material features of a work should be ascertained by considering the originality of the part allegedly taken. (Emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chabot v Davies [1936] 3 All ER 221</tocase>
<text>76 To establish infringement in three dimensions from the applicants' plans, the test is still a visual one and it is necessary here to establish that a substantial part of each of the Alleged Infringing Works resembles visually a substantial part of those plans, namely the alfresco quadrant: see further Lend Lease Homes Pty Ltd v Warrigal Homes Pty Ltd [1970] 3 NSWR 265, 273-274; LED Builders Pty Ltd and, in relation to the Copyright Act 1911 , see Chabot v Davies [1936] 3 All ER 221 at 227-228.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd v Henley Arch Pty Ltd (1999) 46 IPR 309</tocase>
<text>39 In the end, cases such as the instant one are a 'matter of impression' as pointed out by the Full Court in Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd v Henley Arch Pty Ltd (1999) 46 IPR 309 at [34]. In examining the quality of the alfresco quadrant with respect to the whole of the Copyright Works, I view that part as being substantial. This view was also supported by my personal inspection and impression of the Seattle 31 design at the Beaconsfield address. On inspection, I found that the Seattle 31 home consisted of a central hallway leading into the hub of the home that incorporated:
 
&#8226; the kitchen/meals area;
 
&#8226; the family/living area;
 
&#8226; the alfresco; and
 
&#8226; the rumpus room
 
all under a single ('hip') roof-line. The roof-line was viewed on an external inspection of the home. The view that I express here, was my initial view from the third day of the hearing before much of the oral testimony. It remained unchanged throughout the course of the hearing. The parties have agreed that my impression of the Copyright Works and the Alleged Infringing Works, from my personal inspection, are to form part of the evidence. Cases such as Clarendon support this approach.

40 The layout of the Seattle 31 gave the impression of a free-flowing design, leading from the hallway to the hub of the home, with the alfresco quadrant, under one roof-line, being central to the design. The impression was reinforced by the open-plan kitchen that looked over the living and alfresco areas. The design allowed one to view into the rumpus room which enhanced the free-flowing design features of the Seattle 31 plan. These features were clearly based in a communal area of the plan, so as to optimise appreciation of the alfresco quadrant and surrounding living areas. Based on my impression, I would describe the alfresco quadrant as being substantial in a qualitative sense.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/187.html</AustLII>
<text>261 While the Court must take these matters into account, they are not the only matters that may be taken into account: Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 at [13] per Branson J; [135] per Kenny J, French J agreeing (concerning the construction and application of s 101(1A) of the Act which corresponds in terms to s 36(1A), in the context of infringement of copyright in sound recordings, films and the like). Both these sections are premised on the concept of "authorisation" developed by the High Court in University of New South Wales v Moorhouse [1975] HCA 26 ; (1975) 133 CLR 1; Cooper at [136]. The word "authorise" in the cases has been given its dictionary meaning of "sanction, approve or countenance": Falcon v Famous Players Film Company [1926] 2 KB 474; Adelaide City Corporation v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481; Moorhouse at 12 (Gibbs J), 20-21 (Jacobs J); WEA International Inc v Hanimex Corp Ltd (1987) 17 FCR 274, 285-286 (Gummow J); Cooper at [20] per Branson J, French J agreeing.

263 The degree of control which can constitute a sufficient basis for a finding of authorisation is a question of fact and degree: Cooper per Kenny J, French J agreeing at [142].

265 In Cooper at [159]-[164], Kenny J observed that no Full Court of this Court had settled which of these two tests was to be preferred, or indeed whether the exposition by Finkelstein J in Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 231 ought be followed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Data Access Corp v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/49.html</AustLII>
<text>22 Emphasis on quality rather than quantity is further exemplified in more recent Australian authorities. In Data Access Corp v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [32] , a majority of the High Court endorsed the views expressed by Mason CJ in dissent in Autodesk Inc v Dyason (No 2) [1993] HCA 6 ; (1993) 176 CLR 300 at 305. In that case, Mason CJ, citing Ladbroke (Football) Ltd v William Hill (Football) Ltd [1964] 1 WLR 273 stated:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected. For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that 'there is no copyright' in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright.
 
 As this statement makes clear, in determining whether the quality of what is taken makes it a 'substantial part' of the copyright work, it is important to inquire into the importance which the taken portion bears in relation to the work as a whole: is it an 'essential' or 'material' part of the work? 
 
 ...in the context of copyright law, where emphasis is to be placed upon the 'originality' of the work's expression, the essential or material features of a work should be ascertained by considering the originality of the part allegedly taken. (Emphasis added)

23 While the High Court's holding in Powerflex applied to a computer program, the passage is of general application. In any event, a common thread in a case which involves computer programs and one which involves project homes, is that the copyright may overlap with functional considerations.

25 Reference to the essential or material features mirrors the language in Powerflex. The passages in both Powerflex and Tamawood are firmly grounded in Ladbroke . In that case, Lord Pearce stated in dictum:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected . For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that " there is no copyright " in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright. (Emphasis added)

26 In other words, if an unoriginal part of the whole is taken that does not represent a substantial part of the labour, skill and judgment of the author that made the whole work 'original', then there is no infringement: Powerflex at [32]. See also, Klissers Bakeries v Harvest Bakeries (1985) IPR 533 and Dixon Investments and Nine Network Australia Pty Ltd v IceTV Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1172.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490</tocase>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .

26 In other words, if an unoriginal part of the whole is taken that does not represent a substantial part of the labour, skill and judgment of the author that made the whole work 'original', then there is no infringement: Powerflex at [32]. See also, Klissers Bakeries v Harvest Bakeries (1985) IPR 533 and Dixon Investments and Nine Network Australia Pty Ltd v IceTV Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1172.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/138.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Falcon v Famous Players Film Co [1926] 2 KB 474</tocase>
<text>261 While the Court must take these matters into account, they are not the only matters that may be taken into account: Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 at [13] per Branson J; [135] per Kenny J, French J agreeing (concerning the construction and application of s 101(1A) of the Act which corresponds in terms to s 36(1A), in the context of infringement of copyright in sound recordings, films and the like). Both these sections are premised on the concept of "authorisation" developed by the High Court in University of New South Wales v Moorhouse [1975] HCA 26 ; (1975) 133 CLR 1; Cooper at [136]. The word "authorise" in the cases has been given its dictionary meaning of "sanction, approve or countenance": Falcon v Famous Players Film Company [1926] 2 KB 474; Adelaide City Corporation v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481; Moorhouse at 12 (Gibbs J), 20-21 (Jacobs J); WEA International Inc v Hanimex Corp Ltd (1987) 17 FCR 274, 285-286 (Gummow J); Cooper at [20] per Branson J, French J agreeing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587</tocase>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .

115 Where objective similarities are so close that it is open to the Court to draw an inference of copying, then such an inference may be rebutted by the respondents by evidence which explains the provenance of the similarities other than as the result of copying the applicants' copyright works: Pacific Gaming at [19] citing Ibcos Computers Ltd v Barclays Mercantile Highland Finance Ltd [1994] FSR 275, at 296-297; Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd at 284; Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443</tocase>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ibcos Computers Ltd v Barclays Mercantile Highland Finance Ltd [1994] FSR 275</tocase>
<text>115 Where objective similarities are so close that it is open to the Court to draw an inference of copying, then such an inference may be rebutted by the respondents by evidence which explains the provenance of the similarities other than as the result of copying the applicants' copyright works: Pacific Gaming at [19] citing Ibcos Computers Ltd v Barclays Mercantile Highland Finance Ltd [1994] FSR 275, at 296-297; Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd at 284; Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Kenrick &amp; Co v Lawrence &amp; Co (1890) 25 QBD 99</tocase>
<text>13 The application of copyright law to project homes and designs is not without difficulty. The competing concepts in copyright law of 'ideas' and 'expression of ideas' underpin the difficulty: Kenrick &amp; Co v Lawrence &amp; Co (1890) 25 QBD 99 provides an apt illustration. In that case, the author had printed a card that assisted illiterate voters. The card's design was simple. The design depicted a hand holding a pencil in the act of completing a cross within a square. Willis J held that the copyright protection sought would protect the idea rather than the expression alone, since "a square can only be drawn as a square, a cross can only be drawn as a cross, and for such purposes as the plaintiff's drawing was intended to fulfil, there are scarcely more ways than one of drawing a pencil or the hand that holds it": Kenrick at 104. The case is an extreme example, but gives expression to the idea-form dichotomy.

62 The respondents point to the fact that the doors and windows are differently sized and positioned. These differences, it was submitted, were highly significant given the asserted limited scope for variation in what they described as the very restrictive part of the plan relied upon by the applicants. Kenrick was used to support the respondents' submission. I disagree. This is not a " Kenrick "-like case, where there was only one means of expressing the idea of a hand ticking a box. Instead, it conforms with what Wilcox and Lindgren JJ stated in Tamawood , that "broad functional requirements can be satisfied in more ways that one" at [56]. The evidence discloses that there are a number of ways of incorporating an alfresco in combination with a kitchen, living, dining and rumpus. Accordingly, the plan as expressed in the Seattle 31 design is far from obvious, as contended by the respondents' counsel and witnesses. I reject the submission that the design of the alfresco quadrant was 'obvious'. For example, there was no necessity for the shape of the alfresco to be rectangular: there are examples of angled rectangular shapes in the prior art. Longer rectangular features, squares and other shapes thus were possible options.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>King v Milpurrurru (1996) 66 FCR 474</tocase>
<text>264 It was submitted on behalf of Palazzesi and Popple that the authorities on personal liability of corporate officers such as them, for authorising conduct of the company that infringes copyright, are ambiguous. In King v Milpurrurru (1996) 66 FCR 474 at 494 500, Beazley J identified two competing lines of authority: the Performing Right Society test and the Mentmore test. See also Allen Manufacturing Co Pty Ltd v McCallum &amp; Co Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 400. Under the former test, the corporate officer must be shown to have procured or directed the company's infringing conduct. Under the latter test, it is necessary to show the deliberate, wilful and knowing pursuit of a course of conduct that was likely to constitute infringement or that reflected an indifference to the risk of it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Klissers Bakeries v Harvest Bakeries (1985) IPR 533</tocase>
<text>26 In other words, if an unoriginal part of the whole is taken that does not represent a substantial part of the labour, skill and judgment of the author that made the whole work 'original', then there is no infringement: Powerflex at [32]. See also, Klissers Bakeries v Harvest Bakeries (1985) IPR 533 and Dixon Investments and Nine Network Australia Pty Ltd v IceTV Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1172.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ladbroke (Football) Ltd v William Hill (Football) Ltd [1964] 1 WLR 273</tocase>
<text>22 Emphasis on quality rather than quantity is further exemplified in more recent Australian authorities. In Data Access Corp v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [32] , a majority of the High Court endorsed the views expressed by Mason CJ in dissent in Autodesk Inc v Dyason (No 2) [1993] HCA 6 ; (1993) 176 CLR 300 at 305. In that case, Mason CJ, citing Ladbroke (Football) Ltd v William Hill (Football) Ltd [1964] 1 WLR 273 stated:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected. For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that 'there is no copyright' in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright.
 
 As this statement makes clear, in determining whether the quality of what is taken makes it a 'substantial part' of the copyright work, it is important to inquire into the importance which the taken portion bears in relation to the work as a whole: is it an 'essential' or 'material' part of the work? 
 
 ...in the context of copyright law, where emphasis is to be placed upon the 'originality' of the work's expression, the essential or material features of a work should be ascertained by considering the originality of the part allegedly taken. (Emphasis added)

25 Reference to the essential or material features mirrors the language in Powerflex. The passages in both Powerflex and Tamawood are firmly grounded in Ladbroke . In that case, Lord Pearce stated in dictum:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected . For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that " there is no copyright " in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright. (Emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215</tocase>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .

76 To establish infringement in three dimensions from the applicants' plans, the test is still a visual one and it is necessary here to establish that a substantial part of each of the Alleged Infringing Works resembles visually a substantial part of those plans, namely the alfresco quadrant: see further Lend Lease Homes Pty Ltd v Warrigal Homes Pty Ltd [1970] 3 NSWR 265, 273-274; LED Builders Pty Ltd and, in relation to the Copyright Act 1911 , see Chabot v Davies [1936] 3 All ER 221 at 227-228.

82 My personal inspection of the alfresco quadrant in the Prada 35 home demonstrated a close resemblance to that in the Seattle 31 plan: Lend Lease ; LED Builders Pty Ltd . The Prada 35 home also closely resembles the Memphis 33 plan. Accordingly, there is sufficient objective similarity between the two works so as to satisfy the relevant limb of the infringement test espoused in SW Hart . Functional and common stock considerations have been assessed earlier in the judgment, where I compare the Seattle 31 plan and the Prada 35 plan. My findings there in favour of the applicants are similarly found with respect to the Seattle 31 plan and the Prada 35 home in three dimensional form.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Lend Lease Homes Pty Ltd v Warrigal Homes Pty Ltd [1970] 3 NSWR 265</tocase>
<text>76 To establish infringement in three dimensions from the applicants' plans, the test is still a visual one and it is necessary here to establish that a substantial part of each of the Alleged Infringing Works resembles visually a substantial part of those plans, namely the alfresco quadrant: see further Lend Lease Homes Pty Ltd v Warrigal Homes Pty Ltd [1970] 3 NSWR 265, 273-274; LED Builders Pty Ltd and, in relation to the Copyright Act 1911 , see Chabot v Davies [1936] 3 All ER 221 at 227-228.

77 In Lend Lease , the Court reached a conclusion of objective similarity by looking at photographs of the three dimensional structures and comparing them to the plans. However, a visual inspection is perhaps a more telling means of determining this question. I certainly found my inspections in the present case to be most helpful in my analysis. Such inspections occurred in Henley Arch Pty Ltd 41 IPR 443.

78 In this regard, it is important, when considering resemblance from two to three dimensions, to take account of all the matters appearing on the two dimensional floor plans, including the relationship of the rooms and spaces to each other and their approximate dimensions, as indicated in the plan.

79 On the third day of the trial, I inspected a range of properties that were the subject of evidence in two-dimensional form. As to the Prada 35, my impression of a light and spacious interior was derived not from any one particular feature but from the combination of features. The most distinctive features of the Prada 35 home comprised a central hallway leading into a central hub that incorporated:
 
&#8226; the kitchen/dining area (note that the dining room in the Prada 35 is equivalent to the meals room in the Seattle 31); 
 
&#8226; the family/living area;
 
&#8226; the alfresco; and 
 
&#8226; the rumpus room
 
 all under a single ('hip') roof-line.

82 My personal inspection of the alfresco quadrant in the Prada 35 home demonstrated a close resemblance to that in the Seattle 31 plan: Lend Lease ; LED Builders Pty Ltd . The Prada 35 home also closely resembles the Memphis 33 plan. Accordingly, there is sufficient objective similarity between the two works so as to satisfy the relevant limb of the infringement test espoused in SW Hart . Functional and common stock considerations have been assessed earlier in the judgment, where I compare the Seattle 31 plan and the Prada 35 plan. My findings there in favour of the applicants are similarly found with respect to the Seattle 31 plan and the Prada 35 home in three dimensional form.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Milpurrurru &amp; Ors v Indofurn Pty Ltd (1994) 30 IPR 209</tocase>
<text>21 The substantial part inquiry "imputes questions of fact and degree": Tamawood at [51]. What is important is the quality of the part taken, rather than its quantity: SW Hart at 474-5; see also Tamawood at [50] and Milpurrurru &amp; Ors v Indofurn Pty Ltd (1994) 30 IPR 209 at 230 where the Court, in considering the qualitative worth of a part of Aboriginal artwork reproduced on carpets, stated: 
 
 Although as a proportion either of the total artwork, or the total carpet, the area of copied material in comparison with the whole is not great, in a qualitative sense the copying is substantial. The pattern taken from the artwork constitutes the striking feature of the carpet. And again a predominant consideration is the animus furandi of those responsible for the design....</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nationwide News Pty Ltd v Copyright Agency Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 53</tocase>
<text>41 Quantitatively, also, the alfresco quadrant is substantial: it covers about one third of the floor area of the home: see Nationwide News Pty Ltd v Copyright Agency Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 53, where the Court looked at both qualitative and quantitative aspects. While quantitative aspects of the copyright works are of less importance to that of qualitative aspects, I will not disaggregate the fact that the alfresco quadrant constitutes a significant portion of the floor space of the Seattle 31 design. On the contrary, the fact that it covers about one third of the area gives weight to its significance.

42 It follows that I hold that the alfresco quadrant to be a substantial part of the Copyright Works.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nine Network Australia Pty Ltd v IceTV Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1172</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1172.html</AustLII>
<text>26 In other words, if an unoriginal part of the whole is taken that does not represent a substantial part of the labour, skill and judgment of the author that made the whole work 'original', then there is no infringement: Powerflex at [32]. See also, Klissers Bakeries v Harvest Bakeries (1985) IPR 533 and Dixon Investments and Nine Network Australia Pty Ltd v IceTV Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1172.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Pacific Gaming Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Industries Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1636 ; (2001) 116 FCR 448</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1636.html</AustLII>
<text>91 Copying is a question of fact: Skybase Nominees Pty Ltd v Fortuity Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 529 at 531. Generally, access to the copyright works combined with the sufficient objective similarities between the copyright works and the alleged infringing works are relevant. It enables the Court to conclude that independent creation is unlikely and that actual copying has occurred, as I find below: Clarendon at [27]; Pacific Gaming Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Industries Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1636 ; (2001) 116 FCR 448 at [19] .

115 Where objective similarities are so close that it is open to the Court to draw an inference of copying, then such an inference may be rebutted by the respondents by evidence which explains the provenance of the similarities other than as the result of copying the applicants' copyright works: Pacific Gaming at [19] citing Ibcos Computers Ltd v Barclays Mercantile Highland Finance Ltd [1994] FSR 275, at 296-297; Ancher, Mortlock, Murray &amp; Woolley Pty Ltd at 284; Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 231</tocase>
<text>265 In Cooper at [159]-[164], Kenny J observed that no Full Court of this Court had settled which of these two tests was to be preferred, or indeed whether the exposition by Finkelstein J in Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 231 ought be followed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Skybase Nominees Pty Ltd v Fortuity Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 529</tocase>
<text>91 Copying is a question of fact: Skybase Nominees Pty Ltd v Fortuity Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 529 at 531. Generally, access to the copyright works combined with the sufficient objective similarities between the copyright works and the alleged infringing works are relevant. It enables the Court to conclude that independent creation is unlikely and that actual copying has occurred, as I find below: Clarendon at [27]; Pacific Gaming Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Industries Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1636 ; (2001) 116 FCR 448 at [19] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spectravest Inc v Aperknit Ltd [1988] FSR 161</tocase>
<text>20 As rightly pointed out in Eagle Homes the word "reproduction" is not defined in the Act. Its ordinary meaning, however, is to "make a copy, representation, duplicate, or close imitation of" (Macquarie Dictionary) or "repeat in a more or less exact copy; produce a copy or representation of" (New Shorter Oxford English Dictionary). The question that follows from this is: how much of the copyright work must be reproduced before it can be said that the 'work' has been reproduced and how similar must it be to the copyright work? See Eagle Homes at [70]. There Lindgren J considered how s 14(1) and s 31(1)(b)(i) of the Act interrelate as applied to the "Paterson" and "Kookaburra" project homes that were the subject of the litigation. At [70] to [71], his Honour stated:
 
 The effect of s 14(1) of the Act is that the reference in s 31(1)(b)(i) to reproducing an artistic work in a material form includes a reference to reproducing a substantial part of such a work in a material form. In terms, this provision acknowledges a distinction between the undifferentiated whole of a copyright work and a substantial part of it. The 'Paterson' does not reproduce exactly the whole of the 'Kookaburra'. Copinger and Skone James on Copyright (13th ed, 1991), par 8 20 states as follows:
 
 ... Alternatively, the defendant's work may have been taken from part only of the plaintiff's work. Here, the defendant's work may be an exact reproduction of that part of the plaintiff's work or it may only to a greater or lesser degree resemble that part. In this alternative class of case, the first step is to identify the part of the plaintiff's work which is alleged to have been reproduced and then decide whether it constitutes a substantial part of the plaintiff's work. If it does, but it is not an exact copy of that part, it must then be decided whether it is a reproduction or colourable imitation of that part of the plaintiff's work. [ Spectravest Inc v Aperknit Ltd [1988] FSR 161].

244 The Coburn design raises some different considerations. As Dr Cooke points out, the alfresco, dining and sitting areas in the Coburn, compared with the Prada 35, have been repositioned such that the rumpus (or home theatre) opens to the dining area, whereas the Seattle 31 alfresco space is bordered by the rumpus room and meals area. This, he said, results in plans less similar to the Seattle 31 than the Prada 35 plans. Still, his view was that the Coburn plans had been derived by reference to the Seattle 31 plans via modified Prada 35 plans. I accept this opinion and it conforms with my own impressions. The alfresco area, even though repositioned, is under one roof-line and on my view of the home, maintained the same distinct and significant impression. The changes are minor and inconsequential: Spectravest Inc v Aperknit Ltd [1988] FSR 161.

245 Again, I have accepted the expert opinion evidence of Dr John Cooke to the effect that the alfresco quadrant in each of the Tyrell 29, the Connolly 30 and the Streeton 34 plans and homes were subject to minor modifications, essentially the same as the Seattle 31 plan and home. This is so whether the comparison is plan to plan, home to home or plan to home. These opinions involving comparisons with the Seattle 31 plan and home were generally also applicable to the same comparisons but involving the Memphis 33 plan and home. This too was the case in comparisons between the Memphis 33 plan and home and the Coburn plan and home.

246 I have again not, for reasons I explain below, afforded any weight to the opinion of Mr John Permewan.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/59.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The test for infringement is found in the well known passage from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in S W Hart &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Edwards Hot Water Systems [1985] HCA 59 ; (1985) 159 CLR 466 at 472 (with whom Mason and Brennan JJ agreed). In that case, the Chief Justice said:
 
 The notion of reproduction, for the purposes of copyright law, involves two elements -- resemblance to, and actual use of, the copyright work, or, to adopt the words which appear in the judgment of Willmer LJ in Francis Day &amp; Hunter Ltd v Bron [1963] Ch 587 at 614, "a sufficient degree of objective similarity between the two works" and "some causal connection between the plaintiffs' and the defendants' work". (Emphasis added) 
 
 

See also Dixon Investments Pty Ltd v Hall (1990) 18 IPR 490 at 495; LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 215 at 218; Henley Arch Pty Ltd v Clarendon Homes (Aust) Pty Ltd (1998) 41 IPR 443; Eagle Homes Pty Ltd v Austec Homes Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 138 ; (1999) 87 FCR 415 at [17] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Tamawood v Henley Arch (2004) 61 IPR 378</tocase>
<text>14 In Tamawood Ltd v Henley Arch Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 378 at 387, another project home case, the majority at [39] observed that: "The idea-form distinction, often elusive, is particularly so in the case of project homes". This, their Honours said at [38] was because such homes commonly have to be designed to fit blocks of approximately similar shape and dimension and to provide for vehicular access and accommodation. There was, it was said, a certain commonality of features demanded by the market in question:
 
 ... such as, a certain number of bedrooms, a laundry, a kitchen, a family or rumpus room, an ensuite and a walk-in wardrobe ("WIR") in association with the main bedroom, built-in wardrobes in the other bedrooms, at least one bathroom in proximity to the other bedrooms, and certain facilities in the kitchen such as a sink, bench, dishwasher, stove, hot plate and microwave oven.

15 Project homes, and the drawing of such plans, are distinct from paintings and musical works. The distinction lies in the fact that a project home involves a mixture of familiar ideas and common place features "based on the real world" (in the form of previous project homes and plans) and "labour, skill and judgment (in combining the various features)": Tamawood at [41] [43]. The issue is further complicated when one bears in mind that the plan for a project home is "partly functional." For example, placing a kitchen in reasonable "proximity to a dining room" is, broadly, a functional consideration: see Tamawood at [41]. Accordingly, the "dividing line between that which is dictated by broad functional requirements and that which is not, is...often unclear": Tamawood at [56].

16 Importantly, one must bear in mind in this case, and as was explained in Tamawood , that an individual part of a plan or home considered in isolation may merely explain a common idea "...yet there will be copyright in the whole plan if the combination and arrangement originated with the author." (Emphasis added): Tamawood at [41].

17 The applicants in this case point to the particular combination in the alfresco quadrant as central to their claims.

21 The substantial part inquiry "imputes questions of fact and degree": Tamawood at [51]. What is important is the quality of the part taken, rather than its quantity: SW Hart at 474-5; see also Tamawood at [50] and Milpurrurru &amp; Ors v Indofurn Pty Ltd (1994) 30 IPR 209 at 230 where the Court, in considering the qualitative worth of a part of Aboriginal artwork reproduced on carpets, stated: 
 
 Although as a proportion either of the total artwork, or the total carpet, the area of copied material in comparison with the whole is not great, in a qualitative sense the copying is substantial. The pattern taken from the artwork constitutes the striking feature of the carpet. And again a predominant consideration is the animus furandi of those responsible for the design....

24 In Tamawood , the Full Court considered the meaning of the expression, 'substantial part', in the context of plans for project homes. Wilcox and Lindgren JJ concluded at [55] that:
 
 ... it is not infringement of the part, but infringement of the whole that is in question. Whether there has been an infringement of the whole requires that the originality of the part be considered in relation to the work in suit as a whole. It must be determined whether the part is an 'essential or material' feature of the whole work , regarded as a copyright work, in the present case, as an artistic work. In our opinion, it must be asked whether the part or parts taken represent a substantial part of the labour, skill and judgment of the author that made the whole work 'original' . (Emphasis added)

25 Reference to the essential or material features mirrors the language in Powerflex. The passages in both Powerflex and Tamawood are firmly grounded in Ladbroke . In that case, Lord Pearce stated in dictum:
 
 Whether a part is substantial must be decided by its quality rather than its quantity. The reproduction of a part which by itself has no originality will not normally be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore will not be protected . For that which would not attract copyright except by reason of its collocation will, when robbed of that collocation, not be a substantial part of the copyright and therefore the courts will not hold its reproduction to be an infringement. It is this, I think, which is meant by one or two judicial observations that " there is no copyright " in some unoriginal part of a whole that is copyright. (Emphasis added)

36 Third, key features are clearly important and distinct particularly when features of the designs are viewed in collocation and as a whole. The distinctiveness of the Copyright Works also goes to the consideration of the quality of the works. While novelty is not a consideration of copyright, recent cases such as Tamawood suggest that distinctiveness and that which is "essential" to the copyright works are important considerations in cases where substantial part is at issue: see Tamawood at [51]-[54] and particularly at [89]. Cases such as TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd v Network Ten Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 108 ; (2001) 184 ALR 1 also stress the need to look at the essential features. See also McCutcheon's discussion in the article Property in Literary Characters [2007] EIPR 143.

43 I will now compare the alfresco quadrant, being the substantial part of the Copyright Works, with the Alleged Infringing Works, to determine whether there is a sufficient objective similarity, having regard to: 
 
 
 (a) the similarities and differences in the comparison: Tamawood at [28] and [86]-[89]; 
 (b) the essential material and non-functional parts - being the most important and significant parts of the works: Tamawood at [86]-[89]; and
 (c) commonplace features that preceded the design of the Copyright Works: Clarendon at [42].

44 Although I deal with these discretely, in the end, I consider them cumulatively. I will first compare the Seattle 31 plan (Schedule A) with the Prada 35 plan (Schedule C).

45 Before doing so, I note that there is no relevant distinction between the Seattle 31 plan and the Memphis 33 plan. The Memphis 33 plan produces a marginally larger floor area. The applicants' statement of claim outlines the changes that were made to the Seattle 31 to construct the Memphis 33, at paragraph 12. Those changes include:
 
&#8226; additional space in internal areas;
 
&#8226; the garage position pulled back behind the front of the building line; and
 
&#8226; the front wall configuration to allow the inclusion of an attached portico.

48 The assessment is a matter of impression for the Court: see generally Tamawood and Clarendon. In making the assessment, the Court was invited to compare the transparencies of the Seattle 31 and Prada 35 plans. Upon overlay of the transparencies, one can clearly see the striking similarities. In my view, the alfresco quadrant is almost identical in both cases. This is of paramount importance to the present case, as it constitutes the substantial part of the applicants' plan.

49 My view is further fortified by several lay and expert witnesses of both parties. For instance, Popple agreed that the position of the kitchen was "sort of similar" and that of the rumpus, alfresco, family room and meals area were "similar." The area that Popple refers to is, in essence, the alfresco quadrant. Palezzesi also found it difficult to disagree with Popple's assessment.

50 The similarity between the Prada 35 and Seattle 31 designs was confirmed by Popple in cross-examination. Popple's and Palazzesi's observations of similarity given in the witness box in fact extended beyond the alfresco quadrant to include bedrooms two, three and four.

56 In Tamawood at [56], Wilcox and Lindgren JJ considered the functional aspects of the copyright works: 
 
 In applying the "substantial part" test in the present case, one must bear in mind that the plan for a project home is partly functional. Placing a kitchen in reasonable proximity to a dining room, and bedrooms in reasonable proximity to each other and to a bathroom, is suggested by broad functional considerations. Those proximities would not be a substantial part of a plan or house regarded as an artistic work. Moreover, they would be ideas. But broad functional requirements can be satisfied in more ways than one. Some features of a project home plan may be dictated by aesthetic and decorative concerns, for example. In these ways, the labour, skill and judgment of the author are called upon. The dividing line between that which is dictated by broad functional requirements and that which is not, is, however, often unclear.

57 The alfresco quadrant, as I have found, is a most important feature, being both essential and material to the design of the Seattle 31 plan. Significant labour, skill and judgment went into the design of the plan, including 130 drawings over a six month period. The designs are centred around the incorporation of an alfresco, which is the part that the respondents have taken. To arrive at this conclusion, I must also examine why the alfresco quadrant is not functional. This was a key argument submitted by the respondents. I will turn to that issue below.

58 A primary contention of the respondents was that there was very little (if any) room for choice as to where the alfresco and surrounding rooms could be placed in the Prada 35. The respondents' contention was purportedly buttressed by the following points:
 
 &#8226; since any alfresco is situated where the informal living rooms are situated to the "rear" or to the "side" of the house, there are limited options as to how an arrangement of rooms can be configured; 
 &#8226; thus, if one decided to configure an alfresco within a Melbourne project home, either to the "rear" or to the "side" of the house, it would ordinarily be surrounded by rumpus, family and dining or meal rooms; and 
 &#8226; this, the respondents assert, is what happened in the case of the Prada 35. Further, they assert that the applicants' arrangement is not "so unusual" that it must have been derived from the Seattle 31 plan.

62 The respondents point to the fact that the doors and windows are differently sized and positioned. These differences, it was submitted, were highly significant given the asserted limited scope for variation in what they described as the very restrictive part of the plan relied upon by the applicants. Kenrick was used to support the respondents' submission. I disagree. This is not a " Kenrick "-like case, where there was only one means of expressing the idea of a hand ticking a box. Instead, it conforms with what Wilcox and Lindgren JJ stated in Tamawood , that "broad functional requirements can be satisfied in more ways that one" at [56]. The evidence discloses that there are a number of ways of incorporating an alfresco in combination with a kitchen, living, dining and rumpus. Accordingly, the plan as expressed in the Seattle 31 design is far from obvious, as contended by the respondents' counsel and witnesses. I reject the submission that the design of the alfresco quadrant was 'obvious'. For example, there was no necessity for the shape of the alfresco to be rectangular: there are examples of angled rectangular shapes in the prior art. Longer rectangular features, squares and other shapes thus were possible options.

73 It is to be remembered that it is the combination of features producing the alfresco quadrant which is the result of the labour, skill and judgment of the applicants' Copyright Works and, which as a whole, may be characterised as original. Quite apart from the failure to cross-examine as to the matters which I have identified, the conclusion of infringement is not to be challenged by breaking down the alfresco quadrant and considering the individual areas, and then considering each in isolation as to whether it represents a common or stock feature: Tamawood 61 IPR 378 at [41].

74 While there was some discounting of common stock designs in the Tamawood decision, this is not a Tamawood case. Tamawood is distinguishable from this case on the basis that the starting design for the respondent's work in Tamawood was a design that it had owned. The respondent had then incorporated aspects from the applicant's copyright work into the original starting design owned by the respondent. Moreover, the case is distinct for another reason. In Tamawood , the level of specificity of the analysis of the 18 items was particular to that case. Here, the substantial part can be grouped within the back end of the Seattle 31 plan, being the alfresco quadrant. In light of the distinctions with Tamawood, the issue of discounting as outlined in that case is not applicable in this case.

75 Accordingly, in my opinion, there is sufficient objective similarity to satisfy the first limb of the SW Hart test, as between the alfresco quadrant in the Seattle 31 and that in the Prada 35.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd v Network Ten Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 108 ; (2001) 184 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/108.html</AustLII>
<text>36 Third, key features are clearly important and distinct particularly when features of the designs are viewed in collocation and as a whole. The distinctiveness of the Copyright Works also goes to the consideration of the quality of the works. While novelty is not a consideration of copyright, recent cases such as Tamawood suggest that distinctiveness and that which is "essential" to the copyright works are important considerations in cases where substantial part is at issue: see Tamawood at [51]-[54] and particularly at [89]. Cases such as TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd v Network Ten Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 108 ; (2001) 184 ALR 1 also stress the need to look at the essential features. See also McCutcheon's discussion in the article Property in Literary Characters [2007] EIPR 143.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>University of New South Wales v Moorhouse [1975] HCA 26 ; (1975) 133 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1975/26.html</AustLII>
<text>261 While the Court must take these matters into account, they are not the only matters that may be taken into account: Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 at [13] per Branson J; [135] per Kenny J, French J agreeing (concerning the construction and application of s 101(1A) of the Act which corresponds in terms to s 36(1A), in the context of infringement of copyright in sound recordings, films and the like). Both these sections are premised on the concept of "authorisation" developed by the High Court in University of New South Wales v Moorhouse [1975] HCA 26 ; (1975) 133 CLR 1; Cooper at [136]. The word "authorise" in the cases has been given its dictionary meaning of "sanction, approve or countenance": Falcon v Famous Players Film Company [1926] 2 KB 474; Adelaide City Corporation v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481; Moorhouse at 12 (Gibbs J), 20-21 (Jacobs J); WEA International Inc v Hanimex Corp Ltd (1987) 17 FCR 274, 285-286 (Gummow J); Cooper at [20] per Branson J, French J agreeing.

267 As the managing director, Palazzesi accepted that Metricon would not have included the Prada 35 in its product line without his approval. This fact, and the fact that Popple and Bugeja were subject to his direction, were said not in themselves to be enough to constitute authorisation by him. It was contended, in my view correctly, that the necessary mental element required to be established: Moorhouse at p 12 per Gibbs CJ. In other words, in this case, it is necessary, in order to render Palazzesi liable, not only that he approved the Alleged Infringing Works but that he did so knowing that they contained a copy of the alfresco quadrant from the Seattle 31. This is not of universal application but it is the way that the case was put by the applicants.

268 Palazzesi did acknowledge in cross-examination that there are similarities between the Prada 35 and the Seattle 31, identifying the position of the two bedrooms, rumpus room, kitchen, dining and family and alfresco. It was said, however, that there is no evidence that Palazzesi knew or appreciated that Prototype 20B, or the Prada 35, were copied from the Seattle 31 plan or home or were so similar that they must have been copied. Palazzesi denied that he had any such appreciation.

269 Palazzesi pointed particularly to a number of matters which he says demonstrate that he had no relevant knowledge:
 
(a) Popple did not tell him that he, Popple, thought Prototype 20B had similarities to the Seattle 31 display; 
 
(b) the reference by Jason Biasin to the similarity of the Richmond in Perth to the Seattle 31 was a reference to a fa&ccedil;ade and that there was no reason for him to be thinking about the Seattle 31 at the time they were looking at the Pavillion;
 
(c) he had no special interest in the activities of the applicants between January 2000 when the Seattle 31 display opened, and 2002 when the Prada 35 was designed, and in particular:
 
 
 
 (i) he was not aware of how many homes were sold by the Barrett Property Group; 
 (ii) he did not think about the Seattle 31 after his brief visit in January 2000 until Stutterd complained to Kline in mid 2003;
 (iii) while he did hope to keep abreast of the competition, he was not watching the applicants and the pressures on him were to build homes and manage the explosive growth at Metricon; and 
 (iv) he did not know about the applicant's success with the Seattle 31; or how many homes they had sold by February 2002; other than he had heard that "they were doing OK"; 
 
 

(d) courtyard houses, with the meals, kitchen, family and rumpus areas arranged around an outdoor space were well known and he had involvement with a number of such designs (including both the Simonds Monterey and Seville as well as AV Jennings homes); and
 
(e) the points of reference for the alfresco feature or concept were what he (and the others) had seen on the Perth trip.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Winstone v Wurlitzer Automatic Phonograph Co of Australia Pty Ltd [1946] VLR 338</tocase>
<text>262 It is a question of fact in each case, as to what inferences may be drawn from the conduct of the person said to have authorised the act of which complaint is made: Winstone v Wurlitzer Automatic Phonograph Co of Australia Pty Ltd [1946] VLR 338. This was referred to with apparent approval by the Full Court in Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Jain (1990) 26 FCR 53 at 59.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>