<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts (No. 3) [2007] FCA 1567 (11 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1567.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Alphapharm Pty Limited v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Limited [1996] FCA 391</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1996/391.html</AustLII>
<text>57 In his reasons for judgment in Alphapharm Pty Limited v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Limited [1996] FCA 391 ('Alphapharm'), Lindgren J made certain observations concerning Order 15A rule 6 at [41] as follows:
 
 
 '1. Paragraphs 6 (a) and 6 (c) pose an objective test, the opening words "there is" in each paragraph signifying "there exists"; but the "insufficiency test" of para 6 (b) has both subjective and objective aspects. 
 
 
 
 
 
 2. Although I need not explore the subjective aspect fully, it seems clear that if the evidence went so far as to show that a particular applicant was already able to decide to commence a proceeding by, for example, showing that the applicant had in fact decided to do so, para 6 (b) would not be satisfied even though the information available satisfied the objective aspect of the insufficiency test referred to below. 
 
 
 
 
 
 3. The fact that a particular applicant genuinely feels unable, because of a lack of information, to decide to commence a proceeding does not, without more, satisfy para 6 (b); the objective aspect of the paragraph requires it to be shown as an objective fact that the applicant lacks "sufficient information to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding". 
 
 
 
 
 
 4. In my view, the objective aspect of para 6 (b) invokes a notion of "reasonable sufficiency", the question raised being whether it is reasonable that the applicant for an order be required to take its decision without having the information to become available from inspection of the document or documents of which discovery is sought. 
 
 
 
 
 
 5. If the insufficiency test is satisfied, a second question will arise, namely, whether the Court's discretion should be exercised in favour of the making of an order. 
 
 
 
 
 
 6. The questions posed by rule 6 and referred to above are to be answered in the context of an adversary system of forensic contest in which a proposed respondent is ordinarily entitled to withhold its evidence, certainly prior to the commencement of proceedings. 
 
 7. The questions are also to be answered in the light of the nature of the "cause of action" contemplated and the range of information potentially available in respect of a cause of action of that kind. 
 
 
 
 
 
 8. ... in my opinion rule 6 is not necessarily rendered unavailable by the fact that the applicant already has available evidence establishing a prima facie case for the granting of relief. This is made clear by the reference in para (a) to the existence of "reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has ... the right to obtain relief ..." (emphasis supplied). It would impose an artificial constraint on rule 6, not supported by its terms or purpose, to exclude, a priori , all cases in which the insufficiency of the information possessed by the applicant to enable a decision to be made whether to litigate is due to a matter of "defence" which would defeat the prima facie case. 
 
 
 
 
 
 9. Rule 6 does not provide a means by which an applicant will be enabled to have available to it every document which would assist it in deciding whether to litigate. If that were the intention, paras (a) and (c) would stand alone and the additional condition set out in para (b) would not be necessary. 
 
 
 
 
 
 10. Paragraph 6 (b) contemplates that after making all reasonable inquiries, the applicant has come up against a problem, namely, that it is lacking a piece of information or pieces of information reasonably necessary to enable it to decide whether to commence a proceeding.'

58 In St George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 Hely J stated a series of propositions which his Honour considered had emerged from the authorities in relation to the proper application of Order 15A rule 6 at [26] as follows:
 
 
 '(a) the rule is to be beneficially construed, given the fullest scope that its language will reasonably allow, with the proper brake on any excesses lying in the discretion of the court, exercised in the particular circumstances of each case: Paxus Services Ltd v People Bank Pty Ltd (1990) 99 ALR 728 at 733; 20 IPR 79 at 85; Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 ; BC9902167 at [27]; 
 
 (b) each of the elements prescribed in subparas (a), (b) and (c) of the rule must be established: Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at 11 [38] ; 167 ALR 385 at 367; [1999] FCA 1584 ; 47 IPR 21 at 30. Preliminary discovery cannot itself be used to remedy deficiencies in the satisfaction of the conditions themselves: Airservices Australia v Transfield Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 886 ; (1999) 92 FCR 200 at 202 3 [5]; [1999] FCA 886 ; 164 ALR 330 at 332; 
 
 (c) the test for determining whether the applicant has "reasonable cause to believe", as required by subpara (a), is an objective one: Hooper at FCR 11 12 [39]; ALR 367; IPR 30; Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 710 ; BC9902833 at [16]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 [24]; 49 IPR 25 at 31; Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] FCA 391 ; BC9602085 at 23. Further, the words "or may have" cannot be ignored. The applicant does not have to make out a prima facie case: Quanta Software at ALR 541-2 [24]; IPR 31; Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85; 
 
 (d) belief requires more than mere assertion and more than suspicion or conjecture. Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting a proposition. Thus it is not sufficient to point to a mere possibility. The evidence must incline the mind towards the matter or fact in question. If there is no reasonable cause to believe that one of the necessary elements of a potential cause of action exists, that would dispose of the application insofar as it is based on that cause of action: John Holland Services Pty Ltd v Terranora Group Management Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 679 ; BC200403021 at [13], [14], [17] and [73]; 
 
 (e) while uncertainty as to only one element of a cause of action might be compatible with the "reasonable cause to believe" required by subpara (a), uncertainty as to a number of such elements may be sufficient to undermine the reasonableness of the cause to believe: Glowatzky v Insultech Group Pty Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 215 ;
 
 (f) the question posed by subpara (b) of the rule is not whether the applicant has sufficient information to decide if a cause of action is available against the prospective respondent. The question is whether the applicant has sufficient information to make a decision whether to commence proceedings in the court: Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6. Accordingly, an applicant for preliminary discovery may be entitled to discovery in order to determine what defences are available to the respondent and the possible strength of those defences, or to determine the extent of the respondent's breach and the likely quantum of any damages award: CGU Insurance Ltd v Malaysia International Shipping Corp Berhad (2001) 187 ALR at 285 [21]; Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6, Airservices Australia at FCR 202 3 [5]; ALR 332 
 
 (g) whether an applicant has "sufficient information" for the purposes of subpara (b) also requires an objective assessment to be made: Minister for Health at [44]; Alphapharm at 23 4, Hooper at FCR 12 [40]; ALR 367; IPR 31. The subparagraph contemplates that the applicant is lacking a piece (or pieces) of information reasonably necessary to decide whether to commence proceedings; 
 
 (h) it is no answer to an application under the rule to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a "fishing expedition": Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85. Indeed O 15A r 6 "expressly contemplates" what once might have been castigated as "fishing": Bailey v Beagle Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 60 ; (2001) 105 FCR 136 at 143 [27] ; [2001] FCA 60 ; 182 ALR 264 at 270-1; 20 IPR 79 at 85. As Burchett J commented in Paxus Services , the rule is (at ALR 733; IPR 85): 
 
 
 
 
 
 ... designed to enable an applicant, in a situation where his proof can rise no higher than the level the rule describes, to ascertain whether he has a case against the prospective respondent ...'

77 Order 15A rule 6 is directed to aiding an applicant who is having real difficulty, and reasonably so, in deciding whether to litigate because of a lack of key information, whether relating to its own case or to that of the proposed respondent, which is in the possession of the respondent. It requires evidence demonstrating that the applicant for relief is on the horns of a dilemma: whether to sue or not to sue (per Lindgren J in Alphapharm at [45]).

78 Telstra claims that there is reasonable cause to believe that it may have, or already has, the right to obtain judicial review of the relevant administrative action involved in the allocation of an additional $358 million to the Infrastructure Programme, for which the Minister is responsible, without affording all applicants for the base funding of up to $600 million an opportunity to submit proposals as to how a grant to them of $958 million could have been spent to secure the desired outcome and meet the original benchmarks and more.

79 It wishes to mount an argument that it was denied procedural fairness.

125 Given Telstra's predisposition, as evidenced by the memorandum, to in effect 'sue regardless' it seems that the subjective aspect of the rule 6(b) requirement could not be satisfied in this case. The evidence does not, in my opinion, demonstrate that, to use Lindgren J's expression 'Telstra is on the horns of a dilemma: whether to sue or not'.

126 This brings me to the question of discretion. No question of delay arises. It was reasonable for Telstra to await Clayton Utz's response of 26 July 2007 to its Group General Counsel, Legal Services' letter of 19 July 2007 before making its Order 15A rule 6 application, which, in its original form, was filed on 3 August 2007.

127 However, I consider that the evidence of Telstra's 'sue regardless' disposition in respect of the award of $958 million of funding to OPEL Networks Pty Ltd is a matter properly taken into account in considering the proper exercise of the Court's discretion, as is the further observation contained in the internal draft memorandum, namely:
 
 'If we are successful in getting documents this way, there will be limits on how they are used (eg only for litigation purposes, not in the media), but the hearing itself will be public and would presumably of itself be of media interest.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>St George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147</tocase>
<text>58 In St George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 Hely J stated a series of propositions which his Honour considered had emerged from the authorities in relation to the proper application of Order 15A rule 6 at [26] as follows:
 
 
 '(a) the rule is to be beneficially construed, given the fullest scope that its language will reasonably allow, with the proper brake on any excesses lying in the discretion of the court, exercised in the particular circumstances of each case: Paxus Services Ltd v People Bank Pty Ltd (1990) 99 ALR 728 at 733; 20 IPR 79 at 85; Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 ; BC9902167 at [27]; 
 
 (b) each of the elements prescribed in subparas (a), (b) and (c) of the rule must be established: Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at 11 [38] ; 167 ALR 385 at 367; [1999] FCA 1584 ; 47 IPR 21 at 30. Preliminary discovery cannot itself be used to remedy deficiencies in the satisfaction of the conditions themselves: Airservices Australia v Transfield Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 886 ; (1999) 92 FCR 200 at 202 3 [5]; [1999] FCA 886 ; 164 ALR 330 at 332; 
 
 (c) the test for determining whether the applicant has "reasonable cause to believe", as required by subpara (a), is an objective one: Hooper at FCR 11 12 [39]; ALR 367; IPR 30; Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 710 ; BC9902833 at [16]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 [24]; 49 IPR 25 at 31; Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] FCA 391 ; BC9602085 at 23. Further, the words "or may have" cannot be ignored. The applicant does not have to make out a prima facie case: Quanta Software at ALR 541-2 [24]; IPR 31; Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85; 
 
 (d) belief requires more than mere assertion and more than suspicion or conjecture. Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting a proposition. Thus it is not sufficient to point to a mere possibility. The evidence must incline the mind towards the matter or fact in question. If there is no reasonable cause to believe that one of the necessary elements of a potential cause of action exists, that would dispose of the application insofar as it is based on that cause of action: John Holland Services Pty Ltd v Terranora Group Management Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 679 ; BC200403021 at [13], [14], [17] and [73]; 
 
 (e) while uncertainty as to only one element of a cause of action might be compatible with the "reasonable cause to believe" required by subpara (a), uncertainty as to a number of such elements may be sufficient to undermine the reasonableness of the cause to believe: Glowatzky v Insultech Group Pty Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 215 ;
 
 (f) the question posed by subpara (b) of the rule is not whether the applicant has sufficient information to decide if a cause of action is available against the prospective respondent. The question is whether the applicant has sufficient information to make a decision whether to commence proceedings in the court: Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6. Accordingly, an applicant for preliminary discovery may be entitled to discovery in order to determine what defences are available to the respondent and the possible strength of those defences, or to determine the extent of the respondent's breach and the likely quantum of any damages award: CGU Insurance Ltd v Malaysia International Shipping Corp Berhad (2001) 187 ALR at 285 [21]; Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6, Airservices Australia at FCR 202 3 [5]; ALR 332 
 
 (g) whether an applicant has "sufficient information" for the purposes of subpara (b) also requires an objective assessment to be made: Minister for Health at [44]; Alphapharm at 23 4, Hooper at FCR 12 [40]; ALR 367; IPR 31. The subparagraph contemplates that the applicant is lacking a piece (or pieces) of information reasonably necessary to decide whether to commence proceedings; 
 
 (h) it is no answer to an application under the rule to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a "fishing expedition": Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85. Indeed O 15A r 6 "expressly contemplates" what once might have been castigated as "fishing": Bailey v Beagle Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 60 ; (2001) 105 FCR 136 at 143 [27] ; [2001] FCA 60 ; 182 ALR 264 at 270-1; 20 IPR 79 at 85. As Burchett J commented in Paxus Services , the rule is (at ALR 733; IPR 85): 
 
 
 
 
 
 ... designed to enable an applicant, in a situation where his proof can rise no higher than the level the rule describes, to ascertain whether he has a case against the prospective respondent ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Global Intertrade Pty Ltd v Adelaide Festival Centre Trust [1999] FCA 162</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/162.html</AustLII>
<text>61 Whilst Order 15A makes no provision as to the means whereby discovery should be given by a party such as the Minister to a party such as Telstra, it seems clear to me that discovery must be given in the manner for which Order 15 rule 2(2) provides, namely:
 
 
 '2(2) Unless the Court or a Judge orders otherwise, a party must give discovery by serving: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) a list of documents required to be disclosed; and 
 
 (b) an affidavit verifying the list.' 
 
 


Mansfield J expressed the same view in Global Intertrade Pty Ltd v Adelaide Festival Centre Trust [1999] FCA 162 at [2] .

62 The form of the list of documents may, in my opinion, be taken to have been regulated by Order 15 rule 6, which relevantly provides:
 
 
 '6(1) A list of documents required by or under this Order shall, unless the Court otherwise orders, be in accordance with Form 22 and conform to the requirements of this rule. 
 
 
 
 
 
 (2) A list of documents shall enumerate the documents which are ... in the possession ... of the party making the list. 
 
 (3) A list of documents shall enumerate the documents in a convenient sequence and as shortly as possible, but shall describe each document or, in the case of a group of documents of the same nature, shall describe the group, sufficiently to enable the document or group to be identified. 
 ... 
 
 (8) Where a party making a list of documents has a solicitor in the proceeding, the solicitor shall certify on the list that, according to his instructions, the list and the statements in the list are correct.'

63 Form 22, of course, provides for documents to be enumerated one by one in either Schedule 1 Part 1, Schedule 1 Part 2 or Schedule 2 of the relevant list. The operative words in Form 22 are:
 
 
 '1. The party has in his possession ... the documents enumerated in Schedule 1. 
 
 2. The documents enumerated in Part 2 of Schedule 1 are privileged from production on the ground ... 
 ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hall v The Nominal Defendant [1966] HCA 36 ; (1966) 117 CLR 423</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1966/36.html</AustLII>
<text>66 An order made in the course of an action or suit which does not conclude the rights of the parties inter se, although it may conclude the fate of the particular application in which it is made, is interlocutory only (per Taylor J in Hall v The Nominal Defendant [1966] HCA 36 ; (1966) 117 CLR 423 ('Hall') at 440; see also per Owen J at 447).

67 It is not of the essence of an interlocutory order that it is one made in the course of a pending action or suit (per Taylor J in Hall at 440; see also per Owen J at 447).

68 An order made on an application in proceedings preliminary to the bringing of an action, which does not preclude a further application to like effect being brought, is interlocutory (per Taylor J in Hall at 440; see also per Owen J at 447).

69 The character of proceedings such as an application under Order 15A rule 6 may be of more significance than the result for an applicant, in determining whether an order is interlocutory or not (per Windeyer J in Hall at 445).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 284 ; (1999) 86 FCR 134</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/284.html</AustLII>
<text>58 In St George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 Hely J stated a series of propositions which his Honour considered had emerged from the authorities in relation to the proper application of Order 15A rule 6 at [26] as follows:
 
 
 '(a) the rule is to be beneficially construed, given the fullest scope that its language will reasonably allow, with the proper brake on any excesses lying in the discretion of the court, exercised in the particular circumstances of each case: Paxus Services Ltd v People Bank Pty Ltd (1990) 99 ALR 728 at 733; 20 IPR 79 at 85; Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 ; BC9902167 at [27]; 
 
 (b) each of the elements prescribed in subparas (a), (b) and (c) of the rule must be established: Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at 11 [38] ; 167 ALR 385 at 367; [1999] FCA 1584 ; 47 IPR 21 at 30. Preliminary discovery cannot itself be used to remedy deficiencies in the satisfaction of the conditions themselves: Airservices Australia v Transfield Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 886 ; (1999) 92 FCR 200 at 202 3 [5]; [1999] FCA 886 ; 164 ALR 330 at 332; 
 
 (c) the test for determining whether the applicant has "reasonable cause to believe", as required by subpara (a), is an objective one: Hooper at FCR 11 12 [39]; ALR 367; IPR 30; Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 710 ; BC9902833 at [16]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 [24]; 49 IPR 25 at 31; Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] FCA 391 ; BC9602085 at 23. Further, the words "or may have" cannot be ignored. The applicant does not have to make out a prima facie case: Quanta Software at ALR 541-2 [24]; IPR 31; Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85; 
 
 (d) belief requires more than mere assertion and more than suspicion or conjecture. Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting a proposition. Thus it is not sufficient to point to a mere possibility. The evidence must incline the mind towards the matter or fact in question. If there is no reasonable cause to believe that one of the necessary elements of a potential cause of action exists, that would dispose of the application insofar as it is based on that cause of action: John Holland Services Pty Ltd v Terranora Group Management Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 679 ; BC200403021 at [13], [14], [17] and [73]; 
 
 (e) while uncertainty as to only one element of a cause of action might be compatible with the "reasonable cause to believe" required by subpara (a), uncertainty as to a number of such elements may be sufficient to undermine the reasonableness of the cause to believe: Glowatzky v Insultech Group Pty Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 215 ;
 
 (f) the question posed by subpara (b) of the rule is not whether the applicant has sufficient information to decide if a cause of action is available against the prospective respondent. The question is whether the applicant has sufficient information to make a decision whether to commence proceedings in the court: Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6. Accordingly, an applicant for preliminary discovery may be entitled to discovery in order to determine what defences are available to the respondent and the possible strength of those defences, or to determine the extent of the respondent's breach and the likely quantum of any damages award: CGU Insurance Ltd v Malaysia International Shipping Corp Berhad (2001) 187 ALR at 285 [21]; Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6, Airservices Australia at FCR 202 3 [5]; ALR 332 
 
 (g) whether an applicant has "sufficient information" for the purposes of subpara (b) also requires an objective assessment to be made: Minister for Health at [44]; Alphapharm at 23 4, Hooper at FCR 12 [40]; ALR 367; IPR 31. The subparagraph contemplates that the applicant is lacking a piece (or pieces) of information reasonably necessary to decide whether to commence proceedings; 
 
 (h) it is no answer to an application under the rule to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a "fishing expedition": Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85. Indeed O 15A r 6 "expressly contemplates" what once might have been castigated as "fishing": Bailey v Beagle Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 60 ; (2001) 105 FCR 136 at 143 [27] ; [2001] FCA 60 ; 182 ALR 264 at 270-1; 20 IPR 79 at 85. As Burchett J commented in Paxus Services , the rule is (at ALR 733; IPR 85): 
 
 
 
 
 
 ... designed to enable an applicant, in a situation where his proof can rise no higher than the level the rule describes, to ascertain whether he has a case against the prospective respondent ...'

70 An order made in an application under Order 15A rule 6 will be interlocutory, given that it will not preclude a further application (per Beaumont, Lee and Dowsett JJ in Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 284 ; (1999) 86 FCR 134 at 143).

71 Discovery against a prospective respondent is invasive. In Hughes' 'Equity Draftsman' (2 nd Edition) (1828) Vol 1 at page 483 the learned author said:
 
 'As the object of a court of equity in compelling a discovery is either to enable itself or some other court to decide on matters in dispute between the parties, the discovery sought must be material either to the relief prayed by the bill, or to some other suit actually instituted or capable of being instituted. If therefore the plaintiff in a bill for discovery does not show by his bill a title to sue the defendant in some other court, or that he is actually involved in litigation with the defendant or liable to be so, and does not also show that the discovery which he prays is material to enable him to support or defend a suit, he shows no title to the discovery, and consequently a demurrer will hold.' 
 
 (footnotes omitted)

72 To like effect Story 'Commentaries on Equity Jurisprudence, As Administered in England and America' (12 th Edition) (1877) Vol II at page 728 paragraph 1483 states:
 
 '... in general, it seems necessary, in order to maintain a bill of discovery, that an action should be already commenced in another court, to which it should be auxiliary. There are exceptions to this rule, as where the object of discovery is to ascertain who is the proper party against whom the suit should be brought. But these are of rare occurrence.' 
 
 (footnote omitted)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cardale v Watkins (1820) V Maddock 18</tocase>
<text>73 In Cardale v Watkins (1820) V Maddock 18, a case where a bill for discovery was sought but for no stated purpose, Vice Chancellor, Sir John Leach observed:
 
 'a Court of Equity does not compel Discovery for the mere gratification of curiosity, but in aid of some other Proceeding either pending or intended, and ... there must be Allegations to that effect.'

74 In Laussat's edition of 'Fonblanque on Equity' (1831) Vol 1, Chapter 1, paragraph 3 note (f) reference was made to those circumstances in which resort may be had to the 'extraordinary powers of a court of equity' to compel discovery.

75 In Story Vol 1 at paragraph 74 it is stated:
 
 '... to maintain the jurisdiction for relief, as consequent on discovery, it is necessary, in the first place, to allege in the bill, that the facts are material to the plaintiff's case, and that the discovery of them by the defendant is indispensable, as proof; for if the facts lie within the knowledge of witnesses, who may be called in a court of law, that furnishes a sufficient reason for a court of equity to refuse its aid. The bill must, therefore, allege (and if required, the fact must be established) that the plaintiff is unable to prove such facts by other testimony. ...' 
 
 (footnote omitted)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd; Transfield Pty Ltd v Airservices Australia [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1584.html</AustLII>
<text>58 In St George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 Hely J stated a series of propositions which his Honour considered had emerged from the authorities in relation to the proper application of Order 15A rule 6 at [26] as follows:
 
 
 '(a) the rule is to be beneficially construed, given the fullest scope that its language will reasonably allow, with the proper brake on any excesses lying in the discretion of the court, exercised in the particular circumstances of each case: Paxus Services Ltd v People Bank Pty Ltd (1990) 99 ALR 728 at 733; 20 IPR 79 at 85; Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 ; BC9902167 at [27]; 
 
 (b) each of the elements prescribed in subparas (a), (b) and (c) of the rule must be established: Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at 11 [38] ; 167 ALR 385 at 367; [1999] FCA 1584 ; 47 IPR 21 at 30. Preliminary discovery cannot itself be used to remedy deficiencies in the satisfaction of the conditions themselves: Airservices Australia v Transfield Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 886 ; (1999) 92 FCR 200 at 202 3 [5]; [1999] FCA 886 ; 164 ALR 330 at 332; 
 
 (c) the test for determining whether the applicant has "reasonable cause to believe", as required by subpara (a), is an objective one: Hooper at FCR 11 12 [39]; ALR 367; IPR 30; Malouf v Malouf [1999] FCA 710 ; BC9902833 at [16]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 [24]; 49 IPR 25 at 31; Alphapharm Pty Ltd v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Ltd [1996] FCA 391 ; BC9602085 at 23. Further, the words "or may have" cannot be ignored. The applicant does not have to make out a prima facie case: Quanta Software at ALR 541-2 [24]; IPR 31; Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85; 
 
 (d) belief requires more than mere assertion and more than suspicion or conjecture. Belief is an inclination of the mind towards assenting to, rather than rejecting a proposition. Thus it is not sufficient to point to a mere possibility. The evidence must incline the mind towards the matter or fact in question. If there is no reasonable cause to believe that one of the necessary elements of a potential cause of action exists, that would dispose of the application insofar as it is based on that cause of action: John Holland Services Pty Ltd v Terranora Group Management Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 679 ; BC200403021 at [13], [14], [17] and [73]; 
 
 (e) while uncertainty as to only one element of a cause of action might be compatible with the "reasonable cause to believe" required by subpara (a), uncertainty as to a number of such elements may be sufficient to undermine the reasonableness of the cause to believe: Glowatzky v Insultech Group Pty Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 215 ;
 
 (f) the question posed by subpara (b) of the rule is not whether the applicant has sufficient information to decide if a cause of action is available against the prospective respondent. The question is whether the applicant has sufficient information to make a decision whether to commence proceedings in the court: Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6. Accordingly, an applicant for preliminary discovery may be entitled to discovery in order to determine what defences are available to the respondent and the possible strength of those defences, or to determine the extent of the respondent's breach and the likely quantum of any damages award: CGU Insurance Ltd v Malaysia International Shipping Corp Berhad (2001) 187 ALR at 285 [21]; Quanta Software at ALR 543 [33]-[34]; IPR 32-3, Alphapharm at 24 6, Airservices Australia at FCR 202 3 [5]; ALR 332 
 
 (g) whether an applicant has "sufficient information" for the purposes of subpara (b) also requires an objective assessment to be made: Minister for Health at [44]; Alphapharm at 23 4, Hooper at FCR 12 [40]; ALR 367; IPR 31. The subparagraph contemplates that the applicant is lacking a piece (or pieces) of information reasonably necessary to decide whether to commence proceedings; 
 
 (h) it is no answer to an application under the rule to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a "fishing expedition": Paxus Services at ALR 733; IPR 85. Indeed O 15A r 6 "expressly contemplates" what once might have been castigated as "fishing": Bailey v Beagle Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 60 ; (2001) 105 FCR 136 at 143 [27] ; [2001] FCA 60 ; 182 ALR 264 at 270-1; 20 IPR 79 at 85. As Burchett J commented in Paxus Services , the rule is (at ALR 733; IPR 85): 
 
 
 
 
 
 ... designed to enable an applicant, in a situation where his proof can rise no higher than the level the rule describes, to ascertain whether he has a case against the prospective respondent ...'

76 In relation to the power conferred on the court by Order 15A rule 6 of the Rules Wilcox, Sackville and Katz JJ held in Hooper v Kirella Pty Ltd; Transfield Pty Ltd v Airservices Australia [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at [59] that the Court has the power to grant relief against a prospective respondent even though proceedings claiming substantive relief may never be instituted, if the applicant has asserted a claim arising under a law of the Parliament and done so in proceedings instituted, in the Court under the relevant rule (see also at [61]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Bateman's Bay Local Aboriginal Land Council v The Aboriginal Community Benefit Fund Pty Limited [1998] HCA 49 ; (1998) 194 CLR 247</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/49.html</AustLII>
<text>84 In Bateman's Bay Local Aboriginal Land Council v The Aboriginal Community Benefit Fund Pty Limited [1998] HCA 49 ; (1998) 194 CLR 247 ('Bateman's Bay') the first respondent, the Aboriginal Community Benefit Fund Pty Ltd, operated a contributory funeral benefit fund business catering for members of the New South Wales aboriginal community. The second respondent, the Aboriginal Community Benefit Fund No 2 Pty Ltd, operated a contributory life insurance business for members of the same community.
 
The first appellant, the Bateman's Bay Local Aboriginal Land Council, was a body corporate constituted under s 6 of the Aboriginal Land Rights Act 1983 (NSW). Its functions were set out in s 12(1) of that Act. The second appellant, the New South Wales Aboriginal Land Council, was a body corporate constituted under s 22 of the same Act. Its functions were set out in s 23(1) of that Act. There was no power permitting the second appellant to expend monies by providing a subsidy, guarantee or indemnity. 
 
By a deed of trust between the first appellant as trustee, the second appellant as guarantor and the State of New South Wales, the New South Wales Aboriginal Land Council's Funeral Contribution Fund was established. The second appellant provided an indemnity to the first appellant in respect of any liability the first appellant might suffer in connection with the New South Wales Aboriginal Land Council's Funeral Contribution Fund.

85 The respondents instituted proceedings in the Supreme Court of New South Wales seeking an order restraining the appellants from carrying on the New South Wales Aboriginal Land Council's Funeral Contribution Fund. At first instance, McLelland CJ in Eq held that the respondents lacked standing to maintain the proceedings. That decision was reversed on appeal to the New South Wales Court of Appeal. The matter was remitted to McLelland CJ in Eq for hearing. His Honour proceeded to make declarations and grant injunctions in the respondents favour. The appellants proceeded to appeal against the decision of the Court of Appeal in respect of standing. Special leave to appeal was granted on the condition that the appellants withdrew their appeal against McLelland CJ in Eq's decision on the merits. The High Court dismissed the appeal in respect of standing, with costs.

86 It held that the public interest in equity may be vindicated at the suit of a party with a sufficient material interest in the subject matter.

87 At [51]-[52], Gaudron, Gummow and Kirby JJ stated their conclusions as follows:
 
 '51 ... the use of equitable remedies to ensure compliance by the executive and legislative branches of government with the requirements of the Constitution should not be overlooked. No doubt special considerations may apply in that context, but it would be an odd result if the requirements for standing outside the constitutional sphere were more stringent than within it. Prejudice to a sufficient material interest, such as that in the practice of a profession or occupation, will suffice in constitutional cases. 
 
 52 Here, the respondents had an interest in the observance by the appellants of the statutory limitations upon their activities with respect to contributory funeral funds which, as a matter of practical reality, was immediate, significant and peculiar to them. The primary judge found that because the parties would be operating in substantially the same limited market it was highly probable that, if not restrained from commencing and concluding their activities, the appellants would cause severe detriment to the business of the respondents. That, in the circumstances of this litigation, gave the respondents a sufficient special interest to seek equitable relief.' 
 
 (footnotes omitted)

88 McHugh J also concluded that the appeal should be dismissed. In his reasons he said at [83], [86] and [103]:
 
 '83 The enforcement of the public law of a community is part of the political process; it is one of the chief responsibilities of the executive government. In most cases, it is for the executive government and not for the civil courts acting at the behest of disinterested private individuals to enforce the law. There are sometimes very good reasons why the public interest of a society is best served by not attempting to enforce a particular law. To enforce a law at a particular time or in particular circumstances may result in the undermining of the authority of the executive government or the courts of justice. In extreme cases, to enforce it may lead to civil unrest and bloodshed. 
 ... 
 
 86 The decision when and in what circumstances to enforce public law frequently calls for a fine judgment as to what the public interest truly requires. It is a decision that is arguably best made by the Attorney-General who must answer to the people, rather than by unelected judges expanding the doctrine of standing to overcome what they see as a failure of the political process to ensure that the law is enforced. ... 
 ... 


 
 103 As Australian Conservation Foundation and Onus show, a special interest in the subject matter of the proceedings is sufficient to give standing in a case such as the present. The subject matter of this suit is the legality of the Councils' arrangements setting up the State Fund. The respondents had a special interest in that subject. The allegedly unlawful activities of the appellant affected them financially and to an extent that exceeded the injury to any other individual. Moreover, if the arrangement between the appellants was illegal, the continuing financial injury to the respondents, caused by the arrangement, would be remedied by a grant of the injunction they sought.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>89 Given the separation of powers between the Legislature, the Executive and the Judiciary for which the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Australia ('the Constitution ') provides, the opportunity for judicial review of administrative action is not unlimited (see per McHugh and Gummow JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 ('Lam') at [76]-[77]).

90 Under s 64 of the Constitution the Governor-General was empowered to appoint 'officers to administer such departments of State of the Commonwealth as the Governor-General in Council may establish'. Such officers were to 'be members of the Federal Executive Council' and to 'be the Queen's Ministers of State for the Commonwealth'. 
 
The Minister is such an officer.

91 Under s 71 of the Constitution , the judicial power of the Commonwealth was vested in the High Court of Australia and, relevantly, 'in such other federal courts as the Parliament creates'.

94 The jurisdiction under s 75(v) of the Constitution does not exist for the purpose of enabling the judicial branch of government to impose upon the executive branch its ideas of good administration (per Gleeson CJ in Lam at [32]).

95 Constitutional writ relief under s 75(v) of the Constitution is discretionary. (See Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte AALA [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 ('AALA') at [5], [18]-[62], [145]-[150], [172] and [217]; see also Lam at [25] per Gleeson CJ.)

97 Lam concerned a Ministerial decision to cancel a visa held by a person with a substantial criminal history, under s 501(2) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth). At the time when the cancellation of his visa was under consideration Lam was incarcerated, having been sentenced to imprisonment for eight years for trafficking in heroin. He was notified that contact was being sought with his children's carers to assess the possible effect upon them of a cancellation of his visa. As it transpires, the relevant Minister made no attempt to contact the carers.

98 The High Court dismissed Lam's application for prohibition and certiorari in respect of the relevant Ministerial decision to cancel his visa. Lam alleged that the relevant Minister failed to accord him procedural fairness/natural justice by failing to make the foreshadowed contact with the carer of his children.

99 Not every departure from a stated intention necessarily involves unfairness, even if it defeats an expectation (per Gleeson CJ in Lam at [34]).

100 A failure to observe an expectation reasonably attributable to a party such as Telstra does not reasonably (perhaps better expressed as 'necessarily') found a case of denial of natural justice. The notion of legitimate expectation serves only to focus attention on the content of the requirement of natural justice in the particular case. The ends sought to be attained by the requirement of natural justice may be variously identified. The concern is with the fairness of the procedure adopted rather than the fairness of the outcome. It is with the decision-making process, not the decision. (Per McHugh and Gummow JJ in Lam at [105]).

101 On no view can the doctrine of 'legitimate expectation' give rise to substantive rights rather than to procedural rights (per Callinan J in Lam at [148]; see also per Gleeson CJ at [28]).

102 The content of the requirement for procedural fairness may fluctuate during the course of particular administrative decision-making (per Gaudron and Gummow JJ in AALA at [62]; see also per McHugh and Gummow JJ in Lam at [48]).

103 Fairness is not an abstract concept. It is essentially practical. Whether one talks in terms of procedural fairness or natural justice, the concern of the law is to avoid practical injustice (per Gleeson CJ in Lam at [37]).

104 If, in making a decision, a decision-maker is obliged to act with procedural fairness, the decision-maker must give a sufficient opportunity to those directly affected by the decision to present material and argument before the decision is made (per Hayne J in Lam at [114]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>MBA Land Holdings Pty Ltd v Gungahlin Development Authority (2000) 206 FLR 120</tocase>
<text>105 In MBA Land Holdings Pty Ltd v Gungahlin Development Authority (2000) 206 FLR 120 ('Gungahlin') Higgins J, as his Honour then was, sitting in the Supreme Court of the Australian Capital Territory, found that the respondent had failed to accord tenderers procedural fairness in respect of the grant of a lease of certain land within the Territory. Tenders had been submitted by a number of tenderers but it was not apparent whether the bids that were submitted were inclusive or exclusive of goods and services tax ('GST'). After the closing date for tenders, the respondent asked the tenderers to clarify the GST aspects of their respective bids. The successful tenderer, Landco Pty Ltd, had offered $5,700,000. Following the request for clarification in relation to the GST position, Landco Pty Ltd advised that its price 'exclusive of GST' was $6,080,000. Plainly this bid involved an increase in the tender price of $380,000 independently of any GST. In the circumstances, Higgins J found that acceptance of Landco Pty Ltd's revised tender rendered the 'assessment process lacking in procedural fairness' (at [182]).

106 The present case is not such a case. In this case the only evidence of the submission of a different application for funding of up to $600 million, after the closing date for applications, related to Telstra's own application. It will be recalled that Telstra substituted a different proposal for the provision of infrastructure, following its decision to proceed with 'OF installation to Marble Bar' at its own expense for operational reasons.

107 Apart from other considerations, the Court in Gungahlin found that the obligation to accord procedural fairness to tenderers arose by virtue of an implied agreement with the respondent pursuant to the Conditions of Tender independently of the respondent's public law obligations to like effect. Given paragraph 6.1 of the guidelines, no such finding could be made in this case.

108 Telstra submits that 'the policies of the Commonwealth' in respect of the proposed grant must be found within the guidelines.
 
It will be recalled that Part 3 of the guidelines stated that the 'Australian Government's objective' was to improve access to broadband services in regional Australia to the maximum extent possible.
 
It would seem to me that the importance of the guidelines cannot be denied in discerning the relevant policies. However, regard must also be had to the relevant Ministerial Media Releases, notably the joint Media Release of the Minister and the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Trade of 21 September 2006 referred to at [1] above. That Media Release revealed that the guidelines had been 'finalised after an Expressions of Interest process earlier this year'.

109 The relevant ' BROADBAND CONNECT REQUEST FOR EXPRESSION OF INTEREST ' of June 2006 included the following:
 
 ' A. OVERVIEW: THE BROADBAND CONNECT OPPORTUNITY 
 
 Since 1997 the Australian Government has demonstrated an ongoing commitment to improving the quality of communications services in regional areas, particularly where the competitive market has not proved fully effective in bringing the benefits of the digital revolution to regional communities. ... 
 
 ... 
 
 The Australian Government remains committed to continuing to provide targeted funding to support equitable access to high quality, sustainable broadband services across regional and rural Australia. It is becoming increasingly apparent that next generation broadband, characterised by multi-megabit capacity able to support advanced multimedia applications and improved delivery of government services, is becoming essential to Australia's economic and social prosperity. While such services are increasingly available in the major metropolitan areas, there is concern that the purely commercial roll-out of these services may not occur in regional and rural areas in a timely way. 
 
 .... The Australian Government intends to test the feasibility of using a substantial portion of the Broadband Connect funding to facilitate a small number of major infrastructure projects that would also leverage significant commercial investment in order to drive a major advancement in the capacity and reach of Australia's regional broadband networks. 
 
 ... 
 
 ... there are a significant number of areas (and premises) that do not have access to broadband infrastructure that allows for the provision of services comparable in price and quality to metropolitan services ('metro-comparable') in a sustainable way (that is, without the need for ongoing Australian Government subsidies). These areas are considered to be under-served ... 
 
 ... 
 
 It is currently anticipated that up to $500 million could be available for an alternative Broadband Connect approach whereby financial assistance is provided through a competitive grants process to large scale broadband infrastructure projects primarily aimed at addressing currently under-served premises and areas. ... 
 
 Under this approach Australian Government funding support would not be available for investments that were otherwise commercially viable. Funding support would be targeted at supporting the provision of infrastructure to service under-served areas that otherwise would not get timely access to metro-comparable services through commercial investment alone. 
 
 ... 
 
 E. GOVERNMENT OBJECTIVES 
 
 The Australian Government's primary objective for any future competitive grants program would be to achieve sustainable equitable access to broadband in regional areas by supporting the extension of metro-comparable broadband services into currently under-served areas ... on a basis that would provide access to such services without the need for ongoing Australian Government subsidies. 
 ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte AALA [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/57.html</AustLII>
<text>95 Constitutional writ relief under s 75(v) of the Constitution is discretionary. (See Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte AALA [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 ('AALA') at [5], [18]-[62], [145]-[150], [172] and [217]; see also Lam at [25] per Gleeson CJ.)

96 In AALA Gaudron and Gummow JJ said at [55]:
 
 '55 No doubt the discretion with respect to all remedies in s 75(v) is not to be exercised lightly against the grant of a final remedy, particularly where the officers of the Commonwealth in question do not constitute a federal court and there is no avenue of appeal to this Court under s 73 of the Constitution . The discretion is to be exercised against the background of the animating principle described by Gaudron J in Enfield City Corporation v Development Assessment Commission . Her Honour said: 
 
 
 
 "Those exercising executive and administrative powers are as much subject to the law as those who are or may be affected by the exercise of those powers. It follows that, within the limits of their jurisdiction and consistent with their obligation to act judicially, the courts should provide whatever remedies are available and appropriate to ensure that those possessed of executive and administrative powers exercise them only in accordance with the laws which govern their exercise. The rule of law requires no less." (Footnote omitted.)' 
 
 
 
 (footnotes omitted)

102 The content of the requirement for procedural fairness may fluctuate during the course of particular administrative decision-making (per Gaudron and Gummow JJ in AALA at [62]; see also per McHugh and Gummow JJ in Lam at [48]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Allied Pastoral Holdings Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1983) 1 NSWLR 1</tocase>
<text>119 A company, of course, is an abstraction. It has no mind of its own, and its state of mind must consequently be found in the person or persons who is or are really the directing mind and will of the company, 'the very ego and centre of the personality of the corporation' (see per Hunt J, as his Honour then was, in Allied Pastoral Holdings Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1983) 1 NSWLR 1 at 5).

120 It is clear that Mr Smith's standing in the Telstra hierarchy was well down the ladder. No evidence was called as to the information available to Telstra, within the meaning of Order 15A rule 6(b), from Mr Smith's superiors, Messrs Goldsworthy and Booth, from the head of the Project Team within Telstra in relation to the Infrastructure Programme, Mr Don Pinel, or from the senior executive within Telstra whose judgment on any application for funding, to be submitted by Telstra, was critical, namely its Chief Executive Officer, Mr Sol Trujillo. What is more, no evidence was tendered as to the discussions, if any, at board level concerning the information available to Telstra and any consideration by the board of the question as to whether or not to commence a proceeding against the Minister in the Court.

121 In my opinion, there is insufficient evidence to enable the Court to conclude that after making all reasonable enquiries, Telstra does not have sufficient information to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding in the Court against the Minister to obtain the foreshadowed relief.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>