<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Elderslie Finance Corporation Limited v Newpage Pty Ltd (No 6) [2007] FCA 1030 (8 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1030.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dean-Willcocks v ATTT Investments Pty Ltd (1999) 17 ACLC 1310</tocase>
<text>37 In Dean-Willcocks v ATTT Investments Pty Ltd (1999) 17 ACLC 1310, an application was made under s 477(2A) for the Court's approval of an arrangement by which a secured creditor of the company would inject funds in exchange for a particular asset. There was no dispute about the monies owing. Young J held that the Court had no jurisdiction to grant approval under s 477(2A) because what was proposed was not a compromise of a debt, and that the proper course, if the liquidator wanted to pursue the matter, would be for him to seek directions under s 479(3). In Tietyens 31 ACSR 1, Weinberg J held that he lacked jurisdiction under s 477(2A) but gave directions under s 479(3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2003/925.html</AustLII>
<text>36 Cases in which a liquidator has applied under both s 477(2A) and s 479(3) include HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , QBE 56 ACSR 687, Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834; Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925 , and Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HIH Insurance Ltd and Related Matters [2004] NSWSC 5</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2004/5.html</AustLII>
<text>20 As Barrett J observed in HIH Insurance Ltd and Related Matters [2004] NSWSC 5 ( HIH ) at [12], it appears that in some cases a strict approach has not been taken to the jurisdictional question posed by the expression "a debt to the company". In some cases, Judges have granted approval under s 477(2A) without discussion of the jurisdictional question. It can be just as important to decide that a compromised claim is not one of a debt to the company as to decide that it is. In Spalla v St George Motor Finance Ltd (No 7) [2006] FCA 1177 , for example, a challenge was made to a compromise entered into by a liquidator on the ground that approval under s 477(2A) had not been obtained, and Kenny J had no hesitation in holding that the submission failed because it was "based on a misunderstanding as to what constitutes a 'debt' under the relevant section" (at [143]).

26 In HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 at [12] and QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687 ( QBE ) at [4]-[5], Barrett J said that where there is room for argument about whether a claim is one of a debt to the company, the court should err on the side of treating the claim as a debt rather than decline to grant approval under s 477(2A). His Honour pointed out that the opening words of s 477(1) have the effect of making the power to compromise contained in para (d) of that subsection subject to subss (2A) and (2B). It follows that if it transpired that a claim was, indeed, one of "a debt to the company" within subs (2A), a compromise of it without approval of the Court, of the committee of inspection or of a resolution of the creditors, would lie outside the power of the liquidator.

28 Be all this as it may, as Barrett J acknowledged in HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , if the claim is "unquestionably" not a debt, the correct approach is to dismiss any application under s 477(2A) as unnecessary (at [12]).

36 Cases in which a liquidator has applied under both s 477(2A) and s 479(3) include HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , QBE 56 ACSR 687, Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834; Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925 , and Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McGrath re HIH Insurance Ltd [2005] NSWSC 731</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2005/731.html</AustLII>
<text>43 Applications by liquidators for confidentiality orders in respect of compromises for which they have sought Court approval have been considered in McGrath re HIH Insurance Ltd [2005] NSWSC 731 and Re JN Taylor Holdings Ltd (in liq) [2007] SASC 193. The administration of justice, including the just and efficient winding up of a company, requires that proper compromises be facilitated rather than obstructed. Apart from the requirement of leave, Mr Hamilton would have been entitled to bargain for and reach agreement upon a confidentiality r&eacute;gime in respect of the compromise that he has reached with Mr Parsons and CBI. He and they would have been entitled, in particular, to preserve their negotiations and agreement against disclosure to Mr Yii.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nambucca Investments Pty Ltd v Snoco Ltd [1999] NSWSC 211</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/1999/211.html</AustLII>
<text>24 The meaning of the word "debt" can be affected by its context. There is a line of authority to the effect that the expression "a debt to the company" in s 477(2A) bears its familiar meaning of a sum of money that is either immediately payable, or that, by reason of an existing obligation, will become payable in the future ( debitum in praesenti , solvendum in futuro ): Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Re Tietyens Investments Pty Ltd (in liq) (Receiver and Manager appointed) (1999) 31 ACSR 1 ( Tietyens ) at [92] [94]; and see Austin R P and Ramsay I M, Ford's Principles of Corporations Law (13 th ed, LexisNexis Butterworths, 2007) at [28-260] p1412. Accordingly, claims by liquidators to recover amounts paid away by the company under voidable transactions have been held to lie outside the predecessor provision of s 477(2A), namely, s 477(2A) of the Corporations Law : Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Nambucca Investments Pty Ltd v Snoco Ltd [1999] NSWSC 211 at [2] . In Tietyens 31 ACSR 1 a claim of equitable damages based on accessorial liability for breaches of trust, the primary cause of action being a claim based on Barnes v Addy (1874) 9 Ch App 244, was similarly held not to be a claim of a debt to the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687</tocase>
<text>26 In HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 at [12] and QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687 ( QBE ) at [4]-[5], Barrett J said that where there is room for argument about whether a claim is one of a debt to the company, the court should err on the side of treating the claim as a debt rather than decline to grant approval under s 477(2A). His Honour pointed out that the opening words of s 477(1) have the effect of making the power to compromise contained in para (d) of that subsection subject to subss (2A) and (2B). It follows that if it transpired that a claim was, indeed, one of "a debt to the company" within subs (2A), a compromise of it without approval of the Court, of the committee of inspection or of a resolution of the creditors, would lie outside the power of the liquidator.

29 According to the Points of Claim, the present claim is based exclusively on the voidable transaction provisions of the Act, as those provisions apply to two specific payments made by Newpage. The facts of the present case are very different from those that were before Barrett J in HIH and QBE .

30 In HIH and QBE , the liquidator also sought and obtained a direction under s 479(3) of the Act that he was justified in entering into the compromise (in HIH the approval sought and obtained was founded on s 477(2B), as well as on s 477(2A)).

31 Section 479(3) of the Act provides:
 
 The liquidator may apply to the Court for directions in relation to any particular matter arising under the winding up.

32 When recommending the removal of the necessity of approval of the exercise of a liquidator's powers, the Harmer Report stated (at [610]) that the creditors would still have power to give directions to which a liquidator must have regard (the then s 379 of the Companies Code, and now s 479 of the Act), and that the actions of a liquidator could be reviewed by the courts (the then s 538 of the Companies Code , and now s 1321 of the Act). Section 379 of the Companies Code which the Report cited, like s 479 of the Act, also provided in subs (3) for a liquidator to apply to the Court for directions.

36 Cases in which a liquidator has applied under both s 477(2A) and s 479(3) include HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , QBE 56 ACSR 687, Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834; Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925 , and Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834</tocase>
<text>36 Cases in which a liquidator has applied under both s 477(2A) and s 479(3) include HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , QBE 56 ACSR 687, Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834; Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925 , and Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re GB Nathan and Co Pty Ltd (in liq) (1991) 24 NSWLR 674</tocase>
<text>33 It must be remembered that there is a distinction between s 477(2A) and s 479(3): where the claim is of a debt to the company of more than $20,000, the liquidator lacks power to compromise the debt in the absence of "approval", and s 479(3) does not empower the court to grant powers to a liquidator. The different role of directions under s 479(3) of providing guidance and protection to the liquidator appears from the judgments in Re GB Nathan and Co Pty Ltd (in liq) (1991) 24 NSWLR 674, 679-680; Re Spedley Securities Ltd (in liq) (1992) 9 ACSR 83 at 85 ( Spedley ); State Bank of New South Wales v Turner Corporation Ltd (1994) 14 ACSR 480 at 483.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re JN Taylor Holdings Ltd (in liq) [2007] SASC 193</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/2007/193.html</AustLII>
<text>43 Applications by liquidators for confidentiality orders in respect of compromises for which they have sought Court approval have been considered in McGrath re HIH Insurance Ltd [2005] NSWSC 731 and Re JN Taylor Holdings Ltd (in liq) [2007] SASC 193. The administration of justice, including the just and efficient winding up of a company, requires that proper compromises be facilitated rather than obstructed. Apart from the requirement of leave, Mr Hamilton would have been entitled to bargain for and reach agreement upon a confidentiality r&eacute;gime in respect of the compromise that he has reached with Mr Parsons and CBI. He and they would have been entitled, in particular, to preserve their negotiations and agreement against disclosure to Mr Yii.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Luxtrend Pty Ltd (in liq) [1997] 2 Qd R 86</tocase>
<text>21 The history of the requirement that certain compromises by liquidators be approved by the Court, by the committee of inspection or by a resolution of the creditors was referred to by Moynihan J in Re Luxtrend Pty Ltd (in liq) [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ( Luxtrend ) at 87. The position under the 1961-62 cooperative r&eacute;gime and under the 1981 cooperative "Code" scheme, as well as under the Corporations Law in its original form in 1991, made the liquidator's power of compromise generally subject to a requirement of the approval of creditors or of the court, subject to an exception in the case of a debt of not more than a certain monetary limit: see ss 236(1)(d) and 236(2)(i) of the Companies Act 1961 (NSW) (in which the monetary figure was &#8356;300), ss 377(1)(d) and 377(2)(j) of the Companies Code (in which the monetary limit was $20,000), and ss 477(1)(d) and 477(2)(j) of the Corporations Law in their original form (where, again, the monetary limit was $20,000, and compromises of debts to the company being calls and liabilities for calls also required approval regardless of the amount). That is to say, the position was structurally the converse of the present one.

22 It was s 73 of the Corporate Law Reform Act 1992 (Cth) (No 210, 1992) that amended s 477 of the Corporations Law by omitting the general requirement of approval. An exposure draft of the Bill for that Act and an Explanatory Paper were released early in 1992. The Explanatory Paper stated (at [931]) that the proposed amendments implemented a recommendation of the Harmer Report (Australian Law Reform Commission Report 45: General Insolvency Inquiry (1988)). The Harmer Report had recommended (at [608] [610]) that the powers of a liquidator generally be exercisable without the need for approval of creditors or the court, subject to exceptions in the cases of the power to compromise debts above a prescribed amount, and the power to enter into long term commitments. The expansion of the liquidator's powers to act without approval was recommended on the basis of the competence and qualifications of persons who act in the capacity of liquidator.

23 The Harmer Report's recommendations were reflected in the omission of the general requirement of approval from subs (1) and the insertion of a requirement of approval in new subss (2A) (debts to the company of more than any prescribed amount exceeding $20,000, and if none was prescribed, $20,000), and (2B) (agreements that may end or be performed beyond three months after they are entered into).

24 The meaning of the word "debt" can be affected by its context. There is a line of authority to the effect that the expression "a debt to the company" in s 477(2A) bears its familiar meaning of a sum of money that is either immediately payable, or that, by reason of an existing obligation, will become payable in the future ( debitum in praesenti , solvendum in futuro ): Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Re Tietyens Investments Pty Ltd (in liq) (Receiver and Manager appointed) (1999) 31 ACSR 1 ( Tietyens ) at [92] [94]; and see Austin R P and Ramsay I M, Ford's Principles of Corporations Law (13 th ed, LexisNexis Butterworths, 2007) at [28-260] p1412. Accordingly, claims by liquidators to recover amounts paid away by the company under voidable transactions have been held to lie outside the predecessor provision of s 477(2A), namely, s 477(2A) of the Corporations Law : Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Nambucca Investments Pty Ltd v Snoco Ltd [1999] NSWSC 211 at [2] . In Tietyens 31 ACSR 1 a claim of equitable damages based on accessorial liability for breaches of trust, the primary cause of action being a claim based on Barnes v Addy (1874) 9 Ch App 244, was similarly held not to be a claim of a debt to the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Spedley Securities Ltd (in liq) (1992) 9 ACSR 83</tocase>
<text>33 It must be remembered that there is a distinction between s 477(2A) and s 479(3): where the claim is of a debt to the company of more than $20,000, the liquidator lacks power to compromise the debt in the absence of "approval", and s 479(3) does not empower the court to grant powers to a liquidator. The different role of directions under s 479(3) of providing guidance and protection to the liquidator appears from the judgments in Re GB Nathan and Co Pty Ltd (in liq) (1991) 24 NSWLR 674, 679-680; Re Spedley Securities Ltd (in liq) (1992) 9 ACSR 83 at 85 ( Spedley ); State Bank of New South Wales v Turner Corporation Ltd (1994) 14 ACSR 480 at 483.

35 Whether under s 477(2A) or s 479(3), the Court does not enter upon the commercial merits of the compromise. Rather, its concern is with such matters as "lack of good faith, some error in law or principle, or real and substantial ground for doubting the prudence of the liquidator's conduct" ( Spedley 9 ACSR 83 at 85-6 (a s 479(3) directions case)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Tietyens Investments Pty Ltd (in liq) (Receiver and Manager appointed) (1999) 31 ACSR 1</tocase>
<text>24 The meaning of the word "debt" can be affected by its context. There is a line of authority to the effect that the expression "a debt to the company" in s 477(2A) bears its familiar meaning of a sum of money that is either immediately payable, or that, by reason of an existing obligation, will become payable in the future ( debitum in praesenti , solvendum in futuro ): Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Re Tietyens Investments Pty Ltd (in liq) (Receiver and Manager appointed) (1999) 31 ACSR 1 ( Tietyens ) at [92] [94]; and see Austin R P and Ramsay I M, Ford's Principles of Corporations Law (13 th ed, LexisNexis Butterworths, 2007) at [28-260] p1412. Accordingly, claims by liquidators to recover amounts paid away by the company under voidable transactions have been held to lie outside the predecessor provision of s 477(2A), namely, s 477(2A) of the Corporations Law : Luxtrend [1997] 2 Qd R 86 ; Nambucca Investments Pty Ltd v Snoco Ltd [1999] NSWSC 211 at [2] . In Tietyens 31 ACSR 1 a claim of equitable damages based on accessorial liability for breaches of trust, the primary cause of action being a claim based on Barnes v Addy (1874) 9 Ch App 244, was similarly held not to be a claim of a debt to the company.

37 In Dean-Willcocks v ATTT Investments Pty Ltd (1999) 17 ACLC 1310, an application was made under s 477(2A) for the Court's approval of an arrangement by which a secured creditor of the company would inject funds in exchange for a particular asset. There was no dispute about the monies owing. Young J held that the Court had no jurisdiction to grant approval under s 477(2A) because what was proposed was not a compromise of a debt, and that the proper course, if the liquidator wanted to pursue the matter, would be for him to seek directions under s 479(3). In Tietyens 31 ACSR 1, Weinberg J held that he lacked jurisdiction under s 477(2A) but gave directions under s 479(3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98</tocase>
<text>36 Cases in which a liquidator has applied under both s 477(2A) and s 479(3) include HIH [2004] NSWSC 5 , QBE 56 ACSR 687, Re Gate Gourmet Australia Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 23 ACLC 834; Foyster v Foyster Holdings Pty Ltd (in liq) [2003] NSWSC 925 , and Re United Medical Protection; Application of Lombe Ltd (as prov liq) (2003) 46 ACSR 98.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spalla v St George Motor Finance Ltd (No 7) [2006] FCA 1177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1177.html</AustLII>
<text>20 As Barrett J observed in HIH Insurance Ltd and Related Matters [2004] NSWSC 5 ( HIH ) at [12], it appears that in some cases a strict approach has not been taken to the jurisdictional question posed by the expression "a debt to the company". In some cases, Judges have granted approval under s 477(2A) without discussion of the jurisdictional question. It can be just as important to decide that a compromised claim is not one of a debt to the company as to decide that it is. In Spalla v St George Motor Finance Ltd (No 7) [2006] FCA 1177 , for example, a challenge was made to a compromise entered into by a liquidator on the ground that approval under s 477(2A) had not been obtained, and Kenny J had no hesitation in holding that the submission failed because it was "based on a misunderstanding as to what constitutes a 'debt' under the relevant section" (at [143]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>State Bank of NSW v Turner Corporation Ltd (1994) 14 ACSR 480</tocase>
<text>33 It must be remembered that there is a distinction between s 477(2A) and s 479(3): where the claim is of a debt to the company of more than $20,000, the liquidator lacks power to compromise the debt in the absence of "approval", and s 479(3) does not empower the court to grant powers to a liquidator. The different role of directions under s 479(3) of providing guidance and protection to the liquidator appears from the judgments in Re GB Nathan and Co Pty Ltd (in liq) (1991) 24 NSWLR 674, 679-680; Re Spedley Securities Ltd (in liq) (1992) 9 ACSR 83 at 85 ( Spedley ); State Bank of New South Wales v Turner Corporation Ltd (1994) 14 ACSR 480 at 483.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>