<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Australian Abalone Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1834 (26 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1834.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101</tocase>
<text>144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Commercial and General Publications Pty Ltd (No 2) (2002) ATPR |P41-905</tocase>
<text>118 It is also worth noting that the fact that a company has ceased trading and has no assets are not circumstances which ought to prevent the imposition of a penalty: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Commercial and General Publications Pty Ltd (No 2) (2002) ATPR |P41-905 at 45,441 per Heerey J. As O'Loughlin J stated in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Vales Wine Company Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR |P41-528 at 42,776: 
 
 "Even though [the penalties] may not be recovered, they will serve as a warning throughout the wine industry and elsewhere of the attitude of the Court to offences of this nature."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/144.html</AustLII>
<text>144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851</tocase>
<text>144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937</tocase>
<text>144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Vales Wine Company Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR |P41-528</tocase>
<text>118 It is also worth noting that the fact that a company has ceased trading and has no assets are not circumstances which ought to prevent the imposition of a penalty: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Commercial and General Publications Pty Ltd (No 2) (2002) ATPR |P41-905 at 45,441 per Heerey J. As O'Loughlin J stated in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Vales Wine Company Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR |P41-528 at 42,776: 
 
 "Even though [the penalties] may not be recovered, they will serve as a warning throughout the wine industry and elsewhere of the attitude of the Court to offences of this nature."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1617</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1617.html</AustLII>
<text>125 The pecuniary penalties that are sought, and agreed, are for the most part well within what I would regard as the "permissible range". Cartel conduct can take many different forms. On the one hand, it may be so grave as to warrant massive pecuniary penalties on the scale of those recently imposed by Heerey J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1617.

126 Cartel behaviour of the kind with which Heerey J was concerned can, as his Honour noted (at [306]) be extremely damaging to the prosperity of a free market economy. Often the profits to be made can be immense, and the risk of detection slight. That explains, in part, why the legislature has progressively increased the maximum penalties available in relation to this type of conduct.

127 Heerey J went on to observe (at [309]) that many countries with free market economies have enacted laws which make cartel conduct by individuals subject to criminal sanctions, including imprisonment. I note that in April 2003 the Dawson Committee recommended the introduction of criminal sanctions for serious cartel behaviour. I also note that on 2 February 2005 the Treasurer announced proposals for the criminalisation of serious cartel conduct. He stated that the maximum penalties for the new cartel offence would be a term of imprisonment of five years and a fine of $220,000 for individuals, and a fine for corporations that would be the greater of $10 million or three times the value of the benefit from the cartel. Where the value could not be determined the fine would be 10% of annual turnover.

128 Although not all cartel conduct should be viewed as warranting the imposition of criminal sanctions, including imprisonment, plainly that option should be available in relation to serious cases of such conduct. See generally B Fisse, "The Cartel Offence: Dishonesty?" (2007) 35 Australian Business Law Review 235 at 236. I interpolate that in the event such conduct is criminalised in Australia, problems may arise in formulating a cartel offence in terms that would be comprehensible to ordinary jurors. Section 45 is complex enough. The idea, which has been mooted, of simply adding the notion of "dishonesty" to what is already a daunting provision may be counterproductive. As Fisse notes, no country other than the United Kingdom (the Enterprise Act 2002 (UK)) has made dishonesty an element of a cartel offence, and perhaps for good reason.

129 It ought to be possible to define serious cartel conduct in relatively simply terms. Fisse (at 237) makes several useful suggestions as to how this might be done. Whatever else might be said, in appropriate cases imprisonment should be available as a sentencing option. Pecuniary penalties may be seen as simply part of the price of doing business.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Lowe v The Queen [1984] HCA 46 ; (1984) 154 CLR 606</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/46.html</AustLII>
<text>145 In Lowe v The Queen [1984] HCA 46 ; (1984) 154 CLR 606 Mason J, as his Honour then was, underlined the importance of the parity principle. His Honour said (at 610 611): 
 
 "Just as consistency in punishment -- a reflection of the notion of equal justice -- is a fundamental element in any rational and fair system of criminal justice, so inconsistency in punishment, because it is regarded as a badge of unfairness and unequal treatment under the law, is calculated to lead to an erosion of public confidence in the integrity of the administration of justice. It is for this reason that the avoidance and elimination of unjustifiable discrepancy in sentencing is a matter of abiding importance to the administration of justice and to the community."

146 In Postiglione v The Queen [1997] HCA 26 ; (1997) 189 CLR 295 the principle was further explained. Dawson and Gaudron JJ stated (at 301):
 
 "The parity principle upon which the argument in this Court was mainly based is an aspect of equal justice. Equal justice requires that like should be treated alike but that, if there are relevant differences, due allowance should be made for them. In the case of co-offenders, different sentences may reflect different degrees of culpability or their different circumstances. If so, the notion of equal justice is not violated. On some occasions, different sentences may indicate that one or other of them is infected with error. Ordinarily, correction of the error will result in there being a due proportion between the sentences and there will then be equal justice. However, the parity principle, as identified and expounded in Lowe v The Queen , recognises that equal justice requires that, as between co-offenders, there should not be a marked disparity which gives rise to "a justifiable sense of grievance". If there is, the sentence in issue should be reduced, notwithstanding that it is otherwise appropriate and within the permissible range of sentencing options." 
 
 (Footnotes omitted.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd (2004) ATPR |P41-993</tocase>
<text>121 The real question is whether the pecuniary penalties which are now sought, and which have been agreed by the respondents, should be approved. In answering that question it must be emphasised that, in the final analysis, it is for the Court, and not the parties, to determine the amount of any pecuniary penalty. The Court is not to be regarded as a "rubber stamp". See generally NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; and Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd (2004) ATPR |P41-993.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285</tocase>
<text>121 The real question is whether the pecuniary penalties which are now sought, and which have been agreed by the respondents, should be approved. In answering that question it must be emphasised that, in the final analysis, it is for the Court, and not the parties, to determine the amount of any pecuniary penalty. The Court is not to be regarded as a "rubber stamp". See generally NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; and Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd (2004) ATPR |P41-993.

144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Postiglione v The Queen [1997] HCA 26 ; (1997) 189 CLR 295</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/26.html</AustLII>
<text>146 In Postiglione v The Queen [1997] HCA 26 ; (1997) 189 CLR 295 the principle was further explained. Dawson and Gaudron JJ stated (at 301):
 
 "The parity principle upon which the argument in this Court was mainly based is an aspect of equal justice. Equal justice requires that like should be treated alike but that, if there are relevant differences, due allowance should be made for them. In the case of co-offenders, different sentences may reflect different degrees of culpability or their different circumstances. If so, the notion of equal justice is not violated. On some occasions, different sentences may indicate that one or other of them is infected with error. Ordinarily, correction of the error will result in there being a due proportion between the sentences and there will then be equal justice. However, the parity principle, as identified and expounded in Lowe v The Queen , recognises that equal justice requires that, as between co-offenders, there should not be a marked disparity which gives rise to "a justifiable sense of grievance". If there is, the sentence in issue should be reduced, notwithstanding that it is otherwise appropriate and within the permissible range of sentencing options." 
 
 (Footnotes omitted.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Refrigerated Express Lines (A/asia) Pty Ltd v Australian Meat and Live-Stock Corporation (1980) 29 ALR 333</tocase>
<text>5 As is well known, Pt IV of the TPA is directed at restrictive trade practices. It contains a number of provisions which proscribe and regulate agreements and conduct, and which are aimed at maintaining competition in trade and commerce: see Refrigerated Express Lines (A/asia) Pty Ltd v Australian Meat and Live-Stock Corporation (1980) 29 ALR 333 at 340 per Deane J.

6 The Competition Policy Reform Act 1995 (Vic), which introduced the Code, applies the "Schedule Version of Part IV" of the TPA to all "persons" in Victoria.

7 Section 45 of the TPA, which falls within Pt IV, deals with contracts, arrangements or understandings that restrict dealings or affect competition. Section 45(2) is in the following terms: 
 
 "A corporation shall not: 
 
 (a) make a contract or arrangement, or arrive at an understanding, if: 
 
 
 
 
 (i) the proposed contract, arrangement or understanding contains an exclusionary provision; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) a provision of the proposed contract, arrangement or understanding has the purpose, or would have or be likely to have the effect, of substantially lessening competition; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) give effect to a provision of a contract, arrangement or understanding, whether the contract or arrangement was made, or the understanding was arrived at, before or after the commencement of this section, if that provision: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) is an exclusionary provision; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (ii) has the purpose, or has or is likely to have the effect, of substantially lessening competition."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/2.html</AustLII>
<text>144 In Schneider Electric (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 2 ; (2003) 127 FCR 170 at [57] Merkel J (with whom Black CJ and Sackville J relevantly agreed) accepted that the parity principle applies to pecuniary penalties imposed under s 76 of the TPA. His Honour referred to two earlier decisions of the Full Court in support of that proposition, namely NW Frozen Foods at 295, and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ithaca Iceworks Pty Ltd (2002) ATPR |P41-851 at 44,539. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v SIP Australia Pty Limited (2003) ATPR |P41-937 at [57] [58] per Goldberg J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (No 4 ) (2006) ATPR |P42-101 at [71] [74] per Goldberg J; and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v IPM Operation and Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 144 at [11] per Tracey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thomson Australian Holdings Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/48.html</AustLII>
<text>124 The parties have jointly submitted, and I accept, that the Court is entitled to treat the respondents' consent to these orders as involving an admission of all facts necessary or appropriate to the grant of the relief sought. See Thomson Australian Holdings Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150 at 164.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR |P41-076</tocase>
<text>115 Plainly, the matters to be considered include:
 
 &#8226; the nature and extent of the contravening conduct;
 &#8226; the amount of loss or damage caused, if any;
 &#8226; the circumstances in which the conduct took place;
 &#8226; the size of the contravening company; 
 &#8226; the deliberateness of the contravention; 
 &#8226; the period over which the contravention extended; and
 &#8226; whether the respondents have shown a disposition to cooperate with the regulatory authorities. 

See generally Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR |P41-076 per French J at 52,152 52,153.

116 A pecuniary penalty is intended to achieve various goals. These include punishment, proportionate to the gravity of the contravening conduct, and deterrence, both specific and general.

117 At the same time, any penalty that is imposed should not be so high as to be oppressive. Among the factors that may be taken into account by way of mitigation are a blameless prior history, genuine contrition, and a willingness to settle any proceeding so as to avoid unnecessary expense.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 193 ; (2003) 131 FCR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/193.html</AustLII>
<text>139 In Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 193 ; (2003) 131 FCR 529 at [308] [309] the Full Court regarded the fact that legal advice had been obtained as being of little consequence and not as a discounting factor. In that case it was said merely to illustrate that the risk was appreciated.

140 I would regard the principle formulated in Universal Music as being inapplicable to this case. Here it is not so much that legal advice was obtained that is relevant. Rather it is the fact that not one of a bevy of lawyers who were involved in structuring and documenting the arrangement considered for a moment that there might be a breach of s 45. It is that which lends support to the respondents' claim, accepted by the ACCC, that they did not act dishonestly and had no idea that they were contravening that section. In no sense did they "appreciate" the risk, and choose to run it.

141 I am satisfied that all but two of the pecuniary penalties that are agreed are within the permissible range, and that they should be imposed. These penalties are appropriate because they may deter others from engaging in similar conduct. They are not insubstantial, totalling, for example, in the case of Mr North's clients $765,000.

142 The two exceptions are the penalties agreed in relation to Ronda, $65,000, and Mr Bramley, $20,000. Try as I might, and despite the fact that neither of these respondents wished to make any further submissions after discovering what penalties had been agreed between the ACCC and the other respondents, I can see no reason why penalties as severe as these should be imposed upon these two respondents.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>