<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Haneef v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1273 (21 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1273.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hamdan v Ramsfeld 126 S.Ct. 2749 (2006)</tocase>
<text>12 In recent times, challenges to certain US government actions at Guantanamo Bay have centred on appeals as to the lawfulness of the laws rather than their lawful application ( Hamdan v Ramsfeld 126 S.Ct. 2749 (2006)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Marbury v Madison 5 U.S. 137 (1803)</tocase>
<text>13 Section 75(v) appears in the Australian Constitution as a consequence of the finding by the Supreme Court in the United States in Marbury v Madison 5 U.S. 137 (1803). Sir Edmund Barton (later an original judge of the High Court) in the debates of the Australasian Federal Convention in Melbourne in 1898 ("Official Record of the Debates of the Australasian Federal Convention", Melbourne , 4 March 1898 Vol II at page 1883) referred to the terms of section 2 of Article III of the United States Constitution . After referring to Marbury v Madison , Sir Edmund said:
 
 ...although jurisdiction was given as to cases arising out of the Constitution that itself was only an appellate jurisdiction. Jurisdiction was not given in any express terms as to writs of mandamus, prohibition, or injunction. Therefore there was only an appellate jurisdiction. When the United States Congress tried to confer an original jurisdiction upon the Supreme Court of the United States, it was held that, as there was no such jurisdiction conferred by the Constitution , it could not be conferred by an Act of Congress, because such an Act was outside the Constitution . For that reason, the statute was held to be void.

14 The purpose of s 75(v) in the Australian Constitution was to ensure that, unlike the Supreme Court, the High Court had original jurisdiction in respect of writs of mandamus, prohibition or injunction.

15 Sir Edmund said, at p 1884:
 
 This will give the High Court original jurisdiction, as well as appellate jurisdiction, in these cases, so that when a person wishes to obtain the performance of a clear statutory duty, or to restrain an officer of the Commonwealth from going beyond his duty, or to restrain him in the performance of some statutory duty from doing some wrong, he can obtain a writ of mandamus, a writ of prohibition, or a writ of injunction.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Plaintiff S157/2002 v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/2.html</AustLII>
<text>20 In Plaintiff S157/2002 v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476, the High Court was concerned with provisions in the Migration Act , namely ss 474(2) and 474 (1), which, on their face, purported to render some decisions made under the Migration Act immune from judicial review.

21 Section 474(2) provided: 
 
 In this section: "privative clause decision" means a decision of an administrative character made, proposed to be made, or required to be made, as the case may be, under this Act ....

22 Section 474(1) of the Migration Act provided:
 
 A privative clause decision: 
 
 
 (a) is final and conclusive; 
 
 
 
 
 (b) must not be challenged, appealed against, reviewed, quashed or called into question in any court; and
 (c) is not subject to prohibition, mandamus, injunction, declaration or certiorari in any court on any account.

24 The centrality of the constitutional writs for the protection of the Rule of Law in Australia appears from their Honours' observations in Plaintiff S157/2002 , immediately following the significance of the Rule of Law for the Constitution noted in the quotation by Dixon J set out above. The five judges said:
 
 [104] The reservation to this court by the Constitution of the jurisdiction in all matters in which the named constitutional writs or an injunction are sought against an officer of the Commonwealth is a means of assuring to all people affected that officers of the Commonwealth obey the law and neither exceed nor neglect any jurisdiction which the law confers on them. The centrality, and protective purpose, of the jurisdiction of this court in that regard places significant barriers in the way of legislative attempts (by privative clauses or otherwise) to impair judicial review of administrative action. Such jurisdiction exists to maintain the federal compact by ensuring that propounded laws are constitutionally valid and ministerial or other official action lawful and within jurisdiction. In any written constitution, where there are disputes over such matters, there must be an authoritative decision-maker. Under the Constitution of the Commonwealth the ultimate decision-maker in all matters where there is a contest, is this court. The court must be obedient to its constitutional function. In the end, pursuant to s 75 of the Constitution , this limits the powers of the parliament or of the executive to avoid, or confine, judicial review.

25 The primary question in the present proceedings is whether, as the applicant claims, the Minister committed jurisdictional error in his exercise of the powers that s 501 of the Migration Act confers on him in relation to the cancellation of the applicant's visa.

27 Chief Justice Gleeson in Plaintiff S157/2002 said at [5]:
 
 Section 75(v) of the Constitution confers upon this court, as part of its original jurisdiction, jurisdiction in all matters in which a writ of mandamus, or prohibition, or an injunction, is sought against an officer of the Commonwealth. It secures a basic element of the rule of law. The jurisdiction of the court to require officers of the Commonwealth to act within the law cannot be taken away by parliament. Within the limits of its legislative capacity, which are themselves set by the Constitution , parliament may enact the law to which officers of the Commonwealth must conform. If the law imposes a duty, mandamus may issue to compel performance of that duty. If the law confers power or jurisdiction, prohibition may issue to prevent excess of power or jurisdiction. An injunction may issue to restrain unlawful behaviour. Parliament may create, and define, the duty, or the power, or the jurisdiction, and determine the content of the law to be obeyed. But it cannot deprive this court of its constitutional jurisdiction to enforce the law so enacted.

28 Parliament has in s 501 of the Migration Act created and defined the requirements that have to be met before the power given to the Minister to cancel a person's visa can be exercised.

29 Callinan J in Plaintiff S157/2002 commenced his reasons for judgment with the following:
 
 Constitutional law in a federal system has been described as "a unique mixture of history, statutory interpretation, and some political philosophy".[Menzies, Afternoon Light , 1967, p 320.] In resolving this case, resort to each of these is necessary: history for an understanding of the law in relation to prerogative writs at the time of Federation and the considerations which moved the founders to use the language that they did in s 51(xxix) and (xxxvii), and Ch III of the Constitution ; statutory interpretation to construe both the provisions of the enactment under challenge, and the Constitution which is both the source of the power to enact them, and the instrument which prescribes the powers conferred on this court to examine and pronounce upon their validity; and, political philosophy for an understanding of the need for each of the arms of government, the parliament, the executive and the judiciary to pay due deference to, and not to intrude upon the roles of one another, in the good, that is to say the lawful and efficient government of the nation.

30 As Callinan J's observation emphasises, in the proper administration of the lawful and efficient government of the nation, each of the arms of government - the parliament, the executive, and the judiciary - has a role to play, and each of the arms of government must pay due deference to, and not to intrude upon, the roles of the other arms of government.

31 The preceding observations demonstrate that there is no room for the view, sometimes uttered, that the executive should have exclusive responsibility over all matters involving national security.

32 True it is that the executive is charged with a heavy responsibility in matters of national security, but parliament has defined the limits defining the discharge by the executive of that responsibility, and it is for the judicial arm of government "to ensure that ministerial or other official action (is) lawful and within jurisdiction," as the plurality judgment at [104] of Plaintiff S157 , set out at [23], makes plain.

33 As David Jackson said in the article on the growth of constitutional writs earlier referred to (at 29):
 
 ... Section 75(v) reflects a distinct constitutional value, namely that there will always be a court which has jurisdiction to determine the legality of the performance by officers of the Commonwealth, judicial or non-judicial, of their functions, or the legality of their failure to perform them.
 
 It is a value which I think does assist in maintaining the rule of law in this country ...

34 The Right Honourable Lord Bingham of Cornhill, the former Lord Chief Justice of England and Wales, speaking extra-judicially on "The Rule of Law" ((2004) 15(3) Commonwealth Lawyer 22) referred to the Constitutional Reform Act 2005 (UK), which radically reconfigures the legal system in the United Kingdom.

132 The Full Court noted that the joint judgment of Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ in Plaintiff S157 held, at [76], that an administrative decision which involves jurisdictional error is "regarded in law as no decision at all".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re Patterson; Ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 182 ALR 657</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/51.html</AustLII>
<text>26 Gaudron J said in Re Patterson; Ex parte Taylor [2001] HCA 51 ; (2001) 182 ALR 657 at [82] - [83] :
 
 A decision-maker falls into jurisdictional error if he or she misunderstands the nature of the jurisdiction to be exercised, misconceives his or her duty, fails to apply himself or herself to the question to be decided or misunderstands the nature of the opinion which he or she is to form. 
 ...
 ... the parliamentary secretary misunderstood the nature of the jurisdiction she was exercising by failing to appreciate that there would, in effect, be no opportunity for Mr Taylor to seek revocation of her decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sunday Times v United Kingdom (1979) 2 EHRR 245</tocase>
<text>42 The European Court of Human Rights said in Sunday Times v United Kingdom (1979) 2 EHRR 245 at 271, [49]:
 
 The law must be adequately accessible: the citizen must be able to have an indication that is adequate in the circumstances of the legal rules applicable to a given case ... a norm cannot be regarded as a 'law' unless it is formulated with sufficient precision to enable the citizen to regulate his conduct: he must be able if need be with appropriate advice to foresee, to a degree that is reasonable in the circumstances, the consequences which a given action may entail.

43 The third sub-rule advanced by Lord Bingham at 25 was that:
 
 ... the laws of the land should apply equally to all, save to the extent that objective differences justify differentiation. ... While some special legislative provision can properly be made for some categories of people such as children, prisoners and the mentally ill, based on the peculiar characteristics of such categories, we would regard legislation directed to those with red hair (to adapt Warrington LJ's long-lived example) as incompatible with the rule of law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Short v Poole Corporation [1926] Ch 66</tocase>
<text>44 Warrington LJ said in Short v Poole Corporation [1926] Ch 66 at 91:
 
 It may be also possible to prove that an act of the public body, though performed in good faith and without the taint of corruption, was so clearly founded on alien and irrelevant grounds as to be outside the authority conferred upon the body, and therefore inoperative. It is difficult to suggest any act which would be held ultra vires under this head, though performed bona fide. To look for one example germane to the present case, I suppose that if the defendants were to dismiss a teacher because she had red hair, or for some equally frivolous and foolish reason, the Court would declare the attempted dismissal to be void.
 
 My view then is that the only case in which the Court can interfere with an act of a public body which is, on the face of it, regular and within its powers, is when it is proved to be in fact ultra vires, and that the references in the judgments in the several cases cited in argument to bad faith, corruption, alien and irrelevant motives, collateral and indirect objects, and so forth, are merely intended when properly understood as examples of matters which if proved to exist might establish the ultra vires character of the act in question.

238 Further, if the discretion to cancel a visa holder's visa were to be enlivened on the basis of a perfectly innocent association with a person who had engaged in criminal activity, the position is not much different from the exercise of a power conditioned on the circumstance that a person had red hair, in the celebrated example of Warrington LJ in Short v Poole Corporation [1926] Ch 66.

239 It is no answer to this criticism of the Chan test that the Minister's power, if conditioned on such a premise, could be expected to be exercised only in those circumstances where the Minister thought it appropriate to exercise the power. The exercise of a power conditioned on such an consideration would be an exercise of power alien to the object of the purposes of the Migration Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>R v Zaphir [1978] Qd R 151</tocase>
<text>50 In R v Zaphir [1978] Qd. R 151, Zaphir had been charged with an offence under s 359 of the Criminal Code (Qld) which relevantly provided:
 
 Any person who threatens ... cause any detriment ... to another with intent to compel him to do any act which he is lawfully entitled to abstain from doing, is guilty of a misdemeanour ...

51 On the appeal to the Court of Criminal Appeal, it was argued that the "detriment" in the section had necessarily to involve a criminal or unlawful connotation.

52 Wanstall CJ with whom Matthews J agreed said at 164:
 
 It is sufficient for present purposes to treat s. 359 of the Code as at least bringing within its scope the uttering of a threat to cause a detriment to another by inducing a violation of his legal right, contractual or otherwise. Whether or not it extends to threats to cause a detriment to another by bringing about a consequence which is not in violation of the other's legal right should be left for decision in an appropriate case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Railway Express Agency Inc v New York 336 US 106 (1949)</tocase>
<text>55 Concerning the requirement that the law be of general application, and equal in operation, Lord Bingham quotes the observation of Justice Jackson in the Supreme Court of the United States in Railway Express Agency Inc v New York 336 US 106, 112-113 (1949):
 
 The framers of the Constitution knew, and we should not forget today, that there is no more effective practical guaranty against arbitrary and unreasonable government than to require that the principles of law which officials would impose upon a minority must be imposed generally. Conversely, nothing opens the door to arbitrary action so effectively as to allow those officials to pick and choose only a few to whom they will apply legislation and thus to escape the political retribution that might be visited upon them if larger numbers were affected. Courts can take no better measure to assure that laws will be just than to require that laws be equal in operation.

56 These comments, in my opinion, bear on how the "association test" in s 501(6)(b) of the Migration Act is properly to be construed. Did Parliament intend that the definition of "not passing the character test" should apply to persons whose "association" with persons who are criminals does not bear adversely on their character, as well as to those whose "association" with such persons does bear adversely on their character?

57 Lord Bingham said at 27:
 
 My sixth sub-rule expresses what many would, with reason, regard as the core of the rule of law principle. It is that ministers and public officers at all levels must exercise the powers conferred on them reasonably, in good faith, for the purpose for which the powers were conferred and without exceeding the limits of such powers. This sub-rule reflects the well-established and familiar grounds of judicial review. [See Jeffrey Jowell, "The Rule of Law Today" in Jeffrey Jowell and Dawn Oliver (eds), The Changing Constitution , 5 th ed, (Oxford, 2004), pp 20-21]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Church of Scientology v Woodward [1980] HCA 38 ; (1982) 154 CLR 25</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/38.html</AustLII>
<text>62 As to the deference that Courts ought properly give to decisions of the executive in matters of national security, observations by the High Court in Church of Scientology v Woodward [1980] HCA 38 ; (1982) 154 CLR 25 are relevant.

63 Mason J, as his Honour then was, said, at 55:
 
 It would be too much to say that the supervisory jurisdiction of the courts cannot be impliedly excluded by statute, though no case of implied exclusion was cited to us in argument. But it is not too much to say that any suggestion that Parliament has impliedly excluded judicial review, especially for ultra vires, should be viewed with extreme caution, indeed with healthy scepticism.

64 At 59, Mason J said:
 
 Surveillance in association with the obtaining, storage and dissemination by a government organization of information relating to private citizens can only be justified in a democratic society by the need to protect that society, i.e., on security grounds.
 ...
 No-one could doubt that the revelation of security intelligence in legal proceedings would be detrimental to national security. But it does not follow that ASIO's activities should be completely free from judicial review. To so conclude would be to ignore the protection which is given by the doctrine of Crown privilege to information the disclosure of which is prejudicial to national security. 
 
 It is one thing to say that security intelligence is not readily susceptible of judicial evaluation and assessment. It is another thing to say that the courts cannot determine whether intelligence is "relevant to security" and whether a communication of intelligence is "for purposes relevant to security".

65 Brennan J, as his Honour then was, said, at 70:
 
 Judicial review is neither more nor less than the enforcement of the rule of law over executive action; it is the means by which executive action is prevented from exceeding the powers and functions assigned to the executive by law and the interests of the individual are protected accordingly.

66 At 74, Brennan J asked:
 
 ... how can the gravity of a security risk be evaluated by a court? It may be necessary to evaluate Australia's relationships with foreign countries, the stability of international affairs, the passion inspired by a particular cause or the likelihood of adherents to the cause taking violent steps in support of it; it may be necessary to evaluate rumour or suspicion as well as proof. It may be reasonable, even necessary, to determine the gravity of a risk by intuition rather than deduction. It may be truly said that the skills and procedures of a court do not fit it to find the point on the scale of gravity of every risk which may be thought to pose a threat to the Commonwealth, the States and Territories and the people thereof, and it may be accepted that a court will not necessarily have or be able to obtain all the evidence needed to allow it to quantify a risk precisely. However, it does not follow that judicial review is excluded.

67 As to the intersection of matters of national security with the administration of civil justice, Brennan J said at 76:
 
 The secrecy of the work of an intelligence organization which is to counter espionage, sabotage, etc. is essential to national security, and the public interest in national security will seldom yield to the public interest in the administration of civil justice. ...

68 It is right to acknowledge the political character of the Minister's office, and his accountability to the Parliament, and of the government ultimately to the electorate. The Minister is nonetheless susceptible to the requirements of the law that he act within the jurisdiction conferred by the Parliament on him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/17.html</AustLII>
<text>314 Whether such an inference can be drawn in the circumstances where a Minister of the Crown has not given evidence was the subject of separate observations by Kirby J and Callinan J in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507.

315 Before that decision, there was commentary in the textbooks and in the authorities supporting the view that the rule did, in fact, apply to Ministers.

319 In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia , Kirby J and Callinan J, in separate opinions, observed that the rule in Jones v Dunkel may not apply in the same way to Ministers as it does to others.

320 Kirby J said at [143]:
 
 Similarly, I would not attach a great deal of significance to (or draw adverse inferences in these cases from) the failure of the Minister to give oral evidence or to submit himself to cross-examination. Although Ministers, whilst holding office, are not immune in this country from giving evidence before courts, a court would not ordinarily hasten to draw an inference that the Minister had deliberately refrained from giving oral evidence because of a concern that the impugned decision would be revealed as affected by bias or that the Minister would be forced to make concessions damaging to the Minister's case. Ministers have to perform highly complex and onerous functions. They carry heavy burdens that severely limit the time available for them to give evidence in individual cases. In Mr Jia's case, the Minister might have considered it sufficient to rely on the record as, in the opinion of the majority of this Court, it is held to be. Applying the test of whether the parties, or the public, might entertain a reasonable apprehension that the Minister might have been biased, I do not believe that the principle expressed in Jones v Dunkel , that an adverse inference may sometimes be drawn from a failure to give evidence, should loom large in evaluating appearances in the applications brought to this Court by Mr Jia and Mr White.

321 Similarly, Callinan J stated at [284]:
 
 Adverse inferences may not be so readily drawn against a Minister in this type of litigation as might be drawn against a party who avoids the witness box in other proceedings.

323 More recently, in Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [72] , Sackville J referred to the High Court's observations in Jia but found it unnecessary to decide whether it applied to the circumstances of the case before him which did not involve purported bias by the Minister as was the case in Jia , but rather, failure to have regard to certain information. Sackville J had concluded, at [71], that assuming the rule applied, it would not assist the applicant.

325 However, in most, if not all, cases, because of the factors expressed by Pincus J, and also Kirby J and Callinan J in the passages set out above, the absence of a Minister giving evidence in the for the witness box will be easily understood.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Craig v State of South Australia (1995) CLR 163</tocase>
<text>126 As to what constitutes jurisdictional error, the High Court in Craig v State of South Australia (1995) CLR 163 said at 179:
 
 If such an administrative tribunal falls into an error of law which causes it to identify a wrong issue, to ask itself a wrong question, to ignore relevant material, to rely on irrelevant material or, at least in some circumstances, to make an erroneous finding or to reach a mistaken conclusion, and the tribunal's exercise or purported exercise of power is thereby affected, it exceeds its authority or powers. Such an error of law is jurisdictional error which will invalidate any order or decision of the tribunal which reflects it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>MIMA v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>127 This passage was referred to by McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ in MIMA v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323. Their Honours continued at [82]:
 
 "Jurisdictional error" can thus be seen to embrace a number of different kinds of error, the list of which, in the passage cited from Craig, is not exhaustive. Those different kinds of error may well overlap. The circumstances of a particular case may permit more than one characterisation of the error identified, for example, as the decision-maker both asking the wrong question and ignoring relevant material. What is important, however, is that identifying a wrong issue, asking a wrong question, ignoring relevant material or relying on irrelevant material in a way that affects the exercise of power is to make an error of law. Further, doing so results in the decision-maker exceeding the authority or powers given by the relevant statute. In other words, if an error of those types is made, the decision-maker did not have authority to make the decision that was made; he or she did not have jurisdiction to make it. Nothing in the Act suggests that the tribunal is given authority to authoritatively determine questions of law or to make a decision otherwise than in accordance with the law.

128 The central question in this case is whether the Minister misconstrued the terms of s 501(6)(b):
 
 A person does not pass the character test if:
 ... 
 
 
 (b) the person has or has had an association with someone else, or with a group or organisation, whom the Minister reasonably suspects has been or is involved in criminal conduct;</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Lobo v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 168 ; (2003) 200 ALR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/168.html</AustLII>
<text>129 The judgment of the Full Court of the Federal Court (French, Sackville and Hely JJ) in Lobo v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 168 ; (2003) 200 ALR 359 ( Lobo) is directly relevant to the present question.

130 In Lobo , the delegate of the Minister was concerned with the grant of a subclass 845 visa. Clause 845.216 of the Second Schedule of the Migration Regulations prescribed a criterion in which the Minister must be satisfied before he could grant such a visa. His satisfaction that the criterion had been satisfied was a necessary condition of his power to grant the visa. If he was satisfied that the criterion had been satisfied, and that the other conditions set out in s 65(1)(a) of the Migration Act were met, then he had a statutory duty to grant the visa.

131 The Full Court said at [43]:
 
 Where the minister misconstrues one of the criteria prescribed in the Act or regulations and, because of that misconstruction he considers that the criterion has not been satisfied, it is as though he did not consider the criterion at all. For, on the face of it, he has failed to ask the question which the Act and regulations, upon a proper construction of the criterion, require him to ask. In such a case, absent s 474, the minister's decision would be a nullity. The minister has not done that which the Act requires him to have done. The decision would be a purported decision of no legal effect.

133 On the appeal to the Full Court in Lobo , it was not disputed that the departmental policy to which the Tribunal adverted was narrower than the criterion for a subclause 845 visa set out in cl 845.216 of the Second Schedule to the regulations. In the light of that concession, the Full Court concluded that failure to satisfy the criteria set out in the departmental policy did not equate to failure to satisfy the criterion in cl 845.216. In consequence, the Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error.

134 The Full Court said at [65]:
 
 It is apparent from the reasons of the tribunal ... that the tribunal treated assessment according to the departmental policy as assessment for the purposes of cl 845.216. In so doing it erred and its error was jurisdictional. It did not address the question which s 65(1) of the Act required it to address.

135 An application for special leave was refused by the High Court (Gummow and Hayne JJ) [2004] HCATrans 21) on 13 February 2004, their Honours stating that the decision in Lobo by the Full Court of the Federal Court was "not attended by doubt".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MIMIA v SGLB [2004] HCA 32 ; (2004) 207 ALR 12</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/32.html</AustLII>
<text>136 In MIMIA v SGLB [2004] HCA 32 ; (2004) 207 ALR 12, Gummow and Hayne JJ (with whom Gleeson CJ agreed) indicated at [49] that the nature of the alleged error in Plaintiff 157 was the denial to the plaintiff of jurisdictional fairness.

137 Their Honours in [50] and [51] turned to other cases where the nature of the alleged error turned on the meaning of the legislative criterion of jurisdiction. Their Honours said:
 
 [50] In other cases, the nature of the alleged error will turn upon the meaning of the legislative criterion of jurisdiction, making the construction of the legislation the primary and essential task. Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Applicants S134/2002 was such a case. The court divided on the question whether, on the proper construction of the relevant regulations under the Act, as picked up by s 65(1), the tribunal had been obliged to determine to its satisfaction whether applicants were entitled to protection visas by reason of membership of the family unit of a person who had already been granted a protection visa. The majority answered "no"; Gaudron and Kirby JJ were of the other view.
 
 [51] However, in the light of the detailed specification of the criteria for the grant of the various classes of visa, including protection visas, it is impossible to treat the consideration by the minister's delegate (and hence the tribunal) of what are the relevant criteria (the issue in Applicants S134 ), and the satisfaction thereof, as other than conditions precedent to the making of a valid decision to grant or refuse to grant a visa under s 65. Further, certain observations by Gaudron and Kirby JJ in Applicants S134 (not on an issue upon which the division in the court turned) are, with respect, compelling. Their Honours said: 
 
 
 The detailed specification of matters bearing upon the grant of a protection visa inserted into the Act at the same time as was s 474 makes it clear that the Parliament was not enacting provisions to the effect that decision-makers could validly grant or refuse to grant protection visas on the basis of a bona fide attempt to determine whether the criteria for the grant of a protection visa have been satisfied, as distinct from the decision-maker's actual satisfaction or lack of satisfaction as to those criteria. And as already pointed out, a decision-maker cannot be said to be satisfied or not satisfied if effect is not given to those criteria because, for example, they have been misconstrued or overlooked.

138 The grounds of the application to this Court by Dr Haneef are:
 
 1. The Respondent fell into jurisdictional error by deciding that the threshold requirement under s.501(3)(c) of the Migration Act had been satisfied based on upon misconstruction of the expression "association" in s.501(6)(b). 
 
 
 
 2 . The Respondent fell into jurisdictional error by failing to take into account a relevant consideration in the exercise of the discretion under s.501(3) , namely: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) the nature and extent of the alleged "association" between the Applicant and the persons whom the Respondent suspected of criminal conduct; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) the weakness or strength of the evidence supporting the charge against the Applicant; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) hardship to the Applicant as a result of the cancellation;
 ... 
 
 
 
 
 
 3. The Respondent fell into jurisdictional error by taking irrelevant considerations into account in the exercise of the discretion under s.501(3) , namely: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) that the Applicant had been granted bail by the Brisbane Magistrates Court; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) that the "Australian Government has a strong interest in deterring non-citizens from providing support to terrorist organisations/networks", when the Applicant has not been convicted of any offence involving provision of such support. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 4. The Respondent's purpose in cancelling the visa under s.501(3) was to allow the Applicant to be detained when he had been granted bail and that was an improper purpose.
 
 
 Particulars 
 
 
 
 (a) The Respondent knew that the Applicant had been granted bail on 16 July 2007; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) the Respondent expressly took into account that that Applicant had been granted bail in making his decision to cancel the Applicant's visa; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) the Respondent cancelled the visa on 16 July 2007 within several hours of the decision to grant bail being made; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (d) the Respondent had not previously notified the Applicant that he was considering the cancellation of the visa; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (e) on 16 July 2007 the Respondent also knew that the Commissioner of the Australian Federal Police intended to ask the Attorney-General to issue a criminal justice stay certificate, or believed that the Commissioner had the power to issue such a certificate himself; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (f) on 17 July 2007 the Respondent informed the media that the Applicant would remain in detention until his trial; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (g) the Respondent knew that if he cancelled the visa and a criminal justice stay certificate was issued by the Attorney-General, ss.150 and 152 of the Migration Act would operate to require that the Applicant be kept in immigration detention pending his trial; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (h) a criminal justice stay certificate will be issued which will operate to authorise the detention of the Applicant; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (i) the purpose of the Respondent is to be inferred from the matters set out above.

139 It is to be noted, particularly in the light of ground 4, that ground 3(a) was not pressed by the applicant in these proceedings.

140 It is necessary to consider each of these grounds in turn.

141 The argument for the application on this ground focuses on the four paragraphs of the Minister's Statement of Reasons which appear under the heading "Character Test".

183 Its relevance for the present case is for the guidance it gives as to the proper approach of statutory construction of a composite phrase. The High Court (Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Heydon and Crennan JJ) said at [66]:
 
 The primary judge considered "craftsmanship" and "aesthetic appeal" as distinct and consecutive questions, before going on and "considering both aspects together". This was an error in the construction and application of the Copyright Act ...

184 In this case, in my opinion, the importance of context cannot be overestimated.

185 The "association test" is one of four criteria by which a person does not pass the character test. It is relevant that the other three are (a) if the person has a substantial criminal record; (c) if, having regard to either or both of the person's past and present criminal conduct, or the person's past and present general conduct, the person is not of good character; or (d) the presence of the person in Australia would involve a significant risk that the person would engage in criminal conduct or act in the other reprehensible ways specified in s 501(6)(d)(ii)-(v).

186 Each of (a), (c) and (d) requires the decision maker to look at the person (ie, the visa holder); each of them requires an assessment of qualities personal to them, which qualities, parliament has said, determine that that person fails the character test.

187 In that context, it would be striking if the criterion in (b), which this case is concerned, could be met by an or any association with a person, group or organisation reasonably suspected of having been or is involved in criminal conduct. Such an association could be a completely innocent, and involve not the slightest reflection on that person's character. The association could be of the most transient kind, could be not only innocent but historically ancient.

188 Having regard to the context, it seems to me impossible to conclude that Parliament would have intended that a person fail the character test where relationship of a visa holder with a person, group or organisation was utterly remote from the criminality that person, group or organisation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic (1993) 43 FCR 280</tocase>
<text>142 The applicant concedes, "The Respondent's reasons cannot be construed as if they were as statute, or with an eye finely attuned for error." This statement adopts the thrust of the observations of the Full Court in Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic (1993) 43 FCR 280, including the mis-combination of visual and aural senses. Of these observations, the joint judgment in the High Court of Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 said:
 
 These propositions are well settled. They recognise the reality that the reasons of an administrative decision-maker are meant to inform and not to be scrutinised upon over-zealous judicial review by seeking to discern whether some inadequacy may be gleaned from the way in which the reasons are expressed. In the present context, any court reviewing a decision upon refugee status must beware of turning a review of the reasons of the decision-maker upon proper principles into a reconsideration of the merits of the decision. This has been made clear many times in this Court. For example, it was said by Brennan J in Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin : [(1990) [1990] HCA 21 ; 170 CLR 1 at 35-36.] 
 
 
 The duty and jurisdiction of the court to review administrative action do not go beyond the declaration and enforcing of the law which determines the limits and governs the exercise of the repository's power. If, in so doing, the court avoids administrative injustice or error, so be it; but the court has no jurisdiction simply to cure administrative injustice or error. The merits of administrative action, to the extent that they can be distinguished from legality, are for the repository of the relevant power and, subject to political control, for the repository alone.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>142 The applicant concedes, "The Respondent's reasons cannot be construed as if they were as statute, or with an eye finely attuned for error." This statement adopts the thrust of the observations of the Full Court in Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic (1993) 43 FCR 280, including the mis-combination of visual and aural senses. Of these observations, the joint judgment in the High Court of Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 said:
 
 These propositions are well settled. They recognise the reality that the reasons of an administrative decision-maker are meant to inform and not to be scrutinised upon over-zealous judicial review by seeking to discern whether some inadequacy may be gleaned from the way in which the reasons are expressed. In the present context, any court reviewing a decision upon refugee status must beware of turning a review of the reasons of the decision-maker upon proper principles into a reconsideration of the merits of the decision. This has been made clear many times in this Court. For example, it was said by Brennan J in Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin : [(1990) [1990] HCA 21 ; 170 CLR 1 at 35-36.] 
 
 
 The duty and jurisdiction of the court to review administrative action do not go beyond the declaration and enforcing of the law which determines the limits and governs the exercise of the repository's power. If, in so doing, the court avoids administrative injustice or error, so be it; but the court has no jurisdiction simply to cure administrative injustice or error. The merits of administrative action, to the extent that they can be distinguished from legality, are for the repository of the relevant power and, subject to political control, for the repository alone.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Godley v MIMIA (2004) ALD 411</tocase>
<text>146 The applicant submitted that some support for the conclusion that an "innocent association" is not sufficient for the purposes of s 501(6)(b) and that there must be some nexus between the visa holder and the criminal conduct by way of knowledge of, or belief in, or even suspicion of criminal conduct, was to be found in the observations, albeit dicta , of Lee J in Godley v MIMIA (2004) ALD 411.

147 Lee J said at [47]:
 
 [47] Section 501(6)(b) combines a finding of fact by the minister with the formation of a reasonable suspicion. First, the minister must form a reasonable suspicion that a person, group or organisation has been or is involved in criminal conduct. It may be taken that to be a reasonable suspicion the suspicion must be based on reasonable grounds. Second, the minister must make a finding of fact that the visa applicant has, or has had, an association with that person, group or organisation. Again it would be necessary for there to be material capable of supporting that finding. It is unnecessary to consider the meaning of the word "association" but for a visa applicant not to pass the character test it may be taken to require the minister to make relevant findings of fact as to the knowledge, or awareness, by the visa applicant of the facts that point to the involvement of the person, group or organisation in criminal conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>MIMIA v Godley [2005] FCAFC 10 ; (2005) 141 FCR 552</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/10.html</AustLII>
<text>148 The decision of Lee J was upheld on appeal in MIMIA v Godley [2005] FCAFC 10 ; (2005) 141 FCR 552. The Full Court, however, did not refer to or deal with that passage in Lee J's judgment.

149 It was submitted by the Solicitor-General that the Full Court quoted the passage of Lee J's judgment preceding [47] and subsequent to that paragraph, but did not quote that passage, the suggestion being that the Full Court declined to endorse those remarks.

150 However, the position is that, having spoken of s 501(6) generally, Lee J, in [46] dealt with s 501(6)(a) ; in [47], dealt with s 501(6)(b) , and in [48], dealt with s 501(6)(d).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>MIMA v Wai Kuen Chan [2001] FCA 1552</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1552.html</AustLII>
<text>154 For the Minister it was submitted that that test is supported by the decision of Emmett J in MIMA v Wai Kuen Chan [2001] FCA 1552 ; that judgment of Emmett J is correct, and that that is the test which the Minister applied.

155 It is on these competing interpretations that an issue is joined.

156 For the Minister, it was submitted that the expression "an association with" can have various meanings which may range from a mere connection or link, to participation in a common goal or purpose. It was submitted that: 
 
 In the present case, when the word "association" is used as noun without any adjectival qualification the expression of words affords a low threshold test. All that paragraph 501(6)(b) requires is that the visa holder has "an association with" the person, group or organisation that the Minister reasonably suspects has been involved in criminal conduct. If the visa holder has an association the threshold test is satisfied .

157 The submissions by the Minister on the establishment of the required association are as follows: 
 
 
 8.3 The Minister was entitled to take into account and did take into account the following matters of fact relevant to the existence of an association between the Applicant Dr Haneef and Kafeel Ahmed ("Kafeel") and Dr Sabeel Ahmed ("Sabeel") (hereinafter collectively referred to as "the Ahmed Brothers"): 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.3.1. Dr Haneef and the Ahmed Brothers were second cousins; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.3.2. They had stayed in the same boarding house accommodation in the United Kingdom; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.3.3. Kafeel had lent money to Dr Haneef; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.3.4 Dr Haneef had left his mobile phone with some credit remaining on his SIM card to Sabeel; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.3.5 There had been conversations in an internet chat room with Sabeel mainly relating to family matters; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 8.4. These matters were sufficient to enliven the Minister's discretion. They established an association between Dr Haneef and both of the Ahmed Brothers. 
 
 
 (Emphasis added).

158 The fact recited in 8.3.2 involves a slight overstatement. The information before the Minister was that Dr Haneef had stayed in the same boarding house accommodation in the United Kingdom as Dr Sabeel Ahmed.

160 Mr Bennett submitted that facts pointing to an innocent connection was sufficient to establish the "association" in s 501(6)(b), and that the Minister was correct to so find. He advanced six reasons:
 
 
 18.1 First , in applying the test which he did the Minister complied with the only direct authority of this Court on the meaning of the expression "an association with"; 
 
 
 
 
 
 18.2 Secondly , the Minister also applied the test which has been set out in Ministerial Direction 21 in relation to the operation of s.501; 
 
 
 
 
 
 18.3 Thirdly , the decision of Emmett J in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Chan is correct and ought to be followed because it accords with the ordinary meaning of the words used by the section, it accords with the Legislative intention of the provision as derived from the Second Reading Speech in relation to the introduced section and it gives effect to the purpose of the section in its amended form; 
 
 
 
 
 
 18.4 Fourthly , the Applicant's submissions adopt a meaning of "association" not relevant to the word as used in the legislation and by doing so ask the Court to read the section as if it had not been the subject of the 1999 amendment; 
 
 
 
 
 
 18.5 Fifthly , the construction sought to be placed on s.501(6)(b) by the Applicant would deprive it of much of its utility; 
 
 
 
 
 
 18.6 Sixthly , the effect of the legislation was that the circumstances arose (Dr Haneef had an association with his cousins who were involved in criminal activities) which entitled the Minister to cancel Dr Haneef's visa in the first instance. Dr Haneef was invited to and entitled to satisfy the Minister that he did not fail the "character test". He chose not to do so.

161 The Solicitor-General submitted:
 
 The Minister has adopted the approach authorised by this Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Chan . There Emmett J rejected the submission that in order to come within the scope of the section the person had to have some form of community of purpose or ideas with the person, group or organisation involved in the criminal conduct such that there was a nexus between the visa holder and the alleged criminal conduct.

162 The applicant conceded, "The Respondent's view that any association is enough is supported by the decision of Emmett J in MIMA v Wai Kuen Chan [2001] FCA 1552." For the applicant, however, it was pointed out that there was no contradictor in Chan , and that Emmett J's attention "does not seem to have been drawn to all the relevant legislative provisions and the extrinsic material". Emmett J's judgment was given ex tempore, and in particular, the significance of s 501C(4) was not adverted to. The applicant respectfully submitted that Chan was wrongly decided.

174 On the appeal, Ms Chan did not appear. Emmett J summarised the Minister's contention as to the existence of an association between Mrs Chan and her husband, which have been earlier set out. Emmett J said:
 
 [6] The Tribunal concluded that an association by way of family ties such as I have just summarised is not of itself sufficient to ground the relevant association. 
 
 [7] The Tribunal considered that it was necessary that there be some nexus between the visa holder and the criminal conduct of the person with whom the visa holder was associated. However, I do not consider that the language of s501(6)(b) justifies such a limitation . There is nothing in the paragraph itself to limit the association in that way. Rather the scheme of the provision is to confer upon the Minister a discretion under s 501(2) to cancel a visa if certain prerequisites are satisfied. The first prerequisite is that the Minister reasonably suspects that the person does not pass the character test and the second is that the person does not satisfy the Minister that the person passes the character test.
 
 [8] Even if those prerequisites are satisfied, the words "the Minister may cancel a visa" (emphasis added) indicate that there is still a discretion to be exercised by the Minister or his delegate as to whether or not to cancel a visa. There may be good reasons why, in a particular case, notwithstanding that the prerequisites are satisfied, the Minister may in the exercise of his discretion decide not to cancel a visa. For example, it may be that there is no nexus between the criminal conduct of the person with whom the visa holder had an association and the visa holder , as was found to be the case in relation to Mrs Chan.
 
 [9] It may be a relevant consideration that the visa holder had no knowledge of the criminal conduct of the other person . It may be a relevant consideration that the visa holder did not knowingly take a benefit from the proceeds of the associate's criminal conduct . Those matters , however, are matters for consideration upon the exercise of the discretion if the discretion arises. They are not matters to be taken into account in determining whether or not the discretion arises , namely, whether or not the person has had an association with someone else whom the Minister reasonably suspects has been involved in criminal conduct.
 
 [10] It may be significant that s 501 was relevantly amended with effect from June 1999. Prior to 1 June, 1999, the Minister had power to refuse to grant a visa or to cancel a visa, "if ... the Minister ... is satisfied that the person is not of good character because of the person's association with another person ... who the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe has been or is involved in criminal conduct". In that form, the Minister was required to make a judgment as to whether or not the visa holder was not of good character because of the association with the person involved in criminal conduct.
 
 [11] The effect of the amendment was to remove any question of whether the Minister is satisfied as to the good character of a visa holder. The provisions in their present form merely require that the Minister be satisfied that the person does not pass the character test. The character test requires a more mechanical exercise, namely, whether or not for present purposes, the person has satisfies any of the four criteria set out in s 501(6)(a)-(d).
 
 [12] The change in the legislation confirms the construction that I consider is the proper construction of the words contained in the paragraph. It follows in my view that the Tribunal erred in law. Accordingly, the decision should be set aside and the matter should be remitted to the Tribunal for decision according to law.
 (Emphasis added).

175 Emmett J in his reasons for judgment, did not give his opinion as to what the "association" in s 501(6)(b) meant, although it may be inferred that a connection or combination was enough. He clearly held that an association by way of family ties was of itself sufficient to ground the necessary "association". That view suggests that any association, whether innocent or sinister, whether fleeting or regular, whether in the distant past or contemporary, is sufficient to enliven the discretion to cancel.

176 In my opinion, that is the test which the Minister applied, that is the test which the Solicitor-General on behalf of the Minister says the Minister applied, and further, that is the test which the Solicitor-General on behalf of the Minister contends is the correct test.

177 In my respectful opinion, Chan was wrongly decided.

196 Emmett J opined in Chan that the innocence of the association would be a relevant consideration in the exercise of the Minister's discretion. However, the Act does not confer any opportunity to be heard on how the discretion should be exercised, either prospectively or retrospectively, after the decision to cancel: cf s 501C(4). There is no opportunity for a person to make representations as to the exercise of discretion about cancellation, or as to the circumstances whether cancellation was or was not in the national interest. The only opportunity afforded by s 501C(4) is to seek to establish that the person passes the character test. That opportunity is empty, and is doomed to fail if, by definition, totally innocent associations mean that the person does not pass the character test.

197 Section s 501C(4) provides that a person whose visa has been cancelled can make representations to the Minister and the Minister may revoke the original decision if the person satisfies the Minister that the person passes the character test, as defined by s 501.

198 The decision under s 501(3) to cancel a visa is made without any obligation to accord natural justice to the visa holder. The opportunity conferred by s 501C(4) is not to make representations to the Minister concerning whether to exercise the discretion to cancel the visa, nor whether the cancellation is in the national interest. That opportunity is only in respect of the element of whether the person can satisfy the Minister that the person passes the character test.

209 A professional association, whether as a doctor, lawyer, social worker, or teacher, would be within the respondent's construction of the association test. A mere familial or social association would be enough. So much is implicit in Emmet J's rejection of the view of the Tribunal that the association by way of family ties, summarised by Emmett J in [7] of his reasons, was sufficient to ground the relevant association.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Chan v MIMA [2001] AATA 487</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/AATA/2001/487.html</AustLII>
<text>163 It is necessary to consider Emmet Js judgment in Chan in some detail, as well as the reasons for decision of Deputy President Purvis QC in the Administrative Appeals Tribunal from whose decision the appeal was made to the Federal Court by the Minister: Chan v MIMA [2001] AATA 487. Mrs Wai Kuen Chan did not appear on the appeal.

164 The Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs, on 26 February 2001, cancelled the applicant's class UC (temporary business entry) sub class 457 visa on the basis that the respondent Minister was not satisfied that the applicant passed the character test, pursuant to s 501(6) of the Migration Act . Deputy President Purvis said, at [3]:
 
 The issues that arise for determination in this application are:
 
 
 
 (a) Whether there is or has been a relevant association between the Applicant and her ex husband Mr Wong Kam Fei.
 (b) if the answer to (a) is in the affirmative whether, the Tribunal reasonably suspects that Mr Wong has been or is involved in criminal conduct.
 (c) if the answers to (a) and (b) above are both in the affirmative and the applicant thereby does not satisfy the character test, whether the Tribunal should or should not exercise its discretion to cancel the Applicant's visa.

165 Deputy President Purvis, at [10], referred to paragraph 1.5 of Direction Number 17, the forerunner to Direction Number 21, which replaced it. The paragraphs in each Direction are identical:
 
 The meaning of "association" for the purposes of the Character Test encompasses a very wide range of relationships including having an "alliance" or a "link" or "connection" with a person, a group or an organised body that is involved in criminal activities. "Association" does not require actual membership of a group or an organised body that is involved in criminal activities. In establishing criminal association, the decision-maker may have regard to the following:
 (a) the degree and frequency of association the non-citizen had or has with the individual group or organisation;
 (b) the duration of the association; and
 (c) the nature of the association.

209 A professional association, whether as a doctor, lawyer, social worker, or teacher, would be within the respondent's construction of the association test. A mere familial or social association would be enough. So much is implicit in Emmet J's rejection of the view of the Tribunal that the association by way of family ties, summarised by Emmett J in [7] of his reasons, was sufficient to ground the relevant association.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Burge v Swarbrick [2007] HCA 17 ; (2007) 234 ALR 204</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/17.html</AustLII>
<text>182 In a case factually quite different from the present, and involving quite a different statutory regime, namely the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) (the Copyright Act ) the High Court was concerned with the application of provisions of the Copyright Act , particularly the phrase "a work of artistic craftsmanship" which appears in the definition of "artistic work" in s 10 and in s 77(1) of the Copyright Act : Burge v Swarbrick [2007] HCA 17 ; (2007) 234 ALR 204. The case was concerned with the Copyright Act in its form before amendment by the Designs (Consequential Amendments) Act 2003 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/28.html</AustLII>
<text>189 In Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ held at [69], [71] and [78]:
 
 [69] The primary object of statutory construction is to construe the relevant provision so that it is consistent with the language and purpose of all the provisions of the statute. The meaning of the provision must be determined "by reference to the language of the instrument viewed as a whole". In Commissioner for Railways (NSW) v Agalianos , Dixon CJ pointed out that "the context, the general purpose and policy of a provision and its consistency and fairness are surer guides to its meaning than the logic with which it is constructed". Thus, the process of construction must always begin by examining the context of the provision that is being construed. 

...
 

 
 [71] Furthermore, a court construing a statutory provision must strive to give meaning to every word of the provision. In The Commonwealth v Baume Griffith CJ cited R v Berchet to support the proposition that it was "a known rule in the interpretation of Statutes that such a sense is to be made upon the whole as that no clause, sentence, or word shall prove superfluous, void, or insignificant, if by any other construction they may all be made useful and pertinent". 

...
 
 [78] However, the duty of a court is to give the words of a statutory provision the meaning that the legislature is taken to have intended them to have. Ordinarily, that meaning (the legal meaning) will correspond with the grammatical meaning of the provision. But not always. The context of the words, the consequences of a literal or grammatical construction, the purpose of the statute or the canons of construction may require the words of a legislative provision to be read in a way that does not correspond with the literal or grammatical meaning."

190 The third edition of the Macquarie Dictionary defines "association" as:
 
 1. An organisation of people with a common purpose and having a formal structure. 2. the act of associating. 3. the state of being associated. 4. companionship or intimacy. 5. connection or combination.; 6. the connection of ideas in thought, or an idea connected with or suggested by a subject of thought. ...

191 The word "associate", which can either be a verb or a noun, is defined as: 
 
 1. to connect by some relation, as in thought. 2. to join as a companion, partner, or ally. 3. to unite; combine: coal associated with shale. verb (i) 4. to enter into a league or union; unite. 5. to keep company, as a friend or intimate; to associate only with wealthy people. noun 6. a partner in interest, as in business or in an enterprise or action. 7. a companion or comrade: my most intimate associates. 8. a confederate; an accomplice; an ally.

201 The observations of the High Court in Project Blue Sky at [71] in the judgment earlier set out have direct application to this consideration.

202 Counsel for the Minister said that the character test, which a person does not pass if the person has or has an association with a person or group or organisation that the Minister reasonably suspects has been or is involved in criminal conduct, does not involve any question about the character of the person being assessed.

203 Mr Bennett submitted that the words "the character test" are not words to be read as having a meaning. He says that those words are "just a convenient definition". He submitted, "one does not read character test and say, 'oh, well, this is about character; that means something about character'. Of course it doesn't."

240 It is not consistent with the direction given by the High Court in Project Blue Sky to construe a statutory provision in such a wide fashion as to include circumstances that are clearly alien to the object of the statute. The provision should be read so as to accord with the object and purpose of the statute. A wider construction, which goes beyond that object, is not to be adopted on the basis that the Minister will confine the exercise of his powers to only those instances within the wider construction which are consistent with the object and purpose of the statute.

241 In my opinion, there is nothing in the legislative history of the section, including the changes introduced by the Migration Legislation Amendment (Strengthening of Provisions Relating to Character and Conduct) Act 1998 , which provides support for the interpretation which the Minister applied, and for which his counsel in these proceedings, seeks to vindicate.

242 Emmett J in Chan placed some reliance on the amendments to s 501 brought about by that Amending 1998 Act in reaching the "any association is sufficient" view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design and Developments Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 231 ALR 663</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/55.html</AustLII>
<text>223 In Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design and Developments Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 231 ALR 663 at 690, Kirby and Crennan JJ said at [111]:
 
 ... it is important to bear in mind the characteristics of modern litigation as recognised by Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ in Johnson v Johnson [(2000) [2000] HCA 48 ; 174 ALR 655] (at [13]): 
 
 
 [13] Whilst the fictional observer, by reference to whom the test is formulated, is not to be assumed to have a detailed knowledge of the law, or of the character or ability of a particular judge, the reasonableness of any suggested apprehension of bias is to be considered in the context of ordinary judicial practice. The rules and conventions governing such practice are not frozen in time. They develop to take account of the exigencies of modern litigation. At the trial level, modern judges, responding to a need for more active case management, intervene in the conduct of cases to an extent that may surprise a person who came to court expecting a judge to remain, until the moment of pronouncement of judgment, as inscrutable as the Sphinx. In Vakauta v Kelly , Brennan, Deane and Gaudron JJ, referring both to trial and appellate proceedings, spoke of " the dialogue between Bench and Bar which is so helpful in the identification of real issues and real problems in a particular case ". Judges, at trial or appellate level, who, in exchanges with counsel, express tentative views which reflect a certain tendency of mind, are not on that account alone to be taken to indicate prejudgment. Judges are not expected to wait until the end of a case before they start thinking about the issues, or to sit mute while evidence is advanced and arguments are presented. On the contrary, they will often form tentative opinions on matters in issue, and counsel are usually assisted by hearing those opinions, and being given an opportunity to deal with them. 
 
 
 (Emphasis added).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Vakauta v Kelly (1989) 87 ALR 633</tocase>
<text>223 In Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design and Developments Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 231 ALR 663 at 690, Kirby and Crennan JJ said at [111]:
 
 ... it is important to bear in mind the characteristics of modern litigation as recognised by Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ in Johnson v Johnson [(2000) [2000] HCA 48 ; 174 ALR 655] (at [13]): 
 
 
 [13] Whilst the fictional observer, by reference to whom the test is formulated, is not to be assumed to have a detailed knowledge of the law, or of the character or ability of a particular judge, the reasonableness of any suggested apprehension of bias is to be considered in the context of ordinary judicial practice. The rules and conventions governing such practice are not frozen in time. They develop to take account of the exigencies of modern litigation. At the trial level, modern judges, responding to a need for more active case management, intervene in the conduct of cases to an extent that may surprise a person who came to court expecting a judge to remain, until the moment of pronouncement of judgment, as inscrutable as the Sphinx. In Vakauta v Kelly , Brennan, Deane and Gaudron JJ, referring both to trial and appellate proceedings, spoke of " the dialogue between Bench and Bar which is so helpful in the identification of real issues and real problems in a particular case ". Judges, at trial or appellate level, who, in exchanges with counsel, express tentative views which reflect a certain tendency of mind, are not on that account alone to be taken to indicate prejudgment. Judges are not expected to wait until the end of a case before they start thinking about the issues, or to sit mute while evidence is advanced and arguments are presented. On the contrary, they will often form tentative opinions on matters in issue, and counsel are usually assisted by hearing those opinions, and being given an opportunity to deal with them. 
 
 
 (Emphasis added).

224 In Vakauta v Kelly (1989) 87 ALR 633, after comments set out in the above observation, Brennan, Deane, and Gaudron JJ said at p 635:
 
 It seems to us that a trial judge who made necessary rulings but otherwise sat completely silent throughout a non-jury trial with the result that his or her views about the issues, problems and technical difficulties involved in the case remained unknown until they emerged as final conclusions in her or her judgment would not represent a model to be emulated.

225 According to Direction 21: 
 
 The object of the Act is to regulate, in the national interest, the coming into and presence in Australia of non-citizens. To facilitate this object, the Minister has been given a discretion to ... cancel a visa where ... the visa holder does not pass the Character Test. In exercising this power, the Minister has a responsibility to the Parliament and to the Australian community to protect the community from criminal or other reprehensible conduct and to ... cancel visas held by non-citizens whose actions are so abhorrent to the community that they should not be allowed to ... remain within it.
 (Emphases added).

226 In my opinion, the requirement of some nexus between the visa holder and the criminal conduct suspected of the person or group with whom the visa holder has an association, is reinforced by the terms of paragraph 1.5 of Direction 21.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Akpata v MIMIA [2004] FCAFC 65</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/65.html</AustLII>
<text>231 Lander J in Akpata v MIMIA [2004] FCAFC 65 (with whom Carr and Sundberg JJ agreed) said of the purpose of s 501:
 
 
 [103] Section 501 is designed to provide a procedure whereby persons who have been granted visas or persons who would otherwise be entitled to the grant of a visa may have that visa cancelled or refused if those persons are undesirable persons to travel to or remain in Australia . Persons will be undesirable if they fail to pass the character test. 
 
 
 ... 
 
 
 
 [105] The definition of a person passing the character test in s 501(6) shows that Parliament intended that persons who have been convicted of relatively serious crime; associate with criminals ; have a history including an immediate history of criminal conduct or general conduct indicating bad character; are a significant risk of engaging in criminal conduct or undesirable conduct (s 501(6)(d)), should not be permitted to travel to or remain in Australia . Shortly put, persons who have committed or are likely to commit criminal or other like conduct should not be permitted to travel to or remain in Australia. Because the purpose is to exclude those persons, the matters that are relevant to the exercise of the Minister's discretion will include any fact or circumstance which would suggest that a person of otherwise bad character (as it is defined in the Act) should be allowed to travel to or remain in Australia. 
 
 
 (Emphases added).

232 For the Minister, it is said that the approach for the applicant to the interpretation of s 501(6)(b) is to impose limitations in the section, which do not exist, and which could have been easily imposed if the legislature had so intended.

233 However, the submissions by the Minister attribute to the applicant a desire to introduce limitations, which in fact the applicant does not seek to do. The Minister's submissions assert that the section does not say that the visa holder need be a member of a group or organisation, nor a participant in criminal activity, nor does the section say that the association of the visa holder with the person, group, or organisation, need be an ideological or criminal association, or an association by which the visa holder or applicant would benefit from the criminal activity. Moreover, the section does not say that the circumstances identified have to be such as to reflect adversely on the character of the visa holder or applicant. All of this may be accepted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>269 Section 501(3) of the Act confers a discretion on the Minister which is in terms "unconfined". The Minister is not bound to take a particular matter into account in the exercise of that discretion unless an implication to that effect is to be found in the subject matter, scope, and purpose of the statute: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24 at 40 (per Mason J, as his Honour then was). Failure to take into account a particular consideration cannot constitute jurisdictional error unless the consideration is one which, on the proper construction of the Act, is made compulsorily relevant: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 423</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1196.html</AustLII>
<text>269 Section 501(3) of the Act confers a discretion on the Minister which is in terms "unconfined". The Minister is not bound to take a particular matter into account in the exercise of that discretion unless an implication to that effect is to be found in the subject matter, scope, and purpose of the statute: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24 at 40 (per Mason J, as his Honour then was). Failure to take into account a particular consideration cannot constitute jurisdictional error unless the consideration is one which, on the proper construction of the Act, is made compulsorily relevant: Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 at 423</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Huynh [2004] FCAFC 256 ; (2004) 139 FCR 505</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/256.html</AustLII>
<text>270 See also Herrera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 314 at [5] ; and Minister for Immigration v Huynh (2004) 139 FCR 535 per Kiefel and Bennett JJ at [71]-[74].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Herrera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 314</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/314.html</AustLII>
<text>270 See also Herrera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 314 at [5] ; and Minister for Immigration v Huynh (2004) 139 FCR 535 per Kiefel and Bennett JJ at [71]-[74].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Thompson v The Council of the Municipality of Randwick [1950] HCA 33 ; (1950) 81 CLR 87</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1950/33.html</AustLII>
<text>287 If a discretionary statutory power is exercised for a purpose other than the purpose for which the power was conferred, the exercise of that power is invalid. The purpose for the grant of a power is to be derived from the statute conferring it. If there is a combination of purposes actuating the exercise of the discretionary power, the exercise will be invalid if an improper purpose was the "substantial" or the "true and dominant" purpose of the exercise of the power: Thompson v The Council of Municipality of the Randwick [1950] HCA 33 ; (1950) 81 CLR 87 at [186] ; Samrein v Metropolitan Water, Sewerage and Drainage Board (1982) 41 ALR 467 at [7]-[8].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Samrein v Metropolitan Water, Sewerage and Drainage Board (1982) 41 ALR 467</tocase>
<text>287 If a discretionary statutory power is exercised for a purpose other than the purpose for which the power was conferred, the exercise of that power is invalid. The purpose for the grant of a power is to be derived from the statute conferring it. If there is a combination of purposes actuating the exercise of the discretionary power, the exercise will be invalid if an improper purpose was the "substantial" or the "true and dominant" purpose of the exercise of the power: Thompson v The Council of Municipality of the Randwick [1950] HCA 33 ; (1950) 81 CLR 87 at [186] ; Samrein v Metropolitan Water, Sewerage and Drainage Board (1982) 41 ALR 467 at [7]-[8].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719</tocase>
<text>288 Thus in Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719, the Full Court of the Federal Court (Fox, Wilcox and French JJ) held that where a particular deportee was wanted by authorities in West Germany, of which he was a national, Australian authorities were entitled to do everything necessary for the enforcement of a deportation order under the Act, but were not entitled to go beyond that. In particular, the Court held that to deport a person to a particular country for the purpose of presenting a person to the law enforcement authorities of that country is outside the purposes of the Migration Act .

289 Wilcox and French JJ in their joint judgment said, at 731: 
 
 The golden rule is that the Australian authorities are entitled, notwithstanding their knowledge that a particular deportee is wanted in the country of destination, to do everything which is necessary for the enforcement of the Migration Act and the proper implementation of the deportation order. But they are not entitled to go beyond that, and in purported exercise of powers under that Act, to take steps whose only purpose is the bringing to justice of the deportee in a foreign country. At that stage the Australian authorities would not be exercising deportation powers; they would be involved in an unlawful extradition.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Park Oh Ho v Minister of State for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 81 ALR 288</tocase>
<text>290 In Park Oh Ho v Minister of State for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 81 ALR 288, the Full Court of the Federal Court (Sweeney and Foster JJ, Morling J dissenting) held that a deportation order had not been issued for the purpose of securing various persons' removal from Australia, but was to secure their continued detention in custody, so that their evidence would be available in contemplated criminal proceedings.

291 The decision of the Full Court upheld the decision of Davies J at first instance, to declare the deportation orders a nullity and set them aside. The matter went to the High Court, but only on the question of whether the Full Court had been correct in upholding the refusal of Davies J to make a declaration of unlawfulness. It was on this basis that the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court was reversed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Park Oh Ho v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1989) 88 ALR 517</tocase>
<text>292 In the High Court, Park Oh Ho v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1989) 88 ALR 517, (Mason CJ, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ) referred to the findings of Davies J, confirmed by the Full Court, that more of the deportation orders had been made by the delegate of the Minister for the legitimate purpose of giving effect to a decision that a prohibited non-citizen should be deported as soon as appropriate arrangements for that deportation could be made, and that each had been made for the impermissible purpose of detaining the particular appellant in custody so that his evidence would be available in the criminal proceedings, and the conclusion of Davies J that the deportations were all intrinsically flawed.

293 Their Honours noted at 519:
 
 Davies J. held that each of them [the deportation orders] "should be treated as a nullity" and ordered that they be "set aside ab initio ".

294 A decision by the Minister to cancel a visa on character grounds under s 501 of the Migration Act , validly made, has the result of the visa thereupon ceases to be in effect: s 82(1) of the Migration Act . Thereafter, the person to whom the visa is issued is an unlawful non-citizen, in the terms of sections 14 and 15 of the Migration Act , is liable to detention under s 189 of the Migration Act , and for removal from Australia under s 198 of the Migration Act .

295 As a consequence of s 501E , no further application for the grant of a visa can be made by the person whose visa has been cancelled. The only exception, pursuant to s 501E(2)(a) , is an application for a protection visa. Because the person cannot, after cancellation, obtain a visa, that person's status has been determined for all time. That person is an unlawful non-citizen liable to detention and removal from Australia.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sydney Municipal Council v Campbell [1925] AC 338</tocase>
<text>278 A person challenging the exercise of a power on the basis of improper purpose has the onus of establishing that contention: Sydney Municipal Council v Campbell [1925] AC 338 at 343. Where the purpose of a decision has to be ascertained by inference from other facts, there is a presumption of regularity: Industrial Equity Limited v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649 at 671 per Gaudron J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Industrial Equity Limited v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/46.html</AustLII>
<text>278 A person challenging the exercise of a power on the basis of improper purpose has the onus of establishing that contention: Sydney Municipal Council v Campbell [1925] AC 338 at 343. Where the purpose of a decision has to be ascertained by inference from other facts, there is a presumption of regularity: Industrial Equity Limited v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649 at 671 per Gaudron J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Lebanese Moslem Association v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1986) 11 FCR 543</tocase>
<text>316 In Cross on Evidence (6 th Edition, Butterworth, 2000), the learned authors stated at p 39:
 
 A Jones v Dunkel inference can be drawn against a Minister who does not give evidence, [ Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Torres Strait Islander Affairs v State of Western Australia (1996) 67 FCR 40 at 62] notwithstanding that the difficulties busy Ministers could have in giving evidence frequently might justify a departure from the ordinary application of Jones v Dunkel. [ Lebanese Moslem Association v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1986) 11 FCR 543 at 548.]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Lebanese Moslem Association (1987) 17 FCR 373</tocase>
<text>317 In Lebanese Moslem Association (reversed on other points of law in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Lebanese Moslem Association (1987) 17 FCR 373) Pincus J, at 548, found it "hard to resist" drawing certain inferences that assisted the applicants in that case. This was despite the fact that Senior Counsel to the respondent Minister argued, so Pincus J said, "with some cogency that performance of his ministerial duties would be impractical if he were to spend substantial amounts of time in courts being cross-examined about his decisions."

322 After stating, at [316], that Pincus J only hesitantly concluded in Lebanese Moslem Association that the rule applied to Ministers not giving evidence, Callinan J said, at [317]:
 
 It is unnecessary to decide in this case whether the rule should have application to a Minister in modern times. But on any view it cannot be applied in any unqualified way to a modern Minister of State, and not just for the reasons that Pincus J described as cogent. Considerations of public interest immunity may loom large in some cases. A Minister is a policymaker and policy advocate as well as a decision-maker. Further, the statement of principle in Jones v Dunkel is no more than a particular instance of the old rule stated by Lord Mansfield in Blatch v Archer and cited recently by this Court in Vetter v Lake Macquarie City Council , that evidence has to be weighed according to the circumstances of, as well as the capacity of, a party to adduce it.

325 However, in most, if not all, cases, because of the factors expressed by Pincus J, and also Kirby J and Callinan J in the passages set out above, the absence of a Minister giving evidence in the for the witness box will be easily understood.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs v State of Western Australia (1996) 67 FCR 40</tocase>
<text>316 In Cross on Evidence (6 th Edition, Butterworth, 2000), the learned authors stated at p 39:
 
 A Jones v Dunkel inference can be drawn against a Minister who does not give evidence, [ Minister for Aboriginal Affairs and Torres Strait Islander Affairs v State of Western Australia (1996) 67 FCR 40 at 62] notwithstanding that the difficulties busy Ministers could have in giving evidence frequently might justify a departure from the ordinary application of Jones v Dunkel. [ Lebanese Moslem Association v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1986) 11 FCR 543 at 548.]

318 In Minister for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Affairs v State of Western Australia , the Full Court of the Federal Court (Black CJ, Burchett and Kiefel JJ) at 62 (citing the Lebanese Moslem Association ) concluded that the Minister's failure to call evidence allowed the Court to more confidently draw an inference favourable to the other party. See also Citibank Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation &amp; Others (1988) 83 ALR 144 at 159, where Lockhart J notes that if the inference is capable of applying to Ministers and senior corporate executives, then it is capable of applying to senior public servants (citing to Lebanese Moslem Association, Cross on Evidence, and Electronics Industries Ltd v Mayor of City of Oakleigh [1973] VR 177 at 189).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/389.html</AustLII>
<text>323 More recently, in Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [72] , Sackville J referred to the High Court's observations in Jia but found it unnecessary to decide whether it applied to the circumstances of the case before him which did not involve purported bias by the Minister as was the case in Jia , but rather, failure to have regard to certain information. Sackville J had concluded, at [71], that assuming the rule applied, it would not assist the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c40">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ghazal v Government Insurance Office of New South Wales (1992) 29 NSWLR 336</tocase>
<text>324 Given the rule in Jones v Dunkel is one of the "commonsense reasoning" and one which allows parties to satisfactorily explain their failure to call a witness ( Ghazal v Government Insurance Office of New South Wales (1992) 29 NSWLR 336 at 342), there can be no per se rule that a Jones v Dunkel inference is not available where a Minister does not testify.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>