<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cavoli v Etl [2007] FCA 1191 (16 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1191.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>Etl v Cavoli [2007] FMCA 356</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/356.html</AustLII>
<text>1 The appellant Tony Cavoli (the Creditor) appeals against a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court which set aside a bankruptcy notice served on the respondent Karl Etl (the Debtor): Etl v Cavoli [2007] FMCA 356.

2 The Creditor was an assignee of debt from a firm of solicitors called Lennon Settle Mazzeo Lawyers (the Assignor). The learned Magistrate held at [62] that the bankruptcy notice was an abuse of process. His Honour found at [59] that it had been issued "solely for the purpose of securing payment of the debt". The Creditor had failed to take "appropriate action to otherwise recover the debt or even make demand upon the Debtor" (at [59]). There was, his Honour found at [62], a collateral purpose in that the Creditor and the Assignor had a "contrived arrangement" to circumvent the operation of s 44(3) of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth). The Assignor was said to be a secured creditor for a much larger amount. By "syphoning off" a small debt to the Creditor, the Assignor could bring about the Debtor's bankruptcy without having to surrender his security, as required by s 44(3) had it been the petitioning creditor (at [61]).

3 The debt the subject of the bankruptcy notice was $21,638.30 being the amount taxed by Master Bruce of the Supreme Court of Victoria as the costs of the Assignor pursuant to orders made against the Debtor in the Supreme Court in 2004 and 2005. The Master's Certificate was issued on 18 January 2006. The notice of assignment dated 1 May 2006 was in evidence, although not the assignment itself. The notice of assignment was in these terms:
 
 "To: Mr Karl Etl (aka Karel Etl) 
 Of: 5 Richardson Street, Essendon 
 
 
 NOTICE OF ASSIGNMENT OF DEBT 
 
 
 ASSIGNMENT OF DEBT Notice is hereby given to you that Lennon Settle Mazzeo Lawyers (formerly Lennon Settle) has assigned to Tony Cavoli all its legal and beneficial rights, title and interest in the Debt in the sum of $21,638.30 plus interest pursuant to statute payable to Lennon Settle Mazzeo Lawyers and arising out of an Order made by Master Bruce of the Supreme Court of Victoria at Melbourne 18 January, 2006. 
 
 DIRECTION TO PAY Accordingly, you are hereby irrevocably directed to pay the Debt to Tony Cavoli or as he may in writing direct. 
 
 PAYMENT DETAILS Please remit the payment in the sum of $21,638.30 plus interest pursuant to statute to:- 
 
 Tony Cavoli 
 Level 9, 179 Queen Street 
 MELBOURNE 3000 
 
 DISCHARGE OF DEBT You will receive from Tony Cavoli confirmation of the discharge of the Debt upon payment of same in full. 
 
 Dated: 1 May 2006. 
 
 [sgd].................................... [sgd]....................................... 
 LENNON SETTLE MAZZEO TONY CAVOLI"

4 On 8 May 2006 the Debtor was served with a bankruptcy notice in respect of the assigned debt. As required by the statutory form, the notice included the statement:
 
 "You are required, within 21 days after service on you of this Bankruptcy Notice: 
 (a) to pay to the creditor the amount of the debt; or 
 
 
 (b) to make an arrangement to the creditor's satisfaction for settlement of the debt." 
 

The notice also stated that payment could be made to the Creditor at Level 9, 179 Queen Street, Melbourne 3000.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Allesch v Maunz [2000] HCA 40 ; (2000) 203 CLR 172</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/40.html</AustLII>
<text>5 The Debtor swore an affidavit in support of his application. Leaving aside some grounds which were dismissed by the learned Magistrate and not raised on appeal, the Debtor deposed that he was solvent and that any creditor's petition against him would amount to an abuse of process in view of the fact that any such sequestration orders would be "foredoomed to failure based upon my solvency". He deposed that he had "assets which exceed $1 million in value and my liabilities are far less than that figure". The affidavit continued:
 
 
 "11. Further I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice also amounts to an abuse of process by reason of the fact that the assignor of the relevant debt previously filed another Bankruptcy Notice against me in this Court arising out of another proceeding filed in the County Court and has not pursued any bankruptcy proceedings against me on the basis of that principal judgment debt. I believe it has not done so because it knows that I am a solvent person. 
 
 12. The appeal proceedings brought against the assignor arose out of that principal County Court proceeding. The purported assignor of the debt was my previous solicitor in Family law proceedings, Messrs. Lennon Settle, and they know full well that I am a solvent person with ample assets. I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice has been filed as an illegitimate attempt to cause me stress and vexation, knowing full well that I am a solvent person. It smacks of an abuse of process designed to persecute me and designed to ulitise this Court s a debt collector when there are ample alternative remedies available to any judgment credit or assignee thereof to collect any judgment debt owed by me." 
 

The Debtor's speculation about the beliefs and motives of the Assignor and the Creditor would seem to be inadmissible. No objection was taken. However, as this is an appeal by way of rehearing, the judgment appealed from can be set aside where there is legal, factual or discretionary error: Allesch v Maunz [2000] HCA 40 ; (2000) 203 CLR 172 at [23] (a case which concerned the Family Court but is equally applicable to appeals in the Federal Court: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at [75] ). It is not clear whether his Honour relied on this evidence, but if and to the extent that he did there would be an error of fact-finding: CSR Ltd v Della Maddalena [2006] HCA 1 ; (2006) 224 ALR 1 at [16] . Unsupported speculation of this kind has no probative value.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/17.html</AustLII>
<text>5 The Debtor swore an affidavit in support of his application. Leaving aside some grounds which were dismissed by the learned Magistrate and not raised on appeal, the Debtor deposed that he was solvent and that any creditor's petition against him would amount to an abuse of process in view of the fact that any such sequestration orders would be "foredoomed to failure based upon my solvency". He deposed that he had "assets which exceed $1 million in value and my liabilities are far less than that figure". The affidavit continued:
 
 
 "11. Further I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice also amounts to an abuse of process by reason of the fact that the assignor of the relevant debt previously filed another Bankruptcy Notice against me in this Court arising out of another proceeding filed in the County Court and has not pursued any bankruptcy proceedings against me on the basis of that principal judgment debt. I believe it has not done so because it knows that I am a solvent person. 
 
 12. The appeal proceedings brought against the assignor arose out of that principal County Court proceeding. The purported assignor of the debt was my previous solicitor in Family law proceedings, Messrs. Lennon Settle, and they know full well that I am a solvent person with ample assets. I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice has been filed as an illegitimate attempt to cause me stress and vexation, knowing full well that I am a solvent person. It smacks of an abuse of process designed to persecute me and designed to ulitise this Court s a debt collector when there are ample alternative remedies available to any judgment credit or assignee thereof to collect any judgment debt owed by me." 
 

The Debtor's speculation about the beliefs and motives of the Assignor and the Creditor would seem to be inadmissible. No objection was taken. However, as this is an appeal by way of rehearing, the judgment appealed from can be set aside where there is legal, factual or discretionary error: Allesch v Maunz [2000] HCA 40 ; (2000) 203 CLR 172 at [23] (a case which concerned the Family Court but is equally applicable to appeals in the Federal Court: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at [75] ). It is not clear whether his Honour relied on this evidence, but if and to the extent that he did there would be an error of fact-finding: CSR Ltd v Della Maddalena [2006] HCA 1 ; (2006) 224 ALR 1 at [16] . Unsupported speculation of this kind has no probative value.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>CSR Ltd v Della Maddalena [2006] HCA 1 ; (2006) 224 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/1.html</AustLII>
<text>5 The Debtor swore an affidavit in support of his application. Leaving aside some grounds which were dismissed by the learned Magistrate and not raised on appeal, the Debtor deposed that he was solvent and that any creditor's petition against him would amount to an abuse of process in view of the fact that any such sequestration orders would be "foredoomed to failure based upon my solvency". He deposed that he had "assets which exceed $1 million in value and my liabilities are far less than that figure". The affidavit continued:
 
 
 "11. Further I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice also amounts to an abuse of process by reason of the fact that the assignor of the relevant debt previously filed another Bankruptcy Notice against me in this Court arising out of another proceeding filed in the County Court and has not pursued any bankruptcy proceedings against me on the basis of that principal judgment debt. I believe it has not done so because it knows that I am a solvent person. 
 
 12. The appeal proceedings brought against the assignor arose out of that principal County Court proceeding. The purported assignor of the debt was my previous solicitor in Family law proceedings, Messrs. Lennon Settle, and they know full well that I am a solvent person with ample assets. I believe that the Bankruptcy Notice has been filed as an illegitimate attempt to cause me stress and vexation, knowing full well that I am a solvent person. It smacks of an abuse of process designed to persecute me and designed to ulitise this Court s a debt collector when there are ample alternative remedies available to any judgment credit or assignee thereof to collect any judgment debt owed by me." 
 

The Debtor's speculation about the beliefs and motives of the Assignor and the Creditor would seem to be inadmissible. No objection was taken. However, as this is an appeal by way of rehearing, the judgment appealed from can be set aside where there is legal, factual or discretionary error: Allesch v Maunz [2000] HCA 40 ; (2000) 203 CLR 172 at [23] (a case which concerned the Family Court but is equally applicable to appeals in the Federal Court: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at [75] ). It is not clear whether his Honour relied on this evidence, but if and to the extent that he did there would be an error of fact-finding: CSR Ltd v Della Maddalena [2006] HCA 1 ; (2006) 224 ALR 1 at [16] . Unsupported speculation of this kind has no probative value.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maxwell-Smith v S &amp; E Hall Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 825</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/825.html</AustLII>
<text>14 His Honour referred to statements of principle including those in Maxwell-Smith v S &amp; E Hall Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 825 when Jacobson J cited a number of propositions including at [43]: 
 
 "If it is apparent to the Court that the purpose of a bankruptcy notice is to put pressure on a debtor to pay a debt, rather than to invoke the Court's insolvency jurisdiction, the issue of the bankruptcy notice will be an abuse of process." [Authorities cited]

15 The learned Magistrate at [56] found the evidence of the Debtor's solvency "clearly deficient". This aspect has not been pursued on the appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Etl v Settle [2004] FMCA 718</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2004/718.html</AustLII>
<text>16 His Honour at [57] thought that the Creditor had been "less than frank" with the Court in divulging the true circumstances leading up to the execution of the assignment. He noted that the assignment itself had not been produced and there might have been formal defects in it. His Honour continued:
 
 
 "58. In any event, applying the authorities to which reference has been made, I am satisfied that the bankruptcy notice has been issued as a means to secure payment of the debt and further that it has a collateral purpose. On that basis, I am satisfied it is an abuse of process and should be set aside. 
 
 59. It is clear on the evidence before me that the Creditor has issued the bankruptcy notice solely for the purpose of securing payment of the debt and has failed to take any appropriate action to otherwise recover the debt or even make demand upon the Debtor for payment of the debt. The demand made on the Debtor was a demand made by the assignor prior to the assignment of the debt. 
 
 60. The collateral purpose in my view having regard to the history set out in the court's earlier decision in Etl v Settle [[2004] FMCA 718] was to circumvent the operation of s.44 of the Bankruptcy Act . I am satisfied that the close relationship between the Creditor and the assignor illustrates that this procedure undertaken for the first time by the Creditor was a procedure which had as its collateral purpose a benefit to the Creditor's friend and professional colleague of avoiding the operation against the assignor of s.44 of the Bankruptcy Act . 
 
 61. I am satisfied on the material before me, including the history set out in the Court's earlier judgment to which I have already referred, that there was a benefit to the assignor of 'syphoning off' a small part of the total debt allegedly owed by the Debtor to the assignor in a manner that would enable the current Creditor to pursue a sequestration order after the issue of a bankruptcy notice in a manner which would not attract the operation of s.44 of the Bankruptcy Act to the detriment of the assignor. 
 
 
 
 
 
 62. The use of bankruptcy proceedings in this contrived manner in my view is an abuse of process, as it has clearly been undertaken at least in part to satisfy [the] collateral purpose of obtaining a benefit to the assignor of becoming a Creditor without sacrificing security. This contrived arrangement is an inappropriate use of bankruptcy proceedings and a blatant attempt to avoid the consequences of the operation of s.44 of the Bankruptcy Act ."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schellenberg v Tunnel Holdings Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 18 ; (2000) 200 CLR 121</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/18.html</AustLII>
<text>17 There was no evidence to base the finding in [59] that the Creditor issued the notice "solely" for the purpose of securing payment of the debt. Even if the Magistrate did not find him a credible witness, disbelief of him could not found a positive conclusion as to the existence of the relevant purpose, proof whereof lay on the Debtor: Schellenberg v Tunnel Holdings Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 18 ; (2000) 200 CLR 121 at [53] , King v Collins [2007] NSWCA 122 at [42] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>King v Collins [2007] NSWCA 122</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2007/122.html</AustLII>
<text>17 There was no evidence to base the finding in [59] that the Creditor issued the notice "solely" for the purpose of securing payment of the debt. Even if the Magistrate did not find him a credible witness, disbelief of him could not found a positive conclusion as to the existence of the relevant purpose, proof whereof lay on the Debtor: Schellenberg v Tunnel Holdings Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 18 ; (2000) 200 CLR 121 at [53] , King v Collins [2007] NSWCA 122 at [42] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>