<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Silberberg v The Builders Collective of Australia Inc [2007] FCA 1512 (2 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1512.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Comalco Ltd (1986) 12 FCR 510</tocase>
<text>33 The discussion by the High Court in Thompson v Australian Capital Television [1996] HCA 38 ; (1996) 186 CLR 574 of subordinate dissemination is of particular interest (see Brennan CJ, Dawson and Toohey JJ at 585 590, Gaudron J at 591 596 and Gummow J at 617 620). That case concerned the liability of a television station that took to air a direct "feed" of a live current affairs show from another television station. The argument that it was a mere conduit failed. Emphasis was placed upon the choice made by that station to take a live current affairs program likely, to be controversial, directly to air without any editing or scrutiny. For an earlier, brave but unsuccessful, attempt to argue that a television station which puts a debate to air is not responsible for statements by participants see Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Comalco Ltd (1986) 12 FCR 510.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2000/1042.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The ability to prevent publication or the continuance of publication in the context of defamation as applied in Godfrey [2001] QB 201was based in part upon Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818. That case concerned liability of a golf club for a defamatory note on the golf club notice board. That principle, as it applied in defamation, was analysed with some care by Hunt J of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127. It was concluded that it was necessary for the plaintiff to establish that the defendant had, in fact, accepted responsibility for continued publication by consenting to, approving of, adopting or promoting or in some way ratifying the continued publication. Such accepted responsibility could be established by inference. That case involved someone else's defamatory statement being attached to the defendant's property. (See also Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042 and Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248 . )</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bunt v Tilley [2006] 3 All ER 336; [2006] EWHC 407 (QB)</tocase>
<text>31 It was held in Bunt v Tilley [2006] 3 All ER 336; [2006] EWHC 407 (QB) that an Internet service provider that performed no more than a passive role in facilitating postings on the Internet and did not "host" the relevant website was not deemed to be a publisher at common law any more than a telephone company would be liable for defamation over the telephone. Godfrey [2001] QB 201 was distinguished.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818</tocase>
<text>29 In Kaplan v Go Daddy Group [2005] NSWSC 636 White J, in an interlocutory decision, speaking of comments disparaging of a business posted on a website said (at [32] [33]):
 
 "There is also a serious question to be tried that he was the author of the other headings and comments on the site to which I have referred. 
 Even if he was not the author of those headings and comments, there is still a serious question to be tried as to whether he published the statements which appeared on the site. He established the site and thereby invited disparaging comments. He maintained some control over the site. He said that he, along with anyone else, could remove any of the comments from the site. The extent of his control over what was, or was not, published, was not fully explored, but it is seriously arguable that he was at least as much in control of the site and responsible for what appeared on it as was the internet service provider in Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd [2001] QB 201 ; [1999] 4 All ER 342, or the proprietors and secretary of a golf club which allowed a defamatory statement to remain on a notice board in Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818; 2 All ER 204. In Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd , it was held that an internet service provider was a publisher at common law of the defamatory comments posted on the site by an unknown user."

32 The ability to prevent publication or the continuance of publication in the context of defamation as applied in Godfrey [2001] QB 201was based in part upon Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818. That case concerned liability of a golf club for a defamatory note on the golf club notice board. That principle, as it applied in defamation, was analysed with some care by Hunt J of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127. It was concluded that it was necessary for the plaintiff to establish that the defendant had, in fact, accepted responsibility for continued publication by consenting to, approving of, adopting or promoting or in some way ratifying the continued publication. Such accepted responsibility could be established by inference. That case involved someone else's defamatory statement being attached to the defendant's property. (See also Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042 and Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248 . )</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 ; (2006) 156 FCR 380</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/187.html</AustLII>
<text>30 Universal Music Australia v Cooper Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1 dealt with infringement of copyright. The principal claims were based on infringement of copyright by a website that facilitated the free downloading of certain sound recordings. The first respondent was the registered owner and operator of the website. It contained hyperlinks to thousands of sound recordings which were located on remote websites and downloaded directly from those websites to the computer of the Internet user. The music file was not sent to, downloaded on, transmitted through or saved to the first respondent's website. The second to fifth respondents hosted the website and were responsible for maintaining the connection to the Internet. They were unaware of the contents of the website and took no steps to inform themselves of that content. Tamberlin J held that the first respondent infringed copyright by authorising the infringing acts of Internet users who accessed the website and the owners or operators of the remote website from which the infringing recordings were downloaded. He permitted and approved the infringements and had sufficient control over his website to prevent the infringements (150 FCR 1 at [77] [102]). The second to fifth respondents infringed the copyright by authorising the infringing acts (150 FCR 1 at [103] [132]). They had an active role in relation to the website, were aware of the content of the website and had the power to prevent the infringing acts. Those findings were substantially upheld on appeal, although an employee of the Internet service provider was let out ( Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 ; (2006) 156 FCR 380 particularly per Branson J at [28] [52], [61] [65] and Kenny J at [136] [165]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1007.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The test or standard in s 18C(1)(a) of the Act is objective: see Jones v Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at 268-269; Hagan v Trustees of Toowoomba Sports Grounds Trust [2000] FCA 1615 ; Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352 at [12] . It is for the Court to determine whether the act, in all the circumstances in which it was done, would be reasonably likely to offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate another person or a group of people of a particular racial, national or ethnic group: see Hagan [2000] FCA 1615 at [15] . As Hely J remarked in Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at [99] : 
 
 "it is not necessary for an applicant to prove that any person was actually offended, insulted, humiliated or intimidated by the conduct in question ... [but] evidence, for example, that a member of a particular racial group was offended by the conduct in question would be admissible, on, but not determinative of, the issue of contravention."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dow Jones &amp; Company Inc v Gutnick [2002] HCA 56 ; (2002) 210 CLR 575</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/56.html</AustLII>
<text>28 Material posted onto an Internet website may be seen to be published by the author when uploaded or posted onto a web server by or on behalf of the author and also by a person when downloaded onto the computer accessed by a person who has used a web browser to pull the material from the web server in comprehensible form. For the purposes of the law of defamation, publication is regarded as a bilateral, complete at the time of downloading Dow Jones &amp; Company Inc v Gutnick [2002] HCA 56 ; (2002) 210 CLR 575 at [25] [27], [40] and [44]). Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ said (at [11]):
 
 " 'Publishing' and its cognate words is also a term that gives rise to difficulty. As counsel for the interveners pointed out it may be useful, when considering where something is published to distinguish between the (publisher's) act of publication and the fact of publication (to a third party), but even that distinction may not suffice to reveal all the considerations relevant to locating the place of the tort of defamation."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2006/248.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The ability to prevent publication or the continuance of publication in the context of defamation as applied in Godfrey [2001] QB 201was based in part upon Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818. That case concerned liability of a golf club for a defamatory note on the golf club notice board. That principle, as it applied in defamation, was analysed with some care by Hunt J of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127. It was concluded that it was necessary for the plaintiff to establish that the defendant had, in fact, accepted responsibility for continued publication by consenting to, approving of, adopting or promoting or in some way ratifying the continued publication. Such accepted responsibility could be established by inference. That case involved someone else's defamatory statement being attached to the defendant's property. (See also Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042 and Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248 . )</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd [2001] QB 201, [1999] 4 All ER 342; [2000] 3 WLR 1020</tocase>
<text>27 The applicant submits that the decision in Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd [2001] QB 201, [1999] 4 All ER 342; [2000] 3 WLR 1020 should be applied. In that case, the defendants carried on business as an Internet Service Provider and received and stored on their news server an article, defamatory of the plaintiff, which had been posted by an unknown person using another service provider. The plaintiff informed the defendants that the article was defamatory and asked them to remove it from their news server. They failed to do so and it remained available for some 10 days until its automatic expiry. It was held that the defendants were liable at common law as the publisher of the posting they were not merely the passive owner of an electronic device through which postings were transmitted but actively chose to receive and store the news group exchanges containing the posting which could be accessed by their subscribers and could have chosen to obliterate the posting complained of, as they later did. The critical portion of the judgment was as follows ([2001] QB at 208 209):
 
 "In my judgment the defendants, whenever they transmit and whenever there is transmitted from the storage of their news server a defamatory posting, publish that posting to any subscriber to their ISP who accesses the newsgroup containing that posting. Thus every time one of the defendants' customers accesses soc.culture.thai and sees that posting defamatory of the plaintiff there is a publication to that customer. 
 The situation is analogous to that of the bookseller who sells a book defamatory of the plaintiff: see Weldon v 'The Times' Book Co. Ltd (1911) 28 TLR 143 (the case about the books on Gounod); to that of the circulating library who provided books to subscribers: see Vizetelly v Mudie's Select Library Ltd [1900] 2 QB 170 (the case about the book on Stanley's search for Emin Pasha in Africa: see in particular the judgment of Romer LJ pages 178 181); and to that of distributors: see Bottomley v FW Woolworth &amp; Co Ltd (1932) 48 TLR 521 (the case about the article in Detective Story Magazine headed 'Swindlers and Scoundrels. Horatio Bottomley, Editor and Embezzler') and Sun Life Assurance Co of Canada v WH Smith &amp; Son Ltd (1933) 150 LT 211 (the case about newspaper posters announcing 'More grave Sun Life of Canada disclosures'). I do not accept Mr Barca's argument that the defendants were merely owners of an electronic device through which postings were transmitted. The defendants chose to store soc.culture.thai postings within their computers. Such postings could be accessed on that newsgroup. The defendants could obliterate and indeed did so about a fortnight after receipt."

29 In Kaplan v Go Daddy Group [2005] NSWSC 636 White J, in an interlocutory decision, speaking of comments disparaging of a business posted on a website said (at [32] [33]):
 
 "There is also a serious question to be tried that he was the author of the other headings and comments on the site to which I have referred. 
 Even if he was not the author of those headings and comments, there is still a serious question to be tried as to whether he published the statements which appeared on the site. He established the site and thereby invited disparaging comments. He maintained some control over the site. He said that he, along with anyone else, could remove any of the comments from the site. The extent of his control over what was, or was not, published, was not fully explored, but it is seriously arguable that he was at least as much in control of the site and responsible for what appeared on it as was the internet service provider in Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd [2001] QB 201 ; [1999] 4 All ER 342, or the proprietors and secretary of a golf club which allowed a defamatory statement to remain on a notice board in Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818; 2 All ER 204. In Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd , it was held that an internet service provider was a publisher at common law of the defamatory comments posted on the site by an unknown user."

31 It was held in Bunt v Tilley [2006] 3 All ER 336; [2006] EWHC 407 (QB) that an Internet service provider that performed no more than a passive role in facilitating postings on the Internet and did not "host" the relevant website was not deemed to be a publisher at common law any more than a telephone company would be liable for defamation over the telephone. Godfrey [2001] QB 201 was distinguished.

32 The ability to prevent publication or the continuance of publication in the context of defamation as applied in Godfrey [2001] QB 201was based in part upon Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818. That case concerned liability of a golf club for a defamatory note on the golf club notice board. That principle, as it applied in defamation, was analysed with some care by Hunt J of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127. It was concluded that it was necessary for the plaintiff to establish that the defendant had, in fact, accepted responsibility for continued publication by consenting to, approving of, adopting or promoting or in some way ratifying the continued publication. Such accepted responsibility could be established by inference. That case involved someone else's defamatory statement being attached to the defendant's property. (See also Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042 and Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248 . )</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hagan v Trustees of Toowoomba Sports Grounds Trust [2000] FCA 1615</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1615.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The test or standard in s 18C(1)(a) of the Act is objective: see Jones v Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at 268-269; Hagan v Trustees of Toowoomba Sports Grounds Trust [2000] FCA 1615 ; Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352 at [12] . It is for the Court to determine whether the act, in all the circumstances in which it was done, would be reasonably likely to offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate another person or a group of people of a particular racial, national or ethnic group: see Hagan [2000] FCA 1615 at [15] . As Hely J remarked in Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at [99] : 
 
 "it is not necessary for an applicant to prove that any person was actually offended, insulted, humiliated or intimidated by the conduct in question ... [but] evidence, for example, that a member of a particular racial group was offended by the conduct in question would be admissible, on, but not determinative of, the issue of contravention."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/55.html</AustLII>
<text>19 At all material times, the Messages on the Forum were able to be downloaded and received by any member of the public without restriction. The uploading or posting of the Messages by the second respondent was an act of publication done by him. Branson J held in Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 , (2002) 71 ALD 629 at [73] [75] that:
 
 "the act of placing text and graphics on a website which is not password protected is an act of publication, or perhaps more accurately an act which causes repeated publications, in that it allows individuals to access the website with a browser to read that text and see those graphics." 
 

That was unaffected by the appeal ( Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515). That act plainly caused words to be communicated to the public within s 18C(2)(a) and so was not in private. (See also Conti J in Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 , (2002) 71 ALD 629</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/1150.html</AustLII>
<text>19 At all material times, the Messages on the Forum were able to be downloaded and received by any member of the public without restriction. The uploading or posting of the Messages by the second respondent was an act of publication done by him. Branson J held in Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 , (2002) 71 ALD 629 at [73] [75] that:
 
 "the act of placing text and graphics on a website which is not password protected is an act of publication, or perhaps more accurately an act which causes repeated publications, in that it allows individuals to access the website with a browser to read that text and see those graphics." 
 

That was unaffected by the appeal ( Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515). That act plainly caused words to be communicated to the public within s 18C(2)(a) and so was not in private. (See also Conti J in Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jones v Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2001) 120 FCR 243</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/1080.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The test or standard in s 18C(1)(a) of the Act is objective: see Jones v Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at 268-269; Hagan v Trustees of Toowoomba Sports Grounds Trust [2000] FCA 1615 ; Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352 at [12] . It is for the Court to determine whether the act, in all the circumstances in which it was done, would be reasonably likely to offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate another person or a group of people of a particular racial, national or ethnic group: see Hagan [2000] FCA 1615 at [15] . As Hely J remarked in Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 at [99] : 
 
 "it is not necessary for an applicant to prove that any person was actually offended, insulted, humiliated or intimidated by the conduct in question ... [but] evidence, for example, that a member of a particular racial group was offended by the conduct in question would be admissible, on, but not determinative of, the issue of contravention."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kaplan v Go Daddy Group [2005] NSWSC 636</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2005/636.html</AustLII>
<text>29 In Kaplan v Go Daddy Group [2005] NSWSC 636 White J, in an interlocutory decision, speaking of comments disparaging of a business posted on a website said (at [32] [33]):
 
 "There is also a serious question to be tried that he was the author of the other headings and comments on the site to which I have referred. 
 Even if he was not the author of those headings and comments, there is still a serious question to be tried as to whether he published the statements which appeared on the site. He established the site and thereby invited disparaging comments. He maintained some control over the site. He said that he, along with anyone else, could remove any of the comments from the site. The extent of his control over what was, or was not, published, was not fully explored, but it is seriously arguable that he was at least as much in control of the site and responsible for what appeared on it as was the internet service provider in Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd [2001] QB 201 ; [1999] 4 All ER 342, or the proprietors and secretary of a golf club which allowed a defamatory statement to remain on a notice board in Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818; 2 All ER 204. In Godfrey v Demon Internet Ltd , it was held that an internet service provider was a publisher at common law of the defamatory comments posted on the site by an unknown user."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Thompson v Australian Capital Television [1996] HCA 38 ; (1996) 186 CLR 574</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/38.html</AustLII>
<text>33 The discussion by the High Court in Thompson v Australian Capital Television [1996] HCA 38 ; (1996) 186 CLR 574 of subordinate dissemination is of particular interest (see Brennan CJ, Dawson and Toohey JJ at 585 590, Gaudron J at 591 596 and Gummow J at 617 620). That case concerned the liability of a television station that took to air a direct "feed" of a live current affairs show from another television station. The argument that it was a mere conduit failed. Emphasis was placed upon the choice made by that station to take a live current affairs program likely, to be controversial, directly to air without any editing or scrutiny. For an earlier, brave but unsuccessful, attempt to argue that a television station which puts a debate to air is not responsible for statements by participants see Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Comalco Ltd (1986) 12 FCR 510.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/137.html</AustLII>
<text>19 At all material times, the Messages on the Forum were able to be downloaded and received by any member of the public without restriction. The uploading or posting of the Messages by the second respondent was an act of publication done by him. Branson J held in Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 , (2002) 71 ALD 629 at [73] [75] that:
 
 "the act of placing text and graphics on a website which is not password protected is an act of publication, or perhaps more accurately an act which causes repeated publications, in that it allows individuals to access the website with a browser to read that text and see those graphics." 
 

That was unaffected by the appeal ( Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515). That act plainly caused words to be communicated to the public within s 18C(2)(a) and so was not in private. (See also Conti J in Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia v Cooper Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/972.html</AustLII>
<text>30 Universal Music Australia v Cooper Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1 dealt with infringement of copyright. The principal claims were based on infringement of copyright by a website that facilitated the free downloading of certain sound recordings. The first respondent was the registered owner and operator of the website. It contained hyperlinks to thousands of sound recordings which were located on remote websites and downloaded directly from those websites to the computer of the Internet user. The music file was not sent to, downloaded on, transmitted through or saved to the first respondent's website. The second to fifth respondents hosted the website and were responsible for maintaining the connection to the Internet. They were unaware of the contents of the website and took no steps to inform themselves of that content. Tamberlin J held that the first respondent infringed copyright by authorising the infringing acts of Internet users who accessed the website and the owners or operators of the remote website from which the infringing recordings were downloaded. He permitted and approved the infringements and had sufficient control over his website to prevent the infringements (150 FCR 1 at [77] [102]). The second to fifth respondents infringed the copyright by authorising the infringing acts (150 FCR 1 at [103] [132]). They had an active role in relation to the website, were aware of the content of the website and had the power to prevent the infringing acts. Those findings were substantially upheld on appeal, although an employee of the Internet service provider was let out ( Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 187 ; (2006) 156 FCR 380 particularly per Branson J at [28] [52], [61] [65] and Kenny J at [136] [165]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127</tocase>
<text>32 The ability to prevent publication or the continuance of publication in the context of defamation as applied in Godfrey [2001] QB 201was based in part upon Byrne v Deane [1937] 1 KB 818. That case concerned liability of a golf club for a defamatory note on the golf club notice board. That principle, as it applied in defamation, was analysed with some care by Hunt J of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Urbanchich v Drummoyne Municipal Council (1991) Aust Torts Reports 81-127. It was concluded that it was necessary for the plaintiff to establish that the defendant had, in fact, accepted responsibility for continued publication by consenting to, approving of, adopting or promoting or in some way ratifying the continued publication. Such accepted responsibility could be established by inference. That case involved someone else's defamatory statement being attached to the defendant's property. (See also Bishop v State of New South Wales [2000] NSWSC 1042 and Frawley v State of New South Wales [2006] NSWSC 248 . )</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>