<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Liquor, Hospitality Miscellaneous Union, Liquor &amp; Hospitality Division, NSW Branch on behalf of its Member, Wayne Roberts v Woonona Bulli RSL Memorial Club Limited [2007] FCA 1460 (18 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1460.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Industrial Commission of South Australia; ex parte Adelaide Milk Supply Co-op Ltd (1977) 16 SASR 6</tocase>
<text>25 Once the new positions of Sous Chef and Chef de Partie had been filled, I am satisfied that the employer no longer required the job previously undertaken by Mr Roberts as Level 5 Supervisor to be done by anyone. Mr Roberts' position had become redundant ( R v Industrial Commission of South Australia; ex parte Adelaide Milk Supply Co-op Ltd (1977) 16 SASR 6 per Bray CJ at 8). However, Mr Roberts was unwilling to give up the position of Level 5 Supervisor. It seems likely that he did not understand that continuing in that position was not an option open to him.

26 The salary that was to be paid to the holder of the position of Chef was less than Mr Roberts was earning in the position of Level 5 Supervisor. Mr Roberts acknowledged that after he was offered the position of Chef on 10 October 2006 he spoke with Mr Osborne and expressed concern about the position's salary but not the need to sign an AWA. I accept that Mr Roberts was unwilling to sign an AWA that provided for an annual salary of $35,000 per annum. However, I am satisfied that he would not have accepted the Chef's position on that salary even if he were not required to sign an AWA.

27 I conclude that the only reasons why Mr Roberts' employment by the Club was terminated were that his position of Level 5 Supervisor became redundant following the implementation of the catering division's restructure and he was unwilling to accept the lower paid position of Chef. The Club has therefore proved that the termination was for reasons that do not include a proscribed reason (s 664 of the Act).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>