<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Termite Tite (NZ) No 2 Limited v Term-Seal (Aust) Pty Limited [2007] FCA 1493 (28 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1493.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Allsop Inc v Bintang Ltd (1989) 15 IPR 689</tocase>
<text>144 An appropriate starting point is the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Allsop Inc v Bintang Ltd (1989) 15 IPR 686. After referring to the fact that there must be an inventive step, although it can be a small one, and the fact that the cases time and again have warned against the "seductive clarity of hindsight", the Court said (at 701):
 
 "But although a simple idea may be inventive, it is essential for validity that there be inventiveness. Though small, it must be present. As was said in Graham v John Deere Co, supra, at 15, there is a 'requirement that the subject matter sought to be patented must be beyond the skill of the calling'. The question, as Lord Herschell said in Vickers, Sons &amp; Co Ltd v Siddell [1890] 15 App Cas 496 at 502 is whether the subject of the patent 'was so obvious that it would at once occur to anyone acquainted with the subject, and desirous of accomplishing the end, or whether it required some invention to devise it'. In R D Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1989) 13 IPR 513 at 523; 85 ALR 679 at 689, Lockhart J said: 'There must ... be some difficulty overcome, some barrier crossed'. He cited a dictum of Cotton LJ that 'it must be a question of whether there is sufficient invention to justify a monopoly being granted by the Crown in the particular thing'.
 
 When the principles which surround that question have been stated, the question itself remains one of fact involving an evaluation of the claimed invention in the light of the evidence. It has been described as a 'jury question': Wellcome Foundation case at (CLR) 280."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bristol-Myers v F H Faulding [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/316.html</AustLII>
<text>99 In Bristol-Myers v F H Faulding [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at 546, Black CJ and Lehane J considered the case in which the anticipation was a paper anticipation. Their Honours referred with approval to the following passage from the speech of Lord Westbury in Hill v Evans (1862) 4 De G F &amp; J 288; 45 ER 1195:
 
 "The question then is, what must be the nature of the antecedent statement? I apprehend that the principle is correctly thus expressed: -- the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand, and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful. If something remains to be ascertained which is necessary for the useful application of the discovery, that affords sufficient room for another valid patent.
 ...
 The invention must be shewn to have been before made known. Whatever, therefore, is essential to the invention must be read out of the prior publication. If specific details are necessary for the practical working and real utility of the alleged invention, they must be found substantially in the prior publication. 
 
 Apparent generality, or a proposition not true to its full extent, will not prejudice a subsequent statement which is limited and accurate, and gives a specific rule of practical application. 
 
 The reason is manifest, because much further information, and therefore much further discovery, are required before the real truth can be extricated and embodied in a form to serve the use of mankind. It is the difference between the ore and the refined and pure metal which is extracted from it. 
 
 Again, it is not, in my opinion, true in these cases to say, that knowledge, and the means of obtaining knowledge, are the same. There is a great difference between them. To carry me to the place at which I wish to arrive is very different from merely putting me on the road that leads to it. There may be a latent truth in the words of a former writer, not known even to the writer himself; and it would be unreasonable to say that there is no merit in discovering and unfolding it to the world. 
 
 Upon principle, therefore, I conclude that the prior knowledge of an invention to avoid a patent must be knowledge equal to that required to be given by a specification, namely, such knowledge as will enable the public to perceive the very discovery, and to carry the invention into practical use."
 

Black CJ and Lehane J, after referring to more recent authorities, said (at 548 [67]):
 
 "What all those authorities contemplate, in our view, is that a prior publication, if it is to destroy novelty, must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention. A direction, recommendation or suggestion may often, of course, be implicit in what is described and commonly the only question may be whether the publication describes with sufficient clarity the claimed invention or, in the case of a combination, each integer of it."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Patents v Emperor Sports Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 26 ; (2006) 149 FCR 386</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/26.html</AustLII>
<text>50 The re-examination procedure under Chapter 9 of the Act was discussed by Lindgren J in Emperor Sports v Commissioner of Sports [2005] FCA 996 ; (2005) 146 FCR 159 (" Emperor Sports ") and then on appeal by the Full Court of this Court: Commissioner of Patents v Emperor Sports Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 26 ; (2006) 149 FCR 386. The particular facts of that case were different from those in this case in that in Emperor Sports the Commissioner of Patents was asked to re-examine a complete specification under s 97(2) of the Act . She did so and she decided to revoke the patent. The patentee appealed against the Commissioner's decision under s 101(4) of the Act . Lindgren J allowed the appeal. He referred to the purpose of the re-examination provisions. In that context he referred to the report dated 29 August 1984 of the Industrial Property Advisory Committee, "Patents, Innovation and Competition in Australia" to the Minister for Science and Technology, and relating to the introduction of post-grant re-examination. He referred to the position in the United States and in that context he referred to a statement in Congress (HR Rep No 96-1307 at 3-4) on the purpose of the re-examining statute (35 USC SS302) (at [104]-[105]). Speaking generally, it seems that the re-examining procedure enables a party to utilise the expertise of the Patent Office to decide appropriate questions with a view, if possible, to avoiding the expense of legal proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Elconnex Pty Ltd v Gerard Industries Pty Ltd (1991) 32 FCR 491</tocase>
<text>139 In this case there is no information which falls within the terms of s 7(3). None of the witnesses who gave evidence relevant to the question of obviousness identified prior art information, either a single piece or a combination, which they said a person skilled in the relevant art could before 21 December 1998 (that is, the priority date of the Patent) be reasonably expected to have ascertained, understood and regarded as relevant (or, in an appropriate case, combined). In those circumstances it is not necessary to consider the extent of the relaxation of the rules under the repealed s 100(1)(c) of the Patents Act 1952 (Cth) effected by s 7(3): Elconnex Pty Ltd v Gerard Industries Pty Ltd (1991) 32 FCR 491 (" Elconnex "); Tidy Tea Ltd v Unilever Australia Pty Ltd (1995) 32 IPR 405 (" Tidy Tea "); Firebelt Pty Ltd v Brambles Australia Ltd (t/as Cleanaway) [2002] HCA 21 ; (2002) 76 ALJR 816 at 821-823 [31] - [36] (" Firebelt ").

142 The attributes of the person skilled in the relevant art for the purposes of s 7(2) have been referred to in a number of authorities. For present purposes it is enough to say that the hypothetical worker must be taken to be non-inventive, although skilled in the relevant art. By reason of the conditions which prevail in modern industry, he or she may be part of a sophisticated research team, with a great amount of information available to it ( Wellcome Foundation Ltd v VR Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262 at 270 per Aickin J (with whom the other members of the Court agreed); Elconnex at 507 per Burchett J).

145 In Elconnex , Burchett J said (at 507):
 
 "While the hypothetical skilled worker, against whose efforts the claimed invention is to be tested, may be taken to have extensive knowledge, he must be uninventive. Even a small inventive element is sufficient to sustain a patent. However, there is a great difference between the simple idea which really breaks new ground and an unimaginative extension of well-known techniques into a closely similar area. Of course, if the area is not closely similar, so that an imaginative leap (even perhaps a small one) is required to perceive that the techniques are applicable to it, there will be invention."
 

(See also Tidy Tea at 413-415.)

The particular question of the test of obviousness when faced with a patent involving what is said to be a new combination made up of old integers was discussed by Aickin J in Minnesota Mining . His Honour said (at 293):
 
 "In the case of alleged lack of an inventive step the question of making a mosaic must operate (if at all) in a very different matter. An allegation of want of inventive step is not made out by saying you may take one or two, or twenty-one or twenty-two, prior publications and then select from them appropriate extracts or pieces of information, which will add up to the invention claimed and so demonstrate that it was obvious. So to proceed is to mistake the nature of an invention and the nature of the objection of obviousness. The question is, is the invention itself obvious, not whether a diligent searcher might find pieces from which there might have been selected the elements which make up the patent. If this were not so, there could never be a valid patent for a new combination of old integers. The proper question is not whether it would have been obvious to the hypothetical addressee who was presented with an ex post facto selection of prior specifications that elements from them could be combined to produce a new product or process. It is rather whether it would have been obvious to a non-inventive skilled worker in the field to select from a possibly very large range of publications the particular combination subsequently chosen by the opponent in the glare of hindsight and also whether it would have been obvious to that worker to select the particular combination of integers from those selected publications. In the case of a combination patent the invention will lie in the selection of integers, a process which will necessarily involve rejection of other possible integers. The prior existence of publications revealing those integers, as separate items, and other possible integers does not of itself make an alleged invention obvious. It is the selection of the integers out of, perhaps many possibilities, which must be shown to be obvious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Emperor Sports v Commissioner of Sports [2005] FCA 996 ; (2005) 146 FCR 159</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/996.html</AustLII>
<text>50 The re-examination procedure under Chapter 9 of the Act was discussed by Lindgren J in Emperor Sports v Commissioner of Sports [2005] FCA 996 ; (2005) 146 FCR 159 (" Emperor Sports ") and then on appeal by the Full Court of this Court: Commissioner of Patents v Emperor Sports Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 26 ; (2006) 149 FCR 386. The particular facts of that case were different from those in this case in that in Emperor Sports the Commissioner of Patents was asked to re-examine a complete specification under s 97(2) of the Act . She did so and she decided to revoke the patent. The patentee appealed against the Commissioner's decision under s 101(4) of the Act . Lindgren J allowed the appeal. He referred to the purpose of the re-examination provisions. In that context he referred to the report dated 29 August 1984 of the Industrial Property Advisory Committee, "Patents, Innovation and Competition in Australia" to the Minister for Science and Technology, and relating to the introduction of post-grant re-examination. He referred to the position in the United States and in that context he referred to a statement in Congress (HR Rep No 96-1307 at 3-4) on the purpose of the re-examining statute (35 USC SS302) (at [104]-[105]). Speaking generally, it seems that the re-examining procedure enables a party to utilise the expertise of the Patent Office to decide appropriate questions with a view, if possible, to avoiding the expense of legal proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Firebelt Pty Ltd v Brambles Australia Ltd (t/as Cleanaway ) [2002] HCA 21 ; (2002) 76 ALJR 816</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/21.html</AustLII>
<text>139 In this case there is no information which falls within the terms of s 7(3). None of the witnesses who gave evidence relevant to the question of obviousness identified prior art information, either a single piece or a combination, which they said a person skilled in the relevant art could before 21 December 1998 (that is, the priority date of the Patent) be reasonably expected to have ascertained, understood and regarded as relevant (or, in an appropriate case, combined). In those circumstances it is not necessary to consider the extent of the relaxation of the rules under the repealed s 100(1)(c) of the Patents Act 1952 (Cth) effected by s 7(3): Elconnex Pty Ltd v Gerard Industries Pty Ltd (1991) 32 FCR 491 (" Elconnex "); Tidy Tea Ltd v Unilever Australia Pty Ltd (1995) 32 IPR 405 (" Tidy Tea "); Firebelt Pty Ltd v Brambles Australia Ltd (t/as Cleanaway) [2002] HCA 21 ; (2002) 76 ALJR 816 at 821-823 [31] - [36] (" Firebelt ").

146 Part of the above passage was cited with approval by the High Court in Firebelt at [21]. See also Aktiebolagett H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm [2002] HCA 59 ; (2002) 212 CLR 411, at 421-432 [42]-[49] (Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, Gummow and Hayne JJ).

147 I turn now to apply these principles to the facts.

148 Mr Langley gave the clearest and most concise evidence as to what was the common general knowledge in the relevant art before the priority date. The facts I now set out are based on his evidence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>General Tire and Rubber Company v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Company Limited [1972] RPC 457</tocase>
<text>100 In the well known case of General Tire and Rubber Company v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Company Limited [1972] RPC 457 (" General Tire "), the Court of Appeal said (at 486):
 
 "If, on the other hand, the prior publication contains a direction which is capable of being carried out in a manner which would infringe the patentee's claim, but would be at least as likely to be carried out in a way which would not do so, the patentee's claim will not have been anticipated, although it may fail on the ground of obviousness. To anticipate the patentee's claim the prior publication must contain clear and unmistakeable directions to do what the patentee claims to have invented: Flour Oxidizing Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd ((1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457, line 34, approved in B T H Co Ltd v Metropolitan Vickers Electrical Co Ltd (1928) 45 R P C 1 at 24, line 1). A signpost, however clear, upon the road to the patentee's invention will not suffice. The prior inventor must be clearly shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee."

101 In ICI Chemicals v Lubrizol Corporation Inc [2000] FCA 1349 ; (2000) 106 FCR 214, the Full Court of this Court (Lee, Heerey and Lehane JJ) referred to the metaphor involving the flag and said (at 230 [51]):
 
 "In those circumstances, and in the absence of relevant expert evidence, we think that the primary judge was correct to conclude that Williamitis did not anticipate the claims of the patent in suit. A familiar metaphor illustrating the concept of anticipation is that the prior inventor must clearly be shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee: General Tire at 485-486. In the present case, the appellants' argument involved the skilled addressee rummaging through the Williamitis flag locker to find a flag which Williamitis possessed and could have planted."

115 A number of witnesses gave evidence as to whether the claims in the Patent were novel in light of the prior art referred to above. The construction of documents is for the Court but it seems clear that if appropriate the Court can be assisted by a person skilled in the relevant art at the relevant date. In General Tire the Court of Appeal said (at 485):
 
 "The earlier publication and the patentee's claim must each be construed as they would be at the respective relevant dates by a reader skilled in the art to which they relate having regard to the state of knowledge in such art at the relevant date. The construction of these documents is a function of the court, being a matter of law, but, since documents of this nature are almost certain to contain technical material, the court must, by evidence, be put in the position of a person of the kind to whom the document is addressed, that is to say, a person skilled in the relevant art at the relevant date."

116 In his second affidavit Dr Franklin expressed the opinion that the Patent lacks novelty or inventiveness having regard to prior art and he refers to the Kennedy and Hitchen patent, the Ogawa patent, a patent called the Kordon patent, the Groom patent and the Sapsford patent. He also expressed the opinion that the patent is not useful. The applicants submitted that I should not receive Dr Franklin's second affidavit. He had not complied with the practice note relevant to experts' reports and, moreover, he would be giving expert evidence in a case in which he was a party. I would waive compliance with the practice note. The applicants have had an adequate opportunity to respond to Dr Franklin's affidavit. As to the other point raised by the applicants, unless it is a particularly serious case of bias which might enliven the discretion to exclude, the fact that Dr Franklin is a party goes to the weight to be accorded to his evidence, not the admissibility of the evidence: J D Heydon, Cross on Evidence (7 th Australian ed, 2004) (at [29080]) and cases cited therein; Ian Freckelton and Hugh Selby, Expert Evidence (3 rd ed, 2005) (at 26 and 315-16) and cases cited therein.

117 Dr Franklin's area of expertise is chemistry, although I accept that he has acquired some knowledge of termite barrier systems by reason of his association with Mr Hannay. He had never installed a termite barrier system either physical or chemical or both before the priority date. It seems that he received the prior art from Mr Geoffrey Habel, an experienced patent and trademark attorney, and it is likely he has been influenced by his discussion with Mr Habel about the prior art. I am not suggesting that there is anything improper about that; simply that it is unlikely he has any real expertise in the interpretation of the prior art. In those circumstances, I do not think Dr Franklin's evidence as to a lack of novelty because of prior art is of any assistance. As to lack of an inventive step or obviousness his evidence is of no assistance because it relies on material (that is, paper anticipations) which, for reasons I will give, was not part of general common knowledge within s 7(2) of the Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hill v Evans (1862) 4 De G F &amp; J 288</tocase>
<text>99 In Bristol-Myers v F H Faulding [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at 546, Black CJ and Lehane J considered the case in which the anticipation was a paper anticipation. Their Honours referred with approval to the following passage from the speech of Lord Westbury in Hill v Evans (1862) 4 De G F &amp; J 288; 45 ER 1195:
 
 "The question then is, what must be the nature of the antecedent statement? I apprehend that the principle is correctly thus expressed: -- the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand, and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful. If something remains to be ascertained which is necessary for the useful application of the discovery, that affords sufficient room for another valid patent.
 ...
 The invention must be shewn to have been before made known. Whatever, therefore, is essential to the invention must be read out of the prior publication. If specific details are necessary for the practical working and real utility of the alleged invention, they must be found substantially in the prior publication. 
 
 Apparent generality, or a proposition not true to its full extent, will not prejudice a subsequent statement which is limited and accurate, and gives a specific rule of practical application. 
 
 The reason is manifest, because much further information, and therefore much further discovery, are required before the real truth can be extricated and embodied in a form to serve the use of mankind. It is the difference between the ore and the refined and pure metal which is extracted from it. 
 
 Again, it is not, in my opinion, true in these cases to say, that knowledge, and the means of obtaining knowledge, are the same. There is a great difference between them. To carry me to the place at which I wish to arrive is very different from merely putting me on the road that leads to it. There may be a latent truth in the words of a former writer, not known even to the writer himself; and it would be unreasonable to say that there is no merit in discovering and unfolding it to the world. 
 
 Upon principle, therefore, I conclude that the prior knowledge of an invention to avoid a patent must be knowledge equal to that required to be given by a specification, namely, such knowledge as will enable the public to perceive the very discovery, and to carry the invention into practical use."
 

Black CJ and Lehane J, after referring to more recent authorities, said (at 548 [67]):
 
 "What all those authorities contemplate, in our view, is that a prior publication, if it is to destroy novelty, must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention. A direction, recommendation or suggestion may often, of course, be implicit in what is described and commonly the only question may be whether the publication describes with sufficient clarity the claimed invention or, in the case of a combination, each integer of it."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>ICI Chemicals v Lubrizol Corporation Inc [2000] FCA 1349 ; (2000) 106 FCR 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1349.html</AustLII>
<text>101 In ICI Chemicals v Lubrizol Corporation Inc [2000] FCA 1349 ; (2000) 106 FCR 214, the Full Court of this Court (Lee, Heerey and Lehane JJ) referred to the metaphor involving the flag and said (at 230 [51]):
 
 "In those circumstances, and in the absence of relevant expert evidence, we think that the primary judge was correct to conclude that Williamitis did not anticipate the claims of the patent in suit. A familiar metaphor illustrating the concept of anticipation is that the prior inventor must clearly be shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee: General Tire at 485-486. In the present case, the appellants' argument involved the skilled addressee rummaging through the Williamitis flag locker to find a flag which Williamitis possessed and could have planted."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kanzal v Lee [1936] HCA 39 ; (1936) 58 CLR 670</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/39.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Claims 1 and 2 are each claims for a combination. Each claim consists of a number of integers no one of which was not known at the priority date. However, the applicants submit that they are so arranged and related that they work together to produce a single result or a new thing. In Kanzal v Lee [1936] HCA 39 ; (1936) 58 CLR 670 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said (at 687):
 
 "Although the principles relied upon are old and simple and the features, separately considered, are used in daily practice for all sorts of purposes, the production of a new implement by their judicious use may involve an inventive step or display inventive ingenuity, if the integers are so combined and related that they work in co-operation to effect a purpose or provide an appliance which is new . "
 

See also Palmer v Dunlop Perdriau Rubber Company Limited [1937] HCA 43 ; (1937) 59 CLR 30 and Sunbeam Corporation v Morphy Richards (Aust) Pty Ltd [1961] HCA 39 ; (1961) 180 CLR 98 (" Sunbeam Corporation ") at 101 per Windeyer J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Martin Engineering v Trison Holdings (1989) 14 IPR 330</tocase>
<text>163 I have already discussed the relationship between claims 1 and 2 on the one hand and claim 4 on the other (see [86]-[88] above). As a matter of construction, the claims cover a termite resistant product which is a liquid on impregnation and which becomes a solid thereafter. In those circumstances, the argument that the invention is not useful must fail. Had I construed claims 1 and 2 to include a termite resisting product which was in liquid form on impregnation and in a solid or liquid form thereafter then a real question of utility would have arisen ( Norton and Gregory Ltd v Jacobs (1937) 54 RPC 271; Martin Engineering v Trison Holdings (1989) 14 IPR 330 at 337 per Burchett J). However, I would wish to make two points in connexion with that. First, such resulting inutility would be a reason not to construe claims 1 and 2 in that fashion, when the construction not resulting in inutility, which I have adopted, is open: Welch Perrin Co Pty Ltd v Worrel [1960] HCA 91 ; (1961) 106 CLR 588 at 602 per Menzies J. Secondly, it is not to be assumed that had it been necessary to deal with the question, inutility would have been made out on the facts. The respondents bore the onus on the issue of utility and there was no evidence before me as to types of liquid, evaporation rates and atmospheric conditions in the cavity. In the circumstances, it is not necessary for me to resolve that issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Meyers Taylor Pty Ltd v Vicarr Industries Ltd [1977] HCA 19 ; (1977) 137 CLR 228</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/19.html</AustLII>
<text>98 It is well-established that the basic test for anticipation or want of novelty is the same as that for infringement and "one can properly ask oneself whether the alleged anticipation would if the patent were valid, constitute an infringement": Meyers Taylor Pty Ltd v Vicarr Industries Ltd [1977] HCA 19 ; (1977) 137 CLR 228 at 235 per Aickin J. In that case his Honour said that as no prior document or object involved or incorporated all the integers of any one of the claims there could not possibly be an infringement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Australia) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/9.html</AustLII>
<text>92 The Term-Seal FRM also contains the additional two integers in claim 5. The matting is fabricated from natural or artificial fibres. Dr Fredericks examined the samples and he concluded that the matting was fabricated into "a non-woven mat from synthetic (artificial) fibres". As to the second integer, I agree with counsel for the applicants that when the fibres are teased out it is apparent that long fibres have been woven into the fabric. It is permissible for me to draw conclusions from my own inspection of the alleged infringing product: Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Australia) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 (" Minnesota Mining ").

93 The Term-Seal FRM also contains the additional integer identified in claim 6, namely, that the matting is woven fiberglass, polyester or polyethylene wadding, or geofabric. I accept the opinion of Dr Fredericks that the matting of the Term-Seal FRM can properly be described as such and, in particular, as polyester wadding or as geofabric.

94 The Term-Seal FRM also contains the additional integer identified in claim 9, namely, that the termite resisting product additionally includes a water-proofing compound, other additives and/or diluents. Dr Fredericks said, and I accept, that the Term-Seal Multi-Purpose largely comprises an acrylic resin (a polymer) which will, when cured, be waterproof. The Term-Seal Multi-Purpose does not contain as additives, creosote or orminoid, as referred to in claim 10, but the applicants do not allege an infringement of claim 10 and there is no reason to read down claim 9 by reference to claim 10. Claim 10 is a later claim with additional integers.

140 It follows from the above that the knowledge which is to be attributed to the person skilled in the relevant art is the "common general knowledge". That does not include a specification open for public inspection unless there is evidence that the disclosure in question was part of the common general knowledge before the priority date. Aickin J (with whom the other members of the Court agreed) made that point in Minnesota Mining . In this case there is no evidence that any of the prior disclosures identified for the purposes of the submissions as to novelty were part of the common general knowledge before the priority date. Indeed, Mr Christopher Langley, who I considered an impressive witness on the question of obviousness, had not seen many of the disclosures put to him in cross-examination before he began to prepare for this litigation. None of the prior disclosures advanced on the case as to novelty are relevant as such on the case as to obviousness because they are not part of the common general knowledge.

141 The common general knowledge is what is known or used by those in the relevant trade or field of endeavour. In Minnesota Mining , Aickin J said (at 292):
 
 "It forms the background knowledge and experience which is available to all in the trade in considering the making of new products, or the making of improvements in old, and it must be treated as being used by an individual as a general body of knowledge."

145 In Elconnex , Burchett J said (at 507):
 
 "While the hypothetical skilled worker, against whose efforts the claimed invention is to be tested, may be taken to have extensive knowledge, he must be uninventive. Even a small inventive element is sufficient to sustain a patent. However, there is a great difference between the simple idea which really breaks new ground and an unimaginative extension of well-known techniques into a closely similar area. Of course, if the area is not closely similar, so that an imaginative leap (even perhaps a small one) is required to perceive that the techniques are applicable to it, there will be invention."
 

(See also Tidy Tea at 413-415.)

The particular question of the test of obviousness when faced with a patent involving what is said to be a new combination made up of old integers was discussed by Aickin J in Minnesota Mining . His Honour said (at 293):
 
 "In the case of alleged lack of an inventive step the question of making a mosaic must operate (if at all) in a very different matter. An allegation of want of inventive step is not made out by saying you may take one or two, or twenty-one or twenty-two, prior publications and then select from them appropriate extracts or pieces of information, which will add up to the invention claimed and so demonstrate that it was obvious. So to proceed is to mistake the nature of an invention and the nature of the objection of obviousness. The question is, is the invention itself obvious, not whether a diligent searcher might find pieces from which there might have been selected the elements which make up the patent. If this were not so, there could never be a valid patent for a new combination of old integers. The proper question is not whether it would have been obvious to the hypothetical addressee who was presented with an ex post facto selection of prior specifications that elements from them could be combined to produce a new product or process. It is rather whether it would have been obvious to a non-inventive skilled worker in the field to select from a possibly very large range of publications the particular combination subsequently chosen by the opponent in the glare of hindsight and also whether it would have been obvious to that worker to select the particular combination of integers from those selected publications. In the case of a combination patent the invention will lie in the selection of integers, a process which will necessarily involve rejection of other possible integers. The prior existence of publications revealing those integers, as separate items, and other possible integers does not of itself make an alleged invention obvious. It is the selection of the integers out of, perhaps many possibilities, which must be shown to be obvious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Necaro Holdings v Martin Engineering (1990) 16 IPR 545</tocase>
<text>102 In the case of a combination, it is the combination which must be disclosed in the prior specification: Necaro Holdings v Martin Engineering (1990) 16 IPR 545 at 549 per Lockhart J; TA Blanco White Patents for Inventions (5 th ed, 1983) para 4.107.

103 The respondents referred to a number of alleged anticipations but emphasised three in particular. 
 The Kennedy and Hitchen patent (published 22 May 1997)

104 The abstract of this patent is in the following terms:
 
 "A method for preventing or precluding migration of termites or insects through a possible area of migration for example between a concrete slab (13) and a brick wall (28) erected on the slab (13) including the step of applying to a possible area of migration as for example a join line (15) between the slab (13) and wall (28), a settable or curable barrier material which defines a barrier to termite or insect migration through said area. The barrier material may define a physical barrier or may incorporate a chemical to define a chemical barrier. The method may be used also for preventing termite penetration along pipes (19) penetrating a slab (13) by providing beads (68) around the pipe (19) within the slab (13) or at the junction between the pipe (19) and slab (13)."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Norton and Gregory Ltd v Jacobs (1937) 54 RPC 271</tocase>
<text>163 I have already discussed the relationship between claims 1 and 2 on the one hand and claim 4 on the other (see [86]-[88] above). As a matter of construction, the claims cover a termite resistant product which is a liquid on impregnation and which becomes a solid thereafter. In those circumstances, the argument that the invention is not useful must fail. Had I construed claims 1 and 2 to include a termite resisting product which was in liquid form on impregnation and in a solid or liquid form thereafter then a real question of utility would have arisen ( Norton and Gregory Ltd v Jacobs (1937) 54 RPC 271; Martin Engineering v Trison Holdings (1989) 14 IPR 330 at 337 per Burchett J). However, I would wish to make two points in connexion with that. First, such resulting inutility would be a reason not to construe claims 1 and 2 in that fashion, when the construction not resulting in inutility, which I have adopted, is open: Welch Perrin Co Pty Ltd v Worrel [1960] HCA 91 ; (1961) 106 CLR 588 at 602 per Menzies J. Secondly, it is not to be assumed that had it been necessary to deal with the question, inutility would have been made out on the facts. The respondents bore the onus on the issue of utility and there was no evidence before me as to types of liquid, evaporation rates and atmospheric conditions in the cavity. In the circumstances, it is not necessary for me to resolve that issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Palmer v Dunlop Perdriau Rubber Company Limited [1937] HCA 43 ; (1937) 59 CLR 30</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/43.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Claims 1 and 2 are each claims for a combination. Each claim consists of a number of integers no one of which was not known at the priority date. However, the applicants submit that they are so arranged and related that they work together to produce a single result or a new thing. In Kanzal v Lee [1936] HCA 39 ; (1936) 58 CLR 670 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said (at 687):
 
 "Although the principles relied upon are old and simple and the features, separately considered, are used in daily practice for all sorts of purposes, the production of a new implement by their judicious use may involve an inventive step or display inventive ingenuity, if the integers are so combined and related that they work in co-operation to effect a purpose or provide an appliance which is new . "
 

See also Palmer v Dunlop Perdriau Rubber Company Limited [1937] HCA 43 ; (1937) 59 CLR 30 and Sunbeam Corporation v Morphy Richards (Aust) Pty Ltd [1961] HCA 39 ; (1961) 180 CLR 98 (" Sunbeam Corporation ") at 101 per Windeyer J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Radiation Ltd v Galliers and Kleirr Pty Ltd [1938] HCA 17 ; (1938) 60 CLR 36</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/17.html</AustLII>
<text>57 The test for determining if a claim has been infringed by a defendant's product was stated by Dixon J (as his Honour then was) in Radiation Ltd v Galliers and Kleirr Pty Ltd [1938] HCA 17 ; (1938) 60 CLR 36 (at 51-52):
 
 "But, on a question of infringement, the issue is not whether the words of the claim can be applied with verbal accuracy or felicity to the article or device alleged to infringe. It is whether the substantial idea disclosed by the specification and made the subject of a definite claim has been taken and embodied in the infringing thing. It is, no doubt, sometimes the case that an inventor explains in his specification steps or methods involving an idea, conception or principle of wider application or of deeper significance than that for which he claims. Sometimes a claim, particularly a claim for a combination, is expressly confined to a particular form of construction or the like, and in such a case it is useless for the patentee to complain that his idea of what he calls his principle has been applied in a different construction or has been expressed by means of a mechanical equivalent of some element which his claims make of the essence of his monopoly. Such cases are well illustrated by the decisions of this court in Walker v. Alemite Corporation and Shave v. H. V. McKay Massey Harris Pty Ltd But the words of James L.J. in Clark v. Adie, p. 675 must not be forgotten: 'The patent is for the entire combination, but there is, or may be, an essence or substance of the invention underlying the mere accident of form; and that invention, like every other invention, may be pirated by a theft in a disguised or mutilated form, and it will be in every case a question of fact whether the alleged piracy is the same in substance and effect, or is a substantially new or different combination.'"

58 It is necessary at this point to describe the respondents' product, the Term-Seal FRM, in some detail.

59 Pursuant to a notice to produce, samples of the Term-Seal FRM (or fibre re-inforced membrane) were produced and tendered on the hearing before me. The membrane before the application of Term-Seal Multi-Purpose became exhibit A2, three samples of the membrane with the Term-Seal Multi-Purpose applied to it (that is, what I will call the Term-Seal FRM) became exhibits A3, A4 and A5 respectively. The Term-Seal Multi-Purpose in a bucket became exhibit A6 and the same product in a jar became exhibit A7. The "recipe or formula for the Term-Seal Termite Resistant Product which is applied to the Term-Seal FRM" is part of exhibit A1. On occasions the membrane was referred to as the Mopet, which is a brand name.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sunbeam Corporation v Morphy Richards (Aust) Pty Ltd [1961] HCA 39 ; (1961) 180 CLR 98</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1961/39.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Claims 1 and 2 are each claims for a combination. Each claim consists of a number of integers no one of which was not known at the priority date. However, the applicants submit that they are so arranged and related that they work together to produce a single result or a new thing. In Kanzal v Lee [1936] HCA 39 ; (1936) 58 CLR 670 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said (at 687):
 
 "Although the principles relied upon are old and simple and the features, separately considered, are used in daily practice for all sorts of purposes, the production of a new implement by their judicious use may involve an inventive step or display inventive ingenuity, if the integers are so combined and related that they work in co-operation to effect a purpose or provide an appliance which is new . "
 

See also Palmer v Dunlop Perdriau Rubber Company Limited [1937] HCA 43 ; (1937) 59 CLR 30 and Sunbeam Corporation v Morphy Richards (Aust) Pty Ltd [1961] HCA 39 ; (1961) 180 CLR 98 (" Sunbeam Corporation ") at 101 per Windeyer J.

56 The relevant comparison for determining if a claim has been infringed is between the applicants' Patent and the respondents' product. The comparison is not between the applicants' product and the respondents' product: Sunbeam Corporation at 101 per Windeyer J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tidy Tea Ltd v Unilever Australia Pty Ltd (1995) 32 IPR 405</tocase>
<text>139 In this case there is no information which falls within the terms of s 7(3). None of the witnesses who gave evidence relevant to the question of obviousness identified prior art information, either a single piece or a combination, which they said a person skilled in the relevant art could before 21 December 1998 (that is, the priority date of the Patent) be reasonably expected to have ascertained, understood and regarded as relevant (or, in an appropriate case, combined). In those circumstances it is not necessary to consider the extent of the relaxation of the rules under the repealed s 100(1)(c) of the Patents Act 1952 (Cth) effected by s 7(3): Elconnex Pty Ltd v Gerard Industries Pty Ltd (1991) 32 FCR 491 (" Elconnex "); Tidy Tea Ltd v Unilever Australia Pty Ltd (1995) 32 IPR 405 (" Tidy Tea "); Firebelt Pty Ltd v Brambles Australia Ltd (t/as Cleanaway) [2002] HCA 21 ; (2002) 76 ALJR 816 at 821-823 [31] - [36] (" Firebelt ").

145 In Elconnex , Burchett J said (at 507):
 
 "While the hypothetical skilled worker, against whose efforts the claimed invention is to be tested, may be taken to have extensive knowledge, he must be uninventive. Even a small inventive element is sufficient to sustain a patent. However, there is a great difference between the simple idea which really breaks new ground and an unimaginative extension of well-known techniques into a closely similar area. Of course, if the area is not closely similar, so that an imaginative leap (even perhaps a small one) is required to perceive that the techniques are applicable to it, there will be invention."
 

(See also Tidy Tea at 413-415.)

The particular question of the test of obviousness when faced with a patent involving what is said to be a new combination made up of old integers was discussed by Aickin J in Minnesota Mining . His Honour said (at 293):
 
 "In the case of alleged lack of an inventive step the question of making a mosaic must operate (if at all) in a very different matter. An allegation of want of inventive step is not made out by saying you may take one or two, or twenty-one or twenty-two, prior publications and then select from them appropriate extracts or pieces of information, which will add up to the invention claimed and so demonstrate that it was obvious. So to proceed is to mistake the nature of an invention and the nature of the objection of obviousness. The question is, is the invention itself obvious, not whether a diligent searcher might find pieces from which there might have been selected the elements which make up the patent. If this were not so, there could never be a valid patent for a new combination of old integers. The proper question is not whether it would have been obvious to the hypothetical addressee who was presented with an ex post facto selection of prior specifications that elements from them could be combined to produce a new product or process. It is rather whether it would have been obvious to a non-inventive skilled worker in the field to select from a possibly very large range of publications the particular combination subsequently chosen by the opponent in the glare of hindsight and also whether it would have been obvious to that worker to select the particular combination of integers from those selected publications. In the case of a combination patent the invention will lie in the selection of integers, a process which will necessarily involve rejection of other possible integers. The prior existence of publications revealing those integers, as separate items, and other possible integers does not of itself make an alleged invention obvious. It is the selection of the integers out of, perhaps many possibilities, which must be shown to be obvious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Vickers, Sons &amp; Co Ltd v Siddell [1890] 15 App Cas 496</tocase>
<text>144 An appropriate starting point is the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Allsop Inc v Bintang Ltd (1989) 15 IPR 686. After referring to the fact that there must be an inventive step, although it can be a small one, and the fact that the cases time and again have warned against the "seductive clarity of hindsight", the Court said (at 701):
 
 "But although a simple idea may be inventive, it is essential for validity that there be inventiveness. Though small, it must be present. As was said in Graham v John Deere Co, supra, at 15, there is a 'requirement that the subject matter sought to be patented must be beyond the skill of the calling'. The question, as Lord Herschell said in Vickers, Sons &amp; Co Ltd v Siddell [1890] 15 App Cas 496 at 502 is whether the subject of the patent 'was so obvious that it would at once occur to anyone acquainted with the subject, and desirous of accomplishing the end, or whether it required some invention to devise it'. In R D Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1989) 13 IPR 513 at 523; 85 ALR 679 at 689, Lockhart J said: 'There must ... be some difficulty overcome, some barrier crossed'. He cited a dictum of Cotton LJ that 'it must be a question of whether there is sufficient invention to justify a monopoly being granted by the Crown in the particular thing'.
 
 When the principles which surround that question have been stated, the question itself remains one of fact involving an evaluation of the claimed invention in the light of the evidence. It has been described as a 'jury question': Wellcome Foundation case at (CLR) 280."

155 In my opinion, having regard to the evidence before me as to the common general knowledge before the priority date it has not been established by the respondents that the invention embodied in the relevant claims in the Patent would have been obvious to a person skilled in the relevant art. Without necessarily indicating any preference for how the test as to obviousness should be expressed, it has not been established by the first and second respondents that the invention "was so obvious that it would at once occur to anyone acquainted with the subject, and desirous of accomplishing the end ..." ( Vickers, Sons &amp; Co Ltd v Siddell [1890] 15 App Cas 496 at 502 per Lord Herschell). In fact, had it been necessary to do so I would have found that the contrary was established. The idea of a matting impregnated with liquid termite resisting product and used to protect the cavity between masonry wall and concrete slab and thereby forming both a physical and chemical barrier to the entry of termites involved an inventive step having regard to the common general knowledge as I have found it to have been at the relevant time.

156 Although Mr Worthington expressed his conclusion in terms of novelty, it seems that his opinions address the question of obviousness. In addition to saying the invention described in the Patent was not a novel invention, he said that it was "merely an adaptation of an existing detail of construction using another type of material". That opinion appears to be based on the fact that the Termimesh system was in use and the positioning of a damp-proof course and flashing. Those matters do not mean that the invention in the relevant claims was obvious. Nor do the other matters he referred to such as Alcore (which is a roll of aluminium sheets), vapour barriers (which are impervious sheets laid under the slab and up the edge of the slab) and shower damp-proofing mean that the invention disclosed by the relevant claims was obvious.

157 Insofar as Mr Worthington expressed the opinion that the invention in the Patent was obvious, I reject that opinion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Welch Perrin Co Pty Ltd v Worrel [1960] HCA 91 ; (1961) 106 CLR 588</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1960/91.html</AustLII>
<text>163 I have already discussed the relationship between claims 1 and 2 on the one hand and claim 4 on the other (see [86]-[88] above). As a matter of construction, the claims cover a termite resistant product which is a liquid on impregnation and which becomes a solid thereafter. In those circumstances, the argument that the invention is not useful must fail. Had I construed claims 1 and 2 to include a termite resisting product which was in liquid form on impregnation and in a solid or liquid form thereafter then a real question of utility would have arisen ( Norton and Gregory Ltd v Jacobs (1937) 54 RPC 271; Martin Engineering v Trison Holdings (1989) 14 IPR 330 at 337 per Burchett J). However, I would wish to make two points in connexion with that. First, such resulting inutility would be a reason not to construe claims 1 and 2 in that fashion, when the construction not resulting in inutility, which I have adopted, is open: Welch Perrin Co Pty Ltd v Worrel [1960] HCA 91 ; (1961) 106 CLR 588 at 602 per Menzies J. Secondly, it is not to be assumed that had it been necessary to deal with the question, inutility would have been made out on the facts. The respondents bore the onus on the issue of utility and there was no evidence before me as to types of liquid, evaporation rates and atmospheric conditions in the cavity. In the circumstances, it is not necessary for me to resolve that issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wellcome Foundation Ltd v VR Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/12.html</AustLII>
<text>142 The attributes of the person skilled in the relevant art for the purposes of s 7(2) have been referred to in a number of authorities. For present purposes it is enough to say that the hypothetical worker must be taken to be non-inventive, although skilled in the relevant art. By reason of the conditions which prevail in modern industry, he or she may be part of a sophisticated research team, with a great amount of information available to it ( Wellcome Foundation Ltd v VR Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262 at 270 per Aickin J (with whom the other members of the Court agreed); Elconnex at 507 per Burchett J).

144 An appropriate starting point is the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Allsop Inc v Bintang Ltd (1989) 15 IPR 686. After referring to the fact that there must be an inventive step, although it can be a small one, and the fact that the cases time and again have warned against the "seductive clarity of hindsight", the Court said (at 701):
 
 "But although a simple idea may be inventive, it is essential for validity that there be inventiveness. Though small, it must be present. As was said in Graham v John Deere Co, supra, at 15, there is a 'requirement that the subject matter sought to be patented must be beyond the skill of the calling'. The question, as Lord Herschell said in Vickers, Sons &amp; Co Ltd v Siddell [1890] 15 App Cas 496 at 502 is whether the subject of the patent 'was so obvious that it would at once occur to anyone acquainted with the subject, and desirous of accomplishing the end, or whether it required some invention to devise it'. In R D Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1989) 13 IPR 513 at 523; 85 ALR 679 at 689, Lockhart J said: 'There must ... be some difficulty overcome, some barrier crossed'. He cited a dictum of Cotton LJ that 'it must be a question of whether there is sufficient invention to justify a monopoly being granted by the Crown in the particular thing'.
 
 When the principles which surround that question have been stated, the question itself remains one of fact involving an evaluation of the claimed invention in the light of the evidence. It has been described as a 'jury question': Wellcome Foundation case at (CLR) 280."</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>