<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 (7 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1922.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FMCA 457</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/457.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In the Federal Magistrates Court Riley FM dismissed all the appellant's claims: Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FMCA 457. In a subsequent ruling her Honour awarded the respondents costs on an indemnity basis from 2 June 2006, the date of a Calderbank offer: Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng (No2) [2007] FMCA 989.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng (No 2) [2007] FMCA 989</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/989.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In the Federal Magistrates Court Riley FM dismissed all the appellant's claims: Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FMCA 457. In a subsequent ruling her Honour awarded the respondents costs on an indemnity basis from 2 June 2006, the date of a Calderbank offer: Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng (No2) [2007] FMCA 989.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Lott v JBW &amp; Friends Pty Ltd (2000) 76 SASR 105</tocase>
<text>22 In dealing with this issue the learned Magistrate discussed Lott v JBW &amp; Friends Pty Ltd (2000) 76 SASR 105. The work there in question was a graphic bar with the words "Opera in the Outback". The report does not contain a reproduction. Mullighan J held that it was a "drawing". His Honour said at [14]
 
 The graphic designer had to create a design and make choices about the layout, font, colour and dimensions of each part of the design. Having perused the graphic ... I do not regard it as so simple as to deny copyright. 
 ...
 The selection of the font from a computer program is no less creative than manual drawing ...

23 In the present case her Honour, correctly in my view, pointed out at [29] that Lott is not authority for the proposition that anything a graphic designer prepares is a drawing.

24 The same point was made by Mr Minahan, counsel for the respondents, in his written submissions. The submissions, he said, involved the use of a computer and selection of typeface and decisions about layout and presentation including headings and indentation. The same could be said for a newspaper. However neither the submissions nor a newspaper would be regarded as a drawing.

25 Her Honour adopted the statement in Ricketson, S The Law of Intellectual Property, Copyright Designs and Confidential Information , at par 7.365:
 
 Essentially, a drawing is a two-dimensional work in which shapes and images are depicted by lines, often without colouring.

26 I would agree that this is the ordinary meaning of the term "drawing". The Macquarie Dictionary gives us several definitions of the noun "drawing":
 
 ... 
 2. representation by lines; delineation of form without reference to colour. 
 3. a sketch, plan, or design, esp one made with pen, pencil, or crayon.

27 In the context of the visual arts, the traditional distinction has been between paintings, which are coloured, and drawings, which are monotone, usually, but not always, black upon white. The statutory definition, particularly by its inclusion of maps, makes it clear that for the purposes of the Act something may be a drawing notwithstanding that it is coloured. However, the essence of a drawing remains the concept of a representation of some object by a pictorial line.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Millar &amp; Lang Ltd v Polak [1908] 1 Ch 433</tocase>
<text>29 Certainly for something to be a "drawing" for copyright purposes no great complexity or (as the statute tells us) artistic quality is required. In Millar &amp; Lang Ltd v Polak [1908] 1 Ch 433 the works held to be drawings included words such as "Greetings", "Friends ever". "Good luck", "Lest we forget", and "For old times sake" in a distinctive form within an ornamental oval or circular scroll. In Roland Corporation v Lorenzo &amp; Sons Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 111 the devices held by Pincus J to be drawings were based on the letters R and B but, as is apparent from the report at 112, were quite stylised. As his Honour said at 114, they were "by no means random and were plainly drawn with care, to obtain an effect". Clearly a letter or letters of the alphabet can provide the subject matter for a drawing. One thinks of the illuminated manuscripts of medieval works such as the Book of Kells. However, in the present case the text is fulfilling a semiotic function. It is communicating to the reader the message that within the cardboard box will be found a wooden photo box with 6 albums which hold 120 10 x 15 cm photos. The pictorial image of that box is conveyed by a photograph, which is not a drawing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Roland Corporation v Lorenzo &amp; Sons Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 111</tocase>
<text>29 Certainly for something to be a "drawing" for copyright purposes no great complexity or (as the statute tells us) artistic quality is required. In Millar &amp; Lang Ltd v Polak [1908] 1 Ch 433 the works held to be drawings included words such as "Greetings", "Friends ever". "Good luck", "Lest we forget", and "For old times sake" in a distinctive form within an ornamental oval or circular scroll. In Roland Corporation v Lorenzo &amp; Sons Pty Ltd (1991) 33 FCR 111 the devices held by Pincus J to be drawings were based on the letters R and B but, as is apparent from the report at 112, were quite stylised. As his Honour said at 114, they were "by no means random and were plainly drawn with care, to obtain an effect". Clearly a letter or letters of the alphabet can provide the subject matter for a drawing. One thinks of the illuminated manuscripts of medieval works such as the Book of Kells. However, in the present case the text is fulfilling a semiotic function. It is communicating to the reader the message that within the cardboard box will be found a wooden photo box with 6 albums which hold 120 10 x 15 cm photos. The pictorial image of that box is conveyed by a photograph, which is not a drawing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Metwally v University of Wollongong (No 2) [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/28.html</AustLII>
<text>31 It appears that, although not pleaded, this issue was at least touched on in the court below. It is discussed at [34]-[37] of the judgment. Mr Minahan objected to this late amendment, citing the decision of the High Court in Metwally v University of Wollongong (No 2) [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71:
 
 It is elementary that a party is bound by the conduct of his case. Except in the most exceptional circumstances it would contrary to all principle to allow a party, after a case has been decided against him, to raise a new argument which, whether deliberately or by inadvertence, he failed to put during the hearing when he had an opportunity to do so.

32 The application to amend should be refused, primarily for the reason that the proposed amendment lacks arguable merit. The notion of compilation involves a collecting and putting together or arranging or organising of disparate data. That is not the case with the appellant's label. It is simply a photograph and a description of an object. It conveys the one message.

33 The appellant's case was pleaded in the common law tort of passing off as well as alleged contraventions of ss 52 and 53 (c) and (d) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). Section 52 prohibits conduct in trade or commerce which is misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive. More specifically, s 53(c) and (d) prohibits representations that goods or a corporation have sponsorship or approval which they do not have.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd (2007) 159 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>34 In the court below, concentration was very much on the passing off claim. However, as the Full Court has recently pointed out in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd (2007) 159 FCR 397 at [96]-[99], the degree of overlap between the two causes of action should not obscure the important differences between them. The law of passing off protests goodwill as a species of property: Boehringer Ingelheim Ltd v Vetplus Ltd (2007) 73 IPR 593 at [37] per Jacob LJ, citing a passage from the judgment of Millett LJ in Harrods Ltd v Harrodian School Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 355 at 366. However claims under the Trade Practices Act it is not necessary for a plaintiff to establish an exclusive reputation, or indeed any reputation at all. The question is rather whether consumers are likely to be misled or deceived by the defendant's conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Boehringer Ingelheim Ltd v Vetplus Ltd (2007) 73 IPR 593</tocase>
<text>34 In the court below, concentration was very much on the passing off claim. However, as the Full Court has recently pointed out in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd (2007) 159 FCR 397 at [96]-[99], the degree of overlap between the two causes of action should not obscure the important differences between them. The law of passing off protests goodwill as a species of property: Boehringer Ingelheim Ltd v Vetplus Ltd (2007) 73 IPR 593 at [37] per Jacob LJ, citing a passage from the judgment of Millett LJ in Harrods Ltd v Harrodian School Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 355 at 366. However claims under the Trade Practices Act it is not necessary for a plaintiff to establish an exclusive reputation, or indeed any reputation at all. The question is rather whether consumers are likely to be misled or deceived by the defendant's conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harrods Ltd v Harrodian School Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 355</tocase>
<text>34 In the court below, concentration was very much on the passing off claim. However, as the Full Court has recently pointed out in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd (2007) 159 FCR 397 at [96]-[99], the degree of overlap between the two causes of action should not obscure the important differences between them. The law of passing off protests goodwill as a species of property: Boehringer Ingelheim Ltd v Vetplus Ltd (2007) 73 IPR 593 at [37] per Jacob LJ, citing a passage from the judgment of Millett LJ in Harrods Ltd v Harrodian School Ltd (1996) 35 IPR 355 at 366. However claims under the Trade Practices Act it is not necessary for a plaintiff to establish an exclusive reputation, or indeed any reputation at all. The question is rather whether consumers are likely to be misled or deceived by the defendant's conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v F S Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/51.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Moreover, the learned Magistrate's findings support a conclusion that this was a case of deliberate copying. I would apply the principle in Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v F S Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641 at 657.

56 On the trade practices causes of action the appellant's damages claim is based on the number of sales of the respondents' offending boxes. The appellant claims the gross profit on an equivalent number of sales it says it has lost.

57 There were 676 such sales by the respondents. The lowest profit margin for the appellant, being that on its small photo boxes, was $5.45. The resultant figure is $3684.20.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>I &amp; L Securities Pty Limited v HTW Valuers (Brisbane) Pty Limited [2002] HCA 41 ; (2002) 210 CLR 109</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/41.html</AustLII>
<text>59 In my view, the appellant's approach is a realistic one. The competing products were presented side by side to consumers. As already noted, the effect of the offending packaging was likely to induce consumers into thinking that they were getting the same product from the same source but would be saving money by not having to pay for more elaborate packaging, which they did not need. The misleading and deceptive conduct only has to be one among a number of causes which contributes to a consumer decision harmful to a plaintiff. As Gleeson CJ said in I &amp; L Securities Pty Limited v HTW Valuers (Brisbane) Pty Limited [2002] HCA 41 ; (2002) 210 CLR 109 at [33] :
 
 In most business transactions resulting in financial loss there are multiple causes of the loss. The statutory purpose would be defeated if the remedy under s 82 were restricted to loss of which the contravening conduct was the sole cause.

60 While the appellant's claim is based on gross profit lost, that seems a practical measure in the circumstances of this case. It is a modest claim because it assumes that all sales lost were of the small box, which had the lowest margin. It would be an artificial exercise to attempt to calculate some proportion of that profit which represented savings of fixed costs. This case was properly brought in the Federal Magistrates Court, a jurisdiction which is expected to operate as informally as possible: Federal Magistrates Act 1999 (Cth) ss 3(2)(a) and 42 . In a case of this nature parties should not feel they have to engage forensic accountants and similar experts.

61 The appeal will be allowed and the judgment below set aside. In lieu thereof there will be judgment for the appellant against the respondents (the liability of the first respondent under s 79(1)(c) of the Trade Practices Act was not in dispute). The amount of that judgment will be $3684.20 plus appropriate interest under s 51A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth).

62 There remain the questions of costs. As already mentioned, the learned Magistrate made an order for indemnity costs. The respondents had made Calderbank offers as follows:
 
&#8226; 5 April 2006: an undertaking to cease selling products with the offending packaging
 
&#8226; 27 April 2006: the undertaking, $3775 for costs and $1200 damages
 
&#8226; 19 May 2006: the undertaking, $4331 for costs and $2706 damages
 
&#8226; 2 June 2006: the undertaking, $4331 for costs and $9000 damages. (The time for compliance with this offer was extended on two occasions).

63 I direct that the appellant within seven days file written submissions as to interest and costs and that the respondent file answering submissions within seven days thereafter.

 I certify that the preceding sixty three (63) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey 


 Associate:

Dated: 7 December 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: C Golvan SC 
 
 Solicitors for the Appellant: Middletons 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: S Minahan 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondent: F A L Lawyers 
 
 Date of Hearing: 23 November 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 December 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1922.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>