<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 6) [2007] FCA 1608 (26 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1608.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 2) [2006] FCA 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/336.html</AustLII>
<text>27 I refused Mr Siminton's application. Similar strike-out applications had been made to Merkel J on 30 March 2006 and to me on 18 October 2006. Those applications had been supported by substantially the same arguments and, in both cases had been rejected: see Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 2) [2006] FCA 336 ; Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 5) [2006] FCA 1340. There was no substance to the argument advanced in support of the permanent stay applications when they were first made. It was not improved by repetition.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 5) [2006] FCA 1340</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1340.html</AustLII>
<text>27 I refused Mr Siminton's application. Similar strike-out applications had been made to Merkel J on 30 March 2006 and to me on 18 October 2006. Those applications had been supported by substantially the same arguments and, in both cases had been rejected: see Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 2) [2006] FCA 336 ; Australian Prudential Regulation Authority v Siminton (No 5) [2006] FCA 1340. There was no substance to the argument advanced in support of the permanent stay applications when they were first made. It was not improved by repetition.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Mauer-Swisse Securities Limited (2002) 42 ACSR 605</tocase>
<text>64 As already noted, s 65A of the Act is in substantially similar terms to those of s 1324 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth). In Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Mauer-Swisse Securities Limited (2002) 42 ACSR 605 at 613-614 Palmer J, having reviewed a number of authorities on the construction and operation of s 1324 continued:
 
 "[36] At the risk of some repetition, I summarise the principles which I draw from the presently applicable authorities: 
 

&#8226; the jurisdiction which the court exercises under [the Corporations Act ] s 1324 is a statutory jurisdiction, not the court's traditional equity jurisdiction; 
 
&#8226; Parliament has made it increasingly clear by successive statutory enactments that the court, in exercising its statutory jurisdiction under s 1324 , is not to be confined by the considerations which would be applicable if it were exercising its traditional equity jurisdiction; 
 
&#8226; among the considerations which the court must take into account in an application for an injunction under [Corporations Act] s 1324 are the wider issues referred to by Austin J ... and by Davies AJ ...; they may be gathered under the broad question whether the injunction would have some utility or would serve some purpose within the contemplation of the Corporations Act ; 
 
&#8226; these considerations are to be taken into account regardless of whether the application is for a permanent injunction under s 1324(1) or for a interim application under s 1324(4) ; 
 
&#8226; where an application under s 1324(4) is made by ASIC rather than a private litigant the court is more likely to give greater weight to the broad question whether the injunction would serve a purpose within the contemplation of the Corporations Act ; 
 
&#8226; where there is an appreciable that is, not fanciful risk of particular future contraventions of the Corporations Act by a defendant, it would serve a purpose within the contemplation of the Corporations Act that the court grant not only a permanent injunction, but, in an appropriate case, an interim injunction restraining such conduct. Section 1324 evinces an intention that the possibly severe consequences and the relatively promptness of proceedings for contempt of court be added to criminal prosecutions as a deterrent to contraventions of the Corporations Act ..." 
 
In my view these principles have application to the construction of s 65A of the Act. The principle contained in the penultimate bullet point in the passage quoted in this paragraph has equal force where application is made for a permanent injunction.

65 By s 8 of the Australian Prudential Regulation Authority Act 1998 (Cth) APRA is established, inter alia, for the purpose of regulating bodies in the financial sector in accordance with other laws of the Commonwealth, such as the Banking Act , that provide for prudential regulation. Section 65A of the Act is one of many provisions in the Act which enable APRA to take action designed to protect the interests of depositors and to promote the stability of Australia's financial system. Those objectives are to be borne in mind in exercising the discretion which is conferred on the Court by s 65A.

66 Mr Siminton has deliberately embarked on a course of conduct which has involved contraventions of the Act. He has established what he calls a "bank" and, with others, has been successful in encouraging a considerable number of people to make deposits in the "bank". They were promised high interest rates. They were told that interest payments would be made in ways which would facilitate evasion of income taxation payment obligations. Some depositors received some of the promised interest payments but then the payments ceased. Others received no interest. Some, who sought repayment of their deposits, were unsuccessful.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Independent Distributors Ltd v Winter [1964] HCA 78 ; (1964) 112 CLR 443</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/78.html</AustLII>
<text>50 In Australian Independent Distributors Ltd v Winter [1964] HCA 78 ; (1964) 112 CLR 443 the High Court was called on to determine whether a friendly society was carrying on "the business of banking" contrary to s 7 of the Act. The Court quoted the passage from the judgment of Isaacs J in Permewan Wright which Rich J had incorporated in his reasons in Melbourne Corporation. The Court treated what Isaacs J had said as constituting a "definition" of the "business of banking" (at 455). The Court continued: 
 
 "If that definition is applied to the present case, as we think it should be, it is apparent that the second of these essential characteristics is absent. The power to lend money conferred on the Society by Rule 7 was limited to the making of loans to its members to enable them to acquire land or buildings to be used for residential or business and residential purposes and in fact none of the Society's moneys was used for the making of loans for that or any other purpose." 

The second essential characteristic which was found to be absent was the lending function. The society had not made any loans. For this reason, the Court held that the trial judge had been correct to hold that the society had not carried on the business of banking and had not, therefore, contravened s 7 of the Act.

54 Counsel for Mr Siminton, relying on what was said by Isaacs J in Permewan Wright and by the Full Court in Winter , submitted that Mr Siminton could not be found to have carried on a banking business because the Terra Nova Cache did not make loans on a regular basis. It is true that the evidence disclosed only one loan, albeit a substantial loan made by the Terra Nova Cache under Mr Siminton's direction. It is to be noted, in this context, that the decision in Winter turned on the fact that the society had not loaned members' funds to anybody. In any event, the Court is empowered, by s 65A of the Act, to grant relief where a person is proposing to engage in conduct which would constitute a contravention of s 7. When addressing meetings, at which he solicited deposits, Mr Siminton told those present that, once the Terra Nova Cache was established, loans could be made to citizens of the Principality of Camside. Point 12 on the information sheet which was made available at the meetings and in the Principality of Camside's website under the heading "HM Government of Camside Banking Facilities" advised readers that:
 
 "12. It is envisaged that the next stage of Terra Nova Cache's development, once deposits are established, profitably traded and fully precious metal backed, that the bank will be offering interest free loans to its depositors/owners." 

Even if no regular practice of making loans had been established prior to APRA commencing this proceeding it is clear that Mr Siminton proposed to offer loans to "citizens" of Camside once the Terra Nova Cache had become established.

55 For these reasons I conclude that Mr Siminton was a person who carried on and was proposing to carry on the business of banking in Australia. He had engaged and was proposing to engage in conduct which constituted or would constitute a contravention of s 7 of the Act.

56 Section 66. Section 66(1) of the Act makes it an offence for a person who "carries on a financial business" to use the words "bank" or "banking" in relation to such a business. A "financial business" is defined in s 66(4)(c) to refer to a business that consists of, or includes, the provision of financial services or relates, in whole or part, to the provision of financial services. The term "financial services" is not defined. The words should be accorded their ordinary and natural meaning. They comprehend the provision of services of a financial nature.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Burke [2000] NSWSC 694</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2000/694.html</AustLII>
<text>72 Subject to hearing the parties I consider that the better course would be to appoint a receiver to deal with the funds which are subject to Gray J's order. This would seem to be an appropriate case for the appointment of a receiver, if not under s 57(1) of the Federal Court of Australia Act , under s 23 of that Act: see The University of Western Australia v Gray (No 6) [2006] FCA 1825 at [71] . This case bears many of the features which led Austin J, in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Burke [2000] NSWSC 694 , to appoint a receiver. His Honour said (at [8]):
 
 "Without wishing to lay down any general rules, it appears to me that the extraordinary step of appointing a receiver may be justified, even though Mareva Orders are in place, in a case where there is real doubt about the existence and location of assets such as investments, and about the number and identity of claimants and the nature of their claims, and additionally the defendants are engaged in business activities which entail that any Mareva Orders must allow assets to be turned over in the course of business. Where these circumstances exist in combination, and especially where there are allegations of serious fraud involved, the Court may conclude, as I do in this case, that the Mareva Orders are not enough to ensure that the assets are preserved and protected, and indeed identified and brought in for the benefit of investors."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Federal Police v Cox (1986) 78 ALR 509</tocase>
<text>16 In Smithers the High Court also upheld the constitutional validity of s 243E(2)(c)(i) of the Customs Act which empowered this Court to direct the Official Trustee to take control of specified property of a person if there existed reasonable grounds for the belief that the person had engaged in narcotics dealing and derived benefits therefrom. The Court held that s 51(xxxi) had no application because it did not involve an acquisition of property by the Commonwealth, much less an acquisition on just terms. The property was placed under the control of the Official Receiver in order to ensure that the pecuniary penalty provisions in s 243B could not be rendered nugatory by disposition of property. In Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Cox (1986) 78 ALR 509 at 514-515 Pincus J held that the same reasoning supported the validity of s 243E(2)(c)(ii) which empowered the Court to make an order directing the Official Trustee to take control of all of the property of the person involved in narcotic dealings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of State Savings Bank of Victoria v Permewan, Wright &amp; Company Limited [1914] HCA 83 ; (1914) 19 CLR 457</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1914/83.html</AustLII>
<text>49 The critical question is whether Mr Siminton can be said to have carried on any banking business at relevant times. "Banking business" is defined in s 5 of the Act to mean "a business that consists of banking within the meaning of paragraph 51(xiii) of the Constitution ." Section 51(xiii) does not contain the phrase "business of banking". It confers power on the Commonwealth Parliament to make laws with respect to "banking". This word, has, however, been treated by the High Court as referring to "the business of banking". In Melbourne Corporation v The Commonwealth [1947] HCA 26 ; (1947) 74 CLR 31 at 69 Starke J said:
 
 "Banking, within the meaning of the Constitution , relates to the business of a banker and covers all those various functions which a banker undertakes. But his main functions appear to be the taking of deposits and current accounts, the issue and payment of bills and cheques drawn on him and the collection of bills and cheques for his customers." 

Williams J (at 97) held that the legislation authorised by s 51(xiii) "is legislation with respect of the business of banking." Rich J (at 64-5) referred to and relied on the construction placed on the word "banking" by Isaacs J in Commissioner of State Savings Bank of Victoria v Permewan, Wright &amp; Company Limited [1914] HCA 83 ; (1914) 19 CLR 457:
 
 "While the word 'banking' is sometimes used in a colloquial and crude sense to mean the payment of money to the credit of a customer's account at a bank, the word in its normal and ordinary signification denotes the business of banking. Some assistance in defining 'banking' can be obtained from the Bills of Exchange Act 1909-1936. In this Act the word banker includes a body of persons, whether incorporated or not, who carry on the business of banking, and though banking is not defined in this Act it seems reasonable to believe that one legislative interpretation of the word would be the business carried on by a banker. In the case of Commissioners of State Savings Bank of Victoria v Permewan, Wright &amp; Company Limited Isaacs J ... said: 'the fundamental meaning of the term' (banking) 'is not, and never has been, different in Australia from that obtaining in England. Various writers attempt various definitions, more or less discordant and many of them referring to functions that are now very common and convenient, and even prominent, as if they were indispensable attributes. The essential characteristics of the business of banking are, however, all that are necessary to bring the appellants within the scope of the enactments' (s 83 of the Victorian Instruments Act 1980 and s 88 of the Bills of Exchange Act 1909 ) 'and these may be described as the collection of money by receiving deposits upon loan, repayable when and as expressly or impliedly agreed upon, and the utilisation of the money so collected by lending it again in such sums as are required. These are the essential functions of a banker as an instrument of society.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Medibank Private Limited v Cassidy [2002] FCAFC 290 ; (2002) 124 FCR 40</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/290.html</AustLII>
<text>24 Save for its first word s 65A(11) is in the same terms as s 1324 of the Corporations Law 1989 (Cth) (now s 1324 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth)). As the Full Court noted in Medibank Private Limited v Cassidy [2002] FCAFC 290 ; (2002) 124 FCR 40 at 50-51, provisions of this kind can be traced back to the Chancery Amendment Act 1858 (UK) ( Lord Cairns Act). The purpose of such provisions is expressly to empower a Court to award damages to persons who have suffered as a result of conduct which contravenes legislative requirements whether or not a curial power to grant a mandatory injunction might also support such an order. The exercise of the power is conditioned on the existence of a power to grant an injunction. That power is conferred by s 65A(1) which is a valid provision. In my opinion there is no reason, in principle, to distinguish between the power to grant injunctions and the power to require a respondent to pay damages occasioned by the same conduct which might justify the granting of an injunction. The granting of such relief does not cast the Court in the role of a "collection service" acting on behalf of third parties. It involves a judicial act in aid of a legislative purpose. Sections 65A(11) is valid law of the Commonwealth.

25 At the outset of the trial Mr Siminton sought an order that APRA's application should permanently be stayed or struck-out as an abuse of process. No notice of motion seeking such an order had been filed but Mr Siminton had, prior to trial, filed and served a notice of preliminary objections which included a summary of the submissions which he desired to make in support of the strike-out application. Counsel appearing for APRA did not object to the application being made or argued in advance of the trial proper.

26 Mr Siminton submitted that the proceeding was an abuse of process because it had been brought for the collateral purpose of seeking information and evidence to substantiate or justify allegations that Mr Siminton had committed criminal offences under ss 7 and 66 of the Act. He said that the Court should so conclude because:
 
 &#8226; APRA had failed to accept an offer by Mr Siminton to agree to certain forms of injunction;
 &#8226; APRA's statement of claim failed to plead any cause of action for damages;
 &#8226; APRA had conceded that it lacked evidence of lending by Mr Siminton and, therefore, that he had engaged in "banking";
 &#8226; Of the fact that no charges had been laid against Mr Siminton;
 &#8226; Of the alleged paucity of evidence linking Mr Siminton to any alleged breach of s 66;
 &#8226; Of APRA's claim for certain interlocutory orders which Gray J had declined to make;
 &#8226; Of the commencement of contempt proceedings against Mr Siminton which were heard before the trial of the present proceeding;
 &#8226; Of APRA's attempt to use and rely on discovery, its seeking of particulars of Mr Siminton's defence and its application that directions be made requiring Mr Siminton to file witness statements in advance of trial; and
 &#8226; Of what was said to be the "linking of APRA's release of frozen funds for legal expenses to the provision of information." (I take this to be a reference to the terms of order 2 of the orders made by Gray J on 10 January 2006 under which Mr Siminton was given liberty to apply on notice in writing to APRA, supported by affidavit evidence of his means, for an order that he be permitted to withdraw monies for living and legal expenses).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Melbourne Corporation v The Commonwealth [1947] HCA 26 ; (1947) 74 CLR 31</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1947/26.html</AustLII>
<text>49 The critical question is whether Mr Siminton can be said to have carried on any banking business at relevant times. "Banking business" is defined in s 5 of the Act to mean "a business that consists of banking within the meaning of paragraph 51(xiii) of the Constitution ." Section 51(xiii) does not contain the phrase "business of banking". It confers power on the Commonwealth Parliament to make laws with respect to "banking". This word, has, however, been treated by the High Court as referring to "the business of banking". In Melbourne Corporation v The Commonwealth [1947] HCA 26 ; (1947) 74 CLR 31 at 69 Starke J said:
 
 "Banking, within the meaning of the Constitution , relates to the business of a banker and covers all those various functions which a banker undertakes. But his main functions appear to be the taking of deposits and current accounts, the issue and payment of bills and cheques drawn on him and the collection of bills and cheques for his customers." 

Williams J (at 97) held that the legislation authorised by s 51(xiii) "is legislation with respect of the business of banking." Rich J (at 64-5) referred to and relied on the construction placed on the word "banking" by Isaacs J in Commissioner of State Savings Bank of Victoria v Permewan, Wright &amp; Company Limited [1914] HCA 83 ; (1914) 19 CLR 457:
 
 "While the word 'banking' is sometimes used in a colloquial and crude sense to mean the payment of money to the credit of a customer's account at a bank, the word in its normal and ordinary signification denotes the business of banking. Some assistance in defining 'banking' can be obtained from the Bills of Exchange Act 1909-1936. In this Act the word banker includes a body of persons, whether incorporated or not, who carry on the business of banking, and though banking is not defined in this Act it seems reasonable to believe that one legislative interpretation of the word would be the business carried on by a banker. In the case of Commissioners of State Savings Bank of Victoria v Permewan, Wright &amp; Company Limited Isaacs J ... said: 'the fundamental meaning of the term' (banking) 'is not, and never has been, different in Australia from that obtaining in England. Various writers attempt various definitions, more or less discordant and many of them referring to functions that are now very common and convenient, and even prominent, as if they were indispensable attributes. The essential characteristics of the business of banking are, however, all that are necessary to bring the appellants within the scope of the enactments' (s 83 of the Victorian Instruments Act 1980 and s 88 of the Bills of Exchange Act 1909 ) 'and these may be described as the collection of money by receiving deposits upon loan, repayable when and as expressly or impliedly agreed upon, and the utilisation of the money so collected by lending it again in such sums as are required. These are the essential functions of a banker as an instrument of society.'

50 In Australian Independent Distributors Ltd v Winter [1964] HCA 78 ; (1964) 112 CLR 443 the High Court was called on to determine whether a friendly society was carrying on "the business of banking" contrary to s 7 of the Act. The Court quoted the passage from the judgment of Isaacs J in Permewan Wright which Rich J had incorporated in his reasons in Melbourne Corporation. The Court treated what Isaacs J had said as constituting a "definition" of the "business of banking" (at 455). The Court continued: 
 
 "If that definition is applied to the present case, as we think it should be, it is apparent that the second of these essential characteristics is absent. The power to lend money conferred on the Society by Rule 7 was limited to the making of loans to its members to enable them to acquire land or buildings to be used for residential or business and residential purposes and in fact none of the Society's moneys was used for the making of loans for that or any other purpose." 

The second essential characteristic which was found to be absent was the lending function. The society had not made any loans. For this reason, the Court held that the trial judge had been correct to hold that the society had not carried on the business of banking and had not, therefore, contravened s 7 of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Mikasa (NSW) Pty Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/69.html</AustLII>
<text>63 In Mikasa (NSW) Pty Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617 Gibbs J dealt with s 90AA of the Trade Practices Act 1965-1971 (Cth) (the forerunner of the present s 80 of that Act). His Honour said (at 651):
 
 "In my opinion s 90AA does not confer on the Court a discretion of an arbitrary kind. It appears from the section that the object of granting an injunction is to restrain a person who has already engaged in unlawful practice from again engaging in that practice. To acquire, rather than permit, the Court to grant an injunction once the condition precedent to its grant has been established would deny the Court the power to adapt a remedy of the needs of a case and would lead to an injustice; moreover, an injunction is in its nature a discretionary remedy. Since the discretion is conferred on a court and is to be exercised in proceedings inter partes, it must be concluded, when there is no indication in the Act to the contrary, that it is to be exercised judicially. The existence of the discretion does not alter the conclusion that the power conferred by s 90AA is a judicial power."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>R v Smithers; Ex parte McMillan [1982] HCA 76 ; (1982) 152 CLR 477</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/76.html</AustLII>
<text>10 This contention must fail. It is a matter for the Parliament to determine which measures it will adopt in order to secure compliance with legislation which is enacted pursuant to one of the heads of power conferred by s 51 of the Constitution . Parliament may determine to visit contraventions of an Act with criminal sanctions. It may also provide for civil remedies. It may determine to do both. In R v Smithers; Ex parte McMillan [1982] HCA 76 ; (1982) 152 CLR 477 the High Court dealt with a challenge to the validity of provisions of the Customs Act 1901 (Cth) which enabled certain office-holders to apply to this Court for an order that a person, who had been involved in the importation of narcotic substances, pay a pecuniary penalty to the Commonwealth. The application could be made whether or not the person had been charged or convicted of any offence under the Customs Act . The Customs Act also made importation of such substances a criminal offence. The Court held (at 485) that:
 
 "It would be a legitimate exercise of the power [s 51(i) of the Constitution when read with s 51(xxxix)] and this is conceded to make it an offence to engage in dealing in narcotic goods, being prohibited imports, that have been imported in contravention of the Act and to impose severe penalties in respect of that offence. Similarly it would be a legitimate exercise of the power to make that conduct the occasion for liability to a civil action for penalties of the traditional kind. Section 243B, in providing for the imposition of pecuniary penalties of the class provided for in Div. 3, stands in no different position. It penalises dealings in narcotic goods that have been imported in contravention of the Act . In so doing it constitutes a deterrent to importation in breach of the statutory provisions and provides a further sanction with a view to ensuring compliance with the statutory provisions governing importation. Its importance in this respect is that it seeks to deprive the dealing in narcotic goods of the considerable financial rewards which are the chief inducement for importing them into Australia and for dealing in them."

11 Sections 7 and 66 of the Act form part of a legislative scheme, protective of members of the public, which regulates the conduct of banking in Australia. Only approved persons may conduct banking businesses. Persons providing other forms of financial services may not adopt the title "bank" and thereby mislead the public as to their status. People may thereby be induced to deposit funds with the "bank". If conduct which contravenes the Act is discovered charges may be laid. The prosecution of criminal charges, however, will do nothing to protect depositors' funds. Nor will a pending trial prevent the defendant continuing to advertise that he or she is conducting a banking business. Section 65A fills this void. It enables this Court to grant immediate and long term relief where contraventions of the Act have occurred, are occurring or, it is proposed, should occur. Injunctions may issue restraining persons from engaging in contravening conduct and may require such persons to take remedial action. Such provisions are, in my opinion, incidental to the enforcement of the regulatory regime which falls squarely within the banking power.

12 Acquisition Of Property Other Than On Just Terms. The "freezing order" to which Mr Siminton refers was made by Gray J on 10 January 2006 under s 65A of the Act . There were, in fact, multiple orders. Those orders prevented Mr Siminton from dealing with funds and property held by him including deposits held in the Terra Nova Cache. Mr Siminton argues that, under the order of Gray J, the Commonwealth has acquired his property, namely his money and other assets. He has effectively been deprived of that property while the order remains in force. This, he submits, involved a contravention of s 51(xxxi) of the Constitution .

16 In Smithers the High Court also upheld the constitutional validity of s 243E(2)(c)(i) of the Customs Act which empowered this Court to direct the Official Trustee to take control of specified property of a person if there existed reasonable grounds for the belief that the person had engaged in narcotics dealing and derived benefits therefrom. The Court held that s 51(xxxi) had no application because it did not involve an acquisition of property by the Commonwealth, much less an acquisition on just terms. The property was placed under the control of the Official Receiver in order to ensure that the pecuniary penalty provisions in s 243B could not be rendered nugatory by disposition of property. In Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Cox (1986) 78 ALR 509 at 514-515 Pincus J held that the same reasoning supported the validity of s 243E(2)(c)(ii) which empowered the Court to make an order directing the Official Trustee to take control of all of the property of the person involved in narcotic dealings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Director of Public Prosecutions; Ex parte Lawler [1994] HCA 10 ; (1994) 179 CLR 270</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1994/10.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The words "acquisition of property" in s 51(xxxi) of the Constitution are not to be read in isolation. In Re Director of Public Prosecutions; Ex parte Lawler [1994] HCA 10 ; (1994) 179 CLR 270 at 285, Deane and Gaudron JJ observed that:
 
 "[T]he power conferred by s 51(xxxi) is one with respect to "acquisition of property on just terms". That phrase must be read in its entirety and, when so read, it indicates that s 51(xxxi) applies only to acquisitions of a kind that permit of just terms. It is not concerned with laws in connection with which "just terms" is an inconsistent or incongruous notion. Thus, it is not concerned with the law imposing a fine or penalty, including by way of forfeiture, or a law effecting or authorising seizure of the property of enemy aliens or the condemnation of prize. Laws of that kind do not involve acquisitions that permit of just terms and, thus, they are not laws with respect to "acquisition of property", as that expression is used in s 51(xxxi)." 

In Lawler the Court held that a provision of the Fisheries Management Act 1991 (Cth), which empowered a Court, which convicted a person who had engaged in unlicensed commercial fishing in Australian Waters, also to order forfeiture of the boat used to undertake the fishing. The statutory power to order forfeiture was held not to be a law with respect to the acquisition of property within the meaning of s 51(xxxi).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Kirby; Ex parte Boilermakers Society of Australia [1956] HCA 10 ; (1956) 94 CLR 254</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1956/10.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The Separation of Powers Point. It will be convenient to deal with the final two arguments advanced by Mr Siminton together. They allege that s 65A of the Act confers legislative and executive power on the Court contrary to the implied limitation recognised in R v Kirby; Ex parte Boilermakers Society of Australia [1956] HCA 10 ; (1956) 94 CLR 254.

22 As I understood the argument advanced by Mr Siminton it was that s 65A of the Act confers very wide powers on the Court. It is said that these powers are wide enough to enable the Court to act as a Royal Commission or Board of Inquiry, to award damages without the assistance of guiding criteria and to act as a surrogate or "collection service" for third persons who may wish to obtain damages from Mr Siminton.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sterling v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 51 FLR 1</tocase>
<text>20 The hearing of an application, made under s 65A of the Act , is not a trial on indictment of any offence against a law of the Commonwealth and, in particular, of an offence against s 7 of the Act : cf Sterling v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 51 FLR 1 at 8. The application does not place Mr Siminton in jeopardy of a conviction for any offence or the imposition of any criminal penalty.

23 Section 65A of the Act was inserted in 2000, see Financial Sector Legislation Amendment Act (No 1) 2000 , s 20. Under the former legislation, ss 7 and 66 of the Act contained penalty provisions only. The inclusion of s 65A was designed to allow APRA, subject to Court approval, to act pre-emptively to stop undesirable activities rather than simply acting to impose punishment after the damage had occurred: see Explanatory Memorandum, Financial Sector Legislation Amendment Act (No 1) 2000 . Many of its sub-sections are drafted in the same or substantially the same terms as provisions to be found in other Commonwealth legislation. Comparisons can be drawn with s 80 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), s 12GD of the Australian Securities and Investment Commission Act 1989 (Cth), and s 1324 of the Corporations Law 1989 (Cth). The constitutional validity of these equivalent provisions has been upheld by Court decisions spanning many years. Section 80(1) of the Trade Practices Act , which corresponds with s 65A(1) was held by Lockhart J to be a valid law of the Commonwealth Parliament in Trade Practices Commission v Sterling (1980) 28 ALR 497 at 517-9. An appeal from his Honour's decision was dealt with by a Full Court. The appellant did not, on appeal, seek to argue that his Honour's decision as to the validity of s 80(1) was wrong. It was, however, argued that sub-ss (4) and (5) of s 80 which contained provisions equivalent to those to be found in s 65A(3) were invalid, being beyond constitutional power. These submissions were rejected by the Full Court: see Sterling v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 51 FLR 1 at 7-9.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The University of Western Australia v Gray (No 6) [2006] FCA 1825</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1825.html</AustLII>
<text>72 Subject to hearing the parties I consider that the better course would be to appoint a receiver to deal with the funds which are subject to Gray J's order. This would seem to be an appropriate case for the appointment of a receiver, if not under s 57(1) of the Federal Court of Australia Act , under s 23 of that Act: see The University of Western Australia v Gray (No 6) [2006] FCA 1825 at [71] . This case bears many of the features which led Austin J, in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Burke [2000] NSWSC 694 , to appoint a receiver. His Honour said (at [8]):
 
 "Without wishing to lay down any general rules, it appears to me that the extraordinary step of appointing a receiver may be justified, even though Mareva Orders are in place, in a case where there is real doubt about the existence and location of assets such as investments, and about the number and identity of claimants and the nature of their claims, and additionally the defendants are engaged in business activities which entail that any Mareva Orders must allow assets to be turned over in the course of business. Where these circumstances exist in combination, and especially where there are allegations of serious fraud involved, the Court may conclude, as I do in this case, that the Mareva Orders are not enough to ensure that the assets are preserved and protected, and indeed identified and brought in for the benefit of investors."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Mobil Oil Australia Limited (1985) 4 FCR 296</tocase>
<text>68 In my view this is a case which requires the granting of injunctions which will restrain Mr Siminton from any repetition of his past misconduct. There is an appreciable risk that, unless restrained, Mr Siminton will resume the course of conduct which caused APRA to make this application. The granting of an injunction is also warranted as a means of marking the Court's disapproval of the flagrant breaches of the Act which had been perpetrated by Mr Siminton; see Trade Practices Commission v Mobil Oil Australia Limited (1985) 4 FCR 296 at 300.

69 Mr Siminton should be restrained from:
 
 &#8226; Receiving money from members of the public by way of deposit in the Terra Nova Cache or the Principality of Camside;
 &#8226; Assuming or using the words "bank", "banker" or "banking", or any words or phrases of like import, in relation to his business; and
 &#8226; Advertising, representing or stating that he will carry on banking business. 

The injunction should also prevent him undertaking such activities through servants or agents. Mr Siminton should also be required to publish and maintain on the first page that any user views on relevant websites, a notice warning them that neither the Terra Nova Cache nor the Principality of Camside are entities which may lawfully conduct a banking business in Australia.

70 APRA also seeks orders under s 65A(11) of the Act requiring Mr Siminton to pay damages to depositors in the Terra Nova Cache and an order, under s 57 of the Federal Court of Australia Act , appointing a receiver to deal with the funds which are subject to the Mareva Orders made by Gray J on 10 January 2006.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Sterling (1980) 28 ALR 497</tocase>
<text>23 Section 65A of the Act was inserted in 2000, see Financial Sector Legislation Amendment Act (No 1) 2000 , s 20. Under the former legislation, ss 7 and 66 of the Act contained penalty provisions only. The inclusion of s 65A was designed to allow APRA, subject to Court approval, to act pre-emptively to stop undesirable activities rather than simply acting to impose punishment after the damage had occurred: see Explanatory Memorandum, Financial Sector Legislation Amendment Act (No 1) 2000 . Many of its sub-sections are drafted in the same or substantially the same terms as provisions to be found in other Commonwealth legislation. Comparisons can be drawn with s 80 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), s 12GD of the Australian Securities and Investment Commission Act 1989 (Cth), and s 1324 of the Corporations Law 1989 (Cth). The constitutional validity of these equivalent provisions has been upheld by Court decisions spanning many years. Section 80(1) of the Trade Practices Act , which corresponds with s 65A(1) was held by Lockhart J to be a valid law of the Commonwealth Parliament in Trade Practices Commission v Sterling (1980) 28 ALR 497 at 517-9. An appeal from his Honour's decision was dealt with by a Full Court. The appellant did not, on appeal, seek to argue that his Honour's decision as to the validity of s 80(1) was wrong. It was, however, argued that sub-ss (4) and (5) of s 80 which contained provisions equivalent to those to be found in s 65A(3) were invalid, being beyond constitutional power. These submissions were rejected by the Full Court: see Sterling v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 51 FLR 1 at 7-9.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>