<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXMI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1162 (6 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1162.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Chung v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 442</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/442.html</AustLII>
<text>12 Moreover, notification of the Decision cannot be treated as a separate 'decision' from the Decision for the purposes of s 476 of the Migration Act : Chung v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 442. As Conti J said in Chung (at [19]): 
 
 
 
 "For a decision-maker merely to communicate his or her decision to a person to be affected thereby, pursuant to his or her duty so to do, does not involve the making of a decision so to do within s 474(3) , particularly where the decision-maker is subject to a statutory obligation so to do, whether explicit or implicit."

13 This appeal was conducted by the parties on the basis that ss 494B and 494C of the Migration Act prescribed the methods by which the appellant was to be notified of the Decision. Sections 494B and 494C were inserted into the Migration Act by Schedule 3 to the Migration Legislation Amendment (Electronic Transactions and Methods of Notification) Act 2001 (Cth). They took effect on 10 August 2001 and, as a matter of statutory construction, applied to the notification of the Decision by the Minister in 2005: Pearce DC and Geddes RS, Statutory Interpretation in Australia, 5 th ed, para [7.23].

20 No appellable error has been identified. It is inappropriate for the Court to pre-empt a decision of the Tribunal as to whether it has jurisdiction. That is a question for the Tribunal: see Chung at [20].

21 For those reasons, the appeal should be dismissed and the appellant should pay the respondent's costs of the appeal. 

 
 I certify that the preceding twenty-one (21) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gordon. 


 Associate:

Dated: 6 August 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr A Krohn 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: Erskine Rodan &amp; Associates 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr W Mosley 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 6 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 August 2007 

 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1162.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Zhan v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 327</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/327.html</AustLII>
<text>14 The appellant was notified of the Decision some 8 years after the Decision was made. The appellant does not dispute he received notification in September 2005. Counsel for the appellant contended that the notification regime in the Migration Act is strict and peremptory and that the Minister failed to comply with ss 494B and 494C . He concedes the argument is technical. The Minister contends that the notification complied with ss 494B and 494C and referred the Court to the decision of Allsop J in Zhan v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 327 at [49] . I adopt the reasoning of Allsop J in Zhan at [47]-[49]. In my view, the Federal Magistrate was correct to conclude that there was notification of the decision in 2005. The letter enclosing the decision was sent within three days of its date in the manner prescribed by ss 494B(4). The fact that it enclosed the Decision made some years earlier is unfortunate but does not render the notification invalid. As noted earlier, upon being notified of the Decision in September 2005, the appellant had a period of 28 days within which to seek a review of the Decision: s 412. He did not do so.

15 Finally, the Decision was and is a 'primary decision' within the meaning of that term in Division 2 of Part 8 of the Migration Act . Accordingly, the Federal Magistrates' Court had no jurisdiction in relation to the Decision: s 476 of the Migration Act .

16 The appeal should be dismissed on this ground alone.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>