<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cirillo v Consolidated Press Property Ltd (formerly known as Citicorp Australia Limited) (No 2) [2007] FCA 179 (22 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/179.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cirillo v Consolidated Press Property Pty Ltd (formerly known as Citicorp Australia Limited) [2007] FCA 60</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/60.html</AustLII>
<text>1 In Cirillo v Consolidated Press Property Pty Ltd (formerly known as Citicorp Australia Limited) [2007] FCA 60 I have ordered that the application be summarily dismissed against all respondents. Put shortly, I found that the Statement of Claim was, first, offensive, embarrassing and disclosed no reasonable cause of action and, second, the causes of action relied upon were in any event doomed to failure because they sought to impeach a consent order of a superior court of record without first having that order set aside.

2 The respondents have sought to be heard on the question of costs. They now seek an order that costs be awarded in their favour on a solicitor and client basis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727</tocase>
<text>3 The jurisdiction of the Court to order costs is conferred by s 43 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The section provides a broad and ample power which ought not be read down otherwise than in accordance with accepted principle. The discretion so conferred is informed by the ordinary practice of this Court that an unsuccessful party usually will be required to pay the costs of the successful party on a party and party basis. That practice, as was indicated in Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727 at 729 and 732-733, is not departed from unless the justice of the particular case so requires or some special or unusual feature arises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225</tocase>
<text>4 The courts in quite some number of cases have indicated types or categories of case in which the award of costs on a basis other than party and party may appropriately be ordered: see e.g. Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 232-234. However, they have emphasised that the categories are not closed and that, even though circumstances may exist which are capable of warranting a more generous costs order than on a party and party basis, this does not compel that such an order be made: Yates Property Corporation Pty Ltd v Boland (No 2) (1997) 147 ALR 685 at 687-688. For present purposes it is unnecessary to consider the case law in any detail. I am content in this matter to adopt the observations of Gray J (with whom the other members of the court agreed) in Hamod v New South Wales (2002) 188 ALR 659 at [20]:
 
 "Indemnity costs are not designed to punish a party for persisting with a case that turns out to fail. They are not awarded as a means of deterring litigants from putting forward arguments that might be attended by uncertainty. Rather, they serve the purpose of compensating a party fully for costs incurred, as a normal costs order could not be expected to do, when the court takes the view that it was unreasonable for the party against whom the order is made to have subjected the innocent party to the expenditure of costs."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yates Property Corporation Pty Ltd v Boland (No 2) (1997) 147 ALR 685</tocase>
<text>4 The courts in quite some number of cases have indicated types or categories of case in which the award of costs on a basis other than party and party may appropriately be ordered: see e.g. Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 232-234. However, they have emphasised that the categories are not closed and that, even though circumstances may exist which are capable of warranting a more generous costs order than on a party and party basis, this does not compel that such an order be made: Yates Property Corporation Pty Ltd v Boland (No 2) (1997) 147 ALR 685 at 687-688. For present purposes it is unnecessary to consider the case law in any detail. I am content in this matter to adopt the observations of Gray J (with whom the other members of the court agreed) in Hamod v New South Wales (2002) 188 ALR 659 at [20]:
 
 "Indemnity costs are not designed to punish a party for persisting with a case that turns out to fail. They are not awarded as a means of deterring litigants from putting forward arguments that might be attended by uncertainty. Rather, they serve the purpose of compensating a party fully for costs incurred, as a normal costs order could not be expected to do, when the court takes the view that it was unreasonable for the party against whom the order is made to have subjected the innocent party to the expenditure of costs."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Hamod v New South Wales (2002) 188 ALR 659</tocase>
<text>4 The courts in quite some number of cases have indicated types or categories of case in which the award of costs on a basis other than party and party may appropriately be ordered: see e.g. Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 232-234. However, they have emphasised that the categories are not closed and that, even though circumstances may exist which are capable of warranting a more generous costs order than on a party and party basis, this does not compel that such an order be made: Yates Property Corporation Pty Ltd v Boland (No 2) (1997) 147 ALR 685 at 687-688. For present purposes it is unnecessary to consider the case law in any detail. I am content in this matter to adopt the observations of Gray J (with whom the other members of the court agreed) in Hamod v New South Wales (2002) 188 ALR 659 at [20]:
 
 "Indemnity costs are not designed to punish a party for persisting with a case that turns out to fail. They are not awarded as a means of deterring litigants from putting forward arguments that might be attended by uncertainty. Rather, they serve the purpose of compensating a party fully for costs incurred, as a normal costs order could not be expected to do, when the court takes the view that it was unreasonable for the party against whom the order is made to have subjected the innocent party to the expenditure of costs."</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>