<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Investa Properties Limited, in the matter of Investa Properties Limited [2007] FCA 1104 (18 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1104.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>APN News &amp; Media Limited (2007) 25 ACLC 784</tocase>
<text>21 Each Scheme Participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its Shares and Units to be transferred to Morgan Stanley Bidco will at the date of transfer be "fully paid and free from all mortgages, charges, liens, encumbrances and interests of third parties of any kind, whether legal or otherwise, and restrictions on transfer of any kind...", and that the Scheme Participant has full power and capacity to sell and transfer them: cl 7.3. I have no difficulty with a provision of that kind: see APN News &amp; Media Limited (2007) 25 ACLC 784 ( APN ) at [57] [63].

31 The Implementation Agreement contains "no shop" and break fee provisions. I discussed such provisions in APN 25 ACLC 784 at [25] [35] and [36] [55] respectively.

32 The affidavit of Jonathan Peter Callaghan, the Group General Counsel of the Investa Property Group, sworn 17 July 2007 deals at paras 23 26 with such provisions in the present case. The "no shop" provision (cl 14 of the Implementation Agreement) is to the effect that during a "No Shop Period" competing takeover proposals are not to be sought, and that if any are received, Morgan Stanley Bidco is to be given an opportunity to match them.

33 The break fee provision (cl 15 of the Implementation Agreement) is to the general effect that Investa will pay to Morgan Stanley Bidco a break fee of $20 million if, within nine months of the date of the Implementation Agreement, certain events occur. In general terms, these are that the proposed acquisition by Morgan Stanley Bidco fails for certain reasons, such as the acceptance of a competing takeover proposal. The break fee is not payable if the Investa Shareholders simply decide not to accept Morgan Stanley Bidco's offer.

34 Mr Callaghan's affidavit shows that the "no shop" and break fee provisions were agreed to by Investa following ordinary arm's length commercial negotiations between Investa and Morgan Stanley Bidco that were conducted over a period of two months, during which the parties were separately advised and represented by external legal advisers, and (in the case of Investa) by external financial advisers, with extensive experience of transactions of the present kind. Mr Callaghan states that Investa received legal advice on the operation of both provisions, and that Investa had regard to the guidelines set out in the Takeovers Panel Guidance Note 7 when it was negotiating and agreeing to them.

35 The amount of the break fee is $20 million which represents 0.49% of the equity value of the Securities as at 30 May 2007, and 0.43% of the total consideration offered by Morgan Stanley Bidco, including the eight cents per Security dividend or distribution to be paid to Security holders on 22 August 2007. Clearly, the amount of the break fee is well below the 1% of equity value referred to (at [7.18]) in the Takeovers Panel's Guidance Note 7: Lock-up Devices (2 nd Issue, 2005).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Archibald Howie Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Stamp Duties (NSW) [1948] HCA 28 ; (1948) 77 CLR 143</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1948/28.html</AustLII>
<text>26 A "share" is a legal chose in action that is constituted by a bundle of contractual rights and obligations and represents a person's interest in a company, and which, subject to the company's constitution and possibly other constraints, is transferable, transmissible and capable of devolution by will and by operation of law: see the Act s 1070A , and Borland's Trustee v Steel Bros &amp; Co Ltd [1901] 1 Ch 279 at 288; Commissioners of Inland Revenue v Crossman [1937] AC 26 at 66; Archibald Howie Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Stamp Duties (NSW) [1948] HCA 28 ; (1948) 77 CLR 143 at 157. Under general law principles, a buyer of a share enjoys priority over the holder of an earlier equitable interest because of the doctrine of bona fide purchaser of the legal estate without notice: see Meagher RP, Heydon JD and Leeming MJ, Meagher Gummow and Lehane's Equity Doctrines and Remedies (Butterworths LexisNexis, 2002) at [8-230] [8-300].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Borland's Trustee v Steel Bros &amp; Co Ltd [1901] 1 Ch 279</tocase>
<text>26 A "share" is a legal chose in action that is constituted by a bundle of contractual rights and obligations and represents a person's interest in a company, and which, subject to the company's constitution and possibly other constraints, is transferable, transmissible and capable of devolution by will and by operation of law: see the Act s 1070A , and Borland's Trustee v Steel Bros &amp; Co Ltd [1901] 1 Ch 279 at 288; Commissioners of Inland Revenue v Crossman [1937] AC 26 at 66; Archibald Howie Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Stamp Duties (NSW) [1948] HCA 28 ; (1948) 77 CLR 143 at 157. Under general law principles, a buyer of a share enjoys priority over the holder of an earlier equitable interest because of the doctrine of bona fide purchaser of the legal estate without notice: see Meagher RP, Heydon JD and Leeming MJ, Meagher Gummow and Lehane's Equity Doctrines and Remedies (Butterworths LexisNexis, 2002) at [8-230] [8-300].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioners of Inland Revenue v Crossman [1937] AC 26</tocase>
<text>26 A "share" is a legal chose in action that is constituted by a bundle of contractual rights and obligations and represents a person's interest in a company, and which, subject to the company's constitution and possibly other constraints, is transferable, transmissible and capable of devolution by will and by operation of law: see the Act s 1070A , and Borland's Trustee v Steel Bros &amp; Co Ltd [1901] 1 Ch 279 at 288; Commissioners of Inland Revenue v Crossman [1937] AC 26 at 66; Archibald Howie Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Stamp Duties (NSW) [1948] HCA 28 ; (1948) 77 CLR 143 at 157. Under general law principles, a buyer of a share enjoys priority over the holder of an earlier equitable interest because of the doctrine of bona fide purchaser of the legal estate without notice: see Meagher RP, Heydon JD and Leeming MJ, Meagher Gummow and Lehane's Equity Doctrines and Remedies (Butterworths LexisNexis, 2002) at [8-230] [8-300].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Kaz Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/738.html</AustLII>
<text>18 Morgan Stanley Bidco has executed a Deed Poll by which it has covenanted in favour of the Scheme Participants (the holders of Securities other than Excluded Securities) to carry out the obligations to be performed by it under the Share Scheme and the Unit Scheme. In a series of cases, Gyles J has noted that notwithstanding such a deed poll, it is unsatisfactory that persons whose shares have been acquired should have no remedy for non-performance by the acquiring company other than to sue it on the deed poll: see Re Kaz Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 526; Re SFE Corporation Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 82 ( SFE) .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re SFE Corporation Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 82</tocase>
<text>18 Morgan Stanley Bidco has executed a Deed Poll by which it has covenanted in favour of the Scheme Participants (the holders of Securities other than Excluded Securities) to carry out the obligations to be performed by it under the Share Scheme and the Unit Scheme. In a series of cases, Gyles J has noted that notwithstanding such a deed poll, it is unsatisfactory that persons whose shares have been acquired should have no remedy for non-performance by the acquiring company other than to sue it on the deed poll: see Re Kaz Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 526; Re SFE Corporation Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 82 ( SFE) .

19 In SFE 59 ACSR 82, Gyles J suggested that a scheme might provide for payment by the acquiring company to a trustee prior to the vesting of title to the shares in the acquiring company, to be held by the trustee for payment to the shareholders immediately following the vesting. In my experience, this procedure is now commonly followed, as it has been in the present case.

20 Accordingly, under cll 4.2 and 4.4 of the Share Scheme, on or before 12.00 noon on the Implementation Date, Morgan Stanley Bidco is to pay the aggregate Scheme consideration in cleared funds into an account in the name of Investa, to be held by Investa on trust for the Scheme Participants (except that any interest on the amount is to be for the account of Morgan Stanley Bidco) for the purpose of its being paid over to them by dispatch not later than the Implementation Date. Also by 12.00 noon on the Implementation Date Morgan Stanley Bidco is to provide a certificate signed by a director confirming that Morgan Stanley Bidco has made that payment. After 12.00 noon on the same date, and subject to receipt by Investa of that certificate, the Shares, other than the Excluded Shares (if any), together with the Units that are stapled to the Shares, are to be transferred to Morgan Stanley Bidco.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 526</tocase>
<text>18 Morgan Stanley Bidco has executed a Deed Poll by which it has covenanted in favour of the Scheme Participants (the holders of Securities other than Excluded Securities) to carry out the obligations to be performed by it under the Share Scheme and the Unit Scheme. In a series of cases, Gyles J has noted that notwithstanding such a deed poll, it is unsatisfactory that persons whose shares have been acquired should have no remedy for non-performance by the acquiring company other than to sue it on the deed poll: see Re Kaz Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 526; Re SFE Corporation Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 82 ( SFE) .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>WebCentral Group Limited (No 2) (2006) 58 ACSR 742</tocase>
<text>22 As distinct from the deemed warranty just mentioned, the Scheme also includes (in cl 7.3(b)) what may be called a "vesting free of encumbrances" term. I discussed such a term in WebCentral Group Limited (No 2) (2006) 58 ACSR 742 ( WebCentral ) at [14] [24], and will not repeat here what I said there.

23 The question that arises is whether, in the exercise of its discretion in an ex parte proceeding and without a contradictor, the Court should make an order for the convening of the meeting and later approving a scheme containing the particular term proposed.

24 Could the presence of the term detrimentally affect the interests held by third parties in the shares the subject of the scheme? If not, why have, or not have, the term as part of the scheme (see WebCentral 58 ACSR 742 at [20])? If so, should the Court support a term that can detrimentally affect the interests of third parties who have not been heard?

25 The effect of the Court's approval of a scheme agreed to by the requisite majorities in number and in value is that the scheme is binding on all members and on the company: s 411(4). As noted in WebCentral 58 ACSR 742 at [18], in substance the effect is to supply consent to be bound by the scheme, even of members who did not vote in favour of it. The vesting free of encumbrances term would be binding on all members. It would, however, leave the interests of third parties to be governed by general law principles. As noted below, those principles give very substantial protection to an acquiring company.

29 The vesting free of encumbrances term expressed in cl 7.3(b) of the Share Scheme incorporates a qualification in the light of the observations in WebCentral 58 ACSR 742. The term is as follows:
 
 To the extent permitted by law , all Investa Shares (including any rights and entitlements attaching to those shares) which are transferred to Morgan Stanley Bidco under this Investa Share Scheme will, at the date of the transfer of them to Morgan Stanley Bidco, vest in Morgan Stanley Bidco free from all mortgages, charges, liens, encumbrances and interests of third parties of any kind, whether legal or otherwise, and free from any restrictions on transfer of any kind not referred to in this Investa Share Scheme. 
 (Emphasis added.)

30 I regarded the opening words "To the extent permitted by law" as giving adequate notice that a third party would not suffer the extinguishment of an interest in shares if Morgan Stanley Bidco had had notice of that interest. I therefore took the view that those words overcame the difficulty referred to in WebCentral 58 ACSR 742, which was that the presence of a vesting free of encumbrances term might give the impression to third parties that their interests had been extinguished by the presence of the term where they would not have been in its absence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>