<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXKQ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1123 (3 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1123.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>11 An application for an extension of time was filed on 11 May 2007. Pursuant to O 52 r 15(2), the time limit may be extended for "special reasons". In Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187, a Full Court of this Court said at 195:
 
 "...the expression 'special reasons' is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is twenty-one days. But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will, for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in the particular case. Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary. We do not think the use of the expression 'for special reasons' implies something narrower than this."

12 The first applicant has sought to explain the minor delay in filing the notice of appeal. If this were all, I should be disposed to grant the extension that he seeks. Indeed, the first respondent does not object to the extension of the time for filing a notice of appeal. This is not, however, all. This is a case where the prospects of success on the appeal are insufficient to warrant the grant of an extension of time.

13 The applicants' purported notice of appeal filed on 27 April 2007 records the following grounds:
 
 1. His Honour erred in finding that the Refugee Review Tribunal considered whether the applicant was at risk of persecution because of his political associations. 
 
 2. His Honour erred in finding that the Refugee Review Tribunal's decision was not affected by jurisdictional error. 
 
 3. Further grounds and particulars to be provided upon provision of legal advice which is pending." 

As will be seen, the notice was vague and did not specify any grounds with particularity.

14 In written submissions filed on 24 July 2007, counsel for the applicants sought to make good this defect by raising the following grounds of appeal:
 
 1. The Tribunal erred in failing to take into account relevant considerations;
 2. The Tribunal breached s 424A of the Act;
 3. The Tribunal breached common law natural justice obligations; and
 4. The Tribunal failed to consider one of the integers of the applicants' case.

15 In the following consideration, I address each of these matters and others mentioned at the hearing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 70</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/70.html</AustLII>
<text>25 I have also found it unnecessary to consider an affidavit sworn by Pamela Anne Summers on 30 July 2007. The first respondent faced difficulties in seeking to rely on it. The affidavit was not in evidence in the Federal Magistrates Court, although, according to the first respondent, this point was not taken below. I doubt that the first respondent's reliance on s 79 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) was sustainable. I doubt that Ms Summers' familiarity with the practice and procedures of the Tribunal would constitute "specialised knowledge" upon which the opinion she gives can be said to be wholly or substantially based for the purposes of this provision: compare Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 70 at [106] - [107] per Black CJ, Emmett and Middleton JJ. The affidavit was not formally filed until the hearing, although, according to the first respondent, this was the result of the applicants' tardiness in filing their submissions. Ultimately, the first respondent did not press the tender of the affidavit, although counsel outlined a case for its admissibility, in the terms indicated.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/10.html</AustLII>
<text>26 At bottom, the gravamen of the applicants' complaint at the hearing was that the country information before the Tribunal should have led the Tribunal to conclude that the first applicant had a political profile that would have attracted the Chinese authorities' adverse attention if he returned to China. This is in essence to challenge the merits of the Tribunal's determination that the country information supported the contrary findings. This challenge, even if made out, would not support a finding of jurisdictional error. It is the Tribunal's responsibility to identify the country information upon which it rests its decision and to determine the weight to be given the various items of country information. This is not a concern of a Court on judicial review: compare NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10 at [11] per Gray, Tamberlin and Lander JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/1.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Further, it does not follow from the fact that the Tribunal made findings contrary to the first applicant's case, without specifically explaining why it preferred some information to other, that the Tribunal failed to consider the matters on which the first applicant relied. The law does not require the Tribunal to refute all items of evidence that are contrary to its findings of material fact: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 423 per McHugh J and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559 at 593 per Kirby J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/22.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Further, it does not follow from the fact that the Tribunal made findings contrary to the first applicant's case, without specifically explaining why it preferred some information to other, that the Tribunal failed to consider the matters on which the first applicant relied. The law does not require the Tribunal to refute all items of evidence that are contrary to its findings of material fact: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 423 per McHugh J and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559 at 593 per Kirby J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471</tocase>
<text>31 This evidence clearly comes within s 424A(3)(b) of the Act. By virtue of this provision, s 424A does not apply to information that the review applicant gave for the purpose of the application to the Tribunal. Further, in VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471, Finn and Stone JJ made it plain at 477 that the word 'information' "does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations...nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the Tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps".

32 The Tribunal also noted that the first applicant's evidence in his post-hearing submissions did not "correspond to the profile that [he] presented at the hearing or to the period that [he] has been in Australia". This evidence too comes within the exception in s 424A(3)(b). Finally, the Tribunal noted that:
 
 "...the applicant gave contradictory information at the hearing about his employment since his arrival in Australia. The Tribunal also notes the applicant's evidence that he did not lodge a protection visa application until eight years after his arrival because the Australian authorities do not publicise the success of applications. However, having regard to the above findings, the Tribunal need not reach a concluded view on this evidence." 

Again, it is plain enough that the exception in s 424A(3)(b) would apply and, in any event, this contradictory information did not play a part in the Tribunal's decision.

33 It seems, therefore, that to the extent that the Tribunal relied on inconsistencies in the first applicant's evidence, these inconsistencies arose from the applicant's evidence at the hearing and his submissions to the Tribunal. This material was plainly given by him to the Tribunal for the purpose of its review. Accordingly, s 424A was not engaged.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>