<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Capital Reserve Limited (Administrators Appointed) v High Tower Investments Pty Limited (Administrators Appointed); in the matter of High Tower Investments Pty Limited(Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1028 (6 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1028.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australasian Memory Pty Ltd v Brien [2000] HCA 30 ; (2000) 200 CLR 270</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/30.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The power granted by s 447A to make the order sought cannot be doubted. The width of that section was firmly established in Australasian Memory Pty Ltd v Brien [2000] HCA 30 ; (2000) 200 CLR 270 at 281 282 and has been applied in many circumstances since that time. Administrations vary greatly and s 447A provides the necessary flexibility if the object of Pt 5.3A set out in s 435A is to be realised.

16 The respondent EPG companies (by their administrators) appeared and consented to the orders sought. Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC) was advised of the intention to bring the proceeding and was supplied with draft documents. The responsible officer noted that ASIC took no formal position in relation to the application, it being a commercial matter for the parties, and advised that ASIC would not be appearing. No other party was served or given notice of the application.

17 As the administrators of the various companies represent the interests of unsecured creditors, the only other potential parties possibly affected are the other secured creditors of the relevant respondent EPG companies. I accepted the submission of counsel for the applicants that the interests of such creditors are not affected in a manner which would make them necessary parties to this application. The result of this application does not affect the rights of any secured creditor in relation to the enforcement of its security. However, it seemed to me that, rather than make an order applicable only to the charges held by ACR over property of the relevant EPG respondent companies, the extension should be in general terms so as to avoid any possible argument that any other secured creditor had been disadvantaged by a special deal. There was not time on 12 June 2007 for any great reflection about that matter and the form of this order should not be taken as a precedent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Patrick Stevedores Operations No 2 Pty Ltd v Maritime Union of Australia (No 3) [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 195 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/30.html</AustLII>
<text>12 The ACR Administrators did consider an alternative course, namely, to seek to enter a deed or some other form of agreement with the EPG Administrators under which they would give consent under s 440B(a) to ACR enforcing its securities after the "decision period" had expired. The ACR Administrators considered that there was a risk that a court would find that an agreement which fetters the future exercise of discretion and fiduciary obligations by administrators in such a manner would not be enforceable. (cf P Pan, "A Practical Comparison of Corporate Insolvency Procedures" in D Allen et al, Australian Finance Law , (5 th ed, Lawbook Co, 2002), Ch 27, at p 682; Re Java 452 Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed); Permanent Trustee Australia Ltd v Stout (1999) 32 ACSR 507; Patrick Stevedores Operations No 2 Pty Ltd v Maritime Union of Australia (No 3) [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 195 CLR 1 at [54] ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Java 452 Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed); Permanent Trustee Australia Ltd v Stout (1999) 32 ACSR 507</tocase>
<text>12 The ACR Administrators did consider an alternative course, namely, to seek to enter a deed or some other form of agreement with the EPG Administrators under which they would give consent under s 440B(a) to ACR enforcing its securities after the "decision period" had expired. The ACR Administrators considered that there was a risk that a court would find that an agreement which fetters the future exercise of discretion and fiduciary obligations by administrators in such a manner would not be enforceable. (cf P Pan, "A Practical Comparison of Corporate Insolvency Procedures" in D Allen et al, Australian Finance Law , (5 th ed, Lawbook Co, 2002), Ch 27, at p 682; Re Java 452 Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed); Permanent Trustee Australia Ltd v Stout (1999) 32 ACSR 507; Patrick Stevedores Operations No 2 Pty Ltd v Maritime Union of Australia (No 3) [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 195 CLR 1 at [54] ).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>