<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gardiner v Repatriation Commission [2007] FCA 1290 (21 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1290.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bull v Repatriation Commission (2001) 34 AAR 326</tocase>
<text>25 If there is no relevant SoP, s 120A(3) of the VE Act does not apply: s 120A(4). The third step must therefore be taken without reference to any SoP, in accordance with the approach summarised in Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564, at 571, per curiam :
 
 'The position may be summarized as follows: (1) First, sub-s. (3) of s. 120 is applied: do all or some of the facts raised by the material before the Commission give rise to a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's injury with war service? The hypothesis will not be reasonable if it is contrary to known scientific facts or is obviously fanciful or untenable. If the hypothesis is not reasonable, the claim fails. Proof of facts is not in issue at this point. (2) If a reasonable hypothesis is established, sub-s. (1) of s. 120 is applied. The claim will succeed unless: (a) one or more of the facts necessary to support the hypothesis are disproved beyond reasonable doubt; or (b) the truth of another fact in the material, which is inconsistent with the hypothesis, is proved beyond reasonable doubt, thus disproving, beyond reasonable doubt, the hypothesis'. 
 

See Woodward v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCAFC 160 ; (2003) 131 FCR 473, at 483 [55], per curiam ; Bull v Repatriation Commission (2001) 34 AAR 326, at 329-330 [13]-[15], per Emmett and Allsop JJ.

26 In Bull v Repatriation Commission , at 330 [16] Emmett and Allsop JJ regarded the exposition of a ' reasonable hypothesis ' in East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517, as authoritative. In East the Court said this (at 532-533):
 
 'The adoption of Brennan J's notion [in his dissenting judgment in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422] of a reasonable hypothesis meant that Parliament was requiring something by way of a causal link, but which fell short of proof of the link even prima facie as a fact. The meaning of the phrase "reasonable hypothesis" was felicitously explained by a Veterans' Review Board ... 
 
 
 
 "A hypothesis may be conveniently defined as : 'proposition made as basis for reasoning, without assumption of its truth; supposition made as starting point for further investigation from known facts; groundless assumption': The Concise Oxford Dictionary. 
 
 
 
 ...
 
 
 
 The addition of the word 'reasonable' would however seem to imply that what is required is more than a mere hypothesis. In the opinion of the Board, to be reasonable, a hypothesis must possess some degree of acceptability or credibility it must not be obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous. For a reasonable hypothesis to be 'raised' by material before the Board, we think it must find some support in that material that is, the material must point to, and not merely leave open, a hypothesis as a reasonable hypothesis. At the same time, however, a hypothesis may be reasonable without having been proved (either on the balance of probability or beyond reasonable doubt) to be correct as a matter of fact. Were it otherwise, it would no longer be a hypothesis but would have been elevated to some higher status. Accordingly a connection asserted by a hypothesis to exist between death or incapacity and service may still be reasonable even though theoretical, and it may be theoretical in either or both of a least two senses: by postulating a known medical fact but in circumstances not known to have definitely existed in the instant case; or by postulating a medical principle which science is not yet able to definitely prove but is unable to describe as unreasonable." 
 
 
 
 We agree with this analysis. A reasonable hypothesis requires more than a possibility, not fanciful or unreal, consistent with the known facts. It is an hypothesis pointed to by the facts, even though not proved upon the balance of probabilities '. (Emphasis added.)

27 In Bull v Repatriation Commission , Emmett and Allsop JJ made the following comment (at 331 [18]) about East :
 
 'The Court said that an hypothesis is not reasonable if it is obviously fanciful or impossible or incredible or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous. However, the Full Court did not say that if an hypothesis was not obviously fanciful or not impossible, or not incredible or tenable or not too remote or not too tenuous, it was therefore necessarily reasonable. The material must point to the connecting hypothesis ...' (Emphasis in original.)
 

Their Honours observed (at 331 [21]) that there is no doubt that the AAT is obliged to look at all the material, not just some of it and that at this point it is not entitled to find facts or reject matters.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 48 ; (1993) 177 CLR 574</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/48.html</AustLII>
<text>25 If there is no relevant SoP, s 120A(3) of the VE Act does not apply: s 120A(4). The third step must therefore be taken without reference to any SoP, in accordance with the approach summarised in Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564, at 571, per curiam :
 
 'The position may be summarized as follows: (1) First, sub-s. (3) of s. 120 is applied: do all or some of the facts raised by the material before the Commission give rise to a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's injury with war service? The hypothesis will not be reasonable if it is contrary to known scientific facts or is obviously fanciful or untenable. If the hypothesis is not reasonable, the claim fails. Proof of facts is not in issue at this point. (2) If a reasonable hypothesis is established, sub-s. (1) of s. 120 is applied. The claim will succeed unless: (a) one or more of the facts necessary to support the hypothesis are disproved beyond reasonable doubt; or (b) the truth of another fact in the material, which is inconsistent with the hypothesis, is proved beyond reasonable doubt, thus disproving, beyond reasonable doubt, the hypothesis'. 
 

See Woodward v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCAFC 160 ; (2003) 131 FCR 473, at 483 [55], per curiam ; Bull v Repatriation Commission (2001) 34 AAR 326, at 329-330 [13]-[15], per Emmett and Allsop JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Caswell v Powell Duffryn Associated Collieries Limited [1940] AC 152</tocase>
<text>17 The AAT continued as follows:
 
 '18. Apart from his lumbar spondylosis the deceased suffered from other non-war caused illnesses including osteoarthritis of the sacroiliac joints and osteoarthritis of the knee joints. It seems to us that those conditions would also have played their part in the deceased's inability to exit the tractor. 
 
 19. Ten weeks prior to the accident the deceased had obtained a prescription for an anti-depressant and an analgesic. Again nothing is known as to the frequency with which the deceased availed himself of this mediation and if he had taken any on the day of his death. If he had taken an anti-depressant this may have affected his reaction time. 
 
 20. We agree with the Applicant that the material before us has raised an hypothesis, however the real question is whether given all the material before us, the hypothesis can be said to be a reasonable one. 
 
 21. Although facts may be assumed for the purpose of constructing an hypothesis, a distinction must be made between assumed facts on the one hand and speculation and conjecture on the other. 
 
 22. The fact situation and statement of law by Wright LJ in Caswell v Powell Duffryn Associated Collieries Limited [1940] AC 152 at 169 is particularly apposite in this matter, namely: 
 
 
 
 My Lords, the precise manner in which the accident occurred cannot be ascertained as the unfortunate young man was alone when he was killed. The Court therefore is left to inference or circumstantial evidence. Inference must be carefully distinguished from conjecture or speculation. There can be no inference unless there are objective facts from which to infer the other facts which it is sought to establish. In come cases the other facts can be inferred with as much practical certainty as if they had been actually observed. In other cases the inference does not go beyond reasonable probability. But if there are no positive proved facts from which the inference can be made, the method of inference fails and what is left is mere speculation or conjecture.
 
 
 
 23. As we have previously pointed out, facts may be assumed for the purpose of constructing an hypothesis. However in this case, all that is known is that the deceased suffered from war-caused lumbar spondylosis amongst other diseases which would have limited mobility, and had obtained a prescription for anti-depressant medication. He was killed when a tractor he was driving rolled over. To then say that it was his lumbar spondylosis that prevented him jumping clear of the tractor so as to avoid fatal injury when all he had was one to two seconds in which to take that action is, on what is known in this matter, mere speculation and incapable of raising an hypothesis properly categorised as reasonable'.

18 Accordingly, the AAT affirmed the decision under review.

19 In his written submissions, Mr Vincent, who appeared for the applicant, accepted that a finding as to whether a reasonable hypothesis has or has not been raised is a question of fact. However, he argued that the authorities establish that the AAT, when considering whether a reasonable hypothesis has been raised, is not entitled to find facts, prefer certain material, resolve conflicts or reject matters.

38 I should mention one other matter. The applicant sought to derive comfort from the AAT's reference in its reasons to the distinction between assumed facts and conjecture. According to Mr Vincent, the AAT's citation of Caswell v Powell Duffryn showed that the AAT was purporting to make a finding of fact on the balance of probabilities.

39 I read the AAT's reference as intended merely to indicate that something more than conjecture or speculation is required before a hypothesis can be characterised as reasonable. I do not read the AAT's citation of Caswell v Powell Duffryn as indicating that it was making impermissible findings of fact, whether on the balance of probabilities or otherwise. The AAT was only saying what the authorities have said: the material before the AAT must point to the connecting hypothesis, rather than the connection remaining purely in the realm of conjecture or speculation.

40 The applicant has failed to establish that the AAT erred in law. The application must be dismissed, with costs.

 I certify that the preceding forty (40) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Sackville. 

 Associate:

Dated: 21 August 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr M Vincent 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Dibbs Abbott Stillman 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms J MacDonnell 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 15 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 August 2007 




 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1290.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Collins v Administrative Appeals Tribunal [1007] FCAFC 111</tocase>
<text>24 The approach to be taken to the operation of ss 120 and 120A of the VE Act was authoritatively laid down by the Full Federal Court in Repatriation Commission v Deledio (1998) 83 FCR 82: see Collins v Administrative Appeals Tribunal [2007] FCAFC 111 , at [5], per Lindgren J; at [30], per Allsop J. The relevant passage in Deledio is as follows (at 97-98):
 
 '1. The Tribunal must consider all the material which is before it and determine whether that material points to a hypothesis connecting the injury, disease or death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the person. No question of fact finding arises at this stage. If no such hypothesis arises, the application must fail. 
 
 2. If the material does raise such a hypothesis, the Tribunal must then ascertain whether there is in force an SoP [Statement of Principles] determined by the Authority ... 
 
 3. If an SoP is in force, the Tribunal must then form the opinion whether the hypothesis raised is a reasonable one. It will do so if the hypothesis fits, that is to say, is consistent with the "template" to be found in the SoP ... If the hypothesis fails to fit within the template, it will be deemed not to be "reasonable" and the claim will fail. 
 
 4. The Tribunal must then proceed to consider under s 120(1) whether it is satisfied beyond reasonable doubt that the death was not war-caused, or in the case of a claim for incapacity, that the incapacity did not arise from a war-caused injury. If not so satisfied, the claim must succeed. If the Tribunal is so satisfied, the claim must fail. It is only at this stage of the process that the Tribunal will be required to find facts from the material before it. In so doing, no question of onus of proof or the application of any presumption will be involved'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517</tocase>
<text>26 In Bull v Repatriation Commission , at 330 [16] Emmett and Allsop JJ regarded the exposition of a ' reasonable hypothesis ' in East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517, as authoritative. In East the Court said this (at 532-533):
 
 'The adoption of Brennan J's notion [in his dissenting judgment in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422] of a reasonable hypothesis meant that Parliament was requiring something by way of a causal link, but which fell short of proof of the link even prima facie as a fact. The meaning of the phrase "reasonable hypothesis" was felicitously explained by a Veterans' Review Board ... 
 
 
 
 "A hypothesis may be conveniently defined as : 'proposition made as basis for reasoning, without assumption of its truth; supposition made as starting point for further investigation from known facts; groundless assumption': The Concise Oxford Dictionary. 
 
 
 
 ...
 
 
 
 The addition of the word 'reasonable' would however seem to imply that what is required is more than a mere hypothesis. In the opinion of the Board, to be reasonable, a hypothesis must possess some degree of acceptability or credibility it must not be obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous. For a reasonable hypothesis to be 'raised' by material before the Board, we think it must find some support in that material that is, the material must point to, and not merely leave open, a hypothesis as a reasonable hypothesis. At the same time, however, a hypothesis may be reasonable without having been proved (either on the balance of probability or beyond reasonable doubt) to be correct as a matter of fact. Were it otherwise, it would no longer be a hypothesis but would have been elevated to some higher status. Accordingly a connection asserted by a hypothesis to exist between death or incapacity and service may still be reasonable even though theoretical, and it may be theoretical in either or both of a least two senses: by postulating a known medical fact but in circumstances not known to have definitely existed in the instant case; or by postulating a medical principle which science is not yet able to definitely prove but is unable to describe as unreasonable." 
 
 
 
 We agree with this analysis. A reasonable hypothesis requires more than a possibility, not fanciful or unreal, consistent with the known facts. It is an hypothesis pointed to by the facts, even though not proved upon the balance of probabilities '. (Emphasis added.)

27 In Bull v Repatriation Commission , Emmett and Allsop JJ made the following comment (at 331 [18]) about East :
 
 'The Court said that an hypothesis is not reasonable if it is obviously fanciful or impossible or incredible or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous. However, the Full Court did not say that if an hypothesis was not obviously fanciful or not impossible, or not incredible or tenable or not too remote or not too tenuous, it was therefore necessarily reasonable. The material must point to the connecting hypothesis ...' (Emphasis in original.)
 

Their Honours observed (at 331 [21]) that there is no doubt that the AAT is obliged to look at all the material, not just some of it and that at this point it is not entitled to find facts or reject matters.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Deledio (1998) 83 FCR 82</tocase>
<text>24 The approach to be taken to the operation of ss 120 and 120A of the VE Act was authoritatively laid down by the Full Federal Court in Repatriation Commission v Deledio (1998) 83 FCR 82: see Collins v Administrative Appeals Tribunal [2007] FCAFC 111 , at [5], per Lindgren J; at [30], per Allsop J. The relevant passage in Deledio is as follows (at 97-98):
 
 '1. The Tribunal must consider all the material which is before it and determine whether that material points to a hypothesis connecting the injury, disease or death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the person. No question of fact finding arises at this stage. If no such hypothesis arises, the application must fail. 
 
 2. If the material does raise such a hypothesis, the Tribunal must then ascertain whether there is in force an SoP [Statement of Principles] determined by the Authority ... 
 
 3. If an SoP is in force, the Tribunal must then form the opinion whether the hypothesis raised is a reasonable one. It will do so if the hypothesis fits, that is to say, is consistent with the "template" to be found in the SoP ... If the hypothesis fails to fit within the template, it will be deemed not to be "reasonable" and the claim will fail. 
 
 4. The Tribunal must then proceed to consider under s 120(1) whether it is satisfied beyond reasonable doubt that the death was not war-caused, or in the case of a claim for incapacity, that the incapacity did not arise from a war-caused injury. If not so satisfied, the claim must succeed. If the Tribunal is so satisfied, the claim must fail. It is only at this stage of the process that the Tribunal will be required to find facts from the material before it. In so doing, no question of onus of proof or the application of any presumption will be involved'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/10.html</AustLII>
<text>26 In Bull v Repatriation Commission , at 330 [16] Emmett and Allsop JJ regarded the exposition of a ' reasonable hypothesis ' in East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517, as authoritative. In East the Court said this (at 532-533):
 
 'The adoption of Brennan J's notion [in his dissenting judgment in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422] of a reasonable hypothesis meant that Parliament was requiring something by way of a causal link, but which fell short of proof of the link even prima facie as a fact. The meaning of the phrase "reasonable hypothesis" was felicitously explained by a Veterans' Review Board ... 
 
 
 
 "A hypothesis may be conveniently defined as : 'proposition made as basis for reasoning, without assumption of its truth; supposition made as starting point for further investigation from known facts; groundless assumption': The Concise Oxford Dictionary. 
 
 
 
 ...
 
 
 
 The addition of the word 'reasonable' would however seem to imply that what is required is more than a mere hypothesis. In the opinion of the Board, to be reasonable, a hypothesis must possess some degree of acceptability or credibility it must not be obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous. For a reasonable hypothesis to be 'raised' by material before the Board, we think it must find some support in that material that is, the material must point to, and not merely leave open, a hypothesis as a reasonable hypothesis. At the same time, however, a hypothesis may be reasonable without having been proved (either on the balance of probability or beyond reasonable doubt) to be correct as a matter of fact. Were it otherwise, it would no longer be a hypothesis but would have been elevated to some higher status. Accordingly a connection asserted by a hypothesis to exist between death or incapacity and service may still be reasonable even though theoretical, and it may be theoretical in either or both of a least two senses: by postulating a known medical fact but in circumstances not known to have definitely existed in the instant case; or by postulating a medical principle which science is not yet able to definitely prove but is unable to describe as unreasonable." 
 
 
 
 We agree with this analysis. A reasonable hypothesis requires more than a possibility, not fanciful or unreal, consistent with the known facts. It is an hypothesis pointed to by the facts, even though not proved upon the balance of probabilities '. (Emphasis added.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Woodward v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCAFC 160 ; (2003) 131 FCR 473</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/160.html</AustLII>
<text>25 If there is no relevant SoP, s 120A(3) of the VE Act does not apply: s 120A(4). The third step must therefore be taken without reference to any SoP, in accordance with the approach summarised in Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564, at 571, per curiam :
 
 'The position may be summarized as follows: (1) First, sub-s. (3) of s. 120 is applied: do all or some of the facts raised by the material before the Commission give rise to a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's injury with war service? The hypothesis will not be reasonable if it is contrary to known scientific facts or is obviously fanciful or untenable. If the hypothesis is not reasonable, the claim fails. Proof of facts is not in issue at this point. (2) If a reasonable hypothesis is established, sub-s. (1) of s. 120 is applied. The claim will succeed unless: (a) one or more of the facts necessary to support the hypothesis are disproved beyond reasonable doubt; or (b) the truth of another fact in the material, which is inconsistent with the hypothesis, is proved beyond reasonable doubt, thus disproving, beyond reasonable doubt, the hypothesis'. 
 

See Woodward v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCAFC 160 ; (2003) 131 FCR 473, at 483 [55], per curiam ; Bull v Repatriation Commission (2001) 34 AAR 326, at 329-330 [13]-[15], per Emmett and Allsop JJ.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>