<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Futuretronics.com.au Pty Limited v Graphix Labels Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1621 (29 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1621.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Amoco Australia Pty Ltd v Rocca Bros Motor Engineering Co Pty Ltd [1973] HCA 40 ; (1973) 133 CLR 288</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1973/40.html</AustLII>
<text>134 In the circumstances, it is unnecessary to address a further argument put by Graphix Labels and Mr Atta against implying such a term and that was that such a term would amount to an unreasonable restraint of trade. I was referred to Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535; Amoco Australia Pty Ltd v Rocca Bros Motor Engineering Co Pty Ltd [1973] HCA 40 ; (1973) 133 CLR 288. Of course, there have been a number of cases dealing with the common law doctrine of restraint of trade since those two cases (see, for example, the discussion in Seddon and Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Australian ed, 2002) pages 860-863).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ansell Rubber Co Pty Ltd v Allied Rubber Industries Pty Ltd [1967] VR 37</tocase>
<text>154 I do not think that Pioneer Concrete is of assistance on the present point. The issue there was an alleged breach of restraint of trade covenants and required the Court to consider the difference between acts preparatory to the carrying on of a business and carrying on a business. Independent Management is more helpful. The plaintiff in that case alleged that a former employee had misused confidential information obtained during her employment and had breached her duty of fidelity. The employee had successfully tendered for a contract previously held by the plaintiff. Marks J said that the skill and information gained by the defendant was outside the protected category. He referred to the following observations of Gowans J in Ansell Rubber Co Pty Ltd v Allied Rubber Industries Pty Ltd [1967] VR 37 (at 40):
 
 In this field a distinction has to be maintained between information and knowledge acquired in confidence by an employee during his employment which he uses or discloses for his own advantage while he is still an employee, and information and knowledge so acquired which he uses for his own advantage after his employment is finished. A further distinction has to be drawn between information which forms part of the employee's stock of general knowledge, skill and experience, and that which should fairly be regarded as a separate part of the employee's stock of knowledge (whether it be identifiable as "particular" or "detailed" or "special") which a man of ordinary intelligence and honesty would regard as the property of the former employer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Blyth Chemicals v Bushnell [1933] HCA 8 ; (1933) 49 CLR 66</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1933/8.html</AustLII>
<text>151 An employee owes a duty of fidelity and good faith to his employer. That duty arises as a matter of an implied term of the contract of employment: Robb v Green [1895] 2 QB 315 at 317 per Lord Esher MR. As part of the duty of fidelity and good faith, an employee owes certain duties of confidentiality: Blyth Chemicals v Bushnell [1933] HCA 8 ; (1933) 49 CLR 66.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/40.html</AustLII>
<text>120 In the case of a formal contract a party alleging an implied term must show the following:
 
 1. The term must be reasonable and equitable; 
 
 
 2. The term must be necessary to give business efficacy to the contract, so that no term will be implied if the contract is effective without it;
 3. The term must be so obvious that "it goes without saying";
 4. The term must be capable of clear expression; and
 5. The term must not contradict any express term of the contract. 
 

 BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266; Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Railway Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 at 346 per Mason J (as he then was); Gold Peg International Pty Ltd v Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd (2005) IPR 497 (" Gold Peg ").

123 The differences between the test for a formal contract and the test for an informal contract are not easy to identify with precision. In addition to the matters identified in Hawkins v Clayton and Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd it may be assumed that even in the case of an informal contract a term will be implied only if it is capable of clear expression and does not contradict an express term of the contract. The authors of Contract Law in Australia (5 th ed, 2007) JW Carter, E Peden and GJ Tolhurst at 223-224 [11-06] suggest that the matters identified in BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (supra) are, in the case of an informal contract, "more in the nature of factors to be considered than essential requirements".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd [1995] HCA 24 ; (1995) 185 CLR 410</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/24.html</AustLII>
<text>122 That passage was cited with approval by the majority (Brennan CJ, Dawson and Toohey JJ) in Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd [1995] HCA 24 ; (1995) 185 CLR 410 at 422. In that case, their Honours went on to reject the alleged implied term on the ground that the contract was capable of operating reasonably and effectively in the absence of the term.

123 The differences between the test for a formal contract and the test for an informal contract are not easy to identify with precision. In addition to the matters identified in Hawkins v Clayton and Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd it may be assumed that even in the case of an informal contract a term will be implied only if it is capable of clear expression and does not contradict an express term of the contract. The authors of Contract Law in Australia (5 th ed, 2007) JW Carter, E Peden and GJ Tolhurst at 223-224 [11-06] suggest that the matters identified in BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (supra) are, in the case of an informal contract, "more in the nature of factors to be considered than essential requirements".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Railway Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/24.html</AustLII>
<text>120 In the case of a formal contract a party alleging an implied term must show the following:
 
 1. The term must be reasonable and equitable; 
 
 
 2. The term must be necessary to give business efficacy to the contract, so that no term will be implied if the contract is effective without it;
 3. The term must be so obvious that "it goes without saying";
 4. The term must be capable of clear expression; and
 5. The term must not contradict any express term of the contract. 
 

 BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266; Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Railway Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 at 346 per Mason J (as he then was); Gold Peg International Pty Ltd v Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd (2005) IPR 497 (" Gold Peg ").</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Concut Pty Ltd v Worrell (2000) 176 ALR 693</tocase>
<text>152 In addition to the duty of fidelity and good faith arising as a matter of contract, an employee may owe similar duties because the relationship is a fiduciary one or because the elements of ss 182 or 183 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) are made out. The relationship between employee and employer is one of the accepted fiduciary relationships ( Concut Pty Ltd v Worrell (2000) 176 ALR 693) but not every obligation undertaken by an employee is fiduciary in character ( Nottingham University v Fishal [2000] ICR 1462). Within the fiduciary duties is a duty on an employee to act in his employer's interests and not in his own interests at the expense of his employer and also a duty not to misuse confidential information. The duties are not absolute however, and an employee is able to do certain things in preparation for his new employment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Corrs Pavey Whiting and Byrne v Collector of Customs (1987) 14 FCR 434</tocase>
<text>168 As far as the confidentiality agreement is concerned, Mr Atta made the following submissions:
 
 
 1. The confidentiality agreement is void for uncertainty because it contains only an inclusive and not an exclusive definition of confidential information. Reading down or severance is not possible.
 2. The confidentiality agreement is a restraint on competition and void as against public policy because it purports to go beyond what may be lawfully protected. Mr Atta referred to the decision in Wright v Gasweld Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 317. Again, it is said that reading down or severance is not possible.
 3. As I understood it, the submission was that even in the case of a confidentiality agreement which purports to define confidential information a party complaining of a breach of such an agreement must prove the information disclosed was in fact confidential. Reference was made to the requirements in equity for the protection of confidential information: Corrs Pavey Whiting and Byrne v Collector of Customs (1987) 14 FCR 434 at 443 per Gummow J. There is no evidence that the information was confidential and Mr Atta said that it was not confidential.
 4. The information disclosed [to THQ and Cygnett] was disclosed after Mr Atta had left the company's employ.
 5. There is no pleading of loss which could conceivably flow from a breach of the confidentiality agreement. There is a claim for damages for breach of the confidentiality agreement, but the only claim for loss and damage particularised in the statement of claim relates (so it is said) to the alleged breach of the implied term.

170 I do not think the submission in paragraph 3 is right. In the case referred to Gummow J identified the elements of an equitable action for breach of confidence. His Honour was not dealing with a claim for breach of contract by disclosing confidential information as defined in the agreement. There is nothing to suggest that subject to restraint of trade considerations the parties cannot define for themselves what is confidential. They are not bound to protect no more than is already protected in equity.

171 The submission in paragraph 4 cannot succeed because the confidentiality agreement specifically purports to apply to the period after Mr Atta has left the employ of Futuretronics.

172 The submission in paragraph 5 is essentially a pleading point which I would not allow Mr Atta to raise at this late stage or at least without giving Futuretronics the opportunity to apply to further amend.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Forkserve Pty Ltd v Pachiaratta (2000 40 IPR 74</tocase>
<text>159 In Forkserve Pty Ltd v Pachiaratta (2000) 40 IPR 74, Young J considered the obligations of a former employee in terms of general knowledge and skills acquired while he was an employee and confidential information acquired while he was an employee. Two propositions emerge from the case which I accept as correctly stating the law. First, Young J said, after referring to the Restraint of Trade Doctrine , JD Heydon (2 nd ed, 1999) at 80, that an employee can approach a customer or client whose name he can recall without a list or deliberate memorisation. Secondly, by reference to one of his own previous decisions Rosetex Company Pty Ltd v Licata (1994) 12 ACSR 779 his Honour said that the general coverage of the predecessors of ss 182 and 183 "are not to any major extent wider than the duties under the general rules of equity".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wright v Gasweld Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 317</tocase>
<text>168 As far as the confidentiality agreement is concerned, Mr Atta made the following submissions:
 
 
 1. The confidentiality agreement is void for uncertainty because it contains only an inclusive and not an exclusive definition of confidential information. Reading down or severance is not possible.
 2. The confidentiality agreement is a restraint on competition and void as against public policy because it purports to go beyond what may be lawfully protected. Mr Atta referred to the decision in Wright v Gasweld Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 317. Again, it is said that reading down or severance is not possible.
 3. As I understood it, the submission was that even in the case of a confidentiality agreement which purports to define confidential information a party complaining of a breach of such an agreement must prove the information disclosed was in fact confidential. Reference was made to the requirements in equity for the protection of confidential information: Corrs Pavey Whiting and Byrne v Collector of Customs (1987) 14 FCR 434 at 443 per Gummow J. There is no evidence that the information was confidential and Mr Atta said that it was not confidential.
 4. The information disclosed [to THQ and Cygnett] was disclosed after Mr Atta had left the company's employ.
 5. There is no pleading of loss which could conceivably flow from a breach of the confidentiality agreement. There is a claim for damages for breach of the confidentiality agreement, but the only claim for loss and damage particularised in the statement of claim relates (so it is said) to the alleged breach of the implied term.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Gold Peg International Pty Ltd v Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd (2005) IPR 497</tocase>
<text>120 In the case of a formal contract a party alleging an implied term must show the following:
 
 1. The term must be reasonable and equitable; 
 
 
 2. The term must be necessary to give business efficacy to the contract, so that no term will be implied if the contract is effective without it;
 3. The term must be so obvious that "it goes without saying";
 4. The term must be capable of clear expression; and
 5. The term must not contradict any express term of the contract. 
 

 BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266; Codelfa Construction Pty Ltd v State Railway Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 at 346 per Mason J (as he then was); Gold Peg International Pty Ltd v Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd (2005) IPR 497 (" Gold Peg ").</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hawkins v Clayton [1988] HCA 15 ; (1988) 164 CLR 539</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/15.html</AustLII>
<text>121 A formal contract is one which appears complete on its face. The test is not as stringent in the case of an informal contract. The contract or contracts in this case are informal contracts. In Hawkins v Clayton [1988] HCA 15 ; (1988) 164 CLR 539, Deane J said (at 573):
 
 The most that can be said consistently with the need for some degree of flexibility is that, in a case where it is apparent that the parties have not attempted to spell out the full terms of their contract, a court should imply a term by reference to the imputed intention of the parties if, but only if, it can be seen that the implication of the particular term is necessary for the reasonable or effective operation of a contract of that nature in the circumstances of the case. That general statement of principle is subject to the qualification that a term may be implied in a contract by established mercantile usage or professional practice or by a past course of dealing between the parties.

123 The differences between the test for a formal contract and the test for an informal contract are not easy to identify with precision. In addition to the matters identified in Hawkins v Clayton and Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd it may be assumed that even in the case of an informal contract a term will be implied only if it is capable of clear expression and does not contradict an express term of the contract. The authors of Contract Law in Australia (5 th ed, 2007) JW Carter, E Peden and GJ Tolhurst at 223-224 [11-06] suggest that the matters identified in BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (supra) are, in the case of an informal contract, "more in the nature of factors to be considered than essential requirements".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Independent Management Resources Pty Ltd v Brown [1987] VR 605</tocase>
<text>153 In this context the respondents referred to Pioneer Concrete Services Ltd v Galli [1985] VR 675 (" Pioneer Concrete ") and Independent Management Resources Pty Ltd v Brown [1987] VR 605 (" Independent Management ").

154 I do not think that Pioneer Concrete is of assistance on the present point. The issue there was an alleged breach of restraint of trade covenants and required the Court to consider the difference between acts preparatory to the carrying on of a business and carrying on a business. Independent Management is more helpful. The plaintiff in that case alleged that a former employee had misused confidential information obtained during her employment and had breached her duty of fidelity. The employee had successfully tendered for a contract previously held by the plaintiff. Marks J said that the skill and information gained by the defendant was outside the protected category. He referred to the following observations of Gowans J in Ansell Rubber Co Pty Ltd v Allied Rubber Industries Pty Ltd [1967] VR 37 (at 40):
 
 In this field a distinction has to be maintained between information and knowledge acquired in confidence by an employee during his employment which he uses or discloses for his own advantage while he is still an employee, and information and knowledge so acquired which he uses for his own advantage after his employment is finished. A further distinction has to be drawn between information which forms part of the employee's stock of general knowledge, skill and experience, and that which should fairly be regarded as a separate part of the employee's stock of knowledge (whether it be identifiable as "particular" or "detailed" or "special") which a man of ordinary intelligence and honesty would regard as the property of the former employer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd v Gold Peg International Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 117</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/117.html</AustLII>
<text>131 Futuretronics relied on the decision of Crennan J in Gold Peg . That case went on appeal: Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd v Gold Peg International Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 117 but the appeal was dismissed and there was no suggestion by the Full Court that her Honour erred in her approach. The applicant was the inventor of the Direct Steam Injection Cooking Machine (the DSI Cooker). The first respondent was a manufacturer of the DSI Cooker. The principal issue in the case was the ownership of the copyright used in the development and manufacture of the DSI Cooker. That was resolved in favour of the applicant. Her Honour also addressed whether terms could be implied to the following effect:
 
 
 (e) Kovan would not make any use of and would keep confidential the Assigned Rights and the drawings created by Kovan to manufacture the cooking machines for Gold Peg; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 (f) Kovan would not use the Assigned Rights and the drawings created by Kovan to manufacture the cooking machines other than for manufacturing cooking machines for Gold Peg to its order. 
 
 
 

In dealing with those issues her Honour said:
 
 "I am also satisfied that it is necessary to imply a term into the agreement that the first respondent would not make any use on its own behalf of, and would keep confidential, the Alfa Laval Drawings and the drawings created by the first respondent to manufacture the machines. This is a clear matter of business efficacy; the applicant would not have been able to maintain its rights to exclusively manufacture its machine if its manufacturer were to assert rights in the drawings against it or to refuse to maintain confidence in the drawings. I am also satisfied that the first respondent would never have been retained by the applicant to undertake manufacture for it if the first respondent had sought to debate these issues. I am also satisfied Mr Miller and Mr Zakis well understood this at the time of commencement of manufacture for the applicant.
 
 Similarly, I am satisfied that it is appropriate as a matter of business efficacy to imply a term that the first respondent would not use the Alfa Laval Drawings or the manufacturing drawings it created to manufacture cooking machines for the applicant other than for the purposes of manufacturing for the applicant. This term was, in any event, partly oral and was agreed to by Mr Smith and Mr Miller in around 1992. Both Mr Miller and Mr Zakis confirmed this was their understanding of the general agreement between the parties for the manufacture of cooking machines by the first respondent to the order and specification of the applicant."

132 In my opinion, Gold Peg is clearly distinguishable from the present case. The terms in Gold Peg related to the use of drawings of the DSI Cooker either in existence or to be brought into existence. They or their forerunners were technical drawings in respect of which patent applications had been made. In this case the implied term does not relate to drawings but rather to an idea which did not involve a patentable invention or confidential information.

133 In my opinion, the fact that the product was not unique and does not involve confidential information, the fact that the contract or contracts between Futuretronics and Graphix Labels were not for a set term and did not involve a minimum quantity and the fact that the proposed term was so general indicate that it is not appropriate to imply a term of the nature advanced by Futuretronics. It is not necessary for the reasonable or effective operation of the contracts constituted by each order to imply such a term.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535</tocase>
<text>134 In the circumstances, it is unnecessary to address a further argument put by Graphix Labels and Mr Atta against implying such a term and that was that such a term would amount to an unreasonable restraint of trade. I was referred to Nordenfelt v Maxim Nordenfelt Guns and Ammunition Co Ltd [1894] AC 535; Amoco Australia Pty Ltd v Rocca Bros Motor Engineering Co Pty Ltd [1973] HCA 40 ; (1973) 133 CLR 288. Of course, there have been a number of cases dealing with the common law doctrine of restraint of trade since those two cases (see, for example, the discussion in Seddon and Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Australian ed, 2002) pages 860-863).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Nottingham University v Fishal [2000] ICR 1462</tocase>
<text>152 In addition to the duty of fidelity and good faith arising as a matter of contract, an employee may owe similar duties because the relationship is a fiduciary one or because the elements of ss 182 or 183 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) are made out. The relationship between employee and employer is one of the accepted fiduciary relationships ( Concut Pty Ltd v Worrell (2000) 176 ALR 693) but not every obligation undertaken by an employee is fiduciary in character ( Nottingham University v Fishal [2000] ICR 1462). Within the fiduciary duties is a duty on an employee to act in his employer's interests and not in his own interests at the expense of his employer and also a duty not to misuse confidential information. The duties are not absolute however, and an employee is able to do certain things in preparation for his new employment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Pioneer Concrete Services Ltd v Galli [1985] VR 675</tocase>
<text>153 In this context the respondents referred to Pioneer Concrete Services Ltd v Galli [1985] VR 675 (" Pioneer Concrete ") and Independent Management Resources Pty Ltd v Brown [1987] VR 605 (" Independent Management ").

154 I do not think that Pioneer Concrete is of assistance on the present point. The issue there was an alleged breach of restraint of trade covenants and required the Court to consider the difference between acts preparatory to the carrying on of a business and carrying on a business. Independent Management is more helpful. The plaintiff in that case alleged that a former employee had misused confidential information obtained during her employment and had breached her duty of fidelity. The employee had successfully tendered for a contract previously held by the plaintiff. Marks J said that the skill and information gained by the defendant was outside the protected category. He referred to the following observations of Gowans J in Ansell Rubber Co Pty Ltd v Allied Rubber Industries Pty Ltd [1967] VR 37 (at 40):
 
 In this field a distinction has to be maintained between information and knowledge acquired in confidence by an employee during his employment which he uses or discloses for his own advantage while he is still an employee, and information and knowledge so acquired which he uses for his own advantage after his employment is finished. A further distinction has to be drawn between information which forms part of the employee's stock of general knowledge, skill and experience, and that which should fairly be regarded as a separate part of the employee's stock of knowledge (whether it be identifiable as "particular" or "detailed" or "special") which a man of ordinary intelligence and honesty would regard as the property of the former employer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Robb v Green [1895] 2 QB 316</tocase>
<text>151 An employee owes a duty of fidelity and good faith to his employer. That duty arises as a matter of an implied term of the contract of employment: Robb v Green [1895] 2 QB 315 at 317 per Lord Esher MR. As part of the duty of fidelity and good faith, an employee owes certain duties of confidentiality: Blyth Chemicals v Bushnell [1933] HCA 8 ; (1933) 49 CLR 66.

155 Marks J then considered the allegation that the defendant had breached her duty of fidelity to the plaintiff. He accepted that this could be described as a duty to serve faithfully the plaintiff and to act in its interests and not against them. There was an allegation that the defendant's decision to tender while still employed by the plaintiff created a conflict between her own interest and that of the plaintiff. In dealing with that allegation he said (at 613-614):
 
 In Robb v Green [1895] 2 QB 1, at p 15 Hawkins J (who was the Judge at first instance) said: 'In what I have said I do not intend to convey that while the contract of service exists a person intending to enter into business for himself may not do anything by way of preparation, provided only that he does not, when serving his master, fraudulently undermine him by breaking the confidence reposed in him. For instance, he may legitimately canvass, issue his circulars, have his place of business in readiness, hire his servants, etc. Each case must depend on its own circumstances'.
 
 This passage was quoted with approval by Maugham LJ as a member of the Court of Appeal in Wessex Dairies v Smith [1935] 2 KB 80, at 87 although he qualified his acceptance of the reference to canvassing.
 
 I think the essence of the matter is that the plaintiff must satisfy me there was some conduct on the part of the defendant which, to use the phrase of Hawkins J, 'fraudulently undermined' the plaintiff whilst the defendant was in its employ. For the reasons I have stated, the plaintiff has failed to do so.

156 Like the contractual duty, the fiduciary duty ends on cessation of the employment. The qualification to this statement is that a transaction current when the employee leaves his or her employment cannot be exploited by the employee after the employment has ended. Absent a restrictive covenant an employee can compete with his employer after the employment has ended.

157 Another duty an employee may owe the employer is the equitable duty of confidence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rosetex Company Pty Ltd v Licata (1994) 12 ACSR 779</tocase>
<text>159 In Forkserve Pty Ltd v Pachiaratta (2000) 40 IPR 74, Young J considered the obligations of a former employee in terms of general knowledge and skills acquired while he was an employee and confidential information acquired while he was an employee. Two propositions emerge from the case which I accept as correctly stating the law. First, Young J said, after referring to the Restraint of Trade Doctrine , JD Heydon (2 nd ed, 1999) at 80, that an employee can approach a customer or client whose name he can recall without a list or deliberate memorisation. Secondly, by reference to one of his own previous decisions Rosetex Company Pty Ltd v Licata (1994) 12 ACSR 779 his Honour said that the general coverage of the predecessors of ss 182 and 183 "are not to any major extent wider than the duties under the general rules of equity".</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>