<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Peplin Limited [2007] FCA 1387 (23 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1387.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mincom Ltd v EAM Software Finance Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] QSC 207</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2007/207.html</AustLII>
<text>3 I have been taken carefully through the scheme documents themselves and, subject to one matter, I have no difficulty with them. In the course of the hearing I raised with counsel the issue of the warranty said to be given by the party whose shares or options are affected. As counsel has said, clauses along those lines have been approved or have been included in schemes approved in recent times by judges of this Court, the Supreme Court of New South Wales and the Supreme Court of Queensland, albeit misgivings or doubts having been expressed about the effect of such a clause (eg Mincom Ltd v EAM Software Finance Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] QSC 207 at [20] [29]). I also have doubts but I do not believe that it is likely that the inclusion of such a clause would lead to any difficulty about confirmation of these schemes. Against the possibility of somebody coming along and arguing the matter, I cannot, of course, make a final judgment about that. Even if a draconian view were taken about that clause, it is hardly fundamental to these transactions in particular, because they are not at arm's length with parties that might be in contention, but, rather, they represent an internal restructure.

4 I have been taken carefully through the information memorandum and to the material which backs that memorandum including the expert report and the underlying advices which are directed to two topics of significance. The first is that of tax and the second is that of corporate governance, bearing in mind the different regimes in Australia, on the one hand, and Delaware, on the other. As will be appreciated, the question in the expert report is rather different from usual. The financial structure, except perhaps for costs incurred in the course of the transaction, effectively remains the same before and after. The assessment of whether to vote for the change of location will be governed by matters other than the immediate economic consequences to the company. It will involve a broader assessment by investors as to whether they wish to become part of the restructured operation and, if so, how they should do so, noting that there is, if the scheme is approved, an alternative between holding CHESS depository instruments (CDIs) listed on the Australian Securities Exchange, on the one hand, and the American securities listed, hopefully, on the NASDAQ Stock Market on the other.

5 For those reasons I make orders in accordance with the short minutes of order which I have initialled.
 I certify that the preceding five (5) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gyles. 


 Associate:

Dated: 3 September 2007


 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr TF Bathurst QC 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Date of Hearing: 23 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 23 August 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1387.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>