<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Li v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1098 (3 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1098.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Li v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FMCA 454</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/454.html</AustLII>
<text>19 Further, I accept that, as the first respondent submitted, the absence of specific reference to persistence in the Tribunal's reasons does not demonstrate a failure to take into account "all the circumstances of the relationship" for the purposes of reg 1.15A(3). The Tribunal was not obliged to mention the fact that the appellant and her sponsor chose to persist with the application even though the Departmental officers indicated that it would be refused. In the circumstances of the case, the relevance and weight of this matter were entirely for the Tribunal. I agree with the learned Federal Magistrate that:
 
 "[T]he Tribunal was not obliged to give weight to, or mention specifically in its reasons, the evidence about the applicant persisting with the application in the fact of the indications from the delegate that the application would be refused." 

See Li v Minister for Immigration and Another [2007] FMCA 454 at [27] .

20 At the hearing of the appeal, the appellant's counsel sought to call into question the conduct of the Departmental officers. This was not raised by the notice of appeal. Nor was it raised in written submissions prior to the hearing. No such argument was advanced or supporting evidence adduced in the Federal Magistrates Court. Nor was the issue raised in the Tribunal. I would not entertain this argument on appeal.

21 Further, I would not infer from the Tribunal's reasons and its failure to mention the matter specifically that the Tribunal failed to have regard to the duration of the appellant's and sponsor's relationship. It set out in detail the evidence before it, referring to dates in the course of the relationship. It specifically mentioned that the appellant and sponsor were married on 1 March 2001. It was, thus, clearly aware of the duration of the relationship between them. The Tribunal noted in its reasons, however, that the evidence raised a number of issues on the subject of commitment. These issues arose from such matters as inconsistencies in the evidence regarding the financial and social aspects of their relationship, the nature of their household and living arrangements, as well as their purported reconciliation, the sponsor's failure to inform the appellant of his previous relationship and children, and the appellant's lack of knowledge of the sponsor's medical conditions. The state of the evidence led the Tribunal to state that it was "not satisfied that the visa applicant and the sponsor have demonstrated a genuine commitment to each other as spouses at the time of decision". The Tribunal's reasons do not show that it acted otherwise than in conformity with reg 1.15A(3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155</tocase>
<text>28 Both the appellant and the first respondent agree that the Tribunal was not under any general duty to exercise its powers pursuant to ss 359 , 359B and 363 to obtain further information. I reject the appellant's submission that this case raised a circumstance of a kind considered in Prasad v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1985) 6 FCR 155 (' Prasad ') at 170. It was not obvious that there was any additional material that was readily available and centrally relevant to the Tribunal's decision: compare Prasad at 170 per Wilcox J. This was not a case in which the exercise of power was so unreasonable that no reasonable person would have so exercised it in that way.

29 I repeat my earlier observations on the matter of persistence. It should be borne in mind that, as stated above, the appellant's alleged persistence with her application in the face of a foreshadowed refusal was not of itself a consideration that the Tribunal was, as a matter of law, bound to take into account. I add that the Tribunal did not apparently rely in its reasons on any of the inconsistencies or discrepancies in evidence given by the appellant and her sponsor at the Departmental interview.

30 Accordingly, the appellant's fourth ground of appeal is not made out. For the reasons stated, I would dismiss this appeal with costs.















 I certify that the preceding thirty (30) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Kenny. 

 Associate:

Dated: 3 August 2007

 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr A. Krohn 
 
 Solicitors for the Appellant: Chua Tan &amp; Associates 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Mr C. Horan 
 
 Solicitors for the First Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 30 July 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 August 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1098.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>