<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd (ACN 004 743 408) v Multiplex Limited (ACN 008 687 063) [2007] FCA 1659 (2 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1659.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Applicant Y v Australian Prudential Regulation Authority [2005] FCAFC 222</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/222.html</AustLII>
<text>19 The power given to the Court under s 50 of the Federal Court of Australia Act to forbid or restrict the publication of evidence should only be exercised in exceptional circumstances. Section 50 makes it clear that the power should only be exercised in order to prevent "prejudice to the administration of justice or the security of the Commonwealth". In the present case ASIC's concerns relate to prejudice to the administration of justice. It is a fundamental principle of the administration of justice in Australia that the administration of justice be open justice. When considering whether to exercise the power given by s 50 a Court must bear in mind the need to do justice between all relevant parties, taking as its initial position the principle of open justice. The manner in which a Court should approach an application under s 50 of the Federal Court of Australia Act to restrict the publication of evidence was considered by a Full Court of the Federal Court in Applicant Y v Australian Prudential Regulation Authority [2005] FCAFC 222. The Full Court said at pars [14] and [15]:
 
 "The public interest, that the Court should effectively endeavour to achieve in considering the exercise of power under s 50, is the object of doing justice between the parties. That is the function that the Court is appointed to discharge. Where refusal to make an order might well undermine or defeat the purpose of achieving justice between the parties, and disappoint the public interest in having the Court deal responsibly with the affairs of citizens, it may be appropriate to make an order pursuant to s 50 ... 
 
 The Court must, however, take into account what s 50 does not explicitly state, but is the underlying assumption upon which it is based, namely, the principle of open justice. The importance of the principle of open justice is not in doubt. On the other hand, the possibility of prejudice to the administration of justice must be weighed against the public interest in maintaining open justice. Although the principle of open justice is of great importance in exercising the discretion under s 50, it is not necessarily the whole weight of that principle that must be placed on the scales. The derogation from the principle that might be involved in making an order under s 50 may be very great, or it might be very small. The degree of derogation from the principle involved in the proposed order is an important matter to be considered in balancing the principle against possible prejudice to the administration of justice ..." (citation omitted)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Scott v Scott [1913] AC 417</tocase>
<text>20 The basis upon which the Court should approach an application under s 17(4) of the Federal Court of Australia Act is similar to the approach it should take in relation to an application under s 50. The power to order the exclusion of persons from a hearing should only be exercised in exceptional cases. It is clear from s 17(4) that that power should only be exercised in circumstances where not to exercise it would be "contrary to the interests of justice". The primary principle is that the principle of open justice is to be observed in that Court hearings should be open to the public and only closed where the interests of justice require that closure. As Earl Loreburn said in Scott v Scott [1913] AC 417 at 445: "The inveterate rule is that justice shall be administered in open Court." His Lordship accepted that it was appropriate in the interests of justice that the doors of the Court be closed when the subject-matter of the action would be destroyed by a hearing in open court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Raybos Australia Pty Ltd v Jones [1985] 2 NSWLR 47</tocase>
<text>21 In Raybos Australia Pty Ltd v Jones [1985] 2 NSWLR 47, Kirby P (as he then was) said at 55:
 
 "Many cases report the scrutiny by courts of statutory provisions designed to derogate from the open administration of justice. Running through these decisions is a common theme. It is that, by our tradition, the open administration of justice is the rule. Statutory derogation from openness is the exception. In the defence of the rule, such statutes will usually be strictly and narrowly construed. Unless the derogation is specifically provided for, courts are loathe to expand the field of secret justice ..." 


Samuels JA, in the course of analysing whether the publication of the names in suit would defeat the ends of justice, said at 61:
 
 
 "The inquiry must start with the proposition, central to our notions of forensic procedure, that the courts customarily conduct their business in public in order that the integrity, fairness and efficiency of the system, and its administrators, may be maintained by its exposure to public scrutiny."

22 The applicant submitted that ASIC should disclose in open hearing what was the reasoning process to support the protection of the information sought by ASIC without disclosing what that information was. It submitted that it should, to the extent possible, identify the reasons why the information was being withheld without disclosing the information. The difficulty with acceding to that submission is that exposing the reasoning process would inevitably disclose the information sought to be protected. There were also a number of matters in respect of the claim for public interest immunity privilege raised in the confidential material which I wanted to discuss with counsel for ASIC but it was not possible to do this in open session without exposing the information that ASIC sought to protect.

23 The difficulty with which I was faced in this application by ASIC was that in order to determine whether orders should be made under ss 17(4) and 50 of the Federal Court of Australia Act I must have regard to the confidential affidavits (not served on the parties) filed by ASIC and its confidential submissions (not served on the parties) in order to understand the basis for the application. I reached the conclusion that in order to preserve the subject-matter of ASIC's claim for public interest immunity privilege I was compelled to make orders under ss 17(4) and 50 of the Federal Court Act in order to avoid prejudice to the administration of justice. If I had not made such orders I would have destroyed the basis for ASIC's claim. The hearing of ASIC's claim in the presence of the parties to the proceeding would have disclosed the very subject-matter and issues which ASIC claimed were protected from disclosure by the public interest immunity privilege. I therefore heard ASIC's application in camera in the absence of the parties to the proceeding.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>