<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Chief Executive Officer of Customs v ICB Medical Distributors Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1538 (5 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1538.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>59 Customs argued that the question of construction addressed by its proposed declaration was not determinative in the Tribunal but would be likely to be determinative if the matter were remitted. I do not agree. The characterisation of the goods would remain a question of fact on any remitter. The construction in the proposed declaration does not clarify whether the goods are or are not 'special insoles' or orthopaedic appliances outside Note 6 to Chapter 90, as I have held. Declaratory relief must be directed to the determination of legal controversies and not to answering abstract or hypothetical questions: Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 at 582 per Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey and Gaudron JJ. The proposed declaration does not answer any question in respect of the goods. It is framed in the abstract.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Chandler &amp; Co v Collector of Customs [1907] HCA 81 ; (1907) 4 CLR 1719</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1907/81.html</AustLII>
<text>5 As the Tribunal noted, a classifier of goods for the purpose of a customs tariff must look objectively at the goods in their condition as imported in order to identify objectively their classification for duty: Chinese Food and Wine Supplies v Collector of Customs (Vic) (1987) 72 ALR 591 at 599 per Lockhart J with whom Woodward and Ryan JJ agreed. The subjective intention of the manufacturer, exporter or importer is not relevant to this task. In Times Consultants Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (Qld) (1987) 16 FCR 449 at 463, Morling and Wilcox JJ said that the classification of goods for tariff purposes was a practical, 'wharf-side' task. Morling and Wilcox JJ also said that the classifier had to consider the characteristics of the goods themselves as they would present to an informed observer. The heart of the exercise is to determine the essential character of the goods by reference to their state or condition at the time of importation ( Times Consultants 16 FCR at 462). Barton J said in Chandler &amp; Co v Collector of Customs [1907] HCA 81 ; (1907) 4 CLR 1719 at 1729:
 
 '... the dutiable classification of an imported article must be ascertained by an examination of the article itself, in the condition in which it is imported.'

38 As noted above, there were many references in the evidence about particular views of what an orthosis could be called. The Tribunal did not need to go through each of these explaining its conclusions about them. Its task, as the classifier, was to examine the goods in the condition in which they were imported and form its assessment of their essential character as an informed observer: Chandler 4 CLR at 1729 per Barton J; Times Consultants 16 FCR at 462 per Morling and Wilcox JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Chinese Food and Wine Supplies v Collector of Customs (Vic) (1987) 72 ALR 591</tocase>
<text>5 As the Tribunal noted, a classifier of goods for the purpose of a customs tariff must look objectively at the goods in their condition as imported in order to identify objectively their classification for duty: Chinese Food and Wine Supplies v Collector of Customs (Vic) (1987) 72 ALR 591 at 599 per Lockhart J with whom Woodward and Ryan JJ agreed. The subjective intention of the manufacturer, exporter or importer is not relevant to this task. In Times Consultants Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (Qld) (1987) 16 FCR 449 at 463, Morling and Wilcox JJ said that the classification of goods for tariff purposes was a practical, 'wharf-side' task. Morling and Wilcox JJ also said that the classifier had to consider the characteristics of the goods themselves as they would present to an informed observer. The heart of the exercise is to determine the essential character of the goods by reference to their state or condition at the time of importation ( Times Consultants 16 FCR at 462). Barton J said in Chandler &amp; Co v Collector of Customs [1907] HCA 81 ; (1907) 4 CLR 1719 at 1729:
 
 '... the dutiable classification of an imported article must be ascertained by an examination of the article itself, in the condition in which it is imported.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Agfa-Gevaert Pty Ltd [1996] HCA 36 ; (1996) 186 CLR 389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/36.html</AustLII>
<text>39 In characterising the goods the Tribunal was entitled to have recourse to common-sense, as Brennan CJ, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ emphasised in Collector of Customs v Agfa-Gevaert Pty Ltd [1996] HCA 36 ; (1996) 186 CLR 389 at 400.

40 It was for the Tribunal to evaluate, as a factual matter, the essential character which it perceived the goods to have. It also had to identify what the word 'insole' meant as an ordinary English word. That is why it was open to the Tribunal to select its characterisation of the best description of the goods as being orthotic inserts of the kind described in the patent.

41 I am of opinion that Customs' characterisation of the Tribunal's approach to its case is not correct. The Tribunal's reasons show that it proceeded in a conventional manner. First, it identified what the goods were in the condition in which they came to be imported into Australia. It found that they were orthopaedic appliances within the meaning of heading 9021. It explained that this finding was made because the goods were 'more properly defined' as an artificial external device such as a brace or splint which prevented or assisted relative movement in the limbs. In this finding the Tribunal was expressing its ascertainment of the essential character of the goods. It explained that the finding was based on the ordinary and natural meaning of an orthopaedic appliance. That meaning was one which Customs accepted was open to the Tribunal based on its earlier decision in JS Levy (unreported Tribunal decision No 101; dated 8 September 1978) and the Oxford English Dictionary definition.

43 In my opinion, the reasons given by the Tribunal informed the parties why it came to the conclusion that it did. It made a finding as to how the goods would be viewed by an informed observer when they arrived at the wharf in Australia. In Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272, Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ deprecated an attempt to scrutinise, overzealously on judicial review, the reasons of an administrative decision-maker.

54 It is difficult to conceive that Note 6 of Chapter 90 was framed with the intention to exclude every orthotic insert except one made to measure. Such a construction would render otiose the second category of 'footwear' or 'special insole' in Note 6. Customs did not point to a construction that gave any reality to the existence an orthotic insert which was not made to measure and which met the criteria in Note 6 of Chapter 90. That is a good reason for concluding that orthotic inserts are not, in general, to be characterised as 'special insoles': Australian Securities and Investments Commission v DB Management Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 7 ; (2000) 199 CLR 321 at 338 [34] - [35] . The argument of Customs deprives Note 1(e) of Chapter 64 of any real content because all orthotics, except those made to measure, would be excluded from being characterised as an orthopaedic appliance. Such a view is contrary to the words used in the Act and to common-sense ( Agfa-Gevaert 186 CLR at 400). I reject this argument.

55 Customs' proposed amended notice of appeal and application for an order for review seeks leave to add the following prayer for relief:
 
 'That it be declared that the last paragraph to Note 6 to Chapter 90 in the Tariff Act has effect such that "footwear and special insoles designed to correct orthopaedic conditions" are "orthopaedic appliances" only if such footwear and special insoles are "either (1) made to measure or (2) mass-produced, presented singly and not in pairs and designed to fit either foot equally".'

56 In my opinion it would be inappropriate to grant such a declaration in this matter. The circumstances in which Note 6 of Chapter 9 can operate are varied. I am not in a position to review all of them or to assess the impact which any particular form of declaratory relief might have on other goods.

58 What a 'special insole' is in any particular case must be a question of fact, as must the question as to whether the good satisfies any of the criteria in Note 6 which might bring it to assessment under heading 9021. The proposed declaration is loosely framed and objectionable in form: Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559 at 579 per Brennan CJ, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron, McHugh and Gummow JJ.

60 I am of opinion that the proposed amendment does not raise a fairly arguable claim to final relief and ought be refused: Queensland v JL Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146 at 154-155 per Dawson, Gaudron and McHugh JJ.

61 Ordinarily, where an appeal is brought under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act , it will not be appropriate also to entertain proceeding for relief under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act or s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act : Tuite v Administrative Appeals Tribunal (1993) 40 FCR 483 at 484 per Davies J; but where, as here, there is a potential that the proper construction of the words in the Customs Tariff Act may not raise a question of law under s 44, judicial review proceedings to enable all issues to be resolved may be appropriate: see s 22 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) and cp: Rich v CGU Insurance Ltd [2005] HCA 16 ; (2005) 214 ALR 370 at 375 [20] per Gleeson CJ, McHugh and Gummow JJ. I have considered the matter on both bases.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>44 Brennan J said in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422 at 446 that a decision of the Tribunal , if it is made in accordance with the statutory provisions that govern the exercise of its power, is not invalidated by a mere failure to expose fully the reasons for making it. Although that was a dissenting judgment, the principle his Honour stated is of general application (see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 349 [75] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Of course, much will depend on the extent of the decision-maker's exposure of a reasoning process in determining whether or not the decision can stand. So, in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Palme [2003] HCA 56 ; (2003) 216 CLR 212 at 224 [39] , Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Heydon JJ referred to the authorities which enabled a court to infer that, where a decision-maker did not give any reason for his or her decision, he or she had no good reason for it. That is not this case. An obligation to give reasons, such as is found in s 43(2B) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act , did not oblige the Tribunal to give a subset of reasons why it accepted or rejected individual pieces of evidence. It is sufficient if the Tribunal, as the decision-maker, sets out its findings 'on those questions of fact which it considered to be material to the decision which it made and to the reasons it had for reaching that decision': Yusuf 206 CLR at 349 [68] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; see too Repatriation Commission v Cotton (2006) 93 ALD 118 at 128 [42] where I cited the authorities and SZCOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCAFC 9 at [14] per Moore J, [27]-[28] per Besanko J, and [53]-[61] per Buchanan J (dissenting).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407; 74 ALJR 405</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/1.html</AustLII>
<text>47 I am satisfied that the Tribunal addressed the correct question, understood the arguments and had regard to all relevant considerations and ignored irrelevant ones. This was a situation in which the Tribunal was not obliged to give more reasons than s 43(2B) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act required. It set out its findings on material questions of fact and referred to the evidence and other material on which they were based, explaining logically why it came to the characterisation it did: cf: Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 422-423; [2000] HCA 1 ; 74 ALJR 405 at 416-417 [65] - [67] per McHugh J. As Davies and Beazley JJ said in Sharp Corporation of Australia Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (1995) 59 FCR 6 at 13F-G, it is fundamentally a question of fact whether goods have an essential character and what that character is (see too at 14G-15B; and per Hill J at 16A).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Palme [2003] HCA 56 ; (2003) 216 CLR 212</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/56.html</AustLII>
<text>44 Brennan J said in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422 at 446 that a decision of the Tribunal , if it is made in accordance with the statutory provisions that govern the exercise of its power, is not invalidated by a mere failure to expose fully the reasons for making it. Although that was a dissenting judgment, the principle his Honour stated is of general application (see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 349 [75] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Of course, much will depend on the extent of the decision-maker's exposure of a reasoning process in determining whether or not the decision can stand. So, in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Palme [2003] HCA 56 ; (2003) 216 CLR 212 at 224 [39] , Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Heydon JJ referred to the authorities which enabled a court to infer that, where a decision-maker did not give any reason for his or her decision, he or she had no good reason for it. That is not this case. An obligation to give reasons, such as is found in s 43(2B) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act , did not oblige the Tribunal to give a subset of reasons why it accepted or rejected individual pieces of evidence. It is sufficient if the Tribunal, as the decision-maker, sets out its findings 'on those questions of fact which it considered to be material to the decision which it made and to the reasons it had for reaching that decision': Yusuf 206 CLR at 349 [68] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; see too Repatriation Commission v Cotton (2006) 93 ALD 118 at 128 [42] where I cited the authorities and SZCOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCAFC 9 at [14] per Moore J, [27]-[28] per Besanko J, and [53]-[61] per Buchanan J (dissenting).

61 Ordinarily, where an appeal is brought under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act , it will not be appropriate also to entertain proceeding for relief under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act or s 39B(1A) of the Judiciary Act : Tuite v Administrative Appeals Tribunal (1993) 40 FCR 483 at 484 per Davies J; but where, as here, there is a potential that the proper construction of the words in the Customs Tariff Act may not raise a question of law under s 44, judicial review proceedings to enable all issues to be resolved may be appropriate: see s 22 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) and cp: Rich v CGU Insurance Ltd [2005] HCA 16 ; (2005) 214 ALR 370 at 375 [20] per Gleeson CJ, McHugh and Gummow JJ. I have considered the matter on both bases.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/10.html</AustLII>
<text>44 Brennan J said in Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422 at 446 that a decision of the Tribunal , if it is made in accordance with the statutory provisions that govern the exercise of its power, is not invalidated by a mere failure to expose fully the reasons for making it. Although that was a dissenting judgment, the principle his Honour stated is of general application (see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 349 [75] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Of course, much will depend on the extent of the decision-maker's exposure of a reasoning process in determining whether or not the decision can stand. So, in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Palme [2003] HCA 56 ; (2003) 216 CLR 212 at 224 [39] , Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Heydon JJ referred to the authorities which enabled a court to infer that, where a decision-maker did not give any reason for his or her decision, he or she had no good reason for it. That is not this case. An obligation to give reasons, such as is found in s 43(2B) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act , did not oblige the Tribunal to give a subset of reasons why it accepted or rejected individual pieces of evidence. It is sufficient if the Tribunal, as the decision-maker, sets out its findings 'on those questions of fact which it considered to be material to the decision which it made and to the reasons it had for reaching that decision': Yusuf 206 CLR at 349 [68] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; see too Repatriation Commission v Cotton (2006) 93 ALD 118 at 128 [42] where I cited the authorities and SZCOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCAFC 9 at [14] per Moore J, [27]-[28] per Besanko J, and [53]-[61] per Buchanan J (dissenting).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Sharp Corporation of Australia Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (1995) 59 FCR 6</tocase>
<text>47 I am satisfied that the Tribunal addressed the correct question, understood the arguments and had regard to all relevant considerations and ignored irrelevant ones. This was a situation in which the Tribunal was not obliged to give more reasons than s 43(2B) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act required. It set out its findings on material questions of fact and referred to the evidence and other material on which they were based, explaining logically why it came to the characterisation it did: cf: Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at 422-423; [2000] HCA 1 ; 74 ALJR 405 at 416-417 [65] - [67] per McHugh J. As Davies and Beazley JJ said in Sharp Corporation of Australia Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (1995) 59 FCR 6 at 13F-G, it is fundamentally a question of fact whether goods have an essential character and what that character is (see too at 14G-15B; and per Hill J at 16A).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Times Consultants Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (Qld) (1987) 16 FCR 449</tocase>
<text>5 As the Tribunal noted, a classifier of goods for the purpose of a customs tariff must look objectively at the goods in their condition as imported in order to identify objectively their classification for duty: Chinese Food and Wine Supplies v Collector of Customs (Vic) (1987) 72 ALR 591 at 599 per Lockhart J with whom Woodward and Ryan JJ agreed. The subjective intention of the manufacturer, exporter or importer is not relevant to this task. In Times Consultants Pty Ltd v Collector of Customs (Qld) (1987) 16 FCR 449 at 463, Morling and Wilcox JJ said that the classification of goods for tariff purposes was a practical, 'wharf-side' task. Morling and Wilcox JJ also said that the classifier had to consider the characteristics of the goods themselves as they would present to an informed observer. The heart of the exercise is to determine the essential character of the goods by reference to their state or condition at the time of importation ( Times Consultants 16 FCR at 462). Barton J said in Chandler &amp; Co v Collector of Customs [1907] HCA 81 ; (1907) 4 CLR 1719 at 1729:
 
 '... the dutiable classification of an imported article must be ascertained by an examination of the article itself, in the condition in which it is imported.'

38 As noted above, there were many references in the evidence about particular views of what an orthosis could be called. The Tribunal did not need to go through each of these explaining its conclusions about them. Its task, as the classifier, was to examine the goods in the condition in which they were imported and form its assessment of their essential character as an informed observer: Chandler 4 CLR at 1729 per Barton J; Times Consultants 16 FCR at 462 per Morling and Wilcox JJ.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>