<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Repatriation Commission v Farley-Smith [2007] FCA 1058 (18 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1058.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bushell v Repatriation Commission [1992] HCA 47 ; (1992) 175 CLR 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/47.html</AustLII>
<text>35 In addition there was the survey material from Sweden referred to in the Tondel article, and the United Kingdom survey referred to (although also discounted) by Professor Peach, and the bundle of documents produced by the respondent which were specifically relied upon by the Tribunal. Even accepting the criticisms of the applicant in respect of the content of the material, it does nevertheless show that the hypothesis (putting aside temporal issues) was not contrary to known scientific facts, nor was so obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible or untenable, or too remote or too tenuous: see Bushell v Repatriation Commission [1992] HCA 47 ; (1992) 175 CLR 408 at 414 and East 16 FCR at 533.

40 In any event, it was not for the Tribunal to necessarily determine opposing views, just have regard to them in examining the validity of the reasoning which supports the hypothesis: see Bushell 195 CLR at 413-416. This, in my view, was the task the Tribunal undertook.

41 I mention one further matter for completeness. The respondent seemed to suggest that assistance could be obtained by s 119 of the VE Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/51.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Where a claim relates to operational service, the standard of proof to be applied to the question as to whether a death is war-caused is proscribed by s 120(1) and (3) of the VE Act. Those provisions are to be applied in the manner explained by the High Court in Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564 at 571:
 
 The position may be summarised as follows: (1) First, sub-s (3) of s 120 is applied: do all or some of the facts raised by the material before the Commission give rise to a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's injury with war service? The hypothesis will not be reasonable if it is contrary to known scientific facts or is obviously fanciful or untenable. If the hypothesis is not reasonable, the claim fails. Proof of facts is not in issue at this point. (2) If a reasonable hypothesis is established, sub-s (1) of s 120 is applied. The claim will succeed unless: (a) one or more of the facts necessary to support the hypothesis are disproved beyond reasonable doubt; or (b) the truth of another fact in the material, which is inconsistent with the hypothesis, is proved beyond reasonable doubt, thus disproving, beyond reasonable doubt, the hypothesis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Clements v Independent Indigenous Advisory Committee [2003] FCAFC 143 ; (2003) 131 FCR 28</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/143.html</AustLII>
<text>62 There may be an issue whether a denial of procedural fairness is an error of law, but in the circumstances of this case where the lack of procedural fairness is clearly apparent on the reasoning of the Tribunal, in my view, the reasons of the Tribunal do disclose an error of law: see Clements v Independent Indigenous Advisory Committee [2003] FCAFC 143 ; (2003) 131 FCR 28.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517</tocase>
<text>18 I should mention, however, that in this case the hypothesis relied upon is not itself limited to the time and duration of exposure to benzene, to which I will refer as the temporal issues. Whilst I have come to the view that there is sufficient evidence to support the findings of the Tribunal even on the basis of the temporal issues, the necessity for such evidence is not to be assumed. As was said in East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 16 FCR 517 at 533:
 
 The necessity for quantitative evidence in a particular case must depend upon the nature of the hypothesis being expounded. For example, if a Tribunal accepts medical evidence that condition B may be caused by any degree of exposure to factor A, that the veteran was exposed to factor A and that he or she subsequently developed condition B, it would be wrong to reject the claim because of an absence of evidence as to the extent of the exposure. The hypothesis itself makes quantity irrelevant. If, on the other hand, the evidence is that exposure to quantity X of factor A may cause condition B, the hypothesis cannot be described as reasonable unless there is reason to believe that the veteran was exposed to factor A to the extent of quantity X.

19 I turn to the evidence before the Tribunal. Two experts were called by the applicant Professor Fox (a haematologist) and Professor Peach (an epidemiologist). I need not rehearse their evidence except to say they both held the view that there was no connection between exposure to benzene and the contraction of myelofibrosis, especially in the circumstances of the temporal issues raised in this case. I accept that their evidence (without more) could have led to the conclusion that the hypothesis considered by the Tribunal would not have been reasonable. The Tribunal similarly regarded that as the likely position. As the Tribunal observed at [91]:
 
 On the evidence of Professors Fox and Peach alone, it might be thought that medical and/or scientific opinion would not support the hypothesis, and that there was an absence of support within the medical profession and other scientists for the connection between benzene and myelofibrosis.

20 However, as the Tribunal went on to observe, more information was available and was before the Tribunal.

21 The applicant contended that this further material cannot support the hypothesis, particularly when one considers the temporal issues, and that the Tribunal failed to consider, as s 120(3) of the VE Act requires, whether the whole of the material before it raised a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the veteran. Undoubtedly s 120(3) of the VE Act requires the Tribunal to consider that connection. In my view, the Tribunal did undertake that enquiry and it was open for the Tribunal on the whole of the material before it to reach its conclusions.

22 In my view, the applicant underestimated the impact of the other material (in addition to the evidence of Professors Peach and Fox) before the Tribunal and, in particular, the evidence of Dr Collins who was called by the respondent. In fact, if accepted, the evidence of Dr Collins could in itself sufficiently point to the connecting hypothesis, even taking into account the temporal issues.

35 In addition there was the survey material from Sweden referred to in the Tondel article, and the United Kingdom survey referred to (although also discounted) by Professor Peach, and the bundle of documents produced by the respondent which were specifically relied upon by the Tribunal. Even accepting the criticisms of the applicant in respect of the content of the material, it does nevertheless show that the hypothesis (putting aside temporal issues) was not contrary to known scientific facts, nor was so obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible or untenable, or too remote or too tenuous: see Bushell v Repatriation Commission [1992] HCA 47 ; (1992) 175 CLR 408 at 414 and East 16 FCR at 533.

57 I cannot accept that submission. After considering the evidence, particularly of Professors Fox and Peach, the Tribunal stated: 
 
 95. As may be seen from the foregoing, a hypothesis may be reasonable despite the fact that it might be unproved, may have little support within the medical profession and may be dependent upon assumption. I cannot find on the material read and heard in these proceedings, that the raised facts are unreliable. Nor can I find that the evidence of Professors Fox and Peach is of such a superior reliability that there is no sufficient ground to determine that death in the present application was war-caused. At the conclusion of the evidence but before the conclusion of the hearing, Mr De Marchi produced a bundle of extracts from internet web sites, without specific attention or submission being directed to any of them. An analysis of those sites indicates that there is some support within the profession for an association between benzene and myelofibrosis refer www.merck.com/mmhe/sec14 and www.caremark.com/wps/portal. Additionally, one of the documents forming part of the " web " exhibits the copy of which is so poor that the web address cannot be identified refers to an increased incidence of myelofibrosis in the case of firemen who have been exposed to benzene. Regard for this material may appear unorthodox however it does highlight that contrary to the opinion of Professor Peach, in 'world medical literature' there does exist a body of literature raising a connection between benzene and myelofibrosis. 
 
 96. I readily acknowledge that those documents were not the subject of examination by the respondent, nor were they put to Professors Fox or Peach. However, the opinions expressed in those documents found at web sites of reputable medical organisations, do indicate that the hypothesis is reasonable because the connection between benzene and myelofibrosis is more than a possibility. Veterans and their widows need not establish a hypothesis as reasonable by a "causal connection" (refer Professor Peach) or a "definitive causal connection" (refer evidence of Dr Byron Collins). The finding of the reasonableness of the hypothesis does not depend on a resolution of or choice between competing medical theories. The contents of the report of Dr Byron Collins, the survey material from Sweden referred to in the report of Tondel (including his own survey), the United Kingdom survey referred to by Professor Peach and the information found from the internet sources as tendered does point to material raising a reasonable hypothesis connecting the operational service of the deceased, his exposure to benzene by petroleum products and myelofibrosis. The hypothesis is not "obviously fanciful, impossible, incredible, or not tenable or too remote or too tenuous" (refer East v Repatriation Commission (1987) 74 ALR 518 at 533).

58 An analysis of the Tribunal's reasons show, in my view, the bundle of documents was relied upon in at least two respects. One was to impact particularly upon the acceptance of the evidence given by Professor Peach. The other was to show the connection between benzene and myelofibrosis was "more than a possibility", which was a critical issue.

59 It may be said that in view of Dr Collins' evidence and the other material referred to by the Tribunal supporting the relevant connection, the acceptance or otherwise of Professor Peach's evidence has immaterial. However, it does seem to me that the Tribunal did look into the relative strengths of the expert evidence, and could not find the evidence of either Professors Fox or Peach of such a "superior reliability" to persuade it that there was no sufficient ground to determine that the death of the veteran was war-caused. The bundle of documents was used by the Tribunal to highlight a view which was contrary to Professor Peach's in relation to the existence of world medical literature, and impacted upon the Tribunal's assessment of Professor Peach adversely to the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Giretti v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 151</tocase>
<text>64 I have a discretion under s 44(4) of the AAT Act, which includes not remitting the matter if that is appropriate. This is not a case where this Court can be sure what decision would have been reached had procedural fairness be accorded. I cannot be satisfied for the reasons given above that there is no possibility of a different result: see Giretti v Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 151 at 165-166; and O'Sullivan (2003) 128 FCR at [62].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harradine v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 25 FCR 35</tocase>
<text>61 Generally speaking, if a court decides that the Tribunal has erred in law, the Tribunal decision is set aside and the matter is remitted for determination according to law: see Morales v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs (1995) 60 FCR 550 and compare with Harradine v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 25 FCR 35.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/81.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Section 39(1) of the AAT Act provided that, subject to provisions which are irrelevant for present purposes, the Tribunal must ensure that every party sitting before a Tribunal is given a reasonable opportunity to present his or her case and, in particular, to inspect any documents to which the Tribunal proposes to have regard in reaching a decision, and to make submissions in relation to those documents. It seems to be clear that the section provides that the Tribunal must apply notions of procedural fairness: see Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 per Mason J and O'Sullivan v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCA 387 ; (2003) 128 FCR 590 at [45] . Obviously the requirements will depend upon the particular circumstances of each case. It may be in some circumstances where a party is represented then there is some onus upon a party to be proactive in requesting from the Tribunal an opportunity to present its case such as, for instance, in seeking an adjournment: see, e.g. Schiffer v Pattison [2001] FCA 1094. However, as I have said, in this case the Tribunal and the respondent effectively represented there would be an opportunity for the applicant to present further submissions on the issue of the bundle of documents once those documents had been seen. That opportunity was not given.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mason v Repatriation Commission [2000] FCA 1409</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1409.html</AustLII>
<text>42 No reliance can be placed upon s 119 of the VE Act to fill in gaps where there is insufficient evidence to assist the respondent's case: see Repatriation Commission v Bey (1997) 79 FCR 364 at 373-374 and Mason v Repatriation Commission [2000] FCA 1409. However, in my view there were no relevant gaps in the material before the Tribunal, and for the reasons I have indicated, the evidence before the Tribunal supported the Tribunal's conclusions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Morales v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs (1995) 60 FCR 550</tocase>
<text>61 Generally speaking, if a court decides that the Tribunal has erred in law, the Tribunal decision is set aside and the matter is remitted for determination according to law: see Morales v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs (1995) 60 FCR 550 and compare with Harradine v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 25 FCR 35.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>O'Sullivan v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCA 387 ; (2003) 128 FCR 590</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/387.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Section 39(1) of the AAT Act provided that, subject to provisions which are irrelevant for present purposes, the Tribunal must ensure that every party sitting before a Tribunal is given a reasonable opportunity to present his or her case and, in particular, to inspect any documents to which the Tribunal proposes to have regard in reaching a decision, and to make submissions in relation to those documents. It seems to be clear that the section provides that the Tribunal must apply notions of procedural fairness: see Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 per Mason J and O'Sullivan v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCA 387 ; (2003) 128 FCR 590 at [45] . Obviously the requirements will depend upon the particular circumstances of each case. It may be in some circumstances where a party is represented then there is some onus upon a party to be proactive in requesting from the Tribunal an opportunity to present its case such as, for instance, in seeking an adjournment: see, e.g. Schiffer v Pattison [2001] FCA 1094. However, as I have said, in this case the Tribunal and the respondent effectively represented there would be an opportunity for the applicant to present further submissions on the issue of the bundle of documents once those documents had been seen. That opportunity was not given.

63 Another way to approach the present issue is to treat the actions of the Tribunal as a breach of s 39(1) of the AAT Act, and thus there was a failure to comply with its statutory duty. This would itself be an error of law: see O'Sullivan (2003) 128 FCR at [60].

64 I have a discretion under s 44(4) of the AAT Act, which includes not remitting the matter if that is appropriate. This is not a case where this Court can be sure what decision would have been reached had procedural fairness be accorded. I cannot be satisfied for the reasons given above that there is no possibility of a different result: see Giretti v Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 70 FCR 151 at 165-166; and O'Sullivan (2003) 128 FCR at [62].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Bey (1997) 149 ALR 721</tocase>
<text>42 No reliance can be placed upon s 119 of the VE Act to fill in gaps where there is insufficient evidence to assist the respondent's case: see Repatriation Commission v Bey (1997) 79 FCR 364 at 373-374 and Mason v Repatriation Commission [2000] FCA 1409. However, in my view there were no relevant gaps in the material before the Tribunal, and for the reasons I have indicated, the evidence before the Tribunal supported the Tribunal's conclusions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Owens (1996) 70 ALJR 904</tocase>
<text>12 The threshold question posed by s 120(3) requires a consideration of the whole of the material before the decision-maker and the raised hypothesis connecting the death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the veteran: see Repatriation Commission v Owens (1996) 70 ALJR 904. Further, it is mandatory to find in favour of an applicant unless the decision-maker forms an opinion that the whole of the material does not raise the reasonable hypothesis referred to in the statute: see Repatriation Commission v Whetton (1991) 31 FCR 513 at 521.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327</tocase>
<text>8 The question as to the kind of death suffered by a veteran is to be determined by applying the standard of proof in s 120(4) of the VE Act; that is, to the reasonable satisfaction of the decision-maker. That section imports the civil standard of proof: see Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327 at 335.

9 Section 120(1), so far as is relevant, provides:
 
 Where a claim under Part II for a pension in respect of...the death of a veteran, relates to the operational service rendered by the veteran, the Commission shall determine that the death of the veteran was war-caused...unless it is satisfied, beyond reasonable doubt, that there is no sufficient ground for making that determination.

10 Relevantly, s 120(3) provides:
 
 In applying subsection (1)...in respect of the...death of a person, related to service rendered by the person, the Commission shall be satisfied, beyond reasonable doubt, that there is no sufficient ground for determining: 
 ... 
 (c) that the death was war-caused or defence-caused; 
 ...if the Commission, after consideration of the whole of the material before it, is of the opinion that the material before it does not raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting the...death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the person.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Whetton (1991) 31 FCR 513</tocase>
<text>12 The threshold question posed by s 120(3) requires a consideration of the whole of the material before the decision-maker and the raised hypothesis connecting the death with the circumstances of the particular service rendered by the veteran: see Repatriation Commission v Owens (1996) 70 ALJR 904. Further, it is mandatory to find in favour of an applicant unless the decision-maker forms an opinion that the whole of the material does not raise the reasonable hypothesis referred to in the statute: see Repatriation Commission v Whetton (1991) 31 FCR 513 at 521.

17 The question for me is whether there was sufficient material before the Tribunal pointing to or supporting a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's death with the circumstances of his service having regard to these facts. I say having regard to these facts because the reasonableness of the hypothesis is to be considered in the context of the relevant factual scenario. This includes that exposure to benzene occurred some 52 years before the veteran contracted myelofibrosis, and was at best intermittent whilst cleaning guns and machinery over a period of approximately 12 months: see, e.g. the approach taken in Whetton 31 FCR 513. This is not to say that proof of any of these facts is necessary at this stage, just that they needed to be considered in connection with the hypothesis before the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schiffer v Pattison [2001] FCA 1094</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1094.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Section 39(1) of the AAT Act provided that, subject to provisions which are irrelevant for present purposes, the Tribunal must ensure that every party sitting before a Tribunal is given a reasonable opportunity to present his or her case and, in particular, to inspect any documents to which the Tribunal proposes to have regard in reaching a decision, and to make submissions in relation to those documents. It seems to be clear that the section provides that the Tribunal must apply notions of procedural fairness: see Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 per Mason J and O'Sullivan v Repatriation Commission [2003] FCA 387 ; (2003) 128 FCR 590 at [45] . Obviously the requirements will depend upon the particular circumstances of each case. It may be in some circumstances where a party is represented then there is some onus upon a party to be proactive in requesting from the Tribunal an opportunity to present its case such as, for instance, in seeking an adjournment: see, e.g. Schiffer v Pattison [2001] FCA 1094. However, as I have said, in this case the Tribunal and the respondent effectively represented there would be an opportunity for the applicant to present further submissions on the issue of the bundle of documents once those documents had been seen. That opportunity was not given.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>