<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZILI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (Corrigendum dated 26 September 2007) [2007] FCA 1439 (12 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1439.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/26.html</AustLII>
<text>35 The appellant contended that the Tribunal's conclusion concerning the credibility of the applicant in some way affected its reasoning in relation to the claim to fear persecution by reason of membership of a particular social group. However, there is no reason why the Tribunal cannot deal with those contentions in the alternative. That is to say, it would be open for the Tribunal to deal with the claim that the applicant was a member of a particular social group on the assumption that his evidence were to be accepted. It would not be illogical for the Tribunal, having reached an unfavourable conclusion on that question, to express unfavourable views on the credibility of the applicant (see SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 at [26] and [29]. That is in effect the approach adopted by the Tribunal.

36 That is to say, the Tribunal examined the applicant's claims on the basis that the assertions made by him were true. The Tribunal concluded that, even if all of the assertions made by the applicant were true, it was not persuaded that he had a well founded fear of persecution by reason of his membership of a particular social group. As formulated by counsel for the appellant, the alleged group consisted of working families with children who were non-combatants in the civil war between the Maoists and the Government. The Tribunal characterised the formulation of the alleged group consisting of people caught between the Maoists and the Government as being too amorphous to be considered further. The Tribunal made no error in concluding that the general population, who feared harm as a result of the struggle between the Maoists and the authorities, could not properly be characterised as a particular social group that was singled out for persecution.

37 Even on the applicant's evidence, there was no suggestion that non-combatants in the civil war are persecuted by reason of the fact that they are non-combatants in the civil war, whether or not they are members of families. It is, of course, appalling that innocent people might be severely harmed in circumstances where they do not wish to have any part to play in the fight between Maoists and government authorities. Nevertheless, there was no suggestion by the applicant that he was targeted simply by reason of his being a non-combatant in that conflict. Even if he and the appellant were innocent victims of the conflict, that would not be sufficient to attract the Refugees Convention. There would be no fear of harm for a Convention reason. Even if the applicant's evidence were accepted, it would not constitute a basis for concluding that he may be subjected to harm by reason of an imputed political opinion.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>