<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Woodside Energy Ltd (ABN 63 005 482 986) v Commissioner of Taxation (No 2) [2007] FCA 1961 (10 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1961.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Atlantic Sugar Refineries v Minister of National Revenue [1949] CTC 196</tocase>
<text>272 Echo Bay Mines Ltd v R [1992] 3 CF 707, a Canadian Trial Court decision, was cited but was of little assistance. It was a case concerned with the calculation of income tax. The Court there held that the price received by the taxpayer for the silver it produced was the sum of receipts from delivery of actual production and from settlement of forward sales contracts. The judge applied observations made in the Supreme Court of Canada in Atlantic Sugar Refineries v Minister of National Revenue [1949] CTC 196, another income tax case concerned with whether profits on sugar futures formed part of income. In that case Locke J (Kellock J concurring) said (at [12]): 
 
 In trades where natural products are purchased in large quantities, hedging is a common, and in some cases, a necessary practice, and the cost of such operations in trades of this nature is properly allowable as an operating expense of the business. Where, as in the present case, the trader elects to close out his short sales and take a profit, this is, in my opinion, properly classified as profit from carrying on the trade. 
 

In Echo Bay Mines [1992] 3 CF 707, MacKay J said (at 733):
 
 
 I conclude that the price received by the plaintiff for the silver it produced was the sum of receipts from delivery of actual production and from settlement of forward sales contracts. The business of the plaintiff was silver production. In these circumstances where the plaintiff participated in forward sales contracts and settlements, however, as a hedge against price fluctuations in silver, and in which the commodity traded was silver futures, I do not conclude that the plaintiff was involved in futures speculation for investment purposes. There was a clear business purpose in its sales and settlement of silver futures contracts, a purpose integrated with its sales of product to yield income; the plaintiff was trying to obtain an assured price for the sale of the silver it produced. ... 
 
 Here the forward sales transactions were in respect of the same commodity as the plaintiff's production; both were, in my view, integral aspects of the plaintiff's business of producing silver, and returns from these activities were income from production of metals within Regulation 1204(1).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Gas Light Company v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCA 1525 ; (2003) 137 FCR 317</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/1525.html</AustLII>
<text>271 One of the cases cited was Australian Gas Light Company v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCA 1525 ; (2003) 137 FCR 317 in which I said (at [382]):
 
 Although there are some loose, but not entirely appropriate, analogies between the derivative contract and a form of insurance in my opinion, for present purposes, the derivative contracts ought to be regarded as an integral part of the pricing and payment arrangements between generators and retailers in relation to the underlying product, which is electrical energy, and which they deal with "as if" it had been sold from supplier to retailer. 
 

That observation was made in a statutory context quite different from the present. The case was concerned with whether a proposed acquisition of an interest in an electricity base load generator by an electricity retailer would have, or be likely to have, the effect of substantially lessening competition in a market in Australia. The question of the relationship between derivative contracts and sale of the relevant commodity which, in that case was electricity, was relevant to the question whether there were separate markets to be considered, one for the purchase and sale of derivatives and the other for the sale of electricity. The observation which was quoted from the judgment in that case reflects what Professor Garnaut had to say about the way in which an economist would regard hedging expenses in relation to sales. For the reasons which I have already outlined in discussing his evidence, that kind of equation does not assist in the construction of s 24(a) and (b).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Maritime Union of Australia [2001] FCA 1549 ; (2001) 114 FCR 472</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1549.html</AustLII>
<text>270 As I said in the interlocutory decision in Woodside Energy [2006] FCA 1303 ; 155 FCR 357 at 374, the words "in relation to" and similar terms such as "in respect of" or "in connection with" or just "in" have been considered in many cases and many contexts. All of them indicate a necessary connection between two subject matters which may be activities, events, persons or things. The nature and closeness or remoteness of the connection sufficient to answer the statutory description depends upon its context. The term "in respect of" was said to "[gather] meaning from the context in which it appears ...": Workers' Compensation Board (Qld) v Technical Products Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 49 ; (1988) 165 CLR 642 at 653-4 per Deane, Dawson and Toohey JJ. The term "in relation to" has been called a "prepositional phrase" which is "indefinite" and which "subject to any contrary indication derived from its context or drafting history ... requires no more than a relationship whether direct or indirect between two subject matters": O'Grady v Northern Queensland Co Ltd [1990] HCA 16 ; (1990) 169 CLR 356 at 376 (McHugh J). As the present case illustrates the extent of the relationship required depends upon the context in which the words are used. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Maritime Union of Australia [2001] FCA 1549 ; (2001) 114 FCR 472 at 482. Context and purpose are everything in the construction of such indefinite phrases as "in relation to". The citation of authorities, a number of which were canvassed in argument, is of limited assistance where they relate to different statutory settings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Boral Besser Masonry Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 5 ; (2003) 215 CLR 374</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/5.html</AustLII>
<text>204 Debates about the application and purpose of s 46 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) concerning abuse of market power, illustrate the point. On one view the proper purpose of s 46 as enacted was to protect competition rather than competitors: Melway Publishing Pty Ltd v Robert Hicks Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 13 ; (2001) 205 CLR 1 at 13; Boral Besser Masonry Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 5 ; (2003) 215 CLR 374. Nevertheless the section has been subject to amendment designed to protect the interests of small business rather than the competitive process. The High Court has observed that statutes sometimes embody responses to "shifting and contradictory positions" taken by a range of interest holders in legislative outcomes and expressing "an inarticulate (or at least not publicly disclosed) compromise": Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment (2005) 224 CLR 193 at [32].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Echo Bay Mines Ltd v R [1992] CF 707</tocase>
<text>272 Echo Bay Mines Ltd v R [1992] 3 CF 707, a Canadian Trial Court decision, was cited but was of little assistance. It was a case concerned with the calculation of income tax. The Court there held that the price received by the taxpayer for the silver it produced was the sum of receipts from delivery of actual production and from settlement of forward sales contracts. The judge applied observations made in the Supreme Court of Canada in Atlantic Sugar Refineries v Minister of National Revenue [1949] CTC 196, another income tax case concerned with whether profits on sugar futures formed part of income. In that case Locke J (Kellock J concurring) said (at [12]): 
 
 In trades where natural products are purchased in large quantities, hedging is a common, and in some cases, a necessary practice, and the cost of such operations in trades of this nature is properly allowable as an operating expense of the business. Where, as in the present case, the trader elects to close out his short sales and take a profit, this is, in my opinion, properly classified as profit from carrying on the trade. 
 

In Echo Bay Mines [1992] 3 CF 707, MacKay J said (at 733):
 
 
 I conclude that the price received by the plaintiff for the silver it produced was the sum of receipts from delivery of actual production and from settlement of forward sales contracts. The business of the plaintiff was silver production. In these circumstances where the plaintiff participated in forward sales contracts and settlements, however, as a hedge against price fluctuations in silver, and in which the commodity traded was silver futures, I do not conclude that the plaintiff was involved in futures speculation for investment purposes. There was a clear business purpose in its sales and settlement of silver futures contracts, a purpose integrated with its sales of product to yield income; the plaintiff was trying to obtain an assured price for the sale of the silver it produced. ... 
 
 Here the forward sales transactions were in respect of the same commodity as the plaintiff's production; both were, in my view, integral aspects of the plaintiff's business of producing silver, and returns from these activities were income from production of metals within Regulation 1204(1).

273 The decision of MacKay J in Echo Bay Mines [1992] 3 CF 707 was approved by the Supreme Court of Canada in Placer Dome Canada Ltd v Ontario (Minister of Finance) (2006) SCC 20. In that case the Supreme Court held that hedging transactions fixed the price for the output of a mine. It approved the reasoning of Gillese JA who dissented in the Court of Appeal of Ontario: Placer Come Canada Ltd v Ontario (Minister of Finance) (2004) 190 OAC 157. Woodside Energy relied upon a passage from the dissenting judgment of Gillese JA as supportive of the position taken by Woodside Energy. Her Honour said (at [119]):
 
 The general purpose of the Act is to tax output from a mine. However, there is no reason to refer to anything but the first type of consideration in the definition of "proceeds" if the purpose of that provision is limited to taxing output. The apparent purpose of including the second and third types of consideration is to tax gains arising from specified types of financial transactions (ie hedging, future sales or forward sales) that are related to the output of the mine.
 

The view that hedging transactions were related to the output of the mine in that case was said by counsel for Woodside Energy to sit comfortably with the conclusion that hedge expenses can be incurred "in relation to" the sale of petroleum produced from a petroleum project.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Melway Publishing Pty Ltd v Robert Hicks Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 13 ; (2001) 205 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/13.html</AustLII>
<text>204 Debates about the application and purpose of s 46 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) concerning abuse of market power, illustrate the point. On one view the proper purpose of s 46 as enacted was to protect competition rather than competitors: Melway Publishing Pty Ltd v Robert Hicks Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 13 ; (2001) 205 CLR 1 at 13; Boral Besser Masonry Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 5 ; (2003) 215 CLR 374. Nevertheless the section has been subject to amendment designed to protect the interests of small business rather than the competitive process. The High Court has observed that statutes sometimes embody responses to "shifting and contradictory positions" taken by a range of interest holders in legislative outcomes and expressing "an inarticulate (or at least not publicly disclosed) compromise": Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment (2005) 224 CLR 193 at [32].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>O'Grady v Northern Queensland Co Ltd [1990] HCA 16 ; (1990) 169 CLR 356</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/16.html</AustLII>
<text>270 As I said in the interlocutory decision in Woodside Energy [2006] FCA 1303 ; 155 FCR 357 at 374, the words "in relation to" and similar terms such as "in respect of" or "in connection with" or just "in" have been considered in many cases and many contexts. All of them indicate a necessary connection between two subject matters which may be activities, events, persons or things. The nature and closeness or remoteness of the connection sufficient to answer the statutory description depends upon its context. The term "in respect of" was said to "[gather] meaning from the context in which it appears ...": Workers' Compensation Board (Qld) v Technical Products Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 49 ; (1988) 165 CLR 642 at 653-4 per Deane, Dawson and Toohey JJ. The term "in relation to" has been called a "prepositional phrase" which is "indefinite" and which "subject to any contrary indication derived from its context or drafting history ... requires no more than a relationship whether direct or indirect between two subject matters": O'Grady v Northern Queensland Co Ltd [1990] HCA 16 ; (1990) 169 CLR 356 at 376 (McHugh J). As the present case illustrates the extent of the relationship required depends upon the context in which the words are used. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Maritime Union of Australia [2001] FCA 1549 ; (2001) 114 FCR 472 at 482. Context and purpose are everything in the construction of such indefinite phrases as "in relation to". The citation of authorities, a number of which were canvassed in argument, is of limited assistance where they relate to different statutory settings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Placer Dome Canada Ltd v Ontario (Minister of Finance) (2006) SCC 20</tocase>
<text>273 The decision of MacKay J in Echo Bay Mines [1992] 3 CF 707 was approved by the Supreme Court of Canada in Placer Dome Canada Ltd v Ontario (Minister of Finance) (2006) SCC 20. In that case the Supreme Court held that hedging transactions fixed the price for the output of a mine. It approved the reasoning of Gillese JA who dissented in the Court of Appeal of Ontario: Placer Come Canada Ltd v Ontario (Minister of Finance) (2004) 190 OAC 157. Woodside Energy relied upon a passage from the dissenting judgment of Gillese JA as supportive of the position taken by Woodside Energy. Her Honour said (at [119]):
 
 The general purpose of the Act is to tax output from a mine. However, there is no reason to refer to anything but the first type of consideration in the definition of "proceeds" if the purpose of that provision is limited to taxing output. The apparent purpose of including the second and third types of consideration is to tax gains arising from specified types of financial transactions (ie hedging, future sales or forward sales) that are related to the output of the mine.
 

The view that hedging transactions were related to the output of the mine in that case was said by counsel for Woodside Energy to sit comfortably with the conclusion that hedge expenses can be incurred "in relation to" the sale of petroleum produced from a petroleum project.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Robe River Mining Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1989) 21 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>276 In my opinion the requirement that expenditure contemplated by s 38 is liable to be made in carrying on or providing operations, facilities and other things comprising the project is incapable of covering the hedging expenses the subject of these proceedings. The section contemplates a close connection between the expenditure and the physical activities involved in the petroleum project. Interestingly, one of the cases cited on behalf of Woodside Energy, albeit for a different purpose, was Robe River Mining Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1989) 21 FCR 1 in which the Full Federal Court said: 
 
 The use of the phrase "in carrying on prescribed mining operations" suggests a quite direct relationship between the expenditure and the operations, to be distinguished from the looser relationship which would be expressed by the words "in connection with" if they were used in a provision of this kind. 
 

The passage was used to support the proposition that by not using, in s 24(b), language suggesting the kind of direct connection required in the provisions under discussion in Robe River Mining Co Pty Ltd 21 FCR 1, Parliament had intended to provide for a wide range of relationships between expenses and sales for the purposes of s 24(b). As indicated above, for reasons which I have given, I do not accept that proposition. And it is plain that so far as s 38 is concerned it cannot extend to expenses of the kind in issue in this case.

277 For the preceding reasons the application will be dismissed with costs. 

 I certify that the preceding two hundred and seventy-seven (277) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice French. 

 Associate:
Dated: 10 December 2007

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr JW de Wijn QC and Mr AT Broadfoot 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Allens Arthur Robinson 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms M Gordon SC, Mr SHP Steward and Mr A Pound 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Date of Hearing: 11, 12, 13, 14 and 15 December 2006 
 
 Date of Judgment: 10 December 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1961.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment (2005) 224 CLR 193</tocase>
<text>204 Debates about the application and purpose of s 46 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) concerning abuse of market power, illustrate the point. On one view the proper purpose of s 46 as enacted was to protect competition rather than competitors: Melway Publishing Pty Ltd v Robert Hicks Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 13 ; (2001) 205 CLR 1 at 13; Boral Besser Masonry Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 5 ; (2003) 215 CLR 374. Nevertheless the section has been subject to amendment designed to protect the interests of small business rather than the competitive process. The High Court has observed that statutes sometimes embody responses to "shifting and contradictory positions" taken by a range of interest holders in legislative outcomes and expressing "an inarticulate (or at least not publicly disclosed) compromise": Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment (2005) 224 CLR 193 at [32].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Woodside Energy Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 1303 ; (2006) 155 FCR 357</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1303.html</AustLII>
<text>183 Professor Ross Garnaut is Professor of Economics at the Australian National University. By a letter dated 7 October 2005 he was requested by the solicitors for Woodside Energy to provide his expert opinion in relation to a dispute concerning the appropriate treatment of hedge expenses under the PRRTAA. He produced a report, responsive to a number of questions put to him by the solicitors. The report was exhibited to his affidavit of 28 March 2006. Professor Garnaut's evidence was the subject of a ruling as to admissibility in an interlocutory decision published on 4 October 2006: Woodside Energy Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (2006)155 FCR 357. Under the terms of that ruling it was received subject to relevance.

184 Professor Garnaut served as Principal Economic Advisor to the Prime Minister, Mr RJL Hawke, from 1983 to 1985. From 1985 to 1988 he was Australian Ambassador to the People's Republic of China. He did not occupy any economic advisory role with respect to government when the PRRTAA was enacted in 1987. It appears also that he had no part in the preparation of drafting instructions in relation to the legislation.

185 The questions posed for consideration by Professor Garnaut began by asking for an 'economic perspective' on what is conveyed by the description of a tax as a 'resource rent tax'. He was asked to identify 'from an economic perspective' the features and objectives of such a tax distinguishing it from royalty or excise regimes. He was asked about the relationship between the term 'economic rent' and the profit of a particular resource project in respect of which RRT is payable. Against the background of those questions there were then five specific questions put relating to the hedging losses claimed by Woodside Energy. They were as follows: 
 
 
 5. On the assumption that PRRT is intended to be a tax on "economic rent", would an economist make allowance for amounts received and expenses incurred on the hedging activities undertaken by Woodside in relation to the Laminaria project (as described in the Woodside affidavits) in measuring the amount upon which PRRT is to be levied in relation to the Laminaria project? 
 
 6. Would an economist regard the expenses incurred by Woodside in relation to the hedging transactions described in the Woodside affidavits as expenses payable in relation to the sale of petroleum produced from the Laminaria project?
 
 7. Is there any reason why an economist would treat hedging expenses differently from interest paid in respect of monies borrowed for the purposes of assessing economic rent or the amount upon which to levy PRRT?
 
 8. In your opinion, can the hedge expenses incurred by Woodside in relation to the Laminaria project (as described in the Woodside affidavits) be described from an economic point of view as marginal costs associated with the Laminaria project? You should explain what is meant by the description of a cost as a "marginal cost".
 
 9. If one failed to take into account the hedge expenses incurred by Woodside in relation to the Laminaria project (as described in the Woodside affidavits) in measuring the economic rent or the amount upon which to levy PRRT, what would be the consequences of such a failure in terms of meeting or failing to meet the objectives of a resource rent tax?

270 As I said in the interlocutory decision in Woodside Energy [2006] FCA 1303 ; 155 FCR 357 at 374, the words "in relation to" and similar terms such as "in respect of" or "in connection with" or just "in" have been considered in many cases and many contexts. All of them indicate a necessary connection between two subject matters which may be activities, events, persons or things. The nature and closeness or remoteness of the connection sufficient to answer the statutory description depends upon its context. The term "in respect of" was said to "[gather] meaning from the context in which it appears ...": Workers' Compensation Board (Qld) v Technical Products Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 49 ; (1988) 165 CLR 642 at 653-4 per Deane, Dawson and Toohey JJ. The term "in relation to" has been called a "prepositional phrase" which is "indefinite" and which "subject to any contrary indication derived from its context or drafting history ... requires no more than a relationship whether direct or indirect between two subject matters": O'Grady v Northern Queensland Co Ltd [1990] HCA 16 ; (1990) 169 CLR 356 at 376 (McHugh J). As the present case illustrates the extent of the relationship required depends upon the context in which the words are used. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Maritime Union of Australia [2001] FCA 1549 ; (2001) 114 FCR 472 at 482. Context and purpose are everything in the construction of such indefinite phrases as "in relation to". The citation of authorities, a number of which were canvassed in argument, is of limited assistance where they relate to different statutory settings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Workers' Compensation Board (Qld) v Technical Products Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 49 ; (1988) 165 CLR 642</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/49.html</AustLII>
<text>270 As I said in the interlocutory decision in Woodside Energy [2006] FCA 1303 ; 155 FCR 357 at 374, the words "in relation to" and similar terms such as "in respect of" or "in connection with" or just "in" have been considered in many cases and many contexts. All of them indicate a necessary connection between two subject matters which may be activities, events, persons or things. The nature and closeness or remoteness of the connection sufficient to answer the statutory description depends upon its context. The term "in respect of" was said to "[gather] meaning from the context in which it appears ...": Workers' Compensation Board (Qld) v Technical Products Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 49 ; (1988) 165 CLR 642 at 653-4 per Deane, Dawson and Toohey JJ. The term "in relation to" has been called a "prepositional phrase" which is "indefinite" and which "subject to any contrary indication derived from its context or drafting history ... requires no more than a relationship whether direct or indirect between two subject matters": O'Grady v Northern Queensland Co Ltd [1990] HCA 16 ; (1990) 169 CLR 356 at 376 (McHugh J). As the present case illustrates the extent of the relationship required depends upon the context in which the words are used. See also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Maritime Union of Australia [2001] FCA 1549 ; (2001) 114 FCR 472 at 482. Context and purpose are everything in the construction of such indefinite phrases as "in relation to". The citation of authorities, a number of which were canvassed in argument, is of limited assistance where they relate to different statutory settings.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>