<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kelly v Fitzpatrick [2007] FCA 1080 (27 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1080.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>A ustralian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd (2001) ATPR 41-815</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1997) 145 ALR 36</tocase>
<text>30 Another factor which must be taken into account in the fixing of pecuniary penalties for multiple breaches of statutory stipulations is the totality principle. This principle is designed to ensure that the aggregate of the penalties imposed is not such as to be oppressive or crushing. Different views have been expressed as to the manner in which the principle ought properly to be applied. On one view the starting point should be the determination of an appropriate total penalty. That figure would then be divided by the number of breaches to produce a penalty for each breach: see CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228 at 230[7]. The orthodox position, however, which I consider should be adopted, is that the starting point is the determination of appropriate penalties for each contravention of the statutory norm. The aggregate figure is then considered with a view to ensuring that it is an appropriate response to the conduct which led to the breaches: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1997) 145 ALR 36 at 53. See also Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 at [145] per Jessup J. This approach was recently described, in the criminal context from which the totality principle is derived, as "the orthodox, but not necessarily immutable, practice" adopted by sentencing courts: see Johnson v R [2004] HCA 15 ; (2004) 205 ALR 346 at 356[26] per Gummow, Callinan &amp; Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228</tocase>
<text>28 The respondents have expressed contrition and have put in place mechanisms which are designed to ensure that there will be no repetition of the breaches which have led to the present proceeding. Specific deterrence does not, therefore, loom large as a consideration in determining penalty. It does not follow that the need for general deterrence may be disregarded. As Finkelstein J said in CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228 at 231: "even if there be no need for specific deterrence, there will be occasions when general deterrence must take priority, and in that case a penalty should be imposed to mark the law's disapproval of the conduct in question, and to act as a warning to others not to engage in similar conduct ..." No less than large corporate employers, small businesses have an obligation to meet minimum employment standards and their employees, rightly, have an expectation that this will occur. When it does not it will, normally, be necessary to mark the failure by imposing an appropriate monetary sanction. Such a sanction "must be imposed at a meaningful level": see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd [2001] ATPR 41-815 at [13].

29 In fixing appropriate penalties for breach of each of the relevant Award terms it is necessary to bear in mind that, with the exception of the breach of Clause 12.5 (casual loadings), there were repeated breaches of each of the terms over a period in excess of five years. For a little more than half of this period the maximum penalty (calculated, having regard to s 178(2) and 719 (2), as single breaches of each relevant term) was $2,200. It was $6,600 for the rest of the period. The breaches of Clause 12.5 occurred wholly within the period during which the maximum penalty was $2,200. It is also necessary to bear in mind that the various breaches had a differential financial impact on Mr Paynting. The failure to pay him for overtime hours worked on weekdays accounted for well over half the shortfall. The bulk of this sum is attributable to a failure to comply with Clause 12.5. The next most serious shortfall was in the payment of ordinary hours. Again, it was the failure to take into account Mr Paynting's entitlement to the casual loading which was the main contributor to this underpayment. The underpayments for Saturday, Sunday and public holiday work were relatively minor.

30 Another factor which must be taken into account in the fixing of pecuniary penalties for multiple breaches of statutory stipulations is the totality principle. This principle is designed to ensure that the aggregate of the penalties imposed is not such as to be oppressive or crushing. Different views have been expressed as to the manner in which the principle ought properly to be applied. On one view the starting point should be the determination of an appropriate total penalty. That figure would then be divided by the number of breaches to produce a penalty for each breach: see CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228 at 230[7]. The orthodox position, however, which I consider should be adopted, is that the starting point is the determination of appropriate penalties for each contravention of the statutory norm. The aggregate figure is then considered with a view to ensuring that it is an appropriate response to the conduct which led to the breaches: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1997) 145 ALR 36 at 53. See also Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 at [145] per Jessup J. This approach was recently described, in the criminal context from which the totality principle is derived, as "the orthodox, but not necessarily immutable, practice" adopted by sentencing courts: see Johnson v R [2004] HCA 15 ; (2004) 205 ALR 346 at 356[26] per Gummow, Callinan &amp; Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gibbs v The Mayor, Councillors and the Citizens of the City of Altona (1992) 37 FCR 216</tocase>
<text>11 The parties' agreement about the identification of the terms which had been breached was founded on the construction of s 178(2) which was adopted by Gray J in Gibbs v The Mayor, Councillors and the Citizens of the City of Altona (1992) 37 FCR 216 at 223. His Honour there held that "each separate obligation found in an award is to be regarded as a 'term', for the purposes of s 178..." His Honour further held that, in ascertaining what constitutes a 'term', regard should be had "not [to] matters of form, such as how the award maker has chosen to designate by numbers or letters the various provisions of an award, but on matters of substance, namely the different obligations which can be spelt out." In the present case the parties have fixed on the particular provisions of the Award to which it was necessary to have resort for the purpose of calculating Mr Paynting's minimum legal entitlements to wages. In my view the parties were correct to approach the matter in this manner. The six "terms" which have been identified applied throughout the relevant period and, depending on the days of which Mr Paynting worked, imposed obligations on the respondents as to the level of remuneration payable to him. Whilst the Award was varied from time to time to increase the amounts prescribed by the various terms, the substantial obligation did not vary: it was that the prescribed amount should be paid to Mr Paynting.

12 When calculating Mr Paynting's entitlements under the Award for any given day, it was necessary, in many instances, to have regard to more than one of the aforementioned terms. For example, in the period between 8 February 2001 and 23 June 2004, when he was working on a casual basis, his ordinary hourly rate was supplemented by the casual loading and, if the work was undertaken on a Saturday, a further loading was payable.

13 The parties have agreed that the breaches of particular terms led to the following underpayments:
 
 (a) Underpayment of wages for ordinary hours:
 (i) Clause 12.5.3: $21,711.17
 (ii) Clause 15.1: $3,486.60
 (b) Underpayment of wages for overtime hours Monday to Friday:
 (i) Clauses 12.5.4 and 37.2: $38,233.64
 (ii) Clause 37.2: $23,468.85
 (c) Underpayment of wages for Saturday hours:
 (i) Clauses 12.5.4, 33.2.1 and 37.2: $2,223.45 

(ii) Clauses 33.2.1 and 37.2: $460.82
 
 (d) Underpayment of wages for Sunday hours:
 (i) Clauses 12.5.4 and 35: $4,838.39
 (ii) Clause 35: $1,941.87
 (e) Underpayment of wages for public holiday hours:
 (i) Clauses 12.5.4 and 42.7.1: $79.09
 (ii) Clause 42.6.1: $220.88</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Johnson v R [2004] HCA 15 ; (2004) 205 ALR 346</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/15.html</AustLII>
<text>30 Another factor which must be taken into account in the fixing of pecuniary penalties for multiple breaches of statutory stipulations is the totality principle. This principle is designed to ensure that the aggregate of the penalties imposed is not such as to be oppressive or crushing. Different views have been expressed as to the manner in which the principle ought properly to be applied. On one view the starting point should be the determination of an appropriate total penalty. That figure would then be divided by the number of breaches to produce a penalty for each breach: see CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228 at 230[7]. The orthodox position, however, which I consider should be adopted, is that the starting point is the determination of appropriate penalties for each contravention of the statutory norm. The aggregate figure is then considered with a view to ensuring that it is an appropriate response to the conduct which led to the breaches: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1997) 145 ALR 36 at 53. See also Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 at [145] per Jessup J. This approach was recently described, in the criminal context from which the totality principle is derived, as "the orthodox, but not necessarily immutable, practice" adopted by sentencing courts: see Johnson v R [2004] HCA 15 ; (2004) 205 ALR 346 at 356[26] per Gummow, Callinan &amp; Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Mason v Harrington Corporation Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 7</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/7.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In Mason v Harrington Corporation Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 7 Mowbray FM identified "a non-exhaustive range of considerations to which regard may be had in determining whether particular conduct calls for the imposition of a penalty, and if it does the amount of the penalty". Those considerations were derived from a number of decisions of this Court. I gratefully adopt, as potentially relevant and applicable, the various considerations identified by him. They were:
 
 &#8226; The nature and extent of the conduct which led to the breaches.
 &#8226; The circumstances in which that conduct took place.
 &#8226; The nature and extent of any loss or damage sustained as a result of the breaches.
 &#8226; Whether there had been similar previous conduct by the respondent.
 &#8226; Whether the breaches were properly distinct or arose out of the one course of conduct.
 &#8226; The size of the business enterprise involved.
 &#8226; Whether or not the breaches were deliberate.
 &#8226; Whether senior management was involved in the breaches.
 &#8226; Whether the party committing the breach had exhibited contrition.
 &#8226; Whether the party committing the breach had taken corrective action.
 &#8226; Whether the party committing the breach had cooperated with the enforcement authorities.
 &#8226; The need to ensure compliance with minimum standards by provision of an effective means for investigation and enforcement of employee entitlements and
 &#8226; The need for specific and general deterrence. 

The parties accepted that these considerations should guide the exercise of my discretion in the present proceeding.

15 The various breaches of Award terms which occurred in this case can all be traced to a single source. That source was the decision, made by the first respondent, to offer Mr Paynting employment at an hourly rate. Mr Paynting accepted that offer. Throughout the relevant period Mr Paynting was paid, either at the originally agreed rate, or, subsequently, at higher agreed rates. The wages paid to Mr Paynting were calculated on the basis of the agreed hourly rates. Over a period of a little more than five years this led to the underpayment of $96,664.76 in wages which would have been paid to him had the Award requirements been observed. This underpayment represented about a third of Mr Paynting's wages entitlement under the Award. The amount is significant. Although the shortfall was paid in full to Mr Paynting in April 2007 he was deprived of the financial benefits which timely payment of the correct wages would have provided.

16 The respondents operate their business, in what was described in argument as, "an informal partnership". The first respondent ceased formal eduction at the end of Year 8; the second respondent at the end of Year 9. The business operates from a base in rural Victoria. The first respondent is one of six drivers employed in the business. The second respondent works one day a week in the business attending to the payment of wages and accounts rendered. Day to day administration is in the hands of an employed manager. The turnover of the business has fluctuated over time. Between 1996 and 2006 the turnover in each year has fallen within the range of $1.2 million to $1.5 million. The average operating profit over this period, prior to any drawings by the respondents, has been $64,383 per year. In order to make good the underpayment to Mr Paynting it was necessary for the business to extend its overdraft. Apart from an accountant, the business had no external professional advisers. In particular, it did not retain anyone with expertise in industrial law. The respondents were not members of any employer or industry association.

17 The respondents gave uncontradicted evidence that, at all relevant times, prior to June 2006, they were unaware of the existence of the Award or of its application to their business. This was despite the fact that a series of certified letters which related to the making of the Award and its predecessors and the respondency of the business to it was sent to their business address. There was no evidence as to why this correspondence did not come to the respondents' attention or, if it did, why they had overlooked it. Counsel for the respondents accepted that there were avenues available to them which would have enabled them to ascertain their obligations had they been aware of those avenues and minded to utilise them. In these circumstances I infer that the respondent's ignorance of their obligations under the Award, on the view most favourable to them, was the result of carelessness and inadvertence.

18 As already noted the underpayments totalled $96,664.76. They occurred over a period of a little over five years and represented approximately one third of the amount to which Mr Paynting was entitled.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/65.html</AustLII>
<text>30 Another factor which must be taken into account in the fixing of pecuniary penalties for multiple breaches of statutory stipulations is the totality principle. This principle is designed to ensure that the aggregate of the penalties imposed is not such as to be oppressive or crushing. Different views have been expressed as to the manner in which the principle ought properly to be applied. On one view the starting point should be the determination of an appropriate total penalty. That figure would then be divided by the number of breaches to produce a penalty for each breach: see CPSU v Telstra Corporation Limited (2001) 108 IR 228 at 230[7]. The orthodox position, however, which I consider should be adopted, is that the starting point is the determination of appropriate penalties for each contravention of the statutory norm. The aggregate figure is then considered with a view to ensuring that it is an appropriate response to the conduct which led to the breaches: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1997) 145 ALR 36 at 53. See also Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 at [145] per Jessup J. This approach was recently described, in the criminal context from which the totality principle is derived, as "the orthodox, but not necessarily immutable, practice" adopted by sentencing courts: see Johnson v R [2004] HCA 15 ; (2004) 205 ALR 346 at 356[26] per Gummow, Callinan &amp; Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>