<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHPD v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 157 (15 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/157.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/17.html</AustLII>
<text>22 The fourth ground asserts that the Tribunal's findings were biased. There is no basis upon which I can conclude that the allegation of bias is 'distinctly made and clearly proved': Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at 531, [69] per Gleeson CJ and Gummow J. There is simply no evidence to support such a contention.

23 As no arguable basis on which an appeal might succeed has been raised, the present application should be dismissed with costs. I will allow the first respondent to be correctly names at as the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship.
 


 I certify that the preceding twenty-three (23) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Middleton. 


 Associate:

Dated: 20 February 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: B Rayment 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 15 February 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 February 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/157.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SYLB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2005) 87 ALD 498</tocase>
<text>18 In relation to the first ground, I agree with his Honour that there was no error of law in the Tribunal's finding that the applicant could relocate in India as it found that the persecution claimed to be suffered by the applicant was localised in rural areas. The Tribunal correctly applied the principles identified by Branson J in SYLB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2005) 87 ALD 498, and assessed the personal considerations of the applicant to find that he could reasonably be expected to relocate within India. Therefore, no error arises in that regard.

19 The second purported ground of appeal alleges that s 424A of the Act was not applied correctly. I agree with the Federal Magistrate's finding that there was no breach by the Tribunal of s 424A. As his Honour found at [25], the information relied upon was independent country information, which falls within the exceptions in s 424A(3)(a) because it is information that is not specifically about the applicant or another person and is just about a class of persons of which the applicant or other person is a member. Furthermore, as his Honour noted, the Tribunal did put matters relating to the independent country information to the applicant at the hearing.

20 The three further grounds were not raised before the Federal Magistrate but can be considered on their merits. The third and fifth purported grounds in substance allege the same error and so I will consider the allegations together. As I have found above, the Tribunal put the independent country information to the applicant at the hearing. Even though it was not required to put such information to the applicant according to the exception in s 424A(3)(a) , the Tribunal clearly put the applicant on notice that it would be considering the independent country information and in these circumstances there can be no breach of procedural fairness or natural justice.

21 Further, I do not need to consider any common law rules relating to natural justice as s 422B of the Act was in force at the time the applicant made his application to the Tribunal on or about 10 June 2005.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>