<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Telstra Corporation Limited v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission (No 3) [2007] FCA 1905 (12 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1905.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>97 Telstra seeks a declaration that ' the decision of [the Commission] made on or about 12 April 2006 under section 151AKA ' of the Act to issue the Competition Notice was invalid. Telstra submits that it has ' a real interest in a clearly defined, straightforward declaration ' ( Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 at 582).

98 The Commission submits that the appropriate declaration is that, in the events that have happened and in the circumstances of this case, the Commission was not entitled to issue the Competition Notice. The Commission submits that the decision to issue the Competition Notice in the form in which it was issued did not, in and of itself, affect Telstra's rights in any way or have any statutory consequences; it was the issue and service of the Competition Notice that was defective.

99 Telstra relies on s 163A of the Act which relevantly provides:
 
 
 (1) Subject to this section, a person may, in relation to a matter arising under this Act... [seek] the making of: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (aa) a declaration in relation to the validity of any act or thing done, proposed to be done or purporting to have been done under this Act.

100 The act or thing done under the Act was the issue of the Competition Notice. The words "in relation to" in s 163A have wide import but the subject to which the declaration relates is the validity of the issue of the Competition Notice, not the anterior decision to issue that notice, which was not done under the Act. Section 151AKA of the Act is not concerned with the decision to issue the Competition Notice but with the issue of and content of the Competition Notice and the preceding notice under s 151AKA(10), the Consultation Notice.

106 Telstra also relies on s 16(1)(a) of the ADJR Act, which does not provide for a declaration of invalidity. As an alternative to a declaration, Telstra now seeks an order quashing the decision. Telstra points out that it was denied natural justice in the making of the decision. Telstra submits that the Commission's decision has consequences for its reputation. In those circumstances, it submits, it is appropriate that a declaration be made ( Ainsworth at 582). However, apart from the fact that a decision was made to issue the invalid Competition Notice, there is no evidence that the decision had an effect or the consequences alleged.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/72.html</AustLII>
<text>63 Further, Telstra was not given a reasonable opportunity to consult, or to comment and make submissions, or to change its conduct to avoid the issue of the Competition Notice ( Telstra No 2 at [181]). The statutory scheme and common law principles afforded such a right. Telstra was, therefore, denied procedural fairness in the issue of the Competition Notice. The fact that the Commission could have issued a different Part A competition notice, such as the one now proposed, does not discharge the Commission's obligation to give Telstra procedural fairness ( Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88 at [18] ).

64 Section 2 of the Interpretation Act provides that the Interpretation Act applies to all Acts subject to a contrary intention. Subject to a contrary intention the Competition Notice is an instrument which is considered an Act for the purposes of the Interpretation Act and s 46(1) applies (s 46(1)(a)). The Commission submits that any contrary intention for the application of s 46 must be found in the instrument. The parties do not submit a contrary intention is apparent in the Competition Notice.

65 Whether or not there is a contrary intention apparent in the Competition Notice, an indication of contrary intention is not limited to the instrument. It may be apparent from the legislation authorising the making of the instrument.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Azevedo v Secretary, Department of Primary Industries and Energy (1992) 35 FCR 284</tocase>
<text>45 It is not disputed that the Competition Notice is an instrument to which s 46 applies because:
 
 (a) Section 151AKA(2) of the Act specifies the power to issue a Part A competition notice.
 (b) The power is expressly conferred on the Commission, which is a body established by s 6A(1) of the Act and which is a statutory agency under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth) ( Foxtel Management Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2000) 173 ALR 362 at [135] per Wilcox J). The Commission is therefore an "authority" for the purposes of s 46 of the Interpretation Act .
 (c) The relevant power is the power of the Commission to issue a document, namely the Part A competition notice, which is an "instrument" (Shorter Oxford English Dictionary, Azevedo v Secretary, Department of Primary Industries and Energy (1992) 35 FCR 284 at 299-300 per French J; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Lawlor (1979) 24 ALR 307 at 313 and 323-324 referred to in Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 945 at [22] per Merkel J).
 (d) A Part A competition notice is not a legislative instrument under the Legislative Instruments Act as it is not legislative in character, nor is it a rule of Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs (NSW) v Lawlor (1979) 24 ALR 307</tocase>
<text>45 It is not disputed that the Competition Notice is an instrument to which s 46 applies because:
 
 (a) Section 151AKA(2) of the Act specifies the power to issue a Part A competition notice.
 (b) The power is expressly conferred on the Commission, which is a body established by s 6A(1) of the Act and which is a statutory agency under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth) ( Foxtel Management Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2000) 173 ALR 362 at [135] per Wilcox J). The Commission is therefore an "authority" for the purposes of s 46 of the Interpretation Act .
 (c) The relevant power is the power of the Commission to issue a document, namely the Part A competition notice, which is an "instrument" (Shorter Oxford English Dictionary, Azevedo v Secretary, Department of Primary Industries and Energy (1992) 35 FCR 284 at 299-300 per French J; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Lawlor (1979) 24 ALR 307 at 313 and 323-324 referred to in Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 945 at [22] per Merkel J).
 (d) A Part A competition notice is not a legislative instrument under the Legislative Instruments Act as it is not legislative in character, nor is it a rule of Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Darling Casino Limited v Minister for Planning and Sydney Harbour Casino Pty Ltd (1995) 86 LGERA 186</tocase>
<text>57 A distinction is also to be drawn between, on the one hand, questions of severance which involve an excess of power so that the ultra vires portion of an instrument can be severed and the intra vires portion preserved and, on the other hand, a lack of power to make the whole instrument by reason of a failure to comply with the consultation provision in a statute ( Darling Casino Limited v Minister for Planning and Sydney Harbour Casino Pty Ltd (1995) 86 LGERA 186). As Pearlman CJ observed in Darling Casino at 207, if the power was improperly exercised, the instrument is invalid in its totality. It is no answer that part of it could have been validly made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 945</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/945.html</AustLII>
<text>45 It is not disputed that the Competition Notice is an instrument to which s 46 applies because:
 
 (a) Section 151AKA(2) of the Act specifies the power to issue a Part A competition notice.
 (b) The power is expressly conferred on the Commission, which is a body established by s 6A(1) of the Act and which is a statutory agency under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth) ( Foxtel Management Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2000) 173 ALR 362 at [135] per Wilcox J). The Commission is therefore an "authority" for the purposes of s 46 of the Interpretation Act .
 (c) The relevant power is the power of the Commission to issue a document, namely the Part A competition notice, which is an "instrument" (Shorter Oxford English Dictionary, Azevedo v Secretary, Department of Primary Industries and Energy (1992) 35 FCR 284 at 299-300 per French J; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Lawlor (1979) 24 ALR 307 at 313 and 323-324 referred to in Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 945 at [22] per Merkel J).
 (d) A Part A competition notice is not a legislative instrument under the Legislative Instruments Act as it is not legislative in character, nor is it a rule of Court.

85 The Commission submits that Telstra No 2 allows for the invalid parts of the Competition Notice to be distinctly identified so that they can be severed and that there is no indication of interdependence with other sections. Also, the Commission submits that severance would not give the Competition Notice a substantially different operation or effect ( Evans [2002] FCA 945 at [43] per Merkel J). The Commission seeks to sever paragraphs 5(g) and 12(a) referring to Lower Spend Customers and paragraph 12(e) referring to unbundled Fixed Voice Services, being the different kinds of anti-competitive conduct to those summarised in the Consultation Notice.

86 To the extent that the Commission seeks to sever the references to those parts of conduct that were not part of the conduct described in summary form in the Consultation Notice, severance is not possible. The Commission submits that the offending parts of the notice should be disregarded, as if they were not there. While it is possible to rule a line through the offending provisions, such a "blue pencil exercise" is not appropriate. To do so alters the nature of the conduct the subject of the notice ( Victoria at 502) and also alters the content and meaning of the notice. I am not satisfied that the clauses proposed to be severed are other than interrelated and interdependent within the remainder of the Competition Notice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 276 ; (2003) 135 FCR 306</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/276.html</AustLII>
<text>50 If an Act, legislative instrument or an instrument issued by an authority acting within the power of a provision is construed as being in excess of authority, it is to be "read down" or severed to be valid to the extent that it is not within power. It is read down to bring it within power, providing that the instrument itself contains some test that would permit severance ( Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 276 ; (2003) 135 FCR 306 at [63] per Kenny J). However, as Kenny J pointed out at [65], it may not be possible if various aspects or requirements that are within and beyond power are interdependent.

51 The Commission's submissions are as follows:
 
 &#8226; Section 46(1)(c) of the Interpretation Act operates to ensure that the Competition Notice is read and construed subject to Pt XIB of the Act and so as not to exceed the power of the Commission to issue the notice. 
 &#8226; When the Competition Notice is so construed, if it is found still to be in excess of the power of the Commission, then it is taken as a valid notice to the extent that it is not in excess of power by s 46(2). 
 &#8226; If two constructions of the Competition Notice were open and only one was within power, s 46(1)(c) requires the Court to construe the notice so as to be within power. This may be achieved by severing the offending paragraphs, which are those that deal with the Lower Spend Customers and the bundling issues. The balance of the Competition Notice would therefore be valid.

52 Section 46(1)(a) of the Interpretation Act provides that each provision in the Competition Notice is to be construed as if it were a section of an Act. The Commission submits that s 46 can be satisfied by simply excising references to additional matter found to constitute a disconformity between the matter the subject of the Consultation Notice and the terms of the Competition Notice. The Commission recognises that this may not be appropriate if what seems to be a simple excision alters the sense of the Competition Notice or causes it to operate in an otherwise unintended or invalid manner.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fieldhouse v Commissioner of Taxation (1989) 25 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>101 The validity of the Competition Notice and procedural fairness afforded before its issue are determined by the content and context of the provisions of Pt XIB of the Act. There is no evidence of the decision or decisions that were made. A decision or, indeed, a series of decisions concerning a Part A competition notice or its issue could be made and never implemented. The decision itself has no statutory consequences in the Act. It does not sufficiently relate to the validity of the Competition Notice. Counsel were unable to point to any comparable case, such as those arising under s 155 of the Act or ss 263 and 264 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth) where not only the statutory notice but also the decision to issue the notice was quashed or declared invalid (cf Fieldhouse v Commissioner of Taxation (1989) 25 FCR 187 where the validity of four notices issued by the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation pursuant to s 264(1) of the Income Tax Assessment Act was considered but the decision to issue those notices was not, in effect, considered).

102 A declaration under s 163A(1)(aa) of the Act could extend to the validity of the Consultation Notice, the validity of the Competition Notice and the entitlement of the Commission to issue the Competition Notice. It does not extend to the decision to issue the Competition Notice.

103 However, Telstra also relies on the ADJR Act. The Commission did not and does not dispute that the decision to issue the Competition Notice is a decision to which s 5 of the ADJR Act applies. In the light of that concession, I gave no consideration in Telstra No 2 as to whether or not this was so.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Foxtel Management Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2000) 173 ALR 362</tocase>
<text>45 It is not disputed that the Competition Notice is an instrument to which s 46 applies because:
 
 (a) Section 151AKA(2) of the Act specifies the power to issue a Part A competition notice.
 (b) The power is expressly conferred on the Commission, which is a body established by s 6A(1) of the Act and which is a statutory agency under the Public Service Act 1999 (Cth) ( Foxtel Management Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2000) 173 ALR 362 at [135] per Wilcox J). The Commission is therefore an "authority" for the purposes of s 46 of the Interpretation Act .
 (c) The relevant power is the power of the Commission to issue a document, namely the Part A competition notice, which is an "instrument" (Shorter Oxford English Dictionary, Azevedo v Secretary, Department of Primary Industries and Energy (1992) 35 FCR 284 at 299-300 per French J; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Lawlor (1979) 24 ALR 307 at 313 and 323-324 referred to in Evans v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 945 at [22] per Merkel J).
 (d) A Part A competition notice is not a legislative instrument under the Legislative Instruments Act as it is not legislative in character, nor is it a rule of Court.

83 There is a presumption in favour of the independence of various provisions in an enactment, to which effect should be given unless there is a positive indication of interdependence which is apparent from the text, context, content or subject matter of the provision ( Foxtel Management at [136], Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 at 127).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/49.html</AustLII>
<text>83 There is a presumption in favour of the independence of various provisions in an enactment, to which effect should be given unless there is a positive indication of interdependence which is apparent from the text, context, content or subject matter of the provision ( Foxtel Management at [136], Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 at 127).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harrington v Lowe [1996] HCA 8 ; (1996) 190 CLR 311</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/8.html</AustLII>
<text>56 Section 46 of the Interpretation Act , like s 15A, may apply where ' particular clauses, provisos and qualifications, separately expressed' are beyond power ( Harrington v Lowe [1996] HCA 8 ; (1996) 190 CLR 311 at 327). It does not apply to validate a provision which extends beyond power unless the operation of the remaining parts of the instrument remain unchanged. It does not apply where the instrument was intended to operate fully and completely according to its terms or not at all ( Victoria v The Commonwealth [1995] HCA 45 ; (1995) 187 CLR 416 at 502).

87 Section 46 of the Interpretation Act , like s 15A ( Harrington at 327), cannot be applied to effect a partial validation if, as here, it is apparent that the statutory provision for consultation was intended to operate fully and completely according to its terms or not at all ( Victoria at 502).

88 This is not a case of a notice issued within power being, in its terms or content, in excess of power. Assuming, without deciding, that the proposed changes to the Competition Notice make it accord with the Consultation Notice, those changes do not alter the fact that Telstra was, at the time of the issue of the Competition Notice, denied the opportunities provided for in the Act as referred to in Telstra No 2 at [181] and [202]. The notice is invalid in its entirety.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hyster Australia Pty Ltd v Anti-dumping Authority (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 259</tocase>
<text>16 Factors relevant to the exercise of discretion include the interests of the party seeking to have the matter argued, any prejudice to the respondent party, the policy inherent in s 22 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) and the public interest in the finality of justice ( Hyster Australia Pty Ltd v Anti-dumping Authority (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 259 at 263).

17 One consideration is whether s 46 applies to "save" the Competition Notice.

18 The question of utility arises as the Competition Notice is no longer in force. The Competition Notice was revoked on 2 March 2007 with effect from 28 February 2007. Optus has consented to orders dismissing with costs the proceedings it commenced against Telstra in reliance on the Competition Notice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj [2002] HCA 11 ; (2002) 209 CLR 597</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/11.html</AustLII>
<text>60 There was therefore a failure on the part of the Commission to comply with the procedures required by law to be observed. The pre-condition for the issue of the Competition Notice was not met. A failure to comply with mandatory procedures constitutes jurisdictional error ( SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [13]). If there was no authorised decision to issue a Part A competition notice, the Competition Notice did not accord with the [2002] HCA 11 ; Act ( Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj (2002) 209 CLR 597 at [43] and [51] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pacific National (ACT) Ltd v Queensland Rail (2005) 215 ALR 544</tocase>
<text>26 Further, the Commission submits that, as a government agency, the discretionary factors to be applied regarding its position may be approached differently to those of a commercial litigant. The Commission points to the decision of Jacobson J in Pacific National (ACT) Ltd v Queensland Rail (2005) 215 ALR 544 at 560 where his Honour cited P &amp; C Cantarella v Egg Marketing Board (NSW) [1973] 2 NSWLR 366 at 383 per Mahoney JA:
 
 The duty of the executive branch is to ascertain the law and obey it. If there is any difficulty in ascertaining what the law is, as applicable to a particular case, it is open to the executive to approach the court, or afford the citizen the opportunity for approaching the court, to clarify the matter. Where the matter is before the court, it is the duty of the executive to assist the court to arrive at the proper and just result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Park Oh Ho v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1989] HCA 54 ; (1989) 167 CLR 637</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/54.html</AustLII>
<text>105 Telstra relies upon s 16(1)(c) of the ADJR Act to support its application for a declaration that the decision to issue the Competition Notice was invalid. That subsection may extend to any matter connected with an impugned decision that is appropriate to be dealt with by the grant of declaratory relief ( Park Oh Ho v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1989] HCA 54 ; (1989) 167 CLR 637 at 644). However, s 16(1)(c) provides for a declaration in respect of a matter to which the decision relates, not the decision itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pidoto v Victoria [1943] HCA 37 ; (1943) 68 CLR 87 at 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1943/37.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Section 46 of the Interpretation Act is applied as a rule of construction to permit the reading down of instruments. It is not a rule of law ( Vanstone v Clark [2005] FCAFC 189 ; (2005) 147 FCR 299 at [16] per Black CJ referring to Pidoto v Victoria [1943] HCA 37 ; (1943) 68 CLR 87 at 110 per Latham CJ). The Commission has not referred to anything in the Act or in any extrinsic legislative materials to support the proposition that s 46 extends beyond such a limited application. Section 46 of the Interpretation Act concerns the construction of instruments. Both ss 46(1)(c) and 46 (2) provide for a construction to be applied. To read and construe an instrument by the application of s 46(1)(c) is not to rewrite it or to ignore its content. Section 46 has no application to a decision made under an Act. It has no application to a denial of procedural fairness.

84 Severance is more likely when separable words or expressions are used and the test for severance is qualitative rather than quantitative ( Pidoto at 110-111 per Latham CJ). There is no separate specification in s 46(2) of the Interpretation Act that it apply subject to a contrary intention. However, s 2 of the Interpretation Act still applies.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/28.html</AustLII>
<text>70 As stated in Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 28 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at [91] :
 
 An act done in breach of a condition regulating the exercise of a statutory power is not necessarily invalid and of no effect. Whether it is depends upon whether there can be discerned a legislative purpose to invalidate any act that fails to comply with the condition. The existence of the purpose is ascertained by reference to the language of the statute, its subject matter and objects, and the consequences for the parties of holding void every act done in breach of the condition. Unfortunately, a finding of purpose or no purpose in this context often reflects a contestable judgment.

71 The Act does provide for the possibility of variation of a Part A competition notice but specifies in s 151AOA that, while the notice is in force, variation can only be of a minor nature. The proposed variations cannot be said to fall into this category.

72 Part XIB does not envisage that a Part A competition notice may issue with retrospective effect. If an invalid Part A competition notice were subsequently validated by the application of s 46 of the Interpretation Act , the re-construed or amended notice would have retrospective effect for the period that the initial Part A competition notice would have been in force.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>P &amp; C Cantarella v Egg Marketing Board (NSW) [1973] 2 NSWLR 366</tocase>
<text>26 Further, the Commission submits that, as a government agency, the discretionary factors to be applied regarding its position may be approached differently to those of a commercial litigant. The Commission points to the decision of Jacobson J in Pacific National (ACT) Ltd v Queensland Rail (2005) 215 ALR 544 at 560 where his Honour cited P &amp; C Cantarella v Egg Marketing Board (NSW) [1973] 2 NSWLR 366 at 383 per Mahoney JA:
 
 The duty of the executive branch is to ascertain the law and obey it. If there is any difficulty in ascertaining what the law is, as applicable to a particular case, it is open to the executive to approach the court, or afford the citizen the opportunity for approaching the court, to clarify the matter. Where the matter is before the court, it is the duty of the executive to assist the court to arrive at the proper and just result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sportodds Systems Pty Limited v New South Wales [2003] FCAFC 237 ; (2003) 133 FCR 63 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/237.html</AustLII>
<text>89 Severance does not answer the fact that the decision to issue the Competition Notice was not properly made. The condition precedent to its issue had not been complied with. The statutory scheme for consultation prior to the issue of a Part A competition notice is rendered redundant if, once it is found that the procedure was not followed, the Part A competition notice is retrospectively altered to equate "on its face" with the s 151AKA(10) notice. That makes a mockery of the intention of Pt XIB of the Act. Severance is not available in such circumstances ( Sportodds Systems Pty Limited v New South Wales [2003] FCAFC 237 ; (2003) 133 FCR 63 at [19] [24]). As the Full Court said in Sportodds at [18]-[19] in relation to s 15A of the Interpretation Act :
 
 Notwithstanding the broad terms in which these provisions are expressed, the statutory provisions are nevertheless limited...This limits the extent to which a court can redraft a statutory provision. 
 
 ... 
 
 But the essential issue remains is the court carrying out the permissible function of the interpretation of the statute (read in the context of the relevant Acts Interpretation Act provision), or is the court itself making legislation?

90 To overcome the denial of procedural fairness found in Telstra No 2 , the Commission says that, if the Competition Notice is construed by applying s 46 to read down the notice by adopting the alternative construction advanced by the Commission or read to disregard those parts that refer to Lower Spend Customers and bundling issues, there was no problem with procedural fairness as those parts of the Competition Notice were not operative. In the Commission's submission, the Competition Notice identified a number of independent kinds of anti-competitive conduct. It says that, on severance of the kinds of conduct not described in the Consultation Notice, Telstra was given the opportunity to consult on the kinds of conduct that remain. As a consequence, the Commission submits, there is no longer a procedural fairness issue to be considered. The denial of procedural fairness simply disappears. This submission has an air of unreality and demonstrates a reason why s 46 does not apply where there has been jurisdictional error.

91 I do not accept that the offending parts of the Competition Notice can be severed as proposed by the Commission.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Strickland v Rocla Concrete Pipes Ltd [1971] HCA 40 ; (1971) 124 CLR 468</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/40.html</AustLII>
<text>58 Before embarking on the process of reading down, there must be some part of the impugned provision that is capable of being within power. While s 46(2) of the Interpretation Act may apply to cut down the scope of an overly wide provision, there is no occasion for reading down if the provision is wholly beyond power. As with s 15A, s 46 does not turn an Act or instrument which is invalid as being wholly outside legislative power into an Act which is, in part, within power ( Strickland v Rocla Concrete Pipes Ltd [1971] HCA 40 ; (1971) 124 CLR 468 at 504 per Menzies J and cited by Black CJ in Vanstone at [17]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship (2007) 235 ALR 609</tocase>
<text>60 There was therefore a failure on the part of the Commission to comply with the procedures required by law to be observed. The pre-condition for the issue of the Competition Notice was not met. A failure to comply with mandatory procedures constitutes jurisdictional error ( SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [13]). If there was no authorised decision to issue a Part A competition notice, the Competition Notice did not accord with the [2002] HCA 11 ; Act ( Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj (2002) 209 CLR 597 at [43] and [51] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Telstra Corporation Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2006) 68 IPR 571</tocase>
<text>107 Each of Telstra and the Commission submit that its form of declaration encapsulates the result in Telstra No 2 . It is of interest that, in written submissions and correctly, Telstra characterises that result as a decision ' that the Competition Notice was invalid '. The issues that fell for consideration concerned the Competition Notice and the Consultation Notice, not the reasoning behind the issue of those notices. Telstra's claims turned upon the construction of the Competition Notice and the Consultation Notice, a comparison between them and a evaluation of the requirements of s 151AKA(2) of the Act. Telstra did not allege that the Commission had no reason to believe that Telstra had engaged or was engaging in the relevant anti-competitive conduct or that the notices were issued for a collateral or improper purpose. There was no consideration of the decision-making process of the Commission ( Telstra Corporation Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2006) 68 IPR 571).

108 I am not satisfied that Telstra is entitled to the declaration of invalidity of the decision that it seeks or that, were an order to be made that the Competition Notice be quashed ab initio, there is utility in making that declaration. I am not satisfied that it is appropriate to make an order quashing the decision. The form of declaration proffered by the Commission is sufficient to give effect to the reasons in Telstra No 2 . The orders will quash the Competition Notice and set aside, not quash, the decision to issue the Competition Notice. 

 I certify that the preceding one hundred and eight (108) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 


 Associate:

Dated: 11 December 2007

 Counsel for the Applicant: T F Bathurst QC; J E Griffiths SC; J K Kirk 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: L G Foster SC 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Date of Hearing: 8 May 2007; 7 June 2007; 10 July 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 12 December 2007 

 ANNEXURE A
 TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 
 Part A Competition Notice issued pursuant to section 151AKA(2) 

 
 
The Proper Officer
Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556)
Level 41, 242 Exhibition Street
MELBOURNE VIC 3000
 
 PREAMBLE 
 
This notice is a Part A competition notice issued by the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (the Commission ) pursuant to section 151AKA(2) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (the Act ) to Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556) ( Telstra ).
 
 
 DEFINITIONS AND INTERPRETATION 
 
1. In this notice:
 
 
 a. Fixed Voice Services means the following residential telephony services supplied by way of a PSTN: 
 
 
 
 
 .109 Local Services; 
 110 fixed-to-mobile call services; 
 111 national long distance call services; and 
 112 international call services; 
 
 
 
 
 b. Home Access increase has the meaning given in paragraph 5.c;
 c. HomeLine Part increase has the meaning given in paragraph 5.a;
 d. Local Services means residential line rental and local call services supplied for the end-use of Retail Customers, whether supplied on a retail or wholesale basis; 
 e. PSTN means a Public Switched Telephone Network;
 f. PSTN OTA Charges means charges levied by a carrier or carriage service provider in respect of the supply of originating and terminating access to its PSTN; 
 g. Retail Customers means end-user customers throughout Australia who acquire Local Services and who may also acquire other Fixed Voice Service(s); 
 h. Retail FVS Market has the meaning given in paragraph 7.b;
 i. Retail Price means the price at which Retail Customers are supplied with Fixed Voice Services;
 j. Retail Transformation Costs mean the incremental or avoidable costs of transforming Local Services and PSTN originating and terminating services into services suitable for retail supply, including costs associated with customer acquisition and the development and maintenance of support systems necessary for retail supply, such as billing systems;
 k. Telstra's Rivals means: 
 
 
 
 
 113 Telstra's Wholesale Customers; and
 114 Telstra's prospective Wholesale Customers, 
 
 
 
 
 who compete or would compete in the Retail FVS Market on a basis that is no less efficient than Telstra; 
 l. Total Cost means, in respect of a Fixed Voice Service supplied to Retail Customers, the sum of: 
 
 
 
 
 115 the Wholesale Price;
 116 the PSTN OTA Charges; and
 117 the Retail Transformation Costs, 
 
 
 
 
 relating to the supply of that Fixed Voice Service; 
 m. Wholesale Customers means carriers or carriage service providers who acquire Local Services for use in the supply of Fixed Voice Services to Retail Customers;
 n. Wholesale Local Services Market has the meaning given in paragraph 7.a; and
 o. Wholesale Price means the price at which Telstra supplies Telstra's Wholesale Customers with Local Services. 
 

2. In this notice:
 
 
 a. the singular includes the plural and the plural includes the singular;
 b. a defined word appearing in another grammatical form has the equivalent meaning; and
 c. unless the contrary intention appears, words used in this notice which are defined in section 151AB of the Act have the same meaning as given in section 151AB.
 
 
 SECTION 151AKA(2) STATEMENT 
 
 3. Telstra has engaged, and is engaging, in at least one instance of anti-competitive conduct of a kind described in this notice. 
 

 REASON TO BELIEVE 
 
4. The Commission has reason to believe that Telstra has engaged, and is engaging, in at least one instance of anti-competitive conduct of a kind described in this notice.
 

 THE CONDUCT 
 
 5. Telstra has engaged in the following conduct: 
 
 
 a. Effective 1 December 2005, Telstra imposed an increase in the Retail Price of one of its Local Services products, HomeLine Part (the HomeLine Part increase ). Table A of Schedule 1 provides details as to the Retail Price at which Telstra supplied HomeLine Part immediately before the HomeLine Part increase and immediately after the HomeLine Part increase. 
 

 Explanatory note: HomeLine Part permits a Retail Customer to acquire its Local Services from Telstra, but to "pre-select" other providers in respect of all or any of the other Fixed Voice Services. Consequently, HomeLine Part enables Telstra's competitors to supply Fixed Voice Services (other than Local Services) to HomeLine Part customers on a pre-selection basis. 
 
 
 b. At the time of the HomeLine Part increase, Telstra did not increase the Retail Price of any of its other Fixed Voice Services products.
 c. Effective 5 December 2005, Telstra imposed an increase in the Wholesale Price of the monthly charge for a wholesale basic telephone service with its Local Services product, Home Access (the Home Access increase ). Schedule 2 provides details as to the Wholesale Price at which Telstra supplied a wholesale basic telephone service with Home Access immediately before the Home Access increase and immediately after the Home Access increase. 
 

 Explanatory note: Home Access is a wholesale input used by Telstra's Wholesale Customers to provide line rental and local call services (i.e. Local Services) products to Retail Customers. 
 
 
 d. At the time of the Home Access increase, Telstra did not increase the Retail Price of its Local Services products or any of its other Fixed Voice Services products. Table B of Schedule 1 provides details as to the key Retail Prices at which Telstra supplied its various Fixed Voice Services products immediately before the Home Access increase and Table C of Schedule 1 provides details of Telstra's key Retail Prices after the Home Access increase. 
 e. Telstra actively promoted the implications of its new pricing structure for its various Fixed Voice Services to Retail Customers.
 f. From at least 5 December 2005 to the present and continuing: 
 
 
 
 
 118 Telstra has supplied, and continues to supply: 
 
 

119 Local Services to Telstra's Wholesale Customers at the Wholesale Price applicable immediately after the Home Access increase; and
 
 120 Fixed Voice Services to Retail Customers at Retail Prices which are materially unchanged from those applicable immediately after the Home Access increase; 
 
 
 
 121 Telstra has refused, and continues to refuse, to supply: 
 
 

122 Local Services to Telstra's Wholesale Customers other than at the Wholesale Price applicable immediately after the Home Access increase, except in limited circumstances; and
 
 123 Fixed Voice Services (other than new products introduced since the Home Access increase) to Retail Customers other than at Retail Prices which are materially unchanged from those applicable immediately after the Home Access increase.
 
 
 CARRIER 
 
6. Telstra is and was at all material times a carrier.
 

 TELECOMMUNICATIONS MARKETS 
 
 7. At all material times, there were and are markets in Australia that are no wider than markets for:
 
 
 a. the supply and acquisition of wholesale Local Services (the Wholesale Local Services Market ); and
 b. the supply and acquisition of retail Fixed Voice Services (the Retail FVS Market ). 
 

8. Each market identified above at paragraph 7 is a telecommunications market. 
 
 
 MARKET POWER 
 
 9. In the supply of Local Services in the Wholesale Local Services Market, Telstra is not materially constrained by the conduct of:
 
 
 a. Telstra's competitors and potential competitors in the Wholesale Local Services Market; or
 b. persons to whom or from whom Telstra supplies or acquires goods or services in the Wholesale Local Services Market, 
 

as demonstrated by, inter alia : 
 
 
 c. Telstra's ownership and control of network infrastructure, including the only PSTN with near-Australia wide coverage, which is essential for supplying wholesale Local Services; 
 d. Telstra's high and stable market share;
 e. the high barriers to entry into the Wholesale Local Services Market, including the existence of large sunk costs and economies of scale and scope;
 f. Telstra's strong degree of vertical integration in supplying network, wholesale and retail telecommunications services; and
 g. the lack of countervailing power on behalf of Telstra's Wholesale Customers, other potential wholesale purchasers of Local Services, and Retail Customers. 
 

10. Accordingly, and without prejudice to the Commission's views in respect of any other telecommunications market, Telstra has a substantial degree of power in the Wholesale Local Services Market. 
 

 TAKING ADVANTAGE OF MARKET POWER 
 
11. Telstra has taken and is taking advantage of its market power in the Wholesale Local Services Market by engaging in the conduct described in paragraph 5. 
 EFFECT OR LIKELY EFFECT ON COMPETITION 
 
 12. The conduct described in paragraph 5 had and has the effect or likely effect of substantially lessening, preventing or hindering competition in the Retail FVS Market in one or more of the following respects:
 
a. by raising the costs of Telstra's Rivals, and thereby:
 
 
 
 124 substantially reducing the incentives of Telstra's Rivals to engage in competitive activity to acquire new Retail Customers and to retain existing Retail Customers; and / or 
 125 resulting in higher Retail Prices for Fixed Voice Services than would otherwise be the case in a competitive market; 
 
 

b. by substantially increasing the barriers which prevent or hinder Telstra's Rivals from entering into or expanding within the Retail FVS Market, in at least one or more of the following respects;
 
 
 
 i. adversely affecting the capacity of Telstra's Rivals to generate or to maintain sufficient business to develop and to take advantage of economies of scale and scope; and
 126 reducing the ability of Telstra's Rivals to expand product offerings and to invest in or to deploy new infrastructure and / or alternative technology in order to develop and to supply new and innovative products (particularly in the form of facilities-based competition) which may, in the long run, result in more efficient delivery of services; 
 
 

c. by threatening the viability of at least some of Telstra's Rivals.
 
 
 KINDS OF ANTI-COMPETITIVE CONDUCT 
 
 13. Each of the following kinds of conduct is a kind of anti-competitive conduct described in this notice:
 
 
 a. conduct by Telstra of the kind referred to in paragraph 2;
 b. conduct by Telstra of the kind referred to in paragraph 5, 
 
 
 and
 where that conduct has the effect or likely effect of substantially lessening, preventing or hindering competition in a telecommunications market as referred to in paragraph 12.
 
 
 DURATION 
 
 14. This notice comes into force on 13 April 2006.
 
15. This notice remains in force until 12 April 2007.
 

 


DATED: April 2006
 


 ..................................................
Graeme Samuel
Chairman
Australian Competition and Consumer Commission

 SCHEDULE 1 
 TABLE A: TELSTRA'S RETAIL PRICE FOR HOMELINE PART HomeLine Part monthly line rental price immediately before 1 December 2005 increase HomeLine Part monthly line rental price immediately after 1 December 2005 increase 
$26.95 (including GST) 
$31.95 (including GST) 

 TABLE B: TELSTRA'S KEY RETAIL PRICES FOR FIXED VOICE SERVICES PRODUCTS [1] IMMEDIATELY BEFORE HOME ACCESS INCREASE (including GST) 
 HomeLine Advanced HomeLine Plus HomeLine Complete HomeLine Budget HomeLine Part Monthly Line Rental $35.95 $29.95 $26.95 $18.50 $31.95 [2] Local Calls (per call) 15c 17.5c 20c 30c 22c STD Calls 

Capped STD Calls
STD calls capped between 7pm (4pm Saturdays) and midnight

or

Everyday STD option $2.50 per call 24 hours, 7 days for calls up to 3 hours

or

$1.49 per call 24 hours, 7 days for calls up to 20 minutes 

Not Available






Not Available




$1.49 

$1.50 per call







$2.50





$1.49 

$2.00 per call







Not Available





Not Available 

$3.00 per call







Not Available





Not Available 

Not Available







Not Available





Not Available 

 Mobile Calls [3] 
Fixed to Mobile rate (to non-Telstra mobile)

Fixed to Mobile rate (to Telstra mobile) 

37 cents a minute


33 cents a minute 

37 cents a minute


33 cents a minute 

37 cents a minute



33 cents a minute 

42 cents a minute



37 cents a minute 

42 cents a minute


37 cents a minute International Calls Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country 
 

 TABLE C: TELSTRA'S KEY RETAIL PRICES FOR FIXED VOICE SERVICES PRODUCTS [4] IMMEDIATELY AFTER HOME ACCESS INCREASE 
 HomeLine Advanced HomeLine Plus HomeLine Complete HomeLine Budget HomeLine Part Monthly Line Rental $35.95 $29.95 $26.95 $18.50 $31.95 [5] Local Calls (per call) 15c 17.5c 20c 30c 22c STD Calls 

Capped STD Calls
STD calls capped between 7pm (4pm Saturdays) and midnight

or

Everyday STD option $2.50 per call 24 hours, 7 days for calls up to 3 hours

or

$1.49 per call 24 hours, 7 days for calls up to 20 minutes 

Not Available






Not Available




$1.49 

$1.50 per call







$2.50





$1.49 

$2.00 per call







Not Available





Not Available 

$3.00 per call







Not Available





Not Available 

Not Available







Not Available





Not Available Mobile Calls [6] 
Fixed to Mobile rate (to non-Telstra mobile)

Fixed to Mobile rate (to Telstra mobile) 

37 cents a minute


33 cents a minute 

37 cents a minute


33 cents a minute 

37 cents a minute



33 cents a minute 

42 cents a minute



37 cents a minute 

42 cents a minute


37 cents a minute International Calls Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country Rates vary depending on country 
 

 
 Note: no material changes from the Retail Prices which applied immediately before Home Access increase. 
 

 SCHEDULE 2 

 WHOLESALE PRICE FOR HOME ACCESS LINE RENTAL Monthly charge for a wholesale basic telephone service with Home Access immediately before the Home Access increase Monthly charge for a wholesale basic telephone service with Home Access immediately after the Home Access increase 
$24.50 (excluding GST) 
$27.60 (excluding GST) 



 [1] Products listed in the table represent in excess of 97% of Telstra's Retail Customers. [2] Certain discounts apply to monthly line rental depending on the value of calls the customer makes with Telstra. [3] Other caps and options are available, but the table represents baseline pricing for these products. [4] Products listed in the table represent in excess of 97% of Telstra's Retail Customers. [5] Certain discounts apply to monthly line rental depending on the value of calls the customer makes with Telstra. [6] Other caps and options are available, but the table represents baseline pricing for these products.
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1905.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Telstra Corporation Limited v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (No 2) [2007] FCA 493</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/493.html</AustLII>
<text>1 In Telstra Corporation Limited v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (No 2) [2007] FCA 493 (' Telstra No 2' ), I considered a Part A competition notice ('the Competition Notice') issued by the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission ('the Commission') pursuant to s 151AKA(2) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ('the Act'). Telstra challenged the issue of the Competition Notice and the written notice given by the Commission pursuant to s 151AKA(10) of the Act prior to the issue of the Competition Notice ('the Consultation Notice').

2 In Telstra No 2 I determined that the Consultation Notice and the Competition Notice differed in the kind of anti-competitive conduct described, with those differences being ones of substance (at [263]). Due to these differences, the Consultation Notice did not comply with s 151AKA(10) of the Act and the Commission was not entitled to issue the Competition Notice (at [266]). Telstra was not given the opportunity provided by the Act to respond to a s 151AKA(10) notice and to make submissions to the Commission on the conduct the subject of the Competition Notice prior to its issue. Telstra was, therefore, denied procedural fairness and natural justice under statute and at common law (at [267]).

3 The parties subsequently made submissions on the appropriate orders to give effect to the reasons. I then indicated to the parties that I wished to hear further from them concerning the application of s 5 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) ('the ADJR Act') in the context of the concession made by the Commission that the decision to issue a Part A competition notice was a reviewable decision under s 5.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vanstone v Clark [2005] FCAFC 189 ; (2005) 147 FCR 299</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/189.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Section 46 of the Interpretation Act is applied as a rule of construction to permit the reading down of instruments. It is not a rule of law ( Vanstone v Clark [2005] FCAFC 189 ; (2005) 147 FCR 299 at [16] per Black CJ referring to Pidoto v Victoria [1943] HCA 37 ; (1943) 68 CLR 87 at 110 per Latham CJ). The Commission has not referred to anything in the Act or in any extrinsic legislative materials to support the proposition that s 46 extends beyond such a limited application. Section 46 of the Interpretation Act concerns the construction of instruments. Both ss 46(1)(c) and 46 (2) provide for a construction to be applied. To read and construe an instrument by the application of s 46(1)(c) is not to rewrite it or to ignore its content. Section 46 has no application to a decision made under an Act. It has no application to a denial of procedural fairness.

58 Before embarking on the process of reading down, there must be some part of the impugned provision that is capable of being within power. While s 46(2) of the Interpretation Act may apply to cut down the scope of an overly wide provision, there is no occasion for reading down if the provision is wholly beyond power. As with s 15A, s 46 does not turn an Act or instrument which is invalid as being wholly outside legislative power into an Act which is, in part, within power ( Strickland v Rocla Concrete Pipes Ltd [1971] HCA 40 ; (1971) 124 CLR 468 at 504 per Menzies J and cited by Black CJ in Vanstone at [17]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Victoria v The Commonwealth [1995] HCA 45 ; (1995) 187 CLR 416</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/45.html</AustLII>
<text>56 Section 46 of the Interpretation Act , like s 15A, may apply where ' particular clauses, provisos and qualifications, separately expressed' are beyond power ( Harrington v Lowe [1996] HCA 8 ; (1996) 190 CLR 311 at 327). It does not apply to validate a provision which extends beyond power unless the operation of the remaining parts of the instrument remain unchanged. It does not apply where the instrument was intended to operate fully and completely according to its terms or not at all ( Victoria v The Commonwealth [1995] HCA 45 ; (1995) 187 CLR 416 at 502).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>