<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts (No. 2) [2007] FCA 1445 (12 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1445.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Three Rivers District Council v Governor and Company of the Bank of England (No 6) [2004] UKHL 48 ; [2005] 1 AC 610</tocase>
<text>18 In civil litigation there is a general predisposition towards 'all cards being placed on the table'. The public interest in the due administration of justice requires that all relevant material should be available to be taken into account so that an applicant will succeed if he is entitled to do so and will fail if he is not (see Three Rivers District Council v Governor and Company of the Bank of England (No 6) [2004] UKHL 48 ; [2005] 1 AC 610 ('Three Rivers District Council') at 647).

19 Having said that, it is also in the interests of the whole community that lawyers give their clients sound advice, accurate as to the law and sensible as to their conduct (see Three Rivers District Council at 659). In this regard, a man must be able to consult his lawyer in confidence, since otherwise he might hold back half the truth. The client must be sure that what he tells his lawyer in confidence will never be revealed without his consent. Legal professional privilege is more than an ordinary rule of evidence, limited in its application to the facts of a particular case. It is a fundamental condition on which the administration of justice as a whole rests (per Lord Taylor of Gosforth CJ in his speech in Regina v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487 at 507).

21 If a communication qualifies for legal professional privilege, the privilege is absolute. It cannot be overridden by some supposedly greater public interest. It can be waived by the person, the client entitled to it, and it can be overridden by statute, but it is otherwise absolute. There is no balancing exercise that has to be carried out (per Lord Scott of Foscote in Three Rivers District Council at 646 [25]; see also per McHugh J in Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Limited [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 552).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Regina v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487</tocase>
<text>19 Having said that, it is also in the interests of the whole community that lawyers give their clients sound advice, accurate as to the law and sensible as to their conduct (see Three Rivers District Council at 659). In this regard, a man must be able to consult his lawyer in confidence, since otherwise he might hold back half the truth. The client must be sure that what he tells his lawyer in confidence will never be revealed without his consent. Legal professional privilege is more than an ordinary rule of evidence, limited in its application to the facts of a particular case. It is a fundamental condition on which the administration of justice as a whole rests (per Lord Taylor of Gosforth CJ in his speech in Regina v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487 at 507).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Esso Australia Resources Limited v Commissioner of Taxation of The Commonwealth of Australia [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/67.html</AustLII>
<text>20 The obvious tension between the policy of encouraging full and frank disclosure by clients to their lawyers without the apprehension of being prejudiced by subsequent disclosure of the relevant communication, and the desirability, in the interests of justice, of obtaining the fullest possible access to the facts relevant to the issues in a case lies at the heart of the problem of the scope of client legal professional privilege. Where the privilege applies, it inhibits or prevents access to potentially relevant information (per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ in Esso Australia Resources Limited v Commissioner of Taxation of The Commonwealth of Australia [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49 ('Esso') at [35]).

27 It is for a party claiming privilege to show that the documents for which the claim is made are privileged. He may succeed in achieving this objective by pointing to the nature of the documents or by evidence describing the circumstances in which they were brought into existence, but it should not be thought that the privilege is necessarily or conclusively established by resort to any verbal formula or ritual. The Court has power to examine the documents for itself, a power which has been exercised too sparingly in the past, springing possibly from a misplaced reluctance to go behind the formal claim of privilege. It should not be forgotten that in many instances the character of the documents the subject of the claim will illuminate the purpose for which they were brought into existence (per Stephen, Mason (as his Honour then was) and Murphy JJ in Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674 at 689; see also per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ in Esso at [52]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Limited [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/3.html</AustLII>
<text>21 If a communication qualifies for legal professional privilege, the privilege is absolute. It cannot be overridden by some supposedly greater public interest. It can be waived by the person, the client entitled to it, and it can be overridden by statute, but it is otherwise absolute. There is no balancing exercise that has to be carried out (per Lord Scott of Foscote in Three Rivers District Council at 646 [25]; see also per McHugh J in Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Limited [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 552).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/66.html</AustLII>
<text>22 At common law, what brings about a waiver of privilege is the inconsistency which the courts, where necessary informed by considerations of fairness, perceive, between the conduct of the client and maintenance of the confidentiality (per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, Gummow and Callinan JJ in Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 at [28] and [29]).

23 The above principle was preceded by the following passage in the decision of the High Court in Mann v Carnell at [29], which was cited with approval by the Full Court of this Court in Commissioner of Taxation v Rio Tinto Ltd [2006] FCAFC 86 ; (2006) 151 FCR 341 at [43] . The High Court said:
 
 'Waiver may be express or implied. Disputes as to implied waiver usually arise from the need to decide whether particular conduct is inconsistent with the maintenance of the confidentiality which the privilege is intended to protect.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Rio Tinto Ltd [2006] FCAFC 86 ; (2006) 151 FCR 341</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/86.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The above principle was preceded by the following passage in the decision of the High Court in Mann v Carnell at [29], which was cited with approval by the Full Court of this Court in Commissioner of Taxation v Rio Tinto Ltd [2006] FCAFC 86 ; (2006) 151 FCR 341 at [43] . The High Court said:
 
 'Waiver may be express or implied. Disputes as to implied waiver usually arise from the need to decide whether particular conduct is inconsistent with the maintenance of the confidentiality which the privilege is intended to protect.'

47 As I have said, it is unnecessary for me to reach any concluded view in relation to this aspect of the matter. It is not inappropriate, however, to refer to the observations of Gleeson CJ, then sitting as the Chief Justice of New South Wales, in Benecke v National Australia Bank (1993) 35 NSWLR 110 at 111; see also Commissioner of Taxation v Rio Tinto Ltd at [49] and [61].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211</tocase>
<text>26 Now that the test for legal professional privilege is 'dominant purpose' rather than 'sole purpose', there may well be many more cases where, upon the hearing of a disputed claim, there will be occasion for a deponent who has verified a list of documents claiming privilege to be cross-examined. Indeed, it would seem, from a procedural point of view, that if production of a document for which privilege has been claimed is sought, it would be incumbent upon the party claiming the privilege to at least read the affidavit verifying the list and thereby expose the deponent to cross-examination (see National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211; Hartogen Energy Limited (In liquidation) v The Australian Gas Light Company (1992) 36 FCR 557 at 561 and Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 447 at 462).

29 In Barnes their Honours made a series of observations in relation to the sufficiency of the evidence before the trial judge to establish the legal professional privilege claim which was made in that case. Referring to an affidavit claiming privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 '16. This affidavit falls far short of providing any adequate basis for claiming privilege in respect of any individual document. It consists of assertions, conclusions and generalised comments. The documents referred to are from a number of sources. ... the fact that Mr Barnes' affidavit does not clarify the reason why any specific document came into existence means that the Court is left to consider the documents on their face and determine as best it can whether the documents are privileged. This is unsatisfactory. 
 ... 
 


 
 
 18. The authorities emphasise the need for focused and specific evidence in order to ground a claim for legal professional privilege. In Kennedy v Wallis [2004] FCAFC 337 ; (2004) 142 FCR 185 at 189, Black CJ and Emmett J reiterated the principles that verbal formulae and bare conclusory assertions of purpose are not sufficient to make out a claim for privilege: see also National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211 (per Lockhart J); Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674 at 689 (per Stephen, Mason and Murphy JJ). Where possible the Court should be assisted by evidence of the thought processes behind, or the nature and purpose of advice being sought in respect of, each particular document. ... Simply to show that one purpose for creation of the document was to obtain legal advice or assistance is not good enough.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hartogen Energy Limited (In liquidation) v The Australian Gas Light Company (1992) 36 FCR 557</tocase>
<text>26 Now that the test for legal professional privilege is 'dominant purpose' rather than 'sole purpose', there may well be many more cases where, upon the hearing of a disputed claim, there will be occasion for a deponent who has verified a list of documents claiming privilege to be cross-examined. Indeed, it would seem, from a procedural point of view, that if production of a document for which privilege has been claimed is sought, it would be incumbent upon the party claiming the privilege to at least read the affidavit verifying the list and thereby expose the deponent to cross-examination (see National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211; Hartogen Energy Limited (In liquidation) v The Australian Gas Light Company (1992) 36 FCR 557 at 561 and Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 447 at 462).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 447</tocase>
<text>26 Now that the test for legal professional privilege is 'dominant purpose' rather than 'sole purpose', there may well be many more cases where, upon the hearing of a disputed claim, there will be occasion for a deponent who has verified a list of documents claiming privilege to be cross-examined. Indeed, it would seem, from a procedural point of view, that if production of a document for which privilege has been claimed is sought, it would be incumbent upon the party claiming the privilege to at least read the affidavit verifying the list and thereby expose the deponent to cross-examination (see National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211; Hartogen Energy Limited (In liquidation) v The Australian Gas Light Company (1992) 36 FCR 557 at 561 and Re Compass Airlines Pty Ltd (1992) 35 FCR 447 at 462).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/63.html</AustLII>
<text>27 It is for a party claiming privilege to show that the documents for which the claim is made are privileged. He may succeed in achieving this objective by pointing to the nature of the documents or by evidence describing the circumstances in which they were brought into existence, but it should not be thought that the privilege is necessarily or conclusively established by resort to any verbal formula or ritual. The Court has power to examine the documents for itself, a power which has been exercised too sparingly in the past, springing possibly from a misplaced reluctance to go behind the formal claim of privilege. It should not be forgotten that in many instances the character of the documents the subject of the claim will illuminate the purpose for which they were brought into existence (per Stephen, Mason (as his Honour then was) and Murphy JJ in Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674 at 689; see also per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ in Esso at [52]).

29 In Barnes their Honours made a series of observations in relation to the sufficiency of the evidence before the trial judge to establish the legal professional privilege claim which was made in that case. Referring to an affidavit claiming privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 '16. This affidavit falls far short of providing any adequate basis for claiming privilege in respect of any individual document. It consists of assertions, conclusions and generalised comments. The documents referred to are from a number of sources. ... the fact that Mr Barnes' affidavit does not clarify the reason why any specific document came into existence means that the Court is left to consider the documents on their face and determine as best it can whether the documents are privileged. This is unsatisfactory. 
 ... 
 


 
 
 18. The authorities emphasise the need for focused and specific evidence in order to ground a claim for legal professional privilege. In Kennedy v Wallis [2004] FCAFC 337 ; (2004) 142 FCR 185 at 189, Black CJ and Emmett J reiterated the principles that verbal formulae and bare conclusory assertions of purpose are not sufficient to make out a claim for privilege: see also National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211 (per Lockhart J); Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674 at 689 (per Stephen, Mason and Murphy JJ). Where possible the Court should be assisted by evidence of the thought processes behind, or the nature and purpose of advice being sought in respect of, each particular document. ... Simply to show that one purpose for creation of the document was to obtain legal advice or assistance is not good enough.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Barnes v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCAFC 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/88.html</AustLII>
<text>28 The relevant time at which a claim for privilege is to be determined is the time when the document came into existence. The relevant question is whether the document came into existence for the dominant purpose of seeking legal advice or assistance. If the document satisfies that description, then it is privileged from production (per Tamberlin, Stone and Siopis JJ in Barnes v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCAFC 88 ('Barnes') at [5]).

29 In Barnes their Honours made a series of observations in relation to the sufficiency of the evidence before the trial judge to establish the legal professional privilege claim which was made in that case. Referring to an affidavit claiming privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 '16. This affidavit falls far short of providing any adequate basis for claiming privilege in respect of any individual document. It consists of assertions, conclusions and generalised comments. The documents referred to are from a number of sources. ... the fact that Mr Barnes' affidavit does not clarify the reason why any specific document came into existence means that the Court is left to consider the documents on their face and determine as best it can whether the documents are privileged. This is unsatisfactory. 
 ... 
 


 
 
 18. The authorities emphasise the need for focused and specific evidence in order to ground a claim for legal professional privilege. In Kennedy v Wallis [2004] FCAFC 337 ; (2004) 142 FCR 185 at 189, Black CJ and Emmett J reiterated the principles that verbal formulae and bare conclusory assertions of purpose are not sufficient to make out a claim for privilege: see also National Crime Authority v S (1991) 29 FCR 203 at 211 (per Lockhart J); Grant v Downs [1976] HCA 63 ; (1976) 135 CLR 674 at 689 (per Stephen, Mason and Murphy JJ). Where possible the Court should be assisted by evidence of the thought processes behind, or the nature and purpose of advice being sought in respect of, each particular document. ... Simply to show that one purpose for creation of the document was to obtain legal advice or assistance is not good enough.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/142.html</AustLII>
<text>30 In Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142 at [4] Tamberlin J said in respect of legal professional privilege:
 
 
 '4. The dominant purpose test has particular importance in relation to the position of in-house counsel because they may be in a closer relationship to the management than outside counsel and therefore more exposed to participation in commercial aspects of an enterprise. The courts recognise that being a lawyer employed by an enterprise does not of itself entail a level of independence. Each employment will depend on the way in which the position is structured and executed. For example, some enterprises may treat the in-house adviser as concerned solely in advising and dealing with legal problems. As a matter of commercial reality, however, both internal and external legal advisers will often be involved in expressing views and acting on commercial issues. 
 
 5. The authorities recognise that in order to attract privilege the legal adviser should have an appropriate degree of independence so as to ensure that the protection of legal professional privilege is not conferred too widely. ...' 
 


 
(See also Waterford v The Commonwealth of Australia [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 ('Waterford') at 62, 70-71 and 81-82).

31 In respect of the application before his Honour, Tamberlin J said at [38]:
 
 '... I am cognisant of the fact that there is no bright line separating the role of an employed legal counsel as a lawyer advising in-house and his participation in commercial decisions. In other words, it is often practically impossible to segregate commercial activities from purely "legal" functions. The two will often be intertwined and privilege should not be denied simply on the basis of some commercial involvement. ...'

32 In that case, his Honour proceeded to say in respect of Mr Philip, the chief general counsel for News Limited, at [38]:
 
 '... In the present case, however, I am persuaded that Mr Philip was actively engaged in the commercial decisions to such an extent that significant weight must be given to this participation. In many circumstances where in-house counsel are employed there will be considerable overlap between commercial participation and legal functions and opinions. As can be seen from the specific rulings below, I am not persuaded that in this proceeding Mr Philip was acting in a legal context or role in relation to a number of the documents in respect of which privilege was claimed. Nor am I persuaded that the privilege claims were based on an independent and impartial legal appraisal.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Waterford v The Commonwealth of Australia [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/25.html</AustLII>
<text>30 In Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142 at [4] Tamberlin J said in respect of legal professional privilege:
 
 
 '4. The dominant purpose test has particular importance in relation to the position of in-house counsel because they may be in a closer relationship to the management than outside counsel and therefore more exposed to participation in commercial aspects of an enterprise. The courts recognise that being a lawyer employed by an enterprise does not of itself entail a level of independence. Each employment will depend on the way in which the position is structured and executed. For example, some enterprises may treat the in-house adviser as concerned solely in advising and dealing with legal problems. As a matter of commercial reality, however, both internal and external legal advisers will often be involved in expressing views and acting on commercial issues. 
 
 5. The authorities recognise that in order to attract privilege the legal adviser should have an appropriate degree of independence so as to ensure that the protection of legal professional privilege is not conferred too widely. ...' 
 


 
(See also Waterford v The Commonwealth of Australia [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 ('Waterford') at 62, 70-71 and 81-82).

33 In Waterford the court accepted that in some circumstances legal advice may be accompanied by advice of another kind which can be separated from it. In such circumstances, only the legal advice will be privileged. However, if the legal advice contains extraneous matter which cannot be separated from it, the legal advice will not lose its privilege for that reason (per Mason (as his Honour then was) and Wilson JJ at 66 and per Dawson J at 103).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>DSE (Holdings) Pty Ltd v InterTAN Inc [2003] FCA 1191 ; (2003) 135 FCR 151</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/1191.html</AustLII>
<text>34 Legal professional privilege is not limited to express advice about the law. Too literal a requirement of identifying legal advice as express advice about the law would place undue emphasis on formalism and undermine the privilege (per Allsop J in DSE (Holdings) Pty Ltd v InterTAN Inc [2003] FCA 1191 ; (2003) 135 FCR 151 at [52] .

35 In my opinion an in-house lawyer will lack the requisite measure of independence if his or her advice is at risk of being compromised by virtue of the nature of his employment relationship with his employer. On the other hand, if the personal loyalties, duties and interests of the in-house lawyer do not influence the professional legal advice which he gives, the requirement for independence will be satisfied.

36 In the case presently before the Court, there is no evidence, as I have earlier remarked, going to the independence of the internal legal advisers involved in the communications said to have been brought into existence for the dominant purpose of providing or receiving legal advice. There is nothing to indicate from the description of the six documents with which the Court is presently concerned that they must be documents for which privilege is properly claimed. Different considerations may apply if, say, the documents in question were opinions expressed by identified senior counsel where one might start off with the premise that by its nature the document would have privilege attaching to it. This is not such a case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Alphapharm Pty Limited v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Limited [1996] FCA 391</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1996/391.html</AustLII>
<text>43 In Alphapharm Pty Limited v Eli Lilly Australia Pty Limited [1996] FCA 391 ('Alphapharm'), Lindgren J made certain observations at [41] concerning Order 15A rule 6. These included:

 
 
 '1. Paragraphs 6 (a) and 6 (c) pose an objective test, the opening words "there is" in each paragraph signifying "there exists"; but the "insufficiency test" of para 6 (b) has both subjective and objective aspects. 
 
 
 
 
 
 2. Although I need not explore the subjective aspect fully, it seems clear that if the evidence went so far as to show that a particular applicant was already able to decide to commence a proceeding by, for example, showing that the applicant had in fact decided to do so, para 6 (b) would not be satisfied even though the information available satisfied the objective aspect of the insufficiency test referred to below. 
 
 
 
 
 
 3. The fact that a particular applicant genuinely feels unable, because of a lack of information, to decide to commence a proceeding does not, without more, satisfy para 6 (b); the objective aspect of the paragraph requires it to be shown as an objective fact that the applicant lacks "sufficient information to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding". 
 
 
 
 
 
 4. In my view, the objective aspect of para 6 (b) invokes a notion of "reasonable sufficiency", the question raised being whether it is reasonable that the applicant for an order be required to take its decision without having the information to become available from inspection of the document or documents of which discovery is sought.' 
 


 
Much the same was said in respect of paragraph (b) of rule 6 by Emmett J in Leighton Contractors Pty Limited v Page Kirkland Management Pty Limited [2006] FCA 288 at [6] .

44 In his reasons for judgment at [46] in Alphapharm , Lindgren J said:
 
 '... I do not imply that an applicant for an order under the rule must lead evidence that without the documents sought, it will not sue. The rule is, however, directed to aiding an applicant who is having real difficulty, and reasonably so, in deciding whether to litigate because of a lack of key information, whether relating to its own case or to that of the proposed respondent, which is in the possession of the respondent. ...'

45 It would seem to me unjust to allow relief to be granted against a stranger, albeit a prospective respondent, under Order 15A rule 6 if the applicant failed to place before the Court the information which it did have, to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding in the Court to obtain the relevant relief. One of the issues will be, whether viewed objectively or subjectively, the applicant had sufficient information.

46 If information going to the ability of a person in the position of Telstra to make a decision whether to commence a proceeding in the Court against the Minister as a prospective respondent included information contained in documents which may otherwise enjoy legal professional privilege, it would seem surprising if the applicant could advance its claim for relief under Order 15A rule 6 without laying bare all of the information which it had, whether privileged or not.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Benecke v National Australia Bank (1993) 35 NSWLR 110</tocase>
<text>47 As I have said, it is unnecessary for me to reach any concluded view in relation to this aspect of the matter. It is not inappropriate, however, to refer to the observations of Gleeson CJ, then sitting as the Chief Justice of New South Wales, in Benecke v National Australia Bank (1993) 35 NSWLR 110 at 111; see also Commissioner of Taxation v Rio Tinto Ltd at [49] and [61].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>