<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cosdean Investments Pty Ltd v Football Federation Australia Limited (No 5) [2007] FCA 1792 (23 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1792.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Munn v Queensland [2001] FCA 1229 ; (2001) 115 FCR 109</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1229.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>RD Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1988) 18 FCR 389</tocase>
<text>17 
 
There is no doubt that, the "sunset" order made on 17 May 2007 not yet having led to the proceeding being dismissed, the Court has power under O 35 r 7(2) or under O 28 r 5 to set aside that order: see RD Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1988) 18 FCR 389 or to extend the time to appeal from the further orders for security for costs made on 14 February 2007. Although generally the power to set aside a judgment or order should be sparingly exercised (see Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543 at 550-552), I think the power is more readily exercised in the case of an interlocutory order where the public interest in the finality of litigation does not weigh so heavily in the scales.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543</tocase>
<text>17 
 
There is no doubt that, the "sunset" order made on 17 May 2007 not yet having led to the proceeding being dismissed, the Court has power under O 35 r 7(2) or under O 28 r 5 to set aside that order: see RD Werner &amp; Co Inc v Bailey Aluminium Products Pty Ltd (1988) 18 FCR 389 or to extend the time to appeal from the further orders for security for costs made on 14 February 2007. Although generally the power to set aside a judgment or order should be sparingly exercised (see Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543 at 550-552), I think the power is more readily exercised in the case of an interlocutory order where the public interest in the finality of litigation does not weigh so heavily in the scales.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/28.html</AustLII>
<text>18 However, this is not a case where the applicant can assert that it has not had a proper opportunity either to address the applications for further security for costs or, those orders having been made, to address the applications that the proceeding be dismissed for it having failed to pay the further security for costs ordered. That it did not participate in the hearing on 17 May 2007 was a matter for it. Even in respect of that hearing, it does not profess inadvertence or ignorance (although Ms Watson herself may not have known of that hearing): see e.g. Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71; Wentworth v Woollahra Municipal Council [1982] HCA 41 ; (1982) 149 CLR 672 at 684.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wentworth v Woollahra Municipal Council [1982] HCA 41 ; (1982) 149 CLR 672</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/41.html</AustLII>
<text>18 However, this is not a case where the applicant can assert that it has not had a proper opportunity either to address the applications for further security for costs or, those orders having been made, to address the applications that the proceeding be dismissed for it having failed to pay the further security for costs ordered. That it did not participate in the hearing on 17 May 2007 was a matter for it. Even in respect of that hearing, it does not profess inadvertence or ignorance (although Ms Watson herself may not have known of that hearing): see e.g. Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71; Wentworth v Woollahra Municipal Council [1982] HCA 41 ; (1982) 149 CLR 672 at 684.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Council of the City of Greater Wollongong v Cowan [1955] HCA 16 ; (1955) 93 CLR 435</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1955/16.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Accordingly, subject to considering the applicant's second and third contentions, I am not persuaded that it should be granted a further extension of time within which to appeal from the further security for costs orders made on 14 February 2007. In brief, it has not explained the delay satisfactorily at all. It has not demonstrated any relevant significant change in circumstances, even if the Deumer Asia letter of 15 July 2007 were to be permitted to be adduced in evidence on the appeal (as to which see e.g. Council of the City of Greater Wollongong v Cowan [1955] HCA 16 ; (1955) 93 CLR 435 at 444). It has not explained, in any event, why that letter could not have been procured much earlier. It has not sought to have the security for costs orders discharged. It is clearly, and admittedly, unable to pay the further security for costs orders and will be unable to meet any costs of the respondents if the matter proceeds to hearing and the applicant is unsuccessful.

28 Nor has any reason been identified of any substance as to why the orders of 14 February 2007 for further security for costs might be set aside on appeal. There is no draft notice of appeal, nor anything identifying error.

29 The second matter argued by the applicant relates to matters taken into account when the further security for costs orders were made. It is not a new argument. It is discussed in Cosdean (No 2) [2007] FCA 163 at [12] [14].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>House v The King [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/40.html</AustLII>
<text>33 In my view, the second and third matters raised by the applicant may be seen as errors asserted by the applicant in the making of the further security for costs orders on 14 February 2007. Otherwise, they are simply an attempt to re-argue matters which have already been argued. I shall also therefore consider whether those matters might demonstrate some arguable prospect of success if an extension of time to appeal from those orders were granted. I do not think these matters demonstrate a relevant mistake of fact in considering the potential award of damages, in considering the capacity of the applicant to fund the second tranche of key rings as discussed in Cosdean (No 2) [2007] FCA 163at [12] [14]. Nor do I think that they otherwise provide an arguable basis for error from the discretionary judgment to impose the further security for costs orders upon the applicant: See House v The King [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499 at 504 505.

34 For those reasons, I do not consider that the applicant should be granted a further extension of time within which to appeal from the further security for costs orders made on 14 February 2007, or from the order presently staying the proceeding until the further security for costs was paid, made on 19 February 2007.

35 I am further of the view, having regard to the conclusion I have reached that there should be no extension of time within which to appeal from the further security for costs orders, and having regard to the accepted inability of the applicant to comply with those orders by providing further security for costs, that the orders made on 17 May 2007 should not be discharged. The applicant is faced with further orders for security for costs. It cannot satisfy them. It acknowledges that. The proceedings have been permanently stayed. In those circumstances, nothing has been shown to indicate that the orders dismissing the proceedings against each of the respondents were inappropriate in the first place, or should now be discharged.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>