<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Weti v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1531 (5 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1531.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>House v The King [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/40.html</AustLII>
<text>29 In the present case, the application for adjournment was not refused but was limited to one day to 28 November 2006 rather than ten days to 8 December 2006 which was the preferred term of adjournment of the Deputy President. Whether or not an adjournment is granted and the terms of that adjournment are matters entirely within the discretion of the Tribunal. As was said in House v The King [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499 at 504 505:
 
 "The manner in which an appeal against an exercise of discretion should be determined is governed by established principles. It is not enough that the judges composing the appellate court consider that, if they had been in the position of the primary judge, they would have taken a different course. It must appear that some error has been made in exercising the discretion. If the judge acts upon a wrong principle, if he allows extraneous or irrelevant matters to guide or affect him, if he mistakes the facts, if he does not take into account some material consideration, then his determination should be reviewed and the appellate court may exercise its own discretion in substitution for his if it has the materials for doing so."

30 The considerations which led or compelled the Deputy President to so limit the term of adjournment have already been canvassed at some length, and it was not submitted on behalf of the applicant that the exercise of the discretion miscarried because such considerations, or any one or more of them, were not relevant. But the applicant submitted that the Deputy President failed to take into account two relevant considerations, namely:
 
 (1) The possibility of having the matter heard by another member of the Tribunal; and
 (2) the possibility of the matter being heard in the period 1 7 December 2006. 

I have already indicated at [26] above why I do not think these were real possibilities and that may well explain why the Deputy President made no specific reference to them. In the scheme of things, I do not think the lack of any specific reference to them indicates that they were not taken into account; rather they were overtaken by the fact that the Deputy President only had one possible free day between 27 November 2006 and 20 December 2006 (apart from 28 November 2006) and that was 8 December 2006 and the fact that there were no hearing rooms available up until 20 December 2006 even if another member of the Tribunal was available to hear the matter at a date later than 28 November 2006.

31 While there was no express challenge to the Tribunal's exercise of its discretion in limiting the terms of the adjournment to one day in the form of a ground of review, a considerable amount of time was spent in argument on the Tribunal's alleged failure to take these two matters into account. If there was such a ground of review, I would not be prepared to conclude that the Tribunal's exercise of discretion miscarried by reason of such matters.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kuswardana v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs (1981) 35 ALR 186 </tocase>
<text>44 The fact that this alleged failure had not been raised in the Tribunal was no bar to its qualification as an error of law on the part of the Tribunal according to counsel for the applicant. In this regard I was referred to what was said by Bowen CJ in Kuswardana v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs (1981) 35 ALR 186 at 194; see too Fox J at 199; although Deane J at 205 was troubled as to whether the appellant's failure in that case to raise the issue in the Tribunal precludes the intervention of the court on appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>45 Counsel for the Minister accepted that failure to consider a relevant consideration is, as Mason J explained in Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24 at 39, "one instance of an abuse of discretion entitling a party with sufficient standing to seek judicial review of ultra vires administrative action"; but noted that failure by a decision-maker to take into account relevant considerations is only an error where the statute makes the considerations ones which the decision-maker is " bound to take into account in making that decision".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Sales v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1807 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1807.html</AustLII>
<text>42 The applicant's case on this ground relied almost if not entirely on the decision of Allsop J in Sales v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1807 where his Honour held that in the facts and circumstances of that case, the 14 day response period specified in a letter to Mr Sales, informing him that he was liable to the possibility of visa cancellation and deportation, was "plainly inadequate for him to address the task before him" (at [32]) and "was not procedural fairness" (at 36]).

43 Counsel for the applicant submitted that although Sales involved a decision made by the Minister personally, the circumstances of this case include all of the above criteria. Furthermore, like the applicant in Sales , neither the applicant nor her mother could be described as "people of wide or deep resources, or otherwise of significant education" (at [23]). In Sales , Allsop J described Direction 21 as "a comprehensive and careful document" and that the "task to prepare material for a consideration of such matters, objectively understood, is wide-reaching and significant" (at [14]). I was referred to the remarks of Allsop J at [31] to [34] with the submission that they are all applicable to the applicant with the exception that she has not spent "most" of her adult life in prison, however, she has certainly spent a significant part of her adult life in prison.

46 Counsel for the applicant further submitted that the ground of review should be rejected for the following reasons:
 
 (1) As neither the Act , nor Direction No. 21, either expressly, or by implication, mandate the consideration of this factor, the failure to take it into account cannot be an error.
 (2) Any procedural failings by the delegate of the Minister in reaching the original decision could not be relevant in any sense as the Tribunal was making the decision afresh and so any such unfairness was able to be remedied.
 (3) It is not apparent that there was any relevant unfairness by the delegate. Unlike the case in Sales , this was the second time the applicant had to explain why her visa should not be cancelled, the applicant did not complain that she was unable to respond effectively and she took the opportunity to make submissions, similar in substance, to those later made by her solicitor.

47 In the facts and circumstances of this case, I do not think the 14 day response period in the NOICC denied the applicant procedural fairness. While there are some factual similarities between this case and Sales , they are more apparent than real. Importantly, this was the second time within approximately 18 months that the applicant was called upon to respond to such a notice and her responses in that case resulted in a warning. It was made clear in the NOICC that in making a decision whether to cancel the applicant's visa under s 501(2) of the Act , the Minister or delegate would take into account, amongst other things, the information the applicant supplied on the earlier occasion.

48 This ground of review cannot be sustained.

49 This is undoubtedly a factor to which the Tribunal should have had regard in terms of Direction No. 21 see [2.17(a)] thereof. The applicant submitted that the Tribunal failed to give proper consideration to the length of time the applicant, a New Zealand citizen, had lived in Australia continuously; there is little discussion in the Tribunal's decision concerning the length of time the applicant has resided in Australia and the extent of her ties to her family and the disruptive effects of her visa cancellation.

51 It was further submitted that the Tribunal failed to consider the effects of the visa cancellation on the applicant's ties to her siblings her half brother and her half sisters. I was referred to Sales in which Allsop J suggested that the "bests interests of children", dealt with at [2.13] of the Direction, could also include children who are not direct issue of the person concerned such as the "extended family of the applicant, including nephews and nieces" (at [20]). Finally, the applicant submitted that although the Tribunal asserted that there was no evidence "about the Applicant's relationship with other members of her family or members of the community" (at [38]), there was little inquiry made by the Tribunal into the nature of those relationships when the applicant gave evidence notwithstanding that the applicant was unrepresented.

52 However, it is apparent that the Tribunal did give this factor consideration. At [38] it said:
 
 "Disruption would result to the Applicant's family. Her parents reside in Sydney. She maintains that she has a good bonding now with each of them although it is noted neither attended the Hearing. The mother affirmed her 2005 statement. The father did not provide any information to the Tribunal. There was not any evidence about the Applicant's relationship with other members of her family or members of the community."

53 I also reject the inference, implicit in the submissions that there was little inquiry made by the Tribunal into the nature of those relationships when the applicant gave evidence, that the Tribunal was in some way under a duty to make inquiry because the applicant was unrepresented.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Sullivan v Department of Transport (1978) 20 ALR 323</tocase>
<text>24 I was referred to what was said by Deane J in Sullivan v Department of Transport (1978) 20 ALR 323 at 342, namely:
 
 " Section 39 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act provides, for present purposes, that 'the Tribunal shall ensure that every party to a proceeding before the Tribunal is given a reasonable opportunity to present his case'. In dealing with an application for review, the Tribunal is plainly under a duty to act judicially, that is to say, with judicial fairness and detachment. In these circumstances, the requirement contained in s 39 that the Tribunal shall ensure that a party to the proceedings before it be given a reasonable opportunity to present his case constitutes statutory recognition of an obligation which the law would, in any event, imply. Where a Tribunal is under a duty to act judicially, the principle that a party must be given a reasonable opportunity to present his case is at the heart of the requirements of natural justice which it is obliged to observe (see R v Moodie (1977) 17 ALR 219 at 225)."

25 A little later (at 343) his Honour said:
 
 "A refusal to grant an adjournment can constitute a failure to give a party to proceedings the opportunity of adequately presenting his case. ... The absence of any application for an adjournment does not, however, necessarily conclude the issue adversely to the appellant. The failure of a tribunal which is under a duty to act judicially to adjourn a matter may, conceivably, constitute a failure to allow a party the opportunity of properly presenting his case even though the party in question has not expressly sought an adjournment."

26 When pressed as to what the Deputy President should have done in the circumstances but did not do, counsel for the applicant submitted:
 
 (1) "First and foremost he should have canvassed the possibility of having the matter heard by another member of the Tribunal." 

As I have indicated at [20(6)] above, presumably the Deputy President did not undertake any such canvassing because he was aware that no hearing rooms were available on any day up until 20 December 2006.
 
 (2) "[H]e should have canvassed the dates, between 1 December of that year ..." and 7 December as to whether the matter could be heard by himself or another member of the Tribunal.
 

As I have indicated in [20(4)] above, my reading of the relevant excerpt from the transcript indicates that the Deputy President did not have any days available from that moment until 20 December 2006, other than the next day (28 November 2006) and possibly 8 December 2006. That last-mentioned date was not a choice because of lack of availability of a hearing room, and the possibility of the matter being heard by another member of the Tribunal in the 1 to 7 December 2006 period was out for the same reasons.

27 Finally, the applicant submitted that the subsequent conduct of the hearing, together with the Deputy President's initial instinct to accede to the request to adjourn the matter, only serves to emphasize the merits of the adjournment application the reason the Deputy President chose not to do so being apparently based entirely on pragmatic considerations regarding room availability.

28 While it is clear that a refusal to grant an adjournment can constitute a failure to give a party to proceedings the opportunity of adequately presenting his case see Deane J in Sullivan at 343 whether it does or not depends on what underlies the request for an adjournment. For example, and this is close to the example cited by Deane J in Sullivan , if a party makes application for an adjournment to enable him to procure a particular person as a witness, refusal of that application may well constitute such a failure. The refusal of an application for an adjournment predicated on a lack of legal representation and a need for time to secure such representation, as in the present case, may also constitute such a failure, but then again it may not. It will depend on the facts and circumstances of the case, in particular how the lack of legal representation impacted (adversely) on the ability of the applicant to present his/her case.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>