<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZKOP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1650 (1 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1650.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>SZKOP v Minister for Immigration [2007] FMCA 1336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/1336.html</AustLII>
<text>1 This is an application for leave to appeal from a decision of Smith FM ( SZKOP v Minister for Immigration [2007] FMCA 1336) dismissing an application for judicial review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal (the Tribunal) handed down on 27 March 2007, which affirmed the decision of the delegate of the Minister not to grant the applicant/appellant a protection visa. The matter was dismissed pursuant to r 44.12(1)(a) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules, on the basis that the applicant/appellant had not raised an arguable case for the relief claimed.

2 The application to this Court raises two issues, each of which was dealt with by the learned Federal Magistrate. One can be put aside immediately, that is, the reference to the consequences of the one child policy. The claim that is made is that the review was unfair as the applicant/appellant was refused an opportunity to provide further details about his breach of the one child policy. He says that he did provide evidence that his family breached the one child policy and had been heavily fined, but he says the Tribunal refused to hear more from him. The Tribunal said on this topic:
 
 
 "At the hearing the Applicant made passing reference to having breached the one child policy and having been fined for this reason. He did not identify this as a reason for fearing future harm in China when asked at the start of the hearing why he feared to return. Given the brevity and lack of detail volunteered by him on this issue I am not satisfied that he was, in fact, fined for breaching the policy."

3 It does not follow, of course, that being fined for breach of a general law of the country is serious harm or gives rise to a well-founded fear of persecution as required but, in short, there is no evidence that the Tribunal refused to hear more from him. It is the applicant/appellant's obligation to produce all the material which is relevant to his case. If there was a case being made of literally being stopped from doing something, that would have required the adducing of evidence before the Federal Magistrate. There was no such evidence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>