<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZJZW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1197 (9 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1197.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437</tocase>
<text>9 The Tribunal then rejected the appellant's claim because it concluded that he is reasonably capable of relocating to other parts of India if he faces persecution from Muslim fundamentalists in his city of Ahmedabad. After referring to the relocation principle discussed in Randhawa v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs (1994) 52 FCR 437, the Tribunal observed that it did not see any impediment to the appellant's relocation to other parts of India. It explained why. It did not think that the appellant had given the Tribunal any persuasive reason why he should feel uncomfortable in setting up his business in other parts of India. It noted that there was no rational basis for the appellant's claimed belief that he and his wife would not be entitled to the same protection as other business people in other major cities in India. Even if he could not afford to set up business in another city, it noted that the appellant is currently employed in Australia as a farm hand, and is also skilled as a medicine salesman and a diamond polisher. It therefore concluded that he is easily capable of taking up other types of work without the necessity of establishing his own business. It rejected his claim that he had unsuccessfully attempted to relocate in the past because he had been unable to tell the Tribunal where he had tried to relocate. It concluded that he is reasonably capable of relocating in India, and so did not have a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason if he were to return to India, even if he may have been the subject of further attacks in his city of Ahmedabad.

10 The appellants sought to have the Tribunal decision quashed by a Federal Magistrate. That application was refused by a decision of a Federal Magistrate of 3 May 2007. The Federal Magistrate found no jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal in the way it had considered the appellant's claims, including the assertion (which was the only specific assertion in the grounds of the application before the Federal Magistrate) that the Tribunal had failed to comply with s 424A of the Act by having failed to give to the appellant a notice under that section addressing the matters to which the Tribunal may have had regard in deciding whether it was reasonable for him to relocate to some other part of India. The Federal Magistrate said that the matters to which the Tribunal had regard in reaching that conclusion was information given by the appellant to the Tribunal during the course of the hearing.

11 This is an appeal from the decision of the Federal Magistrate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>NAJT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 ; (2005) 147 FCR 51</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/134.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The first step in considering the appellant's contention that his case was that he had a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason throughout India, because he would be a target for Muslim fundamentalists wherever he was located in India, is to decide whether the appellant should be entitled to raise that matter on this appeal. It was not raised as a ground of appeal before the Federal Magistrate, nor in the grounds of appeal before this Court. Leave to amend a notice of appeal to raise a new ground should only be granted where it is expedient in the interests of justice for that leave to be granted: NAJT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 ; (2005) 147 FCR 51 at [163] [166]; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168 at 177; NBKT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 195 ; (2006) 156 FCR 419 at [22] .

19 In NAJT 147 FCR at [166] Madgwick J identified relevant questions on the topic as including whether the new legal argument has a reasonable prospect of success; whether there is an acceptable explanation of why it was not raised before the Federal Magistrate; whether permitting the new ground to be raised would interfere with the efficient use of judicial sitting time; the consequences to the appellant of not permitting the new ground to be raised and to the first respondent in permitting the proposed new ground of appeal to be raised and, if so, how it could be cured; and where the interests of justice lie in all the circumstances.

20 The appellant's application for a protection visa asserts in very general terms that he fears being killed by criminal Muslim fundamentalists in India if he were to return there, and refers specifically to a letter of 16 June 2006 in which he expands upon that information. That letter records the complaints of particular adverse experiences to which the Tribunal has referred in the Gujarat state. It is specific to that state. It says, however, by way of conclusion that:
 
 We have nowhere to go. If we go back to India, We can be killed by Muslims or maybe even by power hungry Hindu fundamentalists. Indian police can never protect us.
 

I note however that in that letter, the appellant said that the incident which occurred on 31 March 2006 when he was beaten by persons he assumed were Muslim fundamentalists, he was warned to leave Gujarat, rather than that he would be attacked elsewhere in India.

21 In a letter to the Tribunal of 20 November 2006, again in my view the claim is somewhat ambiguous. It is focused upon events in and around Ahmedabad. It says:
 
 There was no any [sic] improvement in the law order situation. We were living in a fearful situation. Hiding here and there and begging safety of life from the local police. The local police did not give any solid or effective protection. Because of that we left our country to have a peaceful life.
 

It proceeds to refer to reports about the negligence and corruption of Gujarat police.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/74.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The first step in considering the appellant's contention that his case was that he had a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason throughout India, because he would be a target for Muslim fundamentalists wherever he was located in India, is to decide whether the appellant should be entitled to raise that matter on this appeal. It was not raised as a ground of appeal before the Federal Magistrate, nor in the grounds of appeal before this Court. Leave to amend a notice of appeal to raise a new ground should only be granted where it is expedient in the interests of justice for that leave to be granted: NAJT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 ; (2005) 147 FCR 51 at [163] [166]; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168 at 177; NBKT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 195 ; (2006) 156 FCR 419 at [22] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NBKT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 195 ; (2006) 156 FCR 419</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/195.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The first step in considering the appellant's contention that his case was that he had a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason throughout India, because he would be a target for Muslim fundamentalists wherever he was located in India, is to decide whether the appellant should be entitled to raise that matter on this appeal. It was not raised as a ground of appeal before the Federal Magistrate, nor in the grounds of appeal before this Court. Leave to amend a notice of appeal to raise a new ground should only be granted where it is expedient in the interests of justice for that leave to be granted: NAJT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 134 ; (2005) 147 FCR 51 at [163] [166]; VAAC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 74 ; (2003) 129 FCR 168 at 177; NBKT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 195 ; (2006) 156 FCR 419 at [22] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Respondents S152/2003 [2004] HCA 18 ; (2004) 222 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/18.html</AustLII>
<text>31 There is another reason why, in any event, in my judgment, the appellant's claim is inevitably doomed to failure (even if as widely expressed as he now asserts). That is because, as the Tribunal remarked, there is no reason to consider that the Indian authorities would not provide an appropriate level of protection to the appellant at least outside of the state of Gujarat. In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Respondents S152/2003 [2004] HCA 18 ; (2004) 222 CLR 1, Gleeson CJ, Hayne and Heydon JJ said at [26]:
 
 No country can guarantee that its citizens will at all times, and in all circumstances, be safe from violence. Day by day, Australian courts deal with criminal cases involving violent attacks on person or property. Some of them may occur for reasons of racial or religious intolerance. The religious activities in which the first respondent engaged between May and December 1998 evidently aroused the anger of some other people. Their response was unlawful. The Ukrainian state was obliged to take reasonable measures to protect the lives and safety of its citizens, and those measures would include an appropriate criminal law, and the provision of a reasonably effective and impartial police force and justice system. None of the country information before the Tribunal justified a conclusion that there was a failure on the part of the Ukraine to conform to its obligations in that respect.

32 Those observations apply equally to the present matter. There is no evidence upon which the Tribunal could have found, even if the appellant were at risk of Muslim fundamentalists throughout India, that the Republic of India did not provide reasonable measures to protect the lives and safety of its citizens including providing an appropriate criminal law and the provision of a reasonably effective and impartial police force and justice system. Consequently, even if the appellant were able to show (contrary to what is clearly the Tribunal's conclusion of fact) that he was at risk of attack by Muslim fundamentalists throughout India, there is no basis upon which he could show that that non-state threat was one in which the Indian state itself was complicit, or in respect of which the Indian state did not provide an appropriate level of protection by police and other authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>33 I have also independently considered whether there is some other basis upon which the appellant might have demonstrated jurisdictional error on the part of the Tribunal. Section 425(1) of the Act obliges the Tribunal to have invited the appellant to give evidence and present arguments relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review. As the High Court (Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ) pointed out in SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592 at [33] , the reference to "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review" is important. The issue of relocation was therefore an important one, but it was, as the Tribunal's record of hearing as exposed in its reasons for decision illustrates, raised fairly and squarely before the appellant. Moreover, even if "the issues" to be the subject of a hearing are more refined, and extend to particular factual matters which may go to the question of reasonableness of relocation, in this instance in my judgment the Tribunal adequately gave the appellant the opportunity to address those factual matters. In particular, it put to him that he had travelled to Australia and that, if he were able to set himself up in Australia, there is no reason why he should not be able to do so in another city in India.

34 For those reasons, in my judgment, the appeal must be dismissed. The appellant is to pay to the first respondent the costs of the appeal.

 I certify that the preceding thirty-four (34) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Mansfield. 


 Associate:

Dated: 9 August 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: The appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr D Godwin 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 8 August 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 9 August 2007 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1197.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>