<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Spencer v Lane Rowin Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1519 (15 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1519.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Emerson v Wreckair Pty Ltd (1992) 33 FCR 581</tocase>
<text>21 In Re Wilson v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [1999] FCA 1760 the applicants sought an annulment of their bankruptcies under s 153B of the Act . Sequestration orders had been made on the basis of a judgment debt obtained from the New South Wales District Court. The applicants claimed that the creditor was not entitled to judgment in the full amount of the debt because of certain payments earlier made. Emmett J dismissed the applications. He declined to follow Greenhill and held that s 41(5) "is concerned with a claim of a bankruptcy notice for an amount greater than is, in fact, [owed] under a judgment " (emphasis in original). His Honour explained his reasons for differing from Morling J as follows:
 
 "[39] A bankruptcy notice must require the debtor to pay the judgment debt, in accordance with the judgment. The pre-existing obligation, which the judgment is intended to enforce, will have merged in the new obligation created by the judgment see Corney v Brien [1951] HCA 31 ; (1951) 84 CLR 343 at 353-354. It may well be that there would be good grounds for setting aside a judgment which was entered for an excessive amount. Further, it may be that this Court, as a Court of Bankruptcy would go behind a judgement in order to determine whether there was, in fact, anything due. Following the entry of a judgment, however, the amount due by the judgment debtor to the judgment creditor, and the amount for which execution might issue, is the sum stated in the judgment. Where a bankruptcy notice claims that amount, it cannot be said that it claims an amount that exceeds the amount in fact due. By reason of the judgment itself, the amount of the judgment is due. 
 
 [40] Upon an application to a court exercising jurisdiction in bankruptcy to set aside a bankruptcy notice, the court should not go behind a judgment where the grounds upon which the judgment is challenged are such that, if accepted, they would only support a finding that the amount of the debt be reduced, and would not support a finding that there was, in truth, no debt at all see Emerson v Wreckair Pty Ltd (1992) 33 FCR 581 at 589. That decision of a Full Court of this Court is binding upon me and, it appears to me, that it would preclude a Judge, on hearing a bankruptcy petition, to go behind the judgment if the only purpose for doing so would be to show that the amount of the judgment should be reduced, not to show that no amount was owing. It may be relevant, if the amount of the judgment should be reduced to an amount below the minimum amount that supports a petition. However, that is not the case here."

22 In Emerson the Full Court (presided over by Morling J) accepted that a bankruptcy notice may be invalid if the amount specified in the notice exceeds the amount in fact due. It held that the date on which the inquiry as to whether or not the amount specified in the notice is excessive was to be made as at the date of the issue of the notice. In that case the amount specified in the notice was an amount for which judgment had been obtained in the District Court in Queensland. After the bankruptcy notice had issued the Supreme Court allowed an appeal from the District Court's judgment and reduced the judgment sum by $5,400. The Court held that the notice claimed the amount of the judgment and did not, therefore, exceed the amount in fact due. The subsequent reduction of the amount of the judgment did not alter this position. The Court then dealt with the question of when it might be permissible for a Court of Bankruptcy to go behind a judgment on which a bankruptcy notice was founded. The Court said (at 587 588) that:
 
 "It is not open to doubt that a Court exercising jurisdiction in bankruptcy may, in an appropriate case, 'go behind' a judgment and inquire whether it was founded on a real debt: Corney v Brien ... . Such a Court, however, has no power to set aside a judgment but only to prevent the judgment creditor from having recourse to the provisions of the Bankruptcy Act ... As between the parties, the judgment remains unimpeached and maybe enforced accordingly by what ever means may otherwise be available. 
 
 In the present case, there had been a full hearing before the District Court at which the appellants and the respondent appeared and were legally represented. All the issues were carefully examined and judicially determined. This is not a case, like many of the cases in this area of the law, where judgment was entered in default of appearance or defence. There may be circumstances which justify, in a particular case a review of the proceedings in another Court which, after a hearing, have resulted in the entry of judgment against a debtor ... For example, if an allegation is made that a judgment has been obtained by fraud, it may be proper for a Court exercising jurisdiction in bankruptcy to go behind the judgment to ascertain whether there is a real debt. But there is nothing in the facts of the present case which would have warranted this Court embarking on what would have amounted to a re-trial of the issues that had been determined after a contested hearing and which were the subject of an appeal to the Supreme Court of Queensland. That Court, not this Court, was the appropriate forum in which to review the correctness of the District Court judgment. The circumstance that the Supreme Court subsequently varied the judgment entered in the District Court, reducing it by the sum of $5,400, provides no support for the contention that this Court should have itself examined the correctness of the judgment. Nor, given the particular circumstances of this case, do any of the cases on which the appellants relied support the appellants' contention."

23 The appellants sought to distinguish Emerson on the ground that, in that case, the amount of the judgment debt was determined after a full hearing at which the parties were represented. In my view there is no reason, in principle, for not applying Emerson in the circumstances of the present case. This was not a case where the creditor had obtained a summary default judgment. Nor is it a case in which a tenable allegation that the judgment was fraudulently obtained is made. On the contrary, on their own case, the appellants agreed to sign and did sign consent orders under which they became liable to pay the sum appearing in the bankruptcy notices if, as happened, they failed to pay the nominated sum (and interest) by an agreed date. When this did not occur the consent orders were filed and judgment entered for that sum. The sum then became owing under a judgment of the District Court. The appellants did not, as they could have done, applied to the District Court to vary that judgment. There is no occasion for this Court to go behind the judgment and it should not do so.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>House v R [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1936/40.html</AustLII>
<text>36 A decision to refuse an application for the adjournment of a hearing is a discretionary decision which will not lightly be overruled on appeal: see Sali v SPC Limited [1993] HCA 47 ; (1993) 116 ALR 625; House v R [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499. An appeal court will only intervene if the discretion has not been exercised judicially "or where its exercise was based upon the wrong principle or resulted in gross injustice": Sydney City Council v Ke-Su Investments Pty Ltd (1985) 1 NSWLR 246 at 252.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Livesey v NSW Bar Association [1983] HCA 17 ; (1983) 151 CLR 288</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/17.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The principles which are to be applied, when applications are made for disqualification on the ground of bias in cases such as the present, were explained by the High Court in Livesey v NSW Bar Association [1983] HCA 17 ; (1983) 151 CLR 288. The Court said (at 293-294) that:
 
 "That principle is that a judge should not sit to hear a case if in all the circumstances the parties or the public might entertain a reasonable apprehension that he might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question involved in it." 

The joint judgment continued (at 300):
 
 "It is, however, apparent that, in a case such as the present where it is not suggested that there is any overriding consideration of necessity, special circumstances or consent of a party, a fair minded observer might entertain a reasonable apprehension of bias by reason of prejudgment if a judge sits to hear a case at first instance after he has, in a previous case, expressed clear views either about a question of fact which constitutes a live and significant issue in the subsequent case or about the credit of a witness whose evidence is of significance on such a question of fact."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Perovich v Traditional Values Management Limited [2006] FMCA 1471</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/1471.html</AustLII>
<text>12 In dealing with the disqualification application he said:
 
 "[3] The respondent made two preliminary instanter applications. First, the respondent applied for an order than I disqualify myself from hearing the application. The basis for such application was that I had earlier dismissed an application by the respondent to set aside the bankruptcy notice (see Perovich v Lane Rowin Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 940). That decision is the subject of an appeal, but there is no stay of the judgment in force. In reliance on that fact it was submitted that the respondent perceives that I may be biased against her because of my previous adverse finding against her. I should add that I have not only decided that matter involving the respondent but other matters as well (Perovich v Neolido Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 1105 ; Perovich v Traditional Values Management Ltd [2006] FMCA 1471 ; Perovich v Tesla Nominees Pty Ltd [2006] FMCA 1342). The respondent did not rely on my having heard those matters as founding her application that I disqualify myself." 

His Honour reviewed various authorities and concluded:
 
 "[12] The issue that I have previously decided is whether or not the bankruptcy notice overstated the amount due by the respondent to the applicant. That issue was decided on documentary and unchallenged evidence. No finding of credit was made against the respondent. It is presumably said that having found that the bankruptcy notice did not overstate the amount of the debt owed by the respondent to the applicant there is a reasonable apprehension that I cannot impartially decide the issue of whether the respondent is able to pay her debts, as required by s 52(2)(a) of the Act . In my view the two issues are quite separate and there is not a logical connection between my having previously determined the validity of the bankruptcy notice and the feared deviation from the course of deciding the case on its merits. I have not, because it has not previously arisen, expressed any view about a question of fact which is in issue on the present application, nor about the credit of a witness whose evidence is of significance on such a question of fact. 

His Honour held that in these circumstances authority mandated that he refuse to accede to the application for disqualification.

28 The appellants' argument on appeal did not seek to challenge the finding of the Federal Magistrate that he was not disqualified from dealing with the creditor's petition because of his earlier decision not to set aside the bankruptcy notice. What was argued was that the learned Magistrate should have disqualified himself by reason of the fact that he had made adverse findings relating to Mrs Perovich's credit in another, earlier, decision, to which he referred in his reasons, namely, Perovich v Traditional Values Management Limited [2006] FMCA 1471. In that case the Magistrate had dealt with an application by the appellants for a declaration that a bankruptcy notice had not properly been served on them. Mrs Perovich swore an affidavit in support of the application and gave oral evidence before the Federal Magistrate. He found significant parts of that evidence to be unsatisfactory. He found her to be an unreliable witness. She was "evasive and vague when it suited her, and implausible in other respects." He was not prepared to act on her unsupported evidence. The application was dismissed. This occurred on 14 September 2006.

29 Senior counsel for Mrs Perovich (who did not appear below) accepted that the adverse credit findings in Traditional Values were not relied on in support of the disqualification application. He also accepted that these findings were known to Mrs Perovich prior to the disqualification application being made and that, for some unexplained reason, they were not made known to counsel then appearing. Despite this, it was argued that the Federal Magistrate should be taken to have been aware of his earlier decision, given that he had referred to it in his reasons in the present case. Attention was also directed to the Federal Magistrate's statement that he had not previously expressed any view about the credit of any witness appearing before him.

31 Mrs Perovich contends that a reasonable apprehension of bias on the part of the Federal Magistrate arose in the present case because he had earlier made adverse findings relating to her credit and because there was a significant issue to be decided which depended, if she were to prevail, upon acceptance of her evidence that she was not insolvent. During argument senior counsel accepted that, by reason of the effluxion of time, the Federal Magistrate may well have forgotten that he had earlier made adverse findings concerning Mrs Perovich's credibility. Although Traditional Values had been referred to in the Magistrate's reasons, it was possible that this was because the Magistrate had extracted the case name from Court records without re-reading his reasons. Nonetheless, senior counsel submitted that the reasonable observer, seized of the knowledge that the earlier adverse credit findings had been made, would entertain a reasonable suspicion that the Magistrate would have regard to those findings when resolving credibility issues in the present case. Although the disqualification application had been made only by reference to the Federal Magistrate's earlier refusal to set aside the bankruptcy notice, the application had been made. This was not a case, so the argument ran, in which an applicant with good reason to seek a judge's disqualification stood by in the hope of a favourable decision and only alleged bias once that hope had been disappointed: cf Vakauta v Kelly [1989] HCA 44 ; (1989) 167 CLR 568 at 572.

33 I have read carefully what the Federal Magistrate said in para [12] of his reasons. They may be understood as an assertion that he had not, previously, had occasion to pass on Mrs Perovich's credibility. In this he was mistaken. The mistake was understandable given that almost twelve months separated the Traditional Values decision and the decision presently under appeal. It is also understandable because counsel appearing for Mrs Perovich had not drawn the Federal Magistrate's reasons in Traditional Values to his attention or sought to rely on them in support of the disqualification application. In these circumstances it is reasonable to infer that the learned Magistrate's mistake was attributable to him not remembering that, in Traditional Values , he had reflected adversely on Mrs Perovich's credit. A reasonable observer, knowing that the Federal Magistrate had not recalled what he had earlier said about Mrs Perovich's credibility and knowing that her credit was not in issue in the present matter, would not, in my opinion, entertain a reasonable apprehension of bias on the part of the Federal Magistrate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sali v SPC Limited [1993] HCA 47 ; (1993) 116 ALR 625</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/47.html</AustLII>
<text>36 A decision to refuse an application for the adjournment of a hearing is a discretionary decision which will not lightly be overruled on appeal: see Sali v SPC Limited [1993] HCA 47 ; (1993) 116 ALR 625; House v R [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499. An appeal court will only intervene if the discretion has not been exercised judicially "or where its exercise was based upon the wrong principle or resulted in gross injustice": Sydney City Council v Ke-Su Investments Pty Ltd (1985) 1 NSWLR 246 at 252.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sydney City Council v Ke-Su Investments Pty Ltd (1985) 1 NSWLR 246</tocase>
<text>36 A decision to refuse an application for the adjournment of a hearing is a discretionary decision which will not lightly be overruled on appeal: see Sali v SPC Limited [1993] HCA 47 ; (1993) 116 ALR 625; House v R [1936] HCA 40 ; (1936) 55 CLR 499. An appeal court will only intervene if the discretion has not been exercised judicially "or where its exercise was based upon the wrong principle or resulted in gross injustice": Sydney City Council v Ke-Su Investments Pty Ltd (1985) 1 NSWLR 246 at 252.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Re Greenhill; ex parte Myer (NSW) Limited (1984) 5 FCR 84</tocase>
<text>17 It was common ground that, if such an overstatement had occurred, the bankruptcy notices were invalid: cf Re Greenhill; ex parte Myer (NSW) Limited (1984) 5 FCR 84 at 86. It was also accepted by all parties that the notices given by Mrs Perovich and Mr Spencer on 20 March 2007 were both timely and effective for the purposes of s 41(5) of the Act .

18 The appellants submit that the 17 May letter (together with the email which subsequently varied the date for payment of the $10,000) constituted a simple written contract which provided, unambiguously, that the $10,000 payment, when made, would be treated as a payment on account of the debt owed to the respondent. They complain that the Federal Magistrate erred by treating the written document as being ambiguous on this point, by relying on the solicitor's file note to assist in resolving the ambiguity and by having regard to the conduct of the parties in relation to the subsequent payment of $15,000.

19 The respondent contends that there is authority which binds me to hold that no overstatement has occurred because the bankruptcy notices correctly identified the amounts owing under the consent judgment made by the District Court. In any event, the respondent submits that the contractual terms, recorded in the 17 May letter, do not require that the $10,000 should be credited against the amount owing; rather it is to be treated as consideration for the indulgence, granted by the respondent, to forebear seeking judgment for the debt.

20 Section 41(5) of the Act provides:
 
 "(5) A bankruptcy notice is not invalidated by reason only that the sum specified in the notice as the amount due to the creditor exceeds the amount, in fact, due unless the debtor, within the time allowed for payment, gives notice to the creditor that he or she disputes the validity of the notice on the ground of the misstatement." 

This provision was considered by Morling J Greenhill . In that case final judgment had been entered against the debtor for a particular sum. It was common ground between the parties that, prior to the entry of the judgment, the debtor had paid $200 to the creditor as a part payment of the money due and that, accordingly, the judgment was wrongly entered because it had failed to take into account the $200 payment. It overstated the amount owing by that sum. This overstatement was held to render the notice invalid.

21 In Re Wilson v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [1999] FCA 1760 the applicants sought an annulment of their bankruptcies under s 153B of the Act . Sequestration orders had been made on the basis of a judgment debt obtained from the New South Wales District Court. The applicants claimed that the creditor was not entitled to judgment in the full amount of the debt because of certain payments earlier made. Emmett J dismissed the applications. He declined to follow Greenhill and held that s 41(5) "is concerned with a claim of a bankruptcy notice for an amount greater than is, in fact, [owed] under a judgment " (emphasis in original). His Honour explained his reasons for differing from Morling J as follows:
 
 "[39] A bankruptcy notice must require the debtor to pay the judgment debt, in accordance with the judgment. The pre-existing obligation, which the judgment is intended to enforce, will have merged in the new obligation created by the judgment see Corney v Brien [1951] HCA 31 ; (1951) 84 CLR 343 at 353-354. It may well be that there would be good grounds for setting aside a judgment which was entered for an excessive amount. Further, it may be that this Court, as a Court of Bankruptcy would go behind a judgement in order to determine whether there was, in fact, anything due. Following the entry of a judgment, however, the amount due by the judgment debtor to the judgment creditor, and the amount for which execution might issue, is the sum stated in the judgment. Where a bankruptcy notice claims that amount, it cannot be said that it claims an amount that exceeds the amount in fact due. By reason of the judgment itself, the amount of the judgment is due. 
 
 [40] Upon an application to a court exercising jurisdiction in bankruptcy to set aside a bankruptcy notice, the court should not go behind a judgment where the grounds upon which the judgment is challenged are such that, if accepted, they would only support a finding that the amount of the debt be reduced, and would not support a finding that there was, in truth, no debt at all see Emerson v Wreckair Pty Ltd (1992) 33 FCR 581 at 589. That decision of a Full Court of this Court is binding upon me and, it appears to me, that it would preclude a Judge, on hearing a bankruptcy petition, to go behind the judgment if the only purpose for doing so would be to show that the amount of the judgment should be reduced, not to show that no amount was owing. It may be relevant, if the amount of the judgment should be reduced to an amount below the minimum amount that supports a petition. However, that is not the case here."

24 I do not consider that Greenhill compels a different conclusion. In that case, unlike this, there was agreement between the parties in this Court that the judgment on which the bankruptcy notice was founded had mistakenly been entered for a sum greater than that which was, in fact, owing. In any event, I respectfully agree with Emmett J's reasons for holding that Greenhill should not be followed.

25 Although it is not strictly necessary to do so, I should say something about the issue of whether the contract, evidenced by the 17 May letter, provided for the $10,000 to be credited against the sum owed by the appellants. Nowhere in the terms contained in the letter is there an express term that the $10,000 was to be credited against the principal sum. Paragraphs (f) and (g), when read together, may be understood as suggesting that the $10,000 and the "further moneys" necessary to satisfy the $201,754.44 debt were to be payable on or before 20 July 2006. This suggests, so the appellants contend, that the $10,000, if paid, would, together with the balance needed to meet the debt, be deductible from the principal sum. That may be so if timely payment of the whole of the principal sum were made. The difficulty with the appellants' argument is that the appellants agreed to execute a consent judgment in the sum claimed of $201,754.44. They agreed that if they failed to make any payment due on or before 20 July 2006 (or within the agreed extended period) the respondent would file the consent judgment for the agreed sum. This would occur whether or not there had been partial payment in the intervening period. It is also to be noted that the appellants agreed to pay interest on the principal sum, not the principal sum as reduced by any payments made prior to the due date.

26 Even if it be assumed, in the appellants favour, that there is no ambiguity in the agreement, as recorded in the 17 May letter, rendering it unnecessary to have regard to parol evidence, I do not consider that a literal reading of the terms supports the construction contended for by the appellants. It follows, in my opinion, that the Federal Magistrate came to the correct conclusion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Wilson v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [1999] FCA 1760</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1760.html</AustLII>
<text>21 In Re Wilson v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [1999] FCA 1760 the applicants sought an annulment of their bankruptcies under s 153B of the Act . Sequestration orders had been made on the basis of a judgment debt obtained from the New South Wales District Court. The applicants claimed that the creditor was not entitled to judgment in the full amount of the debt because of certain payments earlier made. Emmett J dismissed the applications. He declined to follow Greenhill and held that s 41(5) "is concerned with a claim of a bankruptcy notice for an amount greater than is, in fact, [owed] under a judgment " (emphasis in original). His Honour explained his reasons for differing from Morling J as follows:
 
 "[39] A bankruptcy notice must require the debtor to pay the judgment debt, in accordance with the judgment. The pre-existing obligation, which the judgment is intended to enforce, will have merged in the new obligation created by the judgment see Corney v Brien [1951] HCA 31 ; (1951) 84 CLR 343 at 353-354. It may well be that there would be good grounds for setting aside a judgment which was entered for an excessive amount. Further, it may be that this Court, as a Court of Bankruptcy would go behind a judgement in order to determine whether there was, in fact, anything due. Following the entry of a judgment, however, the amount due by the judgment debtor to the judgment creditor, and the amount for which execution might issue, is the sum stated in the judgment. Where a bankruptcy notice claims that amount, it cannot be said that it claims an amount that exceeds the amount in fact due. By reason of the judgment itself, the amount of the judgment is due. 
 
 [40] Upon an application to a court exercising jurisdiction in bankruptcy to set aside a bankruptcy notice, the court should not go behind a judgment where the grounds upon which the judgment is challenged are such that, if accepted, they would only support a finding that the amount of the debt be reduced, and would not support a finding that there was, in truth, no debt at all see Emerson v Wreckair Pty Ltd (1992) 33 FCR 581 at 589. That decision of a Full Court of this Court is binding upon me and, it appears to me, that it would preclude a Judge, on hearing a bankruptcy petition, to go behind the judgment if the only purpose for doing so would be to show that the amount of the judgment should be reduced, not to show that no amount was owing. It may be relevant, if the amount of the judgment should be reduced to an amount below the minimum amount that supports a petition. However, that is not the case here."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Vakauta v Kelly [1989] HCA 44 ; (1989) 167 CLR 568</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/44.html</AustLII>
<text>31 Mrs Perovich contends that a reasonable apprehension of bias on the part of the Federal Magistrate arose in the present case because he had earlier made adverse findings relating to her credit and because there was a significant issue to be decided which depended, if she were to prevail, upon acceptance of her evidence that she was not insolvent. During argument senior counsel accepted that, by reason of the effluxion of time, the Federal Magistrate may well have forgotten that he had earlier made adverse findings concerning Mrs Perovich's credibility. Although Traditional Values had been referred to in the Magistrate's reasons, it was possible that this was because the Magistrate had extracted the case name from Court records without re-reading his reasons. Nonetheless, senior counsel submitted that the reasonable observer, seized of the knowledge that the earlier adverse credit findings had been made, would entertain a reasonable suspicion that the Magistrate would have regard to those findings when resolving credibility issues in the present case. Although the disqualification application had been made only by reference to the Federal Magistrate's earlier refusal to set aside the bankruptcy notice, the application had been made. This was not a case, so the argument ran, in which an applicant with good reason to seek a judge's disqualification stood by in the hope of a favourable decision and only alleged bias once that hope had been disappointed: cf Vakauta v Kelly [1989] HCA 44 ; (1989) 167 CLR 568 at 572.

34 Had the resolution of any significant issue in the present case turned on Mrs Perovich's credit, other issues may have arisen as to whether or not Mrs Perovich should be allowed to raise, on appeal, a ground supporting disqualification which could have been, but was not, advanced before the Federal Magistrate: cf Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491 at 497; Vakauta at 572.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/12.html</AustLII>
<text>34 Had the resolution of any significant issue in the present case turned on Mrs Perovich's credit, other issues may have arisen as to whether or not Mrs Perovich should be allowed to raise, on appeal, a ground supporting disqualification which could have been, but was not, advanced before the Federal Magistrate: cf Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491 at 497; Vakauta at 572.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>