<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIMD v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1124 (31 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1124.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>SZIMD v Minister for Immigration [2007] FMCA 445</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/445.html</AustLII>
<text>1 This is an appeal from a decision of a Federal Magistrate which dismissed an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal. The Tribunal had affirmed a decision of a delegate of the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship to refuse the appellant a protection visa. Details of the application, the Tribunal's decision and the decision of the Federal Magistrate are set out in the judgment of the latter, SZIMD v Minister for Immigration [2007] FMCA 445 , which is available on the internet.

2 The appellant is a citizen of the People's Republic of China. He claimed to have well-founded fear of persecution based on his membership of Falun Gong. He claimed to have practised Falun Gong since 1998 in order to assist his health. He also claimed that after the ban on Falun Gong in 1999 his health deteriorated. He claimed to have been detained on five occasions and been tortured.

3 Before the Tribunal the appellant claimed that he practised Falun Gong exercises in Australia with friends. He also claimed that he had a visa to visit Singapore, but had not in fact travelled there because on the way to the airport to go to Singapore he had been stopped and beaten. The Tribunal did not accept that the appellant was a Falun Gong practitioner and was subject to arrest and torture in China. He provided no written evidence and his application contained minimal details. He was not a credible witness in respect of key aspects. His evidence was unconvincing, generalised and lacking specificity, especially in relation to the claims of arrest. He was unable to elaborate in any details on the belief system of Falun Gong. He had not had contact with the Falun Association in Australia. The Tribunal found that the paucity of the appellant's evidence led it to find that he was not genuinely in fear of persecution.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>