<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v FUELbanc Australia Limited (No 2) [2007] FCA 1033 (6 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1033.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission re Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 5) (2006) 58 ACSR 6</tocase>
<text>6 As French J said in Australian Securities and Investments Commission re Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 5) (2006) 58 ACSR 6, s 1323 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) does not authorise the Court to order that the person or company the subject of the orders appointing receivers to the property pay the costs of the receivers in discharging their function. This is consistent with a long established practice in England, see Evans v Clayhope Properties Pty Ltd [1988] 1 All ER 444 at 446.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans v Clayhope Properties Pty Ltd [1988] 1 All ER 444</tocase>
<text>6 As French J said in Australian Securities and Investments Commission re Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 5) (2006) 58 ACSR 6, s 1323 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) does not authorise the Court to order that the person or company the subject of the orders appointing receivers to the property pay the costs of the receivers in discharging their function. This is consistent with a long established practice in England, see Evans v Clayhope Properties Pty Ltd [1988] 1 All ER 444 at 446.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pontifical Society for the Propagation of the Faith v Scales [1962] HCA 19 ; (1962) 107 CLR 9</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1962/19.html</AustLII>
<text>8 It is the almost invariable practice for courts not to make any final order for costs in favour of a plaintiff on an interim application, the reason being that usually the substantive merits remain to be determined. The plaintiff's case may then appear to be very strong, indeed unanswerable, but as Dixon CJ pointed out in Pontifical Society for the Propagation of the Faith v Scales [1962] HCA 19 ; (1962) 107 CLR 9 at 20:
 
 "Experience of forensic contests should confirm the truth of the common saying that one story is good until another is told ..." 


 It would be better if ASIC did not seek final orders for costs in interim applications of this nature.

 I certify that the preceding eight (8) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 6 July 2007
 Counsel for the Plaintiff: M Scott 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff Australian Government Solicitor 
 
 Counsel for Receiver for first and fourth 
Defendants: N Fryde 
 
 No appearance for fifth Defendant 
 
 
 Counsel for sixth and seventh Defendants: N Evans 
 
 Solicitor for sixth and seventh Defendants Baker &amp; McKenzie 
 
 Date of Hearing: 6 July 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 July 2007 

 SCHEDULE OF PARTIES 

 AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES &amp; INVESTMENTS COMMISSION 
 Plaintiff
 
- and -

 FUELBANC AUSTRALIA LIMITED (ACN 117 937 327) ("Fuelbanc") 
 First Defendant
 
- and -

 PAYCARDS GLOBAL PTY LTD (ACN 116 759 472) ("PayCards Global") 
 Second Defendant
 
- and -

 PAYCARDS INVESTMENTS PTY LTD (ACN 118 252 369) ("Paycards Investments") 
 Third Defendant
 
- and -

 C PROPERTY GROUP PTY LTD (ACN 118 252 387) ("PC Property Group") 
 Fourth Defendant
 

- and -

 STEPHEN JOHN MCDOUGALL ("McDougall") 
 Fifth Defendant
 
- and -

 TIMOTHY ROSS MCDOUGALL ("Timothy McDougall") 
 Sixth Defendant
 
- and -

 MATTHEW ALAN MCDOUGALL ("Matthew McDougall") 
 Seventh Defendant
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1033.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>