<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHDY v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1218 (9 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1218.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/10.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The Federal Magistrate held that the choice of country information was a matter for the RRT, and could not give rise to jurisdictional error. His Honour referred to NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10 where the Full Court stated (at [11]): 
 
 "It is not, as the first appellant submitted, an error of law, or a jurisdictional error, for the Tribunal to base a decision on 'country information' that is not true. The question of the accuracy of the 'country information' is one for the Tribunal, not for the Court. If the Court were to make its own assessment of the truth of 'country information', it would be engaging in merits review. The Court does not have power to do that."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZEPZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/107.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In relation to the ground regarding s 424A , the Federal Magistrate noted that a letter which he regarded as having satisfied the requirements of that section had been sent to the appellant by the RRT on 24 January 2000. He concluded that the fact that the s 424A letter had been sent by the RRT at the time of the first hearing, rather than at the time of the second hearing, was of no consequence. He observed that the letter had been sent to the appellant as part of the process leading up to the RRT's earlier decision, which was subsequently set aside, but that this did not affect its significance. He referred to SZEPZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 107 at [37] [44]; and SZJBE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 190 at [16] [17].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZJBE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 190</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/190.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In relation to the ground regarding s 424A , the Federal Magistrate noted that a letter which he regarded as having satisfied the requirements of that section had been sent to the appellant by the RRT on 24 January 2000. He concluded that the fact that the s 424A letter had been sent by the RRT at the time of the first hearing, rather than at the time of the second hearing, was of no consequence. He observed that the letter had been sent to the appellant as part of the process leading up to the RRT's earlier decision, which was subsequently set aside, but that this did not affect its significance. He referred to SZEPZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 107 at [37] [44]; and SZJBE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 190 at [16] [17].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VTAG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 91 ; (2005) 141 FCR 291</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/91.html</AustLII>
<text>12 His Honour further noted that in VTAG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 91 ; (2005) 141 FCR 291 the Full Court held (at [41]):
 
 "In any event, the choice of country information available was a matter for the Tribunal. The Tribunal was not required by law to accept more recent information even if it had been supplied. Such information might for example have come from a less reliable source than the old information. There was in the circumstances no obligation on the Tribunal to make enquiries: see VAO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 161 at [25] . "

13 His Honour went on to state that it was plain that the RRT had not ignored the later country information because it had referred to that information in terms in its reasons for decision. The country information in question related to the position in 2004, while the earlier information went back to 1998 and 2001. His Honour concluded that the appropriate inference was simply that the RRT preferred the earlier country information to the later information. In his Honour's opinion, that was a matter for the RRT. The Court could not substitute its own view of the weight that should be accorded to this material for that of the RRT.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>