<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Ashdown v Spargo [2007] FCA 1399 (5 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1399.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Allanson v Midland Credit Ltd (1977) 16 ALR 43</tocase>
<text>10 The circumstances which a Court must consider when asked to grant leave have been set out in Allanson v Midland Credit Ltd (1977) 16 ALR 43. In that Full Court decision their Honours observed at 48 that if the issues involved would be better and more comprehensively dealt with in a contested trial of the action in the Supreme Court than if a creditor was required to lodge a proof of debt, a grant of leave should follow.

11 The issues as outlined in the Statement of Claim and in the proposed Amended Statement of Claim establish that there are complex factual issues to be determined which, it is apparent, could be determined more effectively in the Supreme Court proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re McMaster; ex parte McMaster (1991) 33 FCR 70</tocase>
<text>9 The words ' in respect of' which appear in s 58(3)(b) have been considered judicially: see for example Re McMaster; ex parte McMaster (1991) 33 FCR 70 at 72 and in Trustees Executors and Agency Company Ltd v Reilly [1941] ALR 105 at 106. Such authorities refer to the wide scope of the words ' in respect of' as contained in the relevant subsection. The Court is satisfied that for the purposes of s 58(3)(b) of the Act the claim the subject of the Supreme Court proceedings falls within the purview of s 82 and that the Supreme Court proceedings are in respect of a provable debt. As such this is a proper case for an application for leave under s 58(3)(b) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Veghelyi; Smith and Others v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy (1993) 45 FCR 413</tocase>
<text>12 As the Supreme Court proceedings were last before that Court for directions on 29 August 2007, an order is sought for leave to be granted effective from that date. The power of the Court to grant leave pursuant to s 58(3)(b) of the Act includes the power to grant such leave nunc pro tunc : see Re Veghelyi; Smith and Others v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy (1993) 45 FCR 413 at 417.

13 Accordingly the Court considers that the orders sought by Ms Marie Ashdown should be made forthwith and the Court makes the orders as set out above. 
 I certify that the preceding thirteen (13) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Cowdroy . 


 Associate:

Dated: 5 September 2007


 Counsel for the Applicant: A. McInerney 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Lee &amp; Lyons Lawyers 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: D. A. Jabbour 
 
 Date of Hearing: 5 September 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 5 September 2007 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1399.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Trustees Executors and Agency Company Ltd v Reilly [1941] ALR 105</tocase>
<text>9 The words ' in respect of' which appear in s 58(3)(b) have been considered judicially: see for example Re McMaster; ex parte McMaster (1991) 33 FCR 70 at 72 and in Trustees Executors and Agency Company Ltd v Reilly [1941] ALR 105 at 106. Such authorities refer to the wide scope of the words ' in respect of' as contained in the relevant subsection. The Court is satisfied that for the purposes of s 58(3)(b) of the Act the claim the subject of the Supreme Court proceedings falls within the purview of s 82 and that the Supreme Court proceedings are in respect of a provable debt. As such this is a proper case for an application for leave under s 58(3)(b) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>