<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rilstone v BP Australia Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1557 (11 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1557.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Federal Police Commissioner v Propend Finance Pty Ltd (1997) 188 CLR</tocase>
<text>12 The privilege asserted is legal advice privilege, which protects confidential communications between a client and his or her legal adviser. The protection of communications passing between third parties and the client's legal adviser does not arise in the present case: all the documents in question are said to be communications created by the OWS or Mr Ronson as State Manager of the OWS (the client) and communicated to the Legal and Advice Branch (the legal adviser). The relevant communications in respect of which privilege is claimed are all contained in documents. Therefore, in determining whether the communications enjoy the privilege claimed, the relevant test to be applied in each case is whether the document was brought into existence for the dominant purpose of obtaining or giving legal advice: Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49. Although no submissions were put directly on the point, it appears from the applicant's list of documents that several of the documents may be copies of documents which, in their original form, are not the subject of privilege. Whether these copy documents enjoy legal professional privilege will depend upon whether the copy was brought into existence for the dominant purpose of obtaining legal advice: Australian Federal Police Commissioner v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Barnes v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCAFC 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/88.html</AustLII>
<text>16 The applicant made two submissions in the alternative. The first related to all the documents in dispute and relied on the fact that Mr Ronson decided on or about 18 August 2006 that legal advice would be sought in relation to the matter being investigated. The submission was that once Mr Ronson decided that he was not going to be able to determine whether there had been a breach of the Act , or whether to recommend the institution of proceedings, without obtaining legal advice, the documents brought into existence thereafter were brought into existence for the main purpose, or the ruling or prevailing purpose, of obtaining legal advice. I am unable to accept this broad submission. Even though I accept Mr Ronson's evidence that on or about 18 August 2006 he decided that it would be necessary for him to seek legal advice, that fact supports, at its highest, only the conclusion that obtaining legal advice was one purpose, alongside the admitted investigatory purpose. To prove the asserted privilege, the applicant is required to show that obtaining legal advice was the dominant purpose. Without 'focused and specific evidence' ( Barnes v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCAFC 88 at [18] per Tamberlin, Stone and Siopis JJ) I am unable to find that obtaining legal advice was the dominant purpose behind the creation of the documents. I wish to make clear that I do not regard Mr Ronson's evidence as being in the nature of bare assertions as to his purpose. His evidence usefully explains the particular circumstances of the relevant investigation, including the political and media interest, and how they informed him in reaching the view that seeking legal advice would be necessary. But it does not follow that obtaining legal advice was his dominant purpose in creating any of the several documents, let alone all of them as a general class of document defined only by the fact that they were created after 18 August 2006.

17 The applicant's second submission, put in the alternative, was that the interview documents were privileged. The submission was that those documents either would not have been created but for the purpose of obtaining legal advice, or, if they would have been created regardless, would not have been created at the time that they were in fact created. As a matter of legal principle, this is a sounder basis upon which to assert a claim for legal professional privilege. The applicant conceded that this submission cannot support each claim for privilege made, but only the claims in respect of what I have called the interview documents.

18 I am not satisfied that the evidence before me supports the alternative submission. Mr Ronson did not suggest in his evidence that statements from witnesses would not be obtained in investigations where there was no intention to seek legal advice. His evidence was only that statements were taken more formally where, as in the present case, seeking legal advice was intended. The more formal procedure involved seeking authorisation to record the witness' voice, issuing a caution to witnesses and advising the witnesses that legal proceedings may eventually be instituted. It is not clear on the evidence whether in the present case the reduction into documentary form of the information obtained in the investigation occurred for the dominant purpose of obtaining legal advice. It was for the applicant to establish that, and he has not done so.

19 In the result, I am not satisfied that the dominant purpose for the creation of the documents was the obtaining of legal advice.

20 As I have said, the OWS was an executive agency. The Legal and Advice Branch was a branch of the OWS or, as Mr Ronson put it in the context of the Workplace Ombudsman, its "central legal division". I think it is appropriate to infer that there are qualified lawyers within the Legal and Advice Branch and that they were employees of the OWS.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/67.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The claims of privilege are to be determined by reference to the common law principles. Section 118 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth), which creates a statutory legal advice privilege, applies only to the adduction of evidence. Where, as in the present case, privilege is claimed at the pre-hearing stage of discovery, the claim is to be determined by reference to the common law: Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49 at 59 [16] - [17] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ, 73-4 [64] per McHugh J and 100-1 [149] per Callinan J. See also Northern Territory v GPAO [1999] HCA 8 ; (1999) 196 CLR 553 at 571 [16] per Gleeson CJ and Gummow J, 606 [135] per Gaudron J and 629 [199] per McHugh and Callinan JJ. The Federal Court Rules , in particular O 33 r 11, do not extend the operation of s 118 beyond 'circumstances in which the order to produce the document or thing is made to facilitate its being immediately adduced in evidence': Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd [2005] FCAFC 125 ; (2005) 144 FCR 379 at 382-3 [17] per Branson J; see also at 384-5 [33] per Allsop J.

12 The privilege asserted is legal advice privilege, which protects confidential communications between a client and his or her legal adviser. The protection of communications passing between third parties and the client's legal adviser does not arise in the present case: all the documents in question are said to be communications created by the OWS or Mr Ronson as State Manager of the OWS (the client) and communicated to the Legal and Advice Branch (the legal adviser). The relevant communications in respect of which privilege is claimed are all contained in documents. Therefore, in determining whether the communications enjoy the privilege claimed, the relevant test to be applied in each case is whether the document was brought into existence for the dominant purpose of obtaining or giving legal advice: Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49. Although no submissions were put directly on the point, it appears from the applicant's list of documents that several of the documents may be copies of documents which, in their original form, are not the subject of privilege. Whether these copy documents enjoy legal professional privilege will depend upon whether the copy was brought into existence for the dominant purpose of obtaining legal advice: Australian Federal Police Commissioner v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Northern Territory v GPAO [1999] HCA 8 ; (1999) 196 CLR 553</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/8.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The claims of privilege are to be determined by reference to the common law principles. Section 118 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth), which creates a statutory legal advice privilege, applies only to the adduction of evidence. Where, as in the present case, privilege is claimed at the pre-hearing stage of discovery, the claim is to be determined by reference to the common law: Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49 at 59 [16] - [17] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ, 73-4 [64] per McHugh J and 100-1 [149] per Callinan J. See also Northern Territory v GPAO [1999] HCA 8 ; (1999) 196 CLR 553 at 571 [16] per Gleeson CJ and Gummow J, 606 [135] per Gaudron J and 629 [199] per McHugh and Callinan JJ. The Federal Court Rules , in particular O 33 r 11, do not extend the operation of s 118 beyond 'circumstances in which the order to produce the document or thing is made to facilitate its being immediately adduced in evidence': Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd [2005] FCAFC 125 ; (2005) 144 FCR 379 at 382-3 [17] per Branson J; see also at 384-5 [33] per Allsop J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/142.html</AustLII>
<text>25 The evidence required to establish the professional relationship necessary to establish independence will depend on the circumstances. In the case of a person engaging a private firm of solicitors, independence almost invariably will be established by those facts alone. In the case of a lawyer employed by a private company more may be required to establish independence, particularly if there is evidence suggesting that the solicitor was on occasion asked to advise on management or commercial matters (see, for example, Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142 at [4] and [38] per Tamberlin J). I do not think Graham J in Telstra was saying any more than that in the circumstances before him the evidence was insufficient to establish the required degree of independence of the internal legal advisers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd [2005] FCAFC 125 ; (2005) 144 FCR 379</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/125.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The claims of privilege are to be determined by reference to the common law principles. Section 118 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth), which creates a statutory legal advice privilege, applies only to the adduction of evidence. Where, as in the present case, privilege is claimed at the pre-hearing stage of discovery, the claim is to be determined by reference to the common law: Esso Australia Resources Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1999] HCA 67 ; (1999) 201 CLR 49 at 59 [16] - [17] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ, 73-4 [64] per McHugh J and 100-1 [149] per Callinan J. See also Northern Territory v GPAO [1999] HCA 8 ; (1999) 196 CLR 553 at 571 [16] per Gleeson CJ and Gummow J, 606 [135] per Gaudron J and 629 [199] per McHugh and Callinan JJ. The Federal Court Rules , in particular O 33 r 11, do not extend the operation of s 118 beyond 'circumstances in which the order to produce the document or thing is made to facilitate its being immediately adduced in evidence': Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd [2005] FCAFC 125 ; (2005) 144 FCR 379 at 382-3 [17] per Branson J; see also at 384-5 [33] per Allsop J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts (No 2) [2007] FCA 1445</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1445.html</AustLII>
<text>23 First, they submit that the onus was on the applicant to establish his claim for privilege and that included adducing evidence that the Legal and Advice Branch was independent of the OWS. It was submitted that the applicant had put forward no evidence, or insufficient evidence, of the Legal and Advice Branch's independence. It was submitted that this case is similar to that before Graham J in Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts (No 2) [2007] FCA 1445 (" Telstra ") in which his Honour held that the absence of evidence establishing the independence of the internal legal advisers was fatal to the claim of privilege.

25 The evidence required to establish the professional relationship necessary to establish independence will depend on the circumstances. In the case of a person engaging a private firm of solicitors, independence almost invariably will be established by those facts alone. In the case of a lawyer employed by a private company more may be required to establish independence, particularly if there is evidence suggesting that the solicitor was on occasion asked to advise on management or commercial matters (see, for example, Seven Network Limited v News Limited [2005] FCA 142 at [4] and [38] per Tamberlin J). I do not think Graham J in Telstra was saying any more than that in the circumstances before him the evidence was insufficient to establish the required degree of independence of the internal legal advisers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Waterford v The Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/25.html</AustLII>
<text>24 In Waterford v The Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 the High Court held that salaried lawyers within the Government were legal advisers to a Government department for the purposes of legal professional privilege and the requirement of independence was discussed in that context. Mason and Wilson JJ said (at 62):
 
 "Whether in any particular case the relationship is such as to give rise to the privilege will be a question of fact. It must be a professional relationship which secures to the advice an independent character notwithstanding the employment."

26 In this case the applicant might have put forward more detailed evidence as to how the Legal and Advice Branch operated and its role in the OWS organisation. However, in my opinion, this case has similarities with the facts in Waterford and, subject to the respondents' second submission, the necessary degree of independence has been established, or, put another way, it has been established that the Legal and Advice Branch was a legal adviser for the purposes of legal professional privilege.

27 Secondly, the respondents submitted that the fact Ms Byrne, as head of the Legal and Advice Branch, was the decision-maker meant that documents brought into existence for the purpose of submission to the Legal and Advice Branch could not have been brought into existence for the purpose of obtaining legal advice. It was submitted that they must have been brought into existence as part of the process of making a recommendation to the Legal and Advice Branch. I reject this submission. One of the Legal and Advice Branch's functions was to provide legal advice and Mr Ronson said that from 18 August 2006 it was clear to him that he was going to seek legal advice in relation to the matter. He said that some time between the end of September 2006 and 5 October 2006 he sought legal advice from the Legal and Advice Branch. I infer that it was not until some time after 23 October 2006 that he made his recommendation and Ms Byrne made her decision. In those circumstances, the fact that the head of the Legal and Advice Branch was the decision-maker does not foreclose a conclusion that a purpose for the creation of the documents was the obtaining of legal advice.

28 Although I reject the respondents' submissions to the effect that the applicant had not shown the necessary degree of independence for the purpose of legal professional privilege none of my conclusions on this issue affect my conclusion on the first issue, namely, that the applicant has failed to establish that the dominant purpose for the creation of the documents was the obtaining of legal advice.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>