<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Angelakos v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] FCA 25 (29 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/25.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Beadle, Re v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1</tocase>
<text>20 The Tribunal member referred to a number of cases which have considered the meaning of 'special circumstances'. He referred to the decision of the Tribunal in Re Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 where it was said that the circumstances must be unusual, uncommon or exceptional, and the reasons for judgment of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541 where her Honour referred to a circumstance taking the case out of the usual or ordinary case. The Tribunal member also referred to observations of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31 and of French J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra). I will discuss the relevant authorities later in these reasons.

32 In Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services (supra) Branson J considered the provisions of s 1237AAD and in particular whether the Tribunal in that case had erred in concluding that special circumstances meant circumstances which were 'unusual, uncommon or exceptional'. Her Honour referred to the first passage from the reasons for judgment of the Full Court in Beadle set out in [28] above. She also referred to the following passage in Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 (at 195):
 
 'What is needed to justify an extension of time is indicated in r 15(2) by the words "for special reasons". It is that there be shown a special reason why the appeal should be permitted to proceed, though filed after the expiry of twenty-one days. In that context, the expression "special reasons" is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is twenty-one days. But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will, for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in the particular case. Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary. We do not think the use of the expression "for special reasons" implies something narrower than this.' 
 

Although those observations were made in the context of the expression 'for special reasons' in the rules of Court, her Honour considered they were of assistance in the interpretation of the expression 'special circumstances'.
 
Her Honour then said (at [25] and [26]):
 
 In my view, the Tribunal probably overstated the significance of the requirement in s 1237AAD(b) for " special circumstances ". The Full Court in Beadle did not endorse the view expressed by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 at 3 that circumstances are special only if they are " unusual, uncommon or exceptional" . 
 However, the Tribunal concluded that the applicant's circumstances " do not differ from those of many income support recipients" . In the context in which the Tribunal reached this conclusion, it is to be understood as having made a judgment that neither hardship nor unfairness made it desirable to waive all or part of the applicant's debt because the applicant's circumstances were common-place rather than special. While, as French J pointed out in Hales , the evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of circumstances which could give rise to hardship or unfairness, the statutory requirement for " special circumstances " discloses an intention to proscribe waiver in ordinary cases. The hardship or unfairness to which French J referred must be understood to be hardship or unfairness sufficient to justify departure from the general rule in the particular case.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225</tocase>
<text>20 The Tribunal member referred to a number of cases which have considered the meaning of 'special circumstances'. He referred to the decision of the Tribunal in Re Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 where it was said that the circumstances must be unusual, uncommon or exceptional, and the reasons for judgment of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541 where her Honour referred to a circumstance taking the case out of the usual or ordinary case. The Tribunal member also referred to observations of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31 and of French J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra). I will discuss the relevant authorities later in these reasons.

26 The applicant's first submission is that the Tribunal member applied too stringent a test as to what might constitute special circumstances within s 1237AAD(b). He submits that the Tribunal member said that to constitute special circumstances the circumstances must be 'unusual uncommon and exceptional'. The applicant submits that that was the test formulated by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (supra) but it was not the test approved on appeal by the Full Court of this Court: Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. Nor, submits the applicant, is the test consistent with other authority of this Court including Dranichnikov v Centrelink (2003) 53 ATR 270 and Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2005] FCA 866. The applicant submits that the correct test as to what constitutes special circumstances is whether the circumstances take the case out of the ordinary.

29 In Dranichnikov v Centrelink (supra) the Full Court, in considering a similar statutory provision to s 1237AAB said (at [65] and [66]):
 
 
 '65. The decision maker clearly also determined that the circumstances were such that they were not exceptional or unusual so that waiver could not be made as a matter of discretion under s 101. That equates "special circumstances", as that expression is used in the Administration Act with either exceptional circumstances or unusual circumstances. The origin of the test apparently adopted by the Secretary appears to be the decision of the first instance Judge in Beadle v Directory-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. That was a decision under previous legislation, the history of which is referred to by French J in Secretary of Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154. The Full Court in Beadle comprising Bowen CJ, Fisher and Lockhart JJ, however, was of the view that it was not possible to lay down precise rules as to what constituted special circumstances under the then s 102(1)(a) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth). Their Honours point out that the question whether there were special circumstances was one for the decision maker (in that case the Director-General) bearing in mind the purpose for which the power was given. The reference to the first instance decision from which the words "unusual, uncommon or exceptional" come was not actually affirmed by the Full Court. 
 66. To some extent the question whether there were special circumstances must depend on how it came about that the error occurred. Again that is not a matter to which the decision maker apparently averted. Other cases which have considered analogous words such as "special reasons" has tended to conclude, albeit in different contexts, that what is required will be circumstances which distinguish the case in consideration from the usual case. There will be a requirement that the circumstances are such that takes the case out of the ordinary: Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 and the cases in various contexts in the decision which Lockhart, Shepherd and Burchett JJ discuss.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Copperart Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1993) 26 ATR 327</tocase>
<text>42 The applicant's second submission was put in terms of the Tribunal taking into account irrelevant considerations, namely, the applicant's interest in the Torrensville property and his interest in the preserved superannuation benefits. As I have said, the applicant submits that he has no interest in the Torrensville property or, in the alternative, no immediately realisable interest in the property and no immediately realisable interest in the preserved superannuation benefits. On the face of it, those issues are issues of fact. If there were incorrect findings of fact with respect to those issues, those findings of fact would not be overturned so as to expose a question of law. The appeal to this Court is limited to an appeal on a question of law and there is no right of appeal if a question of law is only exposed if findings of fact are overturned: Copperart Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1993) 26 ATR 327. Furthermore, even if a question of law is exposed, this Court does not then have a mandate to review the decision generally: TNT Skypak International (Aust) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1988) 19 ATR 1067.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>David Securities Pty Ltd v Commonwealth Bank of Australia Ltd [1992] HCA 48 ; (1992) 175 CLR 353</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/48.html</AustLII>
<text>48 The applicant's third submission is that the Tribunal member failed to take into account a relevant consideration, namely, that the applicant had changed his position as a result of the respondent's error. The applicant referred to cases dealing with the recovery of money paid to a person by mistake ( Lipkin Gorman (a firm) v Karpnale Ltd [1988] UKHL 12 ; [1991] 2 AC 548; David Securities Pty Ltd v Commonwealth Bank of Australia Ltd [1992] HCA 48 ; (1992) 175 CLR 353). I reject the applicant's submission. The Tribunal member was not obliged to approach the matter in this way. He clearly took into account the respondent's error and the nature of the error. He took into account the financial hardship the applicant might suffer if required to repay the debt. I do not think the fact that the applicant might have spent the moneys which are the subject of the debt on ordinary living expenses is of any particular significance. The significant matter was financial hardship and the applicant's capacity to repay the debt, and, as I have said, those matters were addressed by the Tribunal member.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Centrelink (2003) 53 ATR 270</tocase>
<text>26 The applicant's first submission is that the Tribunal member applied too stringent a test as to what might constitute special circumstances within s 1237AAD(b). He submits that the Tribunal member said that to constitute special circumstances the circumstances must be 'unusual uncommon and exceptional'. The applicant submits that that was the test formulated by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (supra) but it was not the test approved on appeal by the Full Court of this Court: Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. Nor, submits the applicant, is the test consistent with other authority of this Court including Dranichnikov v Centrelink (2003) 53 ATR 270 and Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2005] FCA 866. The applicant submits that the correct test as to what constitutes special circumstances is whether the circumstances take the case out of the ordinary.

29 In Dranichnikov v Centrelink (supra) the Full Court, in considering a similar statutory provision to s 1237AAB said (at [65] and [66]):
 
 
 '65. The decision maker clearly also determined that the circumstances were such that they were not exceptional or unusual so that waiver could not be made as a matter of discretion under s 101. That equates "special circumstances", as that expression is used in the Administration Act with either exceptional circumstances or unusual circumstances. The origin of the test apparently adopted by the Secretary appears to be the decision of the first instance Judge in Beadle v Directory-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. That was a decision under previous legislation, the history of which is referred to by French J in Secretary of Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154. The Full Court in Beadle comprising Bowen CJ, Fisher and Lockhart JJ, however, was of the view that it was not possible to lay down precise rules as to what constituted special circumstances under the then s 102(1)(a) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth). Their Honours point out that the question whether there were special circumstances was one for the decision maker (in that case the Director-General) bearing in mind the purpose for which the power was given. The reference to the first instance decision from which the words "unusual, uncommon or exceptional" come was not actually affirmed by the Full Court. 
 66. To some extent the question whether there were special circumstances must depend on how it came about that the error occurred. Again that is not a matter to which the decision maker apparently averted. Other cases which have considered analogous words such as "special reasons" has tended to conclude, albeit in different contexts, that what is required will be circumstances which distinguish the case in consideration from the usual case. There will be a requirement that the circumstances are such that takes the case out of the ordinary: Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 and the cases in various contexts in the decision which Lockhart, Shepherd and Burchett JJ discuss.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541</tocase>
<text>20 The Tribunal member referred to a number of cases which have considered the meaning of 'special circumstances'. He referred to the decision of the Tribunal in Re Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 where it was said that the circumstances must be unusual, uncommon or exceptional, and the reasons for judgment of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541 where her Honour referred to a circumstance taking the case out of the usual or ordinary case. The Tribunal member also referred to observations of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31 and of French J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra). I will discuss the relevant authorities later in these reasons.

34 It is true that in expressing his conclusions the Tribunal member said that there was nothing unusual, uncommon or exceptional about the applicant's case. However, his reasons must be read as a whole and when that is done I do not think that he applied too demanding a test. The first point to note is that contrary to the applicant's submission he did not apply a test of 'unusual, uncommon and exceptional' as distinct from 'unusual, uncommon or exceptional' as submitted by the applicant. Secondly, he referred to the following remarks of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (supra) as to the meaning of the phrase 'special circumstances':
 
 '... would require something to distinguish Mr Groth's case from others, to take it out of the usual or ordinary case. ... It would of course follow that if one were to conclude that something unfair, unintended or unjust had occurred that there must be some feature out of the ordinary. ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Giumelli v Giumelli [1999] HCA 10 ; (1999) 196 CLR 101</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/10.html</AustLII>
<text>44 On appeal, counsel for the applicant referred me to cases such as Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1988) 164 CLR 387, Giumelli v Giumelli [1999] HCA 10 ; (1999) 196 CLR 101 and Plimmer v Wellington Corporation (1884) 9 App Cases 699, and submitted that the Tribunal member should have found that the applicant had no beneficial interest in the Torrensville property, or at least no interest that could be realised in the foreseeable future. In the context of the applicant's preservation benefits, counsel for the applicant made submissions as to the effect of provisions of the Superannuation Industry (Supervision) Act 1993 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>29 In Dranichnikov v Centrelink (supra) the Full Court, in considering a similar statutory provision to s 1237AAB said (at [65] and [66]):
 
 
 '65. The decision maker clearly also determined that the circumstances were such that they were not exceptional or unusual so that waiver could not be made as a matter of discretion under s 101. That equates "special circumstances", as that expression is used in the Administration Act with either exceptional circumstances or unusual circumstances. The origin of the test apparently adopted by the Secretary appears to be the decision of the first instance Judge in Beadle v Directory-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. That was a decision under previous legislation, the history of which is referred to by French J in Secretary of Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154. The Full Court in Beadle comprising Bowen CJ, Fisher and Lockhart JJ, however, was of the view that it was not possible to lay down precise rules as to what constituted special circumstances under the then s 102(1)(a) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth). Their Honours point out that the question whether there were special circumstances was one for the decision maker (in that case the Director-General) bearing in mind the purpose for which the power was given. The reference to the first instance decision from which the words "unusual, uncommon or exceptional" come was not actually affirmed by the Full Court. 
 66. To some extent the question whether there were special circumstances must depend on how it came about that the error occurred. Again that is not a matter to which the decision maker apparently averted. Other cases which have considered analogous words such as "special reasons" has tended to conclude, albeit in different contexts, that what is required will be circumstances which distinguish the case in consideration from the usual case. There will be a requirement that the circumstances are such that takes the case out of the ordinary: Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 and the cases in various contexts in the decision which Lockhart, Shepherd and Burchett JJ discuss.'

32 In Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services (supra) Branson J considered the provisions of s 1237AAD and in particular whether the Tribunal in that case had erred in concluding that special circumstances meant circumstances which were 'unusual, uncommon or exceptional'. Her Honour referred to the first passage from the reasons for judgment of the Full Court in Beadle set out in [28] above. She also referred to the following passage in Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 (at 195):
 
 'What is needed to justify an extension of time is indicated in r 15(2) by the words "for special reasons". It is that there be shown a special reason why the appeal should be permitted to proceed, though filed after the expiry of twenty-one days. In that context, the expression "special reasons" is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is twenty-one days. But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will, for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in the particular case. Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary. We do not think the use of the expression "for special reasons" implies something narrower than this.' 
 

Although those observations were made in the context of the expression 'for special reasons' in the rules of Court, her Honour considered they were of assistance in the interpretation of the expression 'special circumstances'.
 
Her Honour then said (at [25] and [26]):
 
 In my view, the Tribunal probably overstated the significance of the requirement in s 1237AAD(b) for " special circumstances ". The Full Court in Beadle did not endorse the view expressed by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 at 3 that circumstances are special only if they are " unusual, uncommon or exceptional" . 
 However, the Tribunal concluded that the applicant's circumstances " do not differ from those of many income support recipients" . In the context in which the Tribunal reached this conclusion, it is to be understood as having made a judgment that neither hardship nor unfairness made it desirable to waive all or part of the applicant's debt because the applicant's circumstances were common-place rather than special. While, as French J pointed out in Hales , the evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of circumstances which could give rise to hardship or unfairness, the statutory requirement for " special circumstances " discloses an intention to proscribe waiver in ordinary cases. The hardship or unfairness to which French J referred must be understood to be hardship or unfairness sufficient to justify departure from the general rule in the particular case.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lipkin Gorman (a firm) v Karpnale Ltd [1988] UKHL 12 ; [1991] 2 AC 548</tocase>
<text>48 The applicant's third submission is that the Tribunal member failed to take into account a relevant consideration, namely, that the applicant had changed his position as a result of the respondent's error. The applicant referred to cases dealing with the recovery of money paid to a person by mistake ( Lipkin Gorman (a firm) v Karpnale Ltd [1988] UKHL 12 ; [1991] 2 AC 548; David Securities Pty Ltd v Commonwealth Bank of Australia Ltd [1992] HCA 48 ; (1992) 175 CLR 353). I reject the applicant's submission. The Tribunal member was not obliged to approach the matter in this way. He clearly took into account the respondent's error and the nature of the error. He took into account the financial hardship the applicant might suffer if required to repay the debt. I do not think the fact that the applicant might have spent the moneys which are the subject of the debt on ordinary living expenses is of any particular significance. The significant matter was financial hardship and the applicant's capacity to repay the debt, and, as I have said, those matters were addressed by the Tribunal member.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Plimmer v Wellington Corporation (1884) 9 App Cases 699</tocase>
<text>44 On appeal, counsel for the applicant referred me to cases such as Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1988) 164 CLR 387, Giumelli v Giumelli [1999] HCA 10 ; (1999) 196 CLR 101 and Plimmer v Wellington Corporation (1884) 9 App Cases 699, and submitted that the Tribunal member should have found that the applicant had no beneficial interest in the Torrensville property, or at least no interest that could be realised in the foreseeable future. In the context of the applicant's preservation benefits, counsel for the applicant made submissions as to the effect of provisions of the Superannuation Industry (Supervision) Act 1993 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31</tocase>
<text>20 The Tribunal member referred to a number of cases which have considered the meaning of 'special circumstances'. He referred to the decision of the Tribunal in Re Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 where it was said that the circumstances must be unusual, uncommon or exceptional, and the reasons for judgment of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541 where her Honour referred to a circumstance taking the case out of the usual or ordinary case. The Tribunal member also referred to observations of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31 and of French J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra). I will discuss the relevant authorities later in these reasons.

35 Furthermore, the Tribunal member referred to the following remarks of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (supra) (at 38):
 
 'Each particular case must be considered on its merits. It is the essential nature of the provision to create a broad discretion to meet the great variety of circumstances which must occur, raising considerations of individual hardship, need, fairness, reasonableness, and whatever else may move an administrator, keeping in mind the scope and purposes of the Act, to make a decision one way or the other.'

36 There is nothing in the reasons of the Tribunal member to suggest that he did not think it appropriate to apply those remarks to the task he was required to undertake. Thirdly, this is not a case where the facts suggested that a precise formulation of the test was necessary or likely to be decisive. It seems to me to be implicit at the very least that the Tribunal member did not consider that there were any features which meant that the case was unusual or out of the ordinary.

37 I reject the applicant's first submission.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2005] FCA 866</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/866.html</AustLII>
<text>26 The applicant's first submission is that the Tribunal member applied too stringent a test as to what might constitute special circumstances within s 1237AAD(b). He submits that the Tribunal member said that to constitute special circumstances the circumstances must be 'unusual uncommon and exceptional'. The applicant submits that that was the test formulated by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (supra) but it was not the test approved on appeal by the Full Court of this Court: Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. Nor, submits the applicant, is the test consistent with other authority of this Court including Dranichnikov v Centrelink (2003) 53 ATR 270 and Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2005] FCA 866. The applicant submits that the correct test as to what constitutes special circumstances is whether the circumstances take the case out of the ordinary.

32 In Ryde v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services (supra) Branson J considered the provisions of s 1237AAD and in particular whether the Tribunal in that case had erred in concluding that special circumstances meant circumstances which were 'unusual, uncommon or exceptional'. Her Honour referred to the first passage from the reasons for judgment of the Full Court in Beadle set out in [28] above. She also referred to the following passage in Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 (at 195):
 
 'What is needed to justify an extension of time is indicated in r 15(2) by the words "for special reasons". It is that there be shown a special reason why the appeal should be permitted to proceed, though filed after the expiry of twenty-one days. In that context, the expression "special reasons" is intended to distinguish the case from the usual course according to which the time is twenty-one days. But it may be so distinguished (not necessarily will, for the rule gives a discretion) wherever the Court sees a ground which does justify departure from the general rule in the particular case. Such a ground is a special reason because it takes the case out of the ordinary. We do not think the use of the expression "for special reasons" implies something narrower than this.' 
 

Although those observations were made in the context of the expression 'for special reasons' in the rules of Court, her Honour considered they were of assistance in the interpretation of the expression 'special circumstances'.
 
Her Honour then said (at [25] and [26]):
 
 In my view, the Tribunal probably overstated the significance of the requirement in s 1237AAD(b) for " special circumstances ". The Full Court in Beadle did not endorse the view expressed by the Tribunal in Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 at 3 that circumstances are special only if they are " unusual, uncommon or exceptional" . 
 However, the Tribunal concluded that the applicant's circumstances " do not differ from those of many income support recipients" . In the context in which the Tribunal reached this conclusion, it is to be understood as having made a judgment that neither hardship nor unfairness made it desirable to waive all or part of the applicant's debt because the applicant's circumstances were common-place rather than special. While, as French J pointed out in Hales , the evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of circumstances which could give rise to hardship or unfairness, the statutory requirement for " special circumstances " discloses an intention to proscribe waiver in ordinary cases. The hardship or unfairness to which French J referred must be understood to be hardship or unfairness sufficient to justify departure from the general rule in the particular case.'

34 It is true that in expressing his conclusions the Tribunal member said that there was nothing unusual, uncommon or exceptional about the applicant's case. However, his reasons must be read as a whole and when that is done I do not think that he applied too demanding a test. The first point to note is that contrary to the applicant's submission he did not apply a test of 'unusual, uncommon and exceptional' as distinct from 'unusual, uncommon or exceptional' as submitted by the applicant. Secondly, he referred to the following remarks of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (supra) as to the meaning of the phrase 'special circumstances':
 
 '... would require something to distinguish Mr Groth's case from others, to take it out of the usual or ordinary case. ... It would of course follow that if one were to conclude that something unfair, unintended or unjust had occurred that there must be some feature out of the ordinary. ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154</tocase>
<text>5 The Tribunal member made no express finding in terms of s 1237AAD(c). He did find that the debt was not capable of being written off under s 1236(1) and (1A) of the Act and there is no challenge to that conclusion. It is not a pre-requisite to the satisfaction of the matter in s 1237AAD(c) that it be appropriate to write off the debt: Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154 at 163-164 per French J.

6 As I have said, the focus of the applicant's challenge on the appeal was to the Tribunal member's approach and findings with respect to the question of special circumstances. In particular, he submits:
 
 1. That the Tribunal member misconstrued the term 'special circumstances' in s 1237AAD(b) and failed to apply the correct legal test;
 2. In considering whether there were special circumstances, the Tribunal member took into account an irrelevant matter, being the applicant's entitlement to certain assets; and
 3. In considering whether there were special circumstances, the Tribunal member failed to take into account a relevant matter, namely, that the applicant had changed his position by spending the overpayment which had been caused, primarily at least, by an error of the respondent.

7 The following facts are taken from the reasons of the Tribunal member and are not in dispute.

20 The Tribunal member referred to a number of cases which have considered the meaning of 'special circumstances'. He referred to the decision of the Tribunal in Re Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1 where it was said that the circumstances must be unusual, uncommon or exceptional, and the reasons for judgment of Kiefel J in Groth v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1995) 40 ALD 541 where her Honour referred to a circumstance taking the case out of the usual or ordinary case. The Tribunal member also referred to observations of the Full Court of this Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1993) 30 ALD 31 and of French J in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra). I will discuss the relevant authorities later in these reasons.

29 In Dranichnikov v Centrelink (supra) the Full Court, in considering a similar statutory provision to s 1237AAB said (at [65] and [66]):
 
 
 '65. The decision maker clearly also determined that the circumstances were such that they were not exceptional or unusual so that waiver could not be made as a matter of discretion under s 101. That equates "special circumstances", as that expression is used in the Administration Act with either exceptional circumstances or unusual circumstances. The origin of the test apparently adopted by the Secretary appears to be the decision of the first instance Judge in Beadle v Directory-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225. That was a decision under previous legislation, the history of which is referred to by French J in Secretary of Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154. The Full Court in Beadle comprising Bowen CJ, Fisher and Lockhart JJ, however, was of the view that it was not possible to lay down precise rules as to what constituted special circumstances under the then s 102(1)(a) of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth). Their Honours point out that the question whether there were special circumstances was one for the decision maker (in that case the Director-General) bearing in mind the purpose for which the power was given. The reference to the first instance decision from which the words "unusual, uncommon or exceptional" come was not actually affirmed by the Full Court. 
 66. To some extent the question whether there were special circumstances must depend on how it came about that the error occurred. Again that is not a matter to which the decision maker apparently averted. Other cases which have considered analogous words such as "special reasons" has tended to conclude, albeit in different contexts, that what is required will be circumstances which distinguish the case in consideration from the usual case. There will be a requirement that the circumstances are such that takes the case out of the ordinary: Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 and the cases in various contexts in the decision which Lockhart, Shepherd and Burchett JJ discuss.'

30 In Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (supra) French J considered the provisions of s 1237AAD. One particular argument his Honour was required to consider was whether the reference in s 1237AAD(b) to 'other than financial hardship alone' meant that there must be financial hardship before a finding of special circumstances can be made. His Honour rejected that argument and in the course of doing so made some general observations as to the concept of special circumstances. His Honour said (at 162):
 
 'The concept of special circumstances is broad. A constellation of factors, including financial circumstances, may fall within it. The express exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance is an indicator that it would otherwise be included. This gives some measure of the range of circumstances which will qualify as special. But as a matter of grammar and ordinary logic, the exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance does not mandate its inclusion in the range of matters constituting such circumstances for the purpose of enlivening the Secretary's discretion. 
 ... 
 The evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of situations which could give rise to hardship or unfairness in the event of a rigid application of a requirement for recovery of debt. It is inappropriate to constrain that flexibility by imposing a narrow or artificial construction upon the words. It may be that there will be few cases in which the Secretary will be satisfied that there are special circumstances in the absence of financial hardship. It may be that there are few cases in which having found special circumstances to exist, the Secretary would exercise the discretion to waive in the absence of financial hardship. But to anticipate the limits of the categories of possible cases by imposing on the language of the section a fetter upon its application which is not mandated by its words, is to erode its useful purpose.'

31 French J also made the point that the Secretary has a discretion even if the three conditions in s 1237AAD are satisfied. In other words, the Secretary is not obliged to waive the debt even if the three conditions are satisfied.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>TNT Skypak International (Aust) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1988) 19 ATR 1067</tocase>
<text>42 The applicant's second submission was put in terms of the Tribunal taking into account irrelevant considerations, namely, the applicant's interest in the Torrensville property and his interest in the preserved superannuation benefits. As I have said, the applicant submits that he has no interest in the Torrensville property or, in the alternative, no immediately realisable interest in the property and no immediately realisable interest in the preserved superannuation benefits. On the face of it, those issues are issues of fact. If there were incorrect findings of fact with respect to those issues, those findings of fact would not be overturned so as to expose a question of law. The appeal to this Court is limited to an appeal on a question of law and there is no right of appeal if a question of law is only exposed if findings of fact are overturned: Copperart Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1993) 26 ATR 327. Furthermore, even if a question of law is exposed, this Court does not then have a mandate to review the decision generally: TNT Skypak International (Aust) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1988) 19 ATR 1067.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1988) 164 CLR 387</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/7.html</AustLII>
<text>44 On appeal, counsel for the applicant referred me to cases such as Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1988) 164 CLR 387, Giumelli v Giumelli [1999] HCA 10 ; (1999) 196 CLR 101 and Plimmer v Wellington Corporation (1884) 9 App Cases 699, and submitted that the Tribunal member should have found that the applicant had no beneficial interest in the Torrensville property, or at least no interest that could be realised in the foreseeable future. In the context of the applicant's preservation benefits, counsel for the applicant made submissions as to the effect of provisions of the Superannuation Industry (Supervision) Act 1993 (Cth).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>