<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Clough v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [No 3] (includes corrigendum dated 19 February 2008) [2007] FCA 2082 (21 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2082.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert (2005) 223 ALR 467</tocase>
<text>The Banks are respondents and potentially liable in their own right. ONGC is not a necessary party to the claim against them. It is not necessary for Clough to join ONGC in order to establish its claims against the Banks : Matheson Engineers Pty Limited v El Raghy [1992] FCA 417 ; (1992) 37 FCR 6 at 9; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert (2005) 223 ALR 467 at [34]. Of course ONGC, whilst not a necessary party, is amenable as a "proper" party to be joined if in the jurisdiction. A "proper", as distinct from a "necessary" party, is a person who has sufficient connexion to the controversy that he or she might be joined, "but whose absence will not affect the constitution of the action": Edge, in the matter of Eco Panels Australasia Pty Ltd (in liq) [2007] FCA 30 at [12] . As a person who would be a proper party if it were in the jurisdiction, ONGC would be thus amenable to the courts jurisdiction under FCR O 8 r 2, Item 18 (like the former FCR O 8 r 1(g)): Quinlan v Safe International F&ouml;rs&auml;krings AB [2005] FCA 1362 at [24] , applying Costa Vraca Pty Ltd v Bell Regal Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd (2002) 117 FCR 301</tocase>
<text>As to this, it should be recognised that equity will generally intervene to ameliorate the application of a legal right if it is employed capriciously or unreasonably or harshly, or oppressively such as to be unconscionable: Pierce Bell Sales Pty Ltd v Frazer [1973] HCA 13 ; (1973) 130 CLR 575 at 587-588 and 590-591; NC Seddon &amp; MP Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Aust. ed) (2002), [20.9]. This doctrine, although distinct from, is very similar to, the implied contractual duty of good faith: Walker v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (2001) 39 ACSR 557 , [93]-[96], esp. [96]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd (2002) 117 FCR 301. Section 51AA of the TPA likewise may afford relevant protection. This however does not mean that the entitlement at law to call on the whole amount under the performance guarantees should be read down from what is otherwise a construction which is in harmony with the contract as a whole and which in its context produces a commercially sensible meaning. Furthermore, to the extent that the calling up of the performance guarantees resulted in an overpayment to ONGC then there would be an entitlement in Clough to an 'accounting' in due course from ONGC: Cargill International SA Antigua Geneva Branch v Bangladesh Sugar &amp; Food Industries Corporation [1996] 4 All ER 563 at 571.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Bachmann Pty Ltd v B.H.P Power New Zealand Ltd [1998] VSCA 40 ; [1999] 1 VR 420</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSCA/1998/40.html</AustLII>
<text>Bachmann Pty Ltd v B.H.P Power New Zealand Ltd [1998] VSCA 40 ; [1999] 1 VR 420 involved consideration of a letter of credit. The supplier in Bachmann did not seek to establish any case of fraud on the purchaser's part but relied only on the contractual qualification upon the purchaser's powers under the general conditions of the underlying contract to demand payment under the letter of credit. It was conceded that the clause referred to constituted a contractual qualification on the purchaser's powers in relation to the security. This is to be contrasted with earlier Australian cases where the initial question was whether the underlying contract, on its proper construction, qualified the security holder's powers to claim under the security. The only point in the appeal as his Honour put it was as to the content of the qualification at [30].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bray v F Hoffman-La Roche Ltd (2003) 130 FCR 317</tocase>
<text>In relation to the application to set aside service of the Amended Application on ONGC, an application under O 9 r 7 of the Federal Court Rules (FCR) results in a review of the original decision to grant leave to serve ex juris and is a rehearing conducted on the basis of additional materials, recognising that a respondent should have "the opportunity to put before the Court any additional facts or arguments which might suggest that leave ought not to have been granted": Tycoon Holdings Limited v Trencor Jetco Inc [1992] FCA 25 ; (1992) 34 FCR 31 at 33; Bray v F Hoffmann-La Roche Limited (2003) 130 FCR 317 at [53] per Carr J. The onus remains on the applicant to satisfy the Court, in light of those additional materials and facts and arguments, that leave should have been granted: Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Proprietary Limited [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 564.

The task of the Court, at this early stage of the proceedings, does not require evidence to justify a "finding" of the alleged TPA contravention: Bray v F Hoffman-La Roche Ltd at [96].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cargill International SA Antigua Geneva Branch v Bangladesh Sugar &amp; Food Industries Corporation [1996] 4 All ER 563</tocase>
<text>As to this, it should be recognised that equity will generally intervene to ameliorate the application of a legal right if it is employed capriciously or unreasonably or harshly, or oppressively such as to be unconscionable: Pierce Bell Sales Pty Ltd v Frazer [1973] HCA 13 ; (1973) 130 CLR 575 at 587-588 and 590-591; NC Seddon &amp; MP Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Aust. ed) (2002), [20.9]. This doctrine, although distinct from, is very similar to, the implied contractual duty of good faith: Walker v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (2001) 39 ACSR 557 , [93]-[96], esp. [96]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd (2002) 117 FCR 301. Section 51AA of the TPA likewise may afford relevant protection. This however does not mean that the entitlement at law to call on the whole amount under the performance guarantees should be read down from what is otherwise a construction which is in harmony with the contract as a whole and which in its context produces a commercially sensible meaning. Furthermore, to the extent that the calling up of the performance guarantees resulted in an overpayment to ONGC then there would be an entitlement in Clough to an 'accounting' in due course from ONGC: Cargill International SA Antigua Geneva Branch v Bangladesh Sugar &amp; Food Industries Corporation [1996] 4 All ER 563 at 571.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd (No. 2) [2007] FCA 927</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/927.html</AustLII>
<text>Clough's claims against the Banks concern their intention to pay under the performance guarantees where such payment would constitute the Bank's being, directly or indirectly, knowingly concerned in ONGC's contraventions of the TPA. Injunctive relief is available against the Banks under s 80 of the TPA: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd (No. 2) [2007] FCA 927 at [11] - [14] . Injunctive and other relief would also be available under s 87(1A) of the TPA.

The orders, including injunctive orders, previously obtained by Clough against ONGC were obtained on an ex parte basis, and supported by affidavit material which was uncontested. ONGC had not entered an appearance at that time. Only ONGC could contradict Clough's case that Clough was not in breach of the Construction Contract, or where it was in breach, that this was occasioned by ONGC's breach. Accordingly, the claim by Clough, that ONGC was in contravention of s 51AA of the TPA, proceeded on the basis of unchallenged fact, namely, that ONGC had called for payment under the performance guarantees when there was no proper foundation for doing so, because Clough was not in breach of the Construction Contract or if it was, then this was as a direct consequence of breaches by ONGC: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd (No. 2) at [7] and [39].

It was not necessary, then, to consider the question of whether a call by ONGC under the performance guarantees could be made merely upon the basis of a bona fide claim of breach or whether it required, by admission or by curial or arbitral determination, a demonstrated actual breach. This was because, whatever the proper construction of cl 3.3.3, on the uncontroverted facts, a prima facie case, or serious issue that s 51AA had been contravened was made out. Accordingly, I expressly left that question open: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd (No. 2) at [45]. For the first time in these proceedings, the question of construction requires to be considered. It is fundamental to the disposition of the Motion.

In the reasons for judgment in Clough Engineering Limited v Oil and Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [No 2] [2007] FCA 927 at [46] - [66] , I concluded that the balance of convenience strongly favoured the grant of injunctive relief. As I have said, ONGC, although a party, had not then appeared. This, importantly, meant that there was no party to contradict the existence of serious issues to be tried, as contended for by Clough. I formed the view that to have discharged the injunctions could very well lead to irreparable harm to Clough, its shareholders, employees and third parties. I concluded that damages would not be an adequate remedy. [66]

The position has now changed. ONGC has appeared, put on evidence, cross-examined and advanced submissions through counsel. Clough's financial circumstances have also changed.

The changed position is disclosed by a further affidavit of Mr Simons sworn on 7 September 2007. The expression "G1 contract" as used in this affidavit is a reference to the Construction Contract. It is to the following effect: 
 
 (a) Clough's annual results for the financial year ended 30 June 2007 reported an audited loss of $105.3 million, which ' loss directly resulted from provisions taken on the BassGas and G1 contracts ', such that Clough is materially in default of its secured debt facilities with the Banks [3]-[5]; 
 

 
 
 (b) each of the Banks want Clough to repay all secured debt facilities and because of Clough's defaults and because of the legal action threatened by ONGC, the Banks will not allow the use of current facilities or extend any further facilities to Clough ' until such time as the injunction and the related matters are dissolved or otherwise dispensed with ' [6], such that Clough will not have sufficient available debt facilities to fund the encashment of the performance guarantees [7]; 
 

 
 
 (c) the announced capital raising ' will provide new liquidity to replace the cash that has been utilised in funding the costs on the G1 contract which have not been reimbursed or paid to Clough by ONGC ' [10]; 
 

 
 
 (d) Clough has paid creditors of US$167.4 million on the G1 contract, but has received payments from ONGC of only US$139.4 million, a cash short fall of US$28 million [11], and Clough still owed some A$52.4 million to creditors on the G1 contract [13]; 
 

 
 
 (e) between 1 July 2007 and 4 September 2007, Clough has paid G1 contract creditors about A$31.2 million, leaving a balance of A$21.2 million, which will need to be paid from cash flow [14]; 
 

 
 
 (f) the payments to G1 contract creditors is causing significant strain [15]; 
 

 
 
 (g) to replace Clough's cash deposits that have been depleted by reason of the G1 contract, Clough proposes to recapitalise to enable it to make payments to the remaining G1 contract creditors and fund its capital expansion [16]; 
 

 
 
 (h) the recapitalisation is not directed to funding the encashment of the performance guarantees but is for paying the G1 creditors, funding capital expansion and repaying the Banks [17] and, importantly, if the performance guarantees were paid, Clough would be prevented from some or all of these objectives, with the consequences described in Mr Simons' 28 May 2007 affidavit [18]; 
 

 
 
 (i) the proposed recapitalisation will not be completed until the end of December 2007 and is dependent upon shareholder approval [19]-[20].

Against that, in cross-examination, Mr Simons conceded that Clough's capital expansion program will be secured by the Murray and Roberts funding and the recapitalisation and that there will be no need to retrench staff. This is a very different position to that which existed at the time that I refused the application of the Banks to discharge the injunction: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [No 2] [2007] FCA 927 at [54] - [63] . There is no evidence to establish specific irreparable damage to Clough. Consequences of the kind that I have referred to are not uncommon in such matters and indeed are often the probable consequences. Certainly, Mr Simons accepted that such consequences, broadly, were in the anticipation of Clough when the performance guarantees were given.

I have also considered Clough's claims that payment under the performance guarantees will adversely affect its commercial reputation. As to that I accept the submissions of ONGC which derive their factual foundation from the second affidavit of Mr Simons, his cross-examination and various media reports admitted into evidence.

The market knows of Clough's dispute with ONGC, and it has been the subject of public disclosure to the ASX by Clough. Clough's Board has told the market that it considers the claims to be "spurious" and uses public relations to protect its position.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [2007] FCA 881</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/881.html</AustLII>
<text>To maintain service ex juris , Clough needs to demonstrate a prima facie case for the relief claimed: FCR O 8, r 3(2)(c). The threshold for demonstrating a prima facie case is not high. It is whether on the material before the Court, inferences are open which, if translated into findings of fact, would support the relief claimed: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [2007] FCA 881 at [36] ; Western Australian v Vetter Tritter (1991) 30 FCR 102 at 110; Puccini Festival Australia Pty Ltd v Nippon Express (Australia) Pty Ltd [2007] VSC 288. It requires the demonstration of an "arguable case", bearing in mind that this requirement is to be met at the outset of the action, "without the advantage of discovery and other procedural aids to the making out of a case": Ho v Akai Pty Limited (in liquidation) [2006] FCAFC 159 at [10] , [12], [37], [43].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Costa Vraca Pty Ltd v Bell Regal Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 305</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/305.html</AustLII>
<text>The Banks are respondents and potentially liable in their own right. ONGC is not a necessary party to the claim against them. It is not necessary for Clough to join ONGC in order to establish its claims against the Banks : Matheson Engineers Pty Limited v El Raghy [1992] FCA 417 ; (1992) 37 FCR 6 at 9; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert (2005) 223 ALR 467 at [34]. Of course ONGC, whilst not a necessary party, is amenable as a "proper" party to be joined if in the jurisdiction. A "proper", as distinct from a "necessary" party, is a person who has sufficient connexion to the controversy that he or she might be joined, "but whose absence will not affect the constitution of the action": Edge, in the matter of Eco Panels Australasia Pty Ltd (in liq) [2007] FCA 30 at [12] . As a person who would be a proper party if it were in the jurisdiction, ONGC would be thus amenable to the courts jurisdiction under FCR O 8 r 2, Item 18 (like the former FCR O 8 r 1(g)): Quinlan v Safe International F&ouml;rs&auml;krings AB [2005] FCA 1362 at [24] , applying Costa Vraca Pty Ltd v Bell Regal Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Fletcher Construction Australia Ltd v Varnsdorf Pty Ltd (1998) 3 VR 812</tocase>
<text>Secondly, one consideration that might be brought to bear in deciding whether a claimed or asserted entitlement to payment is intended to be sufficient, is where the claimed or asserted entitlement is made in the context of an independent party having first certified that a certain state of affairs exists. Where the parties have entrusted, by agreement, an independent person with the task of being satisfied and certifying that a certain state of affairs exists, and the contract then provides for the payment of money if that state of affairs exists, a claimed entitlement to payment may be inferred to be sufficient: Fletcher Construction Australia Ltd v Varnsdorf Pty Ltd (1998) 3 VR 812 at 822. It would be unusual, it was said, for an entitlement, particularly for A$25 million, to arise on mere assertion of breach, unconnected with some specific independent certification process, subject to one matter, discussed below.

Thirdly, another consideration is that if the contract provides, expressly, for a right to deduct certain moneys, i.e. a right of self-help, it may be inferred that those particular moneys may be payable on an asserted or claimed entitlement: Fletcher v Varnsdorf at 822. There are, in this contract, specific provisions giving ONGC the right to deduct moneys in the period prior to practical completion. They are found in cll 5.9.7.2 and 7.3.9. Notwithstanding the absence of a certification provision, and the onerous terms of cl 5.9.7.2, it may be inferred that the parties intended Clough to pay those amounts on assertion of breach, and for the performance guarantees to be called for that purpose, leaving Clough out of pocket whilst it fought out any dispute about that in an arbitration.

Fourthly, in the period after practical completion, a specific provision, similar to cl 5.9.7.2, also requires Clough to pay moneys to ONGC irrespective, it seems, of any dispute as to the validity of ONGC's claim. This is cl 6.1.2. Again, the provision is onerous in that it purports to require Clough to pay costs associated with reinstatement of the works simply upon a complaint of non-conformity by ONGC. Again, that clause gives ONGC a right to deduct moneys, irrespective of the pendency of any unresolved dispute (by arbitration or otherwise), concerning ONGC's claims that the works are non-conforming. Again, the guarantees are likely to have been intended by the parties to operate on the strength of a claimed entitlement in this circumstance.

Fifthly, cl 6.3.2 is another provision which gives a right to deduct. In the present circumstances, because there has been no agreed extended date for practical completion, it applies where there is an agreement or arbitral or other determination that ONGC has a right to recover liquidated damages.

Sixthly, the magnitude of the guarantees, totalling A$25 million, needs to be considered in the context of a construction which requires that any asserted breach, however trivial, or ephemeral, could see the contractor deprived of A$25 million working capital. That, it is said, would be a peculiar result.

Seventhly, bearing in mind the above considerations, cl 3.3.3 operates to allocate risk to Clough in specified circumstances, and otherwise provides ONGC with substantial security by way of recourse to the Banks, in the event that Clough is slow to, or is unable or unwilling, to pay ONGC, where ONGC has established that Clough has failed to honour its commitments under the contract.

Accordingly, the demands in this case are equivalent to the certificate provided by the National Australia Bank (NAB) to HSBC, certifying in effect that the conditions of the letter of credit had been met: Ideas Plus Investments Ltd v National Australia Bank Ltd (2006) 32 WAR 467 at [14]. The Western Australian Court of Appeal held that the certificate "amounted to no more than an implied representation that it had reasonable grounds for issuing the certificate" at [51]. The reasonable grounds were the bona fide belief by NAB that the conditions were satisfied at [55]. The written demands are also analogous to the requisite statutory declaration in Fletcher Construction v Varnsdorf at p 830 to the effect that the amount claimed represented an amount(s) remaining unpaid to the owner. This was so even where the amount was disputed by the contractor.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hitchcock v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2000] Aust Torts Reports p81-550</tocase>
<text>It is appropriate, in my view, to seek to resolve the construction issue, despite the interlocutory nature of the motion. The hearing engaged some three days. Full argument was presented on the issue by both sides. There was no suggestion that the evidence before me, bearing on the construction issue, was other than complete. The area of contest is neither beset by difficulty or novelty: Kolback Securities Ltd v Epoch Mining NL (1987) 8 NSWLR 533 at 535; Hitchcock v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2000] Aust Torts Reports p81-550 at [22]-[26].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ho v Akai Pty Limited (in liquidation) [2006] FCAFC 159</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/159.html</AustLII>
<text>To maintain service ex juris , Clough needs to demonstrate a prima facie case for the relief claimed: FCR O 8, r 3(2)(c). The threshold for demonstrating a prima facie case is not high. It is whether on the material before the Court, inferences are open which, if translated into findings of fact, would support the relief claimed: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [2007] FCA 881 at [36] ; Western Australian v Vetter Tritter (1991) 30 FCR 102 at 110; Puccini Festival Australia Pty Ltd v Nippon Express (Australia) Pty Ltd [2007] VSC 288. It requires the demonstration of an "arguable case", bearing in mind that this requirement is to be met at the outset of the action, "without the advantage of discovery and other procedural aids to the making out of a case": Ho v Akai Pty Limited (in liquidation) [2006] FCAFC 159 at [10] , [12], [37], [43].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hughes Bros Pty Ltd v Telede Pty Ltd (1989) 7 BCL 210</tocase>
<text>His Honour canvassed a number of cases in which the proper construction of the language contained in the standby letter of credit, "... until the party becomes entitled to exercise a right under the contract ..." had been similarly discussed. Those authorities range from requiring no more than a claimed entitlement which is not specious or fanciful: Hughes Bros Pty Ltd v Telede Pty Ltd (1989) 7 BCL 210 to requiring that the holder of the security establish, whether by litigation or arbitration, an actual entitlement to payment of the moneys: Mitsui Kensetsu Corporation Australia Pty Ltd v State of South Australia (unreported Qld Supreme Court, 9 August 1990 per Byrne J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Ideas Plus Investments Ltd v National Australia Bank Ltd (2006) 32 WAR 467</tocase>
<text>Accordingly, the demands in this case are equivalent to the certificate provided by the National Australia Bank (NAB) to HSBC, certifying in effect that the conditions of the letter of credit had been met: Ideas Plus Investments Ltd v National Australia Bank Ltd (2006) 32 WAR 467 at [14]. The Western Australian Court of Appeal held that the certificate "amounted to no more than an implied representation that it had reasonable grounds for issuing the certificate" at [51]. The reasonable grounds were the bona fide belief by NAB that the conditions were satisfied at [55]. The written demands are also analogous to the requisite statutory declaration in Fletcher Construction v Varnsdorf at p 830 to the effect that the amount claimed represented an amount(s) remaining unpaid to the owner. This was so even where the amount was disputed by the contractor.

If it were the case that, on its proper construction, ONGC could not call on the guarantees until there was an admitted or established breach of contract, the time at which an arbitral tribunal or court might determine that matter could well be after the performance guarantees had expired: cf Ideas Plus Investments at [39] per Steytler P. Such a construction does not, in my view, make commercial common sense: McCann v Switzerland Insurance Australia Limited (2000) 203 CLR 579 at [22] and [23] per Gleeson CJ.

In Ideas Plus Investments Steytler P, with whom McLure and Buss JJA agreed, concluded that the NAB was empowered to claim under a letter of credit granted by HSBC so long as it had a bona fide belief that the conditions were satisfied. The certificate by the NAB issued to HSBC certifying in effect that the conditions of the letter of credit had been met was only a representation of such a bona fide belief and perhaps that there were reasonable grounds for such a belief. [55]-[57], [105] See also Fletcher Construction v Varsdorf at p 830. Steytler P with whom McLure JA agreed held that the basis for the payment made by HSBC pursuant to its independent obligation to NAB under the letter of credit was the provision by NAB of a certificate in the required terms. It was, his Honour found, the presentation of that certificate, not the truth of the facts certified, which conditioned HSBC's obligation to pay.

The provision of cll 3.2.3-3.2.5 and 8.3.5 do not, in my view, assist the construction contended for by Clough. Those concern the contractual entitlement of ONGC to withhold approval and payment of progress claims. That entitlement provides a form of security to ONGC where there is a dispute because, pending arbitration, it is not required to pay the disputed amounts to Clough. It does not inform the question of the circumstances in which the performance guarantees may be called upon.

Nor do I consider that the absence of an independent certification as to the existence of a certain state of affairs to trigger the obligation to make payment advances Clough's argument on construction. That is but one type of mechanism for payment in a contract. Its absence does not assist the construction of this contract.

Performance guarantees play a critical part in international commerce and in international construction contracts, in particular. So much has been recognised by the courts on many occasions: the authorities are collected by Steytler P in Ideas Plus Investments at [32]-[34]. They were, objectively viewed, of critical importance to ONGC under the Construction Contract. This is manifest in two ways. Under cl 3.2.1 of the Construction Contract, no payments become due and payable to Clough until Clough has furnished the necessary performance guarantees and the Certificate of Insurance to ONGC. This would extend to performance guarantees whose validity was required to be extended under cl 3.3.2. Furthermore, as its option, ONGC was entitled, under cl 3.3.3, where Clough failed to furnish the performance guarantee(s) to terminate the Construction Contract.

Completion Date of the Works under the Construction Contract was 15 April 2006 (cll 2.2.5 and 6.3.1). The warranty period under the Construction Contract is 12 months from the date of issue of the Certificate of Completion and Acceptance (cl 6.1.1).

Any performance guarantee was to be initially valid up to 14 June 2007. This was by virtue of the provisions of cl 3.3.1, which provide for the period of validity to extend from the Completion Date, plus the warranty period and a further 60 days. Each performance guarantee is expressed to be valid until 14 June 2007. In the event that completion is delayed beyond the Scheduled Completion Date, Clough was liable to extend the validity of the performance guarantees accordingly, so as to maintain the same period of validity beyond that date.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Kolback Securities Ltd v Epoch Mining NL (1987) 8 NSWLR 533</tocase>
<text>It is appropriate, in my view, to seek to resolve the construction issue, despite the interlocutory nature of the motion. The hearing engaged some three days. Full argument was presented on the issue by both sides. There was no suggestion that the evidence before me, bearing on the construction issue, was other than complete. The area of contest is neither beset by difficulty or novelty: Kolback Securities Ltd v Epoch Mining NL (1987) 8 NSWLR 533 at 535; Hitchcock v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2000] Aust Torts Reports p81-550 at [22]-[26].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Matheson Engineers Pty Limited v El Raghy [1992] FCA 417 ; (1992) 37 FCR 6</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/417.html</AustLII>
<text>The Banks are respondents and potentially liable in their own right. ONGC is not a necessary party to the claim against them. It is not necessary for Clough to join ONGC in order to establish its claims against the Banks : Matheson Engineers Pty Limited v El Raghy [1992] FCA 417 ; (1992) 37 FCR 6 at 9; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert (2005) 223 ALR 467 at [34]. Of course ONGC, whilst not a necessary party, is amenable as a "proper" party to be joined if in the jurisdiction. A "proper", as distinct from a "necessary" party, is a person who has sufficient connexion to the controversy that he or she might be joined, "but whose absence will not affect the constitution of the action": Edge, in the matter of Eco Panels Australasia Pty Ltd (in liq) [2007] FCA 30 at [12] . As a person who would be a proper party if it were in the jurisdiction, ONGC would be thus amenable to the courts jurisdiction under FCR O 8 r 2, Item 18 (like the former FCR O 8 r 1(g)): Quinlan v Safe International F&ouml;rs&auml;krings AB [2005] FCA 1362 at [24] , applying Costa Vraca Pty Ltd v Bell Regal Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McCann v Switzerland Insurance Australia Limited (2000) 203 CLR 579</tocase>
<text>If it were the case that, on its proper construction, ONGC could not call on the guarantees until there was an admitted or established breach of contract, the time at which an arbitral tribunal or court might determine that matter could well be after the performance guarantees had expired: cf Ideas Plus Investments at [39] per Steytler P. Such a construction does not, in my view, make commercial common sense: McCann v Switzerland Insurance Australia Limited (2000) 203 CLR 579 at [22] and [23] per Gleeson CJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mitsui Kensetsu Corporation Australia Pty Ltd v State of South Australia (unreported Qld Supreme Court, 9 August 1990 per Byrne J)</tocase>
<text>His Honour canvassed a number of cases in which the proper construction of the language contained in the standby letter of credit, "... until the party becomes entitled to exercise a right under the contract ..." had been similarly discussed. Those authorities range from requiring no more than a claimed entitlement which is not specious or fanciful: Hughes Bros Pty Ltd v Telede Pty Ltd (1989) 7 BCL 210 to requiring that the holder of the security establish, whether by litigation or arbitration, an actual entitlement to payment of the moneys: Mitsui Kensetsu Corporation Australia Pty Ltd v State of South Australia (unreported Qld Supreme Court, 9 August 1990 per Byrne J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Perri v Coolangatta Investments Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 29 ; (1982) 149 CLR 537</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/29.html</AustLII>
<text>Accordingly, in my opinion, Clough was obliged under cl 3.3.2 of the Construction Contract to extend the validity of the performance guarantees so that they would be valid for 12 months plus 60 days from the date of completion of Works as varied. On the basis of the two variations to which I have referred, Clough, within a reasonable time of the date of each variation, was required to extend the performance guarantees to 31 March 2008 and June 30 2008 respectively. What is a reasonable time is a question of fact. It depends upon the circumstances and its limit is determined by what is fair to both parties: Perri v Coolangatta Investments Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 29 ; (1982) 149 CLR 537 at 567-568.

I do not accept Clough's submissions that the date for Practical Completion was at large and therefore that cl 3.3.2 could not be complied with because the duration of the extension was not clear.

Even if it were the case that cl 3.3.2 required Clough to extend the performance guarantees at any time prior to their lapsing, as Clough contends, it was clear as at: 
 (a) 16 April 2007 that Clough was not then prepared to extend the performance guarantees. In a letter to ONGC it advised ONGC that it required the three performance guarantees then held by ONGC to be returned and stated that it was willing to provide a performance bond to the value of 10% of the remaining work, in the amount of US$2.17 million; and 
 
 (b) 1 June 2007 that the CEO of Clough had no relevant authority from Clough's Board to extend these and in any event such authorisation was, wrongly in my view, stated by him to be subject to ONGC agreeing to "reach a negotiated exit solution". The obligation under cl 3.3.2 is not so conditioned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pierce Bell Sales Pty Ltd v Frazer [1973] HCA 13 ; (1973) 130 CLR 575</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1973/13.html</AustLII>
<text>As to this, it should be recognised that equity will generally intervene to ameliorate the application of a legal right if it is employed capriciously or unreasonably or harshly, or oppressively such as to be unconscionable: Pierce Bell Sales Pty Ltd v Frazer [1973] HCA 13 ; (1973) 130 CLR 575 at 587-588 and 590-591; NC Seddon &amp; MP Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Aust. ed) (2002), [20.9]. This doctrine, although distinct from, is very similar to, the implied contractual duty of good faith: Walker v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (2001) 39 ACSR 557 , [93]-[96], esp. [96]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd (2002) 117 FCR 301. Section 51AA of the TPA likewise may afford relevant protection. This however does not mean that the entitlement at law to call on the whole amount under the performance guarantees should be read down from what is otherwise a construction which is in harmony with the contract as a whole and which in its context produces a commercially sensible meaning. Furthermore, to the extent that the calling up of the performance guarantees resulted in an overpayment to ONGC then there would be an entitlement in Clough to an 'accounting' in due course from ONGC: Cargill International SA Antigua Geneva Branch v Bangladesh Sugar &amp; Food Industries Corporation [1996] 4 All ER 563 at 571.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Puccini Festival Australia Pty Ltd v Nippon Express (Australia) Pty Ltd [2007] VSC 288</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VICSC/2007/288.html</AustLII>
<text>To maintain service ex juris , Clough needs to demonstrate a prima facie case for the relief claimed: FCR O 8, r 3(2)(c). The threshold for demonstrating a prima facie case is not high. It is whether on the material before the Court, inferences are open which, if translated into findings of fact, would support the relief claimed: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [2007] FCA 881 at [36] ; Western Australian v Vetter Tritter (1991) 30 FCR 102 at 110; Puccini Festival Australia Pty Ltd v Nippon Express (Australia) Pty Ltd [2007] VSC 288. It requires the demonstration of an "arguable case", bearing in mind that this requirement is to be met at the outset of the action, "without the advantage of discovery and other procedural aids to the making out of a case": Ho v Akai Pty Limited (in liquidation) [2006] FCAFC 159 at [10] , [12], [37], [43].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Quinlan v Safe International Forsakrings AB [2005] FCA 1362</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1362.html</AustLII>
<text>The Banks are respondents and potentially liable in their own right. ONGC is not a necessary party to the claim against them. It is not necessary for Clough to join ONGC in order to establish its claims against the Banks : Matheson Engineers Pty Limited v El Raghy [1992] FCA 417 ; (1992) 37 FCR 6 at 9; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert (2005) 223 ALR 467 at [34]. Of course ONGC, whilst not a necessary party, is amenable as a "proper" party to be joined if in the jurisdiction. A "proper", as distinct from a "necessary" party, is a person who has sufficient connexion to the controversy that he or she might be joined, "but whose absence will not affect the constitution of the action": Edge, in the matter of Eco Panels Australasia Pty Ltd (in liq) [2007] FCA 30 at [12] . As a person who would be a proper party if it were in the jurisdiction, ONGC would be thus amenable to the courts jurisdiction under FCR O 8 r 2, Item 18 (like the former FCR O 8 r 1(g)): Quinlan v Safe International F&ouml;rs&auml;krings AB [2005] FCA 1362 at [24] , applying Costa Vraca Pty Ltd v Bell Regal Pty Ltd [2003] FCAFC 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Reed Construction Services Pty Ltd v Kheng Seng (Australia) Pty Ltd (1999) 15 BCL 158</tocase>
<text>In particular, Clough contends that the delay in its providing the 'Christmas Trees' was caused by breach on the part of ONGC relating to the 'DHPTT Cards'. It also asserts that ONGC was in breach in other respects, such as failing to effect well-completion in relation to the deep water work and that ONGC lost the first 'Christmas Tree' and certain tools, all of which contributed to delays of the Project. The failure to undertake shallow water works, likewise, Clough says, was occasioned by breaches on the part of ONGC. It is not possible to resolve these factual questions and whether those asserted breaches were occasioned by ONGC's own breaches. This in turn gives rise to a prima facie case or a serious issue to be tried, whether based on those asserted breaches, ONGC acted unconscionably contrary to s 51AA of the TPA in calling up the performance guarantees: Reed Construction Services Pty Ltd v Kheng Seng (Australia) Pty Ltd (1999) 15 BCL 158 at 164.

However, this does not determine the matter. ONGC contends that Clough is indisputably in breach of its contractual obligations in two further important respects. These concern Clough's obligations to extend the validity of the performance guarantees and to provide documentary proof that relevant insurance cover is being maintained by Clough. ONGC submits that these obligations exist, even assuming that the need for the extensions is the result of breach(es) on its part. I now turn to consider each of these. Breach of cl 3.3.2: The performance guarantees

I have, again, set out cl 3.3.2 below, for ease of reference: 
 
 3.3.2 In the event completion of Works is delayed beyond the Scheduled Completion Date for any reasons whatsoever, the Contractor shall get the validity of the guarantee suitably extended so as to make it valid for 12 months plus 60 days from the actual date of completion of Works. However if the delay is attributable to the Company, Company shall bear the cost of extension of such performance guarantee for such extended period at the normal bank rates as applicable to International Banking procedures.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Media, Entertainment and Arts Alliance, Ex parte the Hoyts Corporation Pty Limited [1993] HCA 40 ; (1993) 178 CLR 379</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/40.html</AustLII>
<text>ONGC made demands upon the Banks, HSBC Bank Australia Limited (HSBC) in Perth and upon the Commonwealth Bank of Australia (CBA) and BNP Paribas in Sydney under the performance guarantees, on 4 June 2007, which was a Perth public holiday. These proceedings were commenced the following day. The Construction Contract was terminated by ONGC by a facsimile letter to Clough of 4 June 2007. PREVIOUS ORDERS MADE BY THE COURT 
 
 (a) On 5 June 2007 an ex parte interlocutory injunction was granted against the Banks restraining each of them from making payment to ONGC under the performance guarantees. This injunction was extended on 12 June 2007 and on 19 June 2007, following an inter parties hearing, when an application by the Banks to discharge the injunction was dismissed. 
 
(b) On 7 June 2007 an ex parte interim injunction was granted against ONGC restraining it from taking further steps to demand or obtain payment, or renewing such claims or demands, from the Banks under the performance guarantees. The injunction was extended on 12 and 19 June 2007. 
 
(c) On 7 June 2007 e x parte orders for leave to serve ONGC ex juris were made.

Clough has sought to restrain the calling on, or payment under, the performance guarantees for a number of reasons. The first, it submits, is that the Construction Contact, properly construed, prohibits a demand being made in the prevailing circumstances. The second, alternative, basis is that even if the Construction Contract, by its terms, does not preclude making a demand under the guarantees, nevertheless ONGC has caused or contributed to the circumstances leading to the asserted breach of the Construction Contract by Clough, upon which ONGC relies to make a demand. The third is that alternatively, ONGC's demand constituted unconscionable conduct within the meaning of the unwritten laws of Australia, in contravention of s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ("TPA"). Finally, it is said, that the demand served by ONGC does not conform with the criteria required of a valid demand on the proper construction of the guarantees.

The terms of the performance guarantees to be entered into under the Construction Contract are contained in Appendix III (not II) of Annexure A to the Contract. Clause 3.3.3 requires to be construed in the context of the document as a whole. This includes the context of Appendix III of Annexure A: see, for example, Re Media, Entertainment and Arts Alliance, Ex parte the Hoyts Corporation Pty Limited [1993] HCA 40 ; (1993) 178 CLR 379 at 386-387.

The performance guarantees prescribed by the Construction Contract accordingly promise payment even where disputes, which could include disputes as to whether or not Clough had failed to honour any of its commitments under the Construction Contract, are pending before a Court or arbitrator. This, in my opinion, is a powerful indicator that a mere claimed breach of contract, which is not fraudulently asserted is sufficient to trigger entitlement to call on the performance guarantee. Clough does not assert that ONGC has made a fraudulent claim. This construction is reinforced by the fact that, under the prescribed terms of the guarantees, the Banks are required to pay "without any demur, reservation, contest or protest and/or without any reference to the Contractor".

Under the terms of the performance guarantees, each of the Banks was entitled to treat the written demand by ONGC as conclusive and binding as to the amount due and payable, notwithstanding any dispute pending before any Court, Tribunal, Arbitrator or any other authority. Liability under the performance guarantees was absolute and unequivocal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Resort Hotels Management Pty Ltd v Resort Hotels of Australia Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 730</tocase>
<text>It is also for Clough to establish a case for the continuation of the injunction. No onus lies on ONGC to discharge the injunctions: Resort Hotels Management Pty Ltd v Resort Hotels of Australia Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 730 at 731. Accordingly, Clough requires to establish that there is a serious issue(s) to be tried.

I will firstly deal with the orders sought under paragraph 1 of the Notice of Motion. This involves a consideration of whether Clough has established anew that it has a prima facie case to maintain the grant of service ex juris on ONGC and whether there are any serious issues to be tried to sustain injunctive relief, either pending a trial of issues in this Court, or were the matter to be referred to the Arbitrators in India, by way of a protective interim measure in aid of the arbitration.

This, in particular, requires a detailed consideration of the following:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tycoon Holdings Limited v Trencor Jetco Inc [1992] FCA 25 ; (1992) 34 FCR 31</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/25.html</AustLII>
<text>In relation to the application to set aside service of the Amended Application on ONGC, an application under O 9 r 7 of the Federal Court Rules (FCR) results in a review of the original decision to grant leave to serve ex juris and is a rehearing conducted on the basis of additional materials, recognising that a respondent should have "the opportunity to put before the Court any additional facts or arguments which might suggest that leave ought not to have been granted": Tycoon Holdings Limited v Trencor Jetco Inc [1992] FCA 25 ; (1992) 34 FCR 31 at 33; Bray v F Hoffmann-La Roche Limited (2003) 130 FCR 317 at [53] per Carr J. The onus remains on the applicant to satisfy the Court, in light of those additional materials and facts and arguments, that leave should have been granted: Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Proprietary Limited [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 564.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Proprietary Limited [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/55.html</AustLII>
<text>In relation to the application to set aside service of the Amended Application on ONGC, an application under O 9 r 7 of the Federal Court Rules (FCR) results in a review of the original decision to grant leave to serve ex juris and is a rehearing conducted on the basis of additional materials, recognising that a respondent should have "the opportunity to put before the Court any additional facts or arguments which might suggest that leave ought not to have been granted": Tycoon Holdings Limited v Trencor Jetco Inc [1992] FCA 25 ; (1992) 34 FCR 31 at 33; Bray v F Hoffmann-La Roche Limited (2003) 130 FCR 317 at [53] per Carr J. The onus remains on the applicant to satisfy the Court, in light of those additional materials and facts and arguments, that leave should have been granted: Voth v Manildra Flour Mills Proprietary Limited [1990] HCA 55 ; (1990) 171 CLR 538 at 564.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Walker v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (2001) 39 ACSR 557</tocase>
<text>As to this, it should be recognised that equity will generally intervene to ameliorate the application of a legal right if it is employed capriciously or unreasonably or harshly, or oppressively such as to be unconscionable: Pierce Bell Sales Pty Ltd v Frazer [1973] HCA 13 ; (1973) 130 CLR 575 at 587-588 and 590-591; NC Seddon &amp; MP Ellinghaus, Cheshire &amp; Fifoot's Law of Contract (8 th Aust. ed) (2002), [20.9]. This doctrine, although distinct from, is very similar to, the implied contractual duty of good faith: Walker v ANZ Banking Group Ltd (No 2) (2001) 39 ACSR 557 , [93]-[96], esp. [96]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd (2002) 117 FCR 301. Section 51AA of the TPA likewise may afford relevant protection. This however does not mean that the entitlement at law to call on the whole amount under the performance guarantees should be read down from what is otherwise a construction which is in harmony with the contract as a whole and which in its context produces a commercially sensible meaning. Furthermore, to the extent that the calling up of the performance guarantees resulted in an overpayment to ONGC then there would be an entitlement in Clough to an 'accounting' in due course from ONGC: Cargill International SA Antigua Geneva Branch v Bangladesh Sugar &amp; Food Industries Corporation [1996] 4 All ER 563 at 571.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Western Australian v Vetter Tritter (1991) 30 FCR 102</tocase>
<text>To maintain service ex juris , Clough needs to demonstrate a prima facie case for the relief claimed: FCR O 8, r 3(2)(c). The threshold for demonstrating a prima facie case is not high. It is whether on the material before the Court, inferences are open which, if translated into findings of fact, would support the relief claimed: Clough Engineering Ltd v Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd [2007] FCA 881 at [36] ; Western Australian v Vetter Tritter (1991) 30 FCR 102 at 110; Puccini Festival Australia Pty Ltd v Nippon Express (Australia) Pty Ltd [2007] VSC 288. It requires the demonstration of an "arguable case", bearing in mind that this requirement is to be met at the outset of the action, "without the advantage of discovery and other procedural aids to the making out of a case": Ho v Akai Pty Limited (in liquidation) [2006] FCAFC 159 at [10] , [12], [37], [43].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>