<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHPS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 233 (28 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/233.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corp v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 3 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>19 I would refuse to grant leave in respect of those grounds which require leave. The test for whether leave to appeal is granted or refused is well established: D&eacute;cor Corp v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 3 FCR 397 at [9]. I am of the opinion that none of them has any reasonable prospects of success. The Federal Magistrate's decision is not attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered by the Federal Court. No substantial injustice would result from my refusal to grant leave. It is not "expedient in the interests of justice" to allow these new grounds: H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348 at [6] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1348.html</AustLII>
<text>19 I would refuse to grant leave in respect of those grounds which require leave. The test for whether leave to appeal is granted or refused is well established: D&eacute;cor Corp v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 3 FCR 397 at [9]. I am of the opinion that none of them has any reasonable prospects of success. The Federal Magistrate's decision is not attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered by the Federal Court. No substantial injustice would result from my refusal to grant leave. It is not "expedient in the interests of justice" to allow these new grounds: H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348 at [6] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Le Geng (2001 [2001] HCA 17 ; 205 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/17.html</AustLII>
<text>16 The first and last of these require leave to be raised as they are not raised below. Again they are not particularised and the appellant did not advance any before me. I am satisfied that the Tribunal fully considered the appellant's claims and the material before it. I find that they are without merit. As to bias the applicant has not met the requirement that such an allegation be firmly and distinctly made and clearly proved: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Le Geng (2001 [2001] HCA 17 ; 205 CLR 507. No jurisdictional error has been made out.

17 In the fourth ground the appellant alleges that the Tribunal's decision was not based on rational and logical foundation. The Federal Magistrate correctly found that the Tribunal's decision was based on the paucity of detail and information, such that the Tribunal was unable to be satisfied that the appellant has a well-founded fear of persecution within the meaning of the Convention. This ground is not made out.

18 Lastly, the appellant contends that the Federal Magistrate did not fully consider the information provided. Again no particulars are provided. A reading of his Honour's reasons dispels such a ground. The appellant appeared before the Court assisted by an interpreter in the Mandarin language. He was invited to make oral submissions and did so speaking from a prepared document. These submissions were but a repetition, without particulars, of the grounds of appeal. There is nothing in the material before me to support such a ground.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/142.html</AustLII>
<text>14 The Tribunal, in my opinion, complied with its statutory obligations under the Act to invite the appellant to a hearing. When the appellant failed to appear at the hearing the Tribunal decided to exercise the power under s 426A(1) of the Act and proceeded to make a decision without taking any further action to allow the appellant to appear before it. No error resulted in the Tribunal proceeding in this manner: VNAA v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 134 ; (2004) 136 FCR 407 at [14] - [15] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365 at [135] per Allsop J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZECI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2005] FCA 1201</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1201.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The Federal Magistrate considered the second ground outlined by the appellant and held that it was not information but rather the inability of the Tribunal to be satisfied that the applicant fulfilled the criteria for grant of a protection visa which was the basis of the decision of the Tribunal. The Tribunal did not rely on "information" for the purposes of s 424A: SZECI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2005] FCA 1201 at [24] . Accordingly, both grounds for review were rejected by the Federal Magistrate.

10 The notice of appeal raises the following unparticularised grounds: 
 
 2. I was not given an opportunity to explain my case. 
 
 3. The Tribunal failed to consider my claims. The Tribunal had bias against me and did not consider my application according the s. 91R of the Migration Act 1958 . 
 
 4. The Tribunal's satisfaction that I am not a refugee was not based on a rational and logical foundation for this belief. 
 
 5. Federal Magistrates court did not fully consider the information provided and refused my application. 
 
 
 
 (Transcribed from the original without alteration).

11 There are before me four grounds of appeal. I will adopt the paragraph numbering in the Notice of Appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>VNAA v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 134 ; (2004) 136 FCR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/134.html</AustLII>
<text>14 The Tribunal, in my opinion, complied with its statutory obligations under the Act to invite the appellant to a hearing. When the appellant failed to appear at the hearing the Tribunal decided to exercise the power under s 426A(1) of the Act and proceeded to make a decision without taking any further action to allow the appellant to appear before it. No error resulted in the Tribunal proceeding in this manner: VNAA v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 134 ; (2004) 136 FCR 407 at [14] - [15] ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365 at [135] per Allsop J.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>