<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hadgkiss v Aldin [2007] FCA 2068 (20 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2068.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>ACCC v Dataline.Net.Au Pty Ltd (2006) 236 ALR 665</tocase>
<text>There is a public interest in knowing what conduct constitutes contravention and that it is considered to warrant an order recognising its seriousness. This may be done on the basis of admitted facts: ACCC v Dataline.Net.Au Pty Ltd (2006) 236 ALR 665. Her Honour's approach in that case was expressly approved by a Full Federal Court upon appeal: ACCC v Dataline.Net.Au Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 146 at [91] - [92] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (ACCC) v IPM Operations Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 11</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/11.html</AustLII>
<text>Young J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (ACCC) v IPM Operations Maintenance Loy Yang Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 11 at [66] said, concerning the two aspects of deterrence, "that for a penalty to achieve these objectives, it must be imposed at a meaningful level, consistent with the other considerations that must be taken into account in determining the appropriate level of penalty". There is a need, as his Honour said, to show "the seriousness with which the Court considers such contraventions".

In support of his submissions relating to penalty, the applicant relies upon: 
(a) the Statements of Agreed Facts; 
 
(b) affidavit of Robert John Wallwork sworn on 23 October 2007, paragraphs 1 to 9 and 118 to 125 (both inclusive);
 
(c) affidavit of Francis Patrick Hannagan sworn on 19 October 2007; 
 
(d) affidavit of Nigel Clive Hadgkiss sworn on 26 October 2007; and 
 
(e) affidavit of Douglas Bevan sworn on 17 October 2007 paragraphs 1-32 and 83-129. 
 
There was no cross-examination of any of the deponents. Indeed by agreement between the parties, they were not required to attend.

The applicant submitted that the breach of s 38 of the BCII Act in this case was serious, having regard to the following matters which are drawn from a combination of the several affidavits relied upon as well as the Statements of Agreed Facts: 
(a) It involved the withdrawal of labour by a substantial number of workers, in circumstances that effectively stopped all work on a major and complicated construction project of public importance. The Project involved tunnelling below the Perth central business district and the unlawful industrial action occurred at a critical stage of this tunnelling. Two full weeks of tunnelling were lost; 
 
(b) The contraventions were deliberate in nature and in knowing defiance of the law, the respondents having been advised by their union that they would be exposed to very serious penalties for taking unlawful industrial action; 
 
(c) the Strike had a duration of 7 days, although in the case of each respondent it involved one period of industrial action and thus, for the purpose of imposing penalties in this case, one contravention of the BCII Act; 
 
(d) the Strike caused LKJV to incur substantial losses. Mr Wallwork, in his affidavit, identified the following actual and contingent losses amounting to more than $1.6 million:
 Leighton Contractors, one of the LKJV joint venturers, is exposed to the potential claim under a Deed entered into with the Public Transport Authority, for liquidated damages at the rate of $52,000 per day for each day that the project goes beyond the date for practical completion of the Project; daily recurring overhead costs of approximately $5,000 per day; other preliminary costs of approximately $48,000 per day; and other irrecoverable out-of-pocket expenses of approximately $45,000-$55,000 per day; 
(e) the Strike occurred in contravention of an order of the AIRC for industrial action to stop or not occur which came into force on 6 December 2005 and was to remain in force until 1 July 2007, notice of that order having been placed on the LKJV notice board which was used to convey information to the workers and served upon the relevant respondents; 
 
(f) the Strike had the potential to cause substantial safety issues and damage to property, as the project involved tunnelling and stoppage of the tunnel boring machines has the potential to cause serious damage to the tunnel boring machine as well as to buildings above. A worst case scenario could have involved a tunnel collapse; 
 
(g) the delay on the project caused by the Strike gave rise to public inconvenience, the railway project being for the benefit of the public, in particular commuters to and from the Perth CBD; and 
 
(h) none of the action taken during the Period was based on a reasonable concern by any respondent about an imminent risk to his or her health or safety.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BHP Steel (AIS) Pty Ltd v CFMEU [2000] FCA 1908</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1908.html</AustLII>
<text>In BHP Steel (AIS) Pty Ltd v CFMEU [2000] FCA 1908 , a penalty of $2,200 was imposed on the CFMEU in what the Court described as a "serious" case (at [8]). The maximum was $10,000. The CFMEU defended the case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union v Coal and Allied Operations Pty Ltd (No.2) (1999) 94 IR 231</tocase>
<text>The leading cases concerning the factors that are relevant to the assessment of civil penalties are the judgments of French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076 and Branson J in Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union v Coal and Allied Operations Pty Ltd (No 2) (1999) 94 IR 231. The principles identified in those cases have been applied to determining penalties under the BCII Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Finance Sector Union v Commonwealth Bank of Australia (2005) 224 ALR 467</tocase>
<text>Nonetheless, the contraventions in each case contain common elements, namely, unauthorised industrial action by involvement in the Strike. This is a relevant consideration in weighing the appropriate penalty to be imposed: The Community and Public Sector Union v Telstra Corporation Ltd (2001) 108 IR 228. To punish twice for conduct that contains an area of overlap "would be to punish offenders according to the accidents of legislative history, rather than according to their just desserts": Pearce v R [1998] HCA 57 ; (1998) 156 ALR 684 at [40] . These matters therefore give rise to considerations of cumulation and concurrence, as well as totality: Pearce at [45]; Mill v R [1988] HCA 70 ; (1988) 166 CLR 59; Finance Sector Union v The Commonwealth Bank of Australia (2005) 224 ALR 467 at [25].

If that was the position then it is no longer the position. In Finance Sector Union v Commonwealth Bank of Australia at [72], Merkel J observed that: 
 
may be that breaches by unions and employers of industrial legislation from time to time have been accepted as part of the give and take of industrial disputation. However, in recent years industrial legislation has increasingly codified and prescribed what is acceptable, and what is unacceptable, industrial conduct. The legislature has, over time, also moved to increase the penalties that may be imposed in respect of unlawful industrial conduct. In my view, any light handed approach that might have been taken in the past to serious, wilful and ongoing breaches of the industrial laws should no longer be applicable.

The penalty imposed by Merkel J in respect of the contraventions of s 298K of the WR Act in the above case ($600,000) was overturned on appeal and substituted for a penalty of $300,000. Importantly, however, Branson J (with whom Spender J agreed in relation to the reduction in penalty) indicated that there was no demonstrable error of principle affecting the penalty imposed by Merkel J at first instance. Her Honour reaffirmed the warning that it may well be that it is appropriate for penalties imposed under the WR Act to rise and rise appreciably.

That case was not concerned with breaches by employees, but as I have said, I do not consider that they stand in any different category.

I have had regard to part of the Second Reading Speech of the BCII Act which is instructive in this respect: 
 
Bill reflects the Government's commitment to ensuring the law applies and is observed equally by all participants in the building and construction industry, regardless of whether they are union officials, employers or workers. 
 

 
 
industrial record of this industry is deplorable. 
 

 
 
Royal Commissioner found that the prevalence of industrial action in the building industry is unique. He noted 
 

 
 
 Underlying the attitude of participants in the industry is a disregard of the rule of law, and the adoption of a short term attitude, commercially driven, of expediency. In particular, unions know that the prospect of being held civilly responsible for the losses they cause is remote. 
 
[Volume 11, page 10, para 33] 
 

 
 
level of industrial disputation in the construction industry is substantial. For example, in 2003-04 the construction industry employed 8 per cent of all employed persons in Australia. For the same period, these workers accounted for over 21 per cent of working days lost. 
 

 
 
action negatively impacts upon industry productivity. Industrial unrest and time lost through work stoppages cause immediate loss to head contractors, subcontractors and employees. Even short strikes can cause commercial damage because standing charges and overheads continue even if work on site stops. Commissioner Cole found project completion delays, with contractual penalties of up to $250,000 a day, are a compelling incentive for employers to surrender to union demands. 
 

 
 
those who engage in unlawful industrial action in this industry are seldom held accountable. In addition, the current system for recovery of loss due to unlawful industrial action is difficult, costly and time consuming. As Commissioner Cole noted 
 

 
 
 Litigation for loss recovery is regarded as a bargaining chip to be used in future resolution of industrial disputes, rather than as a serious attempt to hold those causing loss responsible for it. 
 
[Vol 11, page 13, chapter 1] 
 

 
 
Bill seeks to implement a framework where unlawful industrial action is not tolerated and those taking such action are brought to account for their lawlessness.

I have also taken into account the mitigating factors which are set out above.

I have been advised that any penalties which I impose on the respondents will not be paid by them personally although this would not apply to any suspended penalties which became payable upon a further contravention. From around February 2007, the ACTU and CFMEU established and maintained a national fund, known as the Mandurah Dispute Fighting Fund. The monies in the fund will be used to meet the costs of the penalties and legal costs incurred by the respondents. The impecuniosity of individual respondents is not raised as an issue in the proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Leighton Contractors Pty Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2006] WASC 317</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WASC/2006/317.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 "(Mobil Oil") the Full Federal Court acknowledged that deterrence is "one of the principal justifications, if not the only justification for imposing civil penalties" at [53]. In Leighton Contractors Pty Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2006] WASC 317 , which involved industrial action on the very project that is in issue in this case, Le Miere J, said putting it in a more limited way [74]: 
 
penalties should be sufficiently high to deter repetition by the contravener and by others who might be tempted to engage in contravening conduct. Deterrence is a primary objective of penalties."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Metropolitan Fire and Emergency Services Board v United Firefighters' Union of Australia (2005) 148 IR 242</tocase>
<text>In addition, Ryan J's judgment in Metropolitan Fire and Emergency Services Board v United Firefighters' Union of Australia (2005) 148 IR 242 (" United Firefighters "), suggests that, in the context of the imposition of penalties in respect of a contravention of an order of the AIRC under s 127 of the WR Act, the following additional factors are relevant: 
(a) an absence of any basis for misapprehension about what the Order commanded;
 
(b) whether a party in breach has previously contravened an order under s127; and
 
(c) the need to deter participants in industrial relations administered under the WR Act from flouting or disregarding orders of the AIRC, "especially where those orders have been made after a full hearing of both sides and have been tailored to meet the exigencies of a particular industrial dispute".
 Deterrence

The respondents submitted that, in this case, the primary consideration is deterrence and in that regard general deterrence is more important than specific deterrence. The applicants' submissions were to the same effect. I accept this submission. This is not to say that specific deterrence is not of importance. This approach is consistent with the main object of the Act to which I have referred.

It was further submitted by the applicant that the admitted contraventions of s 127 of the WR Act were similarly serious, having regard to: 
(a) the clear and unmistakeable command of the AIRC, as expressed in clause 4(a) and (b) of the Order and accordingly the absence of any basis for misapprehension of what the further 67 respondents were being directed to refrain from doing;
 
(b) the exceptional nature of the Order in that it was made for the life of the Project;
 
(c) the very substantial consequences of the industrial action during the Period, as identified above;
 
(d) the particular need for deterrence of participants in the industrial relations system from flouting such orders, as referred to by Ryan J in United Firefighters .

The applicant favours a disposition of this matter in terms that involve an immediately payable penalty, and a significant suspended penalty, that will apply for a considerable period of time, being three years. The penalty provisions contained in s 49(1)(c) of the BCII Act contemplate the making of "any other order that the court considers appropriate". This, it is submitted, will serve to achieve the objectives of both specific and general deterrence.

In all of the circumstances, the applicant submitted that the following penalties are appropriate and should be considered as being at the lower end of the available range: 
(a) in respect of each of the respondents for admitted contraventions of s 38 of the BCII Act, a penalty of $9,000 of which $3,000 should be payable within 28 days and the balance of $6,000 suspended for 3 years, to be paid only if the respondent further contravenes the BCII Act or the WR Act during the period of the suspension; and
 
(b) in respect of each of the 67 respondents who have admitted contraventions of s 178 of the WR Act, an additional penalty of $3,000 of which $1,000 should be payable within 28 days and the balance of $2,000 suspended for 3 years, upon similar terms.

In United Firefighters, a union was fined $2,500 and its secretary was fined $500 for contravening a s 127 Order. The maximum penalties were $30,000 and $6,000 respectively. The union defended the case.

It was submitted that the present action being the first of its kind, seeking to penalise individual employees as distinct from a union or its officers should therefore be seen in the context of the imposition of penalties for new offences. It was further submitted that it is a clear principle of sentencing that for a new offence, the penalties will normally be regarded as having to start at a low level before any subsequent penalties are considered within a context of escalating requirements for deterrence and punishment. No authority was cited for such a principle. I invited senior counsel for the respondents, if he so wished, to provide such authority in supplementary submissions. None have been provided.

Finally it was submitted that the appropriate penalty range in this case falls very much towards the bottom end of the range for the reasons and that because of the novelty of the application, that any penalty imposed should be fully suspended. In this way, it was said, the Court could, with justice, mark the punishment and issues of specific and general deterrence to the extent required in this instance. Double Punishment

Those respondents who have admitted contraventions of both the WR Act and the BCII Act submit that the contraventions arise from the same conduct and that they ought not to be punished twice for that same conduct.

It was not submitted that s 4C of the Crimes Act 1914 (Cth) which prohibits a person from being punished twice for the same act or omission, has any direct application here. The admitted contraventions are not offences. In any event, it is not the case, in my opinion, that the contraventions arise from the same conduct, if by that it is meant that the elements which comprise the contraventions in the case of each of the BCII Act and the WR Act are the same.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mill v R [1988] HCA 70 ; (1988) 166 CLR 59</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/70.html</AustLII>
<text>Nonetheless, the contraventions in each case contain common elements, namely, unauthorised industrial action by involvement in the Strike. This is a relevant consideration in weighing the appropriate penalty to be imposed: The Community and Public Sector Union v Telstra Corporation Ltd (2001) 108 IR 228. To punish twice for conduct that contains an area of overlap "would be to punish offenders according to the accidents of legislative history, rather than according to their just desserts": Pearce v R [1998] HCA 57 ; (1998) 156 ALR 684 at [40] . These matters therefore give rise to considerations of cumulation and concurrence, as well as totality: Pearce at [45]; Mill v R [1988] HCA 70 ; (1988) 166 CLR 59; Finance Sector Union v The Commonwealth Bank of Australia (2005) 224 ALR 467 at [25].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/72.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 "(Mobil Oil") the Full Federal Court acknowledged that deterrence is "one of the principal justifications, if not the only justification for imposing civil penalties" at [53]. In Leighton Contractors Pty Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2006] WASC 317 , which involved industrial action on the very project that is in issue in this case, Le Miere J, said putting it in a more limited way [74]: 
 
penalties should be sufficiently high to deter repetition by the contravener and by others who might be tempted to engage in contravening conduct. Deterrence is a primary objective of penalties."

I consider that the total penalties in each case, tempered by suspension of a significant part of each gives rise to the appropriate overall penalties. In my view, the penalties in each case give effect to the primacy of both specific and general deterrence and in that regard I have given reasonable weight to the submissions of the applicant: Mobil Oil at [53].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Pearce v R [1998] HCA 57 ; (1998) 156 ALR 684</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/57.html</AustLII>
<text>Nonetheless, the contraventions in each case contain common elements, namely, unauthorised industrial action by involvement in the Strike. This is a relevant consideration in weighing the appropriate penalty to be imposed: The Community and Public Sector Union v Telstra Corporation Ltd (2001) 108 IR 228. To punish twice for conduct that contains an area of overlap "would be to punish offenders according to the accidents of legislative history, rather than according to their just desserts": Pearce v R [1998] HCA 57 ; (1998) 156 ALR 684 at [40] . These matters therefore give rise to considerations of cumulation and concurrence, as well as totality: Pearce at [45]; Mill v R [1988] HCA 70 ; (1988) 166 CLR 59; Finance Sector Union v The Commonwealth Bank of Australia (2005) 224 ALR 467 at [25].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 543</tocase>
<text>This is a repetition of what was said by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076 at 52,152. See also Trade Practices Commission v Pye Industries Sales Pty Ltd (1978) ATPR p40-089 at 17,859; Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 543 per Lander J at [93] and per Jessop J at [164].

The respondents referred to Ponzio , a recent Full Court decision about the imposition of penalties under the WR Act. This was a case against an employer under the former s 187AA and the CFMEU and two of its officials under former s 187AB of the WR Act. It concerned payment to employees for a period of industrial action. It adds nothing of significance to the relevant principles involved in the imposition of a penalty.

In that case, a penalty of $5,000 was imposed on the employer; none of it was to be paid if the company did not breach any provision of the WR Act for a year. The employer was regarded as being less culpable than the union. A penalty of $6,000 was imposed on the CFMEU. No penalty was imposed on the two officials but declarations were made that they had breached the WR Act.

This was the highest penalty imposed under those sections. The other penalties in the 4 earlier cases ranged from $200 to $4,000: [130]-[133] per Jessup J.

There have been two cases where penalties have been imposed for contraventions of ss 127 and 178 of the former WR Act.

I have given no weight in assessing the appropriate penalties to the view of the workforce that Ballard had been unfairly or unlawfully sacked or in relation to the asserted 'sharp practice' on the part of LKJV: Ponzio at [90] per Lander J. In any event I am unable, on the evidence, to conclude that the respondents' perception that Ballard was unfairly or unlawfully terminated was reasonably based or not. Nor am I in a position to characterise the conditions put by the LKJV for his reinstatement as constituting 'sharp practice', or as being provocative. There was no direct evidence as to this nor am I able to infer it.

In any event, if Ballard considered that he had been either unfairly or unlawfully terminated in his employment, then he had both a contractual obligation and a remedy at law. There was a mandatory Dispute Resolution Procedure under the Certified Agreement (cl 4.5) for the resolution of disputes. Ballard was obliged to follow this. He did not. Additionally, an application for relief under s 643(1) of the WR Act was available to Ballard on the ground that the termination was allegedly harsh, unjust or unreasonable. Indeed it was a term of the LKJV New Metro Rail City Project Structural Certified Agreement 2004 that termination of employment by the Joint Venture shall not be harsh, unjust or unreasonable (cl 2.2.3). I was informed by senior counsel for the respondents that Ballard had made an application in relation to his alleged unfair dismissal, claiming that it was harsh, unjust and unreasonable and constituted discrimination.

The respondents' perception that Ballard's dismissal was unfair or unlawful did not constitute a warrant for the unlawful industrial action, nor does it constitute any relevant mitigating circumstance. It would be extraordinary if a wilful disregard of the main object of the legislation, and in particular, in this case, the promotion of the rule of law, should be regarded as somehow mitigating the contravention.

Mr Rozen, who represented the 7 th , 8 th , 9 th , 12 th , 14 th , 16 th , 28 th , 37 th and 64 th respondents, conceded in argument that the unlawful industrial action was, (in part) clearly motivated by an attempt to bring financial pressure to bear on the LKJV to achieve the reinstatement of Ballard rather than through lawful means. In my view, that concession was correctly made and underlines the seriousness of the conduct.

I do not accept that merely because they are employees as opposed to a union, union officials, or an employer, that there is, in principle, any different approach which should be taken on the question of penalty. In any one case there may be different levels of culpability. Each matter requires to be considered by reference to its own facts and circumstances. I was told by senior counsel for the respondents that orders of the AIRC were frequently disobeyed and that this, traditionally, was not regarded as serious. It was also held that this was the first time in which penalty proceedings had been taken against employees in that capacity. This, it was said, was for historical reasons, grounded in the way that industrial disputes have in the past been fought.

In Ponzio , a Full Federal Court made a series of detailed declarations concerning contraventions of the WR Act, on the basis of facts established by an agreed statement of facts. It is apparent from that form of declaration in that case that the Full Court was prepared to accept the detail in the agreed statement of facts as a proper factual foundation for the making of declarations. I propose that equivalent declarations should be made in this case. 
 
 I certify that the preceding one hundred and sixteen (116) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gilmour. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 20 December 2007
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr R J H Maidment SC with Mr R L Hooker and Dr S Donaghue 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicant: Lavan Legal 
 
 Counsel for Respondents 1-6, 10-11, 13, 15, 17, 19-23, 26-27, 29-36, 39-43, 45-53, 55-62, 66, 68-71, 73-75, 77, 79-81, 83-87, 90-97, 99-107 Mr R Richter QC with Mr K Bonomelli 
 
 Counsel for Respondents 7, 8, 9, 12, 14, 16, 28, 37 and 64 Mr P Rozen 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondents: Jeremy Noble, Barristers &amp; Solicitors 
 
 Date of Hearing: 5 November 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 December 2007 
 SCHEDULE 1 BREACH OF SECTION 38 OF THE BCII ACT 
 UNLAWFUL INDUSTRIAL ACTION 24, 25, 27, 28 FEBRUARY 2006, 
 1, 2 AND 3 MARCH 2006 
 
 No. RESPONDENT NAME RESPONDENT NUMBER 1 Gordon William Aldin 1 2 Stephen Banks 4 3 Richard John Beck 5 4 Nathan Ryan Bennett 6 5 Robert Biondillo 7 6 Robert Neil Bradbury 
* Respondent 9 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 24, 27, 28 February 2006 and 1 March 2006.
 8 7 John Francis Bradley 9 8 Jamie Brearley 10 9 Tim Hugh Brown 11 10 Greg James Brown 
* Respondent 14 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 28 February 2006 and 1 3 March 2006.
 12 11 Mathew Bruce 13 12 Michael Burke 14 13 John Joseph Byrne 
* Respondent 16 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 28 February 2006 and 1 3 March 2006.
 15 14 David Barrie Cameron 16 15 Terry Allan Collins 17 16 Martin Rashleigh Corbett 19 17 Graeme Cowling 20 18 Robert John Coyle 21 19 Robert William Crampton 22 20 Christopher Albert Crawford 23 21 Glenn James Daniels 26 22 Stuart John Davies 27 23 Dronzo Laurie De Bari 28 24 Kevin John Donlan 29 25 James Patrick Doyle 30 26 John Engel 31 27 Michael Evans 32 28 Gerard Patrick Farhi 33 29 Alessandro Forte 34 30 Paul Desmond Gleeson 35 31 David Joseph Golding 36 32 Shane Robert Greaves 37 33 David Hackett 39 34 Matt Charles Harvey 40 35 Zachary James Haywood 41 36 Lawrence Henry Healey 42 37 Charlie Graham Isaacs 43 38 Clinton Larkin 45 39 Wayne Robert Lee 46 40 Kevin Joseph Liddy 47 41 Mathew David Lothian 48 42 Colin Henry Luff 49 43 Iain MacBeth 50 44 Ronald John Marsh 51 45 Frank McMahon 52 46 James Dzemal Memic 53 47 Jeremy Kane Mills 55 48 Lindsay John Morison 56 49 Darren Raymond Morris 57 50 Richard Michael Mulcahy 58 51 Michael John Mulcahy 59 52 David Martin Murphy 60 53 Peter David Napper 61 54 Anthony Peter Nichols 62 55 Andrew John O'Donnell 64 56 Stephen Francis O'Sullivan 66 57 John Pes 68 58 Malcolm Stanley Peters 69 59 Fiorello Reitano 70 60 Brent David Rothsay 71 61 Joshua Gerald Scott 73 62 Alan Charles Semple 74 63 Daniel Spizzirri 75 64 John Graham Storrie 77 65 John Anthony Terriaca 79 66 Gary Frederick Wagstaff 80 67 Jye McNamara Walsh 81 68 Steven Barnett 84 69 Nathan Jay Bennett 85 70 Neil Lenard Bennett 86 71 Andrew Patrick Bowden 87 72 Dean Jason Coyle 90 73 Skye Maree Coyle 91 74 Ross Alan Curby 93 75 Stephen Ray Eaton 94 76 Matthew Bruce Ferguson 95 77 Errol Joseph Ferguson 96 78 Mark Phillip Galli 97 79 Scott John Gray 99 80 Wayne Clifford Hawkins 100 81 Scott Anthony Heap 101 82 Dean Michael McBride 102 83 Michael John Moran 103 84 Nemo Mouchemore 104 85 Darren Lee Reiher 105 86 Lee Elliott Soden 106 87 Maksi Vujcic 107 
 SCHEDULE 2 BREACH OF SECTION 127 ORDER 
 UNLAWFUL INDUSTRIAL ACTION 24, 25, 27, 28 FEBRUARY 2006, 
 1, 2 AND 3 MARCH 2006 
 
 No. RESPONDENT NAME RESPONDENT NUMBER 1 Gordon William Aldin 1 2 Stephen Banks 4 3 Richard John Beck 5 4 Nathan Ryan Bennett 6 5 Robert Biondillo 7 6 Robert Neil Bradbury 8 7 John Francis Bradley 
* Respondent 9 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 24, 27, 28 February 2006 and 1 March 2006.
 9 8 Jamie Brearley 10 9 Tim Hugh Brown 11 10 Greg James Brown 
* Respondent 14 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 28 February 2006 and 1 3 March 2006.
 12 11 Mathew Bruce 13 12 Michael Burke 14 13 John Joseph Byrne 
* Respondent 16 only engaged in unlawful industrial action on 28 February 2006 and 1 3 March 2006.
 15 14 David Barrie Cameron 
 16 15 Terry Allan Collins 17 16 Martin Rashleigh Corbett 19 17 Graeme Cowling 20 18 Robert John Coyle 21 19 Robert William Crampton 22 20 Christopher Albert Crawford 23 21 Glenn James Daniels 26 22 Stuart John Davies 27 23 Dronzo Laurie De Bari 28 24 Kevin John Donlan 29 25 James Patrick Doyle 30 26 John Engel 31 27 Michael Evans 32 28 Gerard Patrick Farhi 33 29 Alessandro Forte 34 30 Paul Desmond Gleeson 35 31 David Joseph Golding 36 32 Shane Robert Greaves 37 33 David Hackett 39 34 Matt Charles Harvey 40 35 Zachary James Haywood 41 36 Lawrence Henry Healey 42 37 Charlie Graham Isaacs 43 38 Clinton Larkin 45 39 Wayne Robert Lee 46 40 Kevin Joseph Liddy 47 41 Mathew David Lothian 48 42 Colin Henry Luff 49 43 Iain MacBeth 50 44 Ronald John Marsh 51 45 Frank McMahon 52 46 James Dzemal Memic 53 47 Jeremy Kane Mills 55 48 Lindsay John Morison 56 49 Darren Raymond Morris 57 50 Richard Michael Mulcahy 58 51 Michael John Mulcahy 59 52 David Martin Murphy 60 53 Peter David Napper 61 54 Anthony Peter Nichols 62 55 Andrew John O'Donnell 64 56 Stephen Francis O'Sullivan 66 57 John Pes 68 58 Malcolm Stanley Peters 69 59 Fiorello Reitano 70 60 Brent David Rothsay 71 61 Joshua Gerald Scott 73 62 Alan Charles Semple 74 63 Daniel Spizzirri 75 64 John Graham Storrie 77 65 John Anthony Terriaca 79 66 Gary Frederick Wagstaff 80 67 Jye McNamara Walsh 81 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2068.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/75.html</AustLII>
<text>I consider it appropriate that there be declarations as to the contraventions broadly in the terms sought by the applicant: Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 89. It is convenient and appropriate to do so in order to explain the basis for the penalties ordered: Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Community and Public Sector Union (CPSU) v Telstra Corporation Ltd (2001) 108 IR 228</tocase>
<text>Nonetheless, the contraventions in each case contain common elements, namely, unauthorised industrial action by involvement in the Strike. This is a relevant consideration in weighing the appropriate penalty to be imposed: The Community and Public Sector Union v Telstra Corporation Ltd (2001) 108 IR 228. To punish twice for conduct that contains an area of overlap "would be to punish offenders according to the accidents of legislative history, rather than according to their just desserts": Pearce v R [1998] HCA 57 ; (1998) 156 ALR 684 at [40] . These matters therefore give rise to considerations of cumulation and concurrence, as well as totality: Pearce at [45]; Mill v R [1988] HCA 70 ; (1988) 166 CLR 59; Finance Sector Union v The Commonwealth Bank of Australia (2005) 224 ALR 467 at [25].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076</tocase>
<text>The leading cases concerning the factors that are relevant to the assessment of civil penalties are the judgments of French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076 and Branson J in Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union v Coal and Allied Operations Pty Ltd (No 2) (1999) 94 IR 231. The principles identified in those cases have been applied to determining penalties under the BCII Act.

This is a repetition of what was said by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076 at 52,152. See also Trade Practices Commission v Pye Industries Sales Pty Ltd (1978) ATPR p40-089 at 17,859; Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 543 per Lander J at [93] and per Jessop J at [164].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Pye Industries Sales Pty Ltd (1978) ATPR p40-089</tocase>
<text>This is a repetition of what was said by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR p41-076 at 52,152. See also Trade Practices Commission v Pye Industries Sales Pty Ltd (1978) ATPR p40-089 at 17,859; Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 543 per Lander J at [93] and per Jessop J at [164].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 89</tocase>
<text>I consider it appropriate that there be declarations as to the contraventions broadly in the terms sought by the applicant: Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) (1993) 41 FCR 89. It is convenient and appropriate to do so in order to explain the basis for the penalties ordered: Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>