<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>NAVH v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 373 (27 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/373.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>NAVH v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FMCA 1704</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/1704.html</AustLII>
<text>1 This is an application for leave to appeal from a judgment of Barnes FM of 31 October 2006: NAVH v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FMCA 1704. The application before the Federal Magistrate sought judicial review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal dated 30 June 2003 affirming a decision of a delegate of the Minister to refuse to grant a protection visa to the applicant.

2 The applicant is a citizen of Pakistan who arrived in Australia on 28 July 2001. On 20 May 2002 the applicant lodged an application for a protection visa with the department. On 25 July 2002 a delegate of the Minister refused the application and the applicant applied to the Tribunal for review. In his protection visa application the applicant claimed fear of persecution by reason of his political opinion. The applicant claimed his father had been carrying out activities against drug traffickers and was murdered by drug smugglers because of those activities.

3 The applicant claimed he would be persecuted in Pakistan because of his father's activities. The applicant further claimed he would be arrested because of his opposition to the military regime in Pakistan. In particular, the applicant claimed to be a member of the Pakhtoon Khwa Party and to have written articles against the dictatorial regime of General Musharaf. The applicant claimed he and his father were attacked by ICI members who had connections to drug smugglers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAVH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1558</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2003/1558.html</AustLII>
<text>8 The applicant has challenged the decision not to grant him a protection visa on a previous occasion in this Court. On 16 December 2003, Lindgren J dismissed an application for review of the Tribunal decision: NAVH v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1558.

9 The applicant then commenced further proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court seeking review of the Tribunal's decision.

10 The Minister filed a notice of objection to competency on the grounds that the application was out of time. Notification of the decision of the Tribunal was received by the applicant on 29 July 2003. Pursuant to Part II , Item 42 of Schedule 1 of the Migration Litigation Reform Act 2005 (Cth) the applicant is taken to have been notified of the decision on 1 December 2005. Contrary to s 477(1) of the Migration Act, the application to the Federal Magistrates Court was not made within 28 days. That Court had no power to extend time for commencement of the proceedings beyond 23 February 2006.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>