<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Body Bronze International Pty Ltd v Soleil Tanning Oxford Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 371 (16 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/371.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 96 FCR 491</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/2.html</AustLII>
<text>26 In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 96 FCR 491, French J indicated (at [20] [21]) that the expression "unconscionable", in the context of s 51AA , might extend to include, at least, duress and undue influence. However, in GPG (Australia Trading) Pty Ltd v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [2001] FCA 1761 ; (2001) 117 FCR 23, Gyles J expressed the more narrow view that the provision did not extend to encompass all equitable grounds of relief in which unconscionable or unconscientious conduct was an element. His Honour considered that the section was instead limited in its reference to the recognised "unconscionable dealing" ground of relief. In the High Court Berbatis decision, Gummow and Hayne JJ noted that they were not required to resolve the conflict between these two views. Accordingly, the issue remains unresolved. See the discussion in Paul Vout (ed), Unconscionable Conduct: The Laws of Australia (2006), [35.9:35]; and Russell V Miller, Miller's Annotated Trade Practices Act : Australian Competition and Consumer Law (2007, 28 th ed), 486.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/18.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Mr Parncutt's argument was quite simple. He submitted that the conduct alleged against his clients amounted to nothing more than various breaches of contract. He submitted that in order to amount to unconscionable conduct there had to be something more than a mere breach of contract. He referred to a number of authorities, including, in particular, Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447; Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 62 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301; and Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 62 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/62.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Mr Parncutt's argument was quite simple. He submitted that the conduct alleged against his clients amounted to nothing more than various breaches of contract. He submitted that in order to amount to unconscionable conduct there had to be something more than a mere breach of contract. He referred to a number of authorities, including, in particular, Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447; Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 62 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301; and Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51.

17 Mr Marantelli's response was equally straightforward. He submitted that the categories of unconscionability were not closed. He argued that the Court should not apply strike out procedures in a way that might stultify the development of the law. He contended that this was a case in which, on the facts as pleaded, not only had the ninth to fifteenth respondents been involved in deliberately causing the first to fifth respondents to breach their contractual obligations, they had also facilitated putting the assets of those first five respondents out of the reach of the applicant. He relied in particular upon HECEC Australia Pty Ltd v Hydro-Electric Corp [1999] FCA 822 , where he submitted Einfeld J had accepted the proposition that a breach of contract alone could give rise to unconscionable conduct. He also placed some reliance upon the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court in Samton .

19 Following Amadio , there were a number of cases that discussed the doctrine of unconscionability. However, it was not until Samton that the Full Court of the Federal Court held that unconscionability in the context of s 51AA requires conduct to be identified that supports the grant of relief on principles set out in specific equitable doctrines, rather than requiring unconscionability at large.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/14.html</AustLII>
<text>15 Mr Parncutt's argument was quite simple. He submitted that the conduct alleged against his clients amounted to nothing more than various breaches of contract. He submitted that in order to amount to unconscionable conduct there had to be something more than a mere breach of contract. He referred to a number of authorities, including, in particular, Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447; Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 62 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301; and Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51.

18 As is well-known, the High Court confirmed the doctrine of unconscionability in Amadio . In that case, Mason J (as his Honour then was) stated (at 461):
 
 "But relief on the ground of "unconscionable conduct" is usually taken to refer to the class of case in which a party makes unconscientious use of his superior position or bargaining power to the detriment of a party who suffers from some special disability or is placed in some special situation of disadvantage, e.g., a catching bargain with an expectant heir or an unfair contract made by taking advantage of a person who is seriously affected by intoxicating drink. Although unconscionable conduct in this narrow sense bears some resemblance to the doctrine of undue influence, there is a difference between the two. In the latter the will of the innocent party is not independent and voluntary because it is overborne. In the former the will of the innocent party, even if independent and voluntary, is the result of the disadvantageous position in which he is placed and of the other party unconscientiously taking advantage of that position."

19 Following Amadio , there were a number of cases that discussed the doctrine of unconscionability. However, it was not until Samton that the Full Court of the Federal Court held that unconscionability in the context of s 51AA requires conduct to be identified that supports the grant of relief on principles set out in specific equitable doctrines, rather than requiring unconscionability at large.

22 In Berbatis , the High Court upheld a decision of the Full Court of this Court. It did so on the basis that the facts found fell short of what would attract the operation of the principles expounded in Amadio and therefore a breach of s 51AA could not be established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>GPG (Australia Trading) Pty Ltd v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [2001] FCA 1761 ; (2001) 117 FCR 23</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1761.html</AustLII>
<text>26 In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v C G Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2000] FCA 2 ; (2000) 96 FCR 491, French J indicated (at [20] [21]) that the expression "unconscionable", in the context of s 51AA , might extend to include, at least, duress and undue influence. However, in GPG (Australia Trading) Pty Ltd v GIO Australia Holdings Ltd [2001] FCA 1761 ; (2001) 117 FCR 23, Gyles J expressed the more narrow view that the provision did not extend to encompass all equitable grounds of relief in which unconscionable or unconscientious conduct was an element. His Honour considered that the section was instead limited in its reference to the recognised "unconscionable dealing" ground of relief. In the High Court Berbatis decision, Gummow and Hayne JJ noted that they were not required to resolve the conflict between these two views. Accordingly, the issue remains unresolved. See the discussion in Paul Vout (ed), Unconscionable Conduct: The Laws of Australia (2006), [35.9:35]; and Russell V Miller, Miller's Annotated Trade Practices Act : Australian Competition and Consumer Law (2007, 28 th ed), 486.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>HECEC Australia Pty Ltd v Hydro-Electric Corp [1999] FCA 822</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/822.html</AustLII>
<text>17 Mr Marantelli's response was equally straightforward. He submitted that the categories of unconscionability were not closed. He argued that the Court should not apply strike out procedures in a way that might stultify the development of the law. He contended that this was a case in which, on the facts as pleaded, not only had the ninth to fifteenth respondents been involved in deliberately causing the first to fifth respondents to breach their contractual obligations, they had also facilitated putting the assets of those first five respondents out of the reach of the applicant. He relied in particular upon HECEC Australia Pty Ltd v Hydro-Electric Corp [1999] FCA 822 , where he submitted Einfeld J had accepted the proposition that a breach of contract alone could give rise to unconscionable conduct. He also placed some reliance upon the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court in Samton .

29 Further, I reject the contention that Einfeld J in HECEC held that a breach of contract alone could give rise to unconscionable conduct. The case is replete with references to the economic disadvantage of the applicant as against the respondents who were various government ministers, and State instrumentalities. Mr Marantelli could point to no case in which a mere breach of contract had been held to give rise to unconscionable conduct. That is not surprising. The High Court has made it abundantly clear that there are limits upon the doctrine of unconscionability, and that the term is not to be used simply as a synonym for general unfairness.

30 It was for these reasons that I concluded that the mere allegation that the ninth to fifteenth respondents had caused the first to fifth respondents to breach their contractual obligations to the applicant, and facilitated the sixth to eighth respondents in gaining the benefits of those breaches, could not of itself amount to unconscionable conduct. In effect, all that was alleged against the ninth to fifteenth respondents is that they were responsible, in various ways, for the failure of the first to fifth respondents to comply with the terms of the various licence agreements.

31 There was no suggestion in the further amended statement of claim of any inequality of position, or bargaining power, between the applicant and the ninth to fifteenth respondents. It was also not suggested that the applicant was in a position of special vulnerability. Although it was pleaded that those respondents had been in business with the applicant, it was not suggested that that fact alone gave rise to a fiduciary relationship. Nor was it suggested that the conduct of those respondents amounted to a breach of fiduciary duty. Although it was pleaded that the respondents had extensive knowledge of the business from their involvement in it, it was not suggested that they misused that information when they facilitated the transfer of the business from the first to fifth respondents to the sixth to eighth respondents.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>