<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hume Computers Pty Ltd ACN 003 154 827 v Exact International BV [2007] FCA 478 (3 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/478.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ballas v Theophilos (No 2) [1957] HCA 90 ; (1957) 98 CLR 193</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1957/90.html</AustLII>
<text>53 Applying this approach, in my opinion the letter conveyed clearly and unequivocally that the Distributorship Agreement is to terminate with effect on and from 31 March 2007. If authority is needed for this proposition, it may be found in Ballas v Theophilos (No 2) [1957] HCA 90 ; (1957) 98 CLR 193 at 204-205; see also Young v Lamb at [28].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1995) 8 ANZ Ins Cas 61-232</tocase>
<text>43 It is also to be considered in light of the plain fact that Home Wilkinson Lowry are acting as solicitors for the Hume companies in the present proceedings, notwithstanding that no costs agreement has been produced relating to any such retainer. Thus it may be thought that the solicitors would have authority to deal with all issues which reasonably arise in the pursuit of the proceedings; CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1995) 8 ANZ Ins Cas 61-232 at 75,555 (Kirby P).

44 The observations of Kirby P in CIC Insurance were directed toward ostensible authority. However, here, particularly in light of Mr Leathem's affidavit and the failure to produce a current written retainer, I would infer the existence of actual authority.

45 That termination of the Distributorship under Article 20(3) was part of the subject matter of the proceedings may be seen from my remarks in [32] of my earlier judgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commercial Union Assurance Co of Australia Ltd v Ferrcom Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 389</tocase>
<text>46 In addition, I can be more comfortable in drawing an inference that the solicitors had actual authority by the failure of the Hume companies to call evidence. I am entitled to infer that the testimony would not have been favourable to Hume's case; Commercial Union Assurance Co of Australia Ltd v Ferrcom Pty Ltd (1991) 22 NSWLR 389 at 418 419 (Handley JA).

47 The only other submission which I need to address under this subheading is not concerned with the question of authority. It is whether the email of 22 December 2006, attaching a copy of the letter of the same date, constituted written notice.

48 Counsel for Hume submitted it did not because an email is an electronic representation of writing and therefore does not constitute writing itself as required by Article 20(3). I reject that submission.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>DTR Nominees Pty Ltd v Mona Homes Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 12 ; (1978) 138 CLR 423</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/12.html</AustLII>
<text>55 In my view neither of these statements constituted a repudiation because they do not evince an intention not to comply with the contract as correctly interpreted; DTR Nominees Pty Ltd v Mona Homes Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 12 ; (1978) 138 CLR 423 at 431-432 (Stephen, Mason &amp; Jacobs JJ).

56 In my opinion there is no warrant for the imposition of a condition that Exact pay the compensation required by Article 21.

57 In my earlier judgment at [12] I said that the meaning of Article 21(1)(a) is not entirely clear, although it plainly enough entitles Hume to substantial compensation on termination of the Distributorship Agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Finishing Services Pty Ltd v Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/177.html</AustLII>
<text>52 In Mannai Investment Co Ltd v Eagle Star Life Assurance Co Ltd [1997] UKHL 19 ; (1997) AC 749 at 771, Lord Steyn observed that in determining the meaning of the language of a commercial agreement the law favours a "commercially sensible construction". It is hostile to technical interpretations and undue emphasis on niceties of language; see also Finishing Services Pty Ltd v Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 177 at [25] (Kiefel, Sundberg &amp; Edmonds JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>IVI Pty Ltd v Baycrown Pty Ltd [2005] QCA 205</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QCA/2005/205.html</AustLII>
<text>38 It is true, as counsel for Hume submitted, that in general a solicitor does not have implied or ostensible authority to accept contractual notices on behalf of a client, particularly where that amounts to the exercise of a substantive right; see IVI Pty Ltd v Baycrown Pty Ltd [2005] QCA 205 at [4] and [33]; see especially the helpful review of the authorities by Keane JA at [33] [44].

39 However, I do not need to consider the questions of implied or ostensible authority because in my opinion Messrs Home Wilkinson Lowry had actual authority to receive the notice.

40 This is to be inferred from two pieces of evidence. First, on 20 January 2006, Home Wilkinson Lowry wrote to Exact Software Australia. The letter stated:
 
 "We shall be dealing with matters arising under the Distributorship Agreement directly with Exact on behalf of our client."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Mannai Investment Co Ltd v Eagle Star Life Assurance Co Ltd [1997] UKHL 19 ; (1997) AC 749</tocase>
<text>52 In Mannai Investment Co Ltd v Eagle Star Life Assurance Co Ltd [1997] UKHL 19 ; (1997) AC 749 at 771, Lord Steyn observed that in determining the meaning of the language of a commercial agreement the law favours a "commercially sensible construction". It is hostile to technical interpretations and undue emphasis on niceties of language; see also Finishing Services Pty Ltd v Lactos Fresh Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 177 at [25] (Kiefel, Sundberg &amp; Edmonds JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McGuren v Simpson [2004] NSWSC 35</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2004/35.html</AustLII>
<text>49 The requirement of written notice is to be construed in light of the fact that this is a commercial agreement made between two companies engaged in the computer software business. I would be blinding myself to commercial and technological realities to find that an email communication in the present circumstances was not written notice; McGuren v Simpson [2004] NSWSC 35 at [20] [21].

50 There was no suggestion that the email was not received.

51 Hume submitted that the letter of 22 December 2006 was ineffective to terminate the Distributorship Agreement because it did not convey an unequivocal election. This submission focussed upon the use of the words "intention to terminate". This was said to amount to an indication of an intention to send a further notice, at a future date, actually terminating the agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Townsend Carriers Ltd v Pzifer Ltd (1977) 33 Prop &amp; Comp R 361</tocase>
<text>27 I should add that it is unnecessary for such a notice to disclose the agency; Townsend Carriers at 365. In any event, the letter of 22 December 2006 stated that the solicitors acted for Exact and that "our client" notifies its intention to terminate.

28 For reasons stated under Issue 2, Article 20(3) did not preclude the giving of notice to an agent, provided of course that the agent had authority to receive it.

29 The same principles of agency apply to the giving and receipt of a notice. Megarry VC said in Townsend Carriers at 365 that he did not "think that the principle it is more blessed to give than to receive is part of the law of landlord and tenant." Nor in my opinion is it part of the principles that apply to the exercise of a contractual power of termination of a commercial contract.

30 Before turning to the principles of agency, it is necessary to deal with the circumstances in which the letter was physically delivered to Hume's solicitors.

31 I am satisfied by the evidence of Ms Naylor, a paralegal employed by Bakers, that she delivered the letter to the offices of the Hume companies' solicitors, Messrs Home Wilkinson Lowry, shortly before noon on 22 December 2006. I am also satisfied that the receptionist accepted service even though the solicitor on the record, Mr Webeck, was not in the office. The affidavit of Ms Cameron does not establish the contrary position.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Young v Lamb (2001) 10 BPR 97867</tocase>
<text>21 Townsend Carriers Ltd v Pfizer Ltd ( 1977) 33 Prop &amp; Comp R 361 is authority for the proposition that where an agreement does not preclude the giving of notice by an agent, the notice can be given by the agent in its own name; at 365 per Megarry VC. See also Young v Lamb (2001) 10 BPR 97867 at [36] [38] per Stein JA (Mason P &amp; Hodgson JA agreeing).

22 Counsel for Hume sought to advance an argument that the right of "either party" to terminate under Article 20(3) precluded notice by an agent. This submission was based upon the distinction drawn in Article 18(2) between "the Distributor" and its "employees, agents and advisors".

23 However, in my opinion, Article 18(2) must be read in its own context. It provides for the obligations of confidentiality contained in Article 18(1) to apply to Hume's agents. Its basis may be thought to be that Hume may not have absolute control of an agent's use of confidential information.

53 Applying this approach, in my opinion the letter conveyed clearly and unequivocally that the Distributorship Agreement is to terminate with effect on and from 31 March 2007. If authority is needed for this proposition, it may be found in Ballas v Theophilos (No 2) [1957] HCA 90 ; (1957) 98 CLR 193 at 204-205; see also Young v Lamb at [28].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>