<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Comcare v Holt [2007] FCA 405 (22 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/405.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Rope [2004] FCA 540 ; (2004) 135 FCR 443</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/540.html</AustLII>
<text>20 There were three arguments advanced by Comcare on the appeal. They were:
 
 (1) The AAT had not applied the principles discussed by Stone J in Comcare v Rope [2004] FCA 540 ; (2004) 135 FCR 443 at 448, at [17], and in particular that it did not consider the prospective benefits of the proposed treatment against its prospective costs, that is that it did not weigh the benefit of the retreat against the cost of obtaining it. It was said that the AAT erred by proceeding on the basis that in the absence of a cheaper alternative, the treatment was reasonable, because it failed to consider whether the cost of the proposed treatment was reasonable in the circumstances. That was said to be a failure to take material facts into account and to examine them in relation to a matter the Tribunal had to determine so as to amount to an error of law.
 (2) The AAT took into account irrelevant considerations, namely that Comcare had previously funded such medical treatment, and secondly that Comcare had an obligation upon it to demonstrate an alternative medical treatment that has equivalent therapeutic benefit but at a lower cost.
 (3) The AAT failed to comply with the obligation imposed by s 43(2) of the AAT Act and failed to deal with a submission seriously advanced by Comcare, relevant to the issue before the Tribunal and worthy of consideration, namely that any benefit Mr Holt obtained from the medical treatment was outweighed by the cost of treatment. As to the third argument, Comcare's statement of facts and contentions before the AAT included the proposition that any benefit to Mr Holt from attending the retreat was outweighed by the cost of obtaining the treatment (as the AAT noted about $1650). It was contended that Comcare's contention in that regard was not addressed in the AAT's reasons at all.

21 Counsel for the parties were agreed on the principles to be applied in determining whether the proposed treatment was reasonable for Mr Holt to obtain in the circumstances. In Rope 135 FCR at 448, at [17], Stone J said:
 
 I accept, however, that the reference in s 16(1) to treatment being 'reasonable to obtain in the circumstances' is a clear indication that, in this case, the Tribunal was required to engage in a costs/benefit analysis in relation to PNI treatment. The Tribunal needed, among other things, to weigh the benefit of PNI treatment against the cost of obtaining it (given that the treatment was available only in Townsville), taking into account any other treatment available to Mrs Rope.

22 In that case, the employee had suffered a compensatable injury and had received psychoneuroimmunology (PNI) treatment from a psychotherapist in Canberra. The psychotherapist had subsequently moved her practice to Townsville and the issue was whether the employee was entitled to recover from Comcare the costs of her travel to Townsville to continue her PNI treatment. There was no equivalent treatment available in Canberra. The AAT determined that it was reasonable for that employee to obtain PNI treatment and be reimbursed for the cost of travelling to Townsville to obtain it. Justice Stone found no error of law on the part of the AAT in making that decision.

23 Coincidentally, in that case, the argument of Comcare significantly resembles its argument in this matter. It was argued that the AAT had failed to engage in a costs/benefit analysis in determining that it was reasonable for that employee to obtain PNI treatment in Townsville. Justice Stone concluded that the findings of the Tribunal were open to it on the evidence and provided no basis for the Court to interfere with those findings. Her Honour said, after accepting that there was predominant medical opinion that the proposed PNI treatment had therapeutic value for that employee because it assisted her in managing the pain of her injury and improved her quality of life, at 448, at [19]:
 
 the only additional factor to be considered was whether there was any equivalent treatment available in Canberra. The Tribunal stated that Comcare had 'failed to substantiate its assertion that equivalent treatment to that provided to [the employee] is available in Canberra'. I am satisfied that the Tribunal did consider all the circumstances that, under s 16(1), it was required to consider in determining if it was reasonable for [the employee] to obtain PNI treatment. The findings that the Tribunal made were open to it on the evidence. It is not for this Court to interfere with those findings.

24 The first contention is based upon the observations of the AAT set out in [19] above.

25 I agree that it would have been erroneous for the AAT generally to declare that the therapeutic treatment is unreasonable only if Comcare establishes that there is alternative treatment with equivalent therapeutic benefit available at a lower cost. There may be circumstances where treatment is unreasonable because its anticipated therapeutic benefit does not justify the expense involved in the circumstances. Section 16(1) of the SRC Act does not indicate that a proposed treatment is reasonable unless alternative treatment of more or less equivalent therapeutic benefit and at a lesser cost is shown by Comcare to be available. That is consistent with the approach of Stone J in Rope [2004] FCA 540 ; 135 FCR 443. Of course, it will be common for the reasonableness of proposed medical treatment to be assessed in the light of alternative treatment options, but that is not necessarily so. There might be cases where the cost of the proposed treatment, even if no other treatment options were available, would lead to the view that the proposed treatment is unreasonable having regard to its anticipated benefit. Such a circumstance is, of course, likely to be uncommon if only because treating medical practitioners generally act responsibly and with sound medical judgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bashar v Comcare (2002) 69 ALD 784</tocase>
<text>26 It is plain enough that sometimes proposed therapeutic treatment will be unreasonable because there is some alternative treatment available with potentially similar benefits at a lesser cost. There may be a balancing involved where the potential therapeutic benefits are less, but the cost is significantly less. The extent to which such treatment has been undertaken in the past and the degree of its success may also be relevant. There may be cases, as Comcare points out, where proposed treatment, although of therapeutic benefit, is unreasonable having regard to the extent of the anticipated benefit of the cost involved, even if no similar treatment had previously been undertaken. There may be cases, also as Comcare points out, where treatment like the proposed treatment which in the past has had some therapeutic benefit may no longer be reasonable because the extent of the therapeutic benefit no longer justifies the cost in the light of past experience: see e.g. Bashar v Comcare (2002) 69 ALD 784. There may be other illustrations of facts relevant to the determination of reasonableness of proposed medical treatment.

27 However, in my view, the remarks of the AAT complained of must be seen in the context of the particular case. The context of the case, as explained above in [12] is that Comcare claimed that the treatment was not reasonable in the circumstances for two specific reasons, namely the availability of alternative treatment with potentially similar therapeutic benefits and at a much lesser cost either at home, or otherwise in Alice Springs. That was the primary case which the AAT was called upon to address and it did so. In my view its comments in the passage of concern to Comcare must be read in that context. If they were to be read as supporting the general proposition set out at the concluding part of its reasons. I would agree that the AAT had fallen into error.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>28 In my judgment, the AAT also did not fall into error in the manner asserted in the second ground of appeal. The AAT referred to the fact that Comcare had previously funded the retreat or a similar retreat. It did not suggest that, for that reason, any further retreats are necessarily to be regarded as reasonable. It would have been erroneous to have taken that step. It referred to those facts simply to record that, in the past, there had been therapeutic benefit experienced from such retreats. If there had not been, the case for the retreat being reasonable would have been much weaker. In my view, where proposed treatment is the same or similar to that previously performed, the extent to which the previous treatment had generated therapeutic benefit is relevant to determining the reasonableness of the proposed further treatment. I think that is all that the Tribunal did when it referred to Comcare having previously funded similar retreats, namely to take account of the fact of previous similar retreats and the extent to which in the past such retreats had produced therapeutic benefit: see generally Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272.

29 The observation that Comcare had not demonstrated an alternative medical treatment with equivalent therapeutic benefit but at a lower cost was one to be seen in the context of the case. In this case, the Tribunal rejected the first of Comcare's two propositions (set out at [12] above) because it was not satisfied that the alternative of "home retreat" would produce therapeutic benefits similar to those of the retreat. It did so in addressing Comcare's assertion that, in the circumstances and on the evidence, there was such alternative treatment available. The AAT was obliged to make a finding upon it. It rejected the contention because there was no cogent evidence to support it. The Tribunal did not err in concluding that, on the evidence, the alternative of a retreat conducted by the Northern Territory Buddhist Society in Alice Springs was not an available reasonable alternative treatment. It was true to its role as a substitute arbiter of the facts for the primary decision-maker upon the material before it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McDonald v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 1 FCR 354</tocase>
<text>30 As a matter of commonsense, if Comcare wished the AAT to find that the Northern Territory Buddhist Society would probably offer a retreat with similar benefits in Alice Springs, more evidence in support of that assertion was desirable. In a practical sense, in the particular circumstances, such evidence would have been adduced by Comcare. That is not to impose any onus of proof upon Comcare: cf McDonald v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 1 FCR 354; Comcare v Nichols [1999] FCA 209 at [18] . Mr Holt sought to have a proposed medical treatment paid by Comcare. He was entitled to payment if the treatment was reasonable in all the circumstances. He had the support of his general practitioner. In the normal course, that would be sufficient. Merely because Comcare referred to the Northern Territory Buddhist Society website, Mr Holt did not have to prove that the Society provided an alternative treatment option available to him of probable equivalent therapeutic benefit and at a lower cost. A moment's pause fortifies that conclusion. Were it otherwise, every time an injured person sought medical treatment, that person would otherwise have to positively adduce evidence that the treatment could not be provided at a cheaper price by some other medical practitioner, or that no other treatment of equivalent therapeutic value would be available at a lesser price through another medical practitioner. The AAT, in my view, correctly decided the reasonableness of the retreat on the evidence and in all the circumstances.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Nichols [1999] FCA 209</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/209.html</AustLII>
<text>30 As a matter of commonsense, if Comcare wished the AAT to find that the Northern Territory Buddhist Society would probably offer a retreat with similar benefits in Alice Springs, more evidence in support of that assertion was desirable. In a practical sense, in the particular circumstances, such evidence would have been adduced by Comcare. That is not to impose any onus of proof upon Comcare: cf McDonald v Director-General of Social Security (1984) 1 FCR 354; Comcare v Nichols [1999] FCA 209 at [18] . Mr Holt sought to have a proposed medical treatment paid by Comcare. He was entitled to payment if the treatment was reasonable in all the circumstances. He had the support of his general practitioner. In the normal course, that would be sufficient. Merely because Comcare referred to the Northern Territory Buddhist Society website, Mr Holt did not have to prove that the Society provided an alternative treatment option available to him of probable equivalent therapeutic benefit and at a lower cost. A moment's pause fortifies that conclusion. Were it otherwise, every time an injured person sought medical treatment, that person would otherwise have to positively adduce evidence that the treatment could not be provided at a cheaper price by some other medical practitioner, or that no other treatment of equivalent therapeutic value would be available at a lesser price through another medical practitioner. The AAT, in my view, correctly decided the reasonableness of the retreat on the evidence and in all the circumstances.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>