<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Retractable Technologies v Occupational and Medical Innovations [2007] FCA 545 (17 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/545.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Occupational and Medical Innovations Limited v Retractable Technologies Inc. [2006] FCA 1814</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1814.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The applicant, Retractable Technologies Inc ('RTI') seeks leave to appeal pursuant to s 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 and O 52, r 10 of the Federal Court Rules from an interlocutory judgment of Dowsett J ( Occupational and Medical Innovations Limited v Retractable Technologies Inc. [2006] FCA 1814 ( OMI v RTI )) dismissing RTI's application for preliminary discovery of documents by the respondent, Occupational and Medical Innovations Limited ('OMI') pursuant to O 15A, r 6 of the Federal Court Rules .

3 In the primary application, RTI sought preliminary discovery of a range of documents relating to communications between OMI and its contracting party China Medical Group Inc ('CMG') and/or communications between OMI and an entity described as Double Dove Group Co Ltd ('DDGCL') and other entities said to be related to DDGCL concerning the manufacture, sterilization, packaging and supply by CMG to OMI of a product described as a 'retractable syringe'. The material before the primary Judge comprised five volumes of evidence including one volume (Volume 5) containing confidential information and was therefore comprehensive. For the purposes of these reasons, I have made reference to a number of documents from the confidential volume referred to in submissions before the court on the present application. References to those documents do not include any reference to the commercially sensitive aspects of the documents.

4 Order 15A, r 6, contemplates that where there is reasonable cause to believe that an applicant has or may have the right to obtain relief in the court from an ascertained person; the applicant, after making all reasonable enquiries, does not have sufficient information to enable a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding in the court; and there is reasonable cause to believe that a person 'has or is likely to have or has had or is likely to have had' possession of any document relating to the question of whether the applicant has the right to obtain the postulated relief (and inspection of the documents by the applicant would assist in making a decision whether to commence a proceeding), the court may order that the identified person make discovery of the relevant documents to the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>5 In considering the evidence and dismissing RTI's application, the primary Judge exercised a discretion to be exercised according to settled principle. In seeking leave to appeal from the exercise of that discretion, the considerations are whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary Judge is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant its being reconsidered by the Full Court and whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused supposing the decision to be wrong ( D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ; Jarrett v Seymour (1993) 46 FCR 557 at 559 and 560 per Lockhart, Sheppard and Beaumont JJ).

20 Although plainly enough an application for leave to appeal does not involve a reconsideration of the primary application other than to determine whether the D&eacute;cor Corporation v Dart Industries test is satisfied, it is necessary to consider the contextual facts of the primary application in dealing with the contended errors on the part of the primary Judge.

21 OMI is the patentee of an Australian patent having a priority date of 22 February 2000 for a device described in the patent, in terms of the object of the invention, as 'a single use syringe having a spring biased needle which can shoot back into a hollow plunger stem after use'. The patent describes the problems reflected in the prior art for needle devices, the features of OMI's invention, exhibits particular drawings and defines the integers of each monopoly claim by reference to claims 1 to 13. On 28 October 2003, OMI (or at least a company described as OMI Manufacturing Pty Ltd which for present purposes has been treated by the parties as OMI) entered into a manufacturing and distribution agreement with CMG.

22 The manufacturing and distribution agreement contains these terms:
 
 
 (a) CMG agrees to manufacture the Product in China (the 'Territory'). OMI grants CMG exclusive rights to manufacture the Product worldwide . If CMG cannot supply the Product OMI reserves the right to source an alternative manufacturer. (cl. 2.1) The Product is defined by the schedule to mean each OMI retractable syringe manufactured by CMG in accordance with nominated specifications. The schedule does not identify any specifications. 
 (b) CMG warrants that the Product shall strictly conform with the specifications listed in the schedule (cl. 2.4(c))
 (c) CMG agrees to make the necessary modifications to its plant/s to enable it to manufacture the Product in accordance with the production requirements set out in schedule 3. (cl. 2.5)
 (d) CMG agrees to manufacture the Product only at the locations agreed between the parties from time to time. (cl. 2.6)
 (e) CMG agrees that OMI shall have the right, on reasonable written notice, to make inspections including of Product manufactured by CMG and plant locations where CMG manufactures the Product. (cl. 2.8)
 (f) Schedule 3 deals with 'pricing, annual purchase volumes and production requirements' and sets out the pricing for the Product. The pricing provision contemplates that CMG will supply OMI with a retractable syringe of various dimensions including a 1 ml, 3 ml, 5 ml and 10 ml Product. (cl. 2.9, Schedule 3) 
 (g) Schedule 3(1) contemplates that upon supply and purchase of a substantial number of units of the 1 ml, 3 ml and 5 ml Product, prices payable by OMI will be adjusted. Schedule 3 provides that a production year means each 12 month period commencing on the date of delivery of the first order of 1 ml, 3 ml, 5 ml and 10 ml Products or anniversary thereof. Schedule 3 also provides that CMG will invoice OMI for Product manufactured in accordance with a purchase order, on delivery of the Product and invoices will be paid within 90 days. 
 (h) Schedule 3(2) provides that CMG will provide OMI with a certain number of units of the 1 ml version no later than 31 January 2004 and units of the 3 ml, 5 ml and 10 ml version no later than eight calendar months after the date of agreement. 
 (i) CMG may use such trade marks and names in the Territory as are approved from time to time by OMI on all product. The agreed brand name will be Double Dove and will include the OMI Chinese patent number on all packaging. All such uses shall be consistent with all specifications notified by OMI from time to time. (cl. 2.10, cl. 3.3)
 (j) Clause 2.11 provides 'CMG agrees to manufacture Product in accordance with written purchase orders received from OMI. Each purchase order must set out the number and type of Product required, the date delivery, the delivery point and any other matters as agreed between the parties from time to time. If CMG is unable to meet a purchase order, it must notify OMI as soon as it becomes aware that it will not be able to meet the purchase order'. 
 (k) CMG may not subcontract any part of the manufacturing process in relation to the Product. (cl. 2.13)
 (l) CMG will have the exclusive right to distribute the Product in the Territory. (cl. 3.1)
 (m) The term of the agreement is five years from 28 October 2003 plus one three year option unless terminated by written notice upon material breach by either party. The option might be exercised by either party at least six months before the end of the initial five year term by notice expressing a 'desire to exercise the three year option' and in that event, 'the parties agree to enter into good faith negotiations in respect of extending this agreement for one further term of three years'. (cl. 4.1)
 (n) Clause 4.1 contemplates that OMI might give its written consent for CMG to incur costs in relation to particular manufacturing equipment and in such a circumstance OMI accepts a cost liability for an unamortized portion of the cost upon certain events. 
 (o) CMG agrees to procure Vital Care to keep in place product liability to a certain value in terms and conditions wholly satisfactory to OMI. (cl. 4.5)
 (p) CMG agrees that it will provide OMI or its agent with any information as may be reasonably requested by OMI in relation to the manufacture of the Product. (cl. 4.08)
 (q) CMG and OMI agree to treat any information communicated to it or any other person in relation to the Product as confidential subject to identified permitted disclosure. (cl. 4.9) The confidentiality clause is to survive the termination of the agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jarrett v Seymour (1993) 46 FCR 557</tocase>
<text>5 In considering the evidence and dismissing RTI's application, the primary Judge exercised a discretion to be exercised according to settled principle. In seeking leave to appeal from the exercise of that discretion, the considerations are whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary Judge is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant its being reconsidered by the Full Court and whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused supposing the decision to be wrong ( D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ; Jarrett v Seymour (1993) 46 FCR 557 at 559 and 560 per Lockhart, Sheppard and Beaumont JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>House v The King (1936) 55 CLR 449</tocase>
<text>6 In addressing those considerations it is important to remember that the question of whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary Judge is attended by sufficient doubt is to be considered in the context of the observation of their Honours Dixon, Evatt and McTiernan JJ in the well known passage from House v The King (1936) 55 CLR 449 at pp 504 and 505. See also Johnston v Cameron &amp; Ors [2002] FCAFC 251 ; (2002) 124 FCR 160 (FC, Branson, Tamberlin and Finkelstein JJ) per Branson J p 163 [9] and Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (FC, Bowen CJ, Frankie and Deane JJ) (1980) 29 ALR 228 at p 232 per Bowen CJ.

89 As a result, the conclusion of the primary Judge that RTI's case 'cannot possibly succeed' [16] on the footing discussed at [62] to [88] of these reasons is attended by sufficient doubt as to warrant reconsideration by the Full Court subject to the question of whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused. However, such a conclusion assumes at its centre that the supply of syringes by CMG involves the use by CMG of RTI's confidential information.

104 In those cases where there is no closely substitutable field of common activity (such as the manufacture of immediately substitutable retractable syringes), use of another's confidential information may be more readily identifiable whether in the form of etchings submitted to a publisher, confidential information contained within a manuscript, an instruction manual provided to a third party or a description of a methodology for a manufacturing process or business method. In the absence of very precise identification particularly in the case however of parties involved in closely substitutable fields of common endeavour, of the information, its confidential character and its use, assertions or general conclusionary contentions relied upon to support a claim of use are insufficient and will not give rise to inferences of use.

105 An illustration of the distinction might be that although Charles Darwin received on 18 June 1858 Alfred Wallace's letter setting out a theory of natural selection in the evolution of species, Darwin's address to the Linnean Society in London on 1 July 1858 outlining his central thesis of the origin of species by means of natural selection was the emanation of years of his own research, field studies and thinking.

106 The claims of use of information said to be confidential to RTI made by paragraphs 70(a), (b), (c), (d), (e), (f) and (g); and paragraph 72(b), (d); and paragraphs 73(a), (b), (c), (d), (e), (f), (g), (h), (i) and (j) against the background of 'SW11' are no more than an assertion. As to the plunger seal, RTI's evidence is that OMI uses the 'specific type' of rubber used by RTI. However, in the light of OMI's response that it uses santoprene and specified santoprene 181 as early as January 2002, RTI says that santoprene is a form of rubber. That controversy of fact seems to be inconsistent with the initial contention of use of the 'specific type' of rubber.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnston v Cameron &amp; Ors [2002] FCAFC 251 ; (2002) 124 FCR 160</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/251.html</AustLII>
<text>6 In addressing those considerations it is important to remember that the question of whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary Judge is attended by sufficient doubt is to be considered in the context of the observation of their Honours Dixon, Evatt and McTiernan JJ in the well known passage from House v The King (1936) 55 CLR 449 at pp 504 and 505. See also Johnston v Cameron &amp; Ors [2002] FCAFC 251 ; (2002) 124 FCR 160 (FC, Branson, Tamberlin and Finkelstein JJ) per Branson J p 163 [9] and Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (FC, Bowen CJ, Frankie and Deane JJ) (1980) 29 ALR 228 at p 232 per Bowen CJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (1980) 29 ALR 228</tocase>
<text>6 In addressing those considerations it is important to remember that the question of whether in all the circumstances the decision of the primary Judge is attended by sufficient doubt is to be considered in the context of the observation of their Honours Dixon, Evatt and McTiernan JJ in the well known passage from House v The King (1936) 55 CLR 449 at pp 504 and 505. See also Johnston v Cameron &amp; Ors [2002] FCAFC 251 ; (2002) 124 FCR 160 (FC, Branson, Tamberlin and Finkelstein JJ) per Branson J p 163 [9] and Australian Broadcasting Commission v Parish (FC, Bowen CJ, Frankie and Deane JJ) (1980) 29 ALR 228 at p 232 per Bowen CJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>St. George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147</tocase>
<text>16 As to the settled principles to be applied in an application pursuant to O 15A, r 6, the principles are these: the rule is to be beneficially construed and afforded the fullest scope its language reasonably allows; the 'proper brake' upon any excesses in the application of the rule lies in the exercise of the court's discretion ; the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' is an objective one; 'reasonable cause to believe' strikes a relationship with whether the applicant has a right to obtain particular relief or whether the applicant may have a right to relief and thus hypothecates a remedial outcome in the proposed proceedings on the assumption the evidence makes out each integer in the applicant's cause of action; such a belief, on either footing, requires more than mere assertion, suspicion or conjecture; a mere possibility of a right to relief is insufficient; the evidence, that is, an assessment of all the evidence, must incline the mind towards acceptance of the existence of a matter or fact in controversy out of which a right to relief arises or may arise; it is no answer to an application under O 15A, r 6 to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a 'fishing expedition'; the rule contemplates that an applicant will forensically examine the field of documents the subject of the order expressly for the purpose of enabling a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding; although the rule contemplates such an examination of the respondent's documents the subject of the order, the invasive nature of the order is predicated upon an objectively established reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has or may have a right to contended relief; although an applicant does not need to establish a prima facie case, an applicant must establish that there is a reasonable cause to believe that each element of the potential cause of action is made out; although the threshold test may be set at quite a low level, the evidence must establish facts crystallising all the elements of a cause of action grounding the possible grant of the contended relief (see: St. George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 per Hely J [25] [29]; Hooper &amp; Ors v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at pp 11 and 12 per Wilcox, Sackville and Katz JJ [35] [40]; Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2006) 223 ALR 238 at pp 240 and 241 [8] [16] per Lindgren J; C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864 at [12] per Gyles J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hooper &amp; Ors v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1584.html</AustLII>
<text>16 As to the settled principles to be applied in an application pursuant to O 15A, r 6, the principles are these: the rule is to be beneficially construed and afforded the fullest scope its language reasonably allows; the 'proper brake' upon any excesses in the application of the rule lies in the exercise of the court's discretion ; the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' is an objective one; 'reasonable cause to believe' strikes a relationship with whether the applicant has a right to obtain particular relief or whether the applicant may have a right to relief and thus hypothecates a remedial outcome in the proposed proceedings on the assumption the evidence makes out each integer in the applicant's cause of action; such a belief, on either footing, requires more than mere assertion, suspicion or conjecture; a mere possibility of a right to relief is insufficient; the evidence, that is, an assessment of all the evidence, must incline the mind towards acceptance of the existence of a matter or fact in controversy out of which a right to relief arises or may arise; it is no answer to an application under O 15A, r 6 to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a 'fishing expedition'; the rule contemplates that an applicant will forensically examine the field of documents the subject of the order expressly for the purpose of enabling a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding; although the rule contemplates such an examination of the respondent's documents the subject of the order, the invasive nature of the order is predicated upon an objectively established reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has or may have a right to contended relief; although an applicant does not need to establish a prima facie case, an applicant must establish that there is a reasonable cause to believe that each element of the potential cause of action is made out; although the threshold test may be set at quite a low level, the evidence must establish facts crystallising all the elements of a cause of action grounding the possible grant of the contended relief (see: St. George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 per Hely J [25] [29]; Hooper &amp; Ors v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at pp 11 and 12 per Wilcox, Sackville and Katz JJ [35] [40]; Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2006) 223 ALR 238 at pp 240 and 241 [8] [16] per Lindgren J; C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864 at [12] per Gyles J).

18 First , the reference in the authorities to the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' as an objective test, recognises that the phrase in O 15A, r 6(a) 'where there is reasonable cause to believe' connotes 'where to the court at the hearing of the application' there is reasonable cause to believe. Secondly , a demonstrated controversy of fact emerging on the evidence in the application, to be resolved by findings of fact in the contemplated proceeding out of which a right to obtain identified relief is said to arise, will not answer a contention that there is reasonable cause to believe that the applicant may have a right to the relevant relief. However, the controversy of fact must demonstrate that first, the contended facts go beyond mere suspicion, assertion or conjecture and secondly, potential findings of fact in favour of the applicant support all elements of the cause of action that may give rise to the contended relief (see Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 per Sackville J [28]; Paxus Services Limited v People Bank Pty Limited (1990) 99 ALR 728 per Burchett J (NG 670/1990); Hooper v Kirella (supra) [39]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 per Sackville J [24]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2006) 223 ALR 238</tocase>
<text>16 As to the settled principles to be applied in an application pursuant to O 15A, r 6, the principles are these: the rule is to be beneficially construed and afforded the fullest scope its language reasonably allows; the 'proper brake' upon any excesses in the application of the rule lies in the exercise of the court's discretion ; the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' is an objective one; 'reasonable cause to believe' strikes a relationship with whether the applicant has a right to obtain particular relief or whether the applicant may have a right to relief and thus hypothecates a remedial outcome in the proposed proceedings on the assumption the evidence makes out each integer in the applicant's cause of action; such a belief, on either footing, requires more than mere assertion, suspicion or conjecture; a mere possibility of a right to relief is insufficient; the evidence, that is, an assessment of all the evidence, must incline the mind towards acceptance of the existence of a matter or fact in controversy out of which a right to relief arises or may arise; it is no answer to an application under O 15A, r 6 to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a 'fishing expedition'; the rule contemplates that an applicant will forensically examine the field of documents the subject of the order expressly for the purpose of enabling a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding; although the rule contemplates such an examination of the respondent's documents the subject of the order, the invasive nature of the order is predicated upon an objectively established reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has or may have a right to contended relief; although an applicant does not need to establish a prima facie case, an applicant must establish that there is a reasonable cause to believe that each element of the potential cause of action is made out; although the threshold test may be set at quite a low level, the evidence must establish facts crystallising all the elements of a cause of action grounding the possible grant of the contended relief (see: St. George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 per Hely J [25] [29]; Hooper &amp; Ors v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at pp 11 and 12 per Wilcox, Sackville and Katz JJ [35] [40]; Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2006) 223 ALR 238 at pp 240 and 241 [8] [16] per Lindgren J; C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864 at [12] per Gyles J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1864.html</AustLII>
<text>16 As to the settled principles to be applied in an application pursuant to O 15A, r 6, the principles are these: the rule is to be beneficially construed and afforded the fullest scope its language reasonably allows; the 'proper brake' upon any excesses in the application of the rule lies in the exercise of the court's discretion ; the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' is an objective one; 'reasonable cause to believe' strikes a relationship with whether the applicant has a right to obtain particular relief or whether the applicant may have a right to relief and thus hypothecates a remedial outcome in the proposed proceedings on the assumption the evidence makes out each integer in the applicant's cause of action; such a belief, on either footing, requires more than mere assertion, suspicion or conjecture; a mere possibility of a right to relief is insufficient; the evidence, that is, an assessment of all the evidence, must incline the mind towards acceptance of the existence of a matter or fact in controversy out of which a right to relief arises or may arise; it is no answer to an application under O 15A, r 6 to say that the proceeding is in the nature of a 'fishing expedition'; the rule contemplates that an applicant will forensically examine the field of documents the subject of the order expressly for the purpose of enabling a decision to be made whether to commence a proceeding; although the rule contemplates such an examination of the respondent's documents the subject of the order, the invasive nature of the order is predicated upon an objectively established reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has or may have a right to contended relief; although an applicant does not need to establish a prima facie case, an applicant must establish that there is a reasonable cause to believe that each element of the potential cause of action is made out; although the threshold test may be set at quite a low level, the evidence must establish facts crystallising all the elements of a cause of action grounding the possible grant of the contended relief (see: St. George Bank Ltd v Rabo Australia Ltd (2004) 211 ALR 147 per Hely J [25] [29]; Hooper &amp; Ors v Kirella Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1584 ; (1999) 96 FCR 1 at pp 11 and 12 per Wilcox, Sackville and Katz JJ [35] [40]; Glencore International AG v Selwyn Mines Ltd (2006) 223 ALR 238 at pp 240 and 241 [8] [16] per Lindgren J; C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864 at [12] per Gyles J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/549.html</AustLII>
<text>18 First , the reference in the authorities to the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' as an objective test, recognises that the phrase in O 15A, r 6(a) 'where there is reasonable cause to believe' connotes 'where to the court at the hearing of the application' there is reasonable cause to believe. Secondly , a demonstrated controversy of fact emerging on the evidence in the application, to be resolved by findings of fact in the contemplated proceeding out of which a right to obtain identified relief is said to arise, will not answer a contention that there is reasonable cause to believe that the applicant may have a right to the relevant relief. However, the controversy of fact must demonstrate that first, the contended facts go beyond mere suspicion, assertion or conjecture and secondly, potential findings of fact in favour of the applicant support all elements of the cause of action that may give rise to the contended relief (see Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 per Sackville J [28]; Paxus Services Limited v People Bank Pty Limited (1990) 99 ALR 728 per Burchett J (NG 670/1990); Hooper v Kirella (supra) [39]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 per Sackville J [24]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Paxus Services Limited v People Bank Pty Limited (1990) 99 ALR 728</tocase>
<text>18 First , the reference in the authorities to the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' as an objective test, recognises that the phrase in O 15A, r 6(a) 'where there is reasonable cause to believe' connotes 'where to the court at the hearing of the application' there is reasonable cause to believe. Secondly , a demonstrated controversy of fact emerging on the evidence in the application, to be resolved by findings of fact in the contemplated proceeding out of which a right to obtain identified relief is said to arise, will not answer a contention that there is reasonable cause to believe that the applicant may have a right to the relevant relief. However, the controversy of fact must demonstrate that first, the contended facts go beyond mere suspicion, assertion or conjecture and secondly, potential findings of fact in favour of the applicant support all elements of the cause of action that may give rise to the contended relief (see Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 per Sackville J [28]; Paxus Services Limited v People Bank Pty Limited (1990) 99 ALR 728 per Burchett J (NG 670/1990); Hooper v Kirella (supra) [39]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 per Sackville J [24]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536</tocase>
<text>18 First , the reference in the authorities to the test for determining 'reasonable cause to believe' as an objective test, recognises that the phrase in O 15A, r 6(a) 'where there is reasonable cause to believe' connotes 'where to the court at the hearing of the application' there is reasonable cause to believe. Secondly , a demonstrated controversy of fact emerging on the evidence in the application, to be resolved by findings of fact in the contemplated proceeding out of which a right to obtain identified relief is said to arise, will not answer a contention that there is reasonable cause to believe that the applicant may have a right to the relevant relief. However, the controversy of fact must demonstrate that first, the contended facts go beyond mere suspicion, assertion or conjecture and secondly, potential findings of fact in favour of the applicant support all elements of the cause of action that may give rise to the contended relief (see Minister for Health and Aged Care v Harrington Associates Ltd [1999] FCA 549 per Sackville J [28]; Paxus Services Limited v People Bank Pty Limited (1990) 99 ALR 728 per Burchett J (NG 670/1990); Hooper v Kirella (supra) [39]; Quanta Software International Pty Ltd v Computer Management Services Pty Ltd (2000) 175 ALR 536 at 541-2 per Sackville J [24]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Development Corporation Pty Ltd v White Constructions Ltd &amp; Anor 189 ALR 266</tocase>
<text>61 The evidence does not establish actual knowledge of the terms of any contract between DDGCL and RTI nor any intention to interfere with the contract ( Australian Development Corporation Pty Ltd v White Constructions Ltd &amp; Anor 189 ALR 266 per Handley JA at [89]) nor OMI's actual or constructive (in any analogous sense contemplated by Barnes v Addy (1874) LR 9 Ch App 244 per Lord Selborne at 251-252) knowledge of CMG's contended use of RTI's confidential information and thus the contended error on the part of the primary Judge is not made out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Barnes v Addy (1874) LR 9 Ch App 244</tocase>
<text>61 The evidence does not establish actual knowledge of the terms of any contract between DDGCL and RTI nor any intention to interfere with the contract ( Australian Development Corporation Pty Ltd v White Constructions Ltd &amp; Anor 189 ALR 266 per Handley JA at [89]) nor OMI's actual or constructive (in any analogous sense contemplated by Barnes v Addy (1874) LR 9 Ch App 244 per Lord Selborne at 251-252) knowledge of CMG's contended use of RTI's confidential information and thus the contended error on the part of the primary Judge is not made out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Coco v A N Clark (Engineers) Ltd [1969] RPC 41</tocase>
<text>67 In those cases of bilateral litigation between the originator and primary disclosor of confidential information on the one hand and a recipient from the originator on the other, a court exercising equitable jurisdiction will, independently of any contractual obligation, tort, fiduciary duty or rights derived from copyright, trade mark or patent legislation, grant relief against an actual or threatened abuse of confidential information provided the evidence establishes the well-known three elements derived from the authorities identified by Megarry J in Coco v A N Clark (Engineers) Ltd [1969] RPC 41 at 47 applying the observations of Lord Greene in Saltman Engineering Coy Ltd v Campbell Engineering Coy Ltd [1948] RPC 203 at 211 and 215 and Lord Denning in Seager v Copydex Limited [1967] RPC 349 at 366-367.

69 One of the three elements focuses upon whether the confidential information was imparted in circumstances 'importing an obligation of confidence' ( Coco v Clark at p 47) recognising that 'the notion of an obligation of conscience [arises] from the circumstances in or through which the information was communicated or obtained' ( Moorgate Tobacco v Philip Morris at p 438). The relief 'depends on the broad principle of equity that he who has received information in confidence shall not take unfair advantage of it' ( Seager v Copydex per Lord Denning at p 368).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Saltman Engineering Coy Ltd v Campbell Engineering Coy Ltd [1948] RPC 203</tocase>
<text>67 In those cases of bilateral litigation between the originator and primary disclosor of confidential information on the one hand and a recipient from the originator on the other, a court exercising equitable jurisdiction will, independently of any contractual obligation, tort, fiduciary duty or rights derived from copyright, trade mark or patent legislation, grant relief against an actual or threatened abuse of confidential information provided the evidence establishes the well-known three elements derived from the authorities identified by Megarry J in Coco v A N Clark (Engineers) Ltd [1969] RPC 41 at 47 applying the observations of Lord Greene in Saltman Engineering Coy Ltd v Campbell Engineering Coy Ltd [1948] RPC 203 at 211 and 215 and Lord Denning in Seager v Copydex Limited [1967] RPC 349 at 366-367.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Seager v Copydex Limited [1967] RPC 349</tocase>
<text>67 In those cases of bilateral litigation between the originator and primary disclosor of confidential information on the one hand and a recipient from the originator on the other, a court exercising equitable jurisdiction will, independently of any contractual obligation, tort, fiduciary duty or rights derived from copyright, trade mark or patent legislation, grant relief against an actual or threatened abuse of confidential information provided the evidence establishes the well-known three elements derived from the authorities identified by Megarry J in Coco v A N Clark (Engineers) Ltd [1969] RPC 41 at 47 applying the observations of Lord Greene in Saltman Engineering Coy Ltd v Campbell Engineering Coy Ltd [1948] RPC 203 at 211 and 215 and Lord Denning in Seager v Copydex Limited [1967] RPC 349 at 366-367.

69 One of the three elements focuses upon whether the confidential information was imparted in circumstances 'importing an obligation of confidence' ( Coco v Clark at p 47) recognising that 'the notion of an obligation of conscience [arises] from the circumstances in or through which the information was communicated or obtained' ( Moorgate Tobacco v Philip Morris at p 438). The relief 'depends on the broad principle of equity that he who has received information in confidence shall not take unfair advantage of it' ( Seager v Copydex per Lord Denning at p 368).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/73.html</AustLII>
<text>68 The foundation of Equity's intervention is the exclusive jurisdiction to enforce an obligation of conscience arising out of the demonstrated circumstances ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414 per Deane J at 437 and 438.

69 One of the three elements focuses upon whether the confidential information was imparted in circumstances 'importing an obligation of confidence' ( Coco v Clark at p 47) recognising that 'the notion of an obligation of conscience [arises] from the circumstances in or through which the information was communicated or obtained' ( Moorgate Tobacco v Philip Morris at p 438). The relief 'depends on the broad principle of equity that he who has received information in confidence shall not take unfair advantage of it' ( Seager v Copydex per Lord Denning at p 368).

90 In seeking the court's intervention to restrain use of confidential information it is essential that the applicant demonstrate with precision the information said to be confidential and the content of use sought to be attached. Assertions of confidentiality at high levels of abstraction will not establish a basis for relief against a disclosee. In the case of an innocent third party who simply seeks reliance upon a contract struck without notice of a relationship of confidentiality between the primary disclosor and any other party or breach, the requirement for precision is even more acute. The starting point is the identification of the relevant confidential information ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) (supra) per Deane J at 438; Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434 per Gummow J at 443; O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 per Mason J at pp 326 328; Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629 per Harper J, [13], [35]; Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675 per Crockett, Murphy &amp; Ormiston JJ at 711).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johns v Australian Securities Commission [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/56.html</AustLII>
<text>70 In the case, however, of an innocent third party acting bona fide and thus without notice, the circumstances which condition an obligation of conscience are much removed from the commercial intimacy of a bilateral relationship between the originator and primary disclosor and the originator's immediate recipient, importing that obligation. It seems to follow logically in the case of an innocent third party that the court will closely examine the contended circumstances that are said to warrant intervention beyond simply whether the third party has been put on notice and thus identify the 'matters which determine whether a duty of confidence has devolved' upon a third party ( Johns v Australian Securities Commission [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408 at 460, per Gaudron J). The reasons of the primary Judge suggest that his Honour had in mind the notion that since an assessment of the circumstances in which OMI continues to acquire articles of manufacture said to embody RTI's confidential information includes acceptance of the position that OMI acted as an innocent third party for value pursuant to an arms-length contract, the 'relevant circumstances' of the present applicant, properly examined, do not give rise to an obligation of conscience in OMI, rather than a notion of simply applying a derivative proprietary rule that a bona fide third party for value can not be the subject of the court's intervention.

72 In Johns v Australian Securities Commission at 460, Gaudron J recognised that in Foster v Mountford &amp; Rigby Ltd (1976) 29 FLR 233 at p 238, Muirhead J enjoined a publisher on an interlocutory basis from continuing to publish and distribute a book revealing, in breach of an obligation of confidence on the part of the author, sites and objects of deep religious and cultural significance to particular Aboriginal claimant groups, and in Wheatley v Bell [1982] 2 NSWLR 544 at p 550, Helsham CJ (in Equity) enjoined on an interlocutory basis innocent licensees (described as parties who 'have already been licensed or chosen, or engaged, or are either purchasers or potential purchasers') of a promotional business system from using that system notwithstanding that they had apparently paid contracted amounts to a disclosee who had failed to observe an obligation of confidence to the plaintiff disclosor. Gaudron J noted at p 460 that the law had not developed to a point of identifying in a 'definitive or comprehensive way' the matters which would determine whether a duty of confidence might arise in a third party.

74 The decision in Johns v Australian Securities Commission , on this aspect of the matter at least, turned on the basis that the information made available voluntarily to the relevant media organisations had become publicly available and the question of the innocence of the third parties, Australian Broadcasting Corporation and the Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd, would require further determinations of questions of fact. The decision in Foster v Mountford arose out of an ex parte application and the commercial arrangements with the publisher were not examined. The decision in Fraser v Evans concerned the disclosure to an English national newspaper of aspects of a confidential report submitted by the plaintiff as a public relations consultant to the Greek Government. The case seemed not to involve acquisition of confidential information pursuant to an arms-length contract. Although the consultant had no standing to agitate a contended obligation on the part of the newspaper, and the information, in any event, was of such a nature that disclosure was in the public interest, the statement of general principle recognises that a third party who has not received confidential information in confidence might be restrained 'once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence'. The decision in Wheatley v Bell adopted that expression of principle together with the observation of Professor Pettit ( Equity and the Law of Trusts , 3 rd ed (1974)) that a third party who knowingly obtains confidential information in breach of confidence or in any other fraudulent manner will be restrained from use and 'even if a man obtains the confidential information innocently, once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence, he can be restrained from breaking that confidence', as the foundation for the interlocutory orders against the innocent licensees.

81 There is no doubt that the authorities recognise that an innocent third party thus acting bona fide may come into possession of confidential information of a primary disclosor either by reason of a disclosure in breach of an obligation of confidence by the disclosee owed to the primary disclosor or because an entity dealing with the third party may have a degree of interconnection with the initial recipient such that information has been disclosed to that entity in breach of an obligation of confidence and then disclosed to the third party; and, in principle, 'in some circumstances the restraint of an apprehended or continued breach of confidence may involve enjoining third parties' ( Breen v Williams [1995] HCA 63 ; (1996) 186 CLR 71 per Gummow J at p 129; see also, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Lenah Game Meats Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 161 per Gummow and Hayne JJ [137] [2001] HCA 63 ; (2002) 185 ALR 1; and Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 537 and 567; Johns v Australian Securities Commission (supra)). Although Gummow J in Breen v Williams at p 129 was emphasising that the assertion of a right to relief in respect of an obligation of confidence does not rest upon any species of proprietary right, his Honour also notes that the circumstances of disclosure to the third party condition whether such a party will be enjoined.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Best Australia Ltd &amp; Ors v Aquagas Marketing Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1989) 13 IPR 600</tocase>
<text>71 The same principles derived from the in personam jurisdiction apply to the position of third parties ( Best Australia Ltd &amp; Ors v Aquagas Marketing Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1989) 13 IPR 600 at 603). Accordingly, the circumstances in which the third party received the confidential information require close attention to determine whether the conscience of the third party ought to be bound.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Foster v Mountford &amp; Rigby Ltd (1976) 29 FLR 233</tocase>
<text>72 In Johns v Australian Securities Commission at 460, Gaudron J recognised that in Foster v Mountford &amp; Rigby Ltd (1976) 29 FLR 233 at p 238, Muirhead J enjoined a publisher on an interlocutory basis from continuing to publish and distribute a book revealing, in breach of an obligation of confidence on the part of the author, sites and objects of deep religious and cultural significance to particular Aboriginal claimant groups, and in Wheatley v Bell [1982] 2 NSWLR 544 at p 550, Helsham CJ (in Equity) enjoined on an interlocutory basis innocent licensees (described as parties who 'have already been licensed or chosen, or engaged, or are either purchasers or potential purchasers') of a promotional business system from using that system notwithstanding that they had apparently paid contracted amounts to a disclosee who had failed to observe an obligation of confidence to the plaintiff disclosor. Gaudron J noted at p 460 that the law had not developed to a point of identifying in a 'definitive or comprehensive way' the matters which would determine whether a duty of confidence might arise in a third party.

74 The decision in Johns v Australian Securities Commission , on this aspect of the matter at least, turned on the basis that the information made available voluntarily to the relevant media organisations had become publicly available and the question of the innocence of the third parties, Australian Broadcasting Corporation and the Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd, would require further determinations of questions of fact. The decision in Foster v Mountford arose out of an ex parte application and the commercial arrangements with the publisher were not examined. The decision in Fraser v Evans concerned the disclosure to an English national newspaper of aspects of a confidential report submitted by the plaintiff as a public relations consultant to the Greek Government. The case seemed not to involve acquisition of confidential information pursuant to an arms-length contract. Although the consultant had no standing to agitate a contended obligation on the part of the newspaper, and the information, in any event, was of such a nature that disclosure was in the public interest, the statement of general principle recognises that a third party who has not received confidential information in confidence might be restrained 'once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence'. The decision in Wheatley v Bell adopted that expression of principle together with the observation of Professor Pettit ( Equity and the Law of Trusts , 3 rd ed (1974)) that a third party who knowingly obtains confidential information in breach of confidence or in any other fraudulent manner will be restrained from use and 'even if a man obtains the confidential information innocently, once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence, he can be restrained from breaking that confidence', as the foundation for the interlocutory orders against the innocent licensees.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wheatley v Bell [1982] 2 NSWLR 544</tocase>
<text>72 In Johns v Australian Securities Commission at 460, Gaudron J recognised that in Foster v Mountford &amp; Rigby Ltd (1976) 29 FLR 233 at p 238, Muirhead J enjoined a publisher on an interlocutory basis from continuing to publish and distribute a book revealing, in breach of an obligation of confidence on the part of the author, sites and objects of deep religious and cultural significance to particular Aboriginal claimant groups, and in Wheatley v Bell [1982] 2 NSWLR 544 at p 550, Helsham CJ (in Equity) enjoined on an interlocutory basis innocent licensees (described as parties who 'have already been licensed or chosen, or engaged, or are either purchasers or potential purchasers') of a promotional business system from using that system notwithstanding that they had apparently paid contracted amounts to a disclosee who had failed to observe an obligation of confidence to the plaintiff disclosor. Gaudron J noted at p 460 that the law had not developed to a point of identifying in a 'definitive or comprehensive way' the matters which would determine whether a duty of confidence might arise in a third party.

74 The decision in Johns v Australian Securities Commission , on this aspect of the matter at least, turned on the basis that the information made available voluntarily to the relevant media organisations had become publicly available and the question of the innocence of the third parties, Australian Broadcasting Corporation and the Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd, would require further determinations of questions of fact. The decision in Foster v Mountford arose out of an ex parte application and the commercial arrangements with the publisher were not examined. The decision in Fraser v Evans concerned the disclosure to an English national newspaper of aspects of a confidential report submitted by the plaintiff as a public relations consultant to the Greek Government. The case seemed not to involve acquisition of confidential information pursuant to an arms-length contract. Although the consultant had no standing to agitate a contended obligation on the part of the newspaper, and the information, in any event, was of such a nature that disclosure was in the public interest, the statement of general principle recognises that a third party who has not received confidential information in confidence might be restrained 'once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence'. The decision in Wheatley v Bell adopted that expression of principle together with the observation of Professor Pettit ( Equity and the Law of Trusts , 3 rd ed (1974)) that a third party who knowingly obtains confidential information in breach of confidence or in any other fraudulent manner will be restrained from use and 'even if a man obtains the confidential information innocently, once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence, he can be restrained from breaking that confidence', as the foundation for the interlocutory orders against the innocent licensees.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fraser v Evans [1969] 1 Q.B. 349</tocase>
<text>73 Her Honour also noted the statement of principle of Lord Denning in Fraser v Evans [1969] 1 Q.B. 349 at p 361 to the effect that if a person 'comes by [confidential information] innocently, nevertheless once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence he can be restrained from breaking that confidence' and the statement of principle of Goff J in Butler v Board of Trade [1971] Ch. 680 at 690 that 'an innocent recipient of information conveyed in breach of confidence is liable to be restrained'.

74 The decision in Johns v Australian Securities Commission , on this aspect of the matter at least, turned on the basis that the information made available voluntarily to the relevant media organisations had become publicly available and the question of the innocence of the third parties, Australian Broadcasting Corporation and the Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd, would require further determinations of questions of fact. The decision in Foster v Mountford arose out of an ex parte application and the commercial arrangements with the publisher were not examined. The decision in Fraser v Evans concerned the disclosure to an English national newspaper of aspects of a confidential report submitted by the plaintiff as a public relations consultant to the Greek Government. The case seemed not to involve acquisition of confidential information pursuant to an arms-length contract. Although the consultant had no standing to agitate a contended obligation on the part of the newspaper, and the information, in any event, was of such a nature that disclosure was in the public interest, the statement of general principle recognises that a third party who has not received confidential information in confidence might be restrained 'once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence'. The decision in Wheatley v Bell adopted that expression of principle together with the observation of Professor Pettit ( Equity and the Law of Trusts , 3 rd ed (1974)) that a third party who knowingly obtains confidential information in breach of confidence or in any other fraudulent manner will be restrained from use and 'even if a man obtains the confidential information innocently, once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence, he can be restrained from breaking that confidence', as the foundation for the interlocutory orders against the innocent licensees.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Butler v Board of Trade [1971] Ch. 680</tocase>
<text>73 Her Honour also noted the statement of principle of Lord Denning in Fraser v Evans [1969] 1 Q.B. 349 at p 361 to the effect that if a person 'comes by [confidential information] innocently, nevertheless once he gets to know that it was originally given in confidence he can be restrained from breaking that confidence' and the statement of principle of Goff J in Butler v Board of Trade [1971] Ch. 680 at 690 that 'an innocent recipient of information conveyed in breach of confidence is liable to be restrained'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1951) 68 RPC 190</tocase>
<text>75 These expressions of principle concerning rights to relief against third parties are stated at a reasonably high level of abstraction and do not deal 'definitively or comprehensively' with the 'matters' which determine ultimately whether a duty of confidence has devolved upon a third party. The applicant also relies upon what is said to be an applied expression of the principle to a bona fide third party for value in the decisions of Lloyd-Jacob J in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1951) 68 RPC 190 and the Court of Appeal in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1952) 69 RPC 10 per Evershed M.R. and Denning and Morris LL.JJ. In that case, Lloyd-Jacob J granted an injunction to restrain a publisher from publishing, pursuant to a contract with the author, a book containing confidential information of the plaintiff concerning the application of principles of business management to particular problems encountered at various functional levels of commercial activity. The publisher struck the contract innocently but once put on notice, prior to publication, of the confidential content incorporated within the work, the jurisdiction to grant an injunction was found by Lloyd-Jacob J to arise on the footing that 'an innocent mind at the time of contract could not overcome the consequences of full knowledge at or before the time [of publication]'. This applied statement of principle was said to derive from Prince Albert v Strange (1849) 1 Mac. &amp; G. 25 and Morison v Moat (1851) 9 Hare 241 at 263. On appeal, the Court of Appeal found that the principles of business management reflected in the work were not confidential and in the context of a contention that an injunction will not lie in the absence of some right of property, breach of contract or breach of trust, Evershed M.R. observed at p 16, '... it would be, to my mind somewhat shocking if reputable publishers, who discovered that there was in some work which they had acquired, a gross breach of faith, publication of which would involve the ruin of some business, yet nevertheless could say, having discovered that fact before they had published or incurred any substantial expense that they were entitled to insist on going on with their publication'. Denning LJ at p 22 fully agreed with 'all that [Evershed M.R.] has said on all the issues' and Morris LJ 'at p 23 also fully agreed'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1952) 69 RPC 10</tocase>
<text>75 These expressions of principle concerning rights to relief against third parties are stated at a reasonably high level of abstraction and do not deal 'definitively or comprehensively' with the 'matters' which determine ultimately whether a duty of confidence has devolved upon a third party. The applicant also relies upon what is said to be an applied expression of the principle to a bona fide third party for value in the decisions of Lloyd-Jacob J in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1951) 68 RPC 190 and the Court of Appeal in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1952) 69 RPC 10 per Evershed M.R. and Denning and Morris LL.JJ. In that case, Lloyd-Jacob J granted an injunction to restrain a publisher from publishing, pursuant to a contract with the author, a book containing confidential information of the plaintiff concerning the application of principles of business management to particular problems encountered at various functional levels of commercial activity. The publisher struck the contract innocently but once put on notice, prior to publication, of the confidential content incorporated within the work, the jurisdiction to grant an injunction was found by Lloyd-Jacob J to arise on the footing that 'an innocent mind at the time of contract could not overcome the consequences of full knowledge at or before the time [of publication]'. This applied statement of principle was said to derive from Prince Albert v Strange (1849) 1 Mac. &amp; G. 25 and Morison v Moat (1851) 9 Hare 241 at 263. On appeal, the Court of Appeal found that the principles of business management reflected in the work were not confidential and in the context of a contention that an injunction will not lie in the absence of some right of property, breach of contract or breach of trust, Evershed M.R. observed at p 16, '... it would be, to my mind somewhat shocking if reputable publishers, who discovered that there was in some work which they had acquired, a gross breach of faith, publication of which would involve the ruin of some business, yet nevertheless could say, having discovered that fact before they had published or incurred any substantial expense that they were entitled to insist on going on with their publication'. Denning LJ at p 22 fully agreed with 'all that [Evershed M.R.] has said on all the issues' and Morris LJ 'at p 23 also fully agreed'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Prince Albert v Strange (1849) 1 Mac. &amp; G. 25</tocase>
<text>75 These expressions of principle concerning rights to relief against third parties are stated at a reasonably high level of abstraction and do not deal 'definitively or comprehensively' with the 'matters' which determine ultimately whether a duty of confidence has devolved upon a third party. The applicant also relies upon what is said to be an applied expression of the principle to a bona fide third party for value in the decisions of Lloyd-Jacob J in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1951) 68 RPC 190 and the Court of Appeal in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1952) 69 RPC 10 per Evershed M.R. and Denning and Morris LL.JJ. In that case, Lloyd-Jacob J granted an injunction to restrain a publisher from publishing, pursuant to a contract with the author, a book containing confidential information of the plaintiff concerning the application of principles of business management to particular problems encountered at various functional levels of commercial activity. The publisher struck the contract innocently but once put on notice, prior to publication, of the confidential content incorporated within the work, the jurisdiction to grant an injunction was found by Lloyd-Jacob J to arise on the footing that 'an innocent mind at the time of contract could not overcome the consequences of full knowledge at or before the time [of publication]'. This applied statement of principle was said to derive from Prince Albert v Strange (1849) 1 Mac. &amp; G. 25 and Morison v Moat (1851) 9 Hare 241 at 263. On appeal, the Court of Appeal found that the principles of business management reflected in the work were not confidential and in the context of a contention that an injunction will not lie in the absence of some right of property, breach of contract or breach of trust, Evershed M.R. observed at p 16, '... it would be, to my mind somewhat shocking if reputable publishers, who discovered that there was in some work which they had acquired, a gross breach of faith, publication of which would involve the ruin of some business, yet nevertheless could say, having discovered that fact before they had published or incurred any substantial expense that they were entitled to insist on going on with their publication'. Denning LJ at p 22 fully agreed with 'all that [Evershed M.R.] has said on all the issues' and Morris LJ 'at p 23 also fully agreed'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Morison v Moat (1851) 9 Hare 241</tocase>
<text>75 These expressions of principle concerning rights to relief against third parties are stated at a reasonably high level of abstraction and do not deal 'definitively or comprehensively' with the 'matters' which determine ultimately whether a duty of confidence has devolved upon a third party. The applicant also relies upon what is said to be an applied expression of the principle to a bona fide third party for value in the decisions of Lloyd-Jacob J in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1951) 68 RPC 190 and the Court of Appeal in Stephenson Jordan &amp; Harrison Ltd v MacDonald &amp; Evans (1952) 69 RPC 10 per Evershed M.R. and Denning and Morris LL.JJ. In that case, Lloyd-Jacob J granted an injunction to restrain a publisher from publishing, pursuant to a contract with the author, a book containing confidential information of the plaintiff concerning the application of principles of business management to particular problems encountered at various functional levels of commercial activity. The publisher struck the contract innocently but once put on notice, prior to publication, of the confidential content incorporated within the work, the jurisdiction to grant an injunction was found by Lloyd-Jacob J to arise on the footing that 'an innocent mind at the time of contract could not overcome the consequences of full knowledge at or before the time [of publication]'. This applied statement of principle was said to derive from Prince Albert v Strange (1849) 1 Mac. &amp; G. 25 and Morison v Moat (1851) 9 Hare 241 at 263. On appeal, the Court of Appeal found that the principles of business management reflected in the work were not confidential and in the context of a contention that an injunction will not lie in the absence of some right of property, breach of contract or breach of trust, Evershed M.R. observed at p 16, '... it would be, to my mind somewhat shocking if reputable publishers, who discovered that there was in some work which they had acquired, a gross breach of faith, publication of which would involve the ruin of some business, yet nevertheless could say, having discovered that fact before they had published or incurred any substantial expense that they were entitled to insist on going on with their publication'. Denning LJ at p 22 fully agreed with 'all that [Evershed M.R.] has said on all the issues' and Morris LJ 'at p 23 also fully agreed'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Franklin v Giddins [1978] QdR 72</tocase>
<text>78 In Franklin v Giddins [1978] QdR 72 Dunn J made an order for the delivery up of nectarine trees by a female defendant who from a nominated date knew that an orchard conducted by her husband and herself contained nectarine trees propagated by a grafting process undertaken by her husband based upon budwood cuttings stolen by her husband from the plaintiff's orchard. Because the female defendant knew, from the relevant date, that the trees were propagated from a stolen trade secret Dunn J in reliance upon the observations of Greene M.R. in Saltman Engineering Co. Ltd v Campbell Engineering Co. Ltd (supra) at p 213, held that it was unconscionable for her to derive any benefit from the propagation and sale of the trees and thus she, like her husband, infringed the plaintiff's rights.

79 Since the female defendant jointly conducted the orchard with her husband (the first defendant), and became after knowledge of her husband's conduct an active participant in the continued use of the plaintiff's stolen trade secret, she became an accessory to the primary conduct and thus susceptible to an injunction (although undertakings were ultimately recorded) and delivery up of the trees.

80 No feature of this case involves the notion of a party acting bona fide and striking an arms-length contract with another prior to any notice of a contended breach of an obligation of confidence by such a party and then being enjoined from exercising rights under the contract, upon notice. Accordingly, the primary Judge addressing the O 15A r 6 application, observed [16] that the case of Franklin v Giddins involved use of confidential information by somebody who had obtained it from an infringer rather than a case adapted to the relevant circumstances of the present applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Breen v Williams [1995] HCA 63 ; (1996) 186 CLR 71</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/63.html</AustLII>
<text>81 There is no doubt that the authorities recognise that an innocent third party thus acting bona fide may come into possession of confidential information of a primary disclosor either by reason of a disclosure in breach of an obligation of confidence by the disclosee owed to the primary disclosor or because an entity dealing with the third party may have a degree of interconnection with the initial recipient such that information has been disclosed to that entity in breach of an obligation of confidence and then disclosed to the third party; and, in principle, 'in some circumstances the restraint of an apprehended or continued breach of confidence may involve enjoining third parties' ( Breen v Williams [1995] HCA 63 ; (1996) 186 CLR 71 per Gummow J at p 129; see also, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Lenah Game Meats Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 161 per Gummow and Hayne JJ [137] [2001] HCA 63 ; (2002) 185 ALR 1; and Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 537 and 567; Johns v Australian Securities Commission (supra)). Although Gummow J in Breen v Williams at p 129 was emphasising that the assertion of a right to relief in respect of an obligation of confidence does not rest upon any species of proprietary right, his Honour also notes that the circumstances of disclosure to the third party condition whether such a party will be enjoined.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Lenah Meats Pty Ltd 54 IPR 161</tocase>
<text>81 There is no doubt that the authorities recognise that an innocent third party thus acting bona fide may come into possession of confidential information of a primary disclosor either by reason of a disclosure in breach of an obligation of confidence by the disclosee owed to the primary disclosor or because an entity dealing with the third party may have a degree of interconnection with the initial recipient such that information has been disclosed to that entity in breach of an obligation of confidence and then disclosed to the third party; and, in principle, 'in some circumstances the restraint of an apprehended or continued breach of confidence may involve enjoining third parties' ( Breen v Williams [1995] HCA 63 ; (1996) 186 CLR 71 per Gummow J at p 129; see also, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Lenah Game Meats Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 161 per Gummow and Hayne JJ [137] [2001] HCA 63 ; (2002) 185 ALR 1; and Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 537 and 567; Johns v Australian Securities Commission (supra)). Although Gummow J in Breen v Williams at p 129 was emphasising that the assertion of a right to relief in respect of an obligation of confidence does not rest upon any species of proprietary right, his Honour also notes that the circumstances of disclosure to the third party condition whether such a party will be enjoined.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/3.html</AustLII>
<text>81 There is no doubt that the authorities recognise that an innocent third party thus acting bona fide may come into possession of confidential information of a primary disclosor either by reason of a disclosure in breach of an obligation of confidence by the disclosee owed to the primary disclosor or because an entity dealing with the third party may have a degree of interconnection with the initial recipient such that information has been disclosed to that entity in breach of an obligation of confidence and then disclosed to the third party; and, in principle, 'in some circumstances the restraint of an apprehended or continued breach of confidence may involve enjoining third parties' ( Breen v Williams [1995] HCA 63 ; (1996) 186 CLR 71 per Gummow J at p 129; see also, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v Lenah Game Meats Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 161 per Gummow and Hayne JJ [137] [2001] HCA 63 ; (2002) 185 ALR 1; and Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 537 and 567; Johns v Australian Securities Commission (supra)). Although Gummow J in Breen v Williams at p 129 was emphasising that the assertion of a right to relief in respect of an obligation of confidence does not rest upon any species of proprietary right, his Honour also notes that the circumstances of disclosure to the third party condition whether such a party will be enjoined.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434</tocase>
<text>90 In seeking the court's intervention to restrain use of confidential information it is essential that the applicant demonstrate with precision the information said to be confidential and the content of use sought to be attached. Assertions of confidentiality at high levels of abstraction will not establish a basis for relief against a disclosee. In the case of an innocent third party who simply seeks reliance upon a contract struck without notice of a relationship of confidentiality between the primary disclosor and any other party or breach, the requirement for precision is even more acute. The starting point is the identification of the relevant confidential information ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) (supra) per Deane J at 438; Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434 per Gummow J at 443; O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 per Mason J at pp 326 328; Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629 per Harper J, [13], [35]; Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675 per Crockett, Murphy &amp; Ormiston JJ at 711).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/33.html</AustLII>
<text>90 In seeking the court's intervention to restrain use of confidential information it is essential that the applicant demonstrate with precision the information said to be confidential and the content of use sought to be attached. Assertions of confidentiality at high levels of abstraction will not establish a basis for relief against a disclosee. In the case of an innocent third party who simply seeks reliance upon a contract struck without notice of a relationship of confidentiality between the primary disclosor and any other party or breach, the requirement for precision is even more acute. The starting point is the identification of the relevant confidential information ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) (supra) per Deane J at 438; Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434 per Gummow J at 443; O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 per Mason J at pp 326 328; Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629 per Harper J, [13], [35]; Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675 per Crockett, Murphy &amp; Ormiston JJ at 711).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSC/2005/26.html</AustLII>
<text>90 In seeking the court's intervention to restrain use of confidential information it is essential that the applicant demonstrate with precision the information said to be confidential and the content of use sought to be attached. Assertions of confidentiality at high levels of abstraction will not establish a basis for relief against a disclosee. In the case of an innocent third party who simply seeks reliance upon a contract struck without notice of a relationship of confidentiality between the primary disclosor and any other party or breach, the requirement for precision is even more acute. The starting point is the identification of the relevant confidential information ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) (supra) per Deane J at 438; Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434 per Gummow J at 443; O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 per Mason J at pp 326 328; Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629 per Harper J, [13], [35]; Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675 per Crockett, Murphy &amp; Ormiston JJ at 711).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675</tocase>
<text>90 In seeking the court's intervention to restrain use of confidential information it is essential that the applicant demonstrate with precision the information said to be confidential and the content of use sought to be attached. Assertions of confidentiality at high levels of abstraction will not establish a basis for relief against a disclosee. In the case of an innocent third party who simply seeks reliance upon a contract struck without notice of a relationship of confidentiality between the primary disclosor and any other party or breach, the requirement for precision is even more acute. The starting point is the identification of the relevant confidential information ( Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd (No. 2) (supra) per Deane J at 438; Corrs Pavey Whiting &amp; Byrne v Collector of Customs (Vic) &amp; Anor (1987) 14 FCR 434 per Gummow J at 443; O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 per Mason J at pp 326 328; Liberty Financial Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Scott &amp; Anor (No. 4) [2005] VSC 26 ; (2005) 11 VR 629 per Harper J, [13], [35]; Pioneer Concrete Service Ltd v Galli (1985) VR 675 per Crockett, Murphy &amp; Ormiston JJ at 711).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>