<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Elderslie Finance Corporation Limited v Newpage Pty Ltd (No 4) [2007] FCA 500 (4 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/500.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hayden v Teplitzky (1997) 74 FCR 7</tocase>
<text>72 Although the matter may be arguable, and I would not wish to detract in any way from the duty of a party applying for an order ex parte to make full disclosure to the Court (see Hayden v Teplinsky (1997) 74 FCR 7 at 12), I do not think that it was incumbent on Mr Hamilton to disclose on the application he made on 26 February 2007, that the deponent on whom reliance was placed had engaged in that fraudulent conduct some 13 years earlier. It is easy with the benefit of hindsight, and, in particular, with the benefit of the evidence of the version of events that Mr Yii subsequently gave, to question whether Mr Parsons was telling the truth in his two affidavits. However, at the times when those affidavits were filed and read, there was no reason for the applicants to think that his account was not or might not be true. The factual circumstances of some 13 years earlier had, of course, no connection with the factual circumstances touching the dealings between Mr Parsons and Mr Yii in 2006: they go only to the credit of Mr Parsons. In any event, according to the evidence, all that Mr Hamilton knew was that Mr Parsons had been convicted of fraud of some kind in the early 1990s and had served some time in gaol. Mr Hamilton did not know the nature or degree of seriousness of the fraudulent conduct or the length of the period of imprisonment.

73 In relation to the second matter, likewise I do not think that the applicants for the freezing order were obliged to draw the Court's attention to cl 14(a). It was not relevant to the application for the freezing order that Newpage and Mr Yii had undertaken to a non-party, Lewis, not to dispose of assets.

74 Have the applicants shown that there is a serious question to be tried as to whether Mr Yii will be found on the final hearing to be liable to reimburse Newpage to the extent of $2,137,000? If so, have they shown that there is a risk of dissipation of Mr Yii's assets which would frustrate an order that he reimburse Newpage to that extent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thomas A Edison Ltd v Bullock [1912] HCA 72 ; (1912) 15 CLR 679</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1912/72.html</AustLII>
<text>70 The obligation on an applicant for an order on a hearing ex parte is usually expressed as an obligation to bring to the Court's attention all 'material' facts, that is to say, all facts material to the decision whether to grant the relief: cf Thomas A Edison Ltd v Bullock [1912] HCA 72 ; (1912) 15 CLR 679 at 681-2 per Isaccs J; and see Biscoe P, Mareva and Anton Piller Orders: Freezing and Search Orders (LexisNexis Butterworths, 2005) at [6.44] [6.56], and cases there cited.

71 The conviction and sentence were in respect of transactions that occurred between May and August of 1994. They concerned frauds perpetrated by Mr Parsons on five Victorian newsagents. Mr Parsons obtained from these five people cheques totalling over $160,000 by various false pretences. In substance, he procured the newsagents to make out cheques in favour of his company on the promise that the funds would be used to procure paper from a supplier in South East Asia, for the sale of which his company already had contracts in place with large and reputable buyers in the districts in which the newsagents were carrying on their businesses. In fact, no orders for paper were placed, no supplies of paper in commercial quantities were ever imported, and the funds were squandered. Mr Parsons told a variety of lies to explain the whereabouts of the promised paper. In each case, the deceived person's cheque was paid into a bank account of a company called Canyon Bay Pty Ltd, and shortly afterwards, Mr Parsons procured a withdrawal of the amount.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>