<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZBQT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 547 (14 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/547.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1991) 170 CLR 321</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/33.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The appellant argued that the use of the post-hearing submission as to the age of discovery of his sexuality was not probative of anything. He said that it was not evidence and that for the tribunal to have acted on it showed that the actual decision was based on considerations which were irrelevant or irrational, or on findings or inferences of fact which were not supported by some probative material or logical grounds and that, therefore, the decision constituted a jurisdictional error: Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond [1990] HCA 33 ; (1991) 170 CLR 321 at 366 per Deane J, and see also 358 per Mason CJ, with whom Brennan J agreed at 365.

18 If the appellant had made the statement in the post-hearing submission directly, the tribunal would have been entitled to act on it without any further reference to him and to discern the very inconsistency which it did. Unless there were a basis on which to conclude that the agent could not have made the submission on the appellant's behalf, I can see no basis on which it can be concluded that the tribunal was acting on material which was not probative. Why should the tribunal, it may be asked, have ignored the submission which the appellant was asking it to take into account in assessing his claim? And why should the tribunal have ignored material in that submission which could be treated as being an admission or a statement, of an evidentiary kind, in the sense embraced by s 424A of the Act?

22 Not everyone would have reasoned in the way the tribunal did. A want of logic by an administrative decision-maker in drawing an inference of fact does not amount in itself to an error of law. Nor was there anything in its reasons which amounted to an error of law constituting a jurisdictional error. As Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ pointed out in NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 [22]-[29], illogical reasoning, of itself, does not constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error. Mason CJ said in Bond 170 CLR at 356:
 
 'Thus, at common law, according to the Australian authorities, want of logic is not synonymous with error of law. So long as there is some basis for an inference in other words, the particular inference is reasonably open even if that inference appears to have been drawn as a result of illogical reasoning, there is no place for judicial review because no error of law has taken place.' (His Honour's emphasis)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/235.html</AustLII>
<text>22 Not everyone would have reasoned in the way the tribunal did. A want of logic by an administrative decision-maker in drawing an inference of fact does not amount in itself to an error of law. Nor was there anything in its reasons which amounted to an error of law constituting a jurisdictional error. As Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ pointed out in NACB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 [22]-[29], illogical reasoning, of itself, does not constitute an error of law or jurisdictional error. Mason CJ said in Bond 170 CLR at 356:
 
 'Thus, at common law, according to the Australian authorities, want of logic is not synonymous with error of law. So long as there is some basis for an inference in other words, the particular inference is reasonably open even if that inference appears to have been drawn as a result of illogical reasoning, there is no place for judicial review because no error of law has taken place.' (His Honour's emphasis)</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>