<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIFI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 63 (7 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/63.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZIFI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 1263</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/1263.html</AustLII>
<text>1 In this appeal, the Appellant contends that Federal Magistrate Barnes erred in dismissing ( SZIFI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 1263) on 21 August 2006 an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal ('the Tribunal') delivered on 10 January 2006 affirming a decision of the Minister's Delegate refusing the Appellant's application for a protection visa.

2 The grounds of appeal recited in the notice of appeal filed on 31 August 2006 are these:
 
 'GROUNDS 
 
 That the Learned Federal Magistrate Barnes did not went in to the question of law and facts. The respondents are showing the appellant as a citizen of Indonesia whereas the appellant hails from different country. The respondents also erred in to question of law as to the persecution and well founded fear of life. This has led to the grave miscarriage of justice. 
 
 ORDERS SOUGHT 
 
 The judgment and the order made by the Federal Magistrate Court may kindly be set aside. The applicant be allowed to remain in Australia til the decision of the review before this Honourable Court'.

3 The background facts are these.

4 The Appellant is a married Punjabi man born on 7 July 1977 in Sialkot, Pakistan. He is therefore a national of the State of Pakistan.

5 The Appellant arrived in Australia on 10 September 2005. On 29 September 2005 the Appellant lodged an Application for a Protection (Class XA) Visa with the First Respondent. On 18 October 2005, a Delegate of the First Respondent refused the Appellant's application. On 16 November 2005, the Appellant sought review of that decision before the Tribunal. The Appellant contends that he holds a well-founded fear of persecution for the political opinions he holds and articulates concerning the need for a restoration of democracy in the State of Pakistan and that he is unwilling to return to Pakistan owing to such fear. Accordingly, the Appellant contends that Australia has protection obligations under the Refugee's Convention as amended by the Refugee's Protocol ( 1951 Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees and 1967 Protocol Relating to the Status of Refugees ) for the purposes of s 65(1) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ('the Act').

6 The Appellant's contentions in support of the application for a protection visa are these. 
 
 
 (a) The Appellant is a Sunni Muslim. The Appellant has had the benefit of seven years of education; speaks, reads and writes the Urdu and English languages; was a self-employed salesman from 1995 to 2005; has a wife, son and daughter resident in Pakistan; and elected to leave Pakistan lawfully without any difficulty in obtaining travel documentation. 
 (b) The Appellant was a member of the Pakistan Muslim League Nawaz Group ('the M L N G'). In documentation lodged in support of the application for a protection visa, the Appellant said that the M L N G was able to secure the maximum seats from the district of Sialkot in both the upper house and the lower house in elections prior to the civil governance of Pakistan by the military. The Appellant contends that he 'suffered' due to developing tension between the M L N G and the Pakistan People's Party. 
 (c) After the assumption of power by the military, leaders of the M L N G in Sialkot formed a movement for the restoration of democracy. The Appellant was a 'front line worker' for the M L N G; participated in processions; and distributed flyers and other literature critical of corruption on the part of military generals.
 (d) The Appellant contends that the army 'blackmailed' some of the leaders of the M L N G to join the governing regime. The Appellant says he knows some of these persons as the Appellant was the most senior party worker in the M L N G in Sialkot. As a result, the Appellant was persecuted by the leaders of the military governance group and by the military secret service. 
 (e) The Appellant says that he was taken to a police station and assaulted by the police at the instigation of military authorities. The Appellant was told by the authorities that he should not demonstrate against the military governance group and if he did not comply with these demands, false charges would be brought against him as a result of which he would be declared a terrorist and then executed.
 (f) The Appellant contends that he is an activist struggling for the development of a democratic movement in Pakistan; that he was able to obtain a visa through an agent in order to leave Pakistan; and that if he returns to Pakistan he will ultimately be executed because of the opinions he holds and his prior pro-democracy activity.

7 Notwithstanding these contentions, the Minister's Delegate rejected the Appellant's application for a protection visa.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Plaintiff S157/2002 v Commonwealth [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/2.html</AustLII>
<text>20 As to these matters, Federal Magistrate Barnes said this at paragraphs [13], [14] and [16] of the Reasons for Judgment.
 
 
 '13. The finding that it [the Tribunal] made was that it was not able to be satisfied that the events complained of by the applicant had occurred given the limited particulars and the unsubstantiated assertions. On that basis, the Tribunal was unable to be satisfied that the applicant was at risk of being involved in false cases, declared a terrorist or killed as he had claimed, or that he had a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason. It is not apparent from the claims set out in the protection visa application (which is the only place in which the applicant made such claims) that the Tribunal failed to properly consider the applicant's claims in the manner contended for by him. Insofar as he seeks merits review, merits review is not available in this court. 
 
 14. There is one issue that might be said to be raised by this ground that needs to be addressed. That is the fact that at the commencement of its findings and reasons the Tribunal found that the applicant was a national of "Indonesia" and later in its reasons for decision it found that it was not satisfied on the evidence before it that the applicant faced a real chance of persecution should he return to the "PRC" now or in the foreseeable future. There is absolutely nothing in the material in the protection visa application, the decision of the delegate or the application for review to suggest that the applicant made any claim to be associated in any way with either Indonesia or the PRC, which I take to be a reference to the People's Republic of China. 
 
 Such sloppy references may well be a typographical error or the result of a use of a precedent. The issue is whether they amount to a jurisdictional error. 
 
 15. ... 
 
 16. In these circumstances, while the Tribunal has clearly made a factual error in referring to Indonesia and the PRC in its reasons for decision, I consider that such factual error is not such as to amount to a jurisdictional error, that the Tribunal has understood the applicant's claims and assessed those claims despite the unfortunate reference to the wrong country on two occasions . The written submissions for the respondent cited authority to suggest that in circumstances where the Tribunal accurately recorded the applicant's claims and referred to his correct (Pakistani) nationality on numerous occasions, such a typing error or computer error was clearly irrelevant. (See SZFHM v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FMCA 321). While such error does not establish jurisdictional error, it is clearly a matter of concern, particularly where it has occurred on more than one occasion in the same decision. However, reading the Tribunal decision fairly and as a whole and with an eye not too finely attuned to error (see Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259) it is not apparent that the Tribunal failed to understand or consider the applicant's claims or otherwise erred in a manner constituting jurisdictional error.' 
 
 
 
 [emphasis added]

21 The First Respondent supports the Reasons of the Federal Magistrate on the footing that although the Tribunal made a number of references to incorrect considerations, the Decision Record of the Tribunal demonstrates that the Tribunal member took into account the substratum of fact put before the First Respondent by the Appellant in support of the application for a protection visa and determined that having regard to the contentions said to give rise to a well-founded fear of persecution, the Tribunal was unable to be satisfied that the Appellant was in danger of being implicated in false cases, declared a terrorist and executed at the hands of the authorities, should he return to his country of nationality. Accordingly, having regard to the totality of the Reasons, the First Respondent says that it can be seen that the Tribunal member directed his mind to all the relevant matters and that the Tribunal engaged in a bona fide analysis of the factual matters in an attempt to exercise the statutory power.

22 The First Respondent says that to the extent that there was an error, it was an error within jurisdiction.

34 A question then arises as to whether these failures are jurisdictional failures in which event the decision of the Tribunal is not a decision made 'under the Act' and not within the scope of the protection of the privative clause provisions of the Act ( Plaintiff S157/2002 v Commonwealth [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476).

38 The respondent contends that the Tribunal so acted and did not misdirect itself as to the exercise of the power, as the analysis of the facts reveals a consideration of all the circumstances and claims made by the Appellant. However, importantly, an assumption that the Tribunal acted in the way described by Sir Owen Dixon does not qualify the power of the Tribunal and render within power that which is not. Rather, those considerations might qualify, properly construed in the context of the Act overall, the protection and reach of the privative clause ( Plaintiff S157/2002 v Commonwealth (supra) per Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ [99]).

39 A proper construction of the imperative objective of the Act of a 'fair review' and the statutory direction to the Tribunal to exercise the review jurisdiction according to the 'substantial justice of the case' ([27] of these Reasons), suggests that a jurisdictional limitation upon the relevant decision-making power includes both a failure to act fairly and the taking into account erroneous matters, in the course of the analytical process of considering those facts, circumstances and conditions appropriate to the Appellant's claim. Since such failures go to the valid exercise of the power, the proper construction of 'Division 1 Privative clause' (s 474) of the Act having regard to the legislative instrument overall is that the section does not protect the identified failures of the Tribunal from review.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/58.html</AustLII>
<text>35 In Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163 at 179 their Honours Brennan, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said this:
 
 'At least in the absence of a contrary intent in the statute or other instrument which established it, an administrative tribunal lacks authority either to authoritatively determine questions of law or to make an order or decision otherwise in accordance with the law. That point was made by Lord Diplock in Re Racal Communications Ltd ([1981] AC 374 at 383): 
 
 
 
 "Parliament can, of course, if it so desires, confer upon administrative tribunals or authorities power to decide questions of law as well as questions of fact or of administrative policy; but this requires clear words, for the presumption is that where a decision making power is conferred on a tribunal or authority that is not a court of law, the Parliament did not intend to do so." 
 
 
 
 
 The position is, of course, a fortiori in this country where constitutional limitations arising from the doctrine of the separation of judicial and executive powers may preclude legislative incompetence to confer judicial power upon an administrative tribunal. If such an administrative tribunal falls into an error of law which causes it to identify a wrong issue, to ask itself a wrong question, to ignore relevant material, to rely on irrelevant material or, at least in some circumstances, to make an erroneous finding or to reach a mistaken conclusion, and the tribunal's exercise or purported exercise of power is thereby affected, it exceeds its authority or powers. Such an error of law is jurisdictional error which will invalidate any order or decision of the tribunal which reflects it'. 
 
 
 [emphasis added]

40 In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 351 [82] , McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ had regard to the observations of their Honours Brennan, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ (noted at [34] of these reasons) in Craig and further explained the notion of 'jurisdictional error' in these terms:
 
 'It is necessary, however, to understand what is meant by "jurisdictional error" under the general law and the consequences that follow from a decision-maker making such an error. 
 
 "Jurisdictional error" can [thus] be seen to embrace a number of different kinds of error, the list of which, in the passage cited from Craig is not exhaustive. Those different kinds of error may well overlap. The circumstances of a particular case may permit more than one characterisation of the error identified, for example, as to the decision-maker both asking the wrong question and ignoring relevant material. What is important, however, is that identifying a wrong issue, asking a wrong question, ignoring relevant material or relying on irrelevant material in a way that affects the exercise of power is to make an error of law . Further, doing so results in the decision-maker exceeding the authority or powers given by the relevant statute. In other words, if an error of those types is made, the decision-maker did not have authority to make the decision that was made; he or she did not have jurisdiction to make it.' 
 
 [emphasis added] 
 
 

See also the discussion of supervisory review of administrative decisions and the statutory analogue contained in s 5 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) at pp 39-43 per Mason J, Minister for Aboriginal Affairs &amp; Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited &amp; Others [1986] HCA 40 ; [1986] 162 CLR 24.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Racal Communications Ltd ([1981] AC 374 </tocase>
<text>35 In Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163 at 179 their Honours Brennan, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ said this:
 
 'At least in the absence of a contrary intent in the statute or other instrument which established it, an administrative tribunal lacks authority either to authoritatively determine questions of law or to make an order or decision otherwise in accordance with the law. That point was made by Lord Diplock in Re Racal Communications Ltd ([1981] AC 374 at 383): 
 
 
 
 "Parliament can, of course, if it so desires, confer upon administrative tribunals or authorities power to decide questions of law as well as questions of fact or of administrative policy; but this requires clear words, for the presumption is that where a decision making power is conferred on a tribunal or authority that is not a court of law, the Parliament did not intend to do so." 
 
 
 
 
 The position is, of course, a fortiori in this country where constitutional limitations arising from the doctrine of the separation of judicial and executive powers may preclude legislative incompetence to confer judicial power upon an administrative tribunal. If such an administrative tribunal falls into an error of law which causes it to identify a wrong issue, to ask itself a wrong question, to ignore relevant material, to rely on irrelevant material or, at least in some circumstances, to make an erroneous finding or to reach a mistaken conclusion, and the tribunal's exercise or purported exercise of power is thereby affected, it exceeds its authority or powers. Such an error of law is jurisdictional error which will invalidate any order or decision of the tribunal which reflects it'. 
 
 
 [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>R V Hickman; Ex parte Fox and Clinton [1945] HCA 53 ; (1945) 70 CLR 598</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/53.html</AustLII>
<text>37 The Chief Justice also noted at [18] that concepts of 'manifest defect of jurisdiction' and 'manifest fraud' are the obverse of the notion Sir Owen Dixon had in mind in R v Hickman; Ex parte Fox and Clinton [1945] HCA 53 ; (1945) 70 CLR 598 at p 616 when Sir Owen Dixon observed that invalidity is to be determined as a question of interpretation of the entire legislative instrument in assessing whether steps taken by the administrative tribunal transgress the limits of the instrument. That assessment takes into account whether the Tribunal has acted bona fide in an attempt to properly pursue the power conferred; whether the decision relates to the subject matter of the Act; and whether the decision is reasonably capable of reference to the power. Sir Owen Dixon observed at p 616 in Hickman that any decision of the particular Local Reference Board which 'upon its face appears to be within power and is in fact a bona fide attempt to act in the course of its authority, shall not be regarded as invalid' .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 351 [82] , McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ had regard to the observations of their Honours Brennan, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ (noted at [34] of these reasons) in Craig and further explained the notion of 'jurisdictional error' in these terms:
 
 'It is necessary, however, to understand what is meant by "jurisdictional error" under the general law and the consequences that follow from a decision-maker making such an error. 
 
 "Jurisdictional error" can [thus] be seen to embrace a number of different kinds of error, the list of which, in the passage cited from Craig is not exhaustive. Those different kinds of error may well overlap. The circumstances of a particular case may permit more than one characterisation of the error identified, for example, as to the decision-maker both asking the wrong question and ignoring relevant material. What is important, however, is that identifying a wrong issue, asking a wrong question, ignoring relevant material or relying on irrelevant material in a way that affects the exercise of power is to make an error of law . Further, doing so results in the decision-maker exceeding the authority or powers given by the relevant statute. In other words, if an error of those types is made, the decision-maker did not have authority to make the decision that was made; he or she did not have jurisdiction to make it.' 
 
 [emphasis added] 
 
 

See also the discussion of supervisory review of administrative decisions and the statutory analogue contained in s 5 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) at pp 39-43 per Mason J, Minister for Aboriginal Affairs &amp; Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited &amp; Others [1986] HCA 40 ; [1986] 162 CLR 24.

42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>quoted</class>
<tocase>SDAV v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 43</tocase>
<text>36 The idea that there may be 'degrees' of error on the part of an administrative tribunal or that jurisdictional error is to be found in characterising the error of the Tribunal as a 'manifest' defect or an 'obvious' or an 'incontrovertibly' plain error, has become descriptive of the conclusions ( SDAV v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2003) 199 ALR 43 at 49 [27]) courts reach in the exercise of supervisory review in determining whether an administrative decision is 'an abuse of discretion' and thus ultra vires . At paragraph [13] of Plaintiff S157/2002 v The Commonwealth (supra), Chief Justice Gleeson said this:
 
 'The concept of "manifest" defect in jurisdiction or "manifest fraud", has entered into the taxonomy of error in this field of discourse. The idea that there are degrees of error, or that obviousness should make a difference between one kind of fraud and another, is not always easy to grasp. But it plays a significant part in other forms of judicial review. For example, the principles according to which a court of appeal may interfere with a primary judge's findings of fact, or exercise of discretion, are expressed in terms such as "palpably misused [an] advantage", "glaringly improbable", "inconsistent with facts incontrovertibly established", and "plainly unjust". 
 
 Unless adjectives such as "palpable", "incontrovertible", "plain", or "manifest" are used only for rhetorical effect, then in the context of review of decision-making, whether judicial or administrative, they convey an idea that there are degrees of strictness of scrutiny to which decisions may be subjected. Such an idea is influential in ordinary appellate judicial review, and it is hardly surprising to see it engaged in the related area of judicial review of administrative action'.

41 In SDAV v Minister for Immigration (supra) Hill, Branson and Stone JJ, observed:
 
 '[27] The statement that a particular error is a "jurisdictional error" is a statement of conclusion. The conclusion is that, be the error one of omission or commission, some essential or indispensable requirement for jurisdiction has not been met. An imperative duty has not been discharged or some inviolable limitation has been breached and therefore the action or decision is null and void: Plaintiff S157 at [76] per Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ. The error may be easy to detect (manifest error) or more difficult but, either way, an action or decision is either one which falls within the decision-maker's lawful authority or it is not. If it falls within the decision-maker's lawful authority then the error is made "within jurisdiction". If it does not fall within the decision-maker's lawful authority then the error is a "jurisdictional error" and as such it cannot be a valid action or decision.' 
 
 [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs &amp; Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited &amp; Others [1986] HCA 40 ; [1986] 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at 351 [82] , McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ had regard to the observations of their Honours Brennan, Deane, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ (noted at [34] of these reasons) in Craig and further explained the notion of 'jurisdictional error' in these terms:
 
 'It is necessary, however, to understand what is meant by "jurisdictional error" under the general law and the consequences that follow from a decision-maker making such an error. 
 
 "Jurisdictional error" can [thus] be seen to embrace a number of different kinds of error, the list of which, in the passage cited from Craig is not exhaustive. Those different kinds of error may well overlap. The circumstances of a particular case may permit more than one characterisation of the error identified, for example, as to the decision-maker both asking the wrong question and ignoring relevant material. What is important, however, is that identifying a wrong issue, asking a wrong question, ignoring relevant material or relying on irrelevant material in a way that affects the exercise of power is to make an error of law . Further, doing so results in the decision-maker exceeding the authority or powers given by the relevant statute. In other words, if an error of those types is made, the decision-maker did not have authority to make the decision that was made; he or she did not have jurisdiction to make it.' 
 
 [emphasis added] 
 
 

See also the discussion of supervisory review of administrative decisions and the statutory analogue contained in s 5 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) at pp 39-43 per Mason J, Minister for Aboriginal Affairs &amp; Another v Peko-Wallsend Limited &amp; Others [1986] HCA 40 ; [1986] 162 CLR 24.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Refugee Review Tribunal &amp; Another; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/57.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.

43 Once it is established that the Tribunal has asked itself the wrong question by, for example, asking whether it can be satisfied that the Appellant faces a real chance of persecution should he return to the Peoples Republic of China, or, has identified the wrong issue, or taken into account, in one part of its deliberations, a notion that the Appellant is an Indonesian rather than a Pakistani national, the Tribunal is seen to have failed to provide the Appellant with procedural fairness and thus jurisdictional error arises ( Re Refugee Review Tribunal and Another; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 109 [59] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ). The repository of the power is constrained by an obligation to act reasonably by providing procedural fairness. A decision made in light of a failure to act reasonably is not a decision made under the Act for the purposes of s 474.

44 The obligation to undertake an un-distracted, focussed and deliberative assessment of only those facts and circumstances referrable to the case of the Appellant is an essential element of the discharge of the review function.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/14.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/81.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/22.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/57.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/21.html</AustLII>
<text>42 In Yusuf , their Honours formulated at [82] (in the quote identified at [40] of these Reasons) an understanding of what is meant by 'jurisdictional error', under the general law. In Re Refugee Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 100 (38) Gaudron and Gummow JJ noted that Gaudron J had left open in Abebe v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 14 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at 553 [112] the question of whether procedural fairness is to be seen as a common law duty or an implication from the relevant statute. Their Honours concluded in Ex parte Aala that having regard to Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 615 per Brennan J, Haoucher v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1990] HCA 22 ; (1990) 169 CLR 648 at 652, per Deane J, Annette's v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 at 604 605 per Brennan J, and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650 [126] per Gummow J, that the exercise of a discretionary power statutorily conferred is constrained by an obligation to exercise the power reasonably (which includes an obligation to provide procedural fairness) as a function of the proper construction of the legislation itself.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>