<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pandee Services Pty Limited (ACN 060 674 160) v Roberts [2007] FCA 68 (9 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/68.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Northern Land Council v The Commonwealth (No 2) [1987] HCA 52 ; (1987) 75 ALR 210</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/52.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Because this matter has proceeded as if it were an application to strike out both the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 on the ground that it disclose no reasonable cause of action against the second respondents, it is appropriate to assume that the allegations of fact made in the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 will be made out at trial: Northern Land Council v The Commonwealth (No 2) [1987] HCA 52 ; (1987) 75 ALR 210 at 216; Cubillo v The Commonwealth [1999] FCA 518 ; (1999) 89 FCR 528 at 542. The allegations of fact contained in the statement of claim should be accepted at face value: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd trading as Territory Rent-a-car [1997] FCA 129.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cubillo v The Commonwealth [1999] FCA 518 ; (1999) 89 FCR 528</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/518.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Because this matter has proceeded as if it were an application to strike out both the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 on the ground that it disclose no reasonable cause of action against the second respondents, it is appropriate to assume that the allegations of fact made in the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 will be made out at trial: Northern Land Council v The Commonwealth (No 2) [1987] HCA 52 ; (1987) 75 ALR 210 at 216; Cubillo v The Commonwealth [1999] FCA 518 ; (1999) 89 FCR 528 at 542. The allegations of fact contained in the statement of claim should be accepted at face value: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd trading as Territory Rent-a-car [1997] FCA 129.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd trading as Territory Rent-a-car [1997] FCA 129</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1997/129.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Because this matter has proceeded as if it were an application to strike out both the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 on the ground that it disclose no reasonable cause of action against the second respondents, it is appropriate to assume that the allegations of fact made in the PFASC and the statement of claim of 12 September 2005 will be made out at trial: Northern Land Council v The Commonwealth (No 2) [1987] HCA 52 ; (1987) 75 ALR 210 at 216; Cubillo v The Commonwealth [1999] FCA 518 ; (1999) 89 FCR 528 at 542. The allegations of fact contained in the statement of claim should be accepted at face value: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd trading as Territory Rent-a-car [1997] FCA 129.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>41 I should approach this application on the basis that the PFASC should be allowed to be filed unless it is clearly made out that the pleading discloses no reasonable cause of action, at least against the second respondents. In that regard it would be appropriate to apply the test in General Steel Industries v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 130 and allow the pleading to be filed or, alternatively, in the case of the statement of claim of 12 September 2005, not be struck out unless the cause of action is so untenable that it cannot possibly succeed. The provisions of s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) do not apply to this application because this is not an application for summary judgment.

42 The statement of claim should contain in a summary form the material facts upon which the applicant relies but not the evidence upon which those facts are to be proved. The applicant must include sufficient particulars to enable the respondent to the proceeding to know and understand the case which is brought against him or her. The statement of claim should contain such material facts and particulars as will allow the respondent to prevent the respondent from being taken by surprise at the trial and to know the evidence that needs to be obtained.

43 Essentially, three matters are put against the second respondents. First, that the second respondents are vicariously liable for conduct of the first respondent in using the applicant's confidential information in relation to the written quotes. Secondly, the second respondents knowingly participated in the first respondent's breach of his duty of confidence. Thirdly, the second respondents are accessorily liable because they aided, abetted, counselled or procured the first respondent to contravene s 183(1) of the Act or were knowingly concerned in that contravention. In that regard it is pleaded that the second respondents thereby contravened s 183(2) of the Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Photo Production v Securicor Transport Limited [1980] UKHL 2 ; [1980] AC 827</tocase>
<text>48 The second respondents argued that the doctrine of vicarious liability was confined to a tort committed by an employee in the course of that employee's employment and that therefore that this plea should be struck out. In Photo Production v Securicor Transport Limited [1980] UKHL 2 ; [1980] AC 827 at 848, Lord Diplock said that the expression 'vicarious liability' should be confined to liability for tort. There is, however, authority contrary to the second respondents' proposition. In Coulthard v South Australia (1995) 63 SASR 531 (' Coulthard ') the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia was concerned with the publication of confidential information. King CJ said at 535:
 
 'No authority has come to my attention which establishes that vicarious liability of an employer can exist under the equitable doctrine of breach of confidence. Nevertheless a breach of the equitable obligation of confidence is analogous to a common law tort. It is to be expected that equity would follow the law in such circumstances and that the common law doctrine of the vicarious liability in tort of an employer for the acts of employees in the course of their employment would apply in equity to breaches of confidence. It is to be expected that equity would act upon the conscience of the employer by requiring the employer to accept responsibility for the employee's breach of confidence.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Coulthard v South Australia (1995) 63 SASR 531</tocase>
<text>48 The second respondents argued that the doctrine of vicarious liability was confined to a tort committed by an employee in the course of that employee's employment and that therefore that this plea should be struck out. In Photo Production v Securicor Transport Limited [1980] UKHL 2 ; [1980] AC 827 at 848, Lord Diplock said that the expression 'vicarious liability' should be confined to liability for tort. There is, however, authority contrary to the second respondents' proposition. In Coulthard v South Australia (1995) 63 SASR 531 (' Coulthard ') the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia was concerned with the publication of confidential information. King CJ said at 535:
 
 'No authority has come to my attention which establishes that vicarious liability of an employer can exist under the equitable doctrine of breach of confidence. Nevertheless a breach of the equitable obligation of confidence is analogous to a common law tort. It is to be expected that equity would follow the law in such circumstances and that the common law doctrine of the vicarious liability in tort of an employer for the acts of employees in the course of their employment would apply in equity to breaches of confidence. It is to be expected that equity would act upon the conscience of the employer by requiring the employer to accept responsibility for the employee's breach of confidence.'

49 King CJ concluded that it was not established that any breach of confidence had occurred in the course of the employer's employment. Perry and Debelle JJ both assumed that the respondent employer could be liable for a breach by its employee of his duty of confidence but, like King CJ, found that what was done was not done in the course of employment. I am unable to find any other authority on that point. (But see Jason Pizer 'Holding an Appointor Vicariously Liable for its Nominee Director's Wrongdoing -- an Australian Roadmap' 1997, Vol 15 Company and Securities Law Journal.) However, this is not the time to decide whether the decision in Coulthard is correct. Having regard to that decision and the dicta of King CJ referred to, it cannot be said on an application of this kind that the pleas in par 24 are untenable.

50 Paragraphs 25 and 26 plead actual knowledge on the part of the two male second respondents. Paragraph 27 also pleads actual knowledge on the part of the two male respondents but from a different time, apparently, to that asserted in par 26. In any event, all three paragraphs, 25, 26 and 27, plead actual knowledge on the part of two of the four second respondents.

51 Paragraph 28 pleads a form of constructive knowledge by reason of the failure of the second respondents to do any of the matters particularised in that paragraph. Each of pars 29, 30, 32 and 33 plead a form of constructive knowledge on the part of the two female second respondents, the knowledge it is said being imputed to them. It is not pleaded how or why the acts and conduct and knowledge of each of the second respondents is imputed to all of them. It may be assumed that each partner's act or conduct or knowledge is imputed to the other by reason of their partnership. That may not be important. More importantly, the knowledge of the female second respondents and any imputed knowledge obtained by all respondents by reason of the acts or omissions in par 28 cannot rise above constructive knowledge.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hospital Products Ltd v United States Surgical Corporation [1984] HCA 64 ; (1984) 156 CLR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/64.html</AustLII>
<text>52 The plea that the first respondent breached his duty of trust and confidence is a plea of breach of fiduciary duty: Hospital Products Ltd v United States Surgical Corporation [1984] HCA 64 ; (1984) 156 CLR 41 at 96-97. The plea in par 29 is that the second respondents knowingly participated in that breach of fiduciary duty. As I have said, the knowledge relied on is both actual and, in the alternative, constructive.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1975/8.html</AustLII>
<text>53 It is not suggested that the second respondents owed any fiduciary duty to the applicant. There is no suggestion, nor could there be, that there was any fiduciary relationship between the second respondents and the applicant. The second respondents are said to be liable to the applicant because they knowingly participated in the first respondent's breach of fiduciary duty. A person who knowingly participates in a breach of fiduciary duty is liable to account to the person to whom the fiduciary duty was owed where that person obtains a benefit by that participation: Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373 at 397.

54 It was not put that the second respondents could not be liable without actual knowledge of the first respondent's breach of fiduciary duty. It was accepted that a plea that the second respondents knowingly participated in a breach by the first respondent of his duty of confidence with the kind of knowledge pleaded in par 28 of the PFASC could be allowed to stand.

55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378</tocase>
<text>55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164</tocase>
<text>55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112</tocase>
<text>55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2005/928.html</AustLII>
<text>55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WASC/2004/273.html</AustLII>
<text>55 In Consul Development Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd , Gibbs J (at 398) and Stephen J (at 412) with whom Barwick CJ agreed expressed different views as to the knowledge required to establish liability in circumstances of this kind. The English Courts have expressed different views: Royal Brunei Airlines Sdn Bhd v Tan Kok Ming [1995] UKPC 4 ; [1995] 2 AC 378; Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] UKHL 12 ; [2002] 2 AC 164. It appears that the English view has not been accepted in New South Wales and Stephen J's view has been preferred to that of Gibbs J: Yeshiva Properties No 1 Pty Ltd and Others v Marshall (2005) 219 ALR 112 per Bryson JA at [18]-[22]. Because of the uncertainty in the law in Australia on this topic, it would be difficult to conclude that a plea of the kind in par 28 was untenable: Short (as Executrix of the Estate of Short (decd)) v Crawley (No 25) [2005] NSWSC 928 per White J at [43]; The Bell Group Ltd (in liq) v Westpac Banking Corporation and Ors (No 5) [2004] WASC 273. However, because no issue was raised by the second respondents as to the kind of knowledge required, I do not need to explore this complex issue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/65.html</AustLII>
<text>62 Section 79 of the Act is in the same terms as s 75B of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (the Trade Practices Act ) which was considered by the High Court in Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661. Section 75B plays a similar role in the Trade Practices Act to that played by s 79 in the Act . A person will be accessorily liable to a contravention of a provision of the Trade Practices Act if the person does any of the matters prescribed in s 75B. In Yorke v Lucas the High Court considered each of the paragraphs in s 75B. In respect to paragraph (a) the Court observed that these words have been taken from the criminal law and that to be liable under s 75B(a) a party needed to have intentionally participated in the contravention. The Court said at 668:
 
 'The nature of the prohibition imposed by s. 52 is, however, governed by the terms in which it is created and the context in which it is found. Section 75B , on the other hand, in speaking of aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring, makes use of an existing concept drawn from the criminal law and unless the context requires otherwise, there is every reason to suppose that it was intended to carry with it the settled meaning which it already bore: cf. Barker v. The Queen [1983] HCA 18 ; (1983) 153 C.L.R. 338. Nor is there any reason to suppose that because the application of s. 75B may occur in conjunction with a provision such as s. 52 , which requires no intent, it must also be construed so as to dispense with intent as an element of aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring. In Giorgianni v. The Queen it was held that secondary participation required intent based upon knowledge, notwithstanding that the statutory provision creating the principal offence imposed strict liability.'

63 The High Court held that a person will only be guilty of the offence of aiding and abetting or counselling and procuring the commission of an offence if the person intentionally participates in it. Therefore, to form the requisite intent the person must have knowledge of the essential matters which go to make up the offence. It determined that the same knowledge should be required for a contravention of s 75B of the Trade Practices Act .

64 The majority then addressed s 75B(c) and said at 670:
 
 'There can be no question that a person cannot be knowingly concerned in a contravention unless he has knowledge of the essential facts constituting the contravention.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re HIH Insurance Ltd (In Liq) (2002) 41 ACSR 66</tocase>
<text>67 In my opinion, s 79 of the Act would be construed in the same way as s 75B of the Trade Practices Act : see Re HIH Insurance Ltd (In Liq) (2002) 41 ACSR 66.

68 It follows therefore that a party cannot be involved in a contravention of s 183(1) of the Act unless the party has actual knowledge of the elements of s 183(1). The elements that must be established for a contravention of s 183(1) are that the person referred to in s 183(1) was an officer or employee of the corporation; that he or she acquired information because he or she was an officer or employee; that the person made improper use of that information; that the person did so to gain an advantage for themselves or someone else or to cause detriment to the corporation.

69 In my opinion, the plea that the second respondents had constructive knowledge of the matters contained in par 28 or the female second respondents had constructive knowledge as pleaded in pars 29, 30, 32 and 33 could not support a claim that the second respondents contravened s 183(2) by being involved in a contravention of s 183(1). Those pleas are untenable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fox v H Wood (Harrow) Ltd [1963] 2 QB 601</tocase>
<text>83 In my opinion, the applicant should be required to give particulars of the facts and circumstances which existed after the first respondent was employed by the second respondents which should have put the second respondents on notice to make the inquiries or take the steps pleaded in par 28: Fox v H Wood (Harrow) Ltd [1963] 2 QB 601.

84 As I have already mentioned, in a number of the paragraphs which follow it is said that the acts, conduct and knowledge of each of the second respondents is imputed to all of them. In my opinion, that plea requires particularisation. The applicant ought to particularise the facts and circumstances which allow it to be said that, as a consequence, the acts, conduct and knowledge of each of the second respondents is imputed to all of them.

85 Lastly, as the applicant conceded, the applicant needs to give particulars of the loss or damage which the applicants says that he suffered by reason of the respondents' breaches.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>