<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZESF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCA 6 (12 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/6.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/264.html</AustLII>
<text>25 Although not specifically addressed in the appellant's submissions for completeness I should express my view that, in relation to these photographs, the Tribunal did not come under an obligation under s 424A(1) because of the exemption in s 424A(3)(a). It is clear that the information in the photographs was 'not specifically about the applicant or another person' and, as Merkel and Hely JJ commented in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572 at [138] :
 
 '... the reference in s 424A(3)(a) to the class of persons is not another criterion to be met but ... is designed to underline the specificity required by precluding any argument that reference to a class could be taken as a reference to all individuals (including for example, an applicant) falling within it.' 

In this regard see also VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2004) 80 ALD 559 at [14].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/24.html</AustLII>
<text>22 As long as the information derived from the photographs was even part of the reason for the Tribunal's rejection of the appellant's application then a failure to comply with s 424A will amount to jurisdictional error; see SZEEU at [182] per Weinberg J and [215]-[216] per Allsop J. In SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 McHugh J and Hayne J (with whom Kirby J agreed on this point) were quite clear that the bearing of a breach of procedural fairness on the ultimate decision is not relevant to the question of relief; see also Re Refugee Tribunal; ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 109, [59] . The adverse inferences that the Tribunal drew about the appellant's credibility were central to its ultimate decision and it is not necessary for me to consider whether there is a discretion to refuse relief where there is a completely independent ground for the decision; see however M Izzo, "High Court on procedural fairness: SAAP and VEAL", (2006) 13 AJ Admin L 186.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>SZESF v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FMCA 2</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The appellant's application for judicial review of the Tribunal's decision in the Federal Magistrates Court was filed out of time and accordingly the first respondent filed a notice of objection to competency. The first respondent subsequently filed a notice of motion seeking summary dismissal of the application. As indicated in his Honour's judgment ( SZESF v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FMCA 2 at [4] ), at the hearing of the notice of objection to competency and the notice of motion, his Honour also heard the substantive application which he dismissed.

10 The appellant's primary contention in the Federal Magistrates Court was that the Tribunal had not met its obligations under s 424A of the Act. As the Federal Magistrate expressed it:
 
 'His complaint specifically is that the Tribunal failed to comply with its obligations pursuant to s 424A(1) of the Act in that it did not provide the applicant with the opportunity to comment on, nor did it explain to the applicant the relevance of, the issue of his credibility. At the hearing before me the applicant complained that the Tribunal had asked questions about the taking of the photographs and that he was "pretty sure" that he had convinced the Tribunal that he had taken the photographs. The applicant confirmed that he saw the information that the Tribunal failed to give him pursuant to s 424A(1) as being "the credibility issue" and that further the Tribunal did not bring to his attention that this issue was important for the decision that it would be making, in circumstances where he felt "pretty sure that the Tribunal had no doubts about the truth about his credibility".'

11 The Federal Magistrate found that the Tribunal's adverse thought processes about the appellant's credibility could not constitute 'information' for the purposes of s 424A of the Act and consequently the Tribunal was not required to put them to the appellant. Further, his Honour found:
 
 'In relation specifically to the photographs, these were provided to the Tribunal by the applicant for the purposes of the review before it, and clearly to the extent that the Tribunal relied on these photographs, in that they were part of the material which may be seen as information from which it drew adverse inferences, they fall within the exception provided for in s.424A(3)(b)...'

12 His Honour found that, to the extent that common law rules of procedural fairness were applicable, the Tribunal complied with them by putting adverse information to the appellant orally at the hearing.

13 The appellant's other claims in the Federal Magistrates Court concerned the basis for the Tribunal's adverse credibility finding and its failure to put these concerns to the appellant. His Honour found that the Tribunal's account of the hearing, which was uncontested in the Federal Magistrates Court, showed that the appellant had claimed that the five photos that he produced to the Tribunal were taken at protest meetings different from those in the photographs produced to the Minister's delegate when, as the appellant had conceded, they were of the same demonstration. This provided a basis for the Tribunal's adverse credibility finding.

14 His Honour found that relevant photographs were provided by the appellant at the hearing before the Tribunal and therefore they came within the exception to s 424A(3). Similarly, the appellant complained that the Tribunal did not refer to any evidence in making its finding that it would be dark in Moscow at 5:00 pm on 23 March. However, his Honour found that the Tribunal put this finding to the appellant and the appellant responded with an answer that did not contradict the Tribunal. In addition, the Federal Magistrate found that the relevance of this line of enquiry to the Tribunal's ultimate reasoning was not that it would be dark in Moscow on the relevant date but that at the hearing the appellant changed his evidence as to the hours of his work.

15 Finally the appellant claimed that the Tribunal's findings as to the freedom to demonstrate in Russia could be contradicted by new evidence of the arrest and persecution of protestors by the Russian authorities. His Honour found that the appellant had an opportunity to present this evidence and did not and that the Tribunal's findings were open to it on the evidence.

16 The appellant relied upon three grounds of appeal in this Court, all of which alleged that the Federal Magistrate had erred in failing to find that the Tribunal had made certain errors. The alleged errors may be summarised as follows.
 
 (a) The Tribunal breached s 424A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) in failing to provide particulars of, and invite comment on, certain information that was relevant to the Tribunal's decision to refuse the appellant's application for a protection visa and which the appellant had not given for the purpose of his application to the Tribunal. The information was contained in certain photographs and in letters which the appellant provided to the delegate of the Minister for the purpose of his application for a protection visa but which he did not provide to the Tribunal.
 (b) The Federal Magistrate erred in finding that the Tribunal discharged its obligations under s 424A of the Act by raising information covered by s 424A orally at the hearing.
 (c) In finding that the letters mentioned in the first ground of appeal were not corroborative of the appellant's claims, the Tribunal made an 'unreasonable, illogical, irrational, arbitrary or capricious' decision that gave rise to a reasonable apprehension of bias.

17 As mentioned above, the Court has been assisted by written submissions prepared on behalf of the appellant by Mr Johnson of counsel. These submissions focused on the errors described in (a) and (b) above contending that the Tribunal failed to meet the requirements of s 424A of the Act. Section 424A of the Act provides:
 
 (1) Subject to subsection (3), the Tribunal must: 
 
 
 
 (a) give to the applicant, in the way that the Tribunal considers appropriate in the circumstances, particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the decision that is under review; and 
 (b) ensure, as far as is reasonably practicable, that the applicant understands why it is relevant to the review; and 
 (c) invite the applicant to comment on it. 
 
 
 
 (2) The information and invitation must be given to the applicant: 
 
 
 
 (a) except where paragraph (b) applies--by one of the methods specified in section 441A ; or 
 (b) if the applicant is in immigration detention--by a method prescribed for the purposes of giving documents to such a person. 
 
 
 
 
 (3) This section does not apply to information: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) that is not specifically about the applicant or another person and is just about a class of persons of which the applicant or other person is a member; or 
 
 
 
 (b) that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application; or 
 (c) that is non-disclosable information.

18 The appellant's claims in respect of the Tribunal's use of letters (see (a) and (c) at [16] above) can be dealt with briefly. The appellant claimed that he gave the letters to the Minister's department but not to the Tribunal. This claim is inconsistent with the express and clear statements by the Tribunal that at the hearing the appellant 'produced the originals of the documents which had been produced to the Department'. While there is an argument about whether the Tribunal's use of the term 'documents' includes photographs (as to which see [28] below), in the absence of any evidence to the contrary, I see no reason to doubt that the term includes the letters and that the Tribunal's statement is correct. The letters were provided by the appellant to the Tribunal, for the purpose of his application and accordingly fall within the exception provided by s 424A(3)(b).

19 The appellant also submitted that the Tribunal's finding that the letters did not corroborate the appellant's "account regarding the proceedings he sought to have instituted or his claimed reasons for complaining to the MVD" was unreasonable, irrational and capricious and smacked of bias. This ground must fail for reasons given in the written submissions of the first respondent:
 
 'The Tribunal was quite specific in stating what the letters failed to corroborate. Even a brief examination of the letters reveals that they merely show that applications in relation to criminal proceedings had been made to the respective bodies by the appellant. The letters do not give any detail of what the applications were about. The view taken by the Tribunal as to their corroborative value was clearly open to it on the material before it. Its view was neither illogical, arbitrary nor capricious.'

20 This brings me to the crux of this case in relation to s 424A which, as I see it, is the factual issue of whether all the photographs considered by the Tribunal, and therefore the information contained in the photographs, were provided to the Tribunal for the purpose of the application before it, namely to review the decision of the delegate. To the extent that the photographs, and therefore the information conveyed by them, were provided to the Tribunal by the appellant, then they too would fall within the exception to the Tribunal's obligations under s 424A , provided by s 424A(3)(b). It is not in contention that the Tribunal relied on information gleaned from the photographs in reaching its decision to reject the appellant's application. In his amended notice of appeal the appellant alleged that certain of the photographs had not been given to the Tribunal by the appellant. The claim is also made in the appellant's written submissions although, as the first respondent points out, there is no direct evidence to support this allegation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The Federal Magistrate dismissed the appellant's claim that there had been a breach of s 424A because, in his Honour's view the use that the Tribunal made of these photographs that was only one of a number of factors that led the Tribunal to form an adverse view of the appellant's credibility. As pointed out in the appellant's written submissions his Honour's judgment was delivered before the judgment of the Full Court in SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 and therefore it is not surprising that he failed to apply the principles identified by the majority of the Full Court in that case.

22 As long as the information derived from the photographs was even part of the reason for the Tribunal's rejection of the appellant's application then a failure to comply with s 424A will amount to jurisdictional error; see SZEEU at [182] per Weinberg J and [215]-[216] per Allsop J. In SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 215 ALR 162 McHugh J and Hayne J (with whom Kirby J agreed on this point) were quite clear that the bearing of a breach of procedural fairness on the ultimate decision is not relevant to the question of relief; see also Re Refugee Tribunal; ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at 109, [59] . The adverse inferences that the Tribunal drew about the appellant's credibility were central to its ultimate decision and it is not necessary for me to consider whether there is a discretion to refuse relief where there is a completely independent ground for the decision; see however M Izzo, "High Court on procedural fairness: SAAP and VEAL", (2006) 13 AJ Admin L 186.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471</tocase>
<text>33 The meaning of 'information' in the context of ss 424 and 424A of the Migration Act was considered by the Full Federal Court in Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212. Win concerned the Tribunal's treatment of an anonymous letter containing allegations adverse to the appellant's credibility that was sent to the Department of Immigration and Multicultural Affairs. The Court found that the meaning of 'information' in s 424A was the same as that in s 424. The Court referred (at 217) to the Macquarie Dictionary's definition of the word 'information', which included 'Knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance' (see also Tin v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 at [53] ). The definition in the Oxford English Dictionary , also referred to by the Full Court, included 'Knowledge communicated concerning some particular fact, subject or event; that of which one is apprised or told.' The Full Court considered that 'information', for the purpose of ss 424 and 424A encompassed 'assertions made by a person ... that particular aspects of an applicant's account of events are untrue'. It is clear that the Full Court's focus in Win was not upon the anonymous letter itself, but upon the assertions contained within the letter. This approach was followed in VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 where (at 477) Finn and Stone JJ also focused on what does not constitute information: 
 
 'The word does not encompass the tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations ... nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2004) 80 ALD 559</tocase>
<text>25 Although not specifically addressed in the appellant's submissions for completeness I should express my view that, in relation to these photographs, the Tribunal did not come under an obligation under s 424A(1) because of the exemption in s 424A(3)(a). It is clear that the information in the photographs was 'not specifically about the applicant or another person' and, as Merkel and Hely JJ commented in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v NAMW [2004] FCAFC 264 ; (2004) 140 FCR 572 at [138] :
 
 '... the reference in s 424A(3)(a) to the class of persons is not another criterion to be met but ... is designed to underline the specificity required by precluding any argument that reference to a class could be taken as a reference to all individuals (including for example, an applicant) falling within it.' 

In this regard see also VHAP of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs (2004) 80 ALD 559 at [14].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/56.html</AustLII>
<text>33 The meaning of 'information' in the context of ss 424 and 424A of the Migration Act was considered by the Full Federal Court in Win v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 56 ; (2001) 105 FCR 212. Win concerned the Tribunal's treatment of an anonymous letter containing allegations adverse to the appellant's credibility that was sent to the Department of Immigration and Multicultural Affairs. The Court found that the meaning of 'information' in s 424A was the same as that in s 424. The Court referred (at 217) to the Macquarie Dictionary's definition of the word 'information', which included 'Knowledge communicated or received concerning some fact or circumstance' (see also Tin v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1109 at [53] ). The definition in the Oxford English Dictionary , also referred to by the Full Court, included 'Knowledge communicated concerning some particular fact, subject or event; that of which one is apprised or told.' The Full Court considered that 'information', for the purpose of ss 424 and 424A encompassed 'assertions made by a person ... that particular aspects of an applicant's account of events are untrue'. It is clear that the Full Court's focus in Win was not upon the anonymous letter itself, but upon the assertions contained within the letter. This approach was followed in VAF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (2004) 206 ALR 471 where (at 477) Finn and Stone JJ also focused on what does not constitute information: 
 
 'The word does not encompass the tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations ... nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps ...'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>