<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGPA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 760 (18 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/760.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>WAEE v Minister for Immigration (2003) 75 ALD 630</tocase>
<text>19 The Tribunal is not required to refer to every piece of evidence and every contention made by the appellant in his written reasons: WAEE v Minister for Immigration (2003) 75 ALD 630 at [46].

20 The Tribunal expressly considered and dealt with the appellant's claim that the Maoists had targeted him for his perceived involvement in the deaths of some of its activists, and the appellant's claims regarding the circumstances in which he was forced to leave his village of Singa in the Myagdi District.

21 The second ground which is sought to be argued alleges a breach of s 425 of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act). It is conceded that the Tribunal raised with the appellant the issue to the effect that he was of no adverse interest to the Maoists because his wife had not been seriously harmed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quinn [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>33 Even if it be accepted that there is implicit in the finding set out above an acceptance that the Maoists had the capacity to kill him, unless that can be identified as a "jurisdictional fact", there is no error of law, let alone a jurisdictional error, in the Tribunal accepting that proposition. It is no error of law in making a wrong finding of fact: Attorney-General (NSW) v Quinn [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at [35-36] .

34 For the above reasons, in my opinion, the Court should give leave to the appellant to argue the three grounds which were sought to be relied on by him. However, for those reasons, the appeal should be dismissed with costs.
 
 
 
 


 I certify that the preceding thirty-four (34) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Acting Chief Justice Spender. 

 Associate:

Dated: 18 May 2007


 Counsel for the Appellant: L.J. Karp 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: Parish Patience Immigration Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: T. Wong 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 14 May 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 May 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/760.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>