<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd [2007] FCA 708 (18 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/708.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/18.html</AustLII>
<text>72 The term "unconscionable" as used in s 51AA of the TP Act bears a particular legal meaning. It is the meaning conferred by "the unwritten law, from time to time, of the States and Territories", that is, the common law of Australia: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at 71. The concept of unconscionability, so understood, was explained by Gummow &amp; Hayne JJ in Berbatis Holdings by reference to earlier authority. Their Honours said (at 76 - 77) that:
 
 "In Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 47 at 461 to 463, Mason J referred to passages in the judgments of Fullagar J and Kitto J in Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 at 405, 415. Mason J said (at 462): 
 
 'It is made plain enough, especially by Fullagar J, that the situations mentioned are no more than particular exemplifications of an underlying general principle which may be invoked whenever one party by reason of some condition [or] circumstance is placed at a special disadvantage vis-a-vis another and unfair or unconscientious advantage is then taken of the opportunity thereby created. I qualify the word 'disadvantage' by the adjective 'special' in order to disavow any suggestion that the principle applies whenever there is some difference in the bargaining power of the parties and in order to emphasise that the disabling condition or circumstance is one which seriously affects the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment as to his own best interest, when the other party knows or ought to know of the existence of that condition or circumstance and of its effect on the innocent party.' 
 
 His Honour went on to emphasise at (462 - 463) the need for the plaintiff seeking relief to establish the taking of unconscientious advantage of the plaintiff's disabling condition or circumstance. It will be apparent that the special disadvantage at which Mason J spoke in this passage was one seriously affecting the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment as to that party's own best interests." 

Disadvantage of the kind referred to by Fullagar and Mason JJ can take many forms. Fullagar J cited by way of example "poverty or need of any kind, sickness, age, sex, infirmity of body or mind, drunkenness, illiteracy or lack of education, lack of assistance or explanation where assistance or explanation is necessary": Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 at 405.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1954/79.html</AustLII>
<text>72 The term "unconscionable" as used in s 51AA of the TP Act bears a particular legal meaning. It is the meaning conferred by "the unwritten law, from time to time, of the States and Territories", that is, the common law of Australia: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 at 71. The concept of unconscionability, so understood, was explained by Gummow &amp; Hayne JJ in Berbatis Holdings by reference to earlier authority. Their Honours said (at 76 - 77) that:
 
 "In Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio (1983) 151 CLR 47 at 461 to 463, Mason J referred to passages in the judgments of Fullagar J and Kitto J in Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 at 405, 415. Mason J said (at 462): 
 
 'It is made plain enough, especially by Fullagar J, that the situations mentioned are no more than particular exemplifications of an underlying general principle which may be invoked whenever one party by reason of some condition [or] circumstance is placed at a special disadvantage vis-a-vis another and unfair or unconscientious advantage is then taken of the opportunity thereby created. I qualify the word 'disadvantage' by the adjective 'special' in order to disavow any suggestion that the principle applies whenever there is some difference in the bargaining power of the parties and in order to emphasise that the disabling condition or circumstance is one which seriously affects the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment as to his own best interest, when the other party knows or ought to know of the existence of that condition or circumstance and of its effect on the innocent party.' 
 
 His Honour went on to emphasise at (462 - 463) the need for the plaintiff seeking relief to establish the taking of unconscientious advantage of the plaintiff's disabling condition or circumstance. It will be apparent that the special disadvantage at which Mason J spoke in this passage was one seriously affecting the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment as to that party's own best interests." 

Disadvantage of the kind referred to by Fullagar and Mason JJ can take many forms. Fullagar J cited by way of example "poverty or need of any kind, sickness, age, sex, infirmity of body or mind, drunkenness, illiteracy or lack of education, lack of assistance or explanation where assistance or explanation is necessary": Blomley v Ryan [1954] HCA 79 ; (1956) 99 CLR 362 at 405.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans v Balog [1976] 1 NSWLR 36</tocase>
<text>92 In some cases it may be appropriate to award damages on the basis contended for by the applicant. This will be so in a relatively narrow range of cases where a tenant has so damaged or modified premises that they are unlettable at the conclusion on the lease: see Joyner v Weeks [1891] 2 QB 31. Normally, however, reinstatement costs will not be awarded unless there exists some special interest in reinstatement arising from a radical change to the usage to which the property can be put following renovations by the tenant: see Evans v Balog [1976] 1 NSWLR 36.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hurley v McDonalds Australia Ltd [1999] FCA 1728</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1728.html</AustLII>
<text>73 Section 51AC of the TP Act proscribes unconscionable conduct in trade or commerce on the part of a corporation. In this context the word "unconscionable", bears a wider meaning than that recognised by the common law of Australia. In Hurley v McDonalds Australia Ltd [1999] FCA 1728 Heerey, Drummond and Emmett JJ said that:
 
 " For conduct to be regarded as unconscionable, serious misconduct or something clearly unfair or unreasonable, must be demonstrated Cameron v Qantas Airways Ltd (1994) 55 FCR 147 at 179. Whatever 'unconscionable' means in s 51AC , the term carries the meaning given by the shorter Oxford English Dictionary, namely, action showing no regard for conscience, or that are irreconcilable with what is right or reasonable Qantas Airways Ltd v Cameron (1996) 66 FCR 246 at 262. The various synonyms used in relation to the term 'unconscionable' import a pejorative moral judgment Qantas Airways Ltd v Cameron (1996) 66 FCR 246 at 283-4 and 298 ... Before s 51AC will be applicable, there must be some circumstance other than the mere terms of the contract itself that would render reliance on the terms of the contract 'unfair' or 'unreasonable' or 'immoral' or 'wrong'."

74 In the present case, it may be assumed in the applicant's favour that the respondent was aware of the applicant's mistaken belief that the foyer would need to be reinstated at the end of the lease. There is, however, no evidence that this knowledge in any way motivated the decision to proceed with the renovation of the foyer in July and August 1997. As will emerge later in these reasons, it is my view that the principal imperative which informed Tabcorp's conduct at this time was its desire to have all renovation works concluded by 31 August 1997 when it was due to move to 5 Bowen Crescent.

75 Moreover, Tabcorp cannot be said to have acted unconscionably in either of the senses used in ss 51AA and 51AC of the TP Act . The applicant laboured under no special disadvantage in its relationship with Tabcorp. It had been engaged in the construction and letting of commercial premises for over 30 years. It had access to advice from experienced solicitors. Those solicitors negotiated with solicitors for Tabcorp in order to settle agreed terms for the lease. This process continued over many weeks and was ultimately successful. The applicant continued to have the benefit of its solicitors' advice after the lease had been executed and Tabcorp's tenancy had commenced. There is nothing in Tabcorp's conduct at any stage during this process that attracts any moral opprobrium.

76 Even if it be assumed that the applicant had a cause of action based on ss 51AA or 51AC of the TP Act , Tabcorp contends that such a cause of action is statute barred. I agree. Section 82(2) of the TP Act requires that any proceeding be commenced within six years of the cause of action accruing. What I have already said in relation to the applicant's claim in waste being statute barred applies also to its claims under ss 51AA and 51AC .

77 The applicant's case, insofar as it alleges a breach of the lease, is straight forward. It starts with the uncontroversial proposition that the work undertaken by Tabcorp in July and August 1997 whereby the foyer was stripped back and renovated constituted a substantial alteration to the building. It says that it never gave written consent for the work to be undertaken and that, as a result, a breach of Clause 2.13 of the lease occurred. It seeks damages in the sum of $1,350,000 which is the estimated cost, in 2007 dollars, of restoring the foyer to its former condition.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>James v Hutton [1949] 2 All ER 243</tocase>
<text>101 The present case closely resembles that of James v Hutton [1949] 2 All ER 243, in which the Court of Appeal refused to award more than nominal damages to the plaintiff lessor in circumstances where the outgoing sub-tenant had "modernised" the fa&ccedil;ade of the demised premises. In that case the assignee of a lease was granted a licence by the landlord to construct a new shop front to business premises. The licence contained a covenant that the assignee would, if so required, reinstate the premises in their original condition. The landlord gave the assignee notice to reinstate the premises but the assignee failed to do so. At first instance the landlord was awarded damages calculated by reference to estimates of the probable costs of restoration work. The assignee was successful on appeal. The Court of Appeal applied the general rule as to damages for breach of contract, namely that the landlord could only obtain compensation for damage actually suffered. Speaking for the Court Lord Goddard CJ said (at 246):
 
 "We see no ground here for assuming that the landlord in the present case has suffered any damage at all. She has got back a shop ...provided with a modern and convenient front, and there was no suggestion that the work had not been carried out properly. We do not for one moment suggest that it might not be possible for a landlord, in circumstances such as these to give evidence that she or her superior landlords at the end of the term desire to carry on or to let the premises for the purpose of carrying on a business for which the altered shop front would be inappropriate and the old one suitable. In that case she might well say that it is of value to her to have the shop back in its former condition and she would suffer damage if the tenant's or assignees' covenant to restore was not carried out, but if it is a mere matter of getting back a shop which has been altered and there is no suggestion that any damage whatever has been caused to the landlord thereby, it appears to us that she has suffered no damage by reason of the tenant's or assignee's failure to comply with her requirements to reinstate."

102 The expert evidence, which I accept, acknowledges the existence of differing subjective views as to the aesthetic merit of the former foyer and the one which has replaced it. The applicant has erected and leased the building for commercial purposes. It is an investment property. The evidence supports the conclusion that, apart from the loss of lettable space on the ground floor caused by the movement of one wall in order to expand the size of the foyer, the applicant has suffered no diminution in the lettable value of the building by reason of the works undertaken by Tabcorp in the foyer area. This work has not had any adverse effect on the lettable value of the property while it is being leased by Tabcorp. At the end of that lease the building will be lettable to another tenant or tenants. It is likely that, at that time, refurbishment of the foyer will be necessary (as it would be necessary had it been retained in its original condition) in order to take account of architectural developments and the need to "freshen up" the building to make it attractive to potential tenants.

103 At that time there will have been a loss of net lettable area. That loss has been quantified at about $26,000. The cost involved in removing the existing wall and relocating it in its former position so as to restore the lettable area is of approximately the same order. Mr Robinson gave uncontested evidence that the building work necessary to restore the foyer to its original proportions would be $33,820. The applicant is entitled to damages in this amount. Nominal damages are also appropriate having regard to Tabcorp's failure to abide by its obligations under Clause 2.13 of the lease. I would award the applicant $1,000 under this head.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Joscelyne v Nissen [1970] 2 QB 86</tocase>
<text>58 Courts have long recognised that there exists an "inherent probability that a written instrument truly represents the parties' intention because it is a document signed by the parties": see Thomas Bates and Son Limited v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Limited [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 WLR 505 at 521. Accordingly "convincing proof" is needed to support an order for rectification of a document which records a commercial agreement: see Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447 at 452; Joscelyne v Nissen [1970] 2 QB 86 at 98. The classes of documents which may be rectified include leases: see Murray v Parker (1854) 19 Beav 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Joyner v Weeks [1891] 2 QB 31</tocase>
<text>92 In some cases it may be appropriate to award damages on the basis contended for by the applicant. This will be so in a relatively narrow range of cases where a tenant has so damaged or modified premises that they are unlettable at the conclusion on the lease: see Joyner v Weeks [1891] 2 QB 31. Normally, however, reinstatement costs will not be awarded unless there exists some special interest in reinstatement arising from a radical change to the usage to which the property can be put following renovations by the tenant: see Evans v Balog [1976] 1 NSWLR 36.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Marsden v Edward Heyes Ltd [1927] 2 KB 1</tocase>
<text>64 The applicant claims that the respondent, by gutting and restoring the foyer in the manner in which it has done, has committed a voluntary waste. Waste is a tort which occurs where a positive act, such as demolition, occurs which is injurious to the reversion, usually by diminishing its value: see Marsden v Edward Heyes Ltd [1927] 2 KB 1.

65 The respondent denies that its actions in altering the foyer constituted waste but, in any event, pleads that any cause of action based on waste is statute barred.

66 The Limitation of Actions Act 1958 (Vic) restricts the bringing of a cause of action in tort more than six years after the right of action accrued: see Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth), s 79 and Limitation of Actions Act 1958 (Vic), s 5(1)(a). The cause of action in question accrued no later than July 1998 when Tabcorp unequivocally stated (above at [47] and [48] that it would not restore the foyer. In my view it accrued in July and August 1997 when the works were undertaken. In either event the six year limitation had expired by the time at which the proceeding was commenced on 30 September 2005.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Murray v Parker (1854) 19 Beav 305</tocase>
<text>58 Courts have long recognised that there exists an "inherent probability that a written instrument truly represents the parties' intention because it is a document signed by the parties": see Thomas Bates and Son Limited v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Limited [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 WLR 505 at 521. Accordingly "convincing proof" is needed to support an order for rectification of a document which records a commercial agreement: see Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447 at 452; Joscelyne v Nissen [1970] 2 QB 86 at 98. The classes of documents which may be rectified include leases: see Murray v Parker (1854) 19 Beav 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/63.html</AustLII>
<text>58 Courts have long recognised that there exists an "inherent probability that a written instrument truly represents the parties' intention because it is a document signed by the parties": see Thomas Bates and Son Limited v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Limited [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 WLR 505 at 521. Accordingly "convincing proof" is needed to support an order for rectification of a document which records a commercial agreement: see Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447 at 452; Joscelyne v Nissen [1970] 2 QB 86 at 98. The classes of documents which may be rectified include leases: see Murray v Parker (1854) 19 Beav 305.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Thomas Bates and Son Limited v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Ltd [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 WLR 505</tocase>
<text>58 Courts have long recognised that there exists an "inherent probability that a written instrument truly represents the parties' intention because it is a document signed by the parties": see Thomas Bates and Son Limited v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Limited [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 WLR 505 at 521. Accordingly "convincing proof" is needed to support an order for rectification of a document which records a commercial agreement: see Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447 at 452; Joscelyne v Nissen [1970] 2 QB 86 at 98. The classes of documents which may be rectified include leases: see Murray v Parker (1854) 19 Beav 305.

63 Even if it be accepted that the applicant, acting through Mrs Bergamin, was labouring under a mistake as to the content of the lease when she signed it, there is no evidence that, at that time, Mr Gullquist, or anyone else associated with Tabcorp, was aware of the mistake or acted in an unconscionable manner in order to take advantage of it. What is complained of is Mr Gullquist's alleged awareness, in March 1997, that the applicant asserted that the lease imposed a general "make good" obligation on Tabcorp and failed to draw attention to the falsity of the assertion. As already noted, this failure, on the part of Mr Gullquist, is susceptible of an innocent explanation. Moreover the event post-dated by some three months the execution of the lease. Rectification for unilateral mistake requires knowledge of that mistake by the other party prior to execution of the relevant document and the deliberate failure of the other party to disabuse the party labouring under the mistake in circumstances which may be characterised as unconscionable: Thomas Bates &amp; Son Ltd v Wyndham's (Lingerie) Ltd [1980] EWCA Civ 3 ; [1981] 1 All E R 1077 at 1085-6. In the present case Tabcorp was not aware, in December 1996, that Mrs Bergamin thought that the lease contained a general 'make good' clause and it neither, through action or inaction, took unconscionable advantage of Mrs Bergamin's alleged mistake. This is a matter to which I will return.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1998) 164 CLR 387</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/7.html</AustLII>
<text>85 I do not accept that contention of Tabcorp that the applicant waived strict compliance with the written consent requirement. It did not do so on 11 July 1997 when Tabcorp was told that it had no objection, in principle, to the removal of the existing foyer surfaces and it did not do so on 14 July 1997 by confirming that works could continue. I have already dealt with Tabcorp's submissions relating to the "in principle" approval: see above at [79]. I would only add in the present context that the 11 July 1997 letter spoke of "in princip[le] approval" of the removal of the existing surfaces. It said nothing about approval for subsequent refurbishment. On 14 July 1997 the Bergamins reluctantly accepted the inevitability that refurbishment work would have to take place. They could hardly have done otherwise given what had been done to the foyer. They made it plain that their prior written consent to the necessary works was needed and that, before that consent would be forthcoming, they wished to see the detailed plans (including the finishes board). This was not conditional approval; it was a reiteration of what the Bergamins understood, correctly, to be Tabcorp's obligation under Clause 2.13 of the lease. In no way did the applicant encourage Tabcorp to act on a false assumption that the applicant did not insist on Tabcorp complying with its obligations under clause 2.13. The applicant was not, therefore, estopped from insisting on Tabcorp so complying: Waltons Stores (Interstate) Ltd v Maher [1988] HCA 7 ; (1998) 164 CLR 387.

86 The applicant claims that Tabcorp, by its conduct, contravened ss 52 and 53 (g) of the TP Act . Section 52(1) of the TP Act provides that a "corporation shall not, in trade or commerce, engage in conduct that is misleading or deceptive or is likely to mislead or deceive." Section 53(g) provides that a "corporation shall not, in trade or commerce, in connection with the supply or possible supply of goods or services, make any false or misleading representation concerning the existence, exclusion or effect of any condition, warranty, guarantee, right or remedy."

87 The applicant relies on the following conduct, on the part of Tabcorp, to support its claims under ss 52 and 52 (g) of the TP Act :
 
 &#8226; The representation, by Tabcorp, made on 11 July 1997, that it would replace the existing glass and stone partition, timber panelling and stone floor tiles with materials which reflected the high quality of the building;
 &#8226; The further representation, also allegedly made on 11 July 1997, that alterations to the foyer would not be undertaken without the applicant's prior consent;
 &#8226; Tabcorp's representation, on 14 July 1997, that the construction of a new foyer would not be undertaken without the applicant's prior consent;
 &#8226; The representation, given on the same day, that Tabcorp would supply the applicant with final drawings, a schedule of finishes and a sample board in order to enable the applicant to consider whether or not to approve the proposed works;
 &#8226; The representation, also allegedly made on 14 July 1997, by Tabcorp that the new stone flooring would be equal to or better in quality than the original granite flooring;
 &#8226; Tabcorp's representation also allegedly made at the meeting on 14 July 1997, that the new foyer would be of an exemplary standard, such that no rectification or improvement of the foyer would be needed at the end of the lease. 

The applicant contends that it relied on the representations, made on 11 and 14 July 1997, and that, as a result it did not seek to prevent demolition of the existing foyer or the construction of a new foyer and did not take steps to ensure that the standard of the finishes was as represented. It is alleged that the representations that the proposed fittings and finishes would be of a high standard was a matter of opinion for which Tabcorp had no reasonable basis. It is further alleged that the representations were false and misleading in that:
 
 &#8226; Tabcorp did not obtain the applicant's prior consent before making the alteration;
 &#8226; The finishes to the new foyer were not such as to reflect the high quality of the premises;
 &#8226; Tabcorp did not supply the applicant with final drawings, a schedule of finishes and a sample board before demolishing the foyer and commencing refurbishment; and
 &#8226; Tabcorp did not intend or have the capacity, at relevant times, to obtain the applicant's approval for commencing the works. 

The applicant pleads that, by reason of these contraventions of the TP Act , the applicant has suffered loss and damage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wardley Australia Ltd v The State of Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/55.html</AustLII>
<text>89 By s 82(2) of the TP Act , any action brought under ss 52 or 53 (g) must be commenced within six years after the day on which the cause of action accrued. An action for loss or damage, commenced pursuant to s 82 of the TP Act , for conduct undertaken in contravention of ss 52 and 53 (g) of the TP Act requires that actual loss or damage has occurred. Anticipated loss or damage, at some time in the future, will not suffice: see Wardley Australia Ltd v The State of Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 at 525, 527. No doubt, it is for this reason, that the applicant claims that it "has" suffered loss and damage. Any such loss and damage occurred at the time that the demolition and renovations occurred in July and August 1997. Any cause of action accrued at that time. As a result, the alleged causes of action are statute barred.

90 As already noted the applicant seeks damages for Tabcorp's breaches of Clause 2.13 of the lease. The quantum of damages sought is $1,380,000. This figure is made up of the estimated cost of reinstatement of the foyer to its former condition ($580,000) and loss of rental income during the four month period in which such works are undertaken ($800,000).

91 It is common ground that reinstatement of the foyer will not occur prior to the conclusion of Tabcorp's tenancy. This will not occur, at the earliest, until 2012. If Tabcorp exercises its option to extend the lease by a further five years, it will not occur until 2017. The parties make competing submissions as to the appropriate measure of damages. The applicant seeks the costs of reinstatement of the foyer. Tabcorp, on the other hand, submits that damages should be measured by reference to the diminution, if any, in value of the building occasioned by the works undertaken in the foyer.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>