<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>APN News &amp; Media Limited, in the matter of APN News &amp; Media Limited [2007] FCA 770 (20 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/770.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>In re Paramount Communications Inc Shareholders' Litigation 637 A2d 34 (Del Supr 1993)</tocase>
<text>55 My consideration of the provisions for the no-shop and break fee provisions in this case has led me to the view that it would be desirable that applications under s 411(1) be supported by affidavit evidence directed to showing:
 
&#8226; that the no-shop and break fee provisions are the result of a normal commercial negotiation, and explaining, at least briefly and in general terms, the factual basis for that statement (see [46] above);
 
&#8226; that the directors of the target company, or at least those directors of it who are not affiliated with the offeror, believe that the provisions do not operate against the interests of offeree shareholders, and that in fact it was in the interests of such shareholders that the directors agreed to the inclusion of the provisions in the merger implementation agreement (see [46] above and In re Paramount Communications Inc Shareholders' Litigation 637 A2d 34 (Del Supr 1993) for a case in which a target company's directors' commitment to no-shop and break fee provisions was held, in all the circumstances, to constitute a breach of their fiduciary duty); and
 
&#8226; in the case of the break fee, explaining, by reference to calculations based on the evidence before the Court, the percentage that the break fee represents (a) of the "equity value" of the target company, calculated in accordance with para 7.18 of the Takeovers Panel's Guidance Note 7, and (b) of the scheme consideration (the explanation might, instead, be conveyed in a submission, but still by reference to the evidence before the Court).
If the independent expert is in a position to express an opinion on the matter (see s 79 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth)), the expert should state whether the no-shop and break fee provisions appear to be reasonable and not detrimental to the interests of shareholders, and if so, the basis for that opinion. Of course, the independent expert's opinions that agreement to the Scheme is in the best interests of the offeree shareholders and that no superior proposal is likely to be made, must not have been arrived at as a result of the very existence of the no-shop and break fee provisions (see [52] above).
 Convertible Notes and Options

56 The Scheme Booklet discloses, at sections 11.8 and 11.9 , the existence of convertible notes in APN and of options under an "APN Option Plan". Although the proposed Scheme is between APN and Offeree Shareholders (not option holders), INMAL is making an offer to all option holders to acquire their options at a price per option of $6.20 less the option exercise price. The acquisition by INMAL of the options is, naturally, conditional on the Scheme becoming effective.

57 As noted at [16](i) above, the Scheme provides for a deemed warranty by the APN Scheme participants of freedom from encumbrances. The deemed warranty is found in cl 3.4 of the Scheme document which provides:
 
 3.4 Warranties by Scheme Participants 
 Each Scheme Participant is deemed to have warranted to APN and appointed and authorised APN as its attorney and agent to warrant to INMAL, that all its APN Scheme Shares (including any rights and entitlements attaching to those shares) which are transferred to INMAL under the Scheme will, at the date of the transfer of the APN Scheme Shares to INMAL, be fully paid and free from all mortgages, charges, liens, encumbrances and interests of third parties of any kind, whether legal or otherwise, and any restrictions on their transfer and that it has the full power and capacity to sell and transfer its APN Scheme Shares (including any rights and entitlements) to INMAL under the Scheme.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Arthur Yates &amp; Co Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 758 </tocase>
<text>29 In Re Arthur Yates &amp; Co Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 758, Santow J gave attention to no-shop provisions. His Honour expressed the opinion (at [9]) that such a provision should satisfy the following concerns:
 
 (a) it should be for no more than a reasonable period capable of precise ascertainment;
 (b) while it may differentiate between actively soliciting an alternative merger proposal and simply dealing with an unsolicited one, in either case the provision should be framed so that it is subject to the overriding obligation not to breach the directors' fiduciary duties or be otherwise unlawful; and
 (c) there should be adequate prominence given to the provision in the explanatory memorandum sent to shareholders.

30 Are these three requirements satisfied in the present case?

31 (a) As noted, the Exclusivity Period in this case runs from the date of the SIA to the date when the Scheme becomes effective pursuant to the Court's approval of it. The date of the SIA is 11 February 2007. If we assume that all conditions precedent will be satisfied, apparently the last to be satisfied will be the Court's approving the Scheme under s 411(4)(b) of the Act , which, ex hypothesi , would be likely to take place at the second court hearing, presently fixed for 28 May 2007. I do not regard the period of some three and a half months as unreasonably long.

32 (b) I do not find cl 11.6 comforting. It operates only if and when the matter comes before a court, arbitral tribunal or the Takeovers Panel something that may never happen.

33 Clause 11.5(b) provides:
 
 Nothing in clauses 11.3 or 11.4 prevents APN from undertaking, or requires APN to undertake, any act, if doing so would be inconsistent with the proper exercise of the fiduciary duties of the APN Independent Committee .
 (My emphasis.)
 

This provision may suggest that cl 11.3 and cl 11.4 may properly require APN to act in a manner inconsistent with the proper exercise of the fiduciary duties of its other seven directors. No doubt the provision was framed as it is to recognise the fact that those other directors may be seen to owe duties to INMAL, an indirect wholly owned subsidiary of INM, a member of the Consortium. However, those directors also have fiduciary duties as directors of APN.

34 I do not think, however, that what I regard as a deficiency in the form of expression of cl 11.5(b) should stand in the way of the convening of the Scheme Meeting or of the approval of the Scheme.

35 (c) Is adequate prominence given the no-shop provision in the Scheme Booklet? I think so. First, a copy of the SIA is Annexure A to the Scheme Booklet. In addition, within the text of the Scheme Booklet, at section 10.3 ("Key Terms of the Scheme Implementation Agreement"), the no-shop provision is referred to under the heading "No-Shop and No Due Diligence" and "Right to Respond to Competing Transactions".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Ballarat Goldfields NL (2002) 41 ACSR 691</tocase>
<text>49 The Takeovers Panel has had occasion to consider break fees in the context of takeovers under Ch 6 of the Act : see the discussion in Renard IA and Santamaria JG , Takeovers and Reconstruction in Australia (Butterworths, looseleaf service) at [1149], esp at 11,173 ff. Break fees were considered by the Panel in Re Normandy Mining Ltd (No 3) (2002) 20 ACLC 471; Re Ballarat Goldfields NL (2002) 41 ACSR 691; and Re National Can Industries Ltd (No 1) (2003) 48 ACSR 409 (" National Can "). In National Can , the review panel stated (at 434 [33]):
 
 We consider that a 1% fee is usually not materially anti-competitive and does not place unreasonable pressure on shareholders. This is the basis for the choice of the 1% guideline in GN7. Further, we query whether a sunk cost is anti-competitive if shareholders reject the scheme and agree with the initial panel's statement [made earlier at 418 [42]]: "In these circumstances, we do not entirely reject the notion that a fee should be payable if and when a proposal the directors endorsed was rejected by shareholders. As GN7 puts it, such a fee may be an appropriate price to secure an opportunity broadly in the nature of an option [GN7 at para 7.21]".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Brambles Industries Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 501</tocase>
<text>23 A concern raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications in this Court is that shareholders may be left in a position, once a scheme has become effective, where their shares have been transferred but where there is a delay in the provision of the Scheme Consideration and where their only remedy is to sue on the deed poll (see Re KAZ Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 at [4] - [5] ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 523 at [5]-[6]; Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670 at [4] ; and Re Brambles Industries Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 501 at [9]). Such "performance risk" has been addressed here by requiring that the Scheme Consideration be paid to APN before 8.00 am on the implementation date to be held by it in trust for the purpose of being paid, free of deductions, to the Scheme participants before they are divested of their shares in APN later on the implementation date. This is provided for in the Deed Poll.
 Disadvantages and Risks</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re KAZ Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/738.html</AustLII>
<text>23 A concern raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications in this Court is that shareholders may be left in a position, once a scheme has become effective, where their shares have been transferred but where there is a delay in the provision of the Scheme Consideration and where their only remedy is to sue on the deed poll (see Re KAZ Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 at [4] - [5] ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 523 at [5]-[6]; Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670 at [4] ; and Re Brambles Industries Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 501 at [9]). Such "performance risk" has been addressed here by requiring that the Scheme Consideration be paid to APN before 8.00 am on the implementation date to be held by it in trust for the purpose of being paid, free of deductions, to the Scheme participants before they are divested of their shares in APN later on the implementation date. This is provided for in the Deed Poll.
 Disadvantages and Risks</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Mincom Ltd (2007) 25 ACLC 163</tocase>
<text>62 In Re Mincom Ltd (2007) 25 ACLC 163, Fryberg J described (at [39]) a deemed warranty clause almost identical to the present one as:
 
 onerous, unreasonable and calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty. 
 

As will be clear from what I have said above, I respectfully disagree. At first blush the deemed warranty may appear to attract criticism along these lines, but I think the criticism disappears once it is appreciated that its purpose and effect are as I have described them. Perhaps a better way of framing the provision would have been to avoid the language of warranty, and, instead, to provide simply that if shares continue to be subject to encumbrances after transfer, the shareholder would, upon demand by INMAL, pay the amount required to discharge the encumbrance to the encumbrancee if the encumbrance remains outstanding, or to INMAL if INMAL had already discharged it.

63 On the hearing I indicated that I would require the attention of Scheme participants to be drawn to the existence of the deemed warranty in the Scheme by a specific mention of it in section 2.4 ("Assessment of the Scheme" "Other Relevant Considerations") of the Scheme Booklet. Accordingly, a new cl 2.4(c) will state:
 
 Deemed warranty
 Shareholders' attention is drawn to the warranties that Scheme Participants will be deemed to have given, if the Scheme takes effect, in clause 3.4 of the Scheme (see page 283).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re National Can Industries Ltd (No 1) (2003) 48 ACSR 409 </tocase>
<text>49 The Takeovers Panel has had occasion to consider break fees in the context of takeovers under Ch 6 of the Act : see the discussion in Renard IA and Santamaria JG , Takeovers and Reconstruction in Australia (Butterworths, looseleaf service) at [1149], esp at 11,173 ff. Break fees were considered by the Panel in Re Normandy Mining Ltd (No 3) (2002) 20 ACLC 471; Re Ballarat Goldfields NL (2002) 41 ACSR 691; and Re National Can Industries Ltd (No 1) (2003) 48 ACSR 409 (" National Can "). In National Can , the review panel stated (at 434 [33]):
 
 We consider that a 1% fee is usually not materially anti-competitive and does not place unreasonable pressure on shareholders. This is the basis for the choice of the 1% guideline in GN7. Further, we query whether a sunk cost is anti-competitive if shareholders reject the scheme and agree with the initial panel's statement [made earlier at 418 [42]]: "In these circumstances, we do not entirely reject the notion that a fee should be payable if and when a proposal the directors endorsed was rejected by shareholders. As GN7 puts it, such a fee may be an appropriate price to secure an opportunity broadly in the nature of an option [GN7 at para 7.21]".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Normandy Mining Ltd (No 3) (2002) 20 ACLC 471 </tocase>
<text>49 The Takeovers Panel has had occasion to consider break fees in the context of takeovers under Ch 6 of the Act : see the discussion in Renard IA and Santamaria JG , Takeovers and Reconstruction in Australia (Butterworths, looseleaf service) at [1149], esp at 11,173 ff. Break fees were considered by the Panel in Re Normandy Mining Ltd (No 3) (2002) 20 ACLC 471; Re Ballarat Goldfields NL (2002) 41 ACSR 691; and Re National Can Industries Ltd (No 1) (2003) 48 ACSR 409 (" National Can "). In National Can , the review panel stated (at 434 [33]):
 
 We consider that a 1% fee is usually not materially anti-competitive and does not place unreasonable pressure on shareholders. This is the basis for the choice of the 1% guideline in GN7. Further, we query whether a sunk cost is anti-competitive if shareholders reject the scheme and agree with the initial panel's statement [made earlier at 418 [42]]: "In these circumstances, we do not entirely reject the notion that a fee should be payable if and when a proposal the directors endorsed was rejected by shareholders. As GN7 puts it, such a fee may be an appropriate price to secure an opportunity broadly in the nature of an option [GN7 at para 7.21]".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/670.html</AustLII>
<text>23 A concern raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications in this Court is that shareholders may be left in a position, once a scheme has become effective, where their shares have been transferred but where there is a delay in the provision of the Scheme Consideration and where their only remedy is to sue on the deed poll (see Re KAZ Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 at [4] - [5] ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 523 at [5]-[6]; Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670 at [4] ; and Re Brambles Industries Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 501 at [9]). Such "performance risk" has been addressed here by requiring that the Scheme Consideration be paid to APN before 8.00 am on the implementation date to be held by it in trust for the purpose of being paid, free of deductions, to the Scheme participants before they are divested of their shares in APN later on the implementation date. This is provided for in the Deed Poll.
 Disadvantages and Risks

43 Provisions for the payment of break fees are not uncommon in agreements for schemes of arrangements and in merger and takeover agreements, both in Australia and overseas. Such provisions have not been an obstacle to the making of orders under s 411(1) of the Act for the convening of meetings. In Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670 at [6] - [7] , Gyles J said that he would be dissuaded from making an order by a break fee only if the amount was of such magnitude that it could influence voting or if there were some other unusual circumstances.

44 Break fees are justified by reference to:
 
&#8226; the costs incurred by the offeror company;
 
&#8226; the benefit that that company confers on the members of the target company by increasing its value; and
 
&#8226; the desirability, from the viewpoint of those members, that takeover offers be made to them.

45 Clearly, a company making an approach to the board of a target company is entitled to stipulate as a term of its offer that the target company agree to a provision for a break fee. It is entitled to inform that board that if it does not agree to the break fee, the offer will not be made to the target company's shareholders, and it is entitled not to make the offer to the target's shareholders, if its board does not agree to the break fee. The question is what is the appropriate response of the target company's directors, and later of the Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Stork ICM Australia Pty Ltd (2006) 25 ACLC 208</tocase>
<text>64 Senior counsel for the plaintiff raised the question whether I should take into account at the first hearing stage the position of creditors of APN. In the absence of unusual circumstances (none are obvious here), I do not think I should. Senior counsel acknowledged that it would remain open to the Court to consider the position of creditors as relevant to the Court's discretion to approve the Scheme at the second court hearing, as happened in Re Stork ICM Australia Pty Ltd (2006) 25 ACLC 208.

65 The Australian Securities and Investments Commission has provided the "usual letter" that it provides in relation to schemes of arrangement of the present kind, to the effect that it has had the opportunity to review the Scheme Booklet and does not propose to appear at the first court hearing. As is its practice in such cases, ASIC does not issue a "no objection" statement under s 411(17) of the Act until the second court hearing.

66 Helpfully, APN's legal advisers have provided a "checklist" that identifies the requirements of the Act and the Corporations Regulations 2001 (Cth) ("the Regulations ") with respect to information required to be included in the explanatory statement. The checklist refers to those parts of the Scheme Booklet that constitute the information required by s 411(3) and s 412(1)(a) of the Act , and by the Regulations , Sch 8, Pt 3 ("Prescribed information relating to proposed compromise or arrangement with members or a class of members").</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 523</tocase>
<text>23 A concern raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications in this Court is that shareholders may be left in a position, once a scheme has become effective, where their shares have been transferred but where there is a delay in the provision of the Scheme Consideration and where their only remedy is to sue on the deed poll (see Re KAZ Group Ltd [2004] FCA 738 at [4] - [5] ; Re Tempo Services Ltd (2005) 53 ACSR 523 at [5]-[6]; Re SFE Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 670 at [4] ; and Re Brambles Industries Ltd (2006) 59 ACSR 501 at [9]). Such "performance risk" has been addressed here by requiring that the Scheme Consideration be paid to APN before 8.00 am on the implementation date to be held by it in trust for the purpose of being paid, free of deductions, to the Scheme participants before they are divested of their shares in APN later on the implementation date. This is provided for in the Deed Poll.
 Disadvantages and Risks</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Re WebCentral Group Ltd (No 2) (2006) 58 ACSR 742</tocase>
<text>58 Clause 3.4 is not a "no encumbrances" provision of the kind considered in Re WebCentral Group Ltd (No 2) (2006) 58 ACSR 742 at [14]-[22] because it cannot give the impression to encumbrancees that their security over the shares is being adversely affected by the transfer. Indeed, it assumes that the shares may be transferred subject to encumbrances, to the detriment of INMAL.

59 In substance, the purpose of the deemed warranty is to prevent a shareholder whose shares are subject to encumbrances from receiving the same Scheme Consideration as that to be received by those whose shares are free from encumbrances, without any obligation, in effect, to refund to INMAL the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. It is not practicable for amounts secured by encumbrance to be deducted from the Scheme Consideration payable to the relevant Scheme participants on the implementation date.

60 The warranty will be deemed to have been given, not only by those Offeree Shareholders who vote to agree to the Scheme, and who, therefore, can be seen to be consenting to give it, but also those who do not vote at all or who vote against the Scheme. However, I do not think that this matters. What is important, in my view, is that the deemed warranty is no more than a device directed to ensuring that a Scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty is the amount required to discharge the encumbrance.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>