<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZDJH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 710 (7 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/710.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Applicant S214 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal (2006) 90 ALD 632</tocase>
<text>17 It would appear that s 422B of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) applies to the appellant's application. Prior to the introduction of s 422B there was generally no obligation on the Tribunal to conduct its own investigation or to make some particular inquiry: see generally, WAGJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 277 at [25] ; Applicant S214 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal (2006) 90 ALD 632 at 641; and S1194/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1133 at [13] . With the introduction of s 422B this position is made clear: see SZGQN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 428 at [28] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2005] FCA 1707 ; (2005) 148 FCR 446</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1707.html</AustLII>
<text>20 It is not sufficient to say, as the appellant does, that upon the Federal Magistrates Court making its decision, he tried harder to find further material. The appellant was well aware that his credit was in issue before the Tribunal, and he should have made all efforts to produce all the material he wished to rely upon before the Tribunal. Even if the new evidence would now be admissible, to which I refer to, for example, Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2005] FCA 1707 ; (2005) 148 FCR 446, remembering that this is a review procedure, in my view, I should not allow the additional information to be adduced by the appellant before me.

21 There is a public interest in disposing of public law cases in a timely manner and this is not a case where the issue to be agitated here was not appropriately and clearly put to the appellant before the Tribunal. Fairness does not dictate in this case that I should allow the appellant to tender into evidence any new material for the purposes of this appeal. My function is to review the decision of the federal magistrate and the Tribunal and not to consider the appellant's visa application on the merits and de novo. This is particularly so where the Tribunal did not accept the appellant as a witness of truth.

22 I further observe that the additional material seems to me to be relevant to the appellant's credibility. The Tribunal, in considering the material of Mr Kalin, was treating it as confirmatory of its view that the appellant was not telling the truth about his involvement with Jehovah's Witnesses. Even if the Tribunal had the additional information before it, any response, in my view, would not have affected the Tribunal's finding about the credit-worthiness of the appellant. I am not satisfied that there is any significant possibility that the decision of the Tribunal or the Federal Magistrates Court would have been different if the additional information now sought to be relied upon was in fact before either the Tribunal or the federal magistrate.

23 In my view, the approach of the Tribunal and the federal magistrate, and their conclusions, were correct. Accordingly, the appeal will be dismissed. 

 I certify that the preceding twenty-three (23) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Middleton. 


 Associate:

Dated: 17 May 2007

 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: V McWilliam 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore 
 
 Date of Hearing: 7 May 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 May 2007 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/710.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chopra v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 480</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/480.html</AustLII>
<text>19 I now turn to the question of the additional information. In my view the appellant has had ample opportunity to put material to the Tribunal and to place any evidence to rebut the statements of Mr Kalin. In fact, the appellant did address the Federal Magistrates Court as to Mr Kalin possibly being wrong. Even before the federal magistrate no additional information was sought to be tendered into evidence. No sufficient explanation is now offered in relation to the additional information sought to be relied upon and why it was not sought to be relied upon earlier: see generally, Chopra v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 480 at [68] and following.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/10.html</AustLII>
<text>18 In any event, it is apparent from this case that the Tribunal did make inquiries as to whether conscientious objectors were sent to prison. It relied upon information from Mr Kalin in forming its view on whether conscientious objectors were sent to prison. I see nothing wrong with the approach of the Tribunal in making this choice in its assessment of the information, and this is clearly a factual matter for it: see NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10 at [11] to [13].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>S1194/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1133</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1133.html</AustLII>
<text>17 It would appear that s 422B of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) applies to the appellant's application. Prior to the introduction of s 422B there was generally no obligation on the Tribunal to conduct its own investigation or to make some particular inquiry: see generally, WAGJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 277 at [25] ; Applicant S214 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal (2006) 90 ALD 632 at 641; and S1194/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1133 at [13] . With the introduction of s 422B this position is made clear: see SZGQN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 428 at [28] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZGQN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 428</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/428.html</AustLII>
<text>17 It would appear that s 422B of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) applies to the appellant's application. Prior to the introduction of s 422B there was generally no obligation on the Tribunal to conduct its own investigation or to make some particular inquiry: see generally, WAGJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 277 at [25] ; Applicant S214 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal (2006) 90 ALD 632 at 641; and S1194/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1133 at [13] . With the introduction of s 422B this position is made clear: see SZGQN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 428 at [28] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>WAGJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 277</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/277.html</AustLII>
<text>17 It would appear that s 422B of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) applies to the appellant's application. Prior to the introduction of s 422B there was generally no obligation on the Tribunal to conduct its own investigation or to make some particular inquiry: see generally, WAGJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 277 at [25] ; Applicant S214 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal (2006) 90 ALD 632 at 641; and S1194/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1133 at [13] . With the introduction of s 422B this position is made clear: see SZGQN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 428 at [28] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>