<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Attila Timar-Peregrin v The University of Melbourne [2007] FCA 742 (18 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/742.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/12.html</AustLII>
<text>26 It is not open to the appellant, on this appeal, effectively to advance a case that was not run at trial. This is so, even if the case which it is now sought to run can be supported by reference to particulars contained in the statement of claim. He is bound by the way in which his application was prosecuted at trial: see Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491 at 497. It cannot, fairly, be asserted that the Federal Magistrate fell into error by failing to deal with aspects of the appellant's pleaded case which were not presented at trial.

27 In any event, I do not consider that the appellant's claim that representations were made on occasions other than the 18 April 2002 meeting can be sustained. I have examined each of the documents relied on by the appellant (listed above at [9] and [13]) and the evidence relating to those documents. At best for the appellant, some of them may, arguably, contain statements which might be said to be consistent with the appellant's allegation that the relevant representations were made at the meeting on 18 April 2002. None of them contained evidence of any separate representations of the kind alleged being made at other times. The Federal Magistrate did not overlook this material. Most of it is referred to in his reasons at paras 18ff. He was not invited to find that any of this material evidenced the making of either of the representations at other times and he did not do so.

28 In my view the Federal Magistrate did not err. It was open to him, on the evidence and the case presented to him, to conclude, as he did, that the alleged representations had not been made by Professor Angus on 18 April 2002.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>