<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 794 (29 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/794.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Adams v Naylor [1946] AC 543</tocase>
<text>46 At [157], Heydon JA pointed out that 'the court is not bound to act on admissions made by the parties or on states of fact agreed between the parties.' His Honour then cited the Gramophone Co case, quoting an extensive passage from the speech of Lord Loreburn LC, including the passage I have quoted at [43]. At [158] and [159], his Honour referred to two other English cases, Adams v Naylor [1946] AC 543 and Royster v Cavey [1947] KB 204, in both of which it had been held that crucial admissions on which the cases had been conducted at first instance should not be accepted, because they were contrary to fact. By way of conclusion, at [160], Heydon JA said:
 'In short, the courts are averse to pronouncing judgments on hypotheses which are not correct. To do so is tantamount to giving advisory opinions and to encouraging collusive litigation. On the other hand, the courts will act on admissions of or agreements about matters of fact where there is no reason to doubt their correctness. But they are reluctant to do so where there is reason to question the correctness of the facts admitted or agreed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ahern v R [1988] HCA 39 ; (1988) 165 CLR 87</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/39.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Some confirmation of this proposition is available from the authorities. On two occasions, the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeal has said that s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act 1995 (NSW) (which is in the same form as s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act ) reproduces the pre-existing common law. See R v Macraild (unreported, NSW Court of Criminal Appeal, Sully, Dunford and Simpson JJ, 18 December 1997) at 9 and Watt v R [2000] NSWCCA 37 at [8] . The pre-existing common law is found in Tripodi v R [1961] HCA 22 ; (1961) 104 CLR 1 at 7 and Ahern v R [1988] HCA 39 ; (1988) 165 CLR 87 at 100. In both of these cases, the High Court of Australia made it clear that the statement by B could only be admissible against C if there were 'reasonable evidence' establishing the existence of the common purpose, apart from the statement itself. I do not necessarily accept, as the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeals appears to have done, that the 'reasonable evidence' test is identical to the formulation 'reasonably open to find' preferred by the legislature. For present purposes, however, Macraild and Watt stand as authority for the proposition that, so far as they are consistent with the terms of s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act , Tripodi and Ahern are to be taken as providing authority on the proper construction of that provision. It follows that s 87(1)(c) must be applied on the basis that the admissibility of B's statement as against C can only be determined by reference to evidence other than the statement itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] FCAFC 161 (2005) ATPR 42-078</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/161.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Counsel for the ACCC found it necessary to grapple with the use of the word 'commitment' in the judgment of the Full Court in Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] FCAFC 161 (2005) ATPR 42-078 (' Apco Service Stations ') at [43] [47]. In that case, which concerned allegations that dealers in the Ballarat retail petrol market had been involved in an arrangement or understanding to fix the price of petrol, and which involved some of the parties to the present case, the trial judge had declined to make a finding that one dealer became committed to any price increase agreed on by the other dealers. In addition, his Honour had made a finding that the other dealers had no expectation that the uncommitted dealer's readiness to receive telephone calls about prices meant that the uncommitted dealer would substantially match those prices. The Full Court expressed the view that these findings led to the unavoidable conclusion that the uncommitted dealer was not a party to any understanding that it would fix its prices at the same level as the other dealers or at any particular level, or even that it would increase its prices at all. In expressing this view, at [45], the Full Court pointed out that the appellants in that case had not disputed that the trial judge had enunciated the correct legal principles. The trial judge had referred, and the Full Court also referred, to observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] , which were specifically endorsed by a Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] . Lindgren J said:
 'The cases require that at least one party "assume an obligation" or give an "assurance" or "undertaking" that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the Meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have "aroused" that expectation by things he said at the Meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an "understanding" in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word "understanding" with the words "agreement" and "arrangement" and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ACCC v Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd &amp; Anor [2006] HCATrans 272</tocase>
<text>37 In the present case, counsel for the ACCC recognised that the judgment in Apco Service Stations was binding on me. They made the formal submission that the Full Court was in error when it required that there be some commitment, before there could be an understanding for the purposes of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act . The reality is that the previous authorities dealing with the content of an understanding, as distinct from its formation, provide ample support for what the Full Court said in Apco Service Stations . More than ample support is also found in the analysis of the relevant provisions, which I have already set out in [24] [34]. As I have said, for the purposes of s 45(2)(a) there can be no such thing as an understanding that leaves each party to it free to do whatever it wishes. Whatever word may be chosen to represent the essential element of an understanding for the purposes of the relevant statutory provisions, it is clear that element involves the assumption of an obligation, unenforceable in any court of law, but merely morally binding or binding in honour. Any reservation that may have existed about this has been dispelled by the High Court, which dismissed the ACCC's application for special leave to appeal from the Full Court in Apco Service Stations on 2 June 2006. See ACCC v Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd &amp; Anor [2006] HCATrans 272. At line 619, giving the judgment of himself and Hayne J, Gleeson CJ said:
 'The decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court turned not upon any controversial view of the meaning of the relevant provisions of the Trade Practices Act but upon the Full Court's view of the facts in the light of the case as pleaded and argued by the Commission. In the light of the facts as found, the case does not raise any issue of law suitable to a grant of special leave to appeal. The application is dismissed with costs.'

38 For all of these reasons, quite apart from its binding effect on me, the correctness of the Full Court's judgment in Apco Service Stations cannot be doubted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 (1999) 92 FCR 375</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/954.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Counsel for the ACCC found it necessary to grapple with the use of the word 'commitment' in the judgment of the Full Court in Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] FCAFC 161 (2005) ATPR 42-078 (' Apco Service Stations ') at [43] [47]. In that case, which concerned allegations that dealers in the Ballarat retail petrol market had been involved in an arrangement or understanding to fix the price of petrol, and which involved some of the parties to the present case, the trial judge had declined to make a finding that one dealer became committed to any price increase agreed on by the other dealers. In addition, his Honour had made a finding that the other dealers had no expectation that the uncommitted dealer's readiness to receive telephone calls about prices meant that the uncommitted dealer would substantially match those prices. The Full Court expressed the view that these findings led to the unavoidable conclusion that the uncommitted dealer was not a party to any understanding that it would fix its prices at the same level as the other dealers or at any particular level, or even that it would increase its prices at all. In expressing this view, at [45], the Full Court pointed out that the appellants in that case had not disputed that the trial judge had enunciated the correct legal principles. The trial judge had referred, and the Full Court also referred, to observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] , which were specifically endorsed by a Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] . Lindgren J said:
 'The cases require that at least one party "assume an obligation" or give an "assurance" or "undertaking" that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the Meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have "aroused" that expectation by things he said at the Meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an "understanding" in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word "understanding" with the words "agreement" and "arrangement" and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required.'

39 As I have said, the concepts of contract, arrangement and understanding relevant to the application of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act are concepts representing points on a spectrum of consensual dealings. It is possible that the spectrum might be extended in one direction beyond contract, to include even more solemnly binding consensual obligations, such as deeds under seal. It is difficult to see that the spectrum of consensual dealings could extend in the other direction beyond the concept of 'understanding', whilst still remaining relevant for the purposes of s 45(2)(a). That end of the spectrum, therefore, lies somewhere between the outer limits of what constitutes an 'understanding' and the closest form of non-consensual dealing that could be imagined. It is possible that this closest form is the expectation that a party will act in a particular way, engendered by that party, to which Lindgren J referred in CC (NSW) Pty Ltd at [141]. It may be in the realm of parallel conduct, even conscious parallel conduct, such as the adoption of identical prices for homogeneous products, which clearly lies beyond the realm of 'understanding'. See the American authorities cited by Lockhart J in Email at 56 57.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Francis [2004] FCA 487 (2004) 142 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/487.html</AustLII>
<text>55 Termijtelen is authority for the proposition that the fact that an admission is a deemed admission, pursuant to a provision such as O 11 r 13 of the Federal Court Rules , does not have any effect on the question whether the Court should make a finding in accordance with it if the admission appears unreliable. It is also possible for the Court to dispense with compliance with the requirements of O 11 r 13, under the general dispensing power found in O 1 r 8 of the Federal Court Rules . See Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Francis [2004] FCA 487 (2004) 142 FCR 1 at [42] [43]. It is clear that the powers in O 18 r 4(1) and (2) respectively are discretionary; the Court is not obliged to give judgment on the basis of admissions made, whether in pleadings or otherwise. Nor is it obliged to give such judgment without determining the other issues remaining in the proceeding.

56 The applicant, the ACCC, is established by s 6A(1) of the Trade Practices Act . By s 6A(2)(a) , the ACCC is a body corporate and by s 6A(2)(d) it may sue in its corporate name. The ACCC is a party given standing by s 77(1) of the Trade Practices Act to institute a proceeding for the recovery on behalf of the Commonwealth of a pecuniary penalty referred to in s 76. Section 80(1) also gives the ACCC standing to apply for an injunction.

57 Among the 18 respondents to the proceeding, the first eight are corporations. They are respectively: the first respondent, Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd ('Leahy'); the second respondent, Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd ('Apco'); the third respondent, Pegasus Retail Pty Ltd ('Pegasus'); the fourth respondent, United Geelong Pty Ltd, formerly called United Fuels Pty Ltd ('United Fuels'); the fifth respondent, Brumar (Vic) Pty Ltd ('Brumar'); the sixth respondent, United Retail Pty Ltd ('United Retail'); the seventh respondent, Liberty Petroleum Pty Ltd ('Liberty') and the eighth respondent, Andrianopoulos Motors Pty Ltd ('Andrianopoulos').</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 (2004) 141 FCR 183</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2004/1678.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The starting point for determining the meaning of statutory provisions must be those provisions themselves. Previous authorities, in which the courts have pronounced upon the meanings of particular provisions, may be binding, and are often helpful. Sometimes, however, those pronouncements are made in the context of the resolution of particular issues, which may differ from those raised in a current case. As Merkel J recognised in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 (2004) 141 FCR 183 (' the Ballarat case ') at [57], previous statements of principle can be difficult to apply in a case that raises different issues. As his Honour said, it is necessary to return to the words of the statute.

24 Section 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act uses the terms 'contract', 'arrangement' and 'understanding'. These are plainly intended to represent a spectrum of consensual dealings. The words of the statute themselves so demonstrate. They provide that a corporation is not to 'make' a contract or arrangement, or to 'arrive at' an understanding, if the contract, arrangement or understanding has a specified content. A corporation cannot 'make' a contract or arrangement, or 'arrive at' an understanding, without there being at least one other party to the contract, arrangement or understanding. The other party must also participate in the making, or the arriving at, before there can be a contract, arrangement or understanding. Clearly, it is not possible to 'make' something, or to 'arrive at' something, unless what is made or arrived at exists at the end of the process of making or arriving at. What must exist for s 45(2)(a) to apply is one of the three forms of consensual dealing.

25 The term 'contract' is well understood by lawyers. A contract is the result of the acceptance by one party of an offer made by another, resulting in the minds of the two parties being at one as to the agreement they have made. It must be supported by good consideration, have sufficient certainty of terms that it be possible to determine what has been agreed, and be accompanied by an intention on the part of the parties that a legally binding relationship should be established by it. In ordinary circumstances, the obligations created by a contract are enforceable in a court, but their enforceability is subject to the possibility of defences arising from the nature of the contract itself, or from external circumstances. One defence arising from the nature of the contract itself results from the illegality of its purpose. In using the word 'contract' in s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act , Parliament must have intended to refer to a consensual dealing having the fundamental characteristics of a contract, but not necessarily being enforceable in a court of law, because s 45(2)(a) would itself give rise to the defence of illegality, and thereby prevent enforcement. Thus, the word 'contract' for the purposes of s 45(2)(a) describes a consensual dealing with a high degree of formality.

61 On 17 December 2004, Merkel J delivered judgment in the Ballarat case , to which I have referred in [23], in a proceeding in which the ACCC alleged the existence of an arrangement or understanding to fix the prices of petrol in the City of Ballarat and its surrounding area. Among those found to be parties to the Ballarat arrangement or understanding was Brumar. Merkel J also found that Brumar had given effect to that arrangement or understanding on some 53 occasions. See the Ballarat case at [382]. On 17 March 2005, his Honour imposed a pecuniary penalty of $4 000 000 on Brumar in respect of those contraventions. See Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] FCA 254 at [42] . By that date, Brumar was already in liquidation, consequent upon a creditors' meeting on 17 February 2005. Earlier, Brumar had sold its business assets for a sum exceeding $26 000 000. Settlement of the sale occurred on 26 July 2003. After satisfaction of secured and other creditors out of the proceeds of sale, Brumar was left with $994 400. By the time of the liquidation, Brumar was said to have had total assets of $50 000 and creditors totalling $400. After investigation by the liquidator, on 18 May 2005, the liquidator expressed the view that a distribution to creditors of close to 100c in the dollar would be likely, subject to the resolution of a dispute as to whether any debt in respect of the costs awarded against Brumar by Merkel J on 17 March 2005 was provable in the liquidation. The liquidator contended that such a debt could not be proved in the liquidation. For practical purposes, any surplus of assets over liabilities of Brumar would be more than exhausted by the payment of the penalty imposed by Merkel J and the payment of any costs ordered by his Honour. The prospect of the ACCC recovering any pecuniary penalty from Brumar appears to be non-existent. Accordingly, for reasons similar to those I have given with respect to Leahy in [58], I also refused the ACCC's application, pursuant to s 500(2) of the Corporations Act , for leave to proceed against Brumar.

191 Shortly before Easter 2000, a petrol retailer in Ballarat rang a Melbourne radio station and made public the petrol price-fixing practices in Ballarat, which Merkel J subsequently found to have existed in the Ballarat case . The ACCC then announced that it would conduct an investigation into petrol pricing in Ballarat. Leahy was one of the corporations investigated in respect of its activities in Ballarat. Although he was not involved with the setting of prices for the Leahy outlets in Ballarat, Mr Carmichael became aware of a notice to Leahy under s 155 of the Trade Practices Act in relation to its Ballarat activities. He thereby became aware, about the middle of 2000, that the ACCC was using telephone call records to prove its case in Ballarat.

192 The initial announcement of the ACCC investigation in Ballarat made Ian Carmichael and Peter Anderson reluctant to discuss petrol prices on the telephone. They were not sure that the ACCC was not listening to their telephone calls. They began visiting each other's offices and talking in person about price movements. After a time, Mr Carmichael became 'a little bit cocky'. While he was keen on communications other than by telephone, there were occasions when Mr Carmichael would arrange to meet either Graeme Chisholm or Darren Campigli in the car park between Leahy's depot and the Caltex depot, where Mr Chisholm and Mr Campigli worked.

193 Fear of being detected by telephone bugging also led Mr Carmichael to invent a code, by which he hoped to communicate prices and times to those to whom he spoke. He would ring up and announce to the recipient of the call (Peter Anderson, Darren Campigli, Colin Williamson or Phil Carmichael) that an aeroplane of a particular model (eg a 939, representing 93.9c per litre) was due to land at Avalon Airport at a particular time, with a specified number of passengers (which represented the price of liquefied petroleum gas). The first time Mr Carmichael used this device, the recipient of the call did not understand it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] FCA 254</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/254.html</AustLII>
<text>61 On 17 December 2004, Merkel J delivered judgment in the Ballarat case , to which I have referred in [23], in a proceeding in which the ACCC alleged the existence of an arrangement or understanding to fix the prices of petrol in the City of Ballarat and its surrounding area. Among those found to be parties to the Ballarat arrangement or understanding was Brumar. Merkel J also found that Brumar had given effect to that arrangement or understanding on some 53 occasions. See the Ballarat case at [382]. On 17 March 2005, his Honour imposed a pecuniary penalty of $4 000 000 on Brumar in respect of those contraventions. See Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] FCA 254 at [42] . By that date, Brumar was already in liquidation, consequent upon a creditors' meeting on 17 February 2005. Earlier, Brumar had sold its business assets for a sum exceeding $26 000 000. Settlement of the sale occurred on 26 July 2003. After satisfaction of secured and other creditors out of the proceeds of sale, Brumar was left with $994 400. By the time of the liquidation, Brumar was said to have had total assets of $50 000 and creditors totalling $400. After investigation by the liquidator, on 18 May 2005, the liquidator expressed the view that a distribution to creditors of close to 100c in the dollar would be likely, subject to the resolution of a dispute as to whether any debt in respect of the costs awarded against Brumar by Merkel J on 17 March 2005 was provable in the liquidation. The liquidator contended that such a debt could not be proved in the liquidation. For practical purposes, any surplus of assets over liabilities of Brumar would be more than exhausted by the payment of the penalty imposed by Merkel J and the payment of any costs ordered by his Honour. The prospect of the ACCC recovering any pecuniary penalty from Brumar appears to be non-existent. Accordingly, for reasons similar to those I have given with respect to Leahy in [58], I also refused the ACCC's application, pursuant to s 500(2) of the Corporations Act , for leave to proceed against Brumar.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>British Basic Slag Ltd v Registrar of Restrictive Trading Agreements [1963] 2 All ER 807</tocase>
<text>28 However broad and flexible an understanding might be, for the purposes of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act it must be a consensual dealing between parties. Like an arrangement, it falls outside the sphere of contractual obligations of a kind normally enforceable in a court. Unlike an arrangement, it can be tacit, in the sense that it can be arrived at by each party, either by words or acts, signifying an intention to act in a particular way in relation to a matter of concern to another party. In order to be a consensual dealing, however, an understanding must involve a meeting of minds. In Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 24 FLR 286 at 291, Smithers J (with whom Evatt J agreed) referred to what Diplock LJ said in British Basic Slag Ltd v Registrar of Restrictive Trading Agreements [1963] 2 All ER 807 at 819 in relation to English legislation in terms different from s 45(2) of the Trade Practices Act , and said:
 'by parity of reasoning it would follow that the existence of an arrangement of the kind contemplated in s. 45 is conditional upon a meeting of the minds of the parties to the arrangement in which one of them is understood, by the other or others, and intends to be so understood, as undertaking, in the role of a reasonable and conscientious man, to regard himself as being in some degree under a duty, moral or legal, to conduct himself in some particular way, at any rate so long as the other party or parties conducted themselves in the way contemplated by the arrangement. 
 
 It seems to me also that an understanding must involve the meeting of two or more minds. Where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction between them proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct, it would seem that there would be an understanding within the meaning of the Act.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Damberg v Damberg [2001] NSWCA 87 (2001) 52 NSWLR 492</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2001/87.html</AustLII>
<text>44 In Damberg v Damberg [2001] NSWCA 87 (2001) 52 NSWLR 492 at [148] [160], Heydon JA (as his Honour then was), with whom Spigelman CJ and Sheller JA agreed, engaged in a lengthy examination of the question whether, and to what extent, admissions or agreements between the parties could bind a court. At [148], Heydon JA identified the problem as being 'the extent to which the parties, by their conduct of proceedings, can prevent the court from deciding a case in accordance with the law or the facts.' At [149], his Honour acknowledged that the pleadings define the issues in a civil case, and that a party failing to plead a claim or defence will generally be unable to rely on it at a later time. His Honour then proceeded to discuss the various ways in which admissions of fact can be made: informal out-of-court admissions at [151]; formal admissions in answer to interrogatories at [152]; and formal admissions pursuant to rules of court at [153]. His Honour pointed out that each kind of admission can be contradicted by other evidence, or the court can choose not to act on the admissions. At [154], his Honour said:
 'A party may admit allegations made in pleadings by the opposing party, and may do so either expressly or by non-traverse. The effect of such admissions is to narrow the issues in dispute: they can thus have the effect of restricting the evidence to be tendered and can prevent evidence being called to the contrary.'

45 Heydon JA then mentioned concessions by a solicitor before a trial or by counsel during a trial, or admissions ordered by a court as an alternative to filing evidence to the contrary within a specified time. His Honour also made reference to a statutory power permitting agreed statements of facts. At [155], his Honour said:
 'There are significant limitations on the extent to which the use of the above facilities can compel a court to decide a case on a basis contrary to fact.'

47 In Symes v The Proprietors Strata Plan No 31731 [2003] NSWCA 7 at [45] , Heydon JA (with whom Sheller JA and McClellan J agreed) referred to Damberg , saying:
 'It is true that there are cases where the courts are averse to pronouncing judgments on incorrect factual hypotheses, because to do so amounts to the giving of advisory opinions and to encouraging collusive litigation: see the cases discussed in Damberg v Damberg [2001] NSWCA 87 ; (2001) 52 NSWLR 492 at [148] - [160] . However, these perils do not exist here. It has not been demonstrated that the hypothesis that No 3 wall was common property is plainly incorrect. There is some evidence that it was incorrect; on this appeal evidence strongly pointing in the contrary direction has been filed. Courts commonly act on admissions in relation to matters of fact which might be disputed if the parties desired to do so, but which they have chosen to arrive at a compromise about.'

49 In my view, to confine the non-acceptance of admissions on the pleadings to circumstances in which their falsity has been established would be too stringent a rule. I recognise that it is important that a party whose allegations in the pleadings have been admitted ought to be entitled to rely upon those admissions. Too great a willingness to depart from those admissions would lead to the lengthening of trials and to uncertainty in the administration of justice, both of which are very undesirable. It seems to me, however, that Heydon JA's formulation of the test in Damberg is the appropriate one, namely that the Court can (and perhaps should) decline to act on admissions when there is 'reason to doubt their correctness', or 'reason to question the correctness of the facts admitted or agreed.'

50 In a case such as the present, there are particular public policy reasons for adopting this less stringent test. The size of this piece of litigation, and the expense of retaining solicitors and counsel to conduct a full-scale defence in a long trial, provide a powerful incentive to the making of admissions, in the hope of securing leniency. In a case in which admissions on the pleadings are made by parties who lack the resources to conduct lengthy litigation in their own defence, the Court should be more ready to put aside the admissions if they appear to be unreliable. Further, in a case such as this, allegations are made of the existence, and the giving effect to, of arrangements or understandings between various parties. There is no alleged arrangement or understanding the existence of which is admitted by both (or, in one instance, all three) parties to it. At best for the ACCC, one party to an alleged arrangement or understanding has admitted the existence, and the implementation, of that arrangement or understanding. The other alleged party (or, in one instance, two parties) to each such admitted arrangement or understanding has defended itself against the allegation. In those circumstances, if the applicant fails to prove against the non-admitting party (or parties) the existence of the arrangement or understanding, then there is a considerable risk that the processes of the Court will be brought into disrepute, if the Court should be required to find against the admitting party that the arrangement or understanding existed and was implemented, but finds in favour of the denying party (or parties) that it did not exist. Members of the public would have some difficulty in understanding how the Court, in a civil case, could reach such contradictory findings. Again, this provides a substantial reason for refusing to act on admissions on the pleadings if, in the light of the evidence, those admissions may be unreliable.

51 Another factor pertinent to a case such as the present is that an admission may amount to a concession as to a matter of law, or a conclusion on a matter of mixed fact and law. If the law is complex, or there is difficulty in determining on which side of an indistinct line the particular facts fall, it is necessary to be wary of accepting an admission conflicting with conclusions drawn on the evidence, and with the benefit of full submissions as to the law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd (1979) 41 FLR 277</tocase>
<text>26 The word 'arrangement' is less clearly understood, and more susceptible of elasticity as to its meaning. In general, it appears to connote a consensual dealing lacking some of the essential elements that would otherwise make it a contract. For instance, a dealing that would otherwise be a contract may be described as an 'arrangement' if the parties to it intended not to create a legally binding relationship, but only to give expression to their intentions as to the obligations that each felt morally bound to adhere to in relation to what was to pass between them, or to be carried out by them. Of course, an arrangement might be a broader concept than this, because it is a term the boundaries of which have not been fixed in the traditional understanding of lawyers. The Oxford English Dictionary gives as the apparently appropriate meaning of the word 'arrangement' 'a settlement of mutual relations or claims between parties; an adjustment of disputed or debatable matters; a settlement by agreement', or alternatively, 'disposition of measures for the accomplishment of a purpose; preparations for successful performance.' The ordinary understanding of what amounts to an 'arrangement' makes it difficult to envisage that an arrangement could come about without express negotiations between the parties, although there have been suggestions that an arrangement can be tacit. See Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd (1979) 41 FLR 277 at 301 302 per Fisher J, with whom Brennan and Deane JJ agreed, referred to by Franki J in Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 at 24 in the context of s 45(2) of the Trade Practices Act . At the very least, there must be some express communication between the parties, although what is said may not amount to offer and acceptance for the purposes of the law of contract. The need for express communication is also suggested by the use of the verb 'make' in conjunction with both 'contract' and 'arrangement' in s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act . It is hard to see how two parties could 'make' an 'arrangement' without doing so expressly, at least as to the substance of the arrangement, even if the acceptance by one party of what the other has communicated is implicit in some act, rather than expressed in words.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/55.html</AustLII>
<text>33 In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lutovi Investments Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 55 ; (1978) 140 CLR 434, the High Court was dealing with the meaning of the word 'arrangement' in legislation other than the Trade Practices Act . In a passage that has often been cited in judgments dealing with arrangements or understandings under the Trade Practices Act , Gibbs and Mason JJ (with whom Murphy J agreed) said at 444:
 'It is, however, necessary that an arrangement should be consensual, and that there should be some adoption of it. But in our view it is not essential that the parties are committed to it or are bound to support it. An arrangement may be informal as well as unenforceable and the parties may be free to withdraw from it or to act inconsistently with it, notwithstanding their adoption of it.'

34 This passage cannot be relied upon to suggest that an arrangement or understanding under s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act need have no substance at all. Plainly, it contemplates that there must be something of substance from which the parties can withdraw, or with which they can act inconsistently. By their 'adoption' of whatever matter of substance is part of the arrangement or understanding, the parties will necessarily have adopted a provision that they see as an appropriate way to regulate their future conduct. To say that they are able to withdraw from the adoption of such a provision, or to act inconsistently with it, is to say nothing more than that an arrangement or understanding is not enforceable in a court of law in the way that a contract is. The notion of an arrangement or understanding that each party will act as it sees fit on every occasion is entirely foreign to s 45 of the Trade Practices Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gramophone Co Ltd v Magazine Holder Co (1911) 28 RPC 221</tocase>
<text>43 There is some authority, apparently not conclusive, as to the circumstances in which the discretion might be exercised. As long ago as Gramophone Co Ltd v Magazine Holder Co (1911) 28 RPC 221, the House of Lords recognised that there were circumstances in which a court should not be bound to accept admissions. At 225, Lord Loreburn LC (with whom the Earl of Halsbury, Lord Atkinson and Lord Shaw agreed) said:
 'It is the duty of a Court to decide cases according to the truth and fact, not according to any assumed or artificial state of facts which the parties may find it convenient to present. No doubt Courts of Law allow and indeed encourage parties to simplify litigation by making admissions and to a certain extent by waiving their rights, because, when there is a real controversy depending upon real facts, everyone ought to facilitate its authoritative settlement. But that is a very different thing from allowing people to obtain an adjudication upon the footing that something exists or has happened which in truth does not exist, or has never happened. The objection to such a course is most striking when the parties agree to admit as true something which lies at the root of the jurisdiction, and any judgment obtained upon the footing of its truth may be used as a weapon in terrorem against persons not parties to the admission. A Court of Justice can never be bound to accept as true any fact, merely because it is admitted between the parties.'

46 At [157], Heydon JA pointed out that 'the court is not bound to act on admissions made by the parties or on states of fact agreed between the parties.' His Honour then cited the Gramophone Co case, quoting an extensive passage from the speech of Lord Loreburn LC, including the passage I have quoted at [43]. At [158] and [159], his Honour referred to two other English cases, Adams v Naylor [1946] AC 543 and Royster v Cavey [1947] KB 204, in both of which it had been held that crucial admissions on which the cases had been conducted at first instance should not be accepted, because they were contrary to fact. By way of conclusion, at [160], Heydon JA said:
 'In short, the courts are averse to pronouncing judgments on hypotheses which are not correct. To do so is tantamount to giving advisory opinions and to encouraging collusive litigation. On the other hand, the courts will act on admissions of or agreements about matters of fact where there is no reason to doubt their correctness. But they are reluctant to do so where there is reason to question the correctness of the facts admitted or agreed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81</tocase>
<text>27 The word 'understanding' is obviously intended to connote a less precise dealing than either a contract or arrangement. This is so because of the meaning of the word 'understanding' itself, and because, in the terms of s 45(2)(a) , the parties to it may 'arrive at' it instead of making it. Once again, the Oxford English Dictionary supplies an appropriate definition: 'a mutual arrangement or agreement of an informal but more or less explicit nature.' It is the informal and less explicit nature of an understanding that led Smithers J to describe the concept of an understanding as 'broad and flexible' in L Grollo &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Nu-Statt Decorating Pty Ltd (1978) 34 FLR 81 at 89.

29 Similarly, in Grollo at 89, Smithers J said as to an understanding that:
 'It may arise merely where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct'.

30 This view as to what is necessary for the formation of an understanding has been followed on many occasions. It is unnecessary to set out all of the authorities in which it has been referred to. I accept the correctness of what Smithers J said without hesitation. It is important, however, not to confuse what is required for the formation of an understanding within the meaning of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act with what is required to be the content of an arrangement or understanding for the purposes of s 45(2)(a). Counsel for the ACCC were inclined to rely on authorities describing the formation of an understanding, when attempting to persuade the Court as to the required content.

31 Section 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act , and the other provisions found in s 45 and s 45A , which are set out above, make a number of things very clear. To fall within s 45(2)(a) , an arrangement or understanding must be substantial enough to contain at least one 'provision'. The Oxford English Dictionary relevantly defines 'provision' as meaning:
 'Each of the clauses or divisions of a legal or formal statement, or such a statement itself, providing for some particular matter; also, a clause in such a statement which makes an express stipulation or condition; a proviso.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Macraild (unreported, NSW Court of Criminal Appeal, Sully, Dunford and Simpson JJ, 18 December 1997)</tocase>
<text>54 Some confirmation of this proposition is available from the authorities. On two occasions, the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeal has said that s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act 1995 (NSW) (which is in the same form as s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act ) reproduces the pre-existing common law. See R v Macraild (unreported, NSW Court of Criminal Appeal, Sully, Dunford and Simpson JJ, 18 December 1997) at 9 and Watt v R [2000] NSWCCA 37 at [8] . The pre-existing common law is found in Tripodi v R [1961] HCA 22 ; (1961) 104 CLR 1 at 7 and Ahern v R [1988] HCA 39 ; (1988) 165 CLR 87 at 100. In both of these cases, the High Court of Australia made it clear that the statement by B could only be admissible against C if there were 'reasonable evidence' establishing the existence of the common purpose, apart from the statement itself. I do not necessarily accept, as the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeals appears to have done, that the 'reasonable evidence' test is identical to the formulation 'reasonably open to find' preferred by the legislature. For present purposes, however, Macraild and Watt stand as authority for the proposition that, so far as they are consistent with the terms of s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act , Tripodi and Ahern are to be taken as providing authority on the proper construction of that provision. It follows that s 87(1)(c) must be applied on the basis that the admissibility of B's statement as against C can only be determined by reference to evidence other than the statement itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royster v Cavey [1947] KB 204</tocase>
<text>46 At [157], Heydon JA pointed out that 'the court is not bound to act on admissions made by the parties or on states of fact agreed between the parties.' His Honour then cited the Gramophone Co case, quoting an extensive passage from the speech of Lord Loreburn LC, including the passage I have quoted at [43]. At [158] and [159], his Honour referred to two other English cases, Adams v Naylor [1946] AC 543 and Royster v Cavey [1947] KB 204, in both of which it had been held that crucial admissions on which the cases had been conducted at first instance should not be accepted, because they were contrary to fact. By way of conclusion, at [160], Heydon JA said:
 'In short, the courts are averse to pronouncing judgments on hypotheses which are not correct. To do so is tantamount to giving advisory opinions and to encouraging collusive litigation. On the other hand, the courts will act on admissions of or agreements about matters of fact where there is no reason to doubt their correctness. But they are reluctant to do so where there is reason to question the correctness of the facts admitted or agreed.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 (2002) 118 FCR 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/213.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Counsel for the ACCC found it necessary to grapple with the use of the word 'commitment' in the judgment of the Full Court in Apco Service Stations Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2005] FCAFC 161 (2005) ATPR 42-078 (' Apco Service Stations ') at [43] [47]. In that case, which concerned allegations that dealers in the Ballarat retail petrol market had been involved in an arrangement or understanding to fix the price of petrol, and which involved some of the parties to the present case, the trial judge had declined to make a finding that one dealer became committed to any price increase agreed on by the other dealers. In addition, his Honour had made a finding that the other dealers had no expectation that the uncommitted dealer's readiness to receive telephone calls about prices meant that the uncommitted dealer would substantially match those prices. The Full Court expressed the view that these findings led to the unavoidable conclusion that the uncommitted dealer was not a party to any understanding that it would fix its prices at the same level as the other dealers or at any particular level, or even that it would increase its prices at all. In expressing this view, at [45], the Full Court pointed out that the appellants in that case had not disputed that the trial judge had enunciated the correct legal principles. The trial judge had referred, and the Full Court also referred, to observations of Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 954 (1999) 92 FCR 375 at [141] , which were specifically endorsed by a Full Court in Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 (2002) 118 FCR 236 at [79] . Lindgren J said:
 'The cases require that at least one party "assume an obligation" or give an "assurance" or "undertaking" that it will act in a certain way. A mere expectation that as a matter of fact a party will act in a certain way is not enough, even if it has been engendered by that party. In the present case, for example, each individual who attended the Meeting may have expected that as a matter of fact the others would return to their respective offices by car, or, to express the matter differently, each may have been expected by the others to act in that way. Each may even have "aroused" that expectation by things he said at the Meeting. But these factual expectations do not found an "understanding" in the sense in which the word is used in ss 45 and 45A . The conjunction of the word "understanding" with the words "agreement" and "arrangement" and the nature of the provisions show that something more is required.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Symes v The Proprietors Strata Plan No 31731 [2003] NSWCA 7</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2003/7.html</AustLII>
<text>47 In Symes v The Proprietors Strata Plan No 31731 [2003] NSWCA 7 at [45] , Heydon JA (with whom Sheller JA and McClellan J agreed) referred to Damberg , saying:
 'It is true that there are cases where the courts are averse to pronouncing judgments on incorrect factual hypotheses, because to do so amounts to the giving of advisory opinions and to encouraging collusive litigation: see the cases discussed in Damberg v Damberg [2001] NSWCA 87 ; (2001) 52 NSWLR 492 at [148] - [160] . However, these perils do not exist here. It has not been demonstrated that the hypothesis that No 3 wall was common property is plainly incorrect. There is some evidence that it was incorrect; on this appeal evidence strongly pointing in the contrary direction has been filed. Courts commonly act on admissions in relation to matters of fact which might be disputed if the parties desired to do so, but which they have chosen to arrive at a compromise about.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Termijtelen v Van Arkel [1974] 1 NSWLR 525</tocase>
<text>42 It is clear that the power given to the Court by O 18 r 4(1) of the Federal Court Rules to pronounce judgment based on the admissions of a party is discretionary. The use of the word 'may' in the rule itself indicates this. If authority be needed to make good the proposition that the power is discretionary, it is found in Termijtelen v Van Arkel [1974] 1 NSWLR 525 at 529 per Hope JA and at 534 535 per Bowen CJ in Eq. In that case, the Court of Appeal of New South Wales was examining three separate legislative grants of power to give judgment based on admissions arising from pleadings. Their Honours held that each of the three grants of power was a grant of discretionary power.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 24 FLR 286</tocase>
<text>28 However broad and flexible an understanding might be, for the purposes of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act it must be a consensual dealing between parties. Like an arrangement, it falls outside the sphere of contractual obligations of a kind normally enforceable in a court. Unlike an arrangement, it can be tacit, in the sense that it can be arrived at by each party, either by words or acts, signifying an intention to act in a particular way in relation to a matter of concern to another party. In order to be a consensual dealing, however, an understanding must involve a meeting of minds. In Top Performance Motors Pty Ltd v Ira Berk (Queensland) Pty Ltd (1975) 24 FLR 286 at 291, Smithers J (with whom Evatt J agreed) referred to what Diplock LJ said in British Basic Slag Ltd v Registrar of Restrictive Trading Agreements [1963] 2 All ER 807 at 819 in relation to English legislation in terms different from s 45(2) of the Trade Practices Act , and said:
 'by parity of reasoning it would follow that the existence of an arrangement of the kind contemplated in s. 45 is conditional upon a meeting of the minds of the parties to the arrangement in which one of them is understood, by the other or others, and intends to be so understood, as undertaking, in the role of a reasonable and conscientious man, to regard himself as being in some degree under a duty, moral or legal, to conduct himself in some particular way, at any rate so long as the other party or parties conducted themselves in the way contemplated by the arrangement. 
 
 It seems to me also that an understanding must involve the meeting of two or more minds. Where the minds of the parties are at one that a proposed transaction between them proceeds on the basis of the maintenance of a particular state of affairs or the adoption of a particular course of conduct, it would seem that there would be an understanding within the meaning of the Act.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 31 ALR 53</tocase>
<text>36 In Apco Service Stations at [46], the Full Court said that the trial judge's findings amounted to no more than what Lindgren J described as a 'factual expectation', falling short of an 'understanding'. The Full Court then referred at [47] to the judgment of Lockhart J in Trade Practices Commission v Email Ltd (1980) 31 ALR 53 as a practical illustration of the proposition that a mere hope or expectation that a party will act in a particular way is insufficient to constitute an 'understanding' for the purposes of s 45(2) of the Trade Practices Act . The Full Court pointed out that Lockhart J in Email held that, whilst sending price lists to a competitor assisted the competitor to follow the sender's prices if it chose to do so, and to do so more quickly than might otherwise be the case, in the absence of any commitment such communications were not sufficient to give rise to the meeting of minds essential to an arrangement or understanding. The Full Court held that the same principle was applicable in the Apco Service Stations case. Information conveyed by some dealers to the uncommitted dealer may have been useful to the uncommitted dealer in enabling him to have his franchisees check competitors' prices and know when to raise his own prices if he chose to do so, but the absence of any expectation that he would do so was fatal to the existence of any understanding.

39 As I have said, the concepts of contract, arrangement and understanding relevant to the application of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act are concepts representing points on a spectrum of consensual dealings. It is possible that the spectrum might be extended in one direction beyond contract, to include even more solemnly binding consensual obligations, such as deeds under seal. It is difficult to see that the spectrum of consensual dealings could extend in the other direction beyond the concept of 'understanding', whilst still remaining relevant for the purposes of s 45(2)(a). That end of the spectrum, therefore, lies somewhere between the outer limits of what constitutes an 'understanding' and the closest form of non-consensual dealing that could be imagined. It is possible that this closest form is the expectation that a party will act in a particular way, engendered by that party, to which Lindgren J referred in CC (NSW) Pty Ltd at [141]. It may be in the realm of parallel conduct, even conscious parallel conduct, such as the adoption of identical prices for homogeneous products, which clearly lies beyond the realm of 'understanding'. See the American authorities cited by Lockhart J in Email at 56 57.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>26 The word 'arrangement' is less clearly understood, and more susceptible of elasticity as to its meaning. In general, it appears to connote a consensual dealing lacking some of the essential elements that would otherwise make it a contract. For instance, a dealing that would otherwise be a contract may be described as an 'arrangement' if the parties to it intended not to create a legally binding relationship, but only to give expression to their intentions as to the obligations that each felt morally bound to adhere to in relation to what was to pass between them, or to be carried out by them. Of course, an arrangement might be a broader concept than this, because it is a term the boundaries of which have not been fixed in the traditional understanding of lawyers. The Oxford English Dictionary gives as the apparently appropriate meaning of the word 'arrangement' 'a settlement of mutual relations or claims between parties; an adjustment of disputed or debatable matters; a settlement by agreement', or alternatively, 'disposition of measures for the accomplishment of a purpose; preparations for successful performance.' The ordinary understanding of what amounts to an 'arrangement' makes it difficult to envisage that an arrangement could come about without express negotiations between the parties, although there have been suggestions that an arrangement can be tacit. See Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd (1979) 41 FLR 277 at 301 302 per Fisher J, with whom Brennan and Deane JJ agreed, referred to by Franki J in Trade Practices Commission v TNT Management Pty Ltd (1985) 6 FCR 1 at 24 in the context of s 45(2) of the Trade Practices Act . At the very least, there must be some express communication between the parties, although what is said may not amount to offer and acceptance for the purposes of the law of contract. The need for express communication is also suggested by the use of the verb 'make' in conjunction with both 'contract' and 'arrangement' in s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act . It is hard to see how two parties could 'make' an 'arrangement' without doing so expressly, at least as to the substance of the arrangement, even if the acceptance by one party of what the other has communicated is implicit in some act, rather than expressed in words.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tripodi v R [1961] HCA 22 ; (1961) 104 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1961/22.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Some confirmation of this proposition is available from the authorities. On two occasions, the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeal has said that s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act 1995 (NSW) (which is in the same form as s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act ) reproduces the pre-existing common law. See R v Macraild (unreported, NSW Court of Criminal Appeal, Sully, Dunford and Simpson JJ, 18 December 1997) at 9 and Watt v R [2000] NSWCCA 37 at [8] . The pre-existing common law is found in Tripodi v R [1961] HCA 22 ; (1961) 104 CLR 1 at 7 and Ahern v R [1988] HCA 39 ; (1988) 165 CLR 87 at 100. In both of these cases, the High Court of Australia made it clear that the statement by B could only be admissible against C if there were 'reasonable evidence' establishing the existence of the common purpose, apart from the statement itself. I do not necessarily accept, as the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeals appears to have done, that the 'reasonable evidence' test is identical to the formulation 'reasonably open to find' preferred by the legislature. For present purposes, however, Macraild and Watt stand as authority for the proposition that, so far as they are consistent with the terms of s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act , Tripodi and Ahern are to be taken as providing authority on the proper construction of that provision. It follows that s 87(1)(c) must be applied on the basis that the admissibility of B's statement as against C can only be determined by reference to evidence other than the statement itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Watt v R [2000] NSWCCA 37</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCCA/2000/37.html</AustLII>
<text>54 Some confirmation of this proposition is available from the authorities. On two occasions, the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeal has said that s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act 1995 (NSW) (which is in the same form as s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act ) reproduces the pre-existing common law. See R v Macraild (unreported, NSW Court of Criminal Appeal, Sully, Dunford and Simpson JJ, 18 December 1997) at 9 and Watt v R [2000] NSWCCA 37 at [8] . The pre-existing common law is found in Tripodi v R [1961] HCA 22 ; (1961) 104 CLR 1 at 7 and Ahern v R [1988] HCA 39 ; (1988) 165 CLR 87 at 100. In both of these cases, the High Court of Australia made it clear that the statement by B could only be admissible against C if there were 'reasonable evidence' establishing the existence of the common purpose, apart from the statement itself. I do not necessarily accept, as the New South Wales Court of Criminal Appeals appears to have done, that the 'reasonable evidence' test is identical to the formulation 'reasonably open to find' preferred by the legislature. For present purposes, however, Macraild and Watt stand as authority for the proposition that, so far as they are consistent with the terms of s 87(1)(c) of the Evidence Act , Tripodi and Ahern are to be taken as providing authority on the proper construction of that provision. It follows that s 87(1)(c) must be applied on the basis that the admissibility of B's statement as against C can only be determined by reference to evidence other than the statement itself.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>