<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>In the Application of United Medical Protection Limited (No 2) [2007] FCA 714 (11 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/714.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Alabama, New Orleans, Texas &amp; Pacific Junction Railway Company, In re [1891] 1 Ch 213</tocase>
<text>A brief description of the two schemes for which approval is now sought is to be found in what I said when ordering the convening of the scheme meetings: see In the Application of United Medical Protection Limited [2007] FCA 631. The duty of the court when acting under s 411(6) of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) has been explained more than once. Nothing is served by going over old ground. It will be sufficient to refer to two short passages from the leading case: In re Alabama, New Orleans, Texas &amp; Pacific Junction Railway Company [1891] 1 Ch 213. First there is the passage from Lindley LJ 238-239. He said: 
 
 What the Court has to do is to see, first of all, that the provisions of that statute have been complied with; and, secondly, that the majority has been acting bona fide. The Court also has to see that the minority is not being overridden by a majority having interests of its own clashing with those of the minority whom they seek to coerce. Further than that, the Court has to look at the scheme and see whether it is one as to which persons acting honestly, and viewing the scheme laid before them in the interests of those whom they represent, take a view which can be reasonably taken by business men. The Court must look at the scheme, and see whether the Act has been complied with, whether the majority are acting bona fide, and whether they are coercing the minority in order to promote interests adverse to those of the class whom they purport to represent; and then see whether the scheme is a reasonable one or whether there is any reasonable objection to it, or such an objection to it as that any reasonable man might say that he could not approve of it.

The other passage is from Fry LJ who at 247 said: 
 
 Then the next inquiry is Under what circumstances is the Court to sanction a resolution which has been passed approving of a compromise or arrangement? I shall not attempt to define what elements may enter into the consideration of the Court beyond this, that I do not doubt for a moment that the Court is bound to ascertain that all the conditions required by the statute have been complied with; it is bound to be satisfied that the proposition was made in good faith; and, further, it must be satisfied that the proposal was at least so far fair and reasonable, as that an intelligent and honest man, who is a member of that class, and acting alone in respect of his interest as such a member, might approve of it. What other circumstances the Court may take into consideration I will not attempt to forecast.

These passages make clear that the court does not simply act on the views of members. On the other hand, if the members are acting with full knowledge and complete information and, also, are acting honestly, they are in a far better position than a judge to decide what is in their best interests.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>