<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rana v University of South Australia [2007] FCA 816 (31 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/816.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Baltic Shipping Company v Dillon [1993] HCA 4 ; (1993) 176 CLR 344</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/4.html</AustLII>
<text>51 Mr Rana's claim for loss of reputation and face, including humiliation and embarrassment, fails because, as I have said, I am satisfied that the conversation between Mr Rana and Ms McIver was a measured and relatively quiet one; that no one else was present during the conversation and certainly not any family or friends of Mr Rana, and that Mr Rana left the Convention Centre quietly and without an escort. He was not escorted out of the Convention Centre by security guards or police officers or, indeed, by anyone. Furthermore, Mr Rana was not emotionally distressed or, at least, not openly so. In fact, he had the presence of mind to calmly tell Ms McIver during his conversation with her that he would be suing the University. Mr Rana referred to the decision in Baltic Shipping Co v Dillon [1993] HCA 4 ; (1993) 176 CLR 344, but there is no evidence of disappointment or emotional distress, even if it was otherwise an appropriate case for such an award.

52 The University admits that it is a corporation within s 52 of the Act . Furthermore, the University did not argue that its conduct on 27 March 2006 was not in trade or commerce.

53 The first question is whether any conduct of the University on 27 March 2006 was misleading or deceptive. As I understood Mr Rana's case, the conduct which he alleged was misleading or deceptive was the insertion of the advertisement in The Australian newspaper and the statements made by Ms Ellmers during her conversation with Mr Rana on the telephone. The contents of the advertisement are clear, and I have accepted Ms Ellmers' account of her conversation with Mr Rana as the correct one.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256</tocase>
<text>47 This case is distinguishable from Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256 and the reward cases such as Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101; see also R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227. In this case, having regard to the form and content of the advertisement, the reference to booking and the nature of the event, it cannot be said that there was an offer capable of acceptance merely by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket. In my opinion, the decision in Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701 is distinguishable on the ground that the nature of a railway timetable is quite different from the advertisement in this case. Furthermore, it is commonly understood that the circumstances in which a train cannot carry a passenger are far more limited than the circumstances in which a member of the public is denied entry to an event such as that involved in this case. In any event, I prefer the reasoning of Crompton J in Denton v Great Northern Railway (supra) who doubted that the defendant was answerable in contract (5 E and B 867-870; ER 704-705).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cowell v Rosehill Racecourse Co Ltd [1937] HCA 17 ; (1937) 56 CLR 605</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/17.html</AustLII>
<text>57 In my opinion, neither the advertisement nor Ms Ellmers' statements during her telephone conversation with Mr Rana contained or gave rise to an implied statement or representation as to the right of a member of the public to attend the hypothetical. In saying that, I am directing my attention to the period prior to the purchase of a ticket. On purchase of a ticket there will be contractual rights and obligations between the parties. It is well established that even when a ticket is purchased, the right of a ticketholder, should there be a breach, is reflected in a claim for damages rather than a right to enter or stay on land ( Cowell v Rosehill Racecourse Co Ltd [1937] HCA 17 ; (1937) 56 CLR 605). In any event, in relation to the period prior to the purchase of a ticket, the advertisement or statements of Ms Ellmers do not contain or give rise to an implied statement or representation as to the right of a member of the public to attend the hypothetical. Clearly, there cannot be any implied statement or representation that there is an unqualified right because there might be any number of reasons why the organiser of an event might justifiably deny a person a ticket or entry to the event, ranging from the cancellation of the event or a full auditorium on the one hand, to disruptive conduct or inappropriate dress by the proposed attendee on the other. No reasonable reader of the advertisement or party to the conversation with Ms Ellmers would understand that, prior to the purchase of a ticket, any member of the public had an unqualified right to attend the hypothetical. To my mind, it is not possible to conclude that there is an implied statement or representation as to a right of a more limited nature, for example, a right to enter subject to a good reason to exclude, because there would simply be no unanimity, or even a majority view, as to the particular circumstances which would justify the exclusion of a member of the public.

58 Even if I am wrong in reaching the conclusions set out above and the University has contravened s 52 of the Act , Mr Rana's claim for damages under s 82 must fail because he has not proved any loss or damage within the provisions of that section. I need do no more than refer to my conclusions as to loss and damage in the context of Mr Rana's claim for breach of contract ([46]-[50]).

59 Mr Rana's claim for damages for an alleged contravention of s 52 of the Act fails.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701</tocase>
<text>47 This case is distinguishable from Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256 and the reward cases such as Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101; see also R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227. In this case, having regard to the form and content of the advertisement, the reference to booking and the nature of the event, it cannot be said that there was an offer capable of acceptance merely by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket. In my opinion, the decision in Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701 is distinguishable on the ground that the nature of a railway timetable is quite different from the advertisement in this case. Furthermore, it is commonly understood that the circumstances in which a train cannot carry a passenger are far more limited than the circumstances in which a member of the public is denied entry to an event such as that involved in this case. In any event, I prefer the reasoning of Crompton J in Denton v Great Northern Railway (supra) who doubted that the defendant was answerable in contract (5 E and B 867-870; ER 704-705).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1927/47.html</AustLII>
<text>47 This case is distinguishable from Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256 and the reward cases such as Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101; see also R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227. In this case, having regard to the form and content of the advertisement, the reference to booking and the nature of the event, it cannot be said that there was an offer capable of acceptance merely by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket. In my opinion, the decision in Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701 is distinguishable on the ground that the nature of a railway timetable is quite different from the advertisement in this case. Furthermore, it is commonly understood that the circumstances in which a train cannot carry a passenger are far more limited than the circumstances in which a member of the public is denied entry to an event such as that involved in this case. In any event, I prefer the reasoning of Crompton J in Denton v Great Northern Railway (supra) who doubted that the defendant was answerable in contract (5 E and B 867-870; ER 704-705).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101</tocase>
<text>47 This case is distinguishable from Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co [1892] EWCA Civ 1 ; [1893] 1 QB 256 and the reward cases such as Williams v Carwardine [1833] EWHC J44 (KB) ; (1833) 5 C &amp; P 566; 172 ER 1101; see also R v Clarke [1927] HCA 47 ; (1927) 40 CLR 227. In this case, having regard to the form and content of the advertisement, the reference to booking and the nature of the event, it cannot be said that there was an offer capable of acceptance merely by going to the Convention Centre and offering to purchase a ticket. In my opinion, the decision in Denton v Great Northern Railway Co (1856) 5 E &amp; B 860; 119 ER 701 is distinguishable on the ground that the nature of a railway timetable is quite different from the advertisement in this case. Furthermore, it is commonly understood that the circumstances in which a train cannot carry a passenger are far more limited than the circumstances in which a member of the public is denied entry to an event such as that involved in this case. In any event, I prefer the reasoning of Crompton J in Denton v Great Northern Railway (supra) who doubted that the defendant was answerable in contract (5 E and B 867-870; ER 704-705).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>