<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Sleep v Repatriation Commission [2007] FCA 859 (6 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/859.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Perrone; Re v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2004] AATA 775</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/AATA/2004/775.html</AustLII>
<text>7 The Tribunal found that the applicant suffered from a number of significant war-caused disabilities that included anxiety and a rare blood disorder that left him susceptible to infection. It found that he avoided public places and public transport and that he found that his anxiety, in particular, was helped by regular trips into the Australian outback, where he felt more relaxed and normal within himself. The Tribunal found that the applicant purchased the motor vehicle and the camper trailer for the specific purpose of having annual trips to the outback. The Tribunal found that the motor vehicle was not specifically designed for use by a disabled person. It was a standard motor vehicle and it had not been modified in any way that related to the applicant's particular disabilities. The Tribunal found that the camper trailer was a standard item owned by many members of the community and it was not specifically designed for use by a disabled person. It found that it was not modified in any way to accommodate the applicant's specific disabilities. The Tribunal referred to the only decision of which it was aware that might have been relevant to the issue before it ( Re Perrone v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2004] AATA 775).

8 The Tribunal held that s 52(1)(k) and (l) of the VE Act refers to specific aids for the disabled and did not refer to standard items that have the additional feature that they give some comfort or relief to a disabled person. The Tribunal said that the submission advanced by the applicant, namely, that an asset not normally seen as being designed for a disabled person can be "reinterpreted" to be designed for a disabled person with a particular disability if that item has the effect of alleviating their disability, went well beyond a beneficial interpretation of the legislation. The Tribunal said that the relevant legislative provisions were straightforward and unambiguous. It said that the motor vehicle and camper trailer were not specifically designed or modified for a disabled person and that they were standard items owned by many members of the community. Both came within the definition of "assets", as contained in the VE Act , and had been properly brought to account as assets of the applicant and his wife.

9 The Tribunal affirmed the decisions under review.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>