<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Golden Chef (NSW) Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 874 (7 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/874.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1995) 183 CLR 168</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/23.html</AustLII>
<text>3 This application was filed on 5 April 2007 pursuant to s 39B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) (the Judiciary Act ). The applicant seeks a declaration that the assessment was not properly made by the respondent. It also seeks orders prohibiting the respondent from enforcing the assessment or the penalty assessment. In essence, the applicant claims that the assessment was made in bad faith and for an improper or ulterior purpose, so that in reality there is no assessment at all of its taxation liability in respect of that financial year: cf Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1995) 183 CLR 168.

4 By motion of 20 April 2007, the respondent seeks to have the application summarily dismissed on the grounds that it is clearly untenable and that it amounts to an abuse of the process of the Court. Alternatively, the respondent seeks that the statement of claim be struck out as not disclosing a reasonable cause of action.

5 On 16 August 2006, the respondent issued to the applicant a statutory demand (the first statutory demand) pursuant to s 459E of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Corporations Act ) in respect of the monies owing under the assessment and the penalty assessment, then totalling $72,809 (the assessed amount plus interest). That prompted the applicant, on 7 September 2006, to apply to the Supreme Court of South Australia to set aside the first statutory demand pursuant to s 459G of the Corporations Act . That matter was heard on 17 November 2006. Judgment was reserved. Late in the day of 16 November 2006, the applicant filed an application in this Court also pursuant to s 39B of the Judiciary Act seeking that the notice of assessment and the penalty assessment be declared invalid and quashed (matter SAD 262 of 2006). In the Supreme Court proceedings, on 24 January 2007 Judge Withers set aside the first statutory demand because the proceedings in this Court demonstrated a genuine dispute in relation to the debt. His Honour said at [43] of his reasons:
 
 The plaintiff filed its summons in the Federal Court challenging the Deputy Commissioner's assessment late on the day before the hearing of this matter. The defendant was not aware of this prior to argument. But for the filing of that summons the plaintiff's application would have been dismissed.

6 In the meantime, on 15 January 2007 the respondent applied by motion in the Federal Court proceedings (matter SAD 262 of 2006) to strike out the application. It contended that, on the statement of claim, the application could not possibly succeed. On 1 February 2007, Finn J dismissed the application with costs. The transcript of the hearing of that day reveals that the matter was dismissed because there was no defence mounted to the motion to have the application struck out.

7 Then round two began.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Haritopoulos Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 394</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/394.html</AustLII>
<text>12 On 30 March 2006, Haritopoulos Pty Ltd also issued proceedings under s 39B of the Judiciary Act in this Court (matter SAD 54 of 2006) against the respondent for orders that certain notices of assessment of income tax against it were invalid as not having been made in good faith and having been made for an improper purpose. In particular, Haritopoulos challenged the validity of an assessment issued on 8 November 2005 in respect of the financial year ended 30 June 2002 by which Haritopoulos was assessed for income tax liability at $2,813,000 (plus certain other amounts to which I do not need to refer), and the validity of an assessment issued on 24 November 2005 imposing a penalty assessment of $2,109,750. On 25 May 2006, the respondent applied to summarily dismiss that application. The motion was heard on 29 August 2006. Judgment was given on 23 March 2007. Justice Besanko found that, on the material before the Court, Haritopoulos had no arguable case that the assessment challenged was made in bad faith and entered summary judgment dismissing the proceeding in its entirety: Haritopoulos Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 394.

13 In each of the proceedings heard by Finn J and Besanko J, the nature of the allegations is very similar to those now asserted in the statement of claim filed on behalf of the applicant in this matter.

14 Counsel for the applicant acknowledged that, unless the applicant is given leave to amend its statement of claim to add what is called a new issue, and to rely on an affidavit of Pantelis Charitopoulos sworn on 29 May 2007 in opposition to the motion, the Court would on the motion make an order dismissing the application because the issues raised on the present statement of claim are in essence the same as those already addressed.

19 Taking facts alleged in the present statement of claim at their highest, the issues which might point to invalidity of the assessment and of the penalty assessment are the same as those which Besanko J addressed in Haritopoulos [2007] FCA 394. They are a failure to provide particulars of the assessment and of the penalty assessment; secondly, the issue of the assessment on 15 September 2005 when, a few weeks earlier, an officer of the respondent had anticipated that it would take six to eight weeks for a default assessment to issue; thirdly, the fact that the penalty assessment was issued so close in time to the assessment; and finally, the failure to consider the package of information provided on 3 November 2005 before making the assessment (although it is clear that there was no undertaking given to consider that material before making the assessment, and in fact it was made plain on 20 October 2005 and in the letter of 8 November 2005 that a default assessment would issue notwithstanding the provision of that further information).

20 I agree with Besanko J, for the reasons his Honour gave, that on those allegations no arguable case of bad faith on the part of the respondent in making the assessment or the penalty assessment could be made out. As so much has been acknowledged by counsel for the applicant, I do not need to repeat those reasons. Furthermore, although it has not been expressly stated in this application, I note that Besanko J also rejected the further contention that arguably there had been a breach of s 166 of the 1936 Act and in any event his Honour found it beyond argument that s 175 meant that any such breach would not affect the validity of the assessment. His Honour also noted (as appears also to be the case here) that the claim based upon a want of procedural fairness had not been pursued before him, and in any event it was unarguable as ss 175 and 177 would operate so as not to affect the validity of the assessment even if there had been a want of procedural fairness to which the applicant was entitled. In the light of those provisions, Besanko J concluded, and I agree, that the applicant was bound to confine its challenge (as distinct from any challenge to the amount of the assessment under Pt IVC of the Taxation Administration Act 1953 (Cth)) to the "Hickman grounds" ( R v Hickman; Ex parte Fox and Clinton [1945] HCA 53 ; (1945) 70 CLR 598 per Dixon J at 615), relevantly that the assessment was not made in good faith.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Hickman; Ex parte Fox and Clinton [1945] HCA 53 ; (1945) 70 CLR 598</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/53.html</AustLII>
<text>20 I agree with Besanko J, for the reasons his Honour gave, that on those allegations no arguable case of bad faith on the part of the respondent in making the assessment or the penalty assessment could be made out. As so much has been acknowledged by counsel for the applicant, I do not need to repeat those reasons. Furthermore, although it has not been expressly stated in this application, I note that Besanko J also rejected the further contention that arguably there had been a breach of s 166 of the 1936 Act and in any event his Honour found it beyond argument that s 175 meant that any such breach would not affect the validity of the assessment. His Honour also noted (as appears also to be the case here) that the claim based upon a want of procedural fairness had not been pursued before him, and in any event it was unarguable as ss 175 and 177 would operate so as not to affect the validity of the assessment even if there had been a want of procedural fairness to which the applicant was entitled. In the light of those provisions, Besanko J concluded, and I agree, that the applicant was bound to confine its challenge (as distinct from any challenge to the amount of the assessment under Pt IVC of the Taxation Administration Act 1953 (Cth)) to the "Hickman grounds" ( R v Hickman; Ex parte Fox and Clinton [1945] HCA 53 ; (1945) 70 CLR 598 per Dixon J at 615), relevantly that the assessment was not made in good faith.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/34.html</AustLII>
<text>34 In those circumstances, assuming the Deed had not by then been entered into, it was not inappropriate for the respondent to endeavour to fix an amount in accordance with s 167 of the Act as the assessable income of Haritopoulos. Its decision to do so when it did, to protect or better secure its legal position, does not impugn the bona fides of the exercise of the power: Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509 at 534. Nor could the timing of the decision, or the reason for the timing of the decision, inform the manner in which the power under s 167 has exercised in the particular circumstances.

35 The position of the applicant is even more remote from the proposed Deed of Company Arrangement. There is nothing in that document to suggest that its position, or the position of the respondent in relation to the applicant, could have been affected in any way by it. The applicant is not mentioned in it. The only basis upon which counsel for the applicant sought to attribute the paragraph of the Reasons for Decision referred to in the proposed amended statement of claim to the issue of the assessment against the applicant was by use of the plural "assessments" in the passage that has been quoted. There is no reason to do so. The plural is readily explained by reference to the fact of the primary assessment under s 167 and then the penalty assessment made against Haritopoulos. In the context of that passage in those Reasons, there is no basis upon which the use of that plural expression could be taken to be referring to the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Mendonca; Ex parte Commissioner of Taxation (1969) 15 FLR 256</tocase>
<text>36 It is also clear, for the reasons already expressed, that the particular paragraph of those Reasons for Decision could not have affected the respondent forming the view in terms of s 167(b) of the 1936 Act of not being satisfied with the return furnished by the applicant for the financial year ended 30 June 2002, or the assessment of the amount on which income tax ought to be levied. It is apparent on the material that the respondent had formed the view that a default assessment should be made in respect of the applicant's taxation liability for the financial years ended 30 June 2002, at least by 20 October 2005. The default assessment crystallised the liability of the applicant to pay income tax and determine its extent: Re Mendonca; Ex parte Commissioner of Taxation (1969) 15 FLR 256 at 259-260. It thus identified for the applicant when its taxation liability was due: Taylor v Commissioner of Taxation (1987) 16 FCR 212 at 217. But there is nothing to suggest the decision about the amount was other than made in good faith.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Taylor v Commissioner of Taxation (1987) 16 FCR 212</tocase>
<text>36 It is also clear, for the reasons already expressed, that the particular paragraph of those Reasons for Decision could not have affected the respondent forming the view in terms of s 167(b) of the 1936 Act of not being satisfied with the return furnished by the applicant for the financial year ended 30 June 2002, or the assessment of the amount on which income tax ought to be levied. It is apparent on the material that the respondent had formed the view that a default assessment should be made in respect of the applicant's taxation liability for the financial years ended 30 June 2002, at least by 20 October 2005. The default assessment crystallised the liability of the applicant to pay income tax and determine its extent: Re Mendonca; Ex parte Commissioner of Taxation (1969) 15 FLR 256 at 259-260. It thus identified for the applicant when its taxation liability was due: Taylor v Commissioner of Taxation (1987) 16 FCR 212 at 217. But there is nothing to suggest the decision about the amount was other than made in good faith.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>39 Under s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) the Court may give summary judgment if it is satisfied that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding. That section appears to relax the test imposed by General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125; see e.g. Garrett v National Australia Bank [2007] FCA 530 at [37] [38].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Garrett v National Australia Bank [2007] FCA 530</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/530.html</AustLII>
<text>39 Under s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) the Court may give summary judgment if it is satisfied that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding. That section appears to relax the test imposed by General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125; see e.g. Garrett v National Australia Bank [2007] FCA 530 at [37] [38].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>