<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Porch v Geelong School Supplies Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 857 (5 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/857.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Morlea Professional Services Pty Ltd v Richard Walter Pty Ltd (in liq) [1999] FCA 1820 ; (1999) 96 FCR 217</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1820.html</AustLII>
<text>A somewhat similar point is made in respect of GSS' claim against the third parties. It is said that there may be claims at the suit of GSS that are different from any claim that could be prosecuted by a trustee whose claims against third parties would ordinarily be confined to allegations of procuring a breach of trust or knowingly being in receipt of trust property. Mr Porch says that GSS makes claims in law other than for breach of trust. Reference was made to Morlea Professional Services Pty Ltd v Richard Walter Pty Ltd (in liq) [1999] FCA 1820 ; (1999) 96 FCR 217.

Although the conditions in s 237(2) have been satisfied, I feel some disquiet about allowing the action by GSS to proceed. This is not because I have formed any view about the merits of its case. I am satisfied that Mr Porch genuinely believes that GSS has claims that ought to proceed. However, I am troubled by whether there is any utility in allowing the action to proceed with GSS as a plaintiff. My concern is that GSS may add nothing to the case. By this I mean that if the allegations against the Deans and their co-defendants are made good, the claim by Landmark will succeed and there is little, if anything, additional that GSS could recover in a separate action. Conversely if the claim by Landmark fails, it is difficult to see how the action by GSS could succeed having regard to the almost complete overlap of the allegations against the defendants.

My concern is heightened by the fact that when at the hearing I identified my concern, counsel for Mr Porch did not explain how the GSS Unit Trust would be better off in a financial sense if the action by GSS goes ahead.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>