<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Roche Therapeutics, Inc v GenRx Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 83 (9 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/83.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Anaesthetic Supplies Pty Ltd v Rescare Ltd (1994) 50 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>86 Whether s 117 can apply to a process or method claim, where no product results from the use of the method or process, may be an open question. GenRx says that the Patentees' rights are restricted by paragraph (b) in the definition of " exploit " referred to above, namely, to use the method or process or do any acts mentioned in paragraph (a) in respect of a product resulting from such use (see Anaesthetic Supplies Pty Ltd v Rescare Ltd (1994) 50 FCR 1 at 24).

87 In any event, GenRx says, it cannot be said that the GenRx products are capable of only one reasonable use. Carvedilol is indicated for the treatment of hypertension and treatment of patients with symptomatic mild to severe congestive heart failure. That is the claim made by GenRx in the product information document published in respect of the GenRx products.

88 Further, carvedilol is a useful and beneficial medication for treating the symptoms of congestive heart failure itself. One of the major advantages of carvedilol is that a decrease in heart rate may be achieved, which immediately provides a significant symptomatic benefit to the patient. The information published by the Patentees in respect of DILATREND indicates that administration of carvedilol will cause a significant reduction in systematic blood pressure and heart rate and that it has been shown to reduce cardiovascular hospitalisation, improve patient well being and slow the progression of congestive heart failure. GenRx says, therefore, that they are reasonable uses for carvedilol that are not decreasing mortality.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gillette Safety Razor Company v Anglo-American Trading Co Ltd (1913) 30 RPC 465</tocase>
<text>77 First, GenRx relies upon what it describes as its Gillette defence (see Gillette Safety Razor Company v Anglo-American Trading Co Ltd (1913) 30 RPC 465). That is to say, the dosage regimen for the GenRx products is the regimen disclosed in the Kelly publication and the Metra publication. GenRx says that, if the supply of its products would infringe the Patent, the Patent must be invalid as lacking novelty because that regimen was anticipated in those publications. On the other hand, if the publications do not anticipate the Patent, GenRx is not infringing because it is doing no more than was disclosed in the earlier publications.

78 However, the argument fails to take account of the matter already referred to above concerning the question of whether the publications do, in truth, anticipate the claimed invention of the Patent. That is to say, the element of ' decreasing mortality ' is not present in the publications but it is at least reasonably arguable that it would be an element in the threatened actions of GenRx. I am not persuaded that the so-called Gillette defence is a clear answer to the Patentees' allegations of infringement such that there is not a serious question to be tried.

79 The Patentees contend that the proposed exploitation by GenRx of its carvedilol products is for decreasing mortality in patients suffering from congestive heart failure and that, accordingly, there will be an infringement of Claims of the Patent. They say that listing of the GenRx products under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme for the treatment of mild to severe congestive heart failure was obtained on the basis that the effect of carvedilol in the products on decreasing mortality arising from congestive heart failure was shown to be cost justified having regard to such a clinical outcome. The Patentees contend, therefore, that, since GenRx obtained listing under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme as a bio equivalent of the Patentees' products, they have done so on the basis that the cost-justification for the listing of GenRx's products under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme is a decrease in mortality for patients suffering from congestive heart failure. The Patentees contend that, having regard to the basis upon which GenRx has obtained listing under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme, the GenRx products are medicaments for decreasing mortality resulting from congestive heart failure in humans. Claims 1 to 13 are for the use of carvedilol for the manufacture of such medicaments.

80 Under the Patents Act , it is an exploitation of an invention as claimed to import, sell or otherwise dispose of a product resulting from the method or process for manufacture that is the subject of the claim. Claim 14 is directed to a method of treatment using carvedilol to decrease mortality resulting from congestive heart failure. The dosages for which registration has been obtained for the GenRx products and the listing under the Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme that has been obtained in relation to those products are clearly in relation to treating human patients suffering from congestive heart failure. The Patentees say that such treatment is clearly ' with the objective of decreasing mortality resulting from such congestive heart failure '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1218.html</AustLII>
<text>92 In proceedings in the Court in 2005, the Patentees alleged infringement of the Patent by Hexal Australia Pty Limited and Alphapharm Pty Limited, other threatened suppliers of carvedilol products. Stone J examined grounds of invalidity raised in those proceedings and concluded that there was a serious question to be tried as to whether the Patent is valid and as to whether there was infringement by those parties (see Hexal Australia Pty Limited v Roche Therapeutics Inc [2005] FCA 1218). However, Stone J concluded that there was no likelihood of irreparable injury that could not be adequately compensated by an order form damages or an account and refused interlocutory relief on the basis of the balance of convenience. Those proceedings have now been settled.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re BA's Application (1915) 32 RPC 348</tocase>
<text>70 GenRx says that Claims 8 and 21 do no more than describe a mere new use for an old thing. Once a substance is known, its methods of production ascertained, its characteristics and its constituents well defined, the use of that substance for a purpose that was hitherto unknown cannot be patented ( Re BA's Application (1915) 32 RPC 348 at 349).

71 GenRx also contends that none of the Claims can amount to any more than a direction to doctors and pharmacists on how to treat the patients with carvedilol. GenRx says that the only new component of the Claims is the reference to the fact that the treatment is ' for decreasing mortality ' and says that the fact that treatment with carvedilol may decrease mortality is a mere discovery, since it is an inherent feature of carvedilol. GenRx says that the only act apparently done in relation to the invention was to provide some funding for trials that comprised long-term treatment with known compounds in known dosages for a known condition. GenRx contends that, at most, what is disclosed is mere confirmation of the existing properties of carvedilol in known dosages.

72 There is cogency in GenRx's arguments. However, they raise questions of law that it may be inappropriate to resolve in an interlocutory proceeding such as the present.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rescare Limited v Anaesthetic Supplies Pty Limited (1992) 25 IPR 119</tocase>
<text>73 Under s 18(1)(c) of the Patents Act , a claimed invention will not be a patentable invention unless it is useful. A claim for an invention will not be useful if the invention as claimed, does not meet one or more of the stated objectives of the invention. There will be inutility of a claim if the invention of that claim fails to meet the result promised for it by the Patent ( Rescare Limited v Anaesthetic Supplies Pty Ltd (1992) 25 IPR 119 at 143).

74 GenRx again draws attention to the terms of the Claims that do not disclose a dosage regimen. GenRx says that there is no evidence that carvedilol has any beneficial effect on mortality or otherwise unless it is administered according to the specified regimen over a sufficient period of time. However, it is for GenRx to establish lack of utility. It is not incumbent upon the Patentees to establish that the claimed invention works. GenRx says that the evidence indicates that only administration according to a regimen such as is described in Claims 8 and 21 will have any effect. However, while some claims may be challenged on that basis, Claims 8 and 21 would not be subject to that challenge and would be sufficient to support the allegation of infringement.

75 In relation to Claims 8 and 21, GenRx points out that there is a reference to the final administration as ' a maintenance dose ', the Claims do not specify in terms that the maintenance dose must be continued for a period in the order of 100 days. It points to evidence that such continued dosage is required for effectiveness. However, it is tolerably clear that the reference to maintenance dose means that that dosage is maintained indefinitely. Indefinite maintenance of the dose is shown to have a beneficial effect on mortality.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>