<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lina Obieta v New South Wales Department of Educationand Training and Ors [2007] FCA 86 (7 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/86.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Aboriginal Legal Rights Movement Inc v South Australia and Another (No1) (1995) 64 SASR 551</tocase>
<text>259 Three important considerations arise from the above. Firstly, the burden of proof lies upon Ms Obieta to establish discrimination, harassment or victimisation whether it arises pursuant to the RDA or the SDA. Secondly, with respect to claims of unlawful discrimination, harassment or victimisation under the RDA, it is essential that the discrimination, harassment or victimisation be proved, on the balance of probabilities, on the ground of Ms Obieta's race (see Victoria v Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc and Another [1999] FCA 1287 ; (1999) 91 FCR 47). Similarly, with regard to a claim for sexual discrimination, harassment or victimisation under the SDA, discrimination, harassment or victimisation based upon Ms Obieta's sex must be established on the balance of probabilities: see Aboriginal Legal Rights Movement Inc v South Australia and Another (No1) (1995) 64 SASR 551 at 553.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Baird and Others v Queensland (No 1) (2005) 224 ALR 541</tocase>
<text>210 The requirement to identify that the particular 'distinction', 'exclusion', 'restriction' or 'preference' was ' based on' Ms Obieta's race has been the subject of judicial determination in Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another (1998) 91 FCR 8. At [33] the Court considered that the words 'based on' required a test of 'sufficient connection' with race rather than a 'causal nexus'. Weinberg J distinguished the expression 'based on' from other constructions used elsewhere in Federal anti-discrimination legislation (such as 'by reason of' or 'on the ground of'). The words 'based on' encompass a broader meaning of 'by reference to' and are not limited to 'by reason of' (at [30]). What is required is a close relationship, between the designated characteristic and the impugned conduct, which is not necessarily causal (at [33]): see also Baird and Others v Queensland (No 1) (2005) 224 ALR 541 and Commonwealth v McEvoy and Another [1999] FCA 105 ; (1999) 94 FCR 341 for an analysis of the meaning of 'based on'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bropho v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [2004] FCAFC 16 ; (2004) 135 FCR 105</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/16.html</AustLII>
<text>222 In Bropho v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [2004] FCAFC 16 ; (2004) 135 FCR 105, French J observed at, [69] that the words ' offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate ' are to be considered according to ' their ordinary meaning, in their context, acknowledging their somewhat elastic content and having regard to the objectives of the legislation...' . These objectives, it was noted, are to be gleaned not only from the words of the legislation but also from extraneous material such as, inter alia, the Second Reading Speech of the Racial Hatred Bill 1994 (Cth) ('Second Reading Speech'). The Second Reading Speech provides that the Act was intended to ' close a gap in the legal protection available to the victims of extreme racist behaviour ': see Bropho 135 FCR at [70]. In Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352 at 356-357 Kiefel J said that the conduct which is encompassed by s 18C of the RDA is that which has, ' profound and serious effects not to be likened to mere slights '.

223 Section 18C of the RDA requires the satisfaction of an objective test of the likelihood that the act complained of will have the prohibited effect: see Hagan v Trustees of the Toowoomba Sports Ground Trust [2000] FCA 1615 at [15] . The objective nature of the test was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR where French J at [66] citing the Second Reading Speech said: 
 
 'Community standards of behaviour rather than the subjective views of the complainant are taken into account' (Australia, House of Representatives Debates (1994), p334).

225 The question of causation that arises in the application of s 18C(1)(a) has been considered in numerous cases. In Purvis v New South Wales (Department of Education and Training) and Another [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 202 ALR 133 at 138 the High Court explained per Gleeson CJ, at 171-2 per McHugh and Kirby JJ, at 187 per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, that the accepted test for causation in the context of anti-discrimination legislation focuses on the 'genuine basis' or 'the true basis' or 'real reason' for the act of the alleged discriminator. The question of causation was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR at [71] wherein French J referred to the description by Kiefel J in Creek v Cairns Post 112 FCR at [28] of the key causation issue as 'whether anything suggests race as a factor' in the act in question. Kiefel J at [23] adopted the approach to the construction of statutory provisions similar to s 9 of the RDA taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR at 401.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth v McEvoy and Another [1999] FCA 105 ; (1999) 94 FCR 341</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/105.html</AustLII>
<text>210 The requirement to identify that the particular 'distinction', 'exclusion', 'restriction' or 'preference' was ' based on' Ms Obieta's race has been the subject of judicial determination in Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another (1998) 91 FCR 8. At [33] the Court considered that the words 'based on' required a test of 'sufficient connection' with race rather than a 'causal nexus'. Weinberg J distinguished the expression 'based on' from other constructions used elsewhere in Federal anti-discrimination legislation (such as 'by reason of' or 'on the ground of'). The words 'based on' encompass a broader meaning of 'by reference to' and are not limited to 'by reason of' (at [30]). What is required is a close relationship, between the designated characteristic and the impugned conduct, which is not necessarily causal (at [33]): see also Baird and Others v Queensland (No 1) (2005) 224 ALR 541 and Commonwealth v McEvoy and Another [1999] FCA 105 ; (1999) 94 FCR 341 for an analysis of the meaning of 'based on'.

213 Under s 9 it is also necessary to establish the relevant human right which has been impaired because of race. The expression 'human right' for the purpose of the RDA incorporates the rights set out in the International Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Racial Discrimination (CERD) scheduled to the RDA. The preamble to the RDA recites the entry into force of the CERD and the desirability of parliament making provision for giving effect to the CERD. Von Doussa J in Commonwealth v McEvoy and Another 94 FCR noted at [31] that:
 
 'It is apparent that in adopting the phrase "race, colour, descent or national or ethnic origin" in s 9...Parliament has transported into the domestic law of Australia, through the RDA, text from Article 1.1 of the International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cooke v Plauen Holdings [2001] FMCA 91</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2001/91.html</AustLII>
<text>238 Section 28A(2) defines 'conduct of a sexual nature' as including 'making a statement of a sexual nature to a person, or in the presence of a person, whether the statement is made orally or in writing' . Where it is alleged that conduct is unlawful under the SDA, the context of the conduct must be considered. In Cooke v Plauen Holdings [2001] FMCA 91 , Driver FM observed that whether an act or statement can constitute sexual harassment will depend upon the nature or the quality of the act or statement.

239 For Ms Obieta to establish her claims under section 28F of the SDA she is required to establish that the relevant staff member (s 28F(1)) or adult student (s 28F(2)) of TAFE sexually harassed her. That is, pursuant to s 28A of the SDA, Ms Obieta would have to establish that the relevant respondent made an unwelcome sexual advance, or an unwelcome request for sexual favours (s 28A(1)(a)) or engaged in other unwelcome conduct of a sexual nature (s 28A(1)(b)) in circumstances in which a reasonable person having regard to all the circumstances, would have anticipated that Ms Obieta would be offended, humiliated or intimidated.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Cooper v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [1999] FCA 180 ; (1999) 93 FCR 481</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/180.html</AustLII>
<text>241 Under s 105 of the SDA a person who causes, instructs, aids or permits another person to do an act that is unlawful under Division 1 or 2 of Part II shall, for the purposes of the SDA, be taken also to have done the act. The meaning of the word 'permit' was discussed in Cooper v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [1999] FCA 180 ; (1999) 93 FCR 481 at 494-495, [41] - [45] . Moore J in Elliott v Nanda and Another [2001] FCA 418 ; (2001) 111 FCR 240 at 293, [163] explained the operation of s 105 as pertaining to the situation where a person who is in a position to prevent allegedly unlawful conduct fails to do so. His Honour said: 
 
 'Section 105 provides a means of bringing about lawful conduct by rendering liable a person who could prevent unlawful conduct from occurring or continuing or who assists, directly or indirectly, in its performance. A person can prevent unlawful conduct by not creating a situation where it will or may take place or altering a situation so it will not continue.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/1007.html</AustLII>
<text>222 In Bropho v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [2004] FCAFC 16 ; (2004) 135 FCR 105, French J observed at, [69] that the words ' offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate ' are to be considered according to ' their ordinary meaning, in their context, acknowledging their somewhat elastic content and having regard to the objectives of the legislation...' . These objectives, it was noted, are to be gleaned not only from the words of the legislation but also from extraneous material such as, inter alia, the Second Reading Speech of the Racial Hatred Bill 1994 (Cth) ('Second Reading Speech'). The Second Reading Speech provides that the Act was intended to ' close a gap in the legal protection available to the victims of extreme racist behaviour ': see Bropho 135 FCR at [70]. In Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 ; (2001) 112 FCR 352 at 356-357 Kiefel J said that the conduct which is encompassed by s 18C of the RDA is that which has, ' profound and serious effects not to be likened to mere slights '.

225 The question of causation that arises in the application of s 18C(1)(a) has been considered in numerous cases. In Purvis v New South Wales (Department of Education and Training) and Another [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 202 ALR 133 at 138 the High Court explained per Gleeson CJ, at 171-2 per McHugh and Kirby JJ, at 187 per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, that the accepted test for causation in the context of anti-discrimination legislation focuses on the 'genuine basis' or 'the true basis' or 'real reason' for the act of the alleged discriminator. The question of causation was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR at [71] wherein French J referred to the description by Kiefel J in Creek v Cairns Post 112 FCR at [28] of the key causation issue as 'whether anything suggests race as a factor' in the act in question. Kiefel J at [23] adopted the approach to the construction of statutory provisions similar to s 9 of the RDA taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR at 401.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Damiano and Another v Wilkinson and Another [2004] FMCA 891</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2004/891.html</AustLII>
<text>236 In Sivananthan v Commissioner of Police, New South Wales Police Service [2001] NSWADT 44 , a case which considered, inter alia, the meaning of 'detriment' in comparable state legislation, the Administrative Decisions Tribunal ('ADT') found that the word 'detriment' should be given its common meaning of 'loss, damage or injury' (at [40]). It was also said in that case that '[t]he detriment suffered... must be real and not trivial' and 'whether something constitutes a detriment must be determined objectively and not subjectively' (at [41]). In Damiano and Another v Wilkinson and Another [2004] FMCA 891 at [23] Baumann FM considered the meaning of detriment gleaned from three authorities as follows: 
 
 '... [T]he definition of detriment [is] placing a complainant "under a disadvantage of a matter of substance" (Bogie v University of Western Sydney (1990) EOC 92-313 ) or "suffers a material difference in treatment" (Bailey v Australian National University (1995) EOC 92- 744 ) which is "real and not trivial" (Sivanathan [sic] v Commissioner of Police (NSW) (2001) NSWADT 44 ) '

240 Pursuant to s 94(1) of the SDA it is an offence for a person to commit an act of victimisation against another person. Pursuant to s 94(2) Ms Obieta is required to establish that the relevant respondent subjected, or threatened to subject her to any detriment on the grounds that Ms Obieta had or was believed to have made or proposed to make a complaint under the SDA or under the HREOC Act (s 94(2)(a)); or that Ms Obieta had brought or proposed to bring proceedings under the SDA or the HREOC Act against any person (s 94(2)(b)); or that Ms Obieta had furnished or produced or proposed to furnish or produce any information or documents to anybody exercising functions under the SDA or the HREOC Act (s 94(2)(c)); or that Ms Obieta had attended or proposed to attend a conference held under the SDA or the HREOC Act (s 94(2)(d)); or that Ms Obieta appeared or proposed to appear as a witness in proceedings under the SDA or the HREOC Act (s 94(2)(e)); or that Ms Obeita has reasonably asserted or proposed to assert any rights under the SDA or the HREOC Act (s 94(2)(f)); or that Ms Obieta had made an allegation that a person had done an act that is unlawful under Part II of the SDA (s 94(2)(g)). In Damiano [2004] FMCA 891 Baumann FM at [22] said, referring to Bailey v ANU (1995) EOC 92-744, that for victimisation to be established under comparable legislation one of the grounds under a section comparable to s 94(2) of the SDA must be a 'substantial and operative' factor for the alleged action.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Elliott v Nanda and Another [2001] FCA 418 ; (2001) 111 FCR 240</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2001/418.html</AustLII>
<text>241 Under s 105 of the SDA a person who causes, instructs, aids or permits another person to do an act that is unlawful under Division 1 or 2 of Part II shall, for the purposes of the SDA, be taken also to have done the act. The meaning of the word 'permit' was discussed in Cooper v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another [1999] FCA 180 ; (1999) 93 FCR 481 at 494-495, [41] - [45] . Moore J in Elliott v Nanda and Another [2001] FCA 418 ; (2001) 111 FCR 240 at 293, [163] explained the operation of s 105 as pertaining to the situation where a person who is in a position to prevent allegedly unlawful conduct fails to do so. His Honour said: 
 
 'Section 105 provides a means of bringing about lawful conduct by rendering liable a person who could prevent unlawful conduct from occurring or continuing or who assists, directly or indirectly, in its performance. A person can prevent unlawful conduct by not creating a situation where it will or may take place or altering a situation so it will not continue.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/11.html</AustLII>
<text>214 In addition it was noted in Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70 that for the purposes of s 9 of the RDA 'human rights' may include those included in other international instruments to which Australia is a party. One such other instrument is the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR) (as provided in Schedule 2 to the HREOC Act) which is relied upon by Ms Obieta.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hagan v Trustees of the Toowoomba Sports Ground Trust [2000] FCA 1615</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/1615.html</AustLII>
<text>223 Section 18C of the RDA requires the satisfaction of an objective test of the likelihood that the act complained of will have the prohibited effect: see Hagan v Trustees of the Toowoomba Sports Ground Trust [2000] FCA 1615 at [15] . The objective nature of the test was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR where French J at [66] citing the Second Reading Speech said: 
 
 'Community standards of behaviour rather than the subjective views of the complainant are taken into account' (Australia, House of Representatives Debates (1994), p334).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>In Marriage of Lindsey (1995) 128 FLR 46</tocase>
<text>230 Despite the fact that one of the options of the Court in s 27(2) of the RDA is the imposition of a penal sentence, it has been held that the civil standard should nevertheless apply where the substance of the proceedings are civil (see In Marriage of Lindsey (1995) 128 FLR 46). The majority of the High Court in Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 has emphasised the fact that the ordinary standard of proof in civil litigation is proof on the balance of probabilities even when the matter to be proved involves criminal conduct or fraud (see Rejfek and Another v McElroy and Another [1965] HCA 46 ; (1965) 112 CLR 517 at 519-21). It was also held in that case that the strength of the evidence necessary to establish a fact or facts on the balance of probabilities may vary according to the nature of what it is sought to prove.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kelly-Country v Beers and Another [2004] FMCA 336 ; (2004) 207 ALR 421</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2004/336.html</AustLII>
<text>224 A similar observation of the requirement of objectivity was made by Brown FM in Kelly-Country v Beers and Another [2004] FMCA 336 ; (2004) 207 ALR 421 at [84] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lina Obieta v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2006] FCA 1684</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2006/1684.html</AustLII>
<text>14 Ms Obieta instituted these proceedings nominating the Commission as the first respondent. However, Ms Obieta later instituted separate proceedings against the Commission (see Lina Obieta v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2006] FCA 1684) and the Court ordered that the Commission be removed as first respondent to these proceedings.

15 The fifth and sixth respondents were fellow students of Ms Obieta. Ms Obieta has alleged that they engaged in conduct which was unlawful pursuant to the SDA, RDA and the HREOC Act.

16 A section entitled 'Specific Issues' considered hereunder contains details of the 48 issues raised by Ms Obieta of alleged discrimination, harassment and victimisation under the RDA and SDA. It follows the same order as contained in the Statement of the Precise Matters raised against each respondent contained in Ms Obieta's submissions filed on 16 June 2006. Such document was prepared in response to the Court's direction that Ms Obieta provide a list of precise matters upon which she relied and the sections of the relevant legislation which she claimed were breached.

77 Ms Obieta claims that Mr Norman gave less favourable treatment to her and created hostility in the class. He referred to Ms Roxanna Ramos as ' Roxan' in his greeting to her. He called upon Ms Cecilia Cordova to recite a passage and referred to her as ' Lina' . Ms Obieta claims that when Mr Norman apologised for calling Ms Cordova 'Lina', this created hostility from other students in the class. She claims that Mr Norman's less favourable treatment of her had the effect of violating or impairing her rights on an equal footing with other students and made her feel ridiculed. As such she claims that she was subjected to harassment or bullying which is at law, ' being subject to any other detriment '. Such conduct is alleged to be a breach of ss 9, 17 and 27 of the RDA and s 94 of the SDA.

78 Mr Norman says that he inadvertently referred to Ms Cordova as Lina, realised his mistake and apologised to Ms Cordova. He states that it was not an attempt by him to incite other students to feel contempt for Ms Obieta.

79 Ms Obieta states that during the class discussion on 8 September 2004, Mr Norman came closer to her, looked at her and said in a nasty way:
 
 'Oh, I don't want to be representing a client who assaulted somebody.'

97 Ms Obieta claims that when called upon to recite something, Mr Norman referred to Ms Davis as ' Lina' . When Ms Obieta's name was called out, Ms Obieta alleges that Ms Davis made the noise of a duck or chicken. She claims that Ms Davis was mimicking manner of speech or her Asian accent in class and that Ms Davis made racist sounds in her presence. She claims that such conduct was harassment and constitutes ' being subject to any other detriment '. Ms Obieta claims that this constitutes a breach of ss 9, 17, 18C and 27 of the RDA.

98 Ms Davis states that she has no recollection of such event and does not believe that she has ever done so. She states that she does not mimic ducks or chickens.

99 Ms Fogarty testifies that she does not recall Ms Davis ever making any duck or chicken noises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another (1998) 91 FCR 8</tocase>
<text>210 The requirement to identify that the particular 'distinction', 'exclusion', 'restriction' or 'preference' was ' based on' Ms Obieta's race has been the subject of judicial determination in Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission and Another (1998) 91 FCR 8. At [33] the Court considered that the words 'based on' required a test of 'sufficient connection' with race rather than a 'causal nexus'. Weinberg J distinguished the expression 'based on' from other constructions used elsewhere in Federal anti-discrimination legislation (such as 'by reason of' or 'on the ground of'). The words 'based on' encompass a broader meaning of 'by reference to' and are not limited to 'by reason of' (at [30]). What is required is a close relationship, between the designated characteristic and the impugned conduct, which is not necessarily causal (at [33]): see also Baird and Others v Queensland (No 1) (2005) 224 ALR 541 and Commonwealth v McEvoy and Another [1999] FCA 105 ; (1999) 94 FCR 341 for an analysis of the meaning of 'based on'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/66.html</AustLII>
<text>230 Despite the fact that one of the options of the Court in s 27(2) of the RDA is the imposition of a penal sentence, it has been held that the civil standard should nevertheless apply where the substance of the proceedings are civil (see In Marriage of Lindsey (1995) 128 FLR 46). The majority of the High Court in Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 has emphasised the fact that the ordinary standard of proof in civil litigation is proof on the balance of probabilities even when the matter to be proved involves criminal conduct or fraud (see Rejfek and Another v McElroy and Another [1965] HCA 46 ; (1965) 112 CLR 517 at 519-21). It was also held in that case that the strength of the evidence necessary to establish a fact or facts on the balance of probabilities may vary according to the nature of what it is sought to prove.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Purvis v New South Wales (Department of Education and Training) and Another [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 202 ALR 133</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/62.html</AustLII>
<text>225 The question of causation that arises in the application of s 18C(1)(a) has been considered in numerous cases. In Purvis v New South Wales (Department of Education and Training) and Another [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 202 ALR 133 at 138 the High Court explained per Gleeson CJ, at 171-2 per McHugh and Kirby JJ, at 187 per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, that the accepted test for causation in the context of anti-discrimination legislation focuses on the 'genuine basis' or 'the true basis' or 'real reason' for the act of the alleged discriminator. The question of causation was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR at [71] wherein French J referred to the description by Kiefel J in Creek v Cairns Post 112 FCR at [28] of the key causation issue as 'whether anything suggests race as a factor' in the act in question. Kiefel J at [23] adopted the approach to the construction of statutory provisions similar to s 9 of the RDA taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR at 401.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rejfek and Another v McElroy and Another [1965] HCA 46 ; (1965) 112 CLR 517</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1965/46.html</AustLII>
<text>230 Despite the fact that one of the options of the Court in s 27(2) of the RDA is the imposition of a penal sentence, it has been held that the civil standard should nevertheless apply where the substance of the proceedings are civil (see In Marriage of Lindsey (1995) 128 FLR 46). The majority of the High Court in Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 has emphasised the fact that the ordinary standard of proof in civil litigation is proof on the balance of probabilities even when the matter to be proved involves criminal conduct or fraud (see Rejfek and Another v McElroy and Another [1965] HCA 46 ; (1965) 112 CLR 517 at 519-21). It was also held in that case that the strength of the evidence necessary to establish a fact or facts on the balance of probabilities may vary according to the nature of what it is sought to prove.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Shaikh v Campbell &amp; Nivona Pty Ltd [1998] HREOCA 13</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HREOCA/1998/13.html</AustLII>
<text>231 Under s 17(a) of the RDA it is unlawful for a person to incite the doing of acts made unlawful by a provision of Part II of the RDA. Further s 17(b) makes it unlawful for a person to assist or promote the doing of such an act (whether by financial assistance or otherwise). In Shaikh v Campbell &amp; Nivona Pty Ltd [1998] HREOCA 13 (24 April 1998), in referring to s 17 of the RDA, Commissioner Innes AM stated at 8: 
 
 'In order to make out a case under this section the complainant has to show incitement, assistance or promotion of someone carrying out unlawful acts. Incitement denotes encouragement in an active way.'

232 To establish her claims pursuant to this section, Ms Obieta must show that the particular respondents were actively inciting or encouraging behaviour that is made unlawful by a provision of Part II of the RDA (s 17(a)) or that the respondents assisted or promoted the doing of such acts (s 17(b)).

233 Section 5 of the SDA provides a definition of sex discrimination under the SDA and does not of itself give rise to a cause of action. It essentially provides the conditions that are required before a person called the 'discriminator' (s 5(1)) can be found to have discriminated against another person called the 'aggrieved person' (s 5(1)) on the grounds of the sex of the aggrieved person. Under s 5(1) if by reason of the sex of the aggrieved person, or a characteristic that generally pertains to or is generally imputed to a person of that sex, the discriminator treats the aggrieved person less favourably than the discriminator treats or would treat a person of the opposite sex, then the discriminator has discriminated against the aggrieved person. Ms Obieta must establish that the respondent in question treated her less favourably than the respondent would treat a person of the opposite sex in circumstances that are the same or not materially different.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sharma v Legal Aid (Qld) [2002] FCAFC 196 ; (2002) 115 IR 91</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/196.html</AustLII>
<text>212 The standard of proof that is required to establish unlawful conduct under s 9 of the RDA was considered in Sharma v Legal Aid (Qld) [2002] FCAFC 196 ; (2002) 115 IR 91. The Full Court at [40] said: 
 
 ' It is for the applicant who complains of racial discrimination to make out his or her case on the balance of probabilities. It may be accepted that it is unusual to find direct evidence of racial discrimination, and the outcome of a case will usually depend on what inferences it is proper to draw from the primary facts found: Glasgow City Council v Zafar [1997] UKHL 54 ; [1998] 2 All ER 953, 958. There may be cases in which the motivation may be subconscious. There may be cases in which the proper inference to be drawn from the evidence is that, whether or not the employer realised it at the time or not, race was the reason it acted as it did: Nagarajan v London Regional Transport [1999] UKHL 36 ; [1999] 3 WLR 425, 433. It was common ground at first instance that the standard of proof for breaches of the RDA is the higher standard referred to in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336, 361-362. Racial discrimination is a serious matter, which is not lightly to be inferred: Department of Health v Arumugam [1988] VR 319, 331. No contrary argument was put on the hearing of the appeal, apart from the comment that there is no binding authority on this Court that Briginshaw should be applied in cases of this nature. 
 In a case depending on circumstantial evidence, it is well established that the trier of fact must consider "the weight which is to be given to the united force of all the circumstances put together". One should not put a piece of circumstantial evidence out of consideration merely because an inference does not arise from it alone: Chamberlain v The Queen [No 2] [1984] HCA 7 ; (1983-1984) 153 CLR 521 at 535. It is the cumulative effect of the circumstances which is important provided, of course, that the circumstances relied upon are established as facts.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sivananthan v Commissioner of Police, New South Wales Police Service [2001] NSWADT 44</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWADT/2001/44.html</AustLII>
<text>236 In Sivananthan v Commissioner of Police, New South Wales Police Service [2001] NSWADT 44 , a case which considered, inter alia, the meaning of 'detriment' in comparable state legislation, the Administrative Decisions Tribunal ('ADT') found that the word 'detriment' should be given its common meaning of 'loss, damage or injury' (at [40]). It was also said in that case that '[t]he detriment suffered... must be real and not trivial' and 'whether something constitutes a detriment must be determined objectively and not subjectively' (at [41]). In Damiano and Another v Wilkinson and Another [2004] FMCA 891 at [23] Baumann FM considered the meaning of detriment gleaned from three authorities as follows: 
 
 '... [T]he definition of detriment [is] placing a complainant "under a disadvantage of a matter of substance" (Bogie v University of Western Sydney (1990) EOC 92-313 ) or "suffers a material difference in treatment" (Bailey v Australian National University (1995) EOC 92- 744 ) which is "real and not trivial" (Sivanathan [sic] v Commissioner of Police (NSW) (2001) NSWADT 44 ) '</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tasmanian Wilderness Society Inc and Others v Fraser and Others [1982] HCA 37 ; (1982) 153 CLR 270</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/37.html</AustLII>
<text>17 Some of the alleged breaches refer to definition or explanatory sections, which cannot give rise to a cause of action. Accordingly the Court will make no reference to the alleged breaches of such sections. Further, no cause of action can arise from an alleged breach of an International Convention as claimed by Ms Obieta (see Tasmanian Wilderness Society Inc and Others v Fraser and Others [1982] HCA 37 ; (1982) 153 CLR 270 at 274 per Mason J). Accordingly the Court will similarly not refer to articles of International Conventions which Ms Obieta claims have been breached.

18 Mr Norman was Ms Obieta's teacher of the modules Interaction in a Legal Office , Interaction with Other Parties and Advocacy Skills , each of which were part of the TAFE course for the Diploma of Business-Legal Studies.

19 On Wednesday 5 May 2004 during a class exercise relating to discrimination, Mr Norman proposed that the class be divided into different groups and that each group would be required to report, either ' for' a particular argument or ' against ' it. He made a comment to the effect ' my two blue-eyed good friends over here would report that there is discrimination and the other group would report there is no discrimination '. Ms Obieta says that Mr Norman indicated that one who would be advocating that there was no discrimination came from the Philippines, thereby indicating Ms Obieta, and the other had a history of China, thereby indicating Ms Chong, another student in the class. Ms Obieta claims that by reason of Mr Norman saying such words loudly and repeatedly on two occasions, she felt discriminated against. She alleges that such conduct breached ss 9 and 18C of the RDA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/137.html</AustLII>
<text>227 In Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515 at [31] Carr J agreed with the adoption by Kiefel J of the approach taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR. At 31 Carr J said: 
 
 'The authorities on the issue of causation in the context of the discrimination legislation were reviewed by Kiefel J in Cairns Post at [19]-[27]. It seems clear from what her Honour said at [22] that she regarded the assessment of a reason as being an objective one, but not one which excluded any evidence of the relevant person's intention or motive. Regard was to be had to all the circumstances. I respectfully agree with that approach.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Victoria v Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc and Another [1999] FCA 1287 ; (1999) 91 FCR 47</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1287.html</AustLII>
<text>259 Three important considerations arise from the above. Firstly, the burden of proof lies upon Ms Obieta to establish discrimination, harassment or victimisation whether it arises pursuant to the RDA or the SDA. Secondly, with respect to claims of unlawful discrimination, harassment or victimisation under the RDA, it is essential that the discrimination, harassment or victimisation be proved, on the balance of probabilities, on the ground of Ms Obieta's race (see Victoria v Macedonian Teachers' Association of Victoria Inc and Another [1999] FCA 1287 ; (1999) 91 FCR 47). Similarly, with regard to a claim for sexual discrimination, harassment or victimisation under the SDA, discrimination, harassment or victimisation based upon Ms Obieta's sex must be established on the balance of probabilities: see Aboriginal Legal Rights Movement Inc v South Australia and Another (No1) (1995) 64 SASR 551 at 553.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Waters and Others v Public Transport Corporation [1991] HCA 49 ; (1991) 173 CLR 349</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/49.html</AustLII>
<text>215 To succeed in establishing a claim under s 9(1A) of the RDA that there was an act involving a distinction based on, or done by reason of, her race, colour, decent or national or ethnic origin, Ms Obieta must establish that a term, condition or requirement that was not reasonable in the circumstances was imposed upon her (see s 9(1A)(a)). As was held by McHugh J in Waters and Others v Public Transport Corporation [1991] HCA 49 ; (1991) 173 CLR 349 at 406 in reference to a similar provision in Victorian anti-discrimination legislation (see s 17(5)(a) Equal Opportunity Act 1984 (Vic)), such term, condition or requirement would need to be identified with precision.

216 Further, under s 9(1A)(b) Ms Obieta must established that she does not or cannot comply with the term, condition or requirement and under s 9(1A)(c), that the requirement has the purpose or effect of interfering with the recognition, enjoyment or exercise, on an equal footing, by persons of the same race, colour, descent or national or ethnic origin as Ms Obieta, of any relevant human right or fundamental freedom.

217 Section 10 of the RDA relevantly provides for a right of equality before the law and that the laws of the Commonwealth, States and Territories are to apply generally to all people regardless of their race, colour, national or ethnic origin. Ms Obieta must show that under a particular law, she does not enjoy a right that is enjoyed by persons of another race, colour or national or ethnic origin, or that she enjoys that right to a more limited extent. Once this has been established then notwithstanding the particular law in question, by force of this section, she is entitled to enjoy the right to the same extent as persons of another race, colour or national or ethnic origin.

225 The question of causation that arises in the application of s 18C(1)(a) has been considered in numerous cases. In Purvis v New South Wales (Department of Education and Training) and Another [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 202 ALR 133 at 138 the High Court explained per Gleeson CJ, at 171-2 per McHugh and Kirby JJ, at 187 per Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ, that the accepted test for causation in the context of anti-discrimination legislation focuses on the 'genuine basis' or 'the true basis' or 'real reason' for the act of the alleged discriminator. The question of causation was also considered in Bropho 135 FCR at [71] wherein French J referred to the description by Kiefel J in Creek v Cairns Post 112 FCR at [28] of the key causation issue as 'whether anything suggests race as a factor' in the act in question. Kiefel J at [23] adopted the approach to the construction of statutory provisions similar to s 9 of the RDA taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR at 401.

227 In Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515 at [31] Carr J agreed with the adoption by Kiefel J of the approach taken by McHugh J in Waters 173 CLR. At 31 Carr J said: 
 
 'The authorities on the issue of causation in the context of the discrimination legislation were reviewed by Kiefel J in Cairns Post at [19]-[27]. It seems clear from what her Honour said at [22] that she regarded the assessment of a reason as being an objective one, but not one which excluded any evidence of the relevant person's intention or motive. Regard was to be had to all the circumstances. I respectfully agree with that approach.'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>