<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZJPS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 818 (14 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/818.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Muin v Refugee Review Tribunal [2002] HCA 30 ; (2002) 190 ALR 601</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/30.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal is based on three grounds. The first is that the Federal Magistrate failed to find error of law, jurisdictional error or lack of procedural fairness in the Tribunal's reasons. A second ground refers to the High Court judgment in Muin v Refugee Review Tribunal [2002] HCA 30 ; (2002) 190 ALR 601. The third ground simply refers to the High Court judgment in Plaintiff S157 of 2002 v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476.

12 Finally, it is said that the Federal Magistrate and the Tribunal erred in not finding that the appellant satisfied the definition of refugee. This is simply a generalised statement and no indication of any specific error has been asserted. I should add that in this case there is no evidence of any lack of procedural fairness and the case does not come within the principles enunciated in Muin. There is nothing pointed to by the appellant to indicate that the reasoning in that case has any application.

13 I have also considered the reasoning of the Federal Court Magistrate who deals with the arguments, some of a different nature, which were advanced before him and I can find no error in that reasoning.

14 Accordingly for the above reasons the order of the Court in this matter is that the appeal is dismissed with costs. 

 I certify that the preceding fourteen (14) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tamberlin. 


 Associate:

Dated: 28 May 2007


 Counsel for the Appellants: None 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellants: None 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Ms R. Francois 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 14 May 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 14 May 2007 



 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/818.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Plaintiff S157 of 2002 v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/2.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal is based on three grounds. The first is that the Federal Magistrate failed to find error of law, jurisdictional error or lack of procedural fairness in the Tribunal's reasons. A second ground refers to the High Court judgment in Muin v Refugee Review Tribunal [2002] HCA 30 ; (2002) 190 ALR 601. The third ground simply refers to the High Court judgment in Plaintiff S157 of 2002 v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] HCA 2 ; (2003) 211 CLR 476.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>