<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd (ACN 007 031 905) v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd (ACN 069 894 275) (No 2) [2007] FCA 903 (14 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/903.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Colgate Palmolive v Cussons (1993) 118 ALR 248</tocase>
<text>32 The ordinary rule is that costs are awarded on a party and party basis. From time to time, the Court has made an award of costs on a different basis. The authorities have identified various circumstances in which it may be appropriate to exercise the discretion to award costs on a different basis from a party and party basis. One such category is where there is evidence of particular misconduct by a party that causes loss of time to the Court and to the other parties. However, the authorities also make it clear that the categories of circumstances in which the Court may exercise its discretion to award costs on, for example, an indemnity basis are not closed. I refer to Colgate Palmolive v Cussons (1993) 118 ALR 248 at 254-257; Tetijo Holdings Pty Ltd v Keeprite Australia Pty Ltd (French J, unreported, 3 May 1991), Re Wilcox Ex Parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727 (" Re Wilcox "). The gap between party and party costs and indemnity costs may be increasing. However, while that may be a reason to review the scale rates, it is not in itself a reason to broaden the established criteria for awarding indemnity costs. As I understand it, that is a point made by Cooper and Merkel JJ in Re Wilcox (at 734).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fisher v RAFCORP (WA) (1995) 57 FCR 1</tocase>
<text>28 The respondents asked me to make a self-executing order in relation to the first order I made on 22 May 2007. In other words, they asked me to make an order that if the applicant does not comply with the first order then the proceedings do stand dismissed as to the whole of the relief claimed by the applicant. There is no doubt that I have the power to make such an order: O 35A, r 3(1)(c). I decline to do so. In Fisher v RAFCORP (WA) (1995) 57 FCR 1 at 19, the Full Court of this Court described such orders as unusual. I respectfully agree and I think that such orders should only be made in extreme cases. There may be many circumstances which arise subsequent to the making of such an order, which plainly call for a relaxation of a time limit fixed in the order and it would be unwise to place an obstacle in the way of a favourable exercise of the discretion. In my opinion, such an order should only be made when, in effect, all other efforts to ensure compliance have failed. The present is not such a case.

29 The respondents applied for the costs they incurred between 10 May and 22 May 2007, of the notice of motion dated 3 May 2007, of the hearings on 9 May 2007 and 22 May 2007 and of the adjournment of the trial on an indemnity basis.

30 In my opinion, the respondents are entitled to the costs of their notice of motion dated 3 May 2007. The applicant did not comply with the December orders as amended on 9 May 2007. They are also entitled to the costs of the hearings on 9 May and 22 May 2007 respectively because those hearings were primarily concerned with the variation of the December orders and the respondents' notice of motion. The respondents are also entitled to any costs occasioned by the adjournment of the trial. An adjournment of the trial was necessary because of the applicant's failure to comply with the orders of the Court and, in particular, the order as to the delivery of reports by expert witnesses. Finally, the respondents are entitled to any costs occasioned by the late delivery of statements. Clearly, those costs should be restricted to costs which have been wasted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd (ACN 007 031 905) v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd (ACN 069 894 275) [2007] FCA 489</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/489.html</AustLII>
<text>8. That the costs of this application be reserved."
 
 

I will refer to these orders as "the December orders".
 
3 On 5 March 2007, the applicant issued a notice of motion wherein it sought the following orders:
 
 
 "1. There be judgment for the Applicant against the First Respondent, on that part of the Applicant's claim that the First Respondent has contravened s 51AD of Part IV of the Trade Practices Act 1974 .
 
 2. There be judgment for the Applicant against the Second Respondent, and that part of the Applicant's claim that the Second Respondent has, pursuant to s 75B of the Trade Practices Act 1974 , been involved in a contravention of s 51AD of Part IVB of the Trade Practices Act 1974 .
 
 3. The assessment of the amount of damages, or other relief, be deferred until further order.
 
 4. An order that the Respondents pay the costs of this application.
 
 5. Such further or other order or relief as may be required."
 
 

4 The notice of motion was supported by an affidavit of Mr Nicholas Stewart who is the managing director of the applicant.
 
5 The applicant's notice of motion came on for mention before me on 13 March 2007. I fixed 28 March 2007 as the date for the hearing of the notice of motion and I made a number of directions relating to the material to be relied upon on the hearing of the notice of motion and the filing of outlines of submissions. On 13 March 2007, the respondents asserted that the applicant was in breach of the December orders.
 
6 I heard submissions on the applicant's notice of motion on 28 March 2007 and I reserved my decision. Again on that occasion the respondents asserted that the applicant had not complied with the December orders. The applicant asserted that the respondents had not made proper discovery. 
 
7 On 4 April 2007, I made the following orders:
 
 
 1. The application by the applicant by notice of motion dated 5 March 2007 be dismissed.
 2. The applicant pay the respondents' costs of the application by notice of motion dated 5 March 2007. 
 

I delivered reasons: Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd (ACN 007 031 905) v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd (ACN 069 894 275) [2007] FCA 489 .
 
8 Again on that occasion the respondents asserted that the applicant had not complied with the December orders. I indicated to the parties that if either party complained of a failure to comply with orders of the Court, then an appropriate application should be made on notice.

9 On 3 May 2007, the respondents issued a notice of motion seeking the following orders:
 
 
 "1. That these proceedings be stayed or dismissed as to the whole of the relief claimed by the applicant; or in the alternative
 2. That these proceedings be stayed or dismissed as to the whole of the relief claimed by the applicant, if the applicant does not serve on the respondents' solicitors a draft index for the proposed Court book within two days of the date of this order and further comply with the orders of the Honourable Justice Kenny dated 15 December 2006; and
 
 3. That the applicant pay the respondents' costs of and incidental to this application assessed on the standard basis unless agreed between the respondents on the one part and the applicant on the other part; and
 
 
 
 4. Any other orders that the Court may deem fit in the circumstances."

10 The respondents' notice of motion was supported by an affidavit from Ms Robyn Bartlett, who is a member of the firm of solicitors acting for the respondents. Ms Bartlett deposed to the fact that the applicant had not served on the respondents a draft index for the proposed Court book. The solicitor acting for the applicant swore an affidavit on 8 May 2007 and that affidavit was filed on the following day. The solicitor for the applicant deposed to the fact that the applicant asserted that the respondents had failed to discover any documents relating to the issue of the applicant's claim under the Franchising Code of Conduct and that such discovery was necessary before the applicant could prepare the Court book and Mr Stewart's witness statement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lenijamar Pty Ltd v AGC (Advances) Ltd (1990) 27 FCR 388</tocase>
<text>25 Previously, the power to make orders of this nature was contained in O 10, r 7. In Lenijamar Pty Ltd v AGC (Advances) Ltd (1990) 27 FCR 388, Wilcox and Gummow JJ considered the principles which should govern the discretion to dismiss a proceeding under O 10, r 7 of the Federal Court Rules . In my respectful opinion, their Honours' observations apply equally to the power in O 35A, r 3(1). Their Honours said (at 396-397):
 
 "The discretion conferred by O 10, r 7 is unconfined, except for the condition of non-compliance with a direction. As it is impossible to foresee all of the circumstances under which the rule might be sought to be used, it is undesirable to make any exhaustive statement of the circumstances under which the power granted by the rule will appropriately be exercised. We will not attempt to do so. But two situations are obvious candidates for the exercise of the power: cases in which the history of non-compliance by an applicant is such as to indicate an inability or unwillingness to co-operate with the Court and the other party or parties in having the matter ready for trial within an acceptable period and cases -- whatever the applicant's state of mind or resources -- in which the non-compliance is continuing and occasioning unnecessary delay, expense or other prejudice to the respondent. Although the history of the matter will always be relevant, it is more likely to be decisive in the first of these two situations. Even though the most recent non-compliance may be minor, the cumulative effect of an applicant's defaults may be such as to satisfy the judge that the applicant is either subjectively unwilling to co-operate or, for some reason, is unable to do so. Such a conclusion would not readily be reached; but, where it was, fairness to the respondent would normally require the summary dismissal of the proceeding.
 
 In the second of the two situations we postulate, a significant continuing default, it does not really matter whether there have been earlier omissions to comply with the Court's directions. Ex hypothesi the default is continuing and is imposing an unacceptable burden on the respondent. But the continuance of the non-compliance is of the essence of this situation. If, when the Court looks at the matter, the direction has already been complied with, the defaulting applicant may be ordered to pay any wasted costs; but it would be difficult to justify the dismissal of the proceeding solely because of that default."

26 I do not think that this case falls within either of the two situations identified by their Honours. Whatever else might be said about the applicant's failure to comply with Court orders and its failure to put forward an affidavit explaining in a clear and simple fashion the reason or reasons for those failures, I do not think that it can be inferred that its non-compliance is such as to indicate an inability or unwillingness to cooperate with the Court and the other party or parties in having the matter ready for trial within an acceptable period. Nor do I think that this is a case in which the non-compliance is continuing and occasioning unnecessary delay, expense or other prejudice to the respondents. There has been non-compliance but I would not describe it as continuing, bearing in mind the outlines of evidence that have now been filed and the expert's report which will be filed. There has been delay and there has been some expense to the respondents, but I can make an order for costs in relation to that expense. In the end, I would not describe the applicant's conduct as amounting to "a significant continuing default".

27 In the circumstances, I considered it appropriate to decline to make orders staying or dismissing the proceedings and, instead, I adjourned the commencement of the trial for a relatively short period.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tetijo Holdings Pty Ltd v Keeprite Australia Pty Ltd (unreported, French J, 3 May 1991)</tocase>
<text>32 The ordinary rule is that costs are awarded on a party and party basis. From time to time, the Court has made an award of costs on a different basis. The authorities have identified various circumstances in which it may be appropriate to exercise the discretion to award costs on a different basis from a party and party basis. One such category is where there is evidence of particular misconduct by a party that causes loss of time to the Court and to the other parties. However, the authorities also make it clear that the categories of circumstances in which the Court may exercise its discretion to award costs on, for example, an indemnity basis are not closed. I refer to Colgate Palmolive v Cussons (1993) 118 ALR 248 at 254-257; Tetijo Holdings Pty Ltd v Keeprite Australia Pty Ltd (French J, unreported, 3 May 1991), Re Wilcox Ex Parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727 (" Re Wilcox "). The gap between party and party costs and indemnity costs may be increasing. However, while that may be a reason to review the scale rates, it is not in itself a reason to broaden the established criteria for awarding indemnity costs. As I understand it, that is a point made by Cooper and Merkel JJ in Re Wilcox (at 734).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wilcox, Re; Ex Parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727</tocase>
<text>32 The ordinary rule is that costs are awarded on a party and party basis. From time to time, the Court has made an award of costs on a different basis. The authorities have identified various circumstances in which it may be appropriate to exercise the discretion to award costs on a different basis from a party and party basis. One such category is where there is evidence of particular misconduct by a party that causes loss of time to the Court and to the other parties. However, the authorities also make it clear that the categories of circumstances in which the Court may exercise its discretion to award costs on, for example, an indemnity basis are not closed. I refer to Colgate Palmolive v Cussons (1993) 118 ALR 248 at 254-257; Tetijo Holdings Pty Ltd v Keeprite Australia Pty Ltd (French J, unreported, 3 May 1991), Re Wilcox Ex Parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (1996) 141 ALR 727 (" Re Wilcox "). The gap between party and party costs and indemnity costs may be increasing. However, while that may be a reason to review the scale rates, it is not in itself a reason to broaden the established criteria for awarding indemnity costs. As I understand it, that is a point made by Cooper and Merkel JJ in Re Wilcox (at 734).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>