<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Chen v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship(Corrigendum dated 2 July 2007) [2007] FCA 958 (30 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/958.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ma v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCAFC 69</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/69.html</AustLII>
<text>3 In the reasons that I gave on 9 May 2007, I indicated that I did not consider that there was any error in the reasons of the Federal Magistrates Court. However, because I had not had the advantage of detailed submissions on the question, I adjourned the application for three weeks, in order to give the applicant the opportunity of obtaining legal advice, filing a further draft notice of appeal and making written submission. Since the earlier hearing, my attention has been drawn to a decision of the Full Court given on 11 May 2007 concerning the operation of the relevant regulations: Ma v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCAFC 69. The reasons of the Court in that proceeding tend to support views that have been expressed by judges of the Federal Magistrates Court concerning the operation of Amendment No 8.

4 As I indicated on 9 May, it is perhaps bad luck for the present applicant that his visa was cancelled only shortly before the Regulations were amended. Under the regime that exists, following the amendment, the decision-maker would have a discretion to take into account the circumstances of the applicant that led to his failing to satisfy Condition 8202. However, the language of the transitional provisions is unequivocal. As at the date of the Tribunal's decision, the visa in question had been cancelled. It follows, therefore, that the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court in this proceeding was correct. There is no arguable case that could have been advanced in an amended notice of appeal. There would be no utility in extending the time for filing a notice of appeal. In the circumstances the application must be dismissed with costs.

5 The solicitor for the Minister has asked that I fix the amount of the costs in the sum of $2,400. That is somewhat higher than would normally be expected in relation to an application for an extension of time. The Minister's solicitor assures me that the actual costs exceed that sum. The sum is justified by the nature of the claims made by the applicant in his application for extension of time. That is to say, he asserted that there was a denial of procedural fairness on the part of the Tribunal. That required the Minister to make inquiries and to file evidence, including evidence consisting of the transcript of the proceeding before the Federal Magistrates Court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>