<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nishtom Pty Ltd v Robinson (Trustee); in the matterof Kinsella (Bankrupt) [2007] FCA 978 (2 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/978.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Radaich v Smith [1959] HCA 45 ; (1959) 101 CLR 209</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/45.html</AustLII>
<text>I think it is quite clear that the bankrupt's possession of the property beyond completion of the contract was as a licensee of, and not as a tenant from, the applicants and that that situation did not change at any time before the date of bankruptcy. My reasons for being of this view are as follows: 
 
 (1) The circumstances in which the right of possession was granted as a vendor, from the purchaser, of the property where the common intention of the parties, so far as it can be discerned from the relevant terms of the contract, was to allow the vendor time (six months) to remove his chattels from the property; hence the nominal 'rent' of $50 per week. True, there was no evidence as to what a market rent would be, but having regard to the purchase price of the property ($850,000), the improvements and the business being carried on from the property, 'rent' of $50 per week could not be characterised as anything but 'nominal'.
 (2) The terms of Special Condition 5 (see [10] above), in particular: 
 
 
 (i) The use of the word 'rent' in the first sentence has no characterisation consequences of its own; for example, many chattel bailments use the word 'rent' to describe the consideration payable for the bailment when, strictly speaking, it is a hiring charge. The first sentence is totally neutral in indicating whether what is granted is a licence or a lease.
 (ii) More importantly, the right of the purchaser (the applicants) to enter onto the property is unlimited as to the purpose, frequency and time of entry. It is inconsistent with any claim or entitlement of the vendor (the bankrupt) to exclusive possession, which is the point of distinction between a licensee and a tenant: see Radaich v Smith [1959] HCA 45 ; (1959) 101 CLR 209 at 222 per Windeyer J; Street v Mountford [1985] UKHL 4 ; [1985] AC 809 at 827A E per Lord Templeman with whom the other of their Lordships agreed.
 (iii) The third sentence, which provides that if the vendor does not vacate the property 'at the expiration of six months (following settlement) the rental shall increase to $1,000 per week plus GST', informs the purpose of allowing the vendor to remain in possession beyond completion time in which to remove his chattels from the property and an ongoing weekly penalty if that task is not completed within six months of completion of the contract. These are the words of license, not demise and no covenant for quiet enjoyment could be implied.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Street v Mountford [1985] UKHL 4 ; [1985] AC 809</tocase>
<text>I think it is quite clear that the bankrupt's possession of the property beyond completion of the contract was as a licensee of, and not as a tenant from, the applicants and that that situation did not change at any time before the date of bankruptcy. My reasons for being of this view are as follows: 
 
 (1) The circumstances in which the right of possession was granted as a vendor, from the purchaser, of the property where the common intention of the parties, so far as it can be discerned from the relevant terms of the contract, was to allow the vendor time (six months) to remove his chattels from the property; hence the nominal 'rent' of $50 per week. True, there was no evidence as to what a market rent would be, but having regard to the purchase price of the property ($850,000), the improvements and the business being carried on from the property, 'rent' of $50 per week could not be characterised as anything but 'nominal'.
 (2) The terms of Special Condition 5 (see [10] above), in particular: 
 
 
 (i) The use of the word 'rent' in the first sentence has no characterisation consequences of its own; for example, many chattel bailments use the word 'rent' to describe the consideration payable for the bailment when, strictly speaking, it is a hiring charge. The first sentence is totally neutral in indicating whether what is granted is a licence or a lease.
 (ii) More importantly, the right of the purchaser (the applicants) to enter onto the property is unlimited as to the purpose, frequency and time of entry. It is inconsistent with any claim or entitlement of the vendor (the bankrupt) to exclusive possession, which is the point of distinction between a licensee and a tenant: see Radaich v Smith [1959] HCA 45 ; (1959) 101 CLR 209 at 222 per Windeyer J; Street v Mountford [1985] UKHL 4 ; [1985] AC 809 at 827A E per Lord Templeman with whom the other of their Lordships agreed.
 (iii) The third sentence, which provides that if the vendor does not vacate the property 'at the expiration of six months (following settlement) the rental shall increase to $1,000 per week plus GST', informs the purpose of allowing the vendor to remain in possession beyond completion time in which to remove his chattels from the property and an ongoing weekly penalty if that task is not completed within six months of completion of the contract. These are the words of license, not demise and no covenant for quiet enjoyment could be implied.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>