<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEYK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1940 (19 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1940.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jayasinghe v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1997] FCA 551 ; (1997) 76 FCR 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1997/551.html</AustLII>
<text>21 Further, the second Tribunal had already reviewed the delegate's decision. Once the Tribunal has delivered its decision free from jurisdictional error, it is functus officio . Once the statutory function is performed, there is no further function authorised under the Act for the Tribunal to carry out and it has no power to reopen the delegate's decision ( Jayasinghe v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1997] FCA 551 ; (1997) 76 FCR 301 per Goldberg J at 311).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Thiyagarajah [2000] HCA 9 ; (2000) 199 CLR 343</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/9.html</AustLII>
<text>22 In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Thiyagarajah [2000] HCA 9 ; (2000) 199 CLR 343 Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ noted that the Act contemplates changed circumstances which might found a fresh application to the Tribunal, but imposes the limitations found in ss 48A and 48B. As their Honours said at [30]:
 It would be inconsistent with that scheme and contrary to the ordinary reading of Div 2 of Pt 7 of the Act to treat the decision of the Tribunal as provisional in nature. In the situation where the Tribunal had, without reviewable error, disposed of an application for review of the decision of the delegate made on 11 October 1995, the Act did not confer upon the Tribunal any authority subsequently to reconsider the decision of the delegate by reason of later changed circumstances.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>39 I asked the applicant what he would have said to the third Tribunal had he been given the opportunity to address it on the question of jurisdiction. I also asked the applicant to identify any error in the conclusion by Smith FM that the third Tribunal had not erred in finding that it had no jurisdiction to hear his present application. The applicant was unable to make any relevant submission other than his assertion that the second Tribunal made a mistake and he wished to have the second Tribunal decision reconsidered. Therefore, even if there had been a denial of natural justice or procedural fairness, no practical injustice flows from it ( Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 per Gleeson CJ at [37]). As the Minister submits, an opportunity to address the Tribunal on the question of jurisdiction was ' a hollow opportunity '.

40 In the applicant's affidavit he alleges a failure on the part of the third Tribunal to comply with s 424A of the Act. Such a complaint is misconceived in circumstances where the third Tribunal found that it had no jurisdiction to conduct a second review of the delegate's decision. Section 424A is part of those provisions of the Act which govern the procedures to be adopted in the conduct of a review (set out in Part 7 Div 4 of the Act). Those provisions were not engaged.

41 The applicant has not established any purpose in remitting the matter to the Tribunal or any practical consequence arising from any denial of procedural fairness or natural justice. The applicant has not shown any error on the part of the Federal Magistrate nor has he shown that he has any prospects of success in an appeal from that decision. No substantial injustice would result if leave to appeal is not granted. The application for leave to appeal should be dismissed with costs.

 I certify that the preceding forty-one (41) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 

 Associate:

Dated: 19 December 2008

 The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 25 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 December 2008 

 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1940.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZBWJ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1175</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1175.html</AustLII>
<text>23 In SZBWJ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1175 , the applicants sought a further review by the Tribunal of a delegate's decision. Justice Moore said at [16]:
 In my view, a proper construction of the Act tells against a conclusion that the Tribunal is empowered to again review the delegate's decision in circumstances where the Tribunal's original decision was not attended with jurisdictional error. Treating the Tribunal as authorised to undertake a second review of the delegate's decision would be contrary to the statutory aim of providing a mechanism of review that is "fair, just, economical, informal and quick": see s 420(1) of the Act.

24 As Smith FM said in SZEYK v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1354 at [5] :
 ... the Tribunal referred to well known authority which establishes that it does not have jurisdiction to review a delegate's decision twice. That line of cases has recently been followed by Cowdroy J in SZCKX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 526 and Moore J in SZBWJ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 1175.

25 For these reasons, Smith FM did not err in his conclusion that the third Tribunal did not have jurisdiction to consider the application to conduct a second review of the delegate's decision. The third Tribunal correctly found that it lacked jurisdiction.

26 The applicant contends that he was denied procedural fairness by the third Tribunal. He claims that when he filed his application he was issued with a standard letter and then received no further correspondence from the third Tribunal (until the letter notifying him of the decision) and was not asked the reason for his repeat application. He claims that the third Tribunal did not give him an opportunity to reply concerning the validity of his application.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>