<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Standen v Feehan [2008] FCA 1009 (3 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1009.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/34.html</AustLII>
<text>20 The standard of proof is the civil standard, but because the claim is for a penalty, to the level of satisfaction in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 at 361-362.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<text>31 In my opinion, in the absence of any explanation for failing to call Mr Carslake and none was proffered, it would be right to draw the inference that Mr Carslake's evidence would not have assisted the respondent on this and the other two relevant conversations: Jones v Dunkel (1959) 101 CLR 298. There is no suggestion that Mr Carslake was not available to be called and I find that a conscious decision was made not to call him.

32 I accept Mr Zito's evidence and I find that on 3 May 2004 Mr Feehan told Mr Zito that he would close the site down because Mr Zito's employees were not members of the Union and because the site lacked the appropriate facilities. I also find that either later on 3 May 2004, or on 4 May 2004, Mr Feehan attended the site with Mr Carslake and Mr Carslake spoke to Mr Zito and told Mr Zito that he would not be able to pour concrete the next day.

33 The respondent said that he told Mr Zito that he would be back on 5 May 2004. I accept that aspect of the respondent's evidence because it is consistent with both Mr Potter's and Mr Zito's evidence. Moreover, he did return on 5 May 2004 as he promised.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>O'Reilly v The Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1983] HCA 47 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/47.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The issue to be determined is whether the respondent intentionally hindered or obstructed an employer or employee. That question is simply a question of fact. A person may intentionally hinder or obstruct another person by an active act or conduct which is essentially negative in character: O'Reilly v The Commissioners of the State Bank of Victoria [1983] HCA 47 ; (1983) 153 CLR 1 at 49-50.

22 Here the case against the respondent is that he did both. He both performed acts and failed to perform acts which showed that he intentionally hindered or obstructed both employers and employees.

23 The Halifax Street site is on the corner of Halifax Street and Cardwell Street, Adelaide. It is on the southern side of Halifax Street and its eastern border was on Cardwell Street. Part of its southern border at that time was on Ely Place. The rest of its southern border was on Gilles Street. The site was owned by the Southcott family but it was the Kinsmen Group who was the developer of the site. Scott Salisbury Homes were in May 2004 commencing to build eight separate two-storey townhouses or units with separate strata titles on an area of the site called "Stage 4". Stage 4 was on the western boundary of the site near Ely Place. The only access to the site was from Halifax Street, there being no access either from Cardwell Street or Ely Place. The area of the site immediately adjacent to Halifax Street was called the common access roadway. It was into that area that traffic coming from Halifax Street onto the site would enter. Immediately south of the common access area and to the east of Stage 4 was an area undergoing remediation. There was an access lane area between Stage 4 and the area undergoing remediation upon which traffic, including trucks, could travel to get access to all of Stage 4. Trucks could not turn in that access lane area. If a truck needed to turn it had to turn into the common access area immediately off Halifax Street. If a truck wanted to travel down the access lane area, the truck driver would have had to back down the lane if the truck driver wished to drive out nose first, or back out if the truck driver had chosen to drive in nose first. The common access area was sometimes used as a parking area for employees on the site and had been so used prior to the day in question.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Pine v Doyle (2005) 143 IR 98</tocase>
<text>60 Such a finding is consistent with him telling Mr Zito that he would be back the next day and with his later actions. He parked his car next to Rocky Mastrullo's truck. Shortly after he alighted from his car, he was approached by Mr Potter. He was asked to remove his car from the site. A conversation ensued. During the conversation Mr Potter asked to see the respondent's permit and the written notice of entry. The respondent disputed that he needed a written notice and claimed that Mr Potter knew that he would be there that day. The respondent showed Mr Potter his permit as he was obliged to do under s 285D(1). The exercise of a power of entry under the Act is a matter of fact: Pine v Doyle (2005) 143 IR 98. The respondent exercised that power of entry.

61 Mr Potter told him to move his vehicle and told him that the vehicle was parked in a position which would impede the progress of concrete trucks which needed that space in which to turn so that the trucks might back down the access lane to the Stage 4 development. The respondent did not comply with that request, notwithstanding that he was told that the position of his car was in an area designated for the trucks to turn. His silence amounted to a refusal.

62 It was at the time the practice of the Building Industry Task Force to maintain a running sheet as a record of matters that were attended to on particular days. Mr Concannon kept a running sheet of the events of 5 May 2004 which was exhibited to his affidavit.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>