<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bienstein v Family Court of Australia [2008] FCA 1138 (5 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1138.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bienstein and Family Court of Australia [2006] AATA 385 (2006) 43 AAR 34</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2006/385.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The applicant made a request to the respondent, a court created under Ch III of the Constitution , for certain documents. The respondent declined to grant that request. The applicant's request for internal review of the decision was granted, but the decision was affirmed after internal review. The applicant then sought review of the respondent's decision by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ("the Tribunal"). The Tribunal's decision was to affirm the decision under review. The decision and reasons for decision, which are designated as Bienstein and Family Court of Australia [2006] AATA 385 (2006) 43 AAR 34 , were given on 10 April 2006. The applicant appealed to this Court from that decision of the Tribunal. By s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) ("the AAT Act "), a party to a proceeding before the Tribunal may appeal to this Court from a decision of the Tribunal in that proceeding, but the right of appeal is limited to a question of law.

3 The object of the FOI Act is set out clearly in s 3: 
 (1) The object of this Act is to extend as far as possible the right of the Australian community to access to information in the possession of the Government of the Commonwealth by: (a) making available to the public information about the operations of departments and public authorities and, in particular, ensuring that rules and practices affecting members of the public in their dealings with departments and public authorities are readily available to persons affected by those rules and practices; and (b) creating a general right of access to information in documentary form in the possession of Ministers, departments and public authorities, limited only by exceptions and exemptions necessary for the protection of essential public interests and the private and business affairs of persons in respect of whom information is collected and held by departments and public authorities; and (c) creating a right to bring about the amendment of records containing personal information that is incomplete, incorrect, out of date or misleading. (2) It is the intention of the Parliament that the provisions of this Act shall be interpreted so as to further the object set out in subsection (1) and that any discretions conferred by this Act shall be exercised as far as possible so as to facilitate and promote, promptly and at the lowest reasonable cost, the disclosure of information.

4 Section 5 provides:
 For the purposes of this Act: (a) a court shall be deemed to be a prescribed authority; (b) the holder of a judicial office or other office pertaining to a court in his or her capacity as the holder of that office, being an office established by the legislation establishing the court, shall be deemed not to be a prescribed authority and shall not be included in a Department; and (c) a registry or other office of a court, and the staff of such a registry or other office when acting in a capacity as members of that staff, shall be taken as a part of the court; but this Act does not apply to any request for access to a document of the court unless the document relates to matters of an administrative nature.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Bizuneh v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 42 (2003) 128 FCR 353</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/42.html</AustLII>
<text>73 In Bizuneh v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 42 (2003) 128 FCR 353 , a Full Court rejected an application for leave to appeal from a direction of a judge to a registrar under O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules ("the Federal Court Rules ") not to accept an application and accompanying affidavit for filing. At [16]-[17], the Full Court said:
 No judicial act is carried out by the Registrar in so acting. The Registrar continues to perform an administrative function, albeit that the act of the Registrar may bear upon the ultimate performance of judicial power. Insofar as r 7A gives the Registrar a discretion to seek a direction from a judge as to performance of the Registrar's duties, the direction sought is administrative in character. It is a direction provided by a judge to assist the Registrar in the task of administration and is not a determination of right made by a judge after hearing or considering arguments or submissions upon an application to the Court seeking the exercise of judicial power. Rule 7A provides for a judge to act in aid of administration of the Court. There is no application to the Court by motion or otherwise and no requirement for a party to be heard. It involves determination of administrative obligations with respect to documents presented to a Registrar having regard to the character of the documents on their face. No order or decree intended to bind a party and no determination of right is made by a judge where assistance is provided to a Registrar under r 7A.

74 It appears to follow from the Full Court's judgment that both the decision of the registrar to seek a direction of a judge, and the decision of the judge to direct the registrar, are decisions of an administrative character. Unfortunately, the Full Court does not seem to have had the benefit of citation of the apparently contrary view of Toohey J in Letts . In Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369 , Sackville J took the view that he was bound by Bizuneh to decide that both the registrar seeking a direction of a judge, and the judge giving the direction, pursuant to O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules , made decisions of an administrative character. At [31]-[39], his Honour referred to Edwards , Letts and Bizuneh. At [40]-[41], his Honour drew attention to the fact that the Full Court had not referred to Letts , and expressed doubts about the correctness of the reasoning in Bizuneh , whilst acknowledging that it was binding on him. His Honour made orders adding as respondents to the proceeding before him the deputy registrar who had made the decision to seek the direction of a judge and the judge who gave the direction to refuse to accept the documents. Subsequently, in Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508 , effectively by consent, Sackville J set aside both the decision to seek a direction, and the direction, on the ground referred to in s 5(1)(d) of the ADJR Act , apparently on the basis that his Honour had foreshadowed in the first judgment at [43]-[51]. This was that both the registrar and the judge had taken into account other documents previously filed by the same applicant, whereas O 46 r 7A requires that the originating process "appears...on its face to be an abuse of the process of the Court or to be frivolous or vexatious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1979) 24 ALR 577</tocase>
<text>39 The applicant was wrong to suggest that, simply because the respondent did not adhere to its original decision, the Tribunal should have ordered it to make a new decision. The Tribunal was required to review the decision of the respondent itself, and to make the correct or preferable decision in accordance with the law and on the facts as it found them after its hearing. See Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1979) 24 ALR 577 at 589 per Bowen CJ and Deane J. The fact that the respondent appeared to have retreated somewhat from its original decision did not mean that the decision had disappeared. Nor did the Tribunal possess statutory power to compel the respondent to make another decision on this basis. Section 42D of the AAT Act confers on the Tribunal power to remit the decision to the person who made it for reconsideration. That power does not include power to compel the original decision-maker to make a decision different from that made in the first place. (Section 42D(2) provides that, if the decision is remitted, the original decision-maker may affirm or vary the decision, or set aside the decision and substitute a new decision.) There is no requirement that the Tribunal exercise the power to compel reconsideration, only a discretion to do so. No error of law can result from a failure to exercise the power.

40 In principle, there is nothing wrong with the Tribunal encouraging the parties to an application for review to resolve their differences. Section 42C of the AAT Act makes specific provision for the Tribunal to act in accordance with agreement reached between the parties or their representatives as to the terms of a decision of the Tribunal, if it is satisfied that a decision in those terms or consistent with those terms would be within the powers of the Tribunal. It may be that, in the circumstances, when the applicant had made clear a number of times her intention to press for a decision of the Tribunal, rather than to agree to limiting her access to documents to those available under the Family Court Rules or to those offered to her by the respondent, the Tribunal went too far and delayed too long in attempting to persuade her to settle. This could not be characterised as an error of law. At the most, it was a well-intentioned but perhaps misguided attempt to have the proceeding resolved otherwise than by a decision of the Tribunal.

41 To the extent to which there was delay in the Tribunal proceeding, the delay appears to have been partly due to the applicant's illness, and to her consequent inability or unwillingness to move along her end of the proceeding. Whatever the objects of the FOI Act may say about promptness, it is not an error of law for the Tribunal not to hear and determine an application within any particular period after the filing of the application. Managing the large number of cases that come before the Tribunal is challenging enough without imposing on the Tribunal deadlines in particular types of cases. The object of promptness in s 3(2) of the FOI Act is exhortatory, not mandatory. Lack of promptness is not error of law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Fingleton v The Queen [2005] HCA 34 (2005) 227 CLR 166</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/34.html</AustLII>
<text>34 The senior member then set out the terms of s 5 of the FOI Act , and a passage quoted from the judgment of the High Court in Fingleton v The Queen [2005] HCA 34 (2005) 227 CLR 166 at [52] per Gleeson CJ, to which I refer below. The senior member then referred to MacKeigan v Hickman [1989] 2 SCR 796 , to which Gleeson CJ had referred in Fingleton , for its comments by the Supreme Court of Canada on the limits of the power to investigate the reasons for a decision to assign a judge to a case. The senior member then continued:
 8. The Tribunal has considered the nature of the documents relevant to Ms Bienstein's request, and finds that the documents refer to organisational matters such as Court lists and the assigning of judicial officers to particular cases. As noted in Fingleton, these are matters affecting litigants and the public, and are intimately related to the independent and impartial administration of justice. They are not documents of internal administration. 9. For these reasons under s 5 of the FOI Act the Tribunal finds that the relevant documents are not documents that relate to matters of an administrative nature, so the FOI Act does not apply to the request for access to the documents.

35 The questions of law specified in the applicant's notice of appeal are in the following terms:
 1) Whether a Respondent who claims to have grounds for challenging the Tribunal's jurisdiction is compelled either to issue the challenge and have it determined at the outset or submit to the jurisdiction for the duration of the proceeding; 2) What bearing, if any, do the following statutory provisions have on the s 11 enforceable right of access provision of the Freedom of Information Act : 
 
 
 a) Sections 5 , 14 and 20 FOI Act , generally; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 b) Order 5 Rule 6 Family Court Rules in the context of Tribunal 
 proceedings regarding an FOI request to the Family Court of 
 Australia for access to one's own case management documents; 
 
 
 
 
 
 
3) Whether it is Tribunal's role in Part VI FOI Review proceedings to determine which of the Applicant's rights in respect of the request remain to be satisfied and promptly direct the Respondent to satisfy those rights in a timely manner; 4) Whether an Applicant in Part VI Review proceedings has an immediate right to receive in the Respondent's s 37 statement full and honest disclosure of the Respondent's relevant document holding, an account of the steps the Respondent took in the search and decision-making process, and documents to evidence the account given; 5) Whether documents relating to the case management of matters before the Family Court of Australia necessarily fall within the s 5 FOI Act exclusion and whether the High Court decision in Fingleton v The Queen [2005] HCA 34 (23 June 2005) supports such a conclusion;

36 It is clear that the notice of appeal was prepared without legal assistance. The questions of law are framed in an abstract way, rather than by reference to specific issues decided by the Tribunal or to specific reasons given by it for its decision. Grounds 2 and 5 clearly raise the effect of s 5 of the FOI Act , and therefore raise for consideration the correctness of the Tribunal's decision that all of the possible documents sought in the applicant's request did not relate to matters of an administrative nature. The other questions of law raised concern aspects of the way in which the Tribunal dealt with the applicant's application for review of the respondent's decision, prior to the Tribunal making its decision. These concerns of the applicant are reflected in the orders sought in her notice of appeal, which are expressed in the following terms:
 1) Declare that documents related to the management of cases proceeding in a court or tribunal are documents of the court or tribunal relating matters of an administrative nature and, as such, fall outside the s 5 FOI exclusion. 2) Declare that the Tribunal's role during the course of proceedings and when making a final decision is to promote and enforce the Applicant's rights in relation to the FOI request in question. 3) Declare that the Tribunal has an obligation to ensure that Respondents comply fully and without undue delay with provisions of s 37 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act . 4) Directed the Respondent to file an appropriately amended s 37 statement, incorporating an amended decision with schedule of all documents within scope of the request that had been located, an account of the searches it had conducted and objective documentary evidence in support of the account; 5) Set aside the Tribunal decision and remit the matter to be dealt with according to law. 
 
 6) Make a costs order in favour of the Applicant.

37 The concern of the applicant with the manner in which her request for access to documents was dealt with by the respondent, both initially and while it was pending in the Tribunal, is reflected in the grounds advanced in the notice of appeal. These grounds cover approximately six pages. The applicant sets out in some detail the history, which I have set out above, including some substantial quotes from correspondence and other documents. Woven into this history are indications that the applicant takes issue with various statements made on behalf of the respondent and with the course taken by the Tribunal in relation to her application to review. She also clearly takes issue with the view of the respondent, and that of the Tribunal, in relation to the application of s 5 of the FOI Act .

55 As I have said in [34], the Tribunal relied on a passage quoted from the judgment of Gleeson CJ in Fingleton v The Queen [2005] HCA 34 (2005) 227 CLR 166 at [52] , where his Honour said:
 The answer to that question, and to the respondent's argument, requires closer examination of s 10 of the Magistrates Act . In truth it covers a number of matters closely related to issues of judicial independence. Sub-sections (1) and (2) of s 10 cover the whole range of matters relevant to the orderly and expeditious exercise of the jurisdiction and powers of the Magistrates Courts, and include the organising of court lists, the allocation of magistrates to particular localities, and the assigning of magistrates to particular work. Arrangements of that kind are not merely matters of internal administration. They affect litigants and the public. Within any court, the assignment of a judicial officer to a particular case, or a particular kind of business, or a particular locality, is a matter intimately related to the independent and impartial administration of justice. This was the basis of the decision of the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Rajski v Wood, where it was held that the nomination or allocation of a judge to hear a particular case was not justiciable. As was pointed out in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Wang, where it is the function of a head of jurisdiction to assign members of a court to hear particular cases, the capacity to exercise that function, free from interference by, and scrutiny of, the other branches of government is an essential aspect of judicial independence. The same may be said of the capacity to exercise that function free from the threat of civil or criminal sanctions.

56 When viewed in the context of the judgment of Gleeson CJ, this passage may not lead to the conclusion that the Tribunal drew from it.

57 In Fingleton , the Chief Magistrate of Queensland had been convicted of the offence of unlawful retaliation against a witness under s 119B of the Criminal Code (Qld) ("the Criminal Code "). The facts were that the Chief Magistrate had determined that a magistrate should be transferred to Townsville. The magistrate filed an application for review of that determination. The magistrate wrote to the Magistrates Association, seeking assistance with her application. A Co-ordinating Magistrate, who was also Vice-President of the Magistrates Association, provided an affidavit to assist the magistrate in the review proceeding. The Chief Magistrate then sent to the Co-ordinating Magistrate a letter calling on him to show cause why he should not be removed from the position of Co-ordinating Magistrate. The letter referred specifically to the affidavit in support of the magistrate's review application.

58 On appeal to the High Court, there was raised for the first time s 30 of the Criminal Code , which provided:
 Except as expressly provided by this Code, a judicial officer is not criminally responsible for anything done or omitted to be done by the judicial officer in the exercise of the officer's judicial functions, although the act done is in excess of the officer's judicial authority, or although the officer is bound to do the act omitted to be done.

59 The power the exercise of which by the Chief Magistrate gave rise to the charge was found in s 10 of the Magistrates Act 1991 (Qld) ("the Magistrates Act "). Particularly relevant was the express power in s 10(2)(d) , of nominating a magistrate to be a Supervising Magistrate or a Co-ordinating Magistrate for the purpose of the allocation of work of the Magistrates Court. In conjunction with s 25(1) of the Acts Interpretation Act 1954 (Qld), the power to appoint included a power to remove. It was also necessary to consider s 21A of the Magistrates Act , which provided:
 A magistrate has, in the performance or exercise of an administrative function or power conferred on the magistrate under an Act, the same protection and immunity as a magistrate has in a judicial proceeding in a Magistrates Court.

60 One of the issues determined by the High Court in Fingleton was whether, in combination, s 21A of the Magistrates Act and s 30 of the Criminal Code gave immunity to the Chief Magistrate in exercising the power given to her by s 10(2)(d) of the Magistrates Act . In his reasons for judgment, Gleeson CJ dealt at length with this issue. At [47]-[48], his Honour summarised the competing contentions on the issue:
 The argument for the appellant in this Court was that s 10 of the Magistrates Act conferred on the appellant as Chief Magistrate a series of administrative functions and powers, that she acted in the performance or exercise of those powers, that she had the same protection and immunity as she had in the exercise of her judicial functions, and that, except as expressly provided by the Code, she was not criminally responsible for anything done by her in the exercise of her administrative functions, even if the act done was in excess of her administrative authority. The argument for the respondent turned upon a question of construction of s 21A and, in particular, the words "administrative function or power conferred on [a] magistrate under an Act". The respondent submitted that those words did not cover s 10 of the Magistrates Act itself. The argument called in aid two considerations: one textual; the other related to the rationale of immunity.

61 His Honour then proceeded to deal with what he described as the textual consideration. This involved the question whether the phrase "under an Act" in s 21A of the Magistrates Act referred only to functions or powers conferred on magistrates by legislation other than the Magistrates Act , or whether it included such powers and functions conferred by the Magistrates Act itself. By contrast, the consideration related to the rationale of immunity involved a comparison of the sorts of functions and powers conferred by s 10 of the Magistrates Act with the sorts of functions and powers conferred by various other statutes, as to which there was a need for the protection of magistrates from interference with their independence in the decision-making process. The question that Gleeson CJ answered in the passage from his judgment, which I have quoted in [55] above, is posed in [51] of his Honour's judgment:
 Such independence is important in relation to the exercise by magistrates of the various responsibilities conferred on them by other Acts of the kind set out above. What, the respondent asks, does it have to do with matters of internal court administration and discipline of the kind dealt with by the Magistrates Act itself?

62 It is to be noted that, in the passage quoted in [55] above from his Honour's judgment, Gleeson CJ described s 10 of the Magistrates Act as covering a number of matters "closely related to issues of judicial independence." In other words, they were not themselves issues of judicial independence, but closely related. His Honour referred to the organising of court lists, the allocation of magistrates to particular localities and the assigning of magistrates to particular work. In saying that arrangements of that kind "are not merely matters of internal administration", but that they "affect litigants and the public", his Honour was not saying that those matters fell within the exercise of judicial power. Rather, Gleeson CJ was underlining the public importance of these aspects of court administration, because of their close relationship to issues of judicial independence. Following the passage quoted in [55] above, in [52] of his Honour's reasons for judgment, Gleeson CJ said:
 The responsibilities conferred upon a Chief Magistrate by s 10 would cover some mundane issues of a kind that arise in the administration of any substantial organisation. On the other hand, some of those responsibilities, and especially those involving decisions which directly or indirectly determine how the business of Magistrates Courts will be arranged and allocated, concern matters which go to the essence of judicial independence. The selection of supervising and Co-ordinating Magistrates is a matter that falls into that category. It is, therefore, incorrect to say that the functions and powers conferred on the Chief Magistrate by s 10 are unrelated to the rationale for the immunity in question. As to some of those functions the rationale is directly relevant. As to some it may be of no relevance, or of limited relevance. As to others, its relevance may depend upon the circumstances.

65 In Fingleton at [59], McHugh J expressed his agreement with the reasons of Gummow and Heydon JJ with respect to the issue relevant to this case. At [121]-[123], Gummow and Heydon JJ said:
 The appeal in this Court thus turns upon the construction of s 21A of the Magistrates Act . The submissions for the respondent fix upon the phrase therein "conferred on the magistrate under an Act". The respondent seeks to introduce a limitation upon those words so that the phrase is to be understood as if it read "under any Act other than this Act". Section 10 of the Magistrates Act conferred upon the appellant a range of administrative functions or powers. They included the nomination of Co-ordinating Magistrates, the allocation of magistrates to particular localities and the power of reprimand. Indeed, it was a demand made by the appellant upon a Co-ordinating Magistrate to show cause why he should not be removed from that post which gave rise to the charge against her under s 119B of the Code. Attainment of the evident purpose of s 21A will be limited if it were to be given the qualified reading for which the respondent contends. For these reasons, which concern the construction of s 21A, and those on this issue developed by the Chief Justice in his judgment, the appellant was not liable to be held criminally responsible for the conduct alleged against her.

66 For reasons that he set out at [162]-[169], Kirby J came to the same conclusion on the question of judicial immunity. At [193], Hayne J expressed his agreement with the reasons of Gummow and Heydon JJ. Each of the members of the High Court other than Kirby J therefore expressed their agreement, directly or indirectly, with the reasons given by Gleeson CJ.

67 What emerges from Fingleton , and particularly from the passage quoted by the Tribunal, of relevance to this case is the proposition that there will be powers and functions exercised and performed within a court, even by the judicial officers of that court, that are of an administrative nature. Some of those powers and functions will be such that, of their very nature, they are so close to the overriding consideration of judicial independence as to be an essential part of the adjudicative function. It follows that the exercise of those functions, although it might be termed "administrative", ought to be protected from scrutiny by other arms of government, or by members of the public. Not all of the powers and functions properly characterised as being of an administrative nature will be so closely related to judicial independence that they need this kind of protection. In some cases, it will be necessary to look at the particular exercise of a power, or the particular act or acts in performance of a function, in their context, to determine whether public or executive scrutiny of them would endanger the necessary independence. This accords with the sort of distinction expressed by Senator Evans when he moved the amendment that became ss 5 and 6 of the FOI Act , between documents relating to matters of an administrative nature, and documents the exposure of which to the public view would threaten the independence which is a necessary element of the exercise of adjudicative functions by courts and tribunals. It is this distinction that is of the highest relevance in determining the purpose, and therefore the proper construction, of s 5 (and, incidentally, of s 6) of the FOI Act .

68 Reference was made by counsel for the respondent to a number of other authorities, either on s 5 of the FOI Act or on similar legislation. It is necessary to look at those authorities, to see whether they provide any useful guidance to the construction of s 5 , as relevant to this proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Legal Aid Commission of Western Australia v Edwards (1982) 42 ALR 154</tocase>
<text>72 There is a line of authority, to which Deputy President Walker referred, concerning whether a determination that a court should accept documents for filing, or reject them as an abuse of the court's processes, falls within the phrase "decision of an administrative character" in the ADJR Act . In Legal Aid Commission of Western Australia v Edwards (1982) 42 ALR 154 , Toohey J held that a decision of a deputy registrar of the Family Court of Western Australia to reject an application for taxation of a bill of costs, on the ground that the court did not have jurisdiction to deal with a dispute between the Legal Aid Commission and the solicitors for a legally aided party, was a decision of an administrative character. At 158-159, his Honour pointed out that the decision was not made under the direction of the court, apparently meaning under the direction of a judge. By contrast, in Letts v Commonwealth (1985) 8 FCR 585 at 586-587, Toohey J held that a registrar of the High Court, who sought the direction of a justice with respect to an attempt to file initiating process, had not made a decision of an administrative character. At 587, his Honour said:
 The Registrar was in truth exercising the jurisdiction of the High Court to control frivolous or vexatious applications, a jurisdiction that may be exercised through officers of the court as well as justices. 
His Honour distinguished Edwards on the basis that the decision the subject of Edwards "was not readily susceptible of review by a judge of that Court."

74 It appears to follow from the Full Court's judgment that both the decision of the registrar to seek a direction of a judge, and the decision of the judge to direct the registrar, are decisions of an administrative character. Unfortunately, the Full Court does not seem to have had the benefit of citation of the apparently contrary view of Toohey J in Letts . In Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369 , Sackville J took the view that he was bound by Bizuneh to decide that both the registrar seeking a direction of a judge, and the judge giving the direction, pursuant to O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules , made decisions of an administrative character. At [31]-[39], his Honour referred to Edwards , Letts and Bizuneh. At [40]-[41], his Honour drew attention to the fact that the Full Court had not referred to Letts , and expressed doubts about the correctness of the reasoning in Bizuneh , whilst acknowledging that it was binding on him. His Honour made orders adding as respondents to the proceeding before him the deputy registrar who had made the decision to seek the direction of a judge and the judge who gave the direction to refuse to accept the documents. Subsequently, in Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508 , effectively by consent, Sackville J set aside both the decision to seek a direction, and the direction, on the ground referred to in s 5(1)(d) of the ADJR Act , apparently on the basis that his Honour had foreshadowed in the first judgment at [43]-[51]. This was that both the registrar and the judge had taken into account other documents previously filed by the same applicant, whereas O 46 r 7A requires that the originating process "appears...on its face to be an abuse of the process of the Court or to be frivolous or vexatious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Letts v Commonwealth (1985) 8 FCR 585</tocase>
<text>72 There is a line of authority, to which Deputy President Walker referred, concerning whether a determination that a court should accept documents for filing, or reject them as an abuse of the court's processes, falls within the phrase "decision of an administrative character" in the ADJR Act . In Legal Aid Commission of Western Australia v Edwards (1982) 42 ALR 154 , Toohey J held that a decision of a deputy registrar of the Family Court of Western Australia to reject an application for taxation of a bill of costs, on the ground that the court did not have jurisdiction to deal with a dispute between the Legal Aid Commission and the solicitors for a legally aided party, was a decision of an administrative character. At 158-159, his Honour pointed out that the decision was not made under the direction of the court, apparently meaning under the direction of a judge. By contrast, in Letts v Commonwealth (1985) 8 FCR 585 at 586-587, Toohey J held that a registrar of the High Court, who sought the direction of a justice with respect to an attempt to file initiating process, had not made a decision of an administrative character. At 587, his Honour said:
 The Registrar was in truth exercising the jurisdiction of the High Court to control frivolous or vexatious applications, a jurisdiction that may be exercised through officers of the court as well as justices. 
His Honour distinguished Edwards on the basis that the decision the subject of Edwards "was not readily susceptible of review by a judge of that Court."

74 It appears to follow from the Full Court's judgment that both the decision of the registrar to seek a direction of a judge, and the decision of the judge to direct the registrar, are decisions of an administrative character. Unfortunately, the Full Court does not seem to have had the benefit of citation of the apparently contrary view of Toohey J in Letts . In Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369 , Sackville J took the view that he was bound by Bizuneh to decide that both the registrar seeking a direction of a judge, and the judge giving the direction, pursuant to O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules , made decisions of an administrative character. At [31]-[39], his Honour referred to Edwards , Letts and Bizuneh. At [40]-[41], his Honour drew attention to the fact that the Full Court had not referred to Letts , and expressed doubts about the correctness of the reasoning in Bizuneh , whilst acknowledging that it was binding on him. His Honour made orders adding as respondents to the proceeding before him the deputy registrar who had made the decision to seek the direction of a judge and the judge who gave the direction to refuse to accept the documents. Subsequently, in Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508 , effectively by consent, Sackville J set aside both the decision to seek a direction, and the direction, on the ground referred to in s 5(1)(d) of the ADJR Act , apparently on the basis that his Honour had foreshadowed in the first judgment at [43]-[51]. This was that both the registrar and the judge had taken into account other documents previously filed by the same applicant, whereas O 46 r 7A requires that the originating process "appears...on its face to be an abuse of the process of the Court or to be frivolous or vexatious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Loughnan (Principal Registrar, Family Court of Australia) v Altman [1992] FCA 580 ; (1992) 39 FCR 90</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/580.html</AustLII>
<text>69 In Loughnan (Principal Registrar, Family Court of Australia) v Altman [1992] FCA 580 ; (1992) 39 FCR 90 , the Full Court dealt with an appeal from a decision of the Tribunal, constituted by its then President, O'Connor J, in Re Altman and Family Court of Australia (1992) 27 ALD 369. Her Honour had reached the conclusion that an unrevised transcript of reasons for judgment pronounced in open court by a judge of the respondent was a document that the respondent was required to give access to under s 5 of the FOI Act . Because the unrevised transcript was produced by the agency responsible for providing transcript of court proceedings, the case turns largely on the meaning of the expression "a document of the court" in s 5 , and is therefore of little relevance to the present case. In the course of the Full Court's judgment, at 95, the Court did approve the conclusion of O'Connor J that the unrevised transcript was not a document of an administrative nature. Clearly, the giving of reasons for judgment and the practice of revising the transcript of those reasons for publication as the reasons for judgment are at the very heart of the judicial process, and the ready availability of the unrevised transcript to the public could undermine the independence of the judiciary.

70 Loughnan has since been discussed in a couple of decisions of the Tribunal. In Re O'Sullivan and Family Court of Australia (1997) 47 ALD 765 , Senior Member Dwyer dealt with a case in which access was sought to the handwritten notes of a Family Court counsellor. In her reasons, the learned senior member discussed Loughnan in the context of determining whether the counsellor's notes were documents of the court. Having concluded that they were, at [25] the senior member found that the notes were not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature, because of the professional duties of the counsellor. It is unnecessary to decide in the present case whether that conclusion was correct. In Re Simring and High Court of Australia [2006] AATA 849 (2006) 44 AAR 103 , Deputy President Walker dealt with a request for access to a document created in the course of dealing with an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court. The learned deputy president took the view that, because the document had been brought into existence within the chambers of a judge, as part of the judicial deliberative process, it was a judicial document, and not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature. The deputy president regarded Loughnan as not in point. At [19], the deputy president referred to the words "relates to matters of an administrative nature" in s 5 of the FOI Act in the following terms:
 The language used is relatively flexible and focuses on the general nature of the document rather than on the presence in the document of any administrative features whatever, however insignificant they might be in relation to the document's general nature. Even if the document in issue dealt incidentally with some administrative matters, and there is no evidence that it does, that would not necessarily detract from its overall quality as a document pertaining to the judicial role of the Court rather than to its administrative organisation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MacKeigan v Hickman [1989] 2 SCR 796</tocase>
<text>34 The senior member then set out the terms of s 5 of the FOI Act , and a passage quoted from the judgment of the High Court in Fingleton v The Queen [2005] HCA 34 (2005) 227 CLR 166 at [52] per Gleeson CJ, to which I refer below. The senior member then referred to MacKeigan v Hickman [1989] 2 SCR 796 , to which Gleeson CJ had referred in Fingleton , for its comments by the Supreme Court of Canada on the limits of the power to investigate the reasons for a decision to assign a judge to a case. The senior member then continued:
 8. The Tribunal has considered the nature of the documents relevant to Ms Bienstein's request, and finds that the documents refer to organisational matters such as Court lists and the assigning of judicial officers to particular cases. As noted in Fingleton, these are matters affecting litigants and the public, and are intimately related to the independent and impartial administration of justice. They are not documents of internal administration. 9. For these reasons under s 5 of the FOI Act the Tribunal finds that the relevant documents are not documents that relate to matters of an administrative nature, so the FOI Act does not apply to the request for access to the documents.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/369.html</AustLII>
<text>74 It appears to follow from the Full Court's judgment that both the decision of the registrar to seek a direction of a judge, and the decision of the judge to direct the registrar, are decisions of an administrative character. Unfortunately, the Full Court does not seem to have had the benefit of citation of the apparently contrary view of Toohey J in Letts . In Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369 , Sackville J took the view that he was bound by Bizuneh to decide that both the registrar seeking a direction of a judge, and the judge giving the direction, pursuant to O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules , made decisions of an administrative character. At [31]-[39], his Honour referred to Edwards , Letts and Bizuneh. At [40]-[41], his Honour drew attention to the fact that the Full Court had not referred to Letts , and expressed doubts about the correctness of the reasoning in Bizuneh , whilst acknowledging that it was binding on him. His Honour made orders adding as respondents to the proceeding before him the deputy registrar who had made the decision to seek the direction of a judge and the judge who gave the direction to refuse to accept the documents. Subsequently, in Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508 , effectively by consent, Sackville J set aside both the decision to seek a direction, and the direction, on the ground referred to in s 5(1)(d) of the ADJR Act , apparently on the basis that his Honour had foreshadowed in the first judgment at [43]-[51]. This was that both the registrar and the judge had taken into account other documents previously filed by the same applicant, whereas O 46 r 7A requires that the originating process "appears...on its face to be an abuse of the process of the Court or to be frivolous or vexatious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/508.html</AustLII>
<text>74 It appears to follow from the Full Court's judgment that both the decision of the registrar to seek a direction of a judge, and the decision of the judge to direct the registrar, are decisions of an administrative character. Unfortunately, the Full Court does not seem to have had the benefit of citation of the apparently contrary view of Toohey J in Letts . In Paramasivam v Randwick City Council [2005] FCA 369 , Sackville J took the view that he was bound by Bizuneh to decide that both the registrar seeking a direction of a judge, and the judge giving the direction, pursuant to O 46 r 7A of the Federal Court Rules , made decisions of an administrative character. At [31]-[39], his Honour referred to Edwards , Letts and Bizuneh. At [40]-[41], his Honour drew attention to the fact that the Full Court had not referred to Letts , and expressed doubts about the correctness of the reasoning in Bizuneh , whilst acknowledging that it was binding on him. His Honour made orders adding as respondents to the proceeding before him the deputy registrar who had made the decision to seek the direction of a judge and the judge who gave the direction to refuse to accept the documents. Subsequently, in Paramasivam v Randwick City Council (No. 2) [2005] FCA 508 , effectively by consent, Sackville J set aside both the decision to seek a direction, and the direction, on the ground referred to in s 5(1)(d) of the ADJR Act , apparently on the basis that his Honour had foreshadowed in the first judgment at [43]-[51]. This was that both the registrar and the judge had taken into account other documents previously filed by the same applicant, whereas O 46 r 7A requires that the originating process "appears...on its face to be an abuse of the process of the Court or to be frivolous or vexatious."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Altman and Family Court of Australia (1992) 27 ALD 369</tocase>
<text>69 In Loughnan (Principal Registrar, Family Court of Australia) v Altman [1992] FCA 580 ; (1992) 39 FCR 90 , the Full Court dealt with an appeal from a decision of the Tribunal, constituted by its then President, O'Connor J, in Re Altman and Family Court of Australia (1992) 27 ALD 369. Her Honour had reached the conclusion that an unrevised transcript of reasons for judgment pronounced in open court by a judge of the respondent was a document that the respondent was required to give access to under s 5 of the FOI Act . Because the unrevised transcript was produced by the agency responsible for providing transcript of court proceedings, the case turns largely on the meaning of the expression "a document of the court" in s 5 , and is therefore of little relevance to the present case. In the course of the Full Court's judgment, at 95, the Court did approve the conclusion of O'Connor J that the unrevised transcript was not a document of an administrative nature. Clearly, the giving of reasons for judgment and the practice of revising the transcript of those reasons for publication as the reasons for judgment are at the very heart of the judicial process, and the ready availability of the unrevised transcript to the public could undermine the independence of the judiciary.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Re Bartucciotto and Guardianship and Administration Board [2004] WAICmr 16</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WAICmr/2004/16.html</AustLII>
<text>76 Counsel for the respondent also referred to two decisions of the Western Australian Information Commissioner, exercising powers under the Freedom of Information Act 1992 (WA), in Re Bartucciotto and Guardianship and Administration Board [2004] WAICmr 16 and Re Michael Bartucciotto and State Administrative Tribunal [2006] WAICmr 9. The legislation dealt within those cases also contained the words "relates to matters of an administrative nature", referring to documents of courts. At [41] of the first decision, the commissioner referred to a dictionary definition of the word "administrative", as meaning "concerning or relating to the management of affairs" and held that the relevant words were confined to documents relating to the management of the affairs of a court or tribunal. In the second decision at [100], the commissioner expanded on this view in the following terms:
 In my view, there is only a right of access under the FOI Act to documents relating to the management of the affairs and routine administrative activities of a court or tribunal, and not to documents relating to its judicial or adjudicative functions. The key distinction, in my opinion, is that documents that are created in the course of and for the purpose of particular matters dealt with by the agency in the exercise of its adjudicative functions under the various pieces of legislation which confer jurisdiction upon it are not documents "relating to matters of an administrative nature".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Re Michael Bartucciotto and State Administrative Tribunal [2006] WAICmr 9</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WAICmr/2006/9.html</AustLII>
<text>76 Counsel for the respondent also referred to two decisions of the Western Australian Information Commissioner, exercising powers under the Freedom of Information Act 1992 (WA), in Re Bartucciotto and Guardianship and Administration Board [2004] WAICmr 16 and Re Michael Bartucciotto and State Administrative Tribunal [2006] WAICmr 9. The legislation dealt within those cases also contained the words "relates to matters of an administrative nature", referring to documents of courts. At [41] of the first decision, the commissioner referred to a dictionary definition of the word "administrative", as meaning "concerning or relating to the management of affairs" and held that the relevant words were confined to documents relating to the management of the affairs of a court or tribunal. In the second decision at [100], the commissioner expanded on this view in the following terms:
 In my view, there is only a right of access under the FOI Act to documents relating to the management of the affairs and routine administrative activities of a court or tribunal, and not to documents relating to its judicial or adjudicative functions. The key distinction, in my opinion, is that documents that are created in the course of and for the purpose of particular matters dealt with by the agency in the exercise of its adjudicative functions under the various pieces of legislation which confer jurisdiction upon it are not documents "relating to matters of an administrative nature".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re O'Sullivan and Family Court of Australia (1997) 47 ALD 765</tocase>
<text>70 Loughnan has since been discussed in a couple of decisions of the Tribunal. In Re O'Sullivan and Family Court of Australia (1997) 47 ALD 765 , Senior Member Dwyer dealt with a case in which access was sought to the handwritten notes of a Family Court counsellor. In her reasons, the learned senior member discussed Loughnan in the context of determining whether the counsellor's notes were documents of the court. Having concluded that they were, at [25] the senior member found that the notes were not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature, because of the professional duties of the counsellor. It is unnecessary to decide in the present case whether that conclusion was correct. In Re Simring and High Court of Australia [2006] AATA 849 (2006) 44 AAR 103 , Deputy President Walker dealt with a request for access to a document created in the course of dealing with an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court. The learned deputy president took the view that, because the document had been brought into existence within the chambers of a judge, as part of the judicial deliberative process, it was a judicial document, and not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature. The deputy president regarded Loughnan as not in point. At [19], the deputy president referred to the words "relates to matters of an administrative nature" in s 5 of the FOI Act in the following terms:
 The language used is relatively flexible and focuses on the general nature of the document rather than on the presence in the document of any administrative features whatever, however insignificant they might be in relation to the document's general nature. Even if the document in issue dealt incidentally with some administrative matters, and there is no evidence that it does, that would not necessarily detract from its overall quality as a document pertaining to the judicial role of the Court rather than to its administrative organisation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Simring and High Court of Australia [2006] AATA 849 (2006) 44 AAR 103</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2006/849.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Loughnan has since been discussed in a couple of decisions of the Tribunal. In Re O'Sullivan and Family Court of Australia (1997) 47 ALD 765 , Senior Member Dwyer dealt with a case in which access was sought to the handwritten notes of a Family Court counsellor. In her reasons, the learned senior member discussed Loughnan in the context of determining whether the counsellor's notes were documents of the court. Having concluded that they were, at [25] the senior member found that the notes were not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature, because of the professional duties of the counsellor. It is unnecessary to decide in the present case whether that conclusion was correct. In Re Simring and High Court of Australia [2006] AATA 849 (2006) 44 AAR 103 , Deputy President Walker dealt with a request for access to a document created in the course of dealing with an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court. The learned deputy president took the view that, because the document had been brought into existence within the chambers of a judge, as part of the judicial deliberative process, it was a judicial document, and not a document relating to matters of an administrative nature. The deputy president regarded Loughnan as not in point. At [19], the deputy president referred to the words "relates to matters of an administrative nature" in s 5 of the FOI Act in the following terms:
 The language used is relatively flexible and focuses on the general nature of the document rather than on the presence in the document of any administrative features whatever, however insignificant they might be in relation to the document's general nature. Even if the document in issue dealt incidentally with some administrative matters, and there is no evidence that it does, that would not necessarily detract from its overall quality as a document pertaining to the judicial role of the Court rather than to its administrative organisation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Valente v The Queen [1985] 2 SCR 673</tocase>
<text>63 In [53] of his Honour's reasons, Gleeson CJ referred to judgments of the Supreme Court of Canada and the Constitutional Court of South Africa, and cited the reference to "matters of administration bearing directly on the exercise of [the] judicial function" from Valente v The Queen [1985] 2 SCR 673 at 708. His Honour then said:
 The adjudicative function of a court, considered as an institution, was seen as comprehending matters such as the assignment of judges, sittings of the court and court lists, as well as related matters of allocation of court-rooms and direction of the administrative staff engaged in carrying out that function. Judicial control over such matters was seen as an essential or minimum requirement for institutional independence. The distinction between adjudicative and administrative functions drawn in the context of discussions of judicial independence is not clear cut. Nevertheless, the powers conferred by s 10 of the Magistrates Act include powers that fall squarely within the rationale of the immunity in question.

64 Gleeson CJ therefore held that the words "under an Act" in s 21A of the Magistrates Act applied to the functions and powers given to the Chief Magistrate by s 10. Accordingly, s 30 of the Criminal Code was applicable to them and the appeal should be allowed.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>