<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Fesl v Delegate of the Native Title Registrar [2008] FCA 1469 (1 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1469.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2005] FCA 1707 ; (2005) 148 FCR 446</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1707.html</AustLII>
<text>44 As Weinberg J observed in Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2005] FCA 1707 ; (2005) 148 FCR 446 at 587, [577] , s 5(3)(a) of the AD(JR) Act "seems merely to restate the doctrine of jurisdictional fact". Where the material "jurisdictional fact" is a state of administrative satisfaction that does not leave much scope for the operation of s 5(3)(a). When one recalls the impact of the use of the word "considers" in relation to the "second condition" for which s 24CL provides and that it is evident from the Delegate's reasons that she "considered" that the second condition was satisfied, the "particular matter" to which s 5(3)(a) of the AD(JR) Act refers is, in that language of that paragraph, "established".

45 In Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia , Weinberg J also offered (148 FCR at 587, [578]), a succinct summary of the views expressed by Black CJ (with whom Spender and Gummow JJ agreed) in Curragh Queensland Coal Mining Ltd v Daniel [1992] FCA 44 ; (1992) 34 FCR 212 in what has become a seminal judgment as to the effect of s 5(3)(b) of the AD(JR) Act. It was there held that s 5(3)(b) could only be satisfied if:
 
&#8226; the decision was "based on" the existence of a "particular fact", meaning a fact that was "critical to the making of the decision";
 
&#8226; there was no evidence or other material to support the finding of that particular fact; and
 
&#8226; it could be shown that the particular fact did not exist.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>33 As a matter of construction, the use of the verb "considers" in s 24CL(3) has the effect of placing that subsection within "that category of laws whose operation is made conditional upon the opinion or satisfaction as to certain matters of a designated authority or person, with the consequence that the merits of the matter are not examinable upon judicial review": The Australian Heritage Commission v Mount Isa Mines Ltd [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297 , at 303. As the High Court found in that case (ibid), the word "considers" was used to that end in the legislation then under consideration. Later, in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650, [127] et seq, Gummow J, who had been a member of the Full Court which delivered the unanimous joint judgement in The Australian Heritage Commission Case , comprehensively analysed this type of statutory provision and the amenability of decisions made thereunder to judicial review. In the course of that analysis, Gummow J drew attention (at 653-654, [136]) to the following remarks made by Gibbs J (as his Honour then was) in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 , at 118-119 in relation to the judicial review of a "satisfaction" based decision:
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. 
After citing this passage, Gummow J added (at 654, [137]):
 
 
 137. This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1901.html</AustLII>
<text>41 A decision to register an agreement which was not an ILUA would be no decision under s 24CJ of the Native Title Act at all: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj (2002) 209 CLR 597 at 614-615, [51] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ. Contrary to the submission of QWI, a challenge on such a ground is quite different to a challenge on an alleged error of law said to arise in the failure of an administrative decision-maker to find a fact, which is not a "jurisdictional fact", where such a finding was never sought before the decision-maker and where its materiality is asserted for the first time on "appeal" or judicial review. Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157 at 175-176, [86] [90] and the authorities there discussed by Carr J highlight the difficulty of contending that such a failure is an error of law but such cases are quite different from one where the power to register is only exercisable if what is presented for registration is indeed an ILUA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1980-1981) 147 CLR 297</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/26.html</AustLII>
<text>60 The symmetry of language "hold or may hold" in the paragraphs of s 251A and s 24CG(3)(b) is striking, as are the references in s 251A to "authorise" and "indigenous land use agreement". It seems to me that this is one of those cases where the draftsman has made a mistake and that it is permissible to construe the reference in the preamble to s 251A to "persons holding native title" as if it read "persons holding or who may hold native title": Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1980-1981) 147 CLR 297. I therefore consider that the assumption made by the Applicants and QWI in relation to s 251A was not misplaced.

61 The findings of fact made by the Delegate were such that para (a) of s 251A of the Native Title Act had no application.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Curragh Queensland Coal Mining Ltd v Daniel [1992] FCA 44 ; (1992) 34 FCR 212</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/44.html</AustLII>
<text>45 In Australian Retailers Association v Reserve Bank of Australia , Weinberg J also offered (148 FCR at 587, [578]), a succinct summary of the views expressed by Black CJ (with whom Spender and Gummow JJ agreed) in Curragh Queensland Coal Mining Ltd v Daniel [1992] FCA 44 ; (1992) 34 FCR 212 in what has become a seminal judgment as to the effect of s 5(3)(b) of the AD(JR) Act. It was there held that s 5(3)(b) could only be satisfied if:
 
&#8226; the decision was "based on" the existence of a "particular fact", meaning a fact that was "critical to the making of the decision";
 
&#8226; there was no evidence or other material to support the finding of that particular fact; and
 
&#8226; it could be shown that the particular fact did not exist.

46 The views expressed in Curragh Queensland Coal Mining in relation to s 5(3)(b) of the AD(JR) Act were cited with approval by various members of the High Court in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajamanikkam (2002) 210 CLR 210 at 234. [33] per Gleeson CJ; at 257-258, [115] [118] per Kirby J; at 267, [140] per Callinan J.

47 Grounds 1(a), 1(c), 1(e) and 1(f) each seek to challenge the opinion of the Delegate that the "second condition" was met.

48 The Delegate's reasons reveal that she came to consider whether the "second condition" was met under two headings "Were 'all reasonable efforts' made?" and "Authorisation (s 24CG(3)(b)(ii))". In this commendably focussed fashion, the Delegate expressly directed herself to the very subjects consideration of which s 24CL(3) of the Native Title Act required, i.e. whether the twofold requirements of s 24CG(3)(b) were met. Again recalling the impact of the verb "considers" in s 24CL(3) , what that subsection required in this regard was the making of a value judgement by the Delegate on the basis of the material before her.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/7.html</AustLII>
<text>39 The Delegate was perfectly entitled, as a matter of good public administration, to reach a preliminary view about whether the agreement presented with the application was an ILUA, but the decision to register the same necessarily carried with it the maintenance of that preliminary view that the agreement was an ILUA. For it was only such an agreement that the Delegate was empowered to register. The only decision which falls to the Registrar (or a delegate) to make under Subdiv C of Div 3 of Pt 3 of the Native Title Act which has the requisite quality of statutory provision and affectation of legal rights to make it a "decision" for the purposes of the AD(JR) Act is a decision under s 24CJ as to whether or not to register an agreement on the Register: Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 , at 130-131, [89].

40 One permissible ground of review under s 5 of the AD(JR) Act is "that the decision was not authorized by the enactment in pursuance of which it was purported to be made" (s 5(1)(d)); another is "that the decision involved an error of law, whether or not the error appears on the record of the decision" (s 5(1)(f)); yet another is "that the decision was otherwise contrary to law" (s 5(1)(j)). Each or any of these grounds would be apt as a ground for the challenging, on the basis that it was not in law an ILUA, of what purported to be a decision by the Registrar under s 24CJ to register an agreement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Harrington-Smith v Western Australia (No 9) (2007) 238 ALR 1</tocase>
<text>69 In the course of his reasons for judgment in Harrington-Smith v Western Australia (No 9) (2007) 238 ALR 1 at 242-243, [1265] Lindgren J referred with approval to these observations of Stone J in Lawson's case stating:
 I agree with Stone J's statement in that case that the effect of s 251B is or may be to give the word 'all' in s 61 a more limited effect than it might otherwise have. In that case, however, there was evidence that all the claimants were given a reasonable opportunity to participate in the authorising process. Other judges have observed that notwithstanding the references to 'all' in s 61, it may be sufficient, at least in some cases, that applicants are authorised by a majority of the persons in the claim group (Moran v Minister for Land and Water Conservation for the State of New South Wales [1999] FCA 1637 at [40] ), or all of those whose whereabouts are known and have capacity to authorise (Quall v Risk [2001] FCA 378 at [33] ), or '"all" those who are reasonably available and who are competent to express an opinion' (De Rose FCA/O'Loughlin at [928])." (Internal case citations where not given by his Honour in passage quoted not reproduced).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Kemp v Native Title Registrar [2006] FCA 939 ; (2006) 153 FCR 38</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/939.html</AustLII>
<text>59 Both the Applicants' and QWI's submissions proceeded upon the assumption that it was s 251Athat fell for consideration in relation to "authorisation". The explanation given to cl 24CG(3)(b) in the explanatory memorandum to the Native Title Amendment Bill 1997 which, after further amendments not presently relevant were incorporated, became the Native Title Amendment Act 1998 (Cth), which inserted s 24CG and s 251A into the Native Tile Act , makes reference to "potential native title holders" and also makes reference to cl. 251A as supplying the method of authorisation. Finally, in Kemp v Native Title Registrar [2006] FCA 939 ; (2006) 153 FCR 38 , which was a case where the native title group included those who were but potential native title holders, Branson J and all parties to that case evidently proceeded upon the assumption that s 251A fell for consideration in relation to the authorisation of an ILUA.

62 The Applicants advanced a submission based on the proposition that s 251A was premised on the existence of a single community or other group and that the section could not apply if the community or group were not established on the evidence. Support for this submission was said to be found in the reasons for judgment of Branson J in Kemp v Native Title Registrar [2006] FCA 939 ; (2006) 153 FCR 38. It is true that, in that case, her Honour opined (at 47, [41]):
 
 
 41 Section 251A is not intended to provide, and does not provide, a means whereby a single authorising decision can be obtained which is binding on two or more groups where their respective claims to hold native title in an area are in conflict. This can be seen from the reference in paragraph (a) to a process of decision-making that, under the traditional laws and customs of the persons who hold or may hold the common or group rights comprising the native title, must be complied with in relation to authorising things of that kind. It is hard to imagine any such process of decision-making where the respective claims of two groups to hold the native title are in conflict; it would require traditional laws and customs in relation to jointly authorising things binding on the members of both groups.

63 The difficulty for the Applicants is that, as already noted, the Delegate found that Kabi Kabi, Gubbi Gubbi and other variant spellings were ways of naming one broader group of related persons who, together, assert native title interests in relation to the project area. That finding was open on the material before her. Kemp's case was decided against the different background of there being conflicting claimant groups, not one group in which there happened to be differing views. Kemp's case is thus distinguishable.

64 A noteworthy feature of Kemp's case is that it is not apparent that any of the parties drew her Honour's attention to a body of authority which had developed in relation to s 251B of the Native Title Act , which makes provision in terms analogous to those of s 251A for how "authorisation" by a "native title claim group" of a native title determination application or a compensation application or dealing with matters relating to the same is to occur. QWI referred me to certain of these authorities, one decided before Lawson's case, the other afterwards but which made reference to prior authority. This was in support of its submission that, on the evidence before her, the Delegate's finding that due "authorisation" of the Traveston Dam Agreement by the native title group had occurred was one open in law for her to reach.

65 A consideration of the authorities concerned is assisted by setting out the material provisions in the Native Title Act . Section 251B provides:
 251B Authorising the making of applications For the purposes of this Act, all the persons in a native title claim group or compensation claim group authorise a person or persons to make a native title determination application or a compensation application, and to deal with matters arising in relation to it, if: 
 
 (a) where there is a process of decision-making that, under the traditional laws and customs of the persons in the native title claim group or compensation claim group, must be complied with in relation to authorising things of that kind--the persons in the native title claim group or compensation claim group authorise the person or persons to make the application and to deal with the matters in accordance with that process; or 
 (b) where there is no such process--the persons in the native title claim group or compensation claim group authorise the other person or persons to make the application and to deal with the matters in accordance with a process of decision-making agreed to and adopted, by the persons in the native title claim group or compensation claim group, in relation to authorising the making of the application and dealing with the matters, or in relation to doing things of that kind.

66 Section 253 of the Native Title Act defines a "native title claim group" thus:
 native title claim group means: 
 
 (a) in relation to a claim in an application for a determination of native title made to the Federal Court--the native title claim group mentioned in relation to the application in the table in subsection 61(1); or
 (b) in relation to a claim in an application for an approved determination of native title made to a recognised State/Territory body--the person or persons making the claim, or on whose behalf the claim is made.

73 The facts of this case make it unnecessary to decide whether and to what extent principles to be distilled from cases concerning s 251B are congruent with all of the observations made by Branson J in Kemp's case in relation to s 251A.

74 What is clear, having regard to the analogies to be drawn in relation to s 251A(b) from the case law in relation to s 251B(b) , is that the process which led up to the so-called "authorisation meeting" of 11 August 2007 was lawful, as was the process of decision-making at that meeting. The non-participation or, as the case may be, dissent of the Applicants did not affect the validity of the authorisation decision which was made in respect of the making of the Traveston Dam Agreement. There was evidence before the Delegate by reference to which she was entitled to conclude that the authorisation decision had been duly made and that each of the Applicants had been given a reasonable opportunity to participate in the adoption of a decision-making process and in the decision-making process itself.

75 There is no merit in grounds 1(a), 1(c), 1(e) and 1(f) of the application.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Lawson on behalf of the 'Pooncarie Barkandji (Paakantyi) People) v Minister for Land &amp; Water Conservation (NSW) [2002] FCA 1517</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1517.html</AustLII>
<text>68 In Lawson on behalf of the 'Pooncarie Barkandji (Paakantyi) People) v Minister for Land &amp; Water Conservation (NSW) [2002] FCA 1517 , Stone J made reference to the unfortunately not uncommon experience of internal disputes in a native title claim group interfering with the progress of a native title claim. She cited examples of this experience drawn from earlier cases. The case before her Honour was one where there was no relevant traditional decision-making process capable of dealing with the decisions that needed to be made to progress the claim and to resolve the problem of who was to represent the native title claim group. At issue in Lawson's case was whether a decision-making process adopted in the absence of a traditional decision-making process had resulted in a valid "authorisation" in terms of s 251B of the Native Title Act . Her Honour made the following observations in relation to s 251B: 
 
 
 25 As indicated above, s 251B specifies what is required to establish that 'all the persons in a native title claim ... authorise a person or persons to make a native title determination application' (original emphasis). The effect of the section is to give the word 'all' a more limited meaning than it might otherwise have. If there is no traditional process of decision-making 'in relation to authorising things of that kind' then, in accordance with s 251B(b) , authorisation in accordance with a process of decision-making 'agreed to and adopted, by the persons in the native title claim group' is sufficient. In s 251B(b) there is no mention of 'all' and, in my opinion the subsection does not require that "all" the members of the relevant claim Group must be involved in making the decision. Still less does it require that the vote be a unanimous vote of every member. Adopting that approach would enable an individual member or members to veto any decision and may make it extremely difficult if not impossible for a claimant group to progress a claim. In my opinion the Act does not require such a technical and pedantic approach. It is sufficient if a decision is made once the members of the claim group are given every reasonable opportunity to participate in the decision-making process.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985-1986) 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>76 The review ground of an improper exercise of a power in the making of a decision for which s 5(1)(e) of the AD(JR) Act provides may, inter alia, be established by the taking of an irrelevant consideration into account in the exercise of that power (s 5(2)(a) AD(JR) Act) or by a failure to take into account in the exercise of that power a relevant consideration (s 5(2)(b) AD(JR) Act). A consideration will be "relevant" or, as the case may be, "irrelevant" if the legislation concerned either expressly or by necessary implication either requires or, as the case may be, forbids it to be taken into account by a administrative decision-maker in the making of a decision: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985-1986) 162 CLR 24 at 39-40.

77 Section 24CL of the Native Title Act makes provision for registration of an agreement only if particular conditions are satisfied, and forbids registration if they are not. The conditions for which s 24CL provides are "relevant considerations". Of those conditions, what is made "relevant", so far as the "second condition" is concerned, is that the Registrar (or a delegate) considers that the requirements of s 24CG(3)(b) are met. In turn, in considering that question, it is s 24CG(4) which supplies matters which are "relevant". For reasons which I have already given when discussing the statutory scheme, whether the requirements of s 24CG(3)(b) were in fact met is not a "relevant consideration" in the exercise of the power to register an area agreement.

78 I have already noted that the conditions in s 24CL are imposed in respect of what is an "agreement" for the purposes of Subdiv C of Div 3 of Pt 2 of the Native Title Act and that it is only such an "agreement" that the Registrar (or a delegate) is empowered under s 24CJ to register. In my opinion, it necessarily follows that whether the application concerns such an "agreement" is also a "relevant consideration".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj (2002) 209 CLR 597</tocase>
<text>41 A decision to register an agreement which was not an ILUA would be no decision under s 24CJ of the Native Title Act at all: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj (2002) 209 CLR 597 at 614-615, [51] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ. Contrary to the submission of QWI, a challenge on such a ground is quite different to a challenge on an alleged error of law said to arise in the failure of an administrative decision-maker to find a fact, which is not a "jurisdictional fact", where such a finding was never sought before the decision-maker and where its materiality is asserted for the first time on "appeal" or judicial review. Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157 at 175-176, [86] [90] and the authorities there discussed by Carr J highlight the difficulty of contending that such a failure is an error of law but such cases are quite different from one where the power to register is only exercisable if what is presented for registration is indeed an ILUA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/21.html</AustLII>
<text>33 As a matter of construction, the use of the verb "considers" in s 24CL(3) has the effect of placing that subsection within "that category of laws whose operation is made conditional upon the opinion or satisfaction as to certain matters of a designated authority or person, with the consequence that the merits of the matter are not examinable upon judicial review": The Australian Heritage Commission v Mount Isa Mines Ltd [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297 , at 303. As the High Court found in that case (ibid), the word "considers" was used to that end in the legislation then under consideration. Later, in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650, [127] et seq, Gummow J, who had been a member of the Full Court which delivered the unanimous joint judgement in The Australian Heritage Commission Case , comprehensively analysed this type of statutory provision and the amenability of decisions made thereunder to judicial review. In the course of that analysis, Gummow J drew attention (at 653-654, [136]) to the following remarks made by Gibbs J (as his Honour then was) in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 , at 118-119 in relation to the judicial review of a "satisfaction" based decision:
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. 
After citing this passage, Gummow J added (at 654, [137]):
 
 
 137. This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Noble v Mundraby, Murgha, Harris and Garling [2005] FCAFC 212</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/212.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Also relevant, so far as the meaning and effect of s 251B of the Native Title Act is concerned, is a decision of the Full Court, to which I was not referred by QWI: Noble v Mundraby, Murgha, Harris and Garling [2005] FCAFC 212 (North, Weinberg and Greenwood JJ). In that case (at [18]), the Full Court made the following remarks concerning s 251B: 
 Section 251B does not require proof of a system of decision-making beyond proof of the process used to arrive at the particular decision in question. The section accommodates a situation where a native title claim group agrees to follow a particular procedure for a particular decision even if other procedures are normally used for other decisions. Nor does s 251B require a formal agreement to the process adopted for the making of a particular decision. Agreement within the contemplation of s 251B may be proved by the conduct of the parties. There was evidence in this case that the claim group conducted itself at the meeting on the basis that it agreed to a vote by the members of the group to determine the question of authorisation. All persons present voted in favour of the motion. Nobody is recorded as leaving the meeting or refusing to vote or in any other way conducting to indicate dissent from the course adopted. There was thus evidence from the conduct of the claim group on which the primary judge could base his conclusion that the requirements of s 251B were satisfied.

71 The following may be distilled from these authorities concerning s 251B: 
 
(a) the effect of the s 251B is to give the word 'all' in, materially, the table which appears below s 61(1) a more limited meaning than it might otherwise have;
 
(b) in those cases where there is no relevant traditional decision-making process, s 251B does not mandate any one particular decision-making process, only that it be one that is agreed to and adopted by the persons in the native title claim group or compensation group;
 
(c) "agreed to and adopted by" imports the giving to all of those whose whereabouts are known and have capacity to authorise a reasonable opportunity to participate in the adoption of a particular process and the making of decisions pursuant to that process;
 
(d) unanimous decision-making is not mandated;
 
(e) agreement to a particular process may be proved by the conduct of the parties even in the absence of proof of a formal agreement.

72 Section 251A plays an identical role in relation to native title group "authorisation" decisions as referred to in s 24CG(3)(b)(ii) to that which s 251B plays in relation to native title claim group "authorisation" decisions under s 61 of the Native Title Act . The language employed in s 251A compared to that in s 251B is very similar and each gives content to the word "authorise" in a provision in which the word "all" appears in relation to the making of "authorisation" decisions. The analogy of application between the two sections is indeed a close one. In my opinion therefore, each of the propositions which I have distilled from cases concerning s 251B has like application, mutatis mutandis , to the meaning and effect of s 251A and in relation to the impact of that section on "authorisation" for the purposes of s 24CG(3)(b)(ii) of the Native Title Act . In turn that means that the Delegate was entitled to conclude that the "second condition" for which s 24CL of the Native Title Act provides was satisfied.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>R v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal; ex parte Hardiman [1980] HCA 13 ; (1980) 144 CLR 13</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/13.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Given that QWI was an active contradictor, the Delegate properly took the stance of abiding the order of the court and not wishing to be heard save if need be in respect of costs: R v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal; ex parte Hardiman [1980] HCA 13 ; (1980) 144 CLR 13 , at 17, 35-36.

12 For the reasons which follow, I have concluded that the various grounds upon which, by their amended application, the Applicants sought the judicial review of the agreement registration decision do not lead to the result that the decision should be set aside. Work done under the Traveston Dam Agreement is therefore a valid future act for the purposes of the Native Title Act .

13 The grounds of review which came to be advanced by the Applicants are set out below:
 
 
 1. The First Respondent erred in law and/or improperly exercised the power conferred upon her in finding that the requirements of Section 24CG(3)(b) of the Native Title Act had been satisfied in circumstances where: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) There was no evidence from which the First Respondent could reasonably be satisfied that the Gubbi Gubbi People and the Kabi Kabi People were part of the same wider group;
 (b) The First Respondent failed to take into account the following relevant considerations in reaching the conclusion that the Gubbi Gubbi People and the Kabi Kabi People were part of the same wider group: 
 
 
(i) That membership of the Gubbi Gubbi People was based on matrilineal descent from the apical ancestors James Crowe and Maggie Palmer whereas membership of the Kabi Kabi People was based on cognatic descent from a number of apical ancestors in addition to James Crowe and Maggie Palmer; and (ii) That the Gubbi Gubbi People have a mandatory traditional decision making process in relation to matters affecting land involving the reaching of a consensus decision by the Elders of the respective family groups within the clan without recourse to a majority vote of the group as adopted by the Kabi Kabi People when purporting to authorise the ILUA. 
 
 
 (c) There was no evidence from which the First Respondent could reasonably be satisfied that the Gubbi Gubbi People did not adhere to a mandatory traditional decision making process as aforesaid;
 (d) The First Respondent failed to take into consideration the fact that the Gubbi Gubbi People both before and at the authorisation meeting disputed the decision making process adopted at the authorisation meeting and did not authorise the making of the ILUA;
 (e) The First Respondent concluded that there was no mandatory traditional decision making process applicable to the subject decision in reliance upon evidence that emanated from persons who where no traditional custodians of such information;
 (f) There was no evidence from which the First Respondent could reasonably have concluded that the Gubbi Gubbi People withdrew from the agreement making process;
 (g) The evidence showed that the Gubbi Gubbi People were not afforded the opportunity to separately consider the terms of the ILUA in accordance with the their mandatory traditional decision making process, in circumstances where the persons said to hold native title where encompassed by three separately represented constituent groups;
 (h) By reason of the matters referred to in paragraphs 1(a) (g) hereof the Applicants are not bound by the Kabi Kabi Peoples authorisation decision and did not themselves authorise the meeting of the ILUA. 
 
 
 
 
 2. The First Respondent erred in law and/or improperly exercise the power conferred on her in: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) Limiting her registration decision to the criteria set out in Section 24CL of the Native Title Act ; 
 (b) Failing to consider or properly consider whether the ILUA was an area agreement that complied with the requirements of Sections 24CB and 24CE of the Native Title Act . 
 (c) Failing to find that the Cultural Heritage Investigation Management Agreement ("the CHIMA") component of the ILUA contravened the provisions of the ACHA and so by reason of Section 24CE of the Native Title Act , that the ILUA was invalid either in whole or in part and was thereby no an area agreement capable of being registered. 
 (d) Failing to find that the CHIMA component of the ILUA in so far as it dealt with the regulation of Cultural Heritage matters over land where Native Title rights had been extinguished was no properly the subject matter of an area agreement pursuant to Section 24CB of the Native title Act and thereby the ILUA was not an area agreement capable of being registered. 
 
 
 
 Particulars 
 
 
 
 
 (a) The CHIMA regulates Aboriginal Cultural Heritage matters as defined in the ACHA over areas where Native Title rights have been extinguished; and 
 (b) To the extent that the ILUA deal with areas where Native Title rights have been extinguished: 
 
 
(i) The Aboriginal Party under the ACHA ought to have been a party to the ILUA as required by Section 23(3)(a)(iii) of the ACHA; (ii) The Aboriginal ILUA Parties did not have standing under the Native Title Act to enter into ILUA which purported to regulate Aboriginal Cultural Heritage matters over such areas; and (iii) It is not competent for an ILUA to deal with Cultural Heritage maters properly regulated by existing State legislation over land where Native Title rights do not exist.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>The Australian Heritage Commission v Mount Isa Mines Ltd [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/10.html</AustLII>
<text>33 As a matter of construction, the use of the verb "considers" in s 24CL(3) has the effect of placing that subsection within "that category of laws whose operation is made conditional upon the opinion or satisfaction as to certain matters of a designated authority or person, with the consequence that the merits of the matter are not examinable upon judicial review": The Australian Heritage Commission v Mount Isa Mines Ltd [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297 , at 303. As the High Court found in that case (ibid), the word "considers" was used to that end in the legislation then under consideration. Later, in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 650, [127] et seq, Gummow J, who had been a member of the Full Court which delivered the unanimous joint judgement in The Australian Heritage Commission Case , comprehensively analysed this type of statutory provision and the amenability of decisions made thereunder to judicial review. In the course of that analysis, Gummow J drew attention (at 653-654, [136]) to the following remarks made by Gibbs J (as his Honour then was) in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 , at 118-119 in relation to the judicial review of a "satisfaction" based decision:
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. 
After citing this passage, Gummow J added (at 654, [137]):
 
 
 137. This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>