<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLYK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1708 (12 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1708.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>8 In Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at pages 272-275, in the joint judgment of Brennan CJ and Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ, one finds a definitive exposition of the nature of the decision for which the Migration Act then and presently provides in relation to the granting of a protection visa. In that joint judgment, at pages 274 and 275, the following passage appears:
 it is inappropriate to describe a decision refusing refugee status as a decision not to determine that the person is a refugee. Rather, it is a decision that the Minister is not satisfied that the person has a genuine fear founded on a real risk of persecution. This is the 'decision' for which provision is made by the Act.

11 As was stated in the joint judgment in Wu Shan Liang at page 275, it is no longer the case that a decision as to satisfaction is unreviewable. Authorities at ultimate appellate level, and Wu Shan Liang at page 275 to 276 is an example, have emphasised remarks made by Gibbs J, as his Honour then was, in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at pages 118-119, in respect of the bases upon which a satisfaction based decision is amenable to judicial review. One basis adverted to by Gibbs J is that:
 if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu (1998/1999) [1999] HCA 21 ; 197 CLR 611</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/21.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Later, in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu (1998/1999) [1999] HCA 21 ; 197 CLR 611 at 647, paragraph 119 Gummow J remarked of s 65(1) of the Migration Act that that section:
 imposed on the Minister an obligation to grant or to refuse to grant a visa, rather than a power to be exercised at discretion. The Minister's satisfaction was an anterior matter, being a component of the condition precedent to the discharge of the obligation to grant or refuse the visa.

10 The references in the passages which I have quoted to the Minister, apply equally to the Tribunal, which under the Migration Act sits in the place of the Minister when conducting its merits review function.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>11 As was stated in the joint judgment in Wu Shan Liang at page 275, it is no longer the case that a decision as to satisfaction is unreviewable. Authorities at ultimate appellate level, and Wu Shan Liang at page 275 to 276 is an example, have emphasised remarks made by Gibbs J, as his Honour then was, in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at pages 118-119, in respect of the bases upon which a satisfaction based decision is amenable to judicial review. One basis adverted to by Gibbs J is that:
 if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it.

12 Having referred to this particular passage from Buck v Bavone in Eshetu's case, Gummow J, at page 654 para 137, observed of it that it was:
 consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question.

13 His Honour added:
 It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.

14 It is with these principles in mind that I approach consideration of ground 2 in the appeal. When one looks to the findings and reasons of the Tribunal, see pages 86 and 87 of the Appeal Book, one sees that the Tribunal came not to be satisfied that the Appellant was a person to whom Australia owed protection obligations under the Refugee Convention because of a view reached by the Tribunal as to the Appellant's credibility in relation to the claim which she made. The Tribunal referred to a lack of apparent knowledge of Falun Gong practice and belief on the part of the Appellant during her evidence at the hearing conducted by the Tribunal.

15 The Tribunal also referred to the Appellant's ability freely to travel to and from Singapore to the People's Republic of China on two and perhaps even three occasions. The Tribunal referred to this travel pattern as being inconsistent with a fear of persecution if the Appellant returned to China.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney General (New South Wales) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>17 I respectfully agree with everything stated by the Federal Magistrate in the passage which I have quoted. It is very important in a case like this for Magistrates, and in turn Judges on appeal, firmly to bear in mind the limits of judicial review. A principled restraint is called for. That proposition was stated and has frequently been emphasised thereafter in Attorney General (New South Wales) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35-36, per Brennan J, as his Honour then was. A hearing before the Tribunal in respect of an application for a protection visa is not an examination in theology. Nonetheless, in this particular case and bearing in mind the limits of reasonableness as a ground of challenge, and also inferences reasonably open in relation to the Appellant's travel pattern, the conclusions reached by the Tribunal were open. I discern no error in law in the Federal Magistrates Court so concluding.

18 That being the case, the appeal must be dismissed. 


 I certify that the preceding eighteen (18) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan. 


 Associate:

Dated: 14 November 2008

 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Sparke Helmore 

 Date of Hearing: 12 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 12 November 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1708.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>