<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Huang v University of New South Wales [2008] FCA 1930 (18 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1930.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>AB v Adult Multicultural Education Services [2006] VCAT 1862</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VCAT/2006/1862.html</AustLII>
<text>48 In order to determine whether the contact was sexual harassment within s 28A , regard must be had to all the circumstances. The test is an objective one that does not take into account the motivation of the perpetrator or the individual ( AB v Adult Multicultural Education Services [2006] VCAT 1862 at [19] ).

49 It is relevant that:
 
&#8226; This was an isolated incident.
 
&#8226; It took place in a corridor and was a movement in passing.
 
&#8226; Relations between Mr Huang and Professor Winder both before and after the alleged incident were confined to educational matters.
 
&#8226; No discomfort was apparent on Ms Huang's part in her dealings with Professor Winder after the alleged incident.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gauci v Kennedy [2007] FCA 1051</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1051.html</AustLII>
<text>50 Federal Magistrate Driver considered the evidence in relation to this allegation and rejected it. His Honour gave reasons for that finding. I see no error in his Honour's conclusion. A claim under s 28A must be analysed on the basis of the nature or quality of the act: see, for example, Gauci v Kennedy [2007] FCA 1051 at [22] . Irrespective of Ms Huang's present belief that the contact between Professor Winder's hand and her hip constituted sexual harassment, she has not shown that his Honour was in error in concluding (at [89]) that ' the contact that occurred between Professor Winder and Ms Huang was accidental and non-sexual as they passed in the corridor '.

51 Federal Magistrate Driver accepted the respondents' submission that there were two allegations of sexual harassment against Dr Markovic.

52 The first allegation, described by His Honour at [92], is that in 1999 when he was training a group of students he raised both his hands ' with lustfully laughing and moved towards Ms Huang with his arms outstretched '. Dr Markovic denied laughing lustfully and denied that he sexually harassed Ms Huang. None of the other students present gave evidence. Federal Magistrate Driver found that Ms Huang embellished this alleged incident over time. During cross-examination she added as part of the description that Dr Markovic said as he raised his hands ' I'll kill you ' or ' I would kill you '. Ms Huang conceded that Dr Markovic did not engage in any conduct that indicated a sexual interest in her.

53 His Honour concluded that whatever was said was intended as a joke and was not sexual in nature and was not conduct within s 28A(1)(a) or (b) of the Sex Discrimination Act .

54 The second allegation was that, at some time in late August or September 2001, Dr Markovic made a remark about Ms Huang's marital status. Dr Markovic denied making that remark. Another student present gave evidence and failed to corroborate the allegation. The Federal Magistrate accepted Dr Markovic's denial that he said anything about a need for sex on Ms Huang's part. On that aspect, Driver FM preferred Dr Markovic's evidence and the documentary evidence to Ms Huang's evidence. His Honour noted that one of the other students present at the time but who was not able to be available for cross-examination as he was overseas provided some support for Ms Huang's allegation that Dr Markovic made a comment about her marital status. His Honour found that, on the balance of probabilities, that Dr Markovic did make a comment about Ms Huang's age and marital status. An internal University investigation supported the allegation and Dr Markovic had been required to undergo counselling. Federal Magistrate Driver concluded that the remark was ' offensive and the remedy appropriate ' (at [101]).

55 However, his Honour accepted that the comment did not constitute sexual harassment within the meaning of s 28A of the Sex Discrimination Act , not being conduct of a sexual nature or pertaining to sexual activity or attraction or relationships. Accordingly, his Honour rejected the allegations of sexual harassment against Dr Markovic. Having rejected the allegations of sexual harassment against Dr Markovic and Professor Winder, Driver FM found at [104] that there was nothing to support any other alleged act of sex discrimination under the Sex Discrimination Act .

56 In her complaint to HREOC Ms Huang said that when Dr Markovic was talking about broken glass ' he raised his both hands and came to me like to catch me, but I stepped back and avoided the contact '. She also said that Dr Markovic sometimes talked about sex in front of male students and that he said on one occasion that she had not been married but needed sex and that she was over 30 near 40, but still had pimples on her face.

57 Ms Huang characterises the second incident as being a ' sexual comment about my marital status, my age and my sexual life that I was not married that I needed sex and I was over 30 but I still had pimples on my face, in which he suggested and induced the male students made sex relationship with me. ' This, she submits, constitutes sexual harassment.

58 Ms Huang raises a number of matters concerning her PhD in her amended notice of appeal under the heading of "sexual harassment". These were not the subject of complaint to HREOC under this heading and it is not clear how they constitute sexual harassment within the meaning of the Sex Discrimination Act . They relate to matters such as the provision of assistance and training, her research and the provision of computers.

59 Ms Huang also says in her amended notice of appeal that Dr Markovic indicated ' that [Dr Markovic] would compel obedience from me or conquer me for his sexual favours to me, his support of my PhD would be conditional upon my provision of sexual favours, he made sexual comments and induced his male students sexually harassed me '. She explains that when he said ' I'll kill you ' it meant that ' he would compel obedience from me or conquer me for his sexual favours to me '.

60 Ms Huang is adamant that Dr Markovic said ' I'll kill you '. Federal Magistrate Driver implicitly accepted at [95] that such a comment may have been made. His Honour noted, and Ms Huang repeats, that Dr Markovic did not engage in sexual harassment but indicated a sexual interest in her. She says in her amended notice of appeal that Dr Markovic ' did not touch me and did not (directly through his mouth) invite me for a social occasion '.

61 His Honour concluded that, in the circumstances, the conduct complained of was more likely to have been intended as a joke rather than being sexual in nature. While his Honour accepted that Dr Markovic laughed, and Ms Huang repeats that it was a ' lustful ' laugh, his Honour did not accept what was clearly a subjective interpretation of the laugh.

62 It is difficult to see how one can accurately describe a laugh as ' lustful ' or how that description by Ms Huang is sufficient to establish sexual harassment within the meaning of the Sex Discrimination Act .

63 Much of the detail raised by Ms Huang in support of her claim of sexual harassment by Dr Markovic involves her reading a sexual connotation into things that he said or wrote. For example, she says that his saying ' I'll kill you ' was a result of ' his playing sexual game with me ' and that ' Dr Markovic was so drunk of his sexual favours to me that he really wanted to 'kill' me, but he could not 'kill' me in front of people, and he would 'kill' me in some time after the talking. He would 'kill' me meant he would compel obedience from me or conquer me for his sexual favours to me, as he had known I was afraid and ran away from his sexual favours to me '. She also characterises any assistance given to her by Dr Markovic in her PhD programme as part of his ' sexual advance for sexual favours to me '.

64 Ms Huang says that any failure on Dr Markovic's part to support her, or any criticism of her work, was due to his sexual interest in her. As part of her case that Dr Markovic had made sexual advances to her, Ms Huang describes a series of reasons why he must have done so. She cites examples when he said to her things such as ' you are too hard on yourself ' and when he provided assistance to her. Suggestions by Dr Markovic that she should ' take it easy ' in her PhD, that she should learn from her mistakes, that she was expected to work under her own guidance and that it was up to her to determine and manage her time were all linked by Ms Huang to the question of provision by her of sexual favours to Dr Markovic.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Hall v A &amp; A Sheiban Pty Ltd [1989] FCA 72 ; (1989) 20 FCR 217</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1989/72.html</AustLII>
<text>36 Ms Huang does not contend that the Federal Magistrate was in error in his summary of the principles applicable to conduct in breach of s 28A(1)(b). His Honour recognised the breadth of actions that can constitute conduct of a sexual nature and that single incident could constitute a contravention of s 28A. He also considered the distinction, pointed out by Wilcox J in Hall v A &amp; A Sheiban Pty Ltd [1989] FCA 72 ; (1989) 20 FCR 217 at 247, that '[u] nwelcome sexual conduct may be insensitive, even offensive, but it does not necessarily constitute sexual harassment ', the latter suggesting repetition.

37 The allegation of sexual harassment made to HREOC against Professor Winder is that he touched Ms Huang's hip while passing her in a corridor in the second semester of 1999. The allegation against Professor Winder is described by Ms Huang in her documentation in the appeal as ' an upward affectionate stroking motion on hip ' constituting, she says, a sexual advance for sexual favours which in turn constitutes sexual harassment. Ms Huang confirms that the allegation of sexual harassment against Professor Winder consisted of a single incident late in 1999. In her Notice of Appeal, Ms Huang repeatedly describes the incident with Professor Winder and she also demonstrated his alleged action a number of times during her submissions. The description was in terms of touching of the hip with ' an upwards affectionate stroking motion on my hip, for his sexual advance for his sexual favours to me '.

38 Noting (at [82]) that Professor Winder had no recollection of the incident, Driver FM expressed concern about Ms Huang's evidence. Ms Huang waited more than two years before mentioning the incident and his Honour did not accept her explanation for the delay. His Honour also commented that Ms Huang had changed her account of the incident over time. As his Honour recorded at [87]:
 
 ... Ms Huang has changed and embellished her account of the incident over time. Her initial allegation in 2002 was that 'one day when I passed the passage from the printing room of the school he touched my hip'. In her 29 October 2004 affidavit she deposed that 'he stretched out his right arm towards me and touched me on the hip'. In her oral evidence Ms Huang said that Professor Winder had caressed her. Her submissions allege 'affectionate stroking' and give further details but such detailed recollection is inconsistent with Ms Huang's oral evidence that she did not see Professor's Winder's hand .

39 Federal Magistrate Driver accepted at [82] that an incident occurred and that there was some physical contact between Professor Winder and Ms Huang as they passed each other in the corridor but found nothing to establish that the incident complained of constituted sexual harassment within the meaning of s 28A of the Sex Discrimination Act . His Honour concluded that ' in all probability, the contact that occurred between Professor Winder and Ms Huang was accidental and non-sexual as they passed in the corridor ': at [89]. His Honour noted that the alleged incident did not apparently affect Ms Huang's dealings with Professor Winder after that time; equally significantly, Ms Huang did not allege that there was ever any other physical contact between her and Professor Winder.

40 Ms Huang alleges a number of consequences arising from the alleged sexual harassment by Professor Winder. Those consequences and the existence of them are dependent upon a finding that the single incident alleged against Professor Winder took place and constituted a breach of the Sex Discrimination Act .

41 Ms Huang alleges that Professor Winder ' made unwelcome sexual advance for sexual favours to me, engaged in unwelcome conduct of sexual nature in relation to me, and discriminated against me of a sexual nature in relation to my sex, his sexual favours to me, and his sexual harassment, that he treated me less favourably than other girls and the male students and that his support of my PhD, my progress of my PhD and the continuance of my PhD re-enrolment were conditional upon my provision of sexual favours '.

42 In the Notice of Appeal Ms Huang asserts that, had it not been for the sexual harassment she would have done certain things, such as change her supervisor from Dr Markovic to Professor Winder or not done certain things, such as sent him emails or given him a bottle of wine. She says that if she had intended to invent Professor Winder's actions, she would have suggested other contact. Ms Huang does not suggest that Professor Winder touched her at any other time. She says that she told Ms Frank that the touching of her hip was sexual harassment because ' he showed his sexual intention in me '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Huang v University of New South Wales &amp; Ors [2008] FMCA 11</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/11.html</AustLII>
<text>1 The appellant, Ms Huang, appeals from a decision of the Federal Magistrates Court dismissing her application against the first, second and third respondents: Huang v University of New South Wales &amp; Ors [2008] FMCA 11. The amended notice of appeal raises 61 grounds of appeal and extends to some hundreds of pages. Ms Huang has also filed submissions and an 'Issues Paper'. This is in addition to affidavit material filed in the appeal together with the extensive factual material that was before Driver FM. Despite my urging, Ms Huang seemed unable to reduce or simplify her contentions in any meaningful way. There was a lack of focus and much in the way of irrelevant and repetitive material that made it difficult to ascertain matters relevant to this appeal.

2 Federal Magistrate Driver expressed the difficulties he had in identifying the real issues in the mass of material filed and presented by Ms Huang. It is apparent that the case proceeded in the Federal Magistrates Court (as in this Court) in a way which was, as his Honour noted, ' exceptionally protracted, with far more material filed than was necessary or useful ' (at [63]).

3 I referred the matter to a Registrar of the Court for a case management conference in an attempt to isolate the issues in the appeal. By consent the following issues were elucidated: 
 Issue 1 Whether His Honour erred in not giving appropriate weight to the evidence submitted in the proceedings. Issue 2 Whether His Honour erred in not taking into account crucial evidence and took into account submissions that misinterpreted the evidence or were contrary to the relevant facts. Issue 3 Whether His Honour did not give sufficient time for the appellant to complete her cross-examination of the respondents' witnesses.

4 At the hearing of the appeal Ms Huang seemed to have great difficulty in confining herself to or directing her submissions to the issues that had been identified. She appeared in person and made her submissions in English. A Cantonese interpreter was present at all times to assist Ms Huang and to ensure that she understood everything that was being said and that she was able to present her submissions without the difficulty of not being able to think of a word or an expression.

5 Like Driver FM, I have addressed the issues that I have discerned from the material and submissions advanced by Ms Huang; I have also had the advantage of the Federal Magistrate's reasons and summary of the evidence before him.

6 The nature of Ms Huang's complaints and the factual background are well set out in the Federal Magistrate's reasons for judgment. As an introduction and background, His Honour explained:
 
 
 1. Hong Cui Huang is a former PhD student at the University of New South Wales ("the University"). She did not obtain her degree and holds the University and Dr Boban Markovic (her supervisor) and Professor Chris Winder (her co-supervisor) responsible. Ms Huang has applied to the Court under s.46PO of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act 1986 (Cth) ("the HREOC Act ") seeking compensation in relation to asserted sex, racial and disability discrimination which she believes frustrated her studies. The documentation filed by Ms Huang in support of the application is voluminous. Essentially, however, Ms Huang complains of sexual harassment in 1999 by Professor Winder and by Dr Markovic and alleges inappropriate comments by Dr Markovic in 2001. Ms Huang also makes sexual harassment allegations against two other persons who are not the subject of this present proceeding. 
 


 
 
 2. The application was amended in 2004 in order to add allegations of racial discrimination and disability discrimination in relation to the cancellation of Ms Huang's PhD enrolment. The racial discrimination is said to stem from Ms Huang's limited command of the English language. The disability discrimination is said to be based upon Ms Huang's asserted anxiety and depression. 
 


 
 
 3. Ms Huang made two relevant complaints to HREOC. The first complaint (of sexual harassment) was terminated by a delegate of the President of HREOC on 28 July 2003 pursuant to s.46PH of the HREOC Act . The complaint of sexual harassment against Dr Markovic was terminated on the basis that there was no reasonable prospect of a successful conciliation in relation to the alleged events in 2001 and in relation to the balance, the complaint was made more than 12 months after the alleged events took place. The complaint of sexual harassment by Professor Winder was terminated on the basis that the events took place more than 12 months before the complaint was made. 
 


 
 
 4. The second termination was made by a delegate of the President on 26 May 2004. This related to the complaints of racial discrimination and disability discrimination. The notice was issued pursuant to s.46PH of the HREOC Act on the basis that the complaints related to alleged events occurring more than 12 months before the complaints were made. 
 


 
 
 5. Ms Huang also alleged victimisation as a result of complaining of sexual harassment and also because of her complaints of racial and disability discrimination. [Federal Magistrate Driver] ruled that [he] had no jurisdiction to entertain the application insofar as it was based on the victimisation allegations [Huang v University of New South Wales &amp; Ors (No 2) [2006] FMCA 220 ] . However, [Federal Magistrate Driver] modified that ruling on 5 June 2006 upon the basis that Ms Huang had referred to alleged victimisation in her first complaint to HREOC, and, although HREOC had declined to accept a complaint of victimisation in later correspondence, Ms Huang was free to put a different legal characterisation on her complaint (which was terminated) than had been put on it by HREOC. [Federal Magistrate Driver] confirmed that [he] could not consider allegations of victimisation which post date the termination of the complaint. 
 


 
 
 6. The respondents deny any sexual harassment and deny any unlawful discrimination or victimisation.

7. Ms Huang gives extremely detailed particulars of her claims in a statement of particulars filed on 29 October 2004. She amended this statement by a statement of amended particulars filed in court by leave on 13 February 2006. Ms Huang relies upon ss.28A , 28F , 106 and 21 (2) of the Sex Discrimination Act 1984 (Cth) ("the SDA") in relation to the sexual harassment allegations.

8. Ms Huang asserts direct sex discrimination contrary to ss.5(1) , 21 (2)(a)(c) and 106 of the SDA by the University and Dr Markovic.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Obieta v New South Wales Department of Education and Training [2007] FCA 86</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/86.html</AustLII>
<text>110 Federal Magistrate Driver pointed out that victimisation is dealt with in s 94 of the Sex Discrimination Act . By s 94(2) victimisation for the purposes of the section concerns a person being subjected or threatened with detriment on the ground that they made or proposed to make a complaint under that Act or the HREOC Act or took steps in relation to HREOC. One or more of those matters must be a ' substantial and operative ' factor in the detriment to which Ms Huang was subjected or threatened with (see Obieta v New South Wales Department of Education and Training [2007] FCA 86 at [240] ). Ms Huang did not identify to Driver FM the detriment to which she alleged she was subjected or the acts referred to in s 94(2)(a) (g) of the Sex Discrimination Act , or the course that she took or proposed taking, or the knowledge that the first, second or third respondents had concerning those acts, or the connection between any of those acts and the detriment alleged. The Federal Magistrate pointed out at [122] that Ms Huang had not identified evidence of those matters. His Honour found, from the evidence, that Ms Huang first raised her allegations of sexual harassment at her meeting with Miss Nabke-Hatton on 22 March 2002 and that the respondents did not know of her allegations of unlawful discrimination before that date. His Honour found that there was no evidence that Ms Huang ever raised any assertion of unlawful discrimination before that time. By then her supervisors had already told her that they would not be supporting her re-enrolment.

111 Accordingly His Honour found that there was no unlawful victimisation under the Act.

112 Ms Huang's allegations of discrimination and harassment were considered as part of the decision-making process on her appeal against the cancellation of her enrolment. Federal Magistrate Driver found that these allegations did not appear to have been factors bearing on the decisions that were taken. In any event, the appeal resulted in Ms Huang being offered the opportunity to re-enrol.

113 While there were numerous communications between Ms Huang and the respondents prior to her complaint in March 2002, none could reasonably be interpreted as suggesting an intention to make a complaint within the meaning of s 94(2) of the Sex Discrimination Act (or, for that matter, s 27(2) of the Racial Discrimination Act 1975 (Cth) or s 42(2) of the Disability Discrimination Act 1992 (Cth)). Ms Huang raised the issue of sexual discrimination or disability discrimination after the rejection of the second submission of her literature review on 30 November 2001. The comments predicating the decision that Ms Huang not be permitted to remain as a PhD student were made by Dr Markovic on 31 December 2001 and by Professor Winder on 3 January 2002. That is, all relevant actions taken by Dr Markovic and Professor Winder, and through them the University, of which Ms Huang complains were taken prior to any suggestion of a complaint being made to HREOC or otherwise.

114 In her submissions Ms Huang describes as "victimisation" the attitude towards her during the course of her studies and prior to the decision made by the University that she not be permitted to re-enrol. It is clear from her written submissions that her description of 'victimisation' relates to the time before she first made an allegation to Miss Nabke-Hatton or to the University of sexual harassment, sexual discrimination or disability discrimination. She states in her written submissions that she asserted her complaint about the sexual harassment/discrimination prior to the termination of her PhD but there is no evidence supporting that assertion. The fact remains that, on the evidence, Ms Huang has not shown his Honour to have been in error in concluding that the decision to terminate her PhD preceded any allegation in relation to the Sex Discrimination Act , the Racial Discrimination Act or the Disability Discrimination Act . To the extent that Ms Huang refers to events that occurred after she gave notice of her complaints, it is difficult to identify the victimisation to which she says she was subjected. She has some complaint about the University's process in dealing with her PhD position but it is apparent that the University's decision-making process and consideration of her status as a PhD student were affected by the consideration of her capacity as a PhD student. They were not based on or relate to Ms Huang's complaints of sexual discrimination or harassment against Dr Markovic or Professor Winder.

115 Ms Huang has not established any error in Driver FM's conclusion that there was no unlawful victimisation. I reject, as his Honour did, the contention that there was.

116 Ms Huang has not shown that the Federal Magistrate was in error in dismissing her application or that his Honour erred in any legal, factual or procedural respect. She has not established any of her grounds of appeal. The appeal should be dismissed.

 I certify that the preceding one hundred and sixteen (116) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 

 Associate:

Dated: 18 December 2008

 The Appellant appeared in person. 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Ms J Oakley 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: University of New South Wales Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 9, 10, 13 October 2008 
 
 Date of Final Submissions: 23 October 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 December 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1930.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>