<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Tea Tree Oil Research Institute Ltd (in liq) v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1653 (14 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1653.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Brookton Co-operative Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/28.html</AustLII>
<text>204 In other words, one can look to the circumstances in which the subject entity was formed and the manner in which it is fulfilling the purposes for which it was incorporated, but there remains the issue of whether one can examine the subjective motives and intentions of the promoters of the subject entity and its directors for the purpose of ascertaining if the statutory exemption from income tax operates. In Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club 23 FCR at 98, Lockhart J referred to this issue by reference to the decision of the High Court in Brookton Co-operative Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441 where the ultimate issue was whether the taxpayer was a co-operative company within the meaning of s 117 of the ITAA 1936. One of the elements of the statutory definition was that the company 'is established for the purpose of carrying on any business having as its primary object or objects one or more of the following ... [objects]'.

211 The diversity of opinion in Brookton had previously been commented on by Ormiston J of the Supreme Court of Victoria in SSAU Nominees Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1985) 16 ATR 992 at 1011:
 'Here it is clear that all members of the court on each occasion [Brookton and Ruffy] held the view that the primary object or objects of the appellant's business could not be determined solely, or even initially, by reference to its memorandum of association, and that evidence of its history, setting up and activities, had to be examined. In this instance Mason J (at 453), with the concurrence of Wilson J, thought that the intentions, if not the motives, of the promoters could be looked at, although Aickin J strongly disagreed: at 463.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Business &amp; Research Management Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1652 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1652.html</AustLII>
<text>2 These appeals were heard immediately following the hearing of the appeals by Business and Research Management Limited (in liquidation) ('BARM'). Notwithstanding that the issues in these appeals are not coterminous with the issues in the BARM appeals, there is a possible common issue and they arise out of the same factual background, which is set out in [4] [41] of the reasons for judgment in Business &amp; Research Management Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1652. The roles of ATTORI and AARI as the researchers in the Budplan projects are referred to at various parts of that background. In particular, it is noted at [8(3)] that ATTORI was engaged to conduct research and development for all projects except for Budplan 'A' Series No. 1 and Personal Budplan No. 5, where AARI was engaged to conduct the research and development activities. Unless the context indicates otherwise, terms defined in the BARM reasons that are used in these reasons, have the same meaning.

3 While the issue in the BARM appeals concerned the quantum of the management fees to be brought to account as assessable income in the hands of BARM, the issue of the quantum of the research fees to be brought to account as assessable income in the hands of ATTORI or AARI only arises if the income of ATTORI or AARI is not exempt from income tax on the ground referred to below.

4 There is at least one, but possibly two issues before the Court.

227 This is the same issue that arose, was considered and decided in Business &amp; Research Management Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1652 in respect of the management fees. Here, it is in respect of the research fees, but it arises out of the same factual background.

228 While the arguments in the present case were not identical to those that were ventilated in the BARM case, they do traverse common ground. For the reasons given in that case, the applicants in the present case cannot succeed on this issue.

229 The applications must be dismissed with costs.

 I certify that the preceding two hundred and twenty-nine (229) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Edmonds. 


 Associate:

Dated: 14 November 2008


 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr AH Slater QC and Mr PM Fraser and Mr BL Jones 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: BWS Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr BJ Sullivan SC, Mr TM Thawley and Ms M Hirschorn 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 11 and 16 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 14 November 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1653.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Capital Club Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (2007) 66 ATR 606</tocase>
<text>214 SSAU Nominees involved a claim for a sales tax exemption for 'goods for use ... by a society, institution or organisation established and carried on exclusively or principally for the promotion of the interests of a university or school conducted by an organisation not carried on for the profit of an individual'. Some 17 years later, Mandie J of the Supreme Court of Victoria said in Capital Club Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (2007) 66 ATR 606 at [41]:
 'Ormiston J referred to Ruffy and Brookton noting that the High Court held the view that the primary object or objects of the company's business could not be determined solely or even initially by reference to its Memorandum of Association and that evidence of its history, setting up and activities had to be examined. The case otherwise turned on its own facts and the particular legislation.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 82</tocase>
<text>195 A more detailed and complete analysis of their Honours' respective reasons is given by Lockhart J presiding on a Full Court of this Court in Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 82 at 90 93; see too, Beaumont J at 111 113 and 117, and Foster J at 123.

201 See, also, Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club 23 FCR at 117 per Beaumont J.

202 In the Surgeons' Case , Starke J at 448 indicated that it was permissible to look outside the objects of the entity to its activities in determining whether the qualification for exemption was met, at least where the memorandum did not make it clear which objects of a mixed character are its main or dominating characteristics.

203 Williams J went further when, at 452, he observed:
 '[I]n order to determine what is the main or dominant purpose of the College, it is a mistake to examine the objects contained in the memorandum in ... [a] disjunctive fashion. They should be examined in conjunction with one another and in the light of the circumstances in which the College was formed and of the manner in which the College is fulfilling the purposes for which it was incorporated.'

204 In other words, one can look to the circumstances in which the subject entity was formed and the manner in which it is fulfilling the purposes for which it was incorporated, but there remains the issue of whether one can examine the subjective motives and intentions of the promoters of the subject entity and its directors for the purpose of ascertaining if the statutory exemption from income tax operates. In Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club 23 FCR at 98, Lockhart J referred to this issue by reference to the decision of the High Court in Brookton Co-operative Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441 where the ultimate issue was whether the taxpayer was a co-operative company within the meaning of s 117 of the ITAA 1936. One of the elements of the statutory definition was that the company 'is established for the purpose of carrying on any business having as its primary object or objects one or more of the following ... [objects]'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Word Investments Ltd (2007) 164 FCR 194 </tocase>
<text>196 While the ultimate issue in the present case is the same as it was in the Surgeons' Case , the real or substantive underlying issues are not. In the Surgeons' Case it was, according to Starke J at 447, '... rightly conceded, that the College was an institution'. And in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Word Investments Ltd (2007) 164 FCR 194 , Allsop J noted at [8] and [9] that there was no dispute that 'Word' was an institution; the only question was whether it was a 'charitable institution'. In the present case, there is a real issue as to whether ATTORI and AARI are institutions. As Gibbs CJ observed in Stratton v Simpson [1970] HCA 45 ; (1970) 125 CLR 138 at 158:
 'Although its meaning must depend on its context, [an institution] would not ordinarily connote a mere trust.'

199 Nevertheless, it is unnecessary to break the task up into component parts: Is it an institution? And if so, is it a scientific institution? Rather, as Allsop J said in Word Investments at [14]:
 'The relevant task, as stated in the Surgeons' Case [1943] HCA 34 ; 68 CLR 436 , is to assess the true character or nature of the entity by reference to its objects, purposes and activities. It is an integrated, holistic inquiry directed to whether a body of facts and circumstances satisfies a legal category or conception.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pamas Foundation (Inc) v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 154 ; (1992) 35 FCR 117</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/154.html</AustLII>
<text>197 The mere fact that ATTORI and AARI are companies limited by guarantee does not make them institutions; any more than the fact that they call themselves an 'Institute': see Pamas Foundation (Inc) v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 154 ; (1992) 35 FCR 117 at 125 per Beaumont and Lee JJ. As their Honours there said in the immediately preceding sentence:
 'The context in which the expression "religious institution" appears includes the juxtaposed term "public benevolent institution" which tends to suggest that the word "institution" is to be given a meaning greater than a structure controlled and operated by family members and friends.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Royal Australasian College of Surgeons v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1943] HCA 34 ; (1943) 68 CLR 436</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1943/34.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The relevant facts are not in dispute, although there is an issue as to what is relevant and what is not. It is common ground that facts going to: '[W]hat is the true nature and the objects and activities of the [entity]', to use the words of the Lord President (Clyde) in The Commissioner of Inland Revenue v The Aberdeen Medico-Chirurgical Society (1931) 16 TC 237 at 249 quoted with approval by Latham CJ in Royal Australasian College of Surgeons v Federal Commissioner of Taxation ('the Surgeons' Case ') [1943] HCA 34 ; (1943) 68 CLR 436 at 444, are relevant. But the Commissioner says that facts going to the commercial imperatives that drove both the entity's incorporation and its activities, as well as the arrangements through which, or the manner in which, it carries on its activities, and the lack of public availability or utility of the results of those activities, reflect on the 'true nature' of ATTORI and AARI and their activities and for that reason, are also relevant.

199 Nevertheless, it is unnecessary to break the task up into component parts: Is it an institution? And if so, is it a scientific institution? Rather, as Allsop J said in Word Investments at [14]:
 'The relevant task, as stated in the Surgeons' Case [1943] HCA 34 ; 68 CLR 436 , is to assess the true character or nature of the entity by reference to its objects, purposes and activities. It is an integrated, holistic inquiry directed to whether a body of facts and circumstances satisfies a legal category or conception.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SSAU Nominees Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1985) 16 ATR 992</tocase>
<text>211 The diversity of opinion in Brookton had previously been commented on by Ormiston J of the Supreme Court of Victoria in SSAU Nominees Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1985) 16 ATR 992 at 1011:
 'Here it is clear that all members of the court on each occasion [Brookton and Ruffy] held the view that the primary object or objects of the appellant's business could not be determined solely, or even initially, by reference to its memorandum of association, and that evidence of its history, setting up and activities, had to be examined. In this instance Mason J (at 453), with the concurrence of Wilson J, thought that the intentions, if not the motives, of the promoters could be looked at, although Aickin J strongly disagreed: at 463.'

214 SSAU Nominees involved a claim for a sales tax exemption for 'goods for use ... by a society, institution or organisation established and carried on exclusively or principally for the promotion of the interests of a university or school conducted by an organisation not carried on for the profit of an individual'. Some 17 years later, Mandie J of the Supreme Court of Victoria said in Capital Club Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (2007) 66 ATR 606 at [41]:
 'Ormiston J referred to Ruffy and Brookton noting that the High Court held the view that the primary object or objects of the company's business could not be determined solely or even initially by reference to its Memorandum of Association and that evidence of its history, setting up and activities had to be examined. The case otherwise turned on its own facts and the particular legislation.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Stratton v Simpson [1970] HCA 45 ; (1970) 125 CLR 138</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1970/45.html</AustLII>
<text>196 While the ultimate issue in the present case is the same as it was in the Surgeons' Case , the real or substantive underlying issues are not. In the Surgeons' Case it was, according to Starke J at 447, '... rightly conceded, that the College was an institution'. And in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Word Investments Ltd (2007) 164 FCR 194 , Allsop J noted at [8] and [9] that there was no dispute that 'Word' was an institution; the only question was whether it was a 'charitable institution'. In the present case, there is a real issue as to whether ATTORI and AARI are institutions. As Gibbs CJ observed in Stratton v Simpson [1970] HCA 45 ; (1970) 125 CLR 138 at 158:
 'Although its meaning must depend on its context, [an institution] would not ordinarily connote a mere trust.'

198 As Gibbs CJ further observed in Stratton v Simpson 125 CLR at 158:
 'In its ordinary sense "institution" means "an establishment, organization, or association, instituted for the promotion of some object, especially one of public utility, religious, charitable, educational etc." (The Shorter Oxford English Dictionary).' 
This suggests to me that before an entity can be a 'scientific institution', it must be established for an object or objects of public utility.

205 Gibbs CJ did not find it necessary to decide whether, in considering whether a company came within s 117(1) , the subjective motives and intentions of the promoters should be taken into account, although he said that it was clear that the court must consider the activities that the company actually carried on (at 445).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Commissioner of Inland Revenue v The Aberdeen Medico-Chirurgical Society (1931) 16 TC 237 </tocase>
<text>11 The relevant facts are not in dispute, although there is an issue as to what is relevant and what is not. It is common ground that facts going to: '[W]hat is the true nature and the objects and activities of the [entity]', to use the words of the Lord President (Clyde) in The Commissioner of Inland Revenue v The Aberdeen Medico-Chirurgical Society (1931) 16 TC 237 at 249 quoted with approval by Latham CJ in Royal Australasian College of Surgeons v Federal Commissioner of Taxation ('the Surgeons' Case ') [1943] HCA 34 ; (1943) 68 CLR 436 at 444, are relevant. But the Commissioner says that facts going to the commercial imperatives that drove both the entity's incorporation and its activities, as well as the arrangements through which, or the manner in which, it carries on its activities, and the lack of public availability or utility of the results of those activities, reflect on the 'true nature' of ATTORI and AARI and their activities and for that reason, are also relevant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Incorporated Council of Law Reporting of the State of Queensland v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1971] HCA 44 ; (1971) 125 CLR 659 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/44.html</AustLII>
<text>53 Importantly, proceeds from the 'commercialisation' of the Research Results were not to flow back to ATTORI to be re-invested for further scientific research in accordance with ATTORI's stated 'objects'. Rather, ATTORI was providing a service, as a part of a commercial scheme, to Participants and the Manager, who would be entitled to the proceeds of sale of the fruits of the research: cl 5. In other words, the proceeds derived from the fruits of ATTORI's research were intended 'to be diverted into the pockets of individuals': The Incorporated Council of Law Reporting of the State of Queensland v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1971] HCA 44 ; (1971) 125 CLR 659 at 672.
 Other Budplans for which ATTORI was appointed to conduct research in the relevant years

54 As well as the Budplan Personal Syndicate, ATTORI was also appointed to conduct research in the following Budplans:
 
(a) Personal Budplan No. 2 prospectus dated 3 June 1996
 
(b) Personal Budplan No. 3 prospectus dated 6 November 1996
 
(c) Personal Budplan No. 4 prospectus dated 16 April 1997
 
(d) Company Budplan No. 1 prospectus dated 8 May 1996
 
(e) Company Budplan No. 2 prospectus dated 3 June 1996
 
(f) Company Budplan No. 3 prospectus dated 26 May 1997
 
(g) Melaleuca Biotics Budplan project summary dated June 1996

55 It is apparent that a generic set of documents were used in relation to all of the abovementioned Budplans that were similar in nature to the Budplan Personal Syndicate Deed (although for these other Budplans there was a separate Management Agreement and Research Agreement rather than these being encompassed in one deed as was the case for the Budplan Personal Syndicate).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>