<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Medic-Care Company Ltd v Hamilton Pharmaceutical Pty Limited (ACN 008 204 635) (No 4) [2008] FCA 1038 (10 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1038.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Advanced Medical Institute Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1357 ; (2005) 147 FCR 235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1357.html</AustLII>
<text>8 There is now a considerable body of authority dealing with this provision although its proper application is not altogether free from difficulty. The first matter to emphasise about the exception in subs (3) is that it applies not to a document as such but to a representation or representations contained in a document. It is well accepted that the hearsay rule contained in s 69(2) is founded on the "rationale of reliability" of business records generally. The exception to that subsection is founded on a "rationale of unreliability" of representations made in the circumstances envisaged by subs (3): see generally Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Advanced Medical Institute Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1357 ; (2005) 147 FCR 235 at [27] . As Barrett J put the matter in Vitali v Stachnik [2001] NSWSC 303 at [12] :
 The purpose of the exclusion is ... to prevent the introduction through this exception to the hearsay rule of hearsay material which is prepared in an atmosphere or context which may cause it to be self-serving in the sense of possibly being prepared to assist the proof of something known or at least apprehended to be relevant to the outcome of identifiable legal proceedings.

10 The focus of the contemplation referred to in subs (3)(a) is, as Lindgren J indicated in the Advanced Medical Institute case, upon the contemplation of the person who "prepared" or "obtained" the relevant representation. As his Honour said at [25]-[27]:
 
 
 25. ... In order for s 69(3)(a) to apply, a person must have "prepared" or "obtained" the representation (not the document) in contemplation of a proceeding. It is an unusual use of language to refer to the "preparing" of a representation, but I think that the intention is clear enough; the reference is to the person who prepared, formulated, shaped or framed the terms in which the representation is made. This will typically, perhaps always, be or include the maker of the representation. 
 
 26. The person who "obtains" a representation is a person who seeks the representation or procures it to be made. This person is not the maker of the representation, but may be a person who "prepared" it.
 
 27. By referring to persons who prepared or obtained the representation, the legislature was attempting to encompass all those who might cause a representation to be made in the form which it takes.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vitali v Stachnik [2001] NSWSC 303</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/303.html</AustLII>
<text>8 There is now a considerable body of authority dealing with this provision although its proper application is not altogether free from difficulty. The first matter to emphasise about the exception in subs (3) is that it applies not to a document as such but to a representation or representations contained in a document. It is well accepted that the hearsay rule contained in s 69(2) is founded on the "rationale of reliability" of business records generally. The exception to that subsection is founded on a "rationale of unreliability" of representations made in the circumstances envisaged by subs (3): see generally Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Advanced Medical Institute Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1357 ; (2005) 147 FCR 235 at [27] . As Barrett J put the matter in Vitali v Stachnik [2001] NSWSC 303 at [12] :
 The purpose of the exclusion is ... to prevent the introduction through this exception to the hearsay rule of hearsay material which is prepared in an atmosphere or context which may cause it to be self-serving in the sense of possibly being prepared to assist the proof of something known or at least apprehended to be relevant to the outcome of identifiable legal proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Nikolaidis v Legal Services Commissioner [2007] NSWCA 130</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2007/130.html</AustLII>
<text>11 It is well established that before it can be said that a representation was prepared or obtained in contemplation of a proceeding, it must be established that a proceeding was "likely" or "reasonably probable": see Nikolaidis v Legal Services Commissioner [2007] NSWCA 130 at [61] and the cases there mentioned. The two questions which need to be determined for present purposes are, first, can it be said that legal proceedings were in contemplation and, second, if so, were they in the contemplation of the person or persons who prepared or obtained the relevant representations? For present purposes I am satisfied that representations contained in the documents which indicate that there were products purchased from retailers which did not contain AMC's insert in the packaging (ie products which were parallel imports) are at least presently relevant representations. As to the question whether legal proceedings were in contemplation at that time between AMC and Hamilton, I am not satisfied on the material before me such was the case. As I indicated above, the evidence does not suggest there was a likelihood or reasonable probability of legal proceedings at the relevant time. While the relationship of the parties at this time was undoubtedly tense, they had by then been in a long term relationship spanning 14 years. Such references as were made in correspondence to Hamilton's alleged responsibility to compensate AMC either for Dr Lam's success fee or for loss sustained by AMC from parallel importing could at best only be properly treated as reflecting a negotiating process between the parties at this stage.

12 When one turns to the contemplation of legal proceedings in Hong Kong, the situation is quite different. It is clear that from August 2002, as the investigation into parallel importing appeared to bear fruit in AMC's eyes, the prospect of taking proceedings against distributors and retailers was a very real one. Notwithstanding that AMC obviously was wishing to resolve disputes without resort to legal proceedings and the correspondence reflects this it also makes it perfectly plain that litigation was contemplated. It suggests that, by early September, proceedings were pending and on the evidence before me a writ had been issued by mid-October which, coincidentally, was the time at which the last group of documents in the bundle were referrable. For this reason I am prepared to infer that so far as Dr Keung and Dr Lam were concerned, legal proceedings throughout the time period covered by the business records in question were likely or reasonably probable against Hong Kong distributors and/or retailers involved in alleged parallel importing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Kang v Kwan [2002] NSWSC 1187</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2002/1187.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Those proceedings of course would not have involved Hamilton, ie it could not be said that the representations were made in contemplation of proceedings involving Hamilton and in which proceedings it was subsequently sought to have them tendered. In Kang v Kwan [2002] NSWSC 1187 Santow J, in a very brief passage in his judgment, held that the relevant misrepresentation must have been prepared or obtained in contemplation of the very proceedings in which the document is sought to be used. No reference was made by his Honour to authorities dealing with this question under either the Evidence Act or earlier similar provisions.

14 For my own part, I am satisfied that the decision of Santow J places an undue limitation upon the clear wording of s 69(3) and is inconsistent with the underlying purpose of the provision itself. Section 69(3) refers only to a proceeding without any limitation as to parties: see the observations of Hamilton J in Lewis v Nortex Pty Ltd (in liq) [2002] NSWSC 1083 at [4] (4).

15 The unreliability of evidence of representations made or prepared in a context which might cause the representation to be self serving is, in my view, as likely to exist whether or not the proceedings in contemplation was the one in which the representation was sought to be tendered. It is, in my view, unsurprising that the decision of Santow J has in this respect attracted criticism: see Odgers, Uniform Evidence Law (7 th ed) at [1.3.2880]. For my own part I am not prepared to follow the Kang v Kwan decision. I am satisfied that the legal proceedings in contemplation referred to in s 69(3) relate to any legal proceedings in which the representation might become admissible and is not confined to the proceedings in which the statement is sought to be tendered: cf Feltafield Pty Limited v Heidelberg Graphic Equipment (1995) 56 FCR 481 at [487A].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lewis v Nortex Pty Ltd (in liq) [2002] NSWSC 1083</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2002/1083.html</AustLII>
<text>14 For my own part, I am satisfied that the decision of Santow J places an undue limitation upon the clear wording of s 69(3) and is inconsistent with the underlying purpose of the provision itself. Section 69(3) refers only to a proceeding without any limitation as to parties: see the observations of Hamilton J in Lewis v Nortex Pty Ltd (in liq) [2002] NSWSC 1083 at [4] (4).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Feltafield Pty Limited v Heidelberg Graphic Equipment (1995) 56 FCR 481</tocase>
<text>15 The unreliability of evidence of representations made or prepared in a context which might cause the representation to be self serving is, in my view, as likely to exist whether or not the proceedings in contemplation was the one in which the representation was sought to be tendered. It is, in my view, unsurprising that the decision of Santow J has in this respect attracted criticism: see Odgers, Uniform Evidence Law (7 th ed) at [1.3.2880]. For my own part I am not prepared to follow the Kang v Kwan decision. I am satisfied that the legal proceedings in contemplation referred to in s 69(3) relate to any legal proceedings in which the representation might become admissible and is not confined to the proceedings in which the statement is sought to be tendered: cf Feltafield Pty Limited v Heidelberg Graphic Equipment (1995) 56 FCR 481 at [487A].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>