<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Reward Investment Alliance v Superannuation Complaints Tribunal [2008] FCA 1548 (23 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1548.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond (1990) 170 CLR 321</tocase>
<text>46 Sections 5, 6 and 7 of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1997 (Cth) make provision for persons, who are aggrieved by decisions, by conduct engaged in for the purpose of making decisions or by the failure to make decisions, to apply for orders of review in respect thereof. In that context, Mason CJ, with whose reasons Brennan and Deane JJ relevantly agreed, said in Australian Broadcasting Tribunal v Bond (1990) 170 CLR 321 at 341-342:
 'The distinction between reviewable decisions and conduct engaged for the purpose of making such a decision is somewhat elusive. However, once it is accepted that "decision" connotes a determination for which provision is made by or under a statute, one that generally is substantive, final and operative, the place of "conduct" in the statutory scheme of things becomes reasonably clear. ... .... There is a clear distinction between a "decision" and "conduct" engaged in for the purpose of making a decision. A challenge to conduct is an attack upon the proceedings engaged in before the making of the decision. It is not a challenge to decisions made as part of the decision-making process except in the sense that if the decisions are procedural in character they will precede the conduct which is under challenge. In relation to conduct, the complaint is that the process of decision-making was flawed; in relation to a decision, the complaint is that the actual decision was erroneous. To give an example, the continuation of proceedings in such a way as to involve a denial of natural justice would amount to "conduct". That is not to deny that the final determination of the proceedings would constitute a decision reviewable for denial of natural justice.'

47 In relation to the exercise by the Tribunal of its powers, s 36 of the SRC Act provided:
 '36. The Tribunal, in reviewing a decision or conduct: 
 
 
 (a) is not bound by technicalities, legal forms or rules of evidence; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) is to act as speedily as proper consideration of the review allows, having regard to: 
 
 
 
 
 
 
(i) the objectives laid down by section 11 [providing mechanisms for the conciliation of complaints; and if a complaint cannot be resolved by conciliation the review of the decision or conduct to which the complaint relates; that are fair, economical, informal and quick]; and 
 
 
 
 
 
(ii) if the complaint relates to a fund the interests of all the members of the fund; and 
 
 
 
 (c) may inform itself of any matter relevant to the review in any way it thinks appropriate.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Retail Employees Superannuation Pty Limited v Crocker [2001] FCA 1330 ; (2001) 48 ATR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1330.html</AustLII>
<text>48 In considering the scope of a review by the Tribunal under ss 36-37 of the SRC Act Allsop J, as his Honour then was, said in Retail Employees Superannuation Pty Limited v Crocker [2001] FCA 1330 ; (2001) 48 ATR 359 ('Crocker') at [132]:
 '132 ... if the matters thrown up by events and circumstances, including correspondence from the member, do not properly raise anything beyond what was in fact decided by the Trustee, it is not appropriate for the tribunal, with a matter before it received by way of s 14 and under Pt 4 of the Superannuation (Resolution of Complaints) Act 1993 (Cth), to take the opportunity to deal with other aspects of the relationship between the member and the Trustee foreign to the decision for review: see Hay v Briffa. ...' 

 
The last mentioned case was reported as Briffa v Hay (1997) 75 FCR 428.

92 Even if the Tribunal had power under s 37(1) and (3) of the SRC Act, when taken with s 25 of the 1990 Act and s49(1)(e) of the Trustee Act , to compromise a claim made by a former member in the position of the second respondent for the payment of a benefit greater than that for which the Rules provided, it would not, in my opinion, have been open to the Tribunal, exercising all the powers, obligations and discretions that are conferred on the Board, to compromise the relevant claim in a manner that would be contrary to s 37(5) of the SRC Act. Section 37(5) precludes the Tribunal from doing anything that would be contrary to the 'governing rules of the fund concerned' and those Rules fixed the amount of the second respondent's benefit in the amounts indicated in the letter of 14 January 2006 to which reference has been made. (See Rule B3.5.1 and see generally National Mutual Life Association of Australia Ltd v Campbell [2000] FCA 852 ; (2000) 99 FCR 562 at [10] - [12] and [15]-[16]; see also Crocker at [22]-[23] and [27]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Briffa v Hay (1997) 75 FCR 428</tocase>
<text>48 In considering the scope of a review by the Tribunal under ss 36-37 of the SRC Act Allsop J, as his Honour then was, said in Retail Employees Superannuation Pty Limited v Crocker [2001] FCA 1330 ; (2001) 48 ATR 359 ('Crocker') at [132]:
 '132 ... if the matters thrown up by events and circumstances, including correspondence from the member, do not properly raise anything beyond what was in fact decided by the Trustee, it is not appropriate for the tribunal, with a matter before it received by way of s 14 and under Pt 4 of the Superannuation (Resolution of Complaints) Act 1993 (Cth), to take the opportunity to deal with other aspects of the relationship between the member and the Trustee foreign to the decision for review: see Hay v Briffa. ...' 

 
The last mentioned case was reported as Briffa v Hay (1997) 75 FCR 428.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>In re Earl of Strafford, DECD; Royal Bank of Scotland Ltd v Byng [1980] 1 Ch 36</tocase>
<text>88 The learned authors of Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia (7 th edition 2006) said in relation to the general nature of a trustee's power to compromise that it had been considered in England by the Court of Appeal in In re Earl of Strafford, DECD; Royal Bank of Scotland Ltd v Byng [1980] 1 Ch 36. It was said at [2048]:
 'That case establishes that the power is not to be construed narrowly, nor restricted by considerations which do not clearly emerge from the statute conferring the power. In particular, it was held that, in compromising a claim adverse to the trust, the consent of the beneficiaries is not required.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Irismay Holdings Pty Ltd [1996] 1 QdR 172</tocase>
<text>89 In Re Irismay Holdings Pty Ltd [1996] 1 QdR 172 Lee J identified the matter before the Court as an application raising an important question concerning the powers of a trustee to compromise a dispute with a beneficiary relating to the beneficiary's entitlement to trust property under the trust deed. His Honour ended up considering the matter before him by reference to the power contained in s 44(f) of the Trusts Act 1973 (Qld) which was in substantially the same terms as s 49(1)(e) of the Trustee Act . At 174 Lee J said:
 'At first blush it is difficult to see what limitations can be implied into the subsection which do not arise from the language itself. ... one hardly needs to cite authority for the proposition that expressions such as "claim or thing" and "relating to the trust or to the trust property" are of the widest import and should not be read down unless their context or other circumstances clearly require it. 

 
Later, at 175, his Honour said:
 '... Where the very subject matter of the dispute concerns the nature of a beneficiary's interest under the trust then it would seem eminently sensible to confer on the trustee power to settle that dispute provided that the compromise is entered into bona fide and for the benefit of the trust as a whole, an expression which no doubt encompasses the notion that the compromise is reached for the genuine purpose of settling the dispute and not merely as an expedient means of achieving some ulterior or extraneous agenda ... in other words the mere fact that a dispute has arisen and an agreement has been entered into is not enough; the agreement must relate to the resolution of the dispute before it can come within the power.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dowling v St Vincent De Paul Society of Victoria Inc [2003] VSC 454</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VICSC/2003/454.html</AustLII>
<text>90 In Dowling v St Vincent De Paul Society of Victoria Inc [2003] VSC 454 Nettle J took a somewhat more restrictive view of the breadth of s 19(1)(f) of the Trustee Act 1958 (Vic) being the comparable Victorian provision. That case concerned the efficacy of an agreement to compromise a probate proceeding in which the validity of a will was contested. The question was whether s 19(1)(f) authorised the executors to enter into the compromise in anticipation of a grant of probate. Nettle J reached the view that s 19(1)(f) did not authorise an executor to compromise a dispute as to the validity of a will without the consent of affected parties or an order of the Court that bound them. At [19] his Honour said:
 '19 Despite what has been said about the breadth of s 19(1)(f) I do not consider that s 19(1)(f) empowers an executor as such to compromise a probate proceeding in which the validity of the will is contested.' 

 
His Honour continued at [21]:
 '21 The word "claim" is capable in some contexts of including almost any sort of demand. Equally, according to context, the conception of things which relate to an estate may include a very broad range of possible subject matters. But it requires no recitation of authority to establish that the words of a statutory provision are to be read in context and according to the apparent purpose of the provision. And in their context and according to what I perceive to [be] the purpose of the s 19 of the Trustee Act , "claims relating to ... the estate" appear as limited to claims upon or against the estate. With respect, I think the observations of Sir Robert Megarry VC in Re Earl of Strafford to be persuasive. The section is concerned with claims against the estate be they from the outside world or as between the beneficiaries not proceedings to determine the title of the executor or trustee.'

91 It may be seen from the above that Nettle J took the view that the relevant section could lead to compromises of claims by the relevant trustees or against them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>National Mutual Life Association of Australia Ltd v Campbell [2000] FCA 852 ; (2000) 99 FCR 562</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/852.html</AustLII>
<text>92 Even if the Tribunal had power under s 37(1) and (3) of the SRC Act, when taken with s 25 of the 1990 Act and s49(1)(e) of the Trustee Act , to compromise a claim made by a former member in the position of the second respondent for the payment of a benefit greater than that for which the Rules provided, it would not, in my opinion, have been open to the Tribunal, exercising all the powers, obligations and discretions that are conferred on the Board, to compromise the relevant claim in a manner that would be contrary to s 37(5) of the SRC Act. Section 37(5) precludes the Tribunal from doing anything that would be contrary to the 'governing rules of the fund concerned' and those Rules fixed the amount of the second respondent's benefit in the amounts indicated in the letter of 14 January 2006 to which reference has been made. (See Rule B3.5.1 and see generally National Mutual Life Association of Australia Ltd v Campbell [2000] FCA 852 ; (2000) 99 FCR 562 at [10] - [12] and [15]-[16]; see also Crocker at [22]-[23] and [27]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Vetter v Lake Macquarie City Council [2001] HCA 12 ; (2001) 202 CLR 439</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/12.html</AustLII>
<text>104 Contrary to the submissions of the second respondent, I am satisfied that each of the questions of law identified in the Notice of Appeal were questions of law within the meaning of s 46(1) of the SRC Act (see Vetter v Lake Macquarie City Council [2001] HCA 12 ; (2001) 202 CLR 439 at [24] et seq).

105 In my opinion, it was not open to the Tribunal to find that any decision of the Board in relation to the second respondent was unfair or unreasonable.

106 The directions which the Tribunal purported to give to the Board, upon the remission of the complaint, were beyond the power of the Tribunal. Neither the Board nor the Tribunal could provide for a benefit to be paid to the second respondent out of the PSS Fund which did not accord with the Rules and which contemplated calculations being made on the premise that the second respondent could require the date of termination of her employment as an Australian Public Servant to be notionally treated as a date other than that fixed by her employer.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>