<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Occupational and Medical Innovations Ltd ACN 091 192 871 v Retractable Technologies Inc [2008] FCA 1102 (29 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1102.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Freeman v TJ and FL Pohlmer Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1568 ; (1994) 30 IPR 377</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1568.html</AustLII>
<text>15 In connection with issues of novelty, inventiveness and construction of patents, courts frequently rely upon the evidence of skilled addressees. Such a person would presumably be a person of ordinary skill in the relevant art, possessed of the common general knowledge in that art at the relevant time. See, for example, Freeman v TJ and FL Pohlmer Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1568 ; (1994) 30 IPR 377 at 381 . In connection with novelty and inventiveness, the focus upon such a "skilled addressee" is designed to identify objectively the relevant prior art base and the obviousness of any development going beyond that base. I am not presently concerned with such issues. Where words have a special meaning in the relevant art, it may be necessary that expert evidence concerning such meaning be given by a person skilled in the art. However there is no suggestion of that in the present case. RTI does not dispute the construction of the patent advanced by Mr Davis. Where the words are common technical or scientific words, not limited to use in the particular art, a wider class of persons may be competent to give such evidence. Further, the question of construction is ultimately for the Court.

16 Section 79 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) provides:
 If a person has specialized knowledge based on the person's training, study or experience, the opinion rule does not apply to evidence of an opinion of that person that is wholly or substantially based on that knowledge.

17 In his evidence Mr Davis seeks to compare with the RTI patent, particular samples of the product which OMI proposes to market. Mr Davis also seeks to compare those samples with the OMI patent. Counsel for RTI correctly points out that the diagrams attached to Mr Davis's reports do not precisely depict the OMI samples which are in evidence. However the differences do not seem to be significant. I will discuss them in more detail at a later stage. Mr Davis's evidence is obviously based on his reading of the patent in light of his training and experience. That evidence may assist me to compare the samples which are exhibited to Mr Jenkins' affidavit filed on 25 June 2007 with the claims of the OMI patent and the RTI patent. However it is for me to decide all questions of fact. Mr Davis's evidence can do little more than offer an explanation as to the way in which each "feature" in the respective patents may or may not be present in the OMI samples.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>