<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Factory 5 Pty Ltd (In Liquidation) v State of Victoria [2008] FCA 1952 (19 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1952.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>South Australia v Peat Marwick Mitchell (1995) 65 SASR 72</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/1995/5261.html</AustLII>
<text>13 In South Australia v Peat Marwick Mitchell (1995) 65 SASR 72 at 75-77, Olsson J said:
 [W]here a privileged document is exchanged between two parties with a common interest, both parties are entitled to claim and maintain that privilege. ... It is to be borne in mind that the concept of common interest privilege is invoked so as to counter a suggestion that privilege has been waived by the deliberate release or publication of privileged material, by the party entitled to claim privilege, to a third party. ... [A] joint or common interest is not to be taken as a rigidly defined concept. It spans a variety of potential relationships, including partnership.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thiess Contractors Pty Ltd v Terokell Pty Ltd [1993] 2 Qd R 341</tocase>
<text>14 In order for interests to be common, they need not be identical: Thiess Contractors Pty Ltd v Terokell Pty Ltd [1993] 2 Qd R 341 (an insured/insurer case).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Network Ten Ltd v Capital Television Holdings Ltd (1995) 36 NSWLR 275</tocase>
<text>15 In Network Ten Ltd v Capital Television Holdings Ltd (1995) 36 NSWLR 275 at 279-280, Giles J said:
 If two parties with a common interest exchange information and advice relating to that interest, the documents or copy documents containing that information will be privileged from production in the hands of each; thus, if one of the parties obtains a letter of advice attracting legal professional privilege and provides it to the other, the other can also claim legal professional privilege. ... Examples of interest sufficient for common interest privilege can be seen in the cases, but the concept is not rigidly defined and it is a question of fact in each case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>United Dominions Corporation Ltd v Brian Pty Ltd [1985] HCA 49 ; (1985) 157 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/49.html</AustLII>
<text>16 It is not necessary to decide whether documents 5.2 and 5.3 are protected by common interest privilege. It is now common ground that privilege has been waived in relation to them. Subject to the issues canvassed at [17] to [23], in my view common interest privilege attached to the other documents listed at [3] at the time they came into Mr Glover's possession. I accept the applicant's submission that joint venturers are analogous to partners for the purpose of the existence of a common interest. A fiduciary relationship exists between partners. It will often exist between joint venturers. See United Dominions Corporation Ltd v Brian Pty Ltd [1985] HCA 49 ; (1985) 157 CLR 1 at 10-13 and 15-16. As indicated in the cases discussed earlier, "common interest" is not "a rigidly defined concept", and whether it exists in a particular case is a question of fact. Here the evidence, albeit skimpy as the applicant conceded, is that Stage 5 and The Promotions Factory Pty Ltd (Promotions) entered into a joint venture, using the applicant as the joint venture vehicle, to act as the official concessionaire in respect of souvenirs, memorabilia and apparel for the 2006 Commonwealth Games. Mr Glover was provided with copies of the documents in question at about the time each was created in his capacity as a director of Stage 5 and the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Bauhaus Pyrmont Pty Ltd (in liquidation) [2006] NSWSC 543</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2006/543.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The respondents submit that Mr Glover's claim to "maintain" the privilege is said to derive from Stage 5's shareholding in the applicant, which is then said to give it an interest in the outcome of the proceeding. They contend that it is a question of fact whether, in a particular case, a shareholder has such an interest, and that in a case such as the present, where the applicant is clearly insolvent, no such interest exists because Stage 5's shareholding is valueless. They rely on Re Bauhaus Pyrmont Pty Ltd (in liquidation) [2006] NSWSC 543 ( Bauhaus ). There, one Widdup was a director of the company in liquidation and the indirect owner of all the company's shares. Justice Austin held that Mr Widdup did not have a common interest in privileged documents given to him because there was no prospect of a distribution to contributors in the winding up.

18 The respondents rely on the matters set out at [10] to show that Stage 5 stands in the same position as Mr Widdup in Bauhaus . The applicant sought to distinguish Bauhaus on the ground that it concerned a liquidator of a company giving privileged documents to a shareholder who, at the time of receipt, had no prospect of a return from the winding up.

19 Section 122(5)(b) of the Evidence Act (set out at [11]) excludes the waiver provisions of sub-ss (2) and (4) in relation to a disclosure to a person who, at the time of the disclosure , shared a common interest with the client. Accordingly, I accept the applicant's submission that common interest is to be tested at the time Mr Glover came into possession of the documents.

20 The party claiming privilege has the onus of establishing the basis of the claim. Order 33 rule 11(1) of the Federal Court Rules provides that:
 Where the Court, by subpoena or otherwise, orders any person to produce any document or thing, and any person makes and substantiates sufficient lawful objection to production on grounds of privilege, the Court shall not compel production of that document or thing except production to the Court for the purpose of ruling on the objection. (Emphasis added.)

21 The expression "ground of privilege" is defined in rule 11(5) as a ground on which a person may rely to make an objection under Part 3.10 of the Evidence Act . That includes common interest privilege. See s 122(5)(b) and Bauhaus at [24]. On onus in relation to client legal privilege in general, see Mitsubishi Electric Australia Pty Ltd v Victorian Workcover Authority (2002) 4 VR 332 at 337. The claimant must establish the facts giving rise to the privilege: National Crime Authority v S (1991) 100 ALR 151 at 158-159.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mitsubishi Electric Australia Pty Ltd v Victorian Workcover Authority (2002) 4 VR 332</tocase>
<text>21 The expression "ground of privilege" is defined in rule 11(5) as a ground on which a person may rely to make an objection under Part 3.10 of the Evidence Act . That includes common interest privilege. See s 122(5)(b) and Bauhaus at [24]. On onus in relation to client legal privilege in general, see Mitsubishi Electric Australia Pty Ltd v Victorian Workcover Authority (2002) 4 VR 332 at 337. The claimant must establish the facts giving rise to the privilege: National Crime Authority v S (1991) 100 ALR 151 at 158-159.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>National Crime Authority v S (1991) 100 ALR 151</tocase>
<text>21 The expression "ground of privilege" is defined in rule 11(5) as a ground on which a person may rely to make an objection under Part 3.10 of the Evidence Act . That includes common interest privilege. See s 122(5)(b) and Bauhaus at [24]. On onus in relation to client legal privilege in general, see Mitsubishi Electric Australia Pty Ltd v Victorian Workcover Authority (2002) 4 VR 332 at 337. The claimant must establish the facts giving rise to the privilege: National Crime Authority v S (1991) 100 ALR 151 at 158-159.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (No 2) (1989) 88 ALR 90</tocase>
<text>25 Paragraphs 1 and 2 of the notice of motion can be dealt with together. A notice to produce may be set aside on the ground of lack of apparent relevance. The test of apparent relevance is whether the documents are reasonably likely to add, in the end, in some way or another, to the relevant evidence. Relevance in an evidentiary/admissibility sense is not the test. See Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (No 2) (1989) 88 ALR 90 at 101-103; Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174 at [6] ; Telstra Corp Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [44] - [48] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/174.html</AustLII>
<text>25 Paragraphs 1 and 2 of the notice of motion can be dealt with together. A notice to produce may be set aside on the ground of lack of apparent relevance. The test of apparent relevance is whether the documents are reasonably likely to add, in the end, in some way or another, to the relevant evidence. Relevance in an evidentiary/admissibility sense is not the test. See Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (No 2) (1989) 88 ALR 90 at 101-103; Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174 at [6] ; Telstra Corp Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [44] - [48] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Telstra Corp Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1398.html</AustLII>
<text>25 Paragraphs 1 and 2 of the notice of motion can be dealt with together. A notice to produce may be set aside on the ground of lack of apparent relevance. The test of apparent relevance is whether the documents are reasonably likely to add, in the end, in some way or another, to the relevant evidence. Relevance in an evidentiary/admissibility sense is not the test. See Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (No 2) (1989) 88 ALR 90 at 101-103; Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174 at [6] ; Telstra Corp Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [44] - [48] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Kingsheath Club of the Clubs Ltd (in liquidation) [2003] FCA 1034</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/1034.html</AustLII>
<text>27 The Registrar's order for production of the funding agreement permitted the applicant to redact the document to remove the amounts set out in par 2.1 thereof, that is the sections dealing with the amount of funding available. The only unfairness suggested by the applicant was if there were an order that the document be provided without that redaction. See generally Re Kingsheath Club of the Clubs Ltd (in liquidation) [2003] FCA 1034 at [33] - [34] and Spatialinfo Pty Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2005] FCA 455 at [69] - [73] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spatialinfo Pty Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2005] FCA 455</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/455.html</AustLII>
<text>27 The Registrar's order for production of the funding agreement permitted the applicant to redact the document to remove the amounts set out in par 2.1 thereof, that is the sections dealing with the amount of funding available. The only unfairness suggested by the applicant was if there were an order that the document be provided without that redaction. See generally Re Kingsheath Club of the Clubs Ltd (in liquidation) [2003] FCA 1034 at [33] - [34] and Spatialinfo Pty Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2005] FCA 455 at [69] - [73] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>