<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>AWB Limited v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2008] FCA 1877 (11 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1877.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>46 The question which then arises is whether the disclosure of the AWB Information under s 127(4) requires ASIC to observe procedural fairness not only towards the examinee but also a party in the position of AWB consistent with the principles set out in Johns v ASC [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408. The exercise of the statutory power is conditional upon the observance of the rules of natural justice ( Johns at 470; Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 , 591 and Annetts v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 , 598), but does that natural justice requirement extend to AWB?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Annetts v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/57.html</AustLII>
<text>46 The question which then arises is whether the disclosure of the AWB Information under s 127(4) requires ASIC to observe procedural fairness not only towards the examinee but also a party in the position of AWB consistent with the principles set out in Johns v ASC [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408. The exercise of the statutory power is conditional upon the observance of the rules of natural justice ( Johns at 470; Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 , 591 and Annetts v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 , 598), but does that natural justice requirement extend to AWB?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>British Coal Corporation v Dennis Rye Ltd (No 2) [1988] 3 All ER 816</tocase>
<text>40 Secondly, equity may restrain use of confidential information improperly obtained , especially where the information is used as a "springboard for a claim or defence in litigation": Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301 at [15] - [17] . As Emmett J noted in MM , there is nothing to prevent the holder of a claim for privilege making a privilege claim prior to the tendering of evidence against the holder of any information obtained by ASIC in circumstances not giving rise to a waiver: eg ss 76 - 83 of the ASIC Act ; ss 118 and 122 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) and British Coal Corporation v Dennis Rye Ltd (No 2) [1988] 3 All ER 816. Put another way, "the right of the holder of the privilege not to have privileged material used in evidence against him or her [or it]" is not affected by the disclosure of the privileged material by a party within the scope of the privilege but not entitled to control its exercise: MM at [38]. This is a natural consequence of the basic principle that only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Moreover, although not applicable in the present case (because the third party here is a corporation, which has no privilege against self-incrimination: Daniels at [31]), that preservation of privilege extends not only to legal professional privilege but also privilege against self-incrimination because the ASIC Act abrogates privilege against self-incrimination (s 68(1)) and then provides a "use immunity" to the examinee in relation to information obtained in a s 19 examination where the requirements of s 68(2) are satisfied: s 68(3) of the ASIC Act . Interestingly, unlike other Commonwealth legislation, the "use immunity" in the ASIC Act only applies to persons in relation to the making of an oral statement or the signing of a record and not to the production of documents: s 76(1)(d) of the ASIC Act ; see also Privilege in Perspective , ALRC Report No 107 (2007) at Ch 7 and in particular, paras [7.65] [7.69] and [7.103] and [7.104].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Ltd (2008) 246 ALR 137</tocase>
<text>24 In the course of argument, ASIC appeared to suggest there were qualifications to the general proposition that the ASIC Act did not abrogate legal professional privilege. The qualifications were, first, that the ASIC Act is silent as to whether a person other than a lawyer may refuse to give information on the ground that it would disclose a communication for which the person claims legal privilege. If that observation by ASIC was intended to provide support for a contention that an individual, not a lawyer, could be compelled by ASIC to disclose information for which the individual had a claim for legal professional privilege, then that contention is rejected. It is rejected because it finds no support in the Act and is contrary to authority ( Daniels ). There is no basis for distinguishing between a lawyer and an individual in the context of legal professional privilege. So much is made clear from the express words of s 69 of the ASIC Act . In the circumstances specified (which includes ASIC's powers of investigation, examination and information gathering in Pt 3) , a lawyer may refuse to comply with a requirement to give information or produce a book, where to do so would involve the disclosure of a privileged communication with the lawyer in their capacity as a lawyer " unless ... the person to whom, or by or on behalf of whom, the communication was made consents to the lawyer complying with the requirement" (emphasis added): s 69(2). In other words, consistent with authority, the section proceeds on the premise that the holder of the privilege (being the client regardless of whether the client is an individual or a body corporate) must consent to the disclosure of the privilege it holds. No other party is able to waive the privilege; it is the holder of the privilege (the client) that must act inconsistently with the maintenance of that privilege for privilege to be waived: see Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Ltd (2008) 246 ALR 137 at [17]. Any other result is contrary to the fundamental principles summarised in [21] and [22] above.

26 On the assumption that, at the outset of a s 19 examination, ASIC told an examinee that legal professional privilege may be availed of by that person to resist the giving of information or the production of documents that would reveal communications between a client and his or her lawyer made for the dominant purpose of giving or obtaining legal advice or the provision of legal services, then disclosure by an examinee or witness of information in which he or she holds the privilege would constitute an act inconsistent with the maintenance of that privilege and privilege would be waived: see Cadbury 246 ALR 137 at [13]. So much may be accepted. It is consistent with the established principles on waiver.

27 If ASIC's submission is intended to suggest that if that same person (for example, an employee, director, consultant to, but not a legal adviser of, a third party) was privy to the privileged communications of the third party, then ASIC could compel production of that privileged information, that contention should be rejected for the reasons outlined in [21] and [22] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commodity Futures Trading Commission v Weintraub [1985] USSC 102 ; 471 US 343 (1985)</tocase>
<text>28 If, however, ASIC meant to submit not that it could compel a person (here, an employee or former employee) to disclose a third party's (here, a company's) privilege by force of statute, but rather that the person may lack the standing to assert the third party's privilege, then that contention may be accepted. Just as an employee can only waive a corporation's privilege if he or she has authority to do so (typically, where the person is a current officer or director), so too may an employee only assert a claim of privilege belonging to a corporation if he or she has the requisite authority: Commodity Futures Trading Commission v Weintraub [1985] USSC 102 ; 471 US 343 , 348-49 (1985); In re Grand Jury Proceedings [2006] USCA1 234 ; 469 F3d 24 (1 st Cir 2006); Wrench LLC v Taco Bell Corporation 212 FRD 514 , 517 (WD Mich 2002) (collecting cases); see also S McNicol, Law of Privilege (1992) at 161-62 (citing Rochfort v Trade Practices Commission (1982) 153 CLR 134 for the proposition that an employee cannot assert the privilege of self-incrimination on behalf of a corporation [at that time corporations were still thought to have such a privilege] because the privilege is personal to the holder). To put it another way, the ASIC investigator was legally correct when he told counsel for AWB that "[n]either ... could [the employees] make the claim [of privilege on behalf of AWB] nor [could they] waive the claim...": [12] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSCA/2007/301.html</AustLII>
<text>34 However that may be, the fact of the matter is that ASIC now has possession of information which, at least in theory, could be subject to a valid claim of privilege by AWB. The question then is whether ASIC is entitled to make use of that information, notwithstanding the possible privilege claim, and the answer to that question is yes. As the Court of Appeal in Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301 said (at [32]):
 
 
 [A]lthough it is now accepted that legal professional privilege is more than just a rule of evidence or procedure, it is clear that it is not to be characterised as a rule of law conferring individual rights sounding in damages or an injunction to restrain an apprehended or continued breach [ Commissioner of Australian Federal Police v Propend Finance Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 3 ; (1997) 188 CLR 501 at 565 (Gummow J)]. Consequently, once information in a privileged document has come into the hands of a party to litigation, even as a result of compulsive process which is later reversed, the fact that the document was and remains privileged does not of itself prevent that party from making use of the information [ Calcraft v Guest [1898] 1 QB 759, 763-4; Baker v Campbell [1983] HCA 39 ; (1983) 153 CLR 52 (Gibbs CJ, in diss ), 67, 80 (Mason J, in diss ) 101, 109-110 (Brennan J in diss ), 129 (Dawson J); Trevorrow v State of South Australia (No 4) (2006) 94 SASR 64 , 70 (Doyle CJ), 80 (Debelle J), 101 (White J); Heydon, Cross on Evidence , 7 th Aust Ed (2004) [25025].

40 Secondly, equity may restrain use of confidential information improperly obtained , especially where the information is used as a "springboard for a claim or defence in litigation": Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301 at [15] - [17] . As Emmett J noted in MM , there is nothing to prevent the holder of a claim for privilege making a privilege claim prior to the tendering of evidence against the holder of any information obtained by ASIC in circumstances not giving rise to a waiver: eg ss 76 - 83 of the ASIC Act ; ss 118 and 122 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) and British Coal Corporation v Dennis Rye Ltd (No 2) [1988] 3 All ER 816. Put another way, "the right of the holder of the privilege not to have privileged material used in evidence against him or her [or it]" is not affected by the disclosure of the privileged material by a party within the scope of the privilege but not entitled to control its exercise: MM at [38]. This is a natural consequence of the basic principle that only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Moreover, although not applicable in the present case (because the third party here is a corporation, which has no privilege against self-incrimination: Daniels at [31]), that preservation of privilege extends not only to legal professional privilege but also privilege against self-incrimination because the ASIC Act abrogates privilege against self-incrimination (s 68(1)) and then provides a "use immunity" to the examinee in relation to information obtained in a s 19 examination where the requirements of s 68(2) are satisfied: s 68(3) of the ASIC Act . Interestingly, unlike other Commonwealth legislation, the "use immunity" in the ASIC Act only applies to persons in relation to the making of an oral statement or the signing of a record and not to the production of documents: s 76(1)(d) of the ASIC Act ; see also Privilege in Perspective , ALRC Report No 107 (2007) at Ch 7 and in particular, paras [7.65] [7.69] and [7.103] and [7.104].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Daniels Corporation International Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] HCA 49 ; (2002) 213 CLR 543</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/49.html</AustLII>
<text>22 It is settled that "legal professional privilege is a rule of substantive law which may be availed of by a person to resist the giving of information or the production of documents which would reveal communications between a client or his or her lawyer made for the dominant purpose of giving or obtaining legal advice or the provision of legal services": Daniels Corporation International Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] HCA 49 ; (2002) 213 CLR 543 at [9] and [11] and the authorities cited.

23 In the absence of a statutory provision to the contrary, legal professional privilege may be availed of to resist the giving of information or the production of documents in accordance with investigatory procedures of the kind contained in s 155 of the Trade Practices Act 1975 (Cth) ("the TPA"): Daniels Corporation [2002] HCA 49 ; 213 CLR 543 at [10] and [11]. Despite differences in language between the TPA and the ASIC Act , no different result ensues. There is no express provision in the ASIC Act abrogating legal professional privilege. Moreover, there is nothing in the ASIC Act supporting the contention that the abrogation of legal professional privilege is a necessary implication: see eg ss 1(1) , 1 (2), 1 (3), Pt 3 and, in particular, ss 68 and 69 .

24 In the course of argument, ASIC appeared to suggest there were qualifications to the general proposition that the ASIC Act did not abrogate legal professional privilege. The qualifications were, first, that the ASIC Act is silent as to whether a person other than a lawyer may refuse to give information on the ground that it would disclose a communication for which the person claims legal privilege. If that observation by ASIC was intended to provide support for a contention that an individual, not a lawyer, could be compelled by ASIC to disclose information for which the individual had a claim for legal professional privilege, then that contention is rejected. It is rejected because it finds no support in the Act and is contrary to authority ( Daniels ). There is no basis for distinguishing between a lawyer and an individual in the context of legal professional privilege. So much is made clear from the express words of s 69 of the ASIC Act . In the circumstances specified (which includes ASIC's powers of investigation, examination and information gathering in Pt 3) , a lawyer may refuse to comply with a requirement to give information or produce a book, where to do so would involve the disclosure of a privileged communication with the lawyer in their capacity as a lawyer " unless ... the person to whom, or by or on behalf of whom, the communication was made consents to the lawyer complying with the requirement" (emphasis added): s 69(2). In other words, consistent with authority, the section proceeds on the premise that the holder of the privilege (being the client regardless of whether the client is an individual or a body corporate) must consent to the disclosure of the privilege it holds. No other party is able to waive the privilege; it is the holder of the privilege (the client) that must act inconsistently with the maintenance of that privilege for privilege to be waived: see Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Ltd (2008) 246 ALR 137 at [17]. Any other result is contrary to the fundamental principles summarised in [21] and [22] above.

29 In other words, I accept the contention that although ASIC cannot compel the production of legally privileged communications of a person (ie the ASIC Act does not override or abrogate legal professional privilege), that does not mean that ASIC cannot receive such communications under any circumstances. As ASIC contended, legal professional privilege affords a person immunity from compulsory disclosure of its privileged communication ( Daniels ). That immunity does not prevent receipt by ASIC in the circumstances of the present case of legally privileged information from the examinees and the witnesses where they were not the holder of the privilege.

40 Secondly, equity may restrain use of confidential information improperly obtained , especially where the information is used as a "springboard for a claim or defence in litigation": Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301 at [15] - [17] . As Emmett J noted in MM , there is nothing to prevent the holder of a claim for privilege making a privilege claim prior to the tendering of evidence against the holder of any information obtained by ASIC in circumstances not giving rise to a waiver: eg ss 76 - 83 of the ASIC Act ; ss 118 and 122 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) and British Coal Corporation v Dennis Rye Ltd (No 2) [1988] 3 All ER 816. Put another way, "the right of the holder of the privilege not to have privileged material used in evidence against him or her [or it]" is not affected by the disclosure of the privileged material by a party within the scope of the privilege but not entitled to control its exercise: MM at [38]. This is a natural consequence of the basic principle that only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Moreover, although not applicable in the present case (because the third party here is a corporation, which has no privilege against self-incrimination: Daniels at [31]), that preservation of privilege extends not only to legal professional privilege but also privilege against self-incrimination because the ASIC Act abrogates privilege against self-incrimination (s 68(1)) and then provides a "use immunity" to the examinee in relation to information obtained in a s 19 examination where the requirements of s 68(2) are satisfied: s 68(3) of the ASIC Act . Interestingly, unlike other Commonwealth legislation, the "use immunity" in the ASIC Act only applies to persons in relation to the making of an oral statement or the signing of a record and not to the production of documents: s 76(1)(d) of the ASIC Act ; see also Privilege in Perspective , ALRC Report No 107 (2007) at Ch 7 and in particular, paras [7.65] [7.69] and [7.103] and [7.104].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>disapproved</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citibank Ltd (1989) 20 FCR 403</tocase>
<text>35 Secondly, a government agency or authority (such as ASIC) in the exercise of its compulsory powers must provide the person the subject of the exercise of the power with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on his or her own behalf: see Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citibank Ltd (1989) 20 FCR 403 , 414 and MM v Australian Crime Commission (2007) 244 ALR 452 at [35]-[36]; but see JMA Accounting Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 274 ; (2004) 139 FCR 537 at [10] - [13] . Given the arrangements put in place by ASIC (see [9], [11] above), there was no (and could be no) complaint that the examinees were not provided with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on their own behalf.

36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gangemi v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2003] FCA 494 ; (2003) 129 FCR 284</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/494.html</AustLII>
<text>32 Of course, there cannot be a general rule that a legal representative of the employer or the former employer of the examinee should be permitted to attend to protect the employer's privilege. There may well be circumstances where to do so would jeopardise the investigation: see eg Gangemi v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2003] FCA 494 ; (2003) 129 FCR 284 at [35] , [38]; see also Rochfort at 145 (Mason J) (stating that request for the production of privileged information should generally be directed to the employer but "the protection of the employer's interests [in the information] must give way to the public interest in the efficient administration of justice in case of collision between the two"). But in the absence of such a circumstance, the voluntary grant by ASIC of a limited right to be present in the manner outlined by counsel for AWB might have forestalled the issues raised in these proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>In re Grand Jury Proceedings [2006] USCA1 234 ; 469 F3d 24 (1 st Cir 2006)</tocase>
<text>28 If, however, ASIC meant to submit not that it could compel a person (here, an employee or former employee) to disclose a third party's (here, a company's) privilege by force of statute, but rather that the person may lack the standing to assert the third party's privilege, then that contention may be accepted. Just as an employee can only waive a corporation's privilege if he or she has authority to do so (typically, where the person is a current officer or director), so too may an employee only assert a claim of privilege belonging to a corporation if he or she has the requisite authority: Commodity Futures Trading Commission v Weintraub [1985] USSC 102 ; 471 US 343 , 348-49 (1985); In re Grand Jury Proceedings [2006] USCA1 234 ; 469 F3d 24 (1 st Cir 2006); Wrench LLC v Taco Bell Corporation 212 FRD 514 , 517 (WD Mich 2002) (collecting cases); see also S McNicol, Law of Privilege (1992) at 161-62 (citing Rochfort v Trade Practices Commission (1982) 153 CLR 134 for the proposition that an employee cannot assert the privilege of self-incrimination on behalf of a corporation [at that time corporations were still thought to have such a privilege] because the privilege is personal to the holder). To put it another way, the ASIC investigator was legally correct when he told counsel for AWB that "[n]either ... could [the employees] make the claim [of privilege on behalf of AWB] nor [could they] waive the claim...": [12] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>JMA Accounting Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 274 ; (2004) 139 FCR 537</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/274.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Secondly, a government agency or authority (such as ASIC) in the exercise of its compulsory powers must provide the person the subject of the exercise of the power with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on his or her own behalf: see Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citibank Ltd (1989) 20 FCR 403 , 414 and MM v Australian Crime Commission (2007) 244 ALR 452 at [35]-[36]; but see JMA Accounting Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 274 ; (2004) 139 FCR 537 at [10] - [13] . Given the arrangements put in place by ASIC (see [9], [11] above), there was no (and could be no) complaint that the examinees were not provided with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on their own behalf.

36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Johns v Australian Securities Commission [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/56.html</AustLII>
<text>3 In early 2008, ASIC received a request from the Australian Federal Police ("the AFP") that it disclose certain information, including the AWB Information, to the AFP. AWB's solicitors learned of the request from a current employee and three former employees who had been examined by ASIC. Those current and former employees had been contacted by ASIC about the AFP request. ASIC informed them that ASIC was considering whether to provide the transcript of their s 19 examination to the AFP and, consistent with the decision of the High Court in Johns v Australian Securities Commission [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408 , provided each of them with an opportunity to be heard and to make submissions to ASIC in relation to the proposed release of the transcript of their s 19 examination to the AFP.

4 Upon learning of the proposed disclosure by ASIC, AWB wrote to ASIC on 1 April 2008 seeking an opportunity to be heard and to make submissions to ASIC in relation to the proposed release of information to the AFP including the conditions of the release. ASIC responded on 11 April 2008. At that time, the request was limited to the transcripts of the s 19 examinations. ASIC outlined the terms of the AFP request, its proposal to release the transcripts of the s 19 examinations to the AFP and the conditions upon which that information was proposed to be released. ASIC expressed the view that:
 
 
 It is ASIC's view that the protocols that were applied during the course of the section 19 ASIC Act examinations to ensure that information subject to a valid claim of legal professional privilege was not disclosed were sufficient, and that no privileged information was disclosed during the course of any examinations. 
 
 ...
 
 Further, in light of the conditions on which ASIC proposes to release the examination transcripts to the AFP, and the secrecy provisions imposed on employees of the AFP by section 60A of the Australian Federal Police Act 1979 Cth [sic], ASIC does not consider that [AWB's] interests in the confidentiality of any information provided to ASIC by examinees will be adversely affected by the proposed release.
 
 Although it is ASIC's view that ... [AWB's] interests will [not] be adversely affected by any decision to release the information to the AFP on the limited basis identified in paragraph 5 above, ASIC proposes to give [AWB] an opportunity to make submissions in relation to the conditions to be imposed on the disclosure of the transcripts of examinations of current or former employees of [AWB] to the AFP under section 127(4) of the ASIC Act .

5 ASIC and AWB's solicitors corresponded for some months. By July 2008, the AFP request had extended to disclosure of the witness statements that had been provided voluntarily by the employees and former employees of AWB.

45 However, that is not the end of the enquiry. The disclosure of the AWB Information by ASIC to the AFP was subject to conditions imposed under s 127(4A) (see [7] above). ASIC's s 127 power to disclose is discretionary: Johns at 428 and 469. The conditions are important. When, as here, conditions are imposed they are enforceable as an equitable obligation. The AFP is affected by the terms on which it received the AWB Information: Johns at 429. The obligation (expressed as a condition) is enforceable, at least, by injunction: Johns at 429.

46 The question which then arises is whether the disclosure of the AWB Information under s 127(4) requires ASIC to observe procedural fairness not only towards the examinee but also a party in the position of AWB consistent with the principles set out in Johns v ASC [1993] HCA 56 ; (1993) 178 CLR 408. The exercise of the statutory power is conditional upon the observance of the rules of natural justice ( Johns at 470; Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 , 591 and Annetts v McCann [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 , 598), but does that natural justice requirement extend to AWB?

47 First, it must be recalled that the AWB Information was protected by disclosure (s 127(1)) subject to the qualifications prescribed in ss (2)-(4). That antecedent right or duty is not determinative. However, it is a relevant factor affecting the exercise by ASIC of its discretionary statutory power to disclose the AWB Information to the AFP. Exercise of the authority conferred by s 127(4) was "apt to affect adversely" the interests of the examinees who are prima facie entitled to have the transcripts kept confidential: Johns at 430. It was for that reason, consistent with Johns , that ASIC observed the rules of natural justice and informed each of the examinees that it proposed to disclose the transcripts and gave each examinee an opportunity to oppose: Johns at 430-431.

48 The present case, however, concerns not the examinee but AWB, the employer or previous employer of each examinee. In Johns , McHugh J said (at 472) that "the need to preserve the confidentiality of ASIC's investigation does not exclude procedural fairness, but reduces its content, perhaps in some circumstances to nothing". Here, the question of whether or not ASIC was obliged to observe the rules of natural justice in the case of AWB did not arise. Although AWB was not told by ASIC of the proposed disclosures to the AFP, it learned of that fact, was "given the opportunity to put submissions before [ASIC] relating to matters requiring the non-disclosure of information by [ASIC]" ( Johns at 472) and took advantage of that opportunity by making numerous submissions opposing the disclosure. AWB might have persuaded ASIC to accept or adopt its submissions. It did not. In the circumstances, it is not necessary to pursue McHugh J's observation to its end to determine precisely how much the content of procedural fairness may have been reduced with respect to AWB; I need only find (and do find) that the opportunity to be heard that was given to AWB was sufficient.

49 It follows from what I have just said that none of AWB's grounds of review is made out. The specific grounds are disposed of as follows.

50 There was no and could be no constructive failure to exercise jurisdiction or an absence of power contrary to ss 5(1)(c) and (d) of the ADJR Act . AWB's contentions that ASIC was "[not] empowered by the ASIC Act to obtain confidential and privileged communications from persons other than the holder of the privilege in circumstances where the holder has not expressly or by implication waived the privilege" is too broad a proposition. ASIC is not empowered to compel production from the privilege-holder and did not do so.

55 In my view, there was no denial of natural justice. AWB was "given the opportunity to put submissions before [ASIC] relating to matters requiring the non-disclosure of information by [ASIC]" ( Johns at 472) and took advantage of that opportunity by making numerous submissions opposing the disclosure. As I have found, this opportunity to be heard was enough to satisfy any requirements of natural justice in the circumstances: see [47] above. Moreover, it is of the utmost importance to recall that in a proceeding of this nature it is neither necessary nor right to decide the merits of the decision.

56 For those reasons, I would dismiss the application and order the applicant to pay the respondent's costs to be taxed in default of agreement. 

 I certify that the preceding fifty-six (56) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gordon. 


 Associate:

Dated: 11 December 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr C Scerri QC and Mr P Corbett 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Allens Arthur Robinson 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr S McLeish SC and Ms Z Maud 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Securities and Investments Commission 

 Date of Hearing: 10 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 December 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1877.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/66.html</AustLII>
<text>36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985) 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>42 It is well established that "an administrative decision may be impugned if the decision maker was bound to take a factor into account in reaching his or her decision but failed to do so": MM at [40]. If a statute states expressly the factors that must be taken into account that will be decisive. However, if the relevant factors are not expressly stated, they must be determined by necessary implication from the subject matter, scope and purpose of the Act: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985) 162 CLR 24 , 39-40; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 , 347-348.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>42 It is well established that "an administrative decision may be impugned if the decision maker was bound to take a factor into account in reaching his or her decision but failed to do so": MM at [40]. If a statute states expressly the factors that must be taken into account that will be decisive. However, if the relevant factors are not expressly stated, they must be determined by necessary implication from the subject matter, scope and purpose of the Act: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985) 162 CLR 24 , 39-40; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 , 347-348.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>MM v Australian Crime Commission (2007) 244 ALR 452</tocase>
<text>35 Secondly, a government agency or authority (such as ASIC) in the exercise of its compulsory powers must provide the person the subject of the exercise of the power with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on his or her own behalf: see Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citibank Ltd (1989) 20 FCR 403 , 414 and MM v Australian Crime Commission (2007) 244 ALR 452 at [35]-[36]; but see JMA Accounting Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 274 ; (2004) 139 FCR 537 at [10] - [13] . Given the arrangements put in place by ASIC (see [9], [11] above), there was no (and could be no) complaint that the examinees were not provided with a reasonable opportunity to claim legal professional privilege on their own behalf.

36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.

37 But while there may be a question as to what obligations or abilities a person may have in respect of claims of privilege on behalf of third parties, it is clear that there is no requirement in the ASIC Act , which imposes an obligation on ASIC to afford a person or entity (other than the person the subject of the exercise of the compulsory power) (ie the third party itself):
 
1. an opportunity to intervene or interject in the exercise of the compulsory power over another in order to claim or assert legal professional privilege on behalf of itself: see, in particular Pts 3 and 7 of the ASIC Act ; or
 
2. notice that the exercise of its compulsory power in relation to another individual (such as an examinee) may result in that individual providing information that is subject to a claim of legal professional privilege by that third party. 
 
See by way of example, May v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1999] FCA 287 ; (1999) 92 FCR 152 at [31] , [36] and [38] and MM at [36] and [37].

38 That is not surprising. If ASIC were under an obligation to notify a third party that the exercise of its compulsory power in relation to another individual (such as an examinee) may result in that individual providing information that is subject to a claim of legal professional privilege by that third party, by what criteria would ASIC determine when and in what circumstances it was required to notify a third party? Would ASIC be required to interrupt an examination upon becoming aware of the prospect of or the fact of information being provided by an examinee which might be the subject of a claim of privilege by a third party? How would ASIC determine if it was properly subject to a claim for legal professional privilege? The list of difficulties is endless and the possibility great that efficient and timely investigation of wrongdoing would be frustrated.

39 Moreover, there are measures that the third party can take to prevent disclosure of its privileged information even in the absence of a right to intervene. First, where an examinee is subject to the exercise of compulsory powers by a government authority and in possession of privileged information where the holder of the privilege is a third party, it is open to the holder of privilege to require or authorise the examinee to assert the holder's privilege to the authority: MM at [33] (cf s 122(3) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth)). Of course, the efficacy of this strategy is likely to be limited in situations where the third party does not have prior notice of the examination or other exercise of power over another under the ASIC Act .

40 Secondly, equity may restrain use of confidential information improperly obtained , especially where the information is used as a "springboard for a claim or defence in litigation": Cowell v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2007] VSCA 301 at [15] - [17] . As Emmett J noted in MM , there is nothing to prevent the holder of a claim for privilege making a privilege claim prior to the tendering of evidence against the holder of any information obtained by ASIC in circumstances not giving rise to a waiver: eg ss 76 - 83 of the ASIC Act ; ss 118 and 122 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) and British Coal Corporation v Dennis Rye Ltd (No 2) [1988] 3 All ER 816. Put another way, "the right of the holder of the privilege not to have privileged material used in evidence against him or her [or it]" is not affected by the disclosure of the privileged material by a party within the scope of the privilege but not entitled to control its exercise: MM at [38]. This is a natural consequence of the basic principle that only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Moreover, although not applicable in the present case (because the third party here is a corporation, which has no privilege against self-incrimination: Daniels at [31]), that preservation of privilege extends not only to legal professional privilege but also privilege against self-incrimination because the ASIC Act abrogates privilege against self-incrimination (s 68(1)) and then provides a "use immunity" to the examinee in relation to information obtained in a s 19 examination where the requirements of s 68(2) are satisfied: s 68(3) of the ASIC Act . Interestingly, unlike other Commonwealth legislation, the "use immunity" in the ASIC Act only applies to persons in relation to the making of an oral statement or the signing of a record and not to the production of documents: s 76(1)(d) of the ASIC Act ; see also Privilege in Perspective , ALRC Report No 107 (2007) at Ch 7 and in particular, paras [7.65] [7.69] and [7.103] and [7.104].

42 It is well established that "an administrative decision may be impugned if the decision maker was bound to take a factor into account in reaching his or her decision but failed to do so": MM at [40]. If a statute states expressly the factors that must be taken into account that will be decisive. However, if the relevant factors are not expressly stated, they must be determined by necessary implication from the subject matter, scope and purpose of the Act: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1985) 162 CLR 24 , 39-40; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 , 347-348.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Onefone Australia Pty Ltd v One.Tel Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1188</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2007/1188.html</AustLII>
<text>18 Section 127(1) of the ASIC Act imposes an obligation on ASIC to take all reasonable measures to protect the unauthorised use or disclosure of information given to it in confidence in performance of its functions: Onefone Australia Pty Ltd v One.Tel Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1188 at [7] . Section 127(4) provides an exception to that general principle. Where ASIC is satisfied "particular information" will assist, for example, the AFP, then disclosure of that "particular information" to the AFP will be taken to be an authorised use and disclosure of that "particular information".

19 The exercise of the power under s 127(4) of the ASIC Act is the exercise of an additional power in relation to the "particular information" identified by ASIC at the time of the request by the AFP. It necessarily will involve consideration of "information" that did not exist at the time of the examination (here, the questions and answers recorded in the transcript) or the taking of the witness statement (here, the statement). It will also necessarily involve the consideration of matters that did not exist at the aforementioned times, including the nature of the agency function or power (here, criminal investigation by the AFP) and the usefulness of the information to that exercise of power (here, the conduct of that investigation). Section 127(4A) of the ASIC Act provides that ASIC may impose conditions in relation to disclosure of the "particular information" under s 127(4). The conditions imposed by ASIC in respect of the AWB Information are those set out in [7] above.

20 In the present case, the dispositive issue (see [13] above) has two aspects to it. The two aspects to consider are:
 
1. whether, in exercising the power under s 127(4) , by deciding to pass the AWB Information to the AFP, ASIC failed to consider a relevant matter; and 
 
2. a more basic question of power. 
 
For reasons which will become obvious, it is first necessary to deal with the question of power.

21 There is no factual foundation yet established that there is material in the AWB Information to which the legal professional privilege of AWB attaches. However, if the AWB Information does contain information to which the legal professional privilege of AWB attaches, ASIC would have power to pass on that material to the AFP. That conclusion requires development.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151</tocase>
<text>36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Rochfort v Trade Practices Commission (1982) 153 CLR 134</tocase>
<text>28 If, however, ASIC meant to submit not that it could compel a person (here, an employee or former employee) to disclose a third party's (here, a company's) privilege by force of statute, but rather that the person may lack the standing to assert the third party's privilege, then that contention may be accepted. Just as an employee can only waive a corporation's privilege if he or she has authority to do so (typically, where the person is a current officer or director), so too may an employee only assert a claim of privilege belonging to a corporation if he or she has the requisite authority: Commodity Futures Trading Commission v Weintraub [1985] USSC 102 ; 471 US 343 , 348-49 (1985); In re Grand Jury Proceedings [2006] USCA1 234 ; 469 F3d 24 (1 st Cir 2006); Wrench LLC v Taco Bell Corporation 212 FRD 514 , 517 (WD Mich 2002) (collecting cases); see also S McNicol, Law of Privilege (1992) at 161-62 (citing Rochfort v Trade Practices Commission (1982) 153 CLR 134 for the proposition that an employee cannot assert the privilege of self-incrimination on behalf of a corporation [at that time corporations were still thought to have such a privilege] because the privilege is personal to the holder). To put it another way, the ASIC investigator was legally correct when he told counsel for AWB that "[n]either ... could [the employees] make the claim [of privilege on behalf of AWB] nor [could they] waive the claim...": [12] above.

30 That conclusion sounds, at least at first blush, as harsh or unjust. Even Mason J, in holding that an employee could not claim privilege against self-incrimination on behalf of his or her corporate employer in order to resist a subpoena, accepted that ( Rochfort at 145):
 
 
 To acknowledge that the employee's possession [of privileged information] is sufficient in itself to sustain an obligation to produce, without reference to his employer, would be to disregard the employer's rights with respect to his documents. What is more it would deprive him of the privilege of objecting to produce a document on the ground that it has a tendency to incriminate him. 
 
 

However, closer examination reveals both why this result is not as harsh as it first seems and why it is necessary.

31 First, although the examination under s 19 of the ASIC Act is private, it is an examination where "the inspector may give directions about who may be present during it, or during a part of it": s 22(1). If a direction is made for a person to attend, that person is entitled to attend the examination: s 22(2). The "person" referred to in s 22 is not the examinee's lawyer. The right of the examinee's lawyer to attend and address the inspector is separately and expressly provided for in s 23. Who then could that person be? One obvious contender is the legal adviser of the examinee's employer in circumstances such as those outlined in the extracts of the transcript (see [10] above). But ASIC did not permit that to occur. The power to make directions must include directions not only about the identity of the legal representative who might be entitled to attend on behalf of the company at any examination, but also about the non-disclosure of the contents of the examination to any person or entity (including the entity seeking to protect its privileged communications).

32 Of course, there cannot be a general rule that a legal representative of the employer or the former employer of the examinee should be permitted to attend to protect the employer's privilege. There may well be circumstances where to do so would jeopardise the investigation: see eg Gangemi v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2003] FCA 494 ; (2003) 129 FCR 284 at [35] , [38]; see also Rochfort at 145 (Mason J) (stating that request for the production of privileged information should generally be directed to the employer but "the protection of the employer's interests [in the information] must give way to the public interest in the efficient administration of justice in case of collision between the two"). But in the absence of such a circumstance, the voluntary grant by ASIC of a limited right to be present in the manner outlined by counsel for AWB might have forestalled the issues raised in these proceedings.

36 I should also note that examinees were even given an opportunity to raise an issue as to a possible third-party privilege. No doubt this is the best policy, but whether it was required as a matter of law may be doubted: see Rochfort at 145-47 (noting that in general effort should be made to respect potential interests of the third-party lawyer but that there are various circumstances where the interests of justice will trump protection of those interests). In MM , Emmett J held that a person must be given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of others as well as himself or herself. In support of this proposition, his Honour relied on the Full Court's decision in Citibank ; however, that decision was disapproved by the later Full Court decision in JMA . Moreover, the conclusion in MM rested on a premise which may be in doubt. Emmett J reasoned (at [35]) that an examinee "would be obliged to make claims for privilege in respect of documents where the privilege might reasonably be expected to exist in order to ensure that such a claim for privilege would not be lost ." (Emphasis added.) In other words, his Honour found that the obligation to make a claim on behalf of others must exist in order to prevent waiver. However, as I have already noted, and as the parties in this case recognised from the start, only the holder of the privilege may waive it. Thus there is no possibility that the failure of an employee to claim privilege on behalf of the corporation would result in waiver or loss of the privilege (except perhaps where the employee is authorised to waive the privilege). To the contrary, it is precisely if a general duty to claim the privilege is imposed that a risk of waiver arises - that is, imagine that an employee under a duty was given a reasonable opportunity to claim privilege on behalf of the employer but failed to do so; under Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 that would be conduct inconsistent with the maintenance of the privilege and would mean that any employee, without the knowledge or authority of the corporate employer, could waive the corporation's privilege. For those reasons, it does not seem either necessary or wise to impose a general obligation on an examinee to claim privilege on behalf of a third party, nor to create a general obligation on behalf of the examiner to give the examinee a reasonable opportunity to make such a claim. While an employee may have an obligation in contract or equity to maintain the confidences of his or her employer ( NP Generations Pty Ltd v Feneley (2001) 80 SASR 151 at [16]-[19]), that cannot be converted into an ability to control the exercise of the employer's legal professional privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>United States v Western Electric Corp Inc 1990-1 Trade Cases |P 68,939; 1990 WL 39129 (DDC 1990)</tocase>
<text>33 However, neither AWB nor AWBI took any step to review the decision of the investigator to refuse to permit AWB to be represented at the examinations. Whether such an effort would have succeeded seems unlikely (see [36]-[37] below); in this regard, it is illuminating to examine United States v Western Electric Corp Inc 1990-1 Trade Cases |P 68,939; 1990 WL 39129 at *1 (DDC 1990) (stating that the company had no right to have its own counsel present, whether in addition to or in lieu of individual counsel, at examinations of present or former employees because that "would be an obvious prescription for frustrating investigations into wrongdoing").</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wrench LLC v Taco Bell Corporation 212 FRD 514 (WD Mich 2002)</tocase>
<text>28 If, however, ASIC meant to submit not that it could compel a person (here, an employee or former employee) to disclose a third party's (here, a company's) privilege by force of statute, but rather that the person may lack the standing to assert the third party's privilege, then that contention may be accepted. Just as an employee can only waive a corporation's privilege if he or she has authority to do so (typically, where the person is a current officer or director), so too may an employee only assert a claim of privilege belonging to a corporation if he or she has the requisite authority: Commodity Futures Trading Commission v Weintraub [1985] USSC 102 ; 471 US 343 , 348-49 (1985); In re Grand Jury Proceedings [2006] USCA1 234 ; 469 F3d 24 (1 st Cir 2006); Wrench LLC v Taco Bell Corporation 212 FRD 514 , 517 (WD Mich 2002) (collecting cases); see also S McNicol, Law of Privilege (1992) at 161-62 (citing Rochfort v Trade Practices Commission (1982) 153 CLR 134 for the proposition that an employee cannot assert the privilege of self-incrimination on behalf of a corporation [at that time corporations were still thought to have such a privilege] because the privilege is personal to the holder). To put it another way, the ASIC investigator was legally correct when he told counsel for AWB that "[n]either ... could [the employees] make the claim [of privilege on behalf of AWB] nor [could they] waive the claim...": [12] above.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>