<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGUP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 183 (29 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/183.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/71.html</AustLII>
<text>18 In written submissions, the appellant argued that this reasoning showed that the Tribunal failed to understand and properly apply s 91R(1)(a) and (2) of the Act , because it did not address whether belonging to the relevant social group led to persecution (within the Act ), but instead assessed another social group (sexually overt people of any persuasion) that was not before the Tribunal. Put another way, the appellant submitted that the Tribunal failed to consider whether he would be persecuted because of his imputed membership of the social group that was the subject of his claim. If the Court accepted this submission, it would establish relevant error: see Appellant S395/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 71 ; (2003) 216 CLR 473 (" S395/2002 ") at 486 [31] per McHugh and Kirby JJ.

19 The appellant also maintained that the same passage showed a second error, because, as their Honours said in S395/2002 at 491 [46], in considering the very same law, "the Tribunal was obliged to go on to consider the other implications of the existence of the law in respect of possible persecution". He submitted that the Tribunal failed to do so. The appellant also contended that his Honour not only erred in failing to appreciate this but also "by finding that the Tribunal found that the appellant could live in Bangladesh 'without being imputed with homosexuality'". The appellant argued that the Tribunal made no such finding and merely found that "persecution on that ground would not constitute persecution for a Convention reason based on the flawed reasoning" to which he referred. The appellant augmented these arguments at the hearing.

20 Following these submissions, the appellant was granted leave to file an amended notice of appeal, which included two further grounds. They read as follows:
 
 
 4. His Honour erred in finding that the Tribunal's decision was not affected by jurisdictional error in that the Tribunal failed to consider the applicant's claims to fear persecution because of his likely imputed membership of a Particular Social Group being gay men in Bangladesh. 
 5. His Honour erred in finding that the Tribunal's decision was not affected by jurisdictional error in that the Tribunal failed to consider whether gay men (imputed or actual) as a Particular Social Group were the subject of persecution in Bangladesh for the purposes of the Convention as modified by the Act .

21 It suffices to say that the first respondent contended that none of the grounds of appeal were made out.

32 This case is different from S395/2002 , because in this case the Tribunal found that: (1) the appellant was not in fact homosexual; (2) the appellant had fabricated his claim to be homosexual in order to support his protection visa application; (3) although a homosexual demeanour might be attributed to him in Australia (on account of his activities here) it was unlikely that these activities or subsequent activities in Bangladesh would result in a homosexual demeanour being attributed to him in Bangladesh; and (4) even if such a demeanour were attributed to him, he would not be subjected to serious harm amounting to persecution for a Convention reason. In contrast to S395/2002 , this is not a case where the Tribunal made a decision adverse to an applicant upon the basis that he could avoid persecution by modifying his customary behaviour.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Applicant S20/2002 (2003)198 ALR 59</tocase>
<text>22 As already noted, the Tribunal referred to the fact that the appellant applied for a protection visa on 31 May 2005, which was over three years after his arrival in Australia. I reject the assertion implicit in ground 1 of the appellant's notice of appeal that the Federal Magistrate erred in holding that it was not irrational or unreasonable for the Tribunal to give weight to the consideration that the applicant made no claim to fear persecution in Bangladesh as a homosexual prior to May 2005. The appellant's delay in lodging a protection visa application was one factor that the Tribunal was entitled to take into account and to give such weight as the Tribunal thought appropriate in all the circumstances of the case. The Federal Magistrate did not err in this regard. Further, the Federal Magistrate did not err in his consideration of the Tribunal's treatment of the opinions of the psychiatrists and psychologist, or other lay witnesses. The Tribunal plainly considered both expert and lay witnesses' evidence and it was entitled to treat their evidence as it did. The Tribunal was not obliged to accept the evidence of expert opinion but was entitled to evaluate it as it did. The Tribunal specifically referred to earlier lay witnesses who claimed to have had sexual relations with the appellant, saying it did not "attach any weight" to their evidence because it found that the appellant had manufactured his claims to be a homosexual. It was open to the Tribunal to approach their evidence in this way. The appellant submitted that this approach was illogical, but illogicality on its own, even if demonstrated, does not establish jurisdictional error: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Applicant S20/2002 (2003)198 ALR 59 (" Applicant S20/2002 ") at 60-64 per Gleeson CJ. The appellant's argument at this level was very largely "an emphatic way of expressing disagreement" (to use the words of Gleeson CJ) with the Tribunal's fact finding: see Applicant S20/2002 at 61.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZATV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 40 ; (2007) 237 ALR 634</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/40.html</AustLII>
<text>23 This ground alleged that the Federal Magistrate erred in dismissing the ground of jurisdictional error because, in making its finding about relocation, the Tribunal failed to consider a number of matters relating, broadly speaking, to the practicalities of relocation. The ground is not made out. The Tribunal applied the relocation test, as set out in SZATV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 40 ; (2007) 237 ALR 634 and SZFDV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 41 ; (2007) 237 ALR 660. It inquired as to whether it was reasonable, in the sense of practicable, for the appellant to relocate, given the circumstances of his case, including his personal circumstances relating to education, language ability, family situation and work prospects.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZFDV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 41 ; (2007) 237 ALR 660</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/41.html</AustLII>
<text>23 This ground alleged that the Federal Magistrate erred in dismissing the ground of jurisdictional error because, in making its finding about relocation, the Tribunal failed to consider a number of matters relating, broadly speaking, to the practicalities of relocation. The ground is not made out. The Tribunal applied the relocation test, as set out in SZATV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 40 ; (2007) 237 ALR 634 and SZFDV v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 41 ; (2007) 237 ALR 660. It inquired as to whether it was reasonable, in the sense of practicable, for the appellant to relocate, given the circumstances of his case, including his personal circumstances relating to education, language ability, family situation and work prospects.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam [1999] FCA 794 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/794.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Once the Tribunal's actual findings are set out in this way, it is plain enough that grounds 4 and 5 fail. The Tribunal plainly rejected the appellant's claim to be homosexual. At the same time, it allowed for the possibility that a homosexual demeanour might be attributed to him in Australia on account of his involvement in the CAAH and his association with homosexuals in Australia. It held, however, that it was unlikely that his involvement in CAAH or his association with homosexuals in Australia would result in a homosexual demeanour being attributed to him in Bangladesh. It also held that it was unlikely that he would continue activities of this kind on returning to Bangladesh (since they were done in Australia to enhance his refugee claim). Notwithstanding this, however, in accordance with Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam [1999] FCA 794 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220 (" Rajalingam ") at 62-63, the Tribunal went on to consider the appellant's situation in what it saw as the unlikely event that this attribution or imputation was made in Bangladesh. In this regard, the Tribunal was not satisfied that the appellant would "be subject to serious harm amounting to persecution".

28 If the passage set out at [17] above is understood in this way, it is apparent that no error of the kind for which the appellant contends has occurred. That is, in the Tribunal's reasons, the passage can be read as intended to support the proposition that there is no real chance of serious harm befalling a person in Bangladesh on account of overt (and a fortiori covert) homosexual behaviour.

29 Another passage towards the conclusion of the Tribunal's reasons, on which the appellant relied, must also be read in the light of the findings and in the entirety of the Tribunal's reasons. In this passage, the Tribunal referred first to the provision of country information by the appellant's adviser and to her submission about a lack of state protection. It then commented:
 
 While accepting that Bangladesh is at the moment experiencing severe political disruption and turmoil, and there is some politically orientated violence, the Tribunal has not been able to find any evidence that homosexual males, and even more importantly than [sic] those people like the Applicant who may have a gay demeanour or association imputed to them, are being subject to a particular persecution or are being targeted at this time because of it or that there has been a breakdown in effective state protection for this particular social group. Accordingly, in view of all the above and its earlier findings, the Tribunal does not accept this claim and is satisfied that there is not a real chance that the Applicant would be subject to serious harm amounting to persecution for a Convention reason (including his particular social group, actual or imputed) because of the current political difficulties in Bangladesh.

30 The appellant argued that the expression "like the Applicant" indicated that the Tribunal made a positive finding concerning the imputation of a homosexual demeanour to the appellant in Bangladesh. When this passage is read in the context of the Tribunal's entire reasons, as indeed the Tribunal expressly invited the reader to do, it is clear that this is not so. In this passage, the Tribunal was doing no more than responding to the appellant's adviser's submission concerning effective state protection upon the basis required by Rajalingam. That is, it was considering the appellant's position in what it saw as the unlikely event that an imputation of homosexuality was made in Bangladesh. In this regard, the Tribunal was not satisfied that there was a real chance that the appellant would be subjected to serious harm amounting to persecution for a Convention reason.

31 When the Tribunal's actual findings are stated, it is apparent that the Tribunal gave consideration to the appellant's claims to fear persecution because of "his ... imputed membership of a Particular Social Group being gay men in Bangladesh" (compare ground 4), although it considered the imputation in Bangladesh to be unlikely. In this latter regard, ground 4 misstates the Tribunal's finding. The Tribunal gave this question consideration in accordance with its obligation as outlined in Rajalingam . Ground 4 is therefore not sustainable. Similarly and on the same basis, the Tribunal gave attention to the question "whether gay men (imputed or actual) as a Particular Social Group were the subject of persecution in Bangladesh for the purposes of the Convention as modified by the Act ". Ground 5 also fails. Examination of the Tribunal's reasons and the appellant's submissions shows that the appellant's real argument is with the merits of the Tribunal's decision. This is not, however, a matter that properly falls for consideration in the Federal Magistrates Court on judicial review or in this Court on appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Zhang v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 30</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/30.html</AustLII>
<text>33 Thus far, I have not found it necessary to refer to the guiding principle, that the reasons of the Tribunal are to be read fairly and as a whole, and not "with an eye attuned to the ready perception of error": see in Zhang v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 30 (" Zhang ") at [14] per Moore, Mansfield and Dowsett JJ, citing Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shang Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 271-272 and 291. This principle confirms that the Tribunal's reason should be read in their entirety, without undue emphasis on individual expressions that, by themselves, can take on a meaning different from that clearly intended when regard is had to their proper context. The appellant's argument, it seems to me, paid insufficient regard to this principle.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shang Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>33 Thus far, I have not found it necessary to refer to the guiding principle, that the reasons of the Tribunal are to be read fairly and as a whole, and not "with an eye attuned to the ready perception of error": see in Zhang v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 30 (" Zhang ") at [14] per Moore, Mansfield and Dowsett JJ, citing Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shang Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 271-272 and 291. This principle confirms that the Tribunal's reason should be read in their entirety, without undue emphasis on individual expressions that, by themselves, can take on a meaning different from that clearly intended when regard is had to their proper context. The appellant's argument, it seems to me, paid insufficient regard to this principle.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>