<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 (29 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/178.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corp Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385</tocase>
<text>53 In D&eacute;cor Corp Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, Sheppard J distilled ten rules of construction from the authorities:
 
 
 (1) The claims define the invention which is the subject of the patent. These must be construed according to their terms upon ordinary principles. Any purely verbal or grammatical question that can be answered according to ordinary rules for the construction of written documents is to be resolved accordingly. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (2) It is not legitimate to confine the scope of the claims by reference to limitations which may be found in the body of the specification but are not expressly or by proper inference reproduced in the claims themselves. To put it another way, it is not legitimate to narrow or expand the boundaries of monopoly as fixed by the words of a claim by adding to those words glosses drawn from other parts of the specification. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (3) Nevertheless, in approaching the task of construction, one must read the specification as a whole. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (4) In some cases the meaning of the words used in the claims may be qualified or defined by what is said in the body of the specification. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (5) If a claim be clear, it is not to be made obscure because obscurities can be found in particular sentences in other parts of the document. But if an expression is not clear or is ambiguous, it is permissible to resort to the body of the specification to define or clarify the meaning of words used in the claim. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (6) A patent specification should be given a purposive construction rather than a purely literal one. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (7) In construing the specification, the court is not construing a written instrument operating inter partes , but a public instrument which must define a monopoly in such a way that it is not reasonably capable of being misunderstood. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (8) The body, apart from the preamble, is there to instruct those skilled in the art concerned in the carrying out of the invention; provided it is comprehensive to, and does not mislead, a skilled reader, the language used is seldom of importance. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (9) Nevertheless, the claims, since they define the monopoly, will be scrutinised with as much care as is used in construing other documents defining a legal right. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (10) If it is impossible to ascertain what the invention is from a fair reading of the specification as a whole, it will be invalid. But the specification must be construed in the light of the common knowledge in the art before the priority date.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Ltd v Arico Trading International Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/8.html</AustLII>
<text>55 The High Court recently confirmed in Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Ltd v Arico Trading International Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1 that the specification and claims must not be read in the abstract. Rather, the specification and claims must be construed in light of the common general knowledge and the art before the priority date. Chief Justice Gleeson, McHugh, Gummow, Hayne and Callinan JJ said at [24]:
 
 ...[the complete specification] is to be construed in the light of the common general knowledge and the art before...the priority date; the court is to place itself "in the position of some person acquainted with the surrounding circumstances as to the state of [the] art and manufacture at the time.

143 Nufarm, quoting Kimberly-Clark Australia 207 CLR at 16 [24], agrees that the specification and claims must be 'construed in the light of the common general knowledge and the art before ... the priority date'. It is also not disputed that the Merck patent (obtained in the US in 1983) predates the Nufarm priority date of 4 June 1999.

144 Jurox contended that the 'Merck [p]atent and the micellar solutions described in it, including IVOMEC&reg; [the commercial embodiment of the patent], were common general knowledge at the priority date. The references in the [Nufarm] patent to "emulsions" should be understood against that background, i.e. they do not encompass micellar solutions'.

145 Jurox argues that the evidence supports their view. In this regard they cite the testimony of their expert, Mr Shepherd. Moreover, they note that Nufarm's expert Dr Lichti conceded on cross-examination that Merck patents generally are considered sources of knowledge for skilled addressees in the field.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kirin-Amgen Inc v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444</tocase>
<text>56 More recently, Bennett J made the following observations in Sachtler GMBH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd (2005) 221 ALR 373 at [42] (referred to by the Full Court in Synthetic Turf Development Pty Limited v Sports Technology International Pty Limited (2005) 67 IPR 475):
 
 &#8226; When determining the nature and extent of the monopoly claimed, the specification must be read as a whole. As a whole it is made up of several parts and those parts have different functions. The claim, cast in precise language, marks out the legal limits of the monopoly granted by the patent. What is not claimed is disclaimed. The specification describes how to carry out the process claimed and the best method known to the patentee of doing that: Beltreco at [73]. 
 &#8226; Although the claims are construed in the context of the specification as a whole, it is not legitimate to narrow or expand the boundaries of monopoly, as fixed by the words of a claim, by adding to those words glosses drawn from other parts of the specification. If a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be varied, qualified or made obscure by statements found in other parts of the document: Beltreco at [74]. 
 &#8226; Terms in the claim which are unclear may be defined or clarified by reference to the body of the specification: Welch Perrin at 610; Interlego at 479, both approved in Kimberly-Clark at [15]. 
 &#8226; Reference may be made to the body of the specification to understand the context in which words have been used: Beltreco at [77] following Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 at 272. 
 &#8226; It is legitimate to refer to the rest of the specification to explain the background to the claims, to ascertain the meaning of technical terms and to resolve ambiguities in the construction of the claims. Where the language of the claim is obscure or doubtful the doubt is sometimes resolved by referring to words in the body of the document to explain it: Beltreco at [75]. 
 &#8226; It is not necessary first to construe the claims without reference to the specification and then to determine whether or not ambiguity exists: D&eacute;cor at 410; Beltreco at [76]; PhotoCure at [174]. 
 &#8226; There is a fine line between, on the one hand, reading down the words of a patent claim to reflect how a person skilled in the art would understand it in a practical and commonsense way and, on the other hand, impermissibly limiting the clear words of a claim because a reader skilled in the art would be likely to apply those wide words only in a limited range of all the situations they describe: Stanway Oyster Cylinders Pty Ltd v Marks (1996) 66 FCR 577 at 585 per Drummond J. 
 &#8226; The construction of the claim determines infringement, on both textual and substantive bases: Catnic Components Limited v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 at 242 at 242; PhotoCure at [158]. It is a question of whether the alleged infringement is covered by the language of the claim: Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181 at 189-190 cited in Photocure at [158]. 
 &#8226; A patent should be given a purposive construction: Catnic at 242-3. However, that does not involve extending or going beyond the definition of the technical matter for which the patentee seeks protection in the claims. The question is always what the person skilled in the art would have understood the patentee to be using the language of the claim to mean. For this purpose, the language chosen is usually of critical importance: Kirin-Amgen Inc v Hoeschst Marion Roussel Ltd [2004] UKHL 46 ; (2004) 64 IPR 444; [2005] 1 All ER 667 at [34] . 
 &#8226; Purposive construction, permitting consideration of whether the person skilled in the art would understand a variant that does not strictly comply with the particular descriptive word used in the claim may still fall within the monopoly, does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material effect upon the way the invention worked: Catnic at 243; Kirin-Amgen at [50].

57 It is clear that in construction of patents, one is not concerned with what the author meant to say. It is rather, what the notional addressee would have understood the author to mean by using those words: see Kirin-Amgen Inc v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444 per Lord Hoffman at [32]. His Lordship went on to consider at [34] what is meant by 'purposive construction', as follows:
 
 "Purposive construction" does not mean that one is extending or going beyond the definition of the technical matter for which the patentee seeks protection in the claims. The question is always what the person skilled in the art would have understood the patentee to be using the language of the claim to mean. And for this purpose, the language he has chosen is usually of critical importance. The conventions of word meaning and syntax enable us to express our meanings with great accuracy and subtlety and the skilled man will ordinarily assume that the patentee has chosen his language accordingly. As a number of judges have pointed out, the specification is a unilateral documents in words of the patentee's own choosing. Furthermore, the words will usually have been chosen upon skilled advice. The specification is not a document inter rusticos for which broad allowances must be made. On the other hand, it must be recognised that the patentee is trying to describe something which, at any rate in his opinion, is new; which has not existed before and of which there may be no generally accepted definition. There will be occasions upon which it will be obvious to the skilled man that the patentee must in some respect have departed from conventional use of language or included in his description of the invention some element which he did not mean to be essential. But one would not expect that to happen very often.

58 It is well settled that the plain and unambiguous meaning of a claim cannot be varied or qualified by reference to the body of the specification. In particular, it is not legitimate, in the absence of an express reference in the claim itself to import into a claim, features of the preferred embodiment. The preferred embodiment cannot be used to introduce into the definite words of a claim an additional definition or qualification of the patentee's invention.

59 The dispute between the parties stems from ambiguities which exist as a result of certain wording used in the patent. Fundamentally, those ambiguities reflect a difference of opinions within the relevant audience, namely the skilled addressee, as to the proper meaning of the words 'emulsion' and 'phase'. I set out below a relatively brief summary of the competing views as to the correct definition of these words, along with some other chemical principles and concepts which are relevant to the current dispute and to the evidence which was given during the course of the trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Populin v HB Nominees Pty Ltd (1982) 41 ALR 471</tocase>
<text>52 In determining the meaning to be given to the words of a patent claim the court must make a 'common sense assessment of what the words used convey' in the context of the knowledge prevailing in the relevant art at the priority date. In Populin v HB Nominees Pty Ltd (1982) 41 ALR 471 the Full Court stated at 476:
 
 The complete specification must not be read in the abstract but in the light of common knowledge in the art before the priority date, bearing in mind that what is being construed is a public instrument which must, if it is to be valid, define a monopoly in such a way that it is not reasonably capable of being misunderstood (see generally Welch Perrin &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Worrel [1960] HCA 91 ; (1961) 106 CLR 588 at 610). The essential features of the product or process for which it claims a monopoly are to be determined not as a matter of abstract uninformed construction but by a common sense assessment of what the words used convey in the context of then-existing published knowledge.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd (2000) 49 IPR 225</tocase>
<text>49 In Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd (2000) 49 IPR 225 at 241-242 Finkelstein J stated:
 
 Generally speaking the skilled addressee is the person who works in the art or science with which the invention is connected. In Plimpton v Malcolmson (1876) 3 ChD 531 Jessel MR said (at 556): 
 
 
 
 What is meant is that if [the invention] is a manufacture connected with a particular trade, the people in the trade shall know something about it; if it is a thing connected with a chemical invention, people conversant with chemistry shall know something about it. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 In Catnic Lord Diplock said (at 242) that skilled addressees are "those likely to have a practical interest in the subject matter of [the] invention". A variety of people may have that interest. There are those who might wish to make or construct the invention, those who may wish to compound the invention and those who may wish to use the invention. The skilled addressee seems to me to be a relative expression which does not identify any specific person. Because the patent is directed to a person interested in making, constructing, compounding or using the invention (see for example s 27(3)(b) of the Patent Act 1993 (Canada); International Standard Electric Corporation v Ooms 157 F2d 73 (1946)), this hypothetical person, the patent lawyer's "reasonable man", may be required to be skilled in more than one art. Such a person might be thought of as the composite being, mentioned by Buckley LJ in Tetra Molectric at 583. It may be preferable not to search for a composite addressee but a team whose combined skills are to be employed.

50 The relevant skilled addressee for the purposes of this proceeding is a person skilled in chemistry, and particularly physical chemistry.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sachtler GMBH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd (2005) 221 ALR 373</tocase>
<text>56 More recently, Bennett J made the following observations in Sachtler GMBH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd (2005) 221 ALR 373 at [42] (referred to by the Full Court in Synthetic Turf Development Pty Limited v Sports Technology International Pty Limited (2005) 67 IPR 475):
 
 &#8226; When determining the nature and extent of the monopoly claimed, the specification must be read as a whole. As a whole it is made up of several parts and those parts have different functions. The claim, cast in precise language, marks out the legal limits of the monopoly granted by the patent. What is not claimed is disclaimed. The specification describes how to carry out the process claimed and the best method known to the patentee of doing that: Beltreco at [73]. 
 &#8226; Although the claims are construed in the context of the specification as a whole, it is not legitimate to narrow or expand the boundaries of monopoly, as fixed by the words of a claim, by adding to those words glosses drawn from other parts of the specification. If a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be varied, qualified or made obscure by statements found in other parts of the document: Beltreco at [74]. 
 &#8226; Terms in the claim which are unclear may be defined or clarified by reference to the body of the specification: Welch Perrin at 610; Interlego at 479, both approved in Kimberly-Clark at [15]. 
 &#8226; Reference may be made to the body of the specification to understand the context in which words have been used: Beltreco at [77] following Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 at 272. 
 &#8226; It is legitimate to refer to the rest of the specification to explain the background to the claims, to ascertain the meaning of technical terms and to resolve ambiguities in the construction of the claims. Where the language of the claim is obscure or doubtful the doubt is sometimes resolved by referring to words in the body of the document to explain it: Beltreco at [75]. 
 &#8226; It is not necessary first to construe the claims without reference to the specification and then to determine whether or not ambiguity exists: D&eacute;cor at 410; Beltreco at [76]; PhotoCure at [174]. 
 &#8226; There is a fine line between, on the one hand, reading down the words of a patent claim to reflect how a person skilled in the art would understand it in a practical and commonsense way and, on the other hand, impermissibly limiting the clear words of a claim because a reader skilled in the art would be likely to apply those wide words only in a limited range of all the situations they describe: Stanway Oyster Cylinders Pty Ltd v Marks (1996) 66 FCR 577 at 585 per Drummond J. 
 &#8226; The construction of the claim determines infringement, on both textual and substantive bases: Catnic Components Limited v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 at 242 at 242; PhotoCure at [158]. It is a question of whether the alleged infringement is covered by the language of the claim: Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181 at 189-190 cited in Photocure at [158]. 
 &#8226; A patent should be given a purposive construction: Catnic at 242-3. However, that does not involve extending or going beyond the definition of the technical matter for which the patentee seeks protection in the claims. The question is always what the person skilled in the art would have understood the patentee to be using the language of the claim to mean. For this purpose, the language chosen is usually of critical importance: Kirin-Amgen Inc v Hoeschst Marion Roussel Ltd [2004] UKHL 46 ; (2004) 64 IPR 444; [2005] 1 All ER 667 at [34] . 
 &#8226; Purposive construction, permitting consideration of whether the person skilled in the art would understand a variant that does not strictly comply with the particular descriptive word used in the claim may still fall within the monopoly, does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material effect upon the way the invention worked: Catnic at 243; Kirin-Amgen at [50].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sartas No 1 Pty Ltd v Koukourou &amp; Partners Pty Ltd (1994) 30 IPR 479</tocase>
<text>51 The question of infringement is prefaced by a proper understanding of what is described in the body of the specification and a proper construction of the claims: see Sartas No 1 Pty Ltd v Koukourou &amp; Partners Pty Ltd (1994) 30 IPR 479 at 486 per Gummow J.

54 In Sartas No 1 30 IPR at 485-486, Gummow J set out the following propositions:
 
 The construction of the patent plainly is a matter of primary importance in the litigation. In Glaverbel SA v British Coal Corp [1994] RPC 443 at 485-486, Mummery J set out a number of what his Lordship said were uncontroversial propositions as to construction. Some of these are certainly applicable here, as being in accordance with the development of the law in Australia. From what was said by his Lordship useful guidance, in particular, is to be derived from the following propositions. Some of them were applied in rulings on evidence in the course of the trial. They are: 
 
 
 
 (1) It is for the court, not for any witness, however expert, to decide the question of construction in accordance with the meaning of the language used. Evidence can be given by experts to enlighten the judge on the meaning which those skilled in the art would give to technical or scientific terms and phrases and on unusual or special meanings given by such persons to words which might otherwise bear their ordinary meaning. 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 ( Cf Agfa-Gevaert Ltd v Collector of Customs (1994) 124 ALR 645.) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (2) The specification should be construed without reference to the prior documents relied on as a ground for invalidity with a view to avoiding the effect of the prior documents. A fortiori, documents subsequent to the complete specification are inadmissible in aid of its construction.
 
 (3) ... it is not permissible to construe the claims by reference to the subjective thoughts, intentions, purposes and opinions of the patentee or his witnesses or by reference to his actions before or after the grant of the patent.
 
 (4) In reading the specification as a whole the different functions of the claim and the rest of the specification should be observed. The claim, cast in precise language, marks out the legal limits of the monopoly granted by the patent: and "what is not claimed is disclaimed". The specification describes how to carry out the process claimed and the best method known to the patentee of doing that. Although the claims are construed in the context of the specification as a whole, it is not permissible to restrict, expand or amend the clear language of a claim by reference to a limitation or gloss in the language used in the earlier part of the specification, but not repeated in the claim itself. It is legitimate , however, to refer to the rest of the specification to explain the background to the claims, to ascertain the meaning of the technical terms and resolve ambiguities in the construction of the claims .
 
 
 
 The passage which I have emphasised is better understood by reference to the remarks of Taylor J in Martin v Scribal Pty Ltd [1954] HCA 48 ; (1954) 92 CLR 17 at 97 (affd [1956] HCA 32 ; 95 CLR 213 (PC)): 
 
 
 
 Plain language must be given its plain meaning, and clear words in a claim must not be tortured into an unnatural meaning by importing passages from the body of the specification: see Lord Russell's speech in Electrical and Musical Industries Ltd v Lissen Ltd (1939) 56 RPC at 41, line 34). The claims must also be construed without an eye on the alleged infringer's acts. (So said Greene LJ in RCA Photophone Ltd v Gaumont British Picture Corp (1936) 53 RPC at 202, line 16). On the other hand, it is right to construe a claim with an eye benevolent to the inventor and with a view to making the invention work this is an application of the old doctrine ut res magis valeat quam pereat and is illustrated in Nobel's Case (1894) 11 RPC at 524; and, where the language of a claim is obscure or doubtful, the doubt may sometimes be resolved by referring to words in the body of the document to explain it. This is known as the dictionary principle: see Lord Haldane's speech in British Thomson-Houston Co Ltd v Corona Lamp Works Ltd (1921) 39 RPC at 67, line 44).
 
 
 
 See also Melbourne v Terry Fluid Controls Pty Ltd (1994) AIPC 91-058 at 38,214; CCOM Pty Ltd v Jiejing Pty Ltd (1994) 122 ALR 417 at 424.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Synthetic Turf Development Pty Limited v Sports Technology International Pty Limited (2005) 67 IPR 475</tocase>
<text>56 More recently, Bennett J made the following observations in Sachtler GMBH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd (2005) 221 ALR 373 at [42] (referred to by the Full Court in Synthetic Turf Development Pty Limited v Sports Technology International Pty Limited (2005) 67 IPR 475):
 
 &#8226; When determining the nature and extent of the monopoly claimed, the specification must be read as a whole. As a whole it is made up of several parts and those parts have different functions. The claim, cast in precise language, marks out the legal limits of the monopoly granted by the patent. What is not claimed is disclaimed. The specification describes how to carry out the process claimed and the best method known to the patentee of doing that: Beltreco at [73]. 
 &#8226; Although the claims are construed in the context of the specification as a whole, it is not legitimate to narrow or expand the boundaries of monopoly, as fixed by the words of a claim, by adding to those words glosses drawn from other parts of the specification. If a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be varied, qualified or made obscure by statements found in other parts of the document: Beltreco at [74]. 
 &#8226; Terms in the claim which are unclear may be defined or clarified by reference to the body of the specification: Welch Perrin at 610; Interlego at 479, both approved in Kimberly-Clark at [15]. 
 &#8226; Reference may be made to the body of the specification to understand the context in which words have been used: Beltreco at [77] following Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 at 272. 
 &#8226; It is legitimate to refer to the rest of the specification to explain the background to the claims, to ascertain the meaning of technical terms and to resolve ambiguities in the construction of the claims. Where the language of the claim is obscure or doubtful the doubt is sometimes resolved by referring to words in the body of the document to explain it: Beltreco at [75]. 
 &#8226; It is not necessary first to construe the claims without reference to the specification and then to determine whether or not ambiguity exists: D&eacute;cor at 410; Beltreco at [76]; PhotoCure at [174]. 
 &#8226; There is a fine line between, on the one hand, reading down the words of a patent claim to reflect how a person skilled in the art would understand it in a practical and commonsense way and, on the other hand, impermissibly limiting the clear words of a claim because a reader skilled in the art would be likely to apply those wide words only in a limited range of all the situations they describe: Stanway Oyster Cylinders Pty Ltd v Marks (1996) 66 FCR 577 at 585 per Drummond J. 
 &#8226; The construction of the claim determines infringement, on both textual and substantive bases: Catnic Components Limited v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 at 242 at 242; PhotoCure at [158]. It is a question of whether the alleged infringement is covered by the language of the claim: Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181 at 189-190 cited in Photocure at [158]. 
 &#8226; A patent should be given a purposive construction: Catnic at 242-3. However, that does not involve extending or going beyond the definition of the technical matter for which the patentee seeks protection in the claims. The question is always what the person skilled in the art would have understood the patentee to be using the language of the claim to mean. For this purpose, the language chosen is usually of critical importance: Kirin-Amgen Inc v Hoeschst Marion Roussel Ltd [2004] UKHL 46 ; (2004) 64 IPR 444; [2005] 1 All ER 667 at [34] . 
 &#8226; Purposive construction, permitting consideration of whether the person skilled in the art would understand a variant that does not strictly comply with the particular descriptive word used in the claim may still fall within the monopoly, does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material effect upon the way the invention worked: Catnic at 243; Kirin-Amgen at [50].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>