<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZKLK v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1125 (4 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1125.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>7 Whether or not to grant an extension of time within which to appeal is a matter for the exercise of a discretionary power conferred by O 52 r 15(2). The terms in which that rule confers the discretionary power are such that the only consideration which is expressed to be relevant to its exercise is that "special reasons" must exist. Obviously enough, those "special reasons" must be found in the circumstances of the particular case. Something in the circumstances of one case that provides a "special reason" distinguishing that case from the general position may not when considered against the different context of the circumstances of another. The occasion for the exercise of the power is thus flexible. In Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 , at 196 the Full Court, after a review of authority, repeated a cautionary note which had earlier been sounded against the entanglement of a discretionary power to relax the requirement of a general rule, " in a web of rules spun out of the Court's discretionary decisions ".

8 This cautionary note sounded, factors to which it is nonetheless usual to have regard are the length of the delay in compliance with the specified time for the lodgement of a notice of appeal, the explanation, if any, for the delay, what prejudice, if any, might be occasioned by the grant of an extension (although mere absence of prejudice is not determinative) and the merits of the proposed appeal.

9 The Applicant was represented (using the relevant letterhead as a guide) by a dual qualified solicitor and migration agent in the proceedings before the Tribunal and by that same person, acting in her capacity as a solicitor, as well as counsel in the proceedings before the Federal Magistrates Court. He appeared on his own behalf in the application to this Court, assisted by a Court appointed interpreter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>WAAD v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCAFC 399</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/399.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In WAAD v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCAFC 399 , at [7] the Full Court gave a reminder that the purpose for which the discretion to extend time is conferred is to do justice between the parties observing of an example where the delay was short and no injustice would be occasioned to a respondent that justice would usually be done if the extension of time were granted.

15 There could be no shorter delay than that presented in this case. No prejudice to the Minister was asserted. In such circumstances the question of the applicant's prospects of success in the proposed appeal has a determinative quality in relation to the exercise of the discretion to extend time.

16 Only one ground of appeal is specified in that draft notice of appeal. That is that the learned Federal Magistrate erred in failing to find the following alleged jurisdictional error:
 "I have been a Falun Gong practitioner since 1999. I persecuted by the Chinese authorities. I presented the documents: "Labour Reform Relief Assessment Form" and "[Named] People's Hospital Diagnosis" issued by the official authorities were not accepted by the Tribunal. I think the Tribunal has bias against me. The Tribunal didn't take my claims into account. The Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error." [sic, omitting name of particular hospital]

17 The way in which the Applicant has formulated his ground of challenge reflects his lack of legal training. That does not mean that it fails to state a ground of challenge known to law. The Minister apprehended that the essence of the desired appeal was that the Federal Magistrates Court had erred in failing to set aside the Tribunal's decision on the basis that a reasonable apprehension of bias on the part of the Tribunal had been shown. This seems to me to be a fair way to approach the matter, especially having regard to the ground of review particularised in the amended application lodged in the Federal Magistrates Court.

18 In the amended application to the Federal Magistrates Court the apprehended bias ground was pleaded in this way:
 
 
 "1. The Tribunal fell into jurisdictional error in that the Tribunal denied the applicant procedural fairness by reason of there being a reasonable apprehension of bias. 
 
 PARTICULARS (a) The fact-finding by the Tribunal was performed in a manner which in major respect was capricious, arbitrary, unreasoned, consisted of assertion, lacked rational or reasoned foundations, and/or was in relation to the preponderance of findings selective of material or conclusions going one way only, such that a fair-minded and informed person might reasonably apprehend that the decision maker might not have brought an impartial mind to bear on the decision. (b) The findings of fact to which the fair-minded and informed person might reasonably have regard in forming the apprehension include: 1. The finding that the applicant has learned a few basic facts about the movement (that being Falun Gong). 2. The finding that the applicant had no apparent knowledge or understanding of the philosophy of Falun Gong. 3. The finding that the applicant had no apparent knowledge or understanding of how it was that practising Falun Gong achieved the benefits and outcomes claimed by practitioners. 4. The applicant had no apparent understanding of the key concept of "truthfulness, benevolence and forbearance". 5. The finding that the applicant had ample opportunity at the hearing to demonstrate his knowledge and/or understanding of Falun Gong. 6. The applicant's discussion of Falun Gong was trite and shallow. 7. The finding that the applicant's account shows that he had given seemingly low priority to Falun Gong in Australia. 8. The finding that the Applicant had changed his evidence in relation to why he had stopped exercising in a park. 9. The finding that the applicant's claim to have participated rather than just observed a singing performance in support of withdrawing from the Communist Party had evolved in response to the Tribunal's questions. 10. The finding that there was a change in evidence in relation to the applicant's contact with Falun Gong practitioners in Australia. 11. The finding that the information contained in the purportedly corroborative documents of the applicants claim as to having been sent to labour reform for detention for one year and suffered injury whilst detained are not genuine and that the Tribunal gives no weight to the documents. 12. The finding that the applicant's failure to advise the Department of the purportedly corroborative documents and the conclusion that the applicant did not hold the documents in October 2006 and that he concocted this claim as to having held the documents at that time. 13. The findings in relation to the document from the [the particular named] People's Hospital to the effect that as the document does not show how the injury came about it went against the claim that he was injured in the way he described. 14. The findings in relation to the applicant's differing statements as to his recollection of one of the names of the policeman who had struck him in May 2002. 15. The findings that the explanation by the applicant as to what happened to the persons who were detained and assaulted with him in May 2002 changed during the hearing thus suggesting that the applicant was fabricating claims and details as he gave evidence at the hearing. 16. The findings in relation to the two day difference appearing in the Labour Reform Relief Assessment Form and the finding that the applicant had dissembled in relation to the date of his detention. 17. The finding that the Tribunal's conclusions were reinforced by the applicant's arrangements to depart China. 18. The finding that there was a difference in the claims made in relation to how the applicant obtained his passport, such that it supported a finding that the applicant was fabricating claims and details as he gave evidence at the hearing. 19. The reliance on the passport being stated as having been issued on 21 January 2005, when the applicants claim was that the passport had been illegally obtained and the Tribunal elsewhere in the Decision accepted the prevalence of the irregular or improper issue of documentation. 20. The rejection of any need to consider whether the applicant or his wife had to get the assistance of a "connection" to get his passport on the basis that the Tribunal did not accept that the applicant was a Falun Gong practitioner known to the authorities. Yet the Tribunal relied on the applicants travel arrangements to find reinforcement for its conclusions concerning his Falun Gong practice. 21. The finding that the Tribunal did not accept that the applicant has had any association with the Falun Gong movement in Australia or has practised Falun Gong in Australia despite, and the failure to have regard to the evidence from the applicant's migration agent that she only represents applicants who claimed to have been Falun Gong practitioners on referral from known Falun Gong practitioners in Australia." (Emphasis by italics in original)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Lusink; Ex Parte Shaw (1980) 55 ALJR 12</tocase>
<text>20 Prior authority counsels that to overturn a decision even on the basis of apprehended bias is no light thing: Re Lusink; Ex Parte Shaw (1980) 55 ALJR 12 , at 14B (Gibbs ACJ); s 140 (2) of the Evidence Act 1995 . It is also salutary to remember that the (in this case) administrative officer in respect of whose decision such an allegation is made is not heard from when the merits of that allegation fall for hearing and determination.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex Parte H [2001] HCA 28 ; (2001) 75 ALJR 982</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/28.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The decision made by the Tribunal was administrative, not judicial, in character. The governing principle is not in doubt, nor was it below, as the reasons for judgment of the learned Federal Magistrate reveal. An authoritative statement of principle is to be found in the judgment of the Full Court of the High Court (Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ) in Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex Parte H [2001] HCA 28 ; (2001) 75 ALJR 982 , at 983, [5]:
 It was held in Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex Parte Aala that administrative decisions may be reviewed in this Court for failure to observe the rules of natural justice. Further, it was accepted in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia that such a failure would extend to cases in which apprehended bias is established. However, the rule with respect to apprehended bias, as it has developed in relation to the judicial process, is not based solely on the concept of natural justice. Its development is also referable to the need to maintain confidence in the judicial process. Thus, the rule as to apprehended bias, when applied outside the judicial system, must take account of the different nature of the body or tribunal whose decision is in issue and the different character of its proceedings. Moreover ... regard must be had to the statutory provisions, if any, applicable to the proceedings in question, the nature of the inquiries to be made and the particular subject-matter with which the decision is concerned. (Internal footnote references omitted).

22 And later in that same case:
 The test for apprehended bias in relation to curial proceedings is whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial mind to the resolution of the question to be decided. That formulation owes much to the fact that court proceedings are held in public. There is some incongruity in formulating a test in terms of "a fair-minded lay observer" when, as is the case with the Tribunal, proceedings are held in private. Perhaps it would be better, in the case of administrative proceedings held in private, to formulate the test for apprehended bias by reference to a hypothetical fair-minded lay person who is properly informed as to the nature of the proceedings, the matters in issue and the conduct which is said to give rise to an apprehension of bias. Whether or not that be the appropriate formulation, there is, in our view, no reason to depart from the objective test of possibility, as distinct from probability, as to what will be done or what might have been done. To do otherwise, would be to risk confusion of apprehended bias with actual bias by requiring substantially the same proof: Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex Parte H (2001) 75 ALJR at 990, [27] [28] (Again, internal footnote references omitted)

23 The test then is one of objective possibility.

24 Applying that test to the circumstances of this case, I have reached the conclusion that the learned Federal Magistrate erred in dismissing the challenge to the Tribunal's decision. The explanation of that conclusion requires an analysis in some detail of the nature of the claim for a protection visa made by the Applicant, of how the Tribunal dealt with that claim and of the reasons for judgment below.

25 At the heart of the Applicant's visa claim was his asserted adherence to the tenets and practices of the Falun Gong movement, his consequential experiences in China since July 1999 when that movement became the focus of what he stated was a campaign by the public security authorities to eradicate it and an asserted, consequential fear of persecution in the event of his return to China. He related his experiences in his visa application and related supporting materials as well as in oral evidence before the Tribunal.

26 Two of these alleged experiences in particular should be noted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1989-1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>44 That it is no part of the jurisdiction consigned to the Federal Magistrates Court to reach its own conclusion with regard to the merits of the applicant's protection visa application is unquestionably correct. A fortori that is so in this Court on appeal. It is axiomatic that the limits of the role consigned to a court conducting the judicial review of an administrative decision must firmly be kept in mind and respected in a principled way. The definitive, contemporary, Australian exposition in this regard is that offered by Brennan J (as his Honour then was) in Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1989-1990) 170 CLR 1 , at 35-36.
 "The duty and jurisdiction of the court to review administrative action do not go beyond the declaration and enforcing of the law which determines the limits and governs the exercise of the repository's power. If, in so doing, the court avoids administrative injustice or error, so be it; but the court has no jurisdiction simply to cure administrative injustice or error. The merits of administrative action, to the extent that they can be distinguished from legality, are for the repository of the relevant power and, subject to political control, for the repository alone."

45 Yet the solicitation made in the Applicant's judicial review application was not for the court to reach any conclusion at all on the merits of his protection visa application. Rather, it was objectively to examine in their totality the findings which the Tribunal had made in reaching its conclusion and the reasons for those findings in light of the material before the Tribunal, including the way in which those reasons were expressed. Viewed in this context, collectively and cumulatively, not individually, what this was said to reveal was a tendency or predisposition towards a particular result, an objective possibility of bias. This is the end to which paragraph "a" of the particulars given under ground 1 of the judicial review application is directed.

46 There is no necessary antipathy between the advancing of such an apprehended bias case and a concession that, viewed in isolation, one of many findings of an administrative tribunal might reasonably have been made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>NADH of 2001 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 328</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/328.html</AustLII>
<text>47 Given the role consigned to the Tribunal by the Migration Act 1958 and the nature of the case of apprehended bias that the applicant sought to make, the following passage from the judgment of Allsop J (as his Honour then was), Moore and Tamberlin JJ agreeing, in NADH of 2001 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 328 is, subject to one necessary qualification arising from the particulars of challenge in the present case, apposite:
 
 
 "17 To identify the obligation of the Tribunal, and the content of the necessary apprehension in the circumstances here, a number of matters need be recognised. First, whilst it is necessary to demonstrate that the circumstances are such as would give rise to the relevant apprehension, the apprehension itself is not as to the fact or likelihood of a lack of impartiality, but of a possibility (real and not remote) thereof: Ebner at 345 at [7].
 18 Secondly, the identity, nature and function of the decision-maker are important influences on the content of the requirement to conduct the relevant task with the observance of procedural fairness by not being tainted by the appearance of disqualifying bias: Laws at 90; Ebner at 343-44; Jia Legeng at 563-64.
 19 Thirdly, the place of a decision-maker such as the Tribunal here should be recognised as different from a judge in open court: Jia Legeng at 563-64; Laws at 70-71; Ebner at 343-44. The Tribunal does not administer public justice. The elements which affect the public confidence in the adjudication of disputes by an independent and impartial arm of government (in the broad sense) and which may be seen to inform what might be said to be freestanding norms of conduct and behaviour by judges conducting public hearings are not necessarily as easily transposable as strict obligations of administrative decision-makers acting in private. The Tribunal here must investigate the facts for itself unaided by counsel presenting the parties' cases, to the degree and extent it thinks appropriate. The Tribunal which has to reach a state of satisfaction may want to test and probe a recounted history. It may have particular matters troubling it for resolution, which require questioning and expressions of doubt which are entirely appropriate, but which if undertaken or said by a judge in open court in adversary litigation might give rise to an apprehension of a lack of impartiality." (Internal footnotes omitted).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/17.html</AustLII>
<text>47 Given the role consigned to the Tribunal by the Migration Act 1958 and the nature of the case of apprehended bias that the applicant sought to make, the following passage from the judgment of Allsop J (as his Honour then was), Moore and Tamberlin JJ agreeing, in NADH of 2001 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 328 is, subject to one necessary qualification arising from the particulars of challenge in the present case, apposite:
 
 
 "17 To identify the obligation of the Tribunal, and the content of the necessary apprehension in the circumstances here, a number of matters need be recognised. First, whilst it is necessary to demonstrate that the circumstances are such as would give rise to the relevant apprehension, the apprehension itself is not as to the fact or likelihood of a lack of impartiality, but of a possibility (real and not remote) thereof: Ebner at 345 at [7].
 18 Secondly, the identity, nature and function of the decision-maker are important influences on the content of the requirement to conduct the relevant task with the observance of procedural fairness by not being tainted by the appearance of disqualifying bias: Laws at 90; Ebner at 343-44; Jia Legeng at 563-64.
 19 Thirdly, the place of a decision-maker such as the Tribunal here should be recognised as different from a judge in open court: Jia Legeng at 563-64; Laws at 70-71; Ebner at 343-44. The Tribunal does not administer public justice. The elements which affect the public confidence in the adjudication of disputes by an independent and impartial arm of government (in the broad sense) and which may be seen to inform what might be said to be freestanding norms of conduct and behaviour by judges conducting public hearings are not necessarily as easily transposable as strict obligations of administrative decision-makers acting in private. The Tribunal here must investigate the facts for itself unaided by counsel presenting the parties' cases, to the degree and extent it thinks appropriate. The Tribunal which has to reach a state of satisfaction may want to test and probe a recounted history. It may have particular matters troubling it for resolution, which require questioning and expressions of doubt which are entirely appropriate, but which if undertaken or said by a judge in open court in adversary litigation might give rise to an apprehension of a lack of impartiality." (Internal footnotes omitted).

49 An apprehended bias case has, as Hayne J noted in Minister for Immigration v Jia Legeng [2001] HCA 17 ; (2001) 205 CLR 507 at 564, [185] , "several distinct elements at its roots":
 "First, there is the contention that the decision-maker has an opinion on a relevant aspect of the matter in issue in the particular case. Secondly, there is the contention that the decision-maker will apply that opinion to that matter in issue. Thirdly, there is the contention that the decision-maker will do so without giving the matter fresh consideration in the light of whatever may be the facts and arguments relevant to the particular case. Most importantly, there is the assumption that the question which is said to have been prejudged is one which should be considered afresh in relation to the particular case." 
In an apprehended bias case a conclusion that it is objectively possible that these elements are present is sufficient to establish a want of procedural fairness grounded in an apprehension that the decision maker was biased. That conclusion does not carry with it the additional conclusion that the decision-maker was in fact biased. It is whether there is such an objectively discernable possibility, not the thought processes of the decision-maker, which must be the focus of inquiry.

50 There is an inherent tension between a finding on the one hand that "The Tribunal does not accept that the applicant is a Falun Gong practitioner at all, or has any association with the movement in Australia ," (emphasis added) and, on the other that " The tribunal does not accept that the applicant's apparent association with [a successful, Falun Gong practitioner , protection visa applicant] shows that he is a Falun Gong practitioner" (emphasis added).

51 The Tribunal had before it direct evidence from Miss Byers, which it did not find unworthy of credit, to the effect that:
 
(a) the applicant had come to her on referral from a known Falun Gong practitioner;
 
(b) the referrer had successfully satisfied the Tribunal (differently constituted) that he was indeed a Falun Gong practitioner;
 
(c) in Falun Gong claimant related cases, she only acted for those referred by a Falun Gong practitioner, not those who came "directly off the street".

52 It has been said that there is no error of law merely in making a wrong finding of fact. Likewise, it may be accepted that an administrative tribunal is not obliged to refer in its reasons to every item of evidentiary material placed before it and that its reasons should not be read narrowly and with an eye for error. In this case, the Applicant did have an association with a particular individual. So much was "apparent" to the Tribunal. Further, the Tribunal knew, because it was expressly told, that this particular individual had been accepted by the Tribunal (differently constituted) as a member of the Falun Gong movement in Australia. It was not correct to find that the Applicant had no association at all with the movement in Australia. The Applicant's assertion of his association with the known practitioner was corroborated by the evidence from his migration agent. The Applicant's evidence was that the nature of the association was not that of social acquaintance but rather that of fellow adherents. His migration agent's evidence also at least raised for consideration an inference that this was indeed the nature of the association. "Objectified" though through the prism of what a fair-minded and informed observer would reasonably apprehend: Jia Legeng at 564; Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488 , 493, it is quite possible to regard this error of fact and the omission to consider the ramifications of the asserted nature and quality of the association, having regard to the circumstances of the referral, as an error and omission in respect of an "inconvenient truth".

53 Recalling, at the level of objective possibility, the three elements described by Hayne J in Jia Legeng at 564, what emerges, in my opinion, is the possibility that the Tribunal had a pre-conceived view that the applicant was not a person who feared persecution on the basis of adherence to the practice of Falun Gong, applied that preconception to the question of whether the applicant satisfied the criteria for the grant of a protection visa and did so notwithstanding that there was evidence, at least worthy, prima facie , of credit, that the applicant not only was , not "apparently was", associated with an Australian resident Falun Gong practitioner but had been referred by that person to a solicitor and migration agent whose integrity the Tribunal had no reason to doubt, and who professed to take "Falun Gong" cases only on referral from known Falun Gong practitioners, for the purpose of seeking from Australia the very same refuge from a claimed fear of persecution as the Tribunal itself had regarded as well founded in the case of that referrer.

54 That objective possibility is not removed by regard to the way in which the Tribunal dealt with:
 
(a) the Applicant's knowledge of the Falun Gong movement;
 
(b) the reason advanced by the Applicant for desisting from practising Falun Gong exercises in a park in Australia;
 
(c) the Hospital Document;
 
(d) the Labour Reform Camp Document.

55 The Tribunal was faced with a man of rudimentary education who it found knew the basic tenets of Falun Gong, its founder, its principal text and its five exercises, who claimed benefit from their practice, who claimed to have been prevented by official persecution from readily associating in China with fellow adherents but did so at an asserted price of beating and imprisonment and who it found was unable to engage in a detailed philosophical discussion about the movement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488</tocase>
<text>52 It has been said that there is no error of law merely in making a wrong finding of fact. Likewise, it may be accepted that an administrative tribunal is not obliged to refer in its reasons to every item of evidentiary material placed before it and that its reasons should not be read narrowly and with an eye for error. In this case, the Applicant did have an association with a particular individual. So much was "apparent" to the Tribunal. Further, the Tribunal knew, because it was expressly told, that this particular individual had been accepted by the Tribunal (differently constituted) as a member of the Falun Gong movement in Australia. It was not correct to find that the Applicant had no association at all with the movement in Australia. The Applicant's assertion of his association with the known practitioner was corroborated by the evidence from his migration agent. The Applicant's evidence was that the nature of the association was not that of social acquaintance but rather that of fellow adherents. His migration agent's evidence also at least raised for consideration an inference that this was indeed the nature of the association. "Objectified" though through the prism of what a fair-minded and informed observer would reasonably apprehend: Jia Legeng at 564; Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488 , 493, it is quite possible to regard this error of fact and the omission to consider the ramifications of the asserted nature and quality of the association, having regard to the circumstances of the referral, as an error and omission in respect of an "inconvenient truth".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>57 Disquieting though the Tribunal's conception of what is necessary to evidence a religious belief may be, the conclusion which was reached in relation to this applicant's knowledge of Falun Gong may not, viewed in isolation and in the sense described by Gibbs J (as he then was) in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118-119, be so unreasonable that no reasonable tribunal could have so concluded. Viewed against the broader context of the way in which the Tribunal has dealt with other issues, the deference that would ordinarily be conceded on judicial review to such a conclusion is challenged by a distinct, objective possibility of a belief on the part of the Tribunal that someone could not be a Falun Gong practitioner without an ability, irrespective of educational attainment, to engage in philosophical discourse about the movement, that this belief was brought to the determination of the application and that it was applied without giving consideration to the nature of the applicant, the knowledge of the movement and, particularly, an association with an Australian resident Falun Gong practitioner that he in fact had.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002; Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 77 ALJR 1165</tocase>
<text>58 Any assessment of the impact, in terms of an apprehended bias challenge, of the Tribunal's treatment of the Hospital Document and the Labour Reform Camp Document must be guided by the cautionary note sounded by McHugh and Gummow JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 ; Appellant S106/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 77 ALJR 1165 at 1174, [49].
 "[49] In a dispute adjudicated by adversarial procedures, it is not unknown for a party's credibility to have been so weakened in cross-examination that the tribunal of fact may well treat what is proffered as corroborative evidence as of no weight because the well has been poisoned beyond redemption. It cannot be irrational for a decision-maker, enjoined by statute to apply inquisitorial processes (as here), to proceed on the footing that no corroboration can undo the consequences for a case put by a party of a conclusion that that case comprises lies by that party. If the critical passage in the reasons of the Tribunal be read as indicated above, the Tribunal is reasoning that, because the appellant cannot be believed, it cannot be satisfied with the alleged corroboration. The appellant's argument in this Court then has to be that it was irrational for the Tribunal to decide that the appellant had lied without, at that earlier stage, weighing the alleged corroborative evidence by the witness in question. That may be a preferable method of going about the task presented by s430 of the Act. But it is not irrational to focus first upon the case as it was put by the appellant." (Emphasis added)

59 On one view of matters, that is all that the Tribunal has done here. It is possible to discern differences of detail in respect of an event or experience both within the applicant's evidence at the Tribunal hearing and as between that evidence and that given in other material submitted either with the initial protection visa application or later. Such differences certainly could provide a basis for a finding about the applicant's credibility and an affording of no weight to seemingly corroborative documents. In relation to the apprehended bias challenge, the factors are certainly not all one way.

60 Yet the Tribunal's findings concerning the credibility of the applicant's account have themselves been influenced by comparison with inferences that the Tribunal drew from an inspection of the Hospital Document and the Labour Reform Camp Document. This interplay in my opinion distinguishes the present case from the position described by McHugh and Gummow JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 in the passage quoted above.

61 The Tribunal rightly acknowledged, explicitly, that the general information that it had from the Australian Embassy concerning document fraud in China did not mean that all documents from that country were fraudulent. Possession of such information reasonably puts any administrator on guard, but nothing more than that, in relation to particular documents.

62 The Tribunal's perception of the genuineness of the applicant's account of his beating at the hands of the police, as well as of the Hospital Document itself, was expressed to be influenced by the fact that this document did not state a cause for the injury. That is true, but the Tribunal had no material before it as to whether it was the usual practice in this or any such Chinese hospital to record a cause, especially when this would record an injury inflicted on a citizen at the hands of State officials.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>