<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Oberhardt v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 1923 (17 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1923.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Angelakos v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (2007) 100 ALD 9</tocase>
<text>56 As Beadle, Hales and Riddell indicate, the wording of the section is broad and does not, financial hardship alone aside, impose a fetter on the matters which may be considered by the decision maker. See also Trimboli v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 86 ALR 64 at 73, and Angelakos v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (2007) 100 ALD 9 at [33]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Postal Commission v Wallace (1996) 41 ALD 455</tocase>
<text>75 As Tamberlin J also observed in Australian Postal Commission v Wallace (1996) 41 ALD 455 , at 457:
 It is clear that s 43 is not to be construed with a pedantic eye but in a practical common sense way in order to determine, in substance, whether the decision conveys sufficient of the decision making process to enable the parties and other interested persons to properly understand it. Where the reasons expose the logical process underlying the decision and contain findings on matters of fact essential to that reasoning process, then as Burchett J said in Dodds v Comcare Australia (1993) 31 ALD 690 at 691: 
 
 ... it will not be easy to demonstrate a failure of compliance with the requirements to include "findings on material questions of fact".

76 The appellant in this case argues that the Tribunal's reasons are deficient in several respects. First, the appellant argues that the statutory provision here under consideration requires the exercise of a discretion, as discussed by French J above. Accordingly, the appellant argues, this is not a case where the Tribunal can simply state a finding of fact and then move to a conclusion. It was further submitted that, in the Tribunal's reasons there is not to be found a statement of the evidence upon which the facts found were based; the materials before the Tribunal were listed, but were not discussed; the statements of principle are sometimes contradictory to the result reached; and in many instances, the facts found did not, on their face, answer the question posed by the statute.

77 The respondent argues that the Tribunal's conclusions incorporated its reasoning. By stating that the applicant's circumstances were not so special as to justify waiver, and by indicating that those circumstances were not "outside the ordinary run of cases", the Tribunal fulfilled its obligation. It was not required, argue the respondents, to go further. In direct contrast to the applicant, the respondent submits that this case is within that category of cases described by French J in paragraph [40] of his Honour's judgment set out above in which it is sufficient to state the rule or principle, the facts, the evidence upon which the facts are based, and the result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225</tocase>
<text>51 On my reading of the judgment of Mansfield J in Devriadis v Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services (2000) 62 ALD 145 , his Honour assumed that an unclaimed entitlement to a benefit was relevant to the consideration of special circumstances. However, it was unnecessary for his Honour to decide the point, because of a factual finding that the appellant could not in fact have been entitled to the benefit claimed. Mansfield J, at 159-160, said:
 I have also considered whether the tribunal may have erred in failing to consider as a possible special circumstance that the applicant may have been entitled to some level of benefit under the 1947 Act or the 1991 Act during the relevant period, even if he had made full disclosure to the respondent. I do not consider that it erred in law in that regard. The tribunal has determined that the applicant should not be treated as unemployed under s 116(4) of the 1947 Act, or under s 516(1) or 595(1) of the 1991 Act. Those provisions are directed to enabling a period of employment as being treated as a period of unemployment, having regard to the nature of the work, its duration, and other matters relating to the work. The tribunal decided that the work the applicant did for Zorba during the relevant period was such that it should make an order under any of those provisions. Consequently, the criterion of being unemployed upon which eligibility for benefits depended has been found by the tribunal not to exist. The tribunal is not shown to have erred in its understanding of the expression "special circumstances": see the discussion as to the meaning of that term in Condren v Department of Family and Community Services [2000] FCA 268 , BC20000890 per Lehane J at [11]; Kertland v Department of Family and Community Services [1999] FCA 1596 ; (1999) 57 ALD 600 per Merkel J at [30-45]; Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 7 ALD 670 ; 60 ALR 225 at 228-30.

52 The point made by the Tribunal in the last sentence of the paragraph quoted in [37] above is an important one, and draws attention back to the language of the section in question; that is, that "special circumstances" must be shown.

53 That phrase, as has been noted in a number of decisions of this Court, is broad.

54 French J (as he then was) in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154 ( Hales ) noted, at 161:
 Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225 [Beadle] is a decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court on appeal from Toohey J sitting as a presidential member of the Tribunal: see Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1. The case concerned a claim for family allowance lodged more than six months after the eligibility date. In such a case payment could be backdated only in "special circumstances" (s 102 of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth)). Even within the narrow confine of "special circumstances" which would support a discretion to overlook the delay, the Court said it "[did] not think it is possible to lay down precise limits or precise rules". The phrase, although lacking precision, was in the Court's view, "sufficiently understood ... not to require judicial gloss": Beadle v Director-General of Social Security at 228. 
His Honour continued at 162:
 The concept of special circumstances is broad. A constellation of factors, including financial circumstances, may fall within it. The express exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance is an indicator that it would otherwise be included. This gives some measure of the range of circumstances which will qualify as special. But as a matter of grammar and ordinary logic, the exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance does not mandate its inclusion in the range of matters constituting such circumstances for the purpose of enlivening the Secretary's discretion. ... The evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of situations which could give rise to hardship or unfairness in the event of a rigid application of a requirement for recovery of debt. It is inappropriate to constrain that flexibility by imposing a narrow or artificial construction upon the words. It may be that there will be few cases in which the Secretary will be satisfied that there are special circumstances in the absence of financial hardship. It may be that there are few cases in which having found special circumstances to exist, the Secretary would exercise the discretion to waive in the absence of financial hardship. But to anticipate the limits of the categories of possible cases by imposing on the language of the section a fetter upon its application which is not mandated by its words, is to erode its useful purpose. (Emphasis added).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Dobbie and Secretary, Department of Social Security AATA, No 8661 (23 April 1993) unreported</tocase>
<text>47 In Varhegyi , the applicant was overpaid an Austudy payment after he failed to inform the Department that he was no longer a full-time student. After Centrelink sought to recover the debt, the applicant argued that the debt should be waived on the basis that special circumstances existed. Again, it was argued that a notional entitlement should be considered. Deputy President Forgie said, at [35]-[37]:
 
 
 35. Ms Riley raised the concept of "notional entitlement" as one that is relevant and that has found favour in a number of Tribunal decisions in the context of waiving a debt. In Re Huynh and Secretary, Department of Social Security [(1994) 34 ALD 694] the tribunal accepted that: 
 
 
 
 
 "... where there exists a notional entitlement to another payment under the Act, an applicant is entitled to have this entitlement taken into consideration when the question of waiver is being considered. However, the tribunal is further of the view that in determining whether a nominal entitlement should be offset against an overpayment, the facts which led to the overpayment are important. That is, if the overpayment was fraudulently obtained, this would weigh heavily against the fact there did exist a nominal entitlement to moneys." [(1994) 34 ALD 694 at 713] 
 
 
 
 
 In Re Dobbie and Secretary, Department of Social Security [AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] the tribunal found that the applicant had a "notional entitlement" to age pension, and waived 50% of the overpayment of widow's pension: 
 
 
 
 
 "... the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension during the relevant period having regard to the "married" income tests. In other words, if the true state of affairs had been disclosed the applicant would have been paid age pension during the relevant period in excess of $20,000. As the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension that fact should not be ignored despite the fact that she had received public money to which she was not entitled ... On the other hand, good administration of the social security system relies in large measure on the honesty of claimants in their dealings with the department. It follows in our opinion that an applicant who, notwithstanding a notional entitlement to a pension, misrepresents her position faces the prospect of having to accept the consequences of her actions."[AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] 
 
 
 
 
 36. After these decisions were made, the waiver provisions of the Act were amended with effect from 1 January 1996, introducing specific waiver provisions where there is a notional entitlement to parenting allowance or family allowance.[ Social Security Act 1991 (Cth), s 1237AAC] Eligibility for these allowances is not dependent on a person's satisfying an activity test in order to be eligible for the payment as is the case for Austudy or newstart Allowance.[ Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Radmilovich [2002] AATA 779 ; (2002) 70 ALD 218 at 232; [2002] AATA 779] The effect of these amendments on "notional entitlement" was recently addressed by Deputy President Jarvis in Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services ...
 
 37. I agree with Deputy President Jarvis. There is no room to introduce a concept of notional entitlement in that of special circumstances in s. 1237AAD(1) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re DSGR and Secretary, Department of Education, Science and Technology [2007] AATA 1981</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2007/1981.html</AustLII>
<text>49 For completeness, reference was made to Re DSGR and Secretary, Department of Education, Science and Technology [2007] AATA 1981 , where Senior Member Handley commented, at [43]:
 
 
 43. From my part, whilst I would not exclude the possibility of the circumstances of a person being so special that set off by notional entitlement could never be permitted, I would think that those circumstances would be unusual and set off by notional entitlement would be a relatively uncommon occurrence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>Re Huynh and Secretary, Department of Social Security (1994) 34 ALD 694</tocase>
<text>47 In Varhegyi , the applicant was overpaid an Austudy payment after he failed to inform the Department that he was no longer a full-time student. After Centrelink sought to recover the debt, the applicant argued that the debt should be waived on the basis that special circumstances existed. Again, it was argued that a notional entitlement should be considered. Deputy President Forgie said, at [35]-[37]:
 
 
 35. Ms Riley raised the concept of "notional entitlement" as one that is relevant and that has found favour in a number of Tribunal decisions in the context of waiving a debt. In Re Huynh and Secretary, Department of Social Security [(1994) 34 ALD 694] the tribunal accepted that: 
 
 
 
 
 "... where there exists a notional entitlement to another payment under the Act, an applicant is entitled to have this entitlement taken into consideration when the question of waiver is being considered. However, the tribunal is further of the view that in determining whether a nominal entitlement should be offset against an overpayment, the facts which led to the overpayment are important. That is, if the overpayment was fraudulently obtained, this would weigh heavily against the fact there did exist a nominal entitlement to moneys." [(1994) 34 ALD 694 at 713] 
 
 
 
 
 In Re Dobbie and Secretary, Department of Social Security [AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] the tribunal found that the applicant had a "notional entitlement" to age pension, and waived 50% of the overpayment of widow's pension: 
 
 
 
 
 "... the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension during the relevant period having regard to the "married" income tests. In other words, if the true state of affairs had been disclosed the applicant would have been paid age pension during the relevant period in excess of $20,000. As the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension that fact should not be ignored despite the fact that she had received public money to which she was not entitled ... On the other hand, good administration of the social security system relies in large measure on the honesty of claimants in their dealings with the department. It follows in our opinion that an applicant who, notwithstanding a notional entitlement to a pension, misrepresents her position faces the prospect of having to accept the consequences of her actions."[AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] 
 
 
 
 
 36. After these decisions were made, the waiver provisions of the Act were amended with effect from 1 January 1996, introducing specific waiver provisions where there is a notional entitlement to parenting allowance or family allowance.[ Social Security Act 1991 (Cth), s 1237AAC] Eligibility for these allowances is not dependent on a person's satisfying an activity test in order to be eligible for the payment as is the case for Austudy or newstart Allowance.[ Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Radmilovich [2002] AATA 779 ; (2002) 70 ALD 218 at 232; [2002] AATA 779] The effect of these amendments on "notional entitlement" was recently addressed by Deputy President Jarvis in Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services ...
 
 37. I agree with Deputy President Jarvis. There is no room to introduce a concept of notional entitlement in that of special circumstances in s. 1237AAD(1) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>Re Sara and Secretary, Department of Families, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs [2006] AATA 708 ; (2006) 91 ALD 759</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2006/708.html</AustLII>
<text>48 The appellant referred to decisions in which the Tribunal had considered notional entitlement relevant. Principal among these was the decision, subsequent to Schulze and Varhegyi , in Re Sara and Secretary, Department of Families, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs [2006] AATA 708 ; (2006) 91 ALD 759. In that case, Member Carstairs said, at [30]:
 Ms Dole submitted, referring to the tribunal decisions in Re Schulze and Secretary Department of Family and Community Services (2004) 81 ALD 636 ; [2004] AATA 705 and Re Secretary Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi (2005) 87 ALD 717 ; [2005] AATA 635 that it would be an incorrect approach to the discretion under s 1237AAD of the Act to incorporate a consideration of any notional entitlement to another payment in its exercise. I agree with the reasons expressed in those decisions that there is specific reference in other sections of the Act to particular payments (not including youth allowance) where notional entitlement is recognised. However, I do not understand either deputy president in these decisions to be stating that there are no circumstances in which notional entitlement can be considered in the context of the discretion for special circumstances. There are, after all, no fetters on this discretion, except as expressed in s1237AAD itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>overruled</class>
<tocase>Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2004] AATA 705 ; (2004) 81 ALD 636</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2004/705.html</AustLII>
<text>43 Decisions of the AAT which concluded that notional entitlement was not a relevant matter in considering whether special circumstances exist to justify waiver are Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2004] AATA 705 ; (2004) 81 ALD 636 ( Schulze ) and Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi [2005] AATA 635 ; (2005) 87 ALD 717 ( Varhegyi ).

44 In Schulze , the applicant had been overpaid a parenting allowance, following which the Department raised and sought to recover the debt. The sole question for the Tribunal was whether the debt should be waived. Following consideration of the phrase "special circumstances" and what was required to show such circumstances, Deputy President Jarvis addressed the applicant's argument that a notional entitlement of his son should be considered. The Deputy President said, at [34]-[35]:
 
 
 34. The applicant also urged the Tribunal to consider the notional entitlement of his son to Youth Allowance as a further special circumstance...
 
 35. Notional entitlement has been found to constitute part of the factual matrix of special circumstances in several cases such as Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Lyster (2000) 59 ALD 587. However, I note that the legislature has seen fit to amend the Act to provide for set-off of notional entitlement in the circumstances provided for in s 1237AAC. That provision provides for set-off of notional entitlement in only very limited circumstances and by reference to specific payments. It was the respondent's contention that any attempt to expand notional entitlement by virtue of the special circumstances provision would defeat the intention of Parliament. I think this submission is well founded. In addition, I consider, in any event, that as it is the applicant's son, and not the applicant, who is notionally entitled to youth allowance, the failure of the applicant's son to apply for a payment to which he would have personally been entitled, in circumstances in which the applicant can only estimate what portion of those moneys would have been paid to him and his wife, does not form a sound basis for consideration of waiver of a debt involving public moneys.

45 The basis for the Tribunal's decision in Schulze , therefore, was that as notional entitlement was specifically included in s 1237AAC, and therein was subject to a number of limitations, a notional entitlement was not a relevant consideration in assessing "special circumstances" within s 1237AAD.

46 A further basis for the decision in Schulze (which distinguishes it from the present case) is that the notional entitlement was not the applicant's, but rather the applicant's son's, and therefore was not a relevant factor in the applicant's case.

47 In Varhegyi , the applicant was overpaid an Austudy payment after he failed to inform the Department that he was no longer a full-time student. After Centrelink sought to recover the debt, the applicant argued that the debt should be waived on the basis that special circumstances existed. Again, it was argued that a notional entitlement should be considered. Deputy President Forgie said, at [35]-[37]:
 
 
 35. Ms Riley raised the concept of "notional entitlement" as one that is relevant and that has found favour in a number of Tribunal decisions in the context of waiving a debt. In Re Huynh and Secretary, Department of Social Security [(1994) 34 ALD 694] the tribunal accepted that: 
 
 
 
 
 "... where there exists a notional entitlement to another payment under the Act, an applicant is entitled to have this entitlement taken into consideration when the question of waiver is being considered. However, the tribunal is further of the view that in determining whether a nominal entitlement should be offset against an overpayment, the facts which led to the overpayment are important. That is, if the overpayment was fraudulently obtained, this would weigh heavily against the fact there did exist a nominal entitlement to moneys." [(1994) 34 ALD 694 at 713] 
 
 
 
 
 In Re Dobbie and Secretary, Department of Social Security [AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] the tribunal found that the applicant had a "notional entitlement" to age pension, and waived 50% of the overpayment of widow's pension: 
 
 
 
 
 "... the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension during the relevant period having regard to the "married" income tests. In other words, if the true state of affairs had been disclosed the applicant would have been paid age pension during the relevant period in excess of $20,000. As the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension that fact should not be ignored despite the fact that she had received public money to which she was not entitled ... On the other hand, good administration of the social security system relies in large measure on the honesty of claimants in their dealings with the department. It follows in our opinion that an applicant who, notwithstanding a notional entitlement to a pension, misrepresents her position faces the prospect of having to accept the consequences of her actions."[AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] 
 
 
 
 
 36. After these decisions were made, the waiver provisions of the Act were amended with effect from 1 January 1996, introducing specific waiver provisions where there is a notional entitlement to parenting allowance or family allowance.[ Social Security Act 1991 (Cth), s 1237AAC] Eligibility for these allowances is not dependent on a person's satisfying an activity test in order to be eligible for the payment as is the case for Austudy or newstart Allowance.[ Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Radmilovich [2002] AATA 779 ; (2002) 70 ALD 218 at 232; [2002] AATA 779] The effect of these amendments on "notional entitlement" was recently addressed by Deputy President Jarvis in Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services ...
 
 37. I agree with Deputy President Jarvis. There is no room to introduce a concept of notional entitlement in that of special circumstances in s. 1237AAD(1) of the Act.

48 The appellant referred to decisions in which the Tribunal had considered notional entitlement relevant. Principal among these was the decision, subsequent to Schulze and Varhegyi , in Re Sara and Secretary, Department of Families, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs [2006] AATA 708 ; (2006) 91 ALD 759. In that case, Member Carstairs said, at [30]:
 Ms Dole submitted, referring to the tribunal decisions in Re Schulze and Secretary Department of Family and Community Services (2004) 81 ALD 636 ; [2004] AATA 705 and Re Secretary Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi (2005) 87 ALD 717 ; [2005] AATA 635 that it would be an incorrect approach to the discretion under s 1237AAD of the Act to incorporate a consideration of any notional entitlement to another payment in its exercise. I agree with the reasons expressed in those decisions that there is specific reference in other sections of the Act to particular payments (not including youth allowance) where notional entitlement is recognised. However, I do not understand either deputy president in these decisions to be stating that there are no circumstances in which notional entitlement can be considered in the context of the discretion for special circumstances. There are, after all, no fetters on this discretion, except as expressed in s1237AAD itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations and QX2006/1 [2006] AATA 372 ; (2006) 90 ALD 320</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2006/372.html</AustLII>
<text>50 Ms Kidson, counsel for the appellant, also referred to the decision of Deputy President Hack and Member Carstairs in Re Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations and QX2006/1 [2006] AATA 372 ; (2006) 90 ALD 320 ( QX2006/1 ). In that case, the applicant had applied for and received benefits using an assumed identity. After discovering the use of a false name, the Department sought to recover the payments made. It was acknowledged that had the applicant applied using his real name, he would have been entitled to the benefits paid. The applicant argued, amongst other things, that the debt should be waived under s 1237AAD. That case, therefore, is somewhat different to that under consideration here. The case was decided on other grounds; however the Tribunal made the following comments, which may be seen as relevant, with regard to "special circumstances" in s 1237AAD(b) (at 329-330):
 We are well satisfied that special circumstances exist where the payments made are identical to those to which the respondent would have been entitled had he applied in his own name. Provisions of this nature are designed to protect the revenue and permit the recovery of payments made in excess of an entitlement. Here, were it to be determined that there was a debt, the fact that the respondent had an equivalent, but not claimed, entitlement takes the present case out of the ordinary run of cases and gives to it a "special" character. (Emphasis added).

63 The view reflected by the Tribunal in Lyster, Huynh, Dobbie, Sara, and QX2006/1 referred to above, to the effect that notional entitlement is not necessarily excluded in considering whether "special circumstances" exist, for the purposes of s 1237AAD, is correct.

64 It follows that, in my view, notional entitlement should not be excluded from the range of available relevant considerations in deciding whether there are "special circumstances" to waive a debt under s 1237AAD.

65 The Tribunal's conclusion to the contrary, expressed in the first two sentences of [48] of its reasons, is wrong.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>Re Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations and Tracey Oberhardt [2008] AATA 85</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2008/85.html</AustLII>
<text>36 The Tribunal appears to have disagreed: Re Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations and Tracey Oberhardt [2008] AATA 85 , at [48]:
 
 
 48. For its part, this Tribunal considered that a notional entitlement basis for special circumstances waiver in income support law stands also outside the legislative signpost in section 1237AAD. It is also outside of the preponderance of authority. If the notional entitlement concept applies in section 1237AAD (which is doubtful), then it must itself come under the rubric of the range of accepted integers of special circumstances.

37 By the first sentence of this paragraph (which unfortunately is expressed in clumsily pretentious language) I take it that the Tribunal is expressing the conclusion that a notional entitlement is not a relevant consideration in deciding whether to waive a debt.

38 The second sentence is equally pretentiously expressed: by saying that "[i] t is outside of the preponderance of authority ", the Tribunal, I suspect, meant to say that the weight of authority is against the conclusion that a notional entitlement to a benefit is a relevant factor in deciding whether to waive a debt.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Lyster (2000) 59 ALD 587</tocase>
<text>44 In Schulze , the applicant had been overpaid a parenting allowance, following which the Department raised and sought to recover the debt. The sole question for the Tribunal was whether the debt should be waived. Following consideration of the phrase "special circumstances" and what was required to show such circumstances, Deputy President Jarvis addressed the applicant's argument that a notional entitlement of his son should be considered. The Deputy President said, at [34]-[35]:
 
 
 34. The applicant also urged the Tribunal to consider the notional entitlement of his son to Youth Allowance as a further special circumstance...
 
 35. Notional entitlement has been found to constitute part of the factual matrix of special circumstances in several cases such as Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Lyster (2000) 59 ALD 587. However, I note that the legislature has seen fit to amend the Act to provide for set-off of notional entitlement in the circumstances provided for in s 1237AAC. That provision provides for set-off of notional entitlement in only very limited circumstances and by reference to specific payments. It was the respondent's contention that any attempt to expand notional entitlement by virtue of the special circumstances provision would defeat the intention of Parliament. I think this submission is well founded. In addition, I consider, in any event, that as it is the applicant's son, and not the applicant, who is notionally entitled to youth allowance, the failure of the applicant's son to apply for a payment to which he would have personally been entitled, in circumstances in which the applicant can only estimate what portion of those moneys would have been paid to him and his wife, does not form a sound basis for consideration of waiver of a debt involving public moneys.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>overruled</class>
<tocase>Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi [2005] AATA 635 ; (2005) 87 ALD 717</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2005/635.html</AustLII>
<text>43 Decisions of the AAT which concluded that notional entitlement was not a relevant matter in considering whether special circumstances exist to justify waiver are Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services [2004] AATA 705 ; (2004) 81 ALD 636 ( Schulze ) and Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi [2005] AATA 635 ; (2005) 87 ALD 717 ( Varhegyi ).

47 In Varhegyi , the applicant was overpaid an Austudy payment after he failed to inform the Department that he was no longer a full-time student. After Centrelink sought to recover the debt, the applicant argued that the debt should be waived on the basis that special circumstances existed. Again, it was argued that a notional entitlement should be considered. Deputy President Forgie said, at [35]-[37]:
 
 
 35. Ms Riley raised the concept of "notional entitlement" as one that is relevant and that has found favour in a number of Tribunal decisions in the context of waiving a debt. In Re Huynh and Secretary, Department of Social Security [(1994) 34 ALD 694] the tribunal accepted that: 
 
 
 
 
 "... where there exists a notional entitlement to another payment under the Act, an applicant is entitled to have this entitlement taken into consideration when the question of waiver is being considered. However, the tribunal is further of the view that in determining whether a nominal entitlement should be offset against an overpayment, the facts which led to the overpayment are important. That is, if the overpayment was fraudulently obtained, this would weigh heavily against the fact there did exist a nominal entitlement to moneys." [(1994) 34 ALD 694 at 713] 
 
 
 
 
 In Re Dobbie and Secretary, Department of Social Security [AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] the tribunal found that the applicant had a "notional entitlement" to age pension, and waived 50% of the overpayment of widow's pension: 
 
 
 
 
 "... the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension during the relevant period having regard to the "married" income tests. In other words, if the true state of affairs had been disclosed the applicant would have been paid age pension during the relevant period in excess of $20,000. As the applicant had an entitlement to a rate of age pension that fact should not be ignored despite the fact that she had received public money to which she was not entitled ... On the other hand, good administration of the social security system relies in large measure on the honesty of claimants in their dealings with the department. It follows in our opinion that an applicant who, notwithstanding a notional entitlement to a pension, misrepresents her position faces the prospect of having to accept the consequences of her actions."[AATA, No 8661, 23 April 1993, unreported] 
 
 
 
 
 36. After these decisions were made, the waiver provisions of the Act were amended with effect from 1 January 1996, introducing specific waiver provisions where there is a notional entitlement to parenting allowance or family allowance.[ Social Security Act 1991 (Cth), s 1237AAC] Eligibility for these allowances is not dependent on a person's satisfying an activity test in order to be eligible for the payment as is the case for Austudy or newstart Allowance.[ Re Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services and Radmilovich [2002] AATA 779 ; (2002) 70 ALD 218 at 232; [2002] AATA 779] The effect of these amendments on "notional entitlement" was recently addressed by Deputy President Jarvis in Re Schulze and Secretary, Department of Family and Community Services ...
 
 37. I agree with Deputy President Jarvis. There is no room to introduce a concept of notional entitlement in that of special circumstances in s. 1237AAD(1) of the Act.

48 The appellant referred to decisions in which the Tribunal had considered notional entitlement relevant. Principal among these was the decision, subsequent to Schulze and Varhegyi , in Re Sara and Secretary, Department of Families, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs [2006] AATA 708 ; (2006) 91 ALD 759. In that case, Member Carstairs said, at [30]:
 Ms Dole submitted, referring to the tribunal decisions in Re Schulze and Secretary Department of Family and Community Services (2004) 81 ALD 636 ; [2004] AATA 705 and Re Secretary Department of Family and Community Services and Varhegyi (2005) 87 ALD 717 ; [2005] AATA 635 that it would be an incorrect approach to the discretion under s 1237AAD of the Act to incorporate a consideration of any notional entitlement to another payment in its exercise. I agree with the reasons expressed in those decisions that there is specific reference in other sections of the Act to particular payments (not including youth allowance) where notional entitlement is recognised. However, I do not understand either deputy president in these decisions to be stating that there are no circumstances in which notional entitlement can be considered in the context of the discretion for special circumstances. There are, after all, no fetters on this discretion, except as expressed in s1237AAD itself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security [1993] FCA 261 ; (1993) 42 FCR 443</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/261.html</AustLII>
<text>55 The Full Federal Court in Riddell v Secretary, Department of Social Security [1993] FCA 261 ; (1993) 42 FCR 443 ( Riddell ) held, at 450:
 Each particular case must be considered on its merits. It is the essential nature of the provision to create a broad discretion to meet the great variety of circumstances which must occur, raising considerations of individual hardship, need, fairness, reasonableness, and whatever else may move an administrator, keeping in mind the scope and purposes of the Act, to make a decision one way or the other.

56 As Beadle, Hales and Riddell indicate, the wording of the section is broad and does not, financial hardship alone aside, impose a fetter on the matters which may be considered by the decision maker. See also Trimboli v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 86 ALR 64 at 73, and Angelakos v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (2007) 100 ALD 9 at [33]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Roncevich v Repatriation Commission [2005] HCA 40 ; (2005) 222 CLR 115</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/40.html</AustLII>
<text>73 It is also important, however, not to pick apart the reasons of an administrative tribunal in search of error. Kirby J in Roncevich v Repatriation Commission [2005] HCA 40 ; (2005) 222 CLR 115 stated, at 135:
 ... sufficient reasons on the part of the Tribunal would be required to make the system of appeals effective and to fulfil its assumptions.

74 His Honour further observed, at 136:
 Courts conducting [judicial] review have been repeatedly enjoined by this Court to avoid overly pernickety examination of the reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations v Homewood (2006) 91 ALD 103</tocase>
<text>71 French J in Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations v Homewood (2006) 91 ALD 103 made the following relevant observations, at 111:
 [40] The obligations set out in s 43 are not necessarily discharged by merely setting out findings on material questions of fact, referring to the evidence on which those findings are based and then stating a conclusion. There will always be some legal rule or principle or discretion to apply. It may be that a rule or principle, like the major premise of a syllogism, will embody the factual circumstance necessary to give rise to a right or liability. Then it may be sufficient to state that rule or principle in the reasons, the facts found as the minor premise, the evidence on which they are based and the result which follows. Not all, and perhaps not many results are so easily explained. Whether the reasoning is syllogistic or otherwise, the tribunal will have discharged its duty under s 43 if its reasons disclose its findings of fact, the evidence on which they were based and the logical process by which it moved from those findings to the result in the case. [41] Where a case involves the exercise of a discretion, the tribunal's duty is not discharged by setting out the findings of fact necessary to enliven the relevant discretion. That is so even in a case in which the enlivening facts are of an evaluative character, such as the existence of special circumstances. What must appear from the reasons is why the discretion was exercised in the way it was.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154</tocase>
<text>54 French J (as he then was) in Secretary, Department of Social Security v Hales (1998) 82 FCR 154 ( Hales ) noted, at 161:
 Beadle v Director-General of Social Security (1985) 60 ALR 225 [Beadle] is a decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court on appeal from Toohey J sitting as a presidential member of the Tribunal: see Re Beadle and Director-General of Social Security (1984) 6 ALD 1. The case concerned a claim for family allowance lodged more than six months after the eligibility date. In such a case payment could be backdated only in "special circumstances" (s 102 of the Social Security Act 1947 (Cth)). Even within the narrow confine of "special circumstances" which would support a discretion to overlook the delay, the Court said it "[did] not think it is possible to lay down precise limits or precise rules". The phrase, although lacking precision, was in the Court's view, "sufficiently understood ... not to require judicial gloss": Beadle v Director-General of Social Security at 228. 
His Honour continued at 162:
 The concept of special circumstances is broad. A constellation of factors, including financial circumstances, may fall within it. The express exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance is an indicator that it would otherwise be included. This gives some measure of the range of circumstances which will qualify as special. But as a matter of grammar and ordinary logic, the exclusion of financial hardship alone as a special circumstance does not mandate its inclusion in the range of matters constituting such circumstances for the purpose of enlivening the Secretary's discretion. ... The evident purpose of s 1237AAD is to enable a flexible response to the wide range of situations which could give rise to hardship or unfairness in the event of a rigid application of a requirement for recovery of debt. It is inappropriate to constrain that flexibility by imposing a narrow or artificial construction upon the words. It may be that there will be few cases in which the Secretary will be satisfied that there are special circumstances in the absence of financial hardship. It may be that there are few cases in which having found special circumstances to exist, the Secretary would exercise the discretion to waive in the absence of financial hardship. But to anticipate the limits of the categories of possible cases by imposing on the language of the section a fetter upon its application which is not mandated by its words, is to erode its useful purpose. (Emphasis added).

78 Further, the respondent argues that the discussion in paragraph [41] of French J's judgment regarding decisions involving discretion is not relevant. This is because the existence or otherwise of special circumstances is a question of fact; the issue of discretion does not arise. Such an argument finds support in French J's statement in Hales that (at 162) " [The discretion to waive] is only enlivened when the Secretary is satisfied that the three conditions specified in (a), (b) and (c) of the section are met. " It is argued that the Tribunal set out the principle, set out the materials before it, and then by its comment that the appellant's circumstances were not outside of the ordinary run of cases, and were not so special as to justify waiver, reached a factual conclusion sufficient to discharge its obligations.

79 The Tribunal set out at paragraph [17] of its reasons the basic findings of fact from which the decision proceeded. Those findings related primarily to the debts owed, the appellant's physical and mental state, correspondence and other contact between the appellant and Centrelink, and the appellant's financial situation.

80 The Tribunal then moved to a consideration of the authorities as they relate to the phrase "special circumstances". In particular, the cases on the use of the phrase "unusual, uncommon or exceptional" were examined, along with other paraphrases used to aid interpretation of what can be "special circumstances". The Tribunal concluded by saying that such paraphrases "... cannot supplant the statutory language" (at [38]) and that "... the clear and ordinary meaning of the words "special circumstances" is the meaning that should be assigned to them." (at [39]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>The Queen v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal; Ex parte 2HD Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 62 ; (1979) 144 CLR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1979/62.html</AustLII>
<text>60 The High Court in The Queen v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal; Ex parte 2HD Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 62 ; (1979) 144 CLR 45 said, at 50. 
 However, it is not a legitimate approach to interpretation to compare a statutory discretion which is expressed in unlimited terms as to one subject with another discretion in the same statute which is confined to specified considerations with reference to a different subject and thereby conclude that the first discretion necessarily excludes the considerations specified in relation to the second discretion. The general rule is that a discretion expressed without any qualification is unconfined except in so far as it is affected by limitations to be derived from the context and scope and purpose of the statute. The fact that a discretion relating to a different subject matter is confined to a particular consideration provides no rational reason for saying that another discretion expressed without qualification does not embrace that particular consideration. Applied to the criterion of public interest, the argument is even less attractive. It would bring about the result, if accepted, that a discretion generally expressed may extend to any factor except public interest merely because another discretion directed to a very different subject matter is limited to the exclusive criterion of public interest.

61 Further, the thrust of s 1237AAC, although also dealing with debt relief, is significantly different. Section 1237AAC deals with specifically enumerated benefits in particular situations which, if found, have mandatory consequences; that is, if it is shown that there was an entitlement to a particular benefit which was unclaimed, the debt must be waived. That is not the case in s 1237AAD. That section provides a more general avenue for relief, and grants a broad discretion to the Secretary to waive debts, having regard to the way in which the debt resulted, any special circumstances that might exist, and the appropriateness of waiving the debt.

62 The words in s 1237AAD(b) should not be fettered, or narrowed, in the manner argued for by the respondent and accepted by the Tribunal in this case.

68 In oral argument, Mr Rangiah, counsel for the respondent, submitted that the reason for this was that the Tribunal considered the matter should not be given any weight in the circumstances of the case. The Court was asked to infer from the Tribunal's opinion that " The notional entitlement of the Applicant ... is not sufficiently unusual, uncommon or exceptional as to justify special circumstances waiver" , that the Tribunal did in fact consider the appellant's notional entitlement within the range of relevant factors going to special circumstances, but gave it no weight, and for that reason it was unnecessary to mention it specifically.

69 In my opinion, following its conclusion that notional entitlement could not of itself amount to special circumstances, the Tribunal did not mention notional entitlement as one of a range of relevant considerations, simply because it did not consider it relevant. It follows that, in my judgment, the Tribunal misdirected itself in deciding whether special circumstances existed for the purposes of waiver under s 1237AAD of the Social Security Act. Ground one of the Notice of Appeal has therefore been made out.

70 The appellant argues that the Tribunal's reasons are insufficient to discharge its obligations under ss 43(2) and (2B) of the AAT Act. Those sections provide:
 
 
 (2) Subject to this section and to sections 35 and 36D, the Tribunal shall give reasons either orally or in writing for its decision. 
 ...
 (2B) Where the Tribunal gives in writing the reasons for its decision, those reasons shall include its findings on material questions of fact and a reference to the evidence or other material on which those findings were based.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trimboli v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 86 ALR 64</tocase>
<text>56 As Beadle, Hales and Riddell indicate, the wording of the section is broad and does not, financial hardship alone aside, impose a fetter on the matters which may be considered by the decision maker. See also Trimboli v Secretary, Department of Social Security (1989) 86 ALR 64 at 73, and Angelakos v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (2007) 100 ALD 9 at [33]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Vock v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 967</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/967.html</AustLII>
<text>72 In Vock v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 967 , Tamberlin J said, at [17]:
 The rationale for the requirement that a decision-maker spell out the reasons for its conclusions on substantial issues is the need to inform the public and the parties with an immediate interest in the outcome of the proceedings of the manner in which the decision was arrived at. This, in turn, enables a determination to be made as to whether an error of law has been committed by the decision-maker. ...</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>