<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v PM Developments Pty Ltd (corrigendum 15 December 2008) [2008] FCA 1886 (12 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1886.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Futuris Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 32 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 1177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/32.html</AustLII>
<text>23 Such considerations led Gummow, Hayne, Heydon and Crennan JJ to observe in their joint judgement in Commissioner of Taxation v Futuris Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 32 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 1177 at 1183, [10] that, "as a matter of discretion, relief under ss 75(v) and s 39B may be (and often will be) withheld where there is another remedy provided by Part IVC".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Linter Textiles Australia Limited (In liquidation) [2005] HCA 20 ; (2005) 220 CLR 592</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/20.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The making of a winding up order changes the control of the affairs of a corporation but does not affect its beneficial ownership of its assets: Commissioner of Taxation v Linter Textiles Australia Limited (In liquidation) [2005] HCA 20 ; (2005) 220 CLR 592 at 612-613, [54] . In this regard, the position with respect to corporate insolvency differs from that which prevails in respect of the administration of an individual's bankrupt estate. The effect of s 58(1)(a) of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth) is that, when a debtor becomes a bankrupt either by the making of a sequestration order or upon the acceptance of a debtor's petition by the Official Receiver, the property of the bankrupt vests forthwith in the Official Trustee or, if there be a registered trustee of the bankrupt's estate, in that registered trustee.

31 When on 5 July 2007 this Court ordered the winding up of PMD and appointed Mr Greig as its liquidator he did not become the beneficial owner of Lot 8. Title to that Lot remained vested in the corporation. It was PMD, not its liquidator, which came to sell Lot 8. Further, insofar as PMD might be thought then to have been in the business of property development, that business, after Mr Greig decided that it ought to be continued for a short time for the purpose of best preserving and then realising Lot 8 as an asset of that corporation, remained the business of the corporation: s 477(1)(a) of the Corporations Act . It did not upon liquidation become Mr Greig's business. Contrary to the submission of the Commissioner, there is no support for any contrary conclusion to be found in s 9-20 of the GST Act . It was no more Mr Greig's business than it was not that of the directors of PMD prior to the making of the winding up order. Indeed, I did not understand the Commissioner to suggest that, before the winding up order, s 9-20 made PMD's business that of its directors. The only business relevantly conducted by Mr Grieg was the practise of his profession as an official liquidator, which included undertaking the liquidation of PMD. As will be seen, when acting in that latter capacity, he constituted an "entity" and "you" for the purposes of the GST Act, If does not follow from his possession of that status that he is liable to GST in respect of the sale of Lot 8.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Reliance Carpet Co Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 22 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 968</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/22.html</AustLII>
<text>33 A description, which I gratefully adopt, of the general scheme of the GST Act in respect of liability to GST and a summary of some presently pertinent provisions is to be found in the recent judgement of the High Court in Commissioner of Taxation v Reliance Carpet Co Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 22 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 968 at 970-971, [3] to [9]:
 The GST 
 
 3 Provision respecting the assessment and payment of the GST is made by the statute styled A New Tax System (Goods and Services Tax) Act 1999 (Cth) ("the Act "). An important point respecting the nature of the GST was made as follows by the Full Court of the Federal Court in Sterling Guardian Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation: [2006] FCAFC 12 ; (2006) 149 FCR 255 at 258: 
 
 
 
 
 
 "In economic terms it may be correct to call the GST a consumption tax, because the effective burden falls on the ultimate consumer. But as a matter of legal analysis what is taxed, that is to say what generates the tax liability (and the obligations of recording and reporting), is not consumption but a particular form of transaction, namely supply ..." 
 
 
 
 
 
 By way of contrast to the Australian system, counsel for the Commissioner referred to Art 2(1) of the first Council directive [Directive 67/227] on the harmonisation of legislation of member states of the European Community concerning turnover taxes; this indicates that VAT is a general tax on the consumption of goods and services.
 
 4 Section 7-1 of the Act relevantly states that GST is payable on "*taxable supplies" [The use of the asterisk is a device to alert the reader to the presence of a definition in the Dictionary to the Act ]. Section 9-5 answers a question "what are taxable supplies?", posed by a hypothetical taxpayer, by stating that "you make a taxable supply " if, among other criteria not presently relevant, "you make the supply for *consideration". 
 
 
 
 5 The composite expression "a taxable supply" is of critical importance for the creation of liability to GST . In the facts and circumstances of a given case there may be disclosed consecutive acts each of which answers the statutory description of "supply", but upon examination it may appear that there is no more than one "taxable supply". 
 
 
 
 6 The meaning of "supply" is given in s 9-10 and in addition to the general words "any form of supply" in s 9-10(1), par (d) of s 9-10(2) includes "a grant, assignment or surrender of *real property", and "real property" is defined [In the Dictionary provision of s 195 -1].expansively as including: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) any interest in or right over land; or 
 (b) a personal right to call for or be granted any interest in or right over land; or 
 (c) a licence to occupy land or any other contractual right exercisable over or in relation to land". 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Further, par (g) of s 9-10(2) includes "an entry into ... an obligation ... to do anything.
 
 7 The term "consideration" is defined in par (a) of s 9-15(1) as including: 
 
 
 
 
 "any payment, or any act or forbearance, in connection with a supply of anything". 
 
 
 
 
 
 The payment, act or forbearance may be voluntary and need not be by the recipient of the supply (s 9-15(2)).
 
 8 The amount of GST on a taxable supply is 10 per cent of "the value of the taxable supply" (s 9-70), and in the present case this was assessed as being the consideration represented by the forfeited deposit. 
 
 
 
 9 Division 29 lays down rules for the attribution to a tax period of the GST payable on a taxable supply. The general rule (s 29-5) is that the supplier becomes liable to pay GST on the earlier of two events, namely the receipt by the supplier of any of the consideration for the taxable supply, and the issue of an invoice relating to that supply; in the present case no invoice was issued by the taxpayer and the only relevant event was the receipt of the alleged consideration. 
 
 [Emphasis added in quotation of paragraph 5; footnote references incorporated into text of quote for reasons of different style requirements]

34 Given its "critical importance for the creation of liability to GST", it is as well to set out in full the text of s 9-5 of the GST Act :
 9-5 - Taxable supplies You make a taxable supply if: 
 
 (a) you make the supply for *consideration; and
 (b) the supply is made in the course or furtherance of an *enterprise that you *carry on; and
 (c) the supply is *connected with Australia; and
 (d) you are *registered, or *required to be registered. 
 
 However, the supply is not a *taxable supply to the extent that it is *GST-free or *input taxed.

35 Reading the passage quoted from Reliance Carpet and s 9-5, and seized with the knowledge that an order for the winding up of a corporation does not vest its property in its liquidator one might, without more, think that the answer to the question posed in this case was clear; the sale of Lot 8 could only be a supply by PMD, not by Mr Greig. That is because the "supply" of Lot 8 was, prima facie , made by PMD and it was that corporation, not Mr Greig, to which the consideration for the sale of Lot 8 was payable and paid under the contract.

36 This position is submitted by the Commissioner to be affected by the operation of Div 147 of the GST Act in a way which renders Mr Greig personally liable for the GST payable in respect of the sale of Lot 8.

37 The nature of the Commissioner's submission is such that the whole of Division 147 should be set out:
 Division 147--Representatives of incapacitated entities 
 
 147-1 What this Division is about 
 
 Representatives of incapacitated entities may be required to register for GST purposes. 
 
 147-5 Representatives are required to be registered 
 
 
 
 (1) A *representative of an *incapacitated entity is required to be registered in that capacity if the incapacitated entity is *registered or *required to be registered.
 (2) This section has effect despite section 23-5 (which is about who is required to be registered).
 
 147-10 Cancellation of registration of a representative 
 
 (1) The Commissioner must cancel the *registration of a *representative of an *incapacitated entity if the Commissioner is satisfied that the representative is not *required to be registered in that capacity.
 
 
Note: Cancelling the registration of a representative under this subsection is a reviewable GST decision (see Subdivision 110-F in Schedule 1 to the Taxation Administration Act 1953 ). 
 
 (2) The Commissioner must notify the *representative of the cancellation.
 (3) Sections 25-50 and 25-55 do not apply to the cancellation of the *registration of a *representative of an *incapacitated entity. 
 
 147-15 Notice of cessation of representation A *representative who ceases to be a representative of an *incapacitated entity must notify the Commissioner of that cessation, in the *approved form, within 21 days after so ceasing. 147-20 Adjustments (1) If: 
 
 
 (a) an *adjustment relates to a supply, acquisition or importation that an *incapacitated entity made before a *representative of the incapacitated entity was appointed; and 
 
 
 
 
 (b) the adjustment arises after that appointment; and 
 
 
 
 
 (c) in the case of an *increasing adjustment--the representative gives the Commissioner written notice that:
 (i) states that the adjustment has arisen in these circumstances; and
 (ii) specifies the amount of the adjustment; 
 
 
 
 
 the adjustment is to be treated as if:
 (d) the representative did not have the adjustment; and
 (e) the incapacitated entity had the adjustment.
 (2) This section has effect despite section 17 - 10 (which is about the effect of adjustments on net amounts). 
 
 147-25 Tax periods of representatives 
 
 (1) If a *representative of an *incapacitated entity is required to be registered in that capacity, the tax periods applying to the representative in that capacity are the same tax periods that apply to the incapacitated entity.
 (2) This section has effect despite Division 27 (which is about how to work out the tax periods that apply).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1980-1981) 147 CLR 297</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/26.html</AustLII>
<text>56 Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1980-1981) 147 CLR 297 was referred to in the course of the Commissioner's submissions as providing an alternative basis upon which to find that a liquidator was personally liable for post liquidation supplies. No doubt if the literal meaning of any of the provisions within Div 147 produced an irrational or absurd result this case might be called in aid so as to prefer an alternative construction, especially if that construction was evidently intended by an amending Act having regard to the history of the legislation. The difficulty here though is not with the literal meaning of statutory provisions but with the complete absence of basal deeming provisions necessary to achieve the end of rendering a liquidator personally liable in a way which is contrary to the position prevailing under both the general law and the ordinary position under s 9-5.

57 Within the GST Act it is s 9-5, not any of those in Div 147, which is the leading provision. The elements within s 9-5 are cumulative. To require a liquidator to register is to bring that official within but one of the four elements that cumulatively comprise a "taxable supply", so far as a post liquidation sale of property of the corporation is concerned. The registration requirement does not carry with it the other three. To regard Div 147 as achieving this is to give its provisions a weight that their language cannot bear, especially so as to create a counter intuitive taxation liability on the part of a liquidator.

58 As the GST Act presently stands, the effect of requiring a liquidator of a corporation to register will be that any supplies which the liquidator makes in that "representative" capacity in the event that any property of the corporation is ordered to be vested in him will become a "taxable supply" by him in that capacity; otherwise the disposal of the property of a corporation, insofar as that constitutes a supply for the purposes of the GST Act, will remain a taxable supply by the corporation and have to be accounted for and paid by it accordingly.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Broadbeach Properties Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 41 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 1411</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/41.html</AustLII>
<text>18 No assessment has been raised by the Commissioner in respect of the GST said to owed to the Commonwealth by the liquidator personally as a result of the post-liquidation sale of Lot 8. In these proceedings the tender of such an assessment would have been conclusive evidence of that liability: s 105-100 Sch 1, Taxation Administration Act 1953 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Broadbeach Properties Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 41 ; (2008) 82 ALJR 1411 , at 1418 [33] and 1420 [40] to [45] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Director of Public Prosecutions (Victoria) v Le [2007] HCA 52 ; (2007) 232 CLR 562</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/52.html</AustLII>
<text>47 An assertion as to its meaning and effect in an explanatory memorandum circulated by or with the authority of the Minister introducing a Bill into Parliament, like the Second Reading Speech in respect of that Bill, is not a substitute for the language employed by the Parliament in the Bill as enacted: Re Bolton; ex parte Beane [1987] HCA 12 ; (1987) 162 CLR 514 , at 518; Director of Public Prosecutions (Victoria) v Le [2007] HCA 52 ; (2007) 232 CLR 562 at 573, [29] and 586, [85]. It is the duty of the courts to construe enactments, not to make them. If, truly, the language of an enactment does not translate into law a meaning and effect that one might apprehend from secondary materials was intended it is for the Parliament to rectify that by further legislative provision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hepples v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 3 ; (1991-1992) 173 CLR 492</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/3.html</AustLII>
<text>27 These are not the only principles of statutory construction which are at large in this case. The GST Act is a taxing statute. Giving full measure to the reminders offered in Project Blue Sky v ABA , it remains the case, in my opinion, that the subjection of a person to tax by Parliament requires clarity of language, not inexactitude or indirect references. Especially that is so where the asserted subjection of a particular person to tax is counter intuitive to what one might expect having regard to the prevailing general law position and the otherwise usual incidence of the tax in question. I conceive that the following passage from the judgment of Deane J in Hepples v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 3 ; (1991-1992) 173 CLR 492 at 510-511 is indicative of the contemporary approach to take to the construction of a taxing statute:
 There has been a marked, and justifiable, tendency in recent times for the courts to construe taxation provisions as being directed to the substance as well as the form of transactions to an extent which previously would have been thought to be inconsistent with statements of high authority in cases such as Partington v. The Attorney-General (1869) LR 4 HL 100, at p 122, and Inland Revenue Commissioners v. The Duke of Westminster [1936] AC 1 , at pp 20, 24-25, 28, 31. Nonetheless, at least in cases where tax avoidance is not involved and where the substance of relevant transactions is not concealed by artificialities of form, the basic 'principles of statutory construction' of taxing provisions remain those identified and explained by Rich and Dixon JJ. in their joint judgment in Anderson v. Commissioner of Taxes (Vict.) [1937] HCA 24 ; (1937) 57 CLR 233 , at p 243. It is appropriate to repeat what their Honours there said: 
 
 
 In Brunton v. Commissioner of Stamp Duties ((1913) AC 747 , at p 760), Lord Parker of Waddington, speaking for the Privy Council, says: "The intention to impose a tax or duty, or to increase a tax or duty already imposed, must be shown by clear and unambiguous language and cannot be inferred from ambiguous words." This rule he again emphasized in Attorney-General v. Milne ([1914] AC 765 , at p 781), where he said, in the House of Lords: "The Finance Act is a taxing statute, and if the Crown claims a duty thereunder it must show that such duty is imposed by clear and unambiguous words." In Ormond Investment Co. v. Betts ([1928] AC 143 , at p 151), Lord Buckmaster, although differing from the majority of their Lordships and holding that in the particular case the Crown had satisfied the burden lying upon it, described the rule as a "cardinal principle ... a principle well known to the common law that has not been and ought not to be weakened - namely, that the imposition of a tax must be in plain terms." He added: "The subject ought not to be involved in these liabilities by an elaborate process of hair-splitting arguments." Lord Atkinson, who agreed in the decision of the House, expressed the rule as follows (at p 162): "It is well established that one is bound, in construing Revenue Acts, to give a fair and reasonable construction to their language without leaning to one side or the other, that no tax can be imposed on a subject by an Act of Parliament without words in it clearly showing an intention to lay the burden upon him, that the words of the statute must be adhered to, and that so-called equitable constructions of them are not permissible".

28 Before proceeding to a more detailed consideration of the provisions of the GST Act it is instructive to consider some aspects of the general position of liquidators.

29 When a corporation is being wound up in insolvency, the liquidator's duty is to take into his custody or under his control all of the property to which the corporation is or appears to be entitled: s 474(1) of the Corporations Act . Control of the corporation concerned is removed from the hands of its director or directors and vested in the liquidator for the purposes of the winding up of the corporation in insolvency in accordance with the provisions of the Corporations Act : s 471A(1) of the Corporations Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Oil Basins Ltd v Commonwealth of Australia [1993] HCA 60 ; (1993) 178 CLR 643</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/60.html</AustLII>
<text>19 Where an assessment has not been made, this Court has jurisdiction to grant declaratory relief in an appropriate case against the Commissioner in respect of a Commonwealth revenue law controversy: s 39B(1A)(c) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth); Oil Basins Ltd v Commonwealth of Australia [1993] HCA 60 ; (1993) 178 CLR 643. Thus, even though the relief sought by the liquidator, insofar as declaratory relief is sought against the Deputy Commissioner, might be thought to extend beyond the bounds of the provision of directions under the Corporations Act , there is ample jurisdiction nonetheless to grant it. As to the cross-claim for declaratory relief made by the Deputy Commissioner, s 39B(1A)(a) of the Judiciary Act is a source of jurisdiction.

20 Jurisdiction to grant declaratory relief is one thing; whether or not as a matter of discretion such relief ought to be granted is another. The Taxation Administration Act 1953 makes comprehensive provision for the resolution of Commonwealth revenue law controversies. That Act contemplates that, ordinarily, the Commissioner's view of the meaning and application of a Commonwealth revenue law will be reflected in an assessment with the recipient of the assessment then being granted, by the provisions of Part IVC of that Act, a right of objection and, if dissatisfied with the Commissioner's objection decision, an ability to challenge the objection decision either by way of review in the Administrative Appeals Tribunal (AAT) or on a so-called "appeal" heard in the original jurisdiction of this Court.

21 Unlike income tax, where liability to pay that tax is not complete until the making of an assessment, liability to pay GST is not dependent on the making of an assessment by the Commissioner. Even so, by s 105-10 in Sch 1, the Taxation Administration Act anticipates that a person whom the Commissioner asserts to be subject to a liability to GST may require the Commissioner to make an assessment, thereby initiating the process that may lead to external merits review by the AAT or the exercise of original jurisdiction by this Court in a taxation appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Muroa Pty Ltd v O'Meara (1997) 15 ACLC 1427</tocase>
<text>32 It is possible for a liquidator to secure from this Court or another invested with jurisdiction under the Corporations Act an order vesting in him in his official capacity some or all of the property of a corporation being wound up in insolvency: s 474(2) of the Corporations Act . However, as is noted in the definitive Australian text on corporate insolvency law, McPherson's Law of Company Liquidation, p 7-1053, such applications are uncommon given the wide powers conferred on liquidators by the Corporations Act . At least in some jurisdictions, one circumstance which might prompt a liquidator to seek such an order is a need in the course of a liquidation to lodge a caveat: Re Application by the Liquidator of Haupiri Courts Ltd [1969] NZLR 348; Muroa Pty Ltd v O'Meara (1997) 15 ACLC 1427.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Platypus Leasing Inc v Commissioner of Taxation (2005) 61 ATR 239</tocase>
<text>24 In this case, exceptionally, it seems to me appropriate, as a matter of discretion, not to withhold the granting of declaratory relief. I do so for these reasons. The declaratory relief has been sought in this Court, which unlike these days a State or Territory Supreme Court, is the usual forum for the resolution of Commonwealth revenue law liability controversies. The point raised is novel, controversial not only between the parties but evidently also in academic literature (see Anderson and Morrison, GST and Insolvency Practitioner Liability: Who are you? (2001) 11 Revenue LJ 23) and one of pervasive significance to corporate insolvency administration. The latter factor was recognised by the Deputy Commissioner in submissions and evidenced by his disposition, exceptionally, to pay the liquidator's taxed party and party costs of and incidental to the application in any event and, equally exceptionally, by his obviously considered decision not to make and tender an assessment, which would be the usual course for the Commissioner to adopt in a proceeding such as this in either this Court or, a fortiori , in a State or Territory Supreme Court: see, e.g. Platypus Leasing Inc v Commissioner of Taxation (2005) 61 ATR 239 (NSW Court of Appeal). There is no evidentiary controversy. Further, and as was also conceded on behalf of the Deputy Commissioner in submissions, the point is one always destined for this Court even in the event of assessment with the raising of the same and determination of an objection and attendant delays and related expenses only serving, in the circumstances, further to diminish such funds as may be available for distribution to creditors (principally, the Commissioner on behalf of the Commonwealth).

25 I turn then to consider the substantive revenue law liability question raised in the proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 29 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/29.html</AustLII>
<text>26 In their joint judgment in Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 29 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 381-382, [69] to [71] McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ offer an authoritative reminder that consistency as between the relevant statutory provision and the language and purpose of all provisions of the statute is the primary object of statutory construction and of the correlative need to construe a statute as a whole, not piecemeal, with careful regard to context, purpose and with the object of giving sensible meaning to all of the language employed by Parliament. Their Honours also remind that the reconciliation of conflicting provisions may well require the ascertainment of which is the leading provision to which others in apparent conflict should yield so as to achieve, if possible, a conformity of meaning. I accept readily the Deputy Commissioner's submission that these principles should inform the approach to deciding whether Division 147 of the GST Act renders Mr Greig personally liable for GST in respect of the sale of Lot 8.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Application by the Liquidator of Haupiri Courts Ltd [1969] NZLR 348</tocase>
<text>32 It is possible for a liquidator to secure from this Court or another invested with jurisdiction under the Corporations Act an order vesting in him in his official capacity some or all of the property of a corporation being wound up in insolvency: s 474(2) of the Corporations Act . However, as is noted in the definitive Australian text on corporate insolvency law, McPherson's Law of Company Liquidation, p 7-1053, such applications are uncommon given the wide powers conferred on liquidators by the Corporations Act . At least in some jurisdictions, one circumstance which might prompt a liquidator to seek such an order is a need in the course of a liquidation to lodge a caveat: Re Application by the Liquidator of Haupiri Courts Ltd [1969] NZLR 348; Muroa Pty Ltd v O'Meara (1997) 15 ACLC 1427.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Bolton; ex parte Beane [1987] HCA 12 ; (1987) 162 CLR 514</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/12.html</AustLII>
<text>47 An assertion as to its meaning and effect in an explanatory memorandum circulated by or with the authority of the Minister introducing a Bill into Parliament, like the Second Reading Speech in respect of that Bill, is not a substitute for the language employed by the Parliament in the Bill as enacted: Re Bolton; ex parte Beane [1987] HCA 12 ; (1987) 162 CLR 514 , at 518; Director of Public Prosecutions (Victoria) v Le [2007] HCA 52 ; (2007) 232 CLR 562 at 573, [29] and 586, [85]. It is the duty of the courts to construe enactments, not to make them. If, truly, the language of an enactment does not translate into law a meaning and effect that one might apprehend from secondary materials was intended it is for the Parliament to rectify that by further legislative provision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Judiciary and Navigation Acts [1921] HCA 20 ; (1921) 29 CLR 257</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1921/20.html</AustLII>
<text>17 I am satisfied that, in the events that have transpired, there is a justiciable "matter" with the present being a proceeding in that matter: In Re Judiciary and Navigation Acts [1921] HCA 20 ; (1921) 29 CLR 257.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Case W59 (2004) 21 NZTC 11,551</tocase>
<text>55 To note this particular absence of s 9-5 reference quality in Div 147 is to note a resemblance between the provision in s 147-5 of the GST Act for the registration of representatives of incapacitated persons and the position which prevailed under the Goods and Services Tax Act 1985 (NZ) (the NZ GST Act) as originally enacted. Subsection 58(1) of the NZ GST Act originally allowed the Commissioner for Inland Revenue to deem such persons to be registered. Section 58 of the NZ GST Act was amended in 1992 by s 11 of the Goods and Services Tax Amendment Act (No 2) 1992 (NZ) so as to substitute a new subsection 1 and, tellingly, to add a new subsection, s 58(1A) which provided, materially that, "For the purposes of this Act ..., where any person becomes a specified agent [defined so as to include a liquidator] that person shall ... be deemed to be a registered person carrying on the taxable activity of the incapacitated person during [the agency period] and the incapacitated person shall during that period be deemed not to be carrying on that taxable activity" . Section 58 of the NZ GST Act has since been further amended so as to remove an anomaly in the operation of this subsection exposed in Case W59 (2004) 21 NZTC 11,551 (Willy DCJ constituting the Taxation Review Authority). Perhaps surprisingly, given the affinities between New Zealand's GST regime and Australia's, Div 147 contains no equivalent to s 58(1A) of the NZ GST Act .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>