<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>IO Group Inc v Prestige Club Australasia Pty Ltd (No 3) [2008] FCA 1223 (13 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1223.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Ampolex Ltd v Perpetual Trustee Co (Canberra) Ltd (1995) 37 NSWLR 405</tocase>
<text>7 Heydon J D, Cross on Evidence (7 th Australian ed, 2004) sets forth as follows the circumstances in which a common interest privilege may arise (at [25265]):
 Where in circumstances of a mutual interest in a particular transaction or transactions the recipient of legal advice relating to such transactions passes documents or information containing that advice to someone who shares that interest, the essential question in each case is whether the nature of their mutual interest in the context of their relationship is such that the party to whom the documents are passed receives them subject to a duty of confidence which the law will protect in the interests of justice. Two persons interested in a particular question will not have a common interest if their individual interests in the question are selfish and potentially adverse to each other. ... 
See also: University of Western Australia v Gray (No 12) [2007] FCA 396 at [4] per French J. Potential differences in the respective positions of parties may lead to their not having a " common interest ": eg, Ampolex Ltd v Perpetual Trustee Co (Canberra) Ltd (1995) 37 NSWLR 405 at 410. Thus, in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1998) 81 FCR 526 , no common interest privilege arose as between the Commission and entities providing witness statements to the Commission in circumstances where the Commission was asserting that those entities had been involved in breaches of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). " In that respect they each had interests which were either adverse, or potentially adverse, to each other. In such circumstances common interest privilege cannot arise as there is no common interest ": (1998) 81 FCR at 564 per Goldberg J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1998) 81 FCR 526</tocase>
<text>7 Heydon J D, Cross on Evidence (7 th Australian ed, 2004) sets forth as follows the circumstances in which a common interest privilege may arise (at [25265]):
 Where in circumstances of a mutual interest in a particular transaction or transactions the recipient of legal advice relating to such transactions passes documents or information containing that advice to someone who shares that interest, the essential question in each case is whether the nature of their mutual interest in the context of their relationship is such that the party to whom the documents are passed receives them subject to a duty of confidence which the law will protect in the interests of justice. Two persons interested in a particular question will not have a common interest if their individual interests in the question are selfish and potentially adverse to each other. ... 
See also: University of Western Australia v Gray (No 12) [2007] FCA 396 at [4] per French J. Potential differences in the respective positions of parties may lead to their not having a " common interest ": eg, Ampolex Ltd v Perpetual Trustee Co (Canberra) Ltd (1995) 37 NSWLR 405 at 410. Thus, in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1998) 81 FCR 526 , no common interest privilege arose as between the Commission and entities providing witness statements to the Commission in circumstances where the Commission was asserting that those entities had been involved in breaches of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). " In that respect they each had interests which were either adverse, or potentially adverse, to each other. In such circumstances common interest privilege cannot arise as there is no common interest ": (1998) 81 FCR at 564 per Goldberg J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Farrow Mortgage Services Pty Ltd (in liq) v Webb (1996) 132 FLR 466</tocase>
<text>10 A " mere common interest in the outcome of litigation will be sufficient to enable any party with that interest to rely on " common interest privilege: Farrow Mortgage Services Pty Ltd (in liq) v Webb (1996) 132 FLR 466 at 472 per Sheller JA (Waddell A-JA agreeing). No submission was advanced that for a common interest privilege to be sustained there had to be such an identity of interests that the parties concerned could (had they chosen to do so) have used the same solicitor.

11 It is not considered that such a clear distinction can be drawn between those issues going to liability as opposed to quantum as is contended by the Applicants.

12 Although not of immediate relevance, s 122(2) and (4) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth), it may be noted, provides for circumstances in which " client legal privilege " may be lost by reason of the disclosure of evidence. An exception to that provision is that set forth as follows in s 122(5)(b): 
 Loss of client legal privilege: consent and related matters ... (5) Subsections (2) and (4) do not apply to: ... (b) a disclosure to a person with whom the client or party had, at the time of the disclosure, a common interest relating to a proceeding or an anticipated or pending proceeding in an Australian court or a foreign court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Network Ten Ltd v Capital Television Holdings Ltd (1995) 36 NSWLR 275</tocase>
<text>8 In the circumstances of the present proceeding, it is considered that there is a sufficient common interest such that each of the documents is privileged. Common interest privilege is not a concept " rigidly defined " and it is a question of fact in each case whether there is a sufficient mutual interest: Network Ten Ltd v Capital Television Holdings Ltd (1995) 36 NSWLR 275 at 280.

9 Common to the position of the Respondents is their alleged factual involvement in the breaches of copyright being pursued by the Applicants. The fact that one or other of them has decided not to put in issue an entitlement of declaratory and injunctive relief does not otherwise deny a common involvement. All resist relief in the form of damages or an account of profits. All of the relevant Respondents also have in common a Defence asserting the illegality of the sales of the films the subject of the proceeding. And there has been no Cross-Claim filed as between any of the Respondents.

13 Nor is there considered to be anything " unfair " in maintaining the privilege otherwise attaching to such legal advice or views as were being exchanged between the solicitors for the Respondents: Network Ten Ltd v Capital Television Holdings Ltd (1995) 36 NSWLR 275. The limited exchange of views as between the solicitors on a confidential basis could not be construed as a waiver of privilege: (1995) 36 NSWLR 275 at 286.

14 There remains outstanding those documents the subject of the reservation. These documents were described as " copies of tax invoices from Tzovaras Legal to the Fifth Respondent, including detailed narration of work undertaken by Tzovaras Legal on behalf of the Fifth Respondent in relation to the proceedings, including communications between Mr Tzovaras and Mr Armenis ". This is the document of 108 pages identified in the Affidavit of Ms Chylek as falling within paragraph [4] of the Subpoena .

15 Tzovaras Legal were lawyers formerly acting on behalf of the Fifth Respondent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>University of Western Australia v Gray (No 12) [2007] FCA 396</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/396.html</AustLII>
<text>7 Heydon J D, Cross on Evidence (7 th Australian ed, 2004) sets forth as follows the circumstances in which a common interest privilege may arise (at [25265]):
 Where in circumstances of a mutual interest in a particular transaction or transactions the recipient of legal advice relating to such transactions passes documents or information containing that advice to someone who shares that interest, the essential question in each case is whether the nature of their mutual interest in the context of their relationship is such that the party to whom the documents are passed receives them subject to a duty of confidence which the law will protect in the interests of justice. Two persons interested in a particular question will not have a common interest if their individual interests in the question are selfish and potentially adverse to each other. ... 
See also: University of Western Australia v Gray (No 12) [2007] FCA 396 at [4] per French J. Potential differences in the respective positions of parties may lead to their not having a " common interest ": eg, Ampolex Ltd v Perpetual Trustee Co (Canberra) Ltd (1995) 37 NSWLR 405 at 410. Thus, in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Safeway Stores Pty Ltd (1998) 81 FCR 526 , no common interest privilege arose as between the Commission and entities providing witness statements to the Commission in circumstances where the Commission was asserting that those entities had been involved in breaches of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). " In that respect they each had interests which were either adverse, or potentially adverse, to each other. In such circumstances common interest privilege cannot arise as there is no common interest ": (1998) 81 FCR at 564 per Goldberg J.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>