<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Carantinos v Magafas [2008] FCA 1107 (31 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1107.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Colgate-Palmolive Company v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225</tocase>
<text>10 The respondent sought an order for indemnity costs. The circumstances in which the Court has exercised its discretion to order indemnity costs were considered by Sheppard J in Colgate-Palmolive Company v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 233-234. His Honour there observed that the question must always be whether the particular facts and circumstances of the case in question warrant the making of an order for payment of costs other than on a party and party basis.

11 The present application was made and brought on for hearing in haste and, as it seems, without consideration, or adequate consideration, being given to s 32AA of the Federal Court Act . I am not persuaded that urgency inimicable to proper consideration of the provisions of the Federal Court Act has been demonstrated. No critical step is apparently imminent in the Federal Magistrates Court. I conclude that this is a case for indemnity costs.

12 The orders of the Court will be:
 
1. The application be dismissed.
 
2. The applicant pay all costs incurred by the respondent except insofar as they are of an unreasonable amount or were unreasonably incurred.

 I certify that the preceding twelve (12) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Branson. 

 Associate:

Dated: 31 July 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr B Skinner and Mr V Baird 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Munro Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr S Golledge 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Rockliffs Solicitors and IP Lawyers 

 Date of Hearing: 21 July 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 31 July 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1107.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Truth About Motorways Pty Limited v Macquarie Infrastructure Investment Management Limited [2000] HCA 11 ; (2000) 200 CLR 591</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/11.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The jurisdiction vested in the Federal Court by the Parliament is necessarily a jurisdiction with respect to "matters" (see s 77(i) of the Constitution ). In the constitutional sense a "matter" includes a controversy as to some immediate right, duty or liability to be established by the determination of the Court ( Truth About Motorways Pty Limited v Macquarie Infrastructure Investment Management Limited [2000] HCA 11 ; (2000) 200 CLR 591 per Gaudron J at [43]).

5 The justiciable controversy between the parties to which Mr Carantinos's application to this Court relates concerns the respondent's entitlement to obtain a sequestration order in respect of Mr Carantinos's estate. In particular, Mr Carantinos contends, and the respondent disputes, that by reason of the conduct of the respondent, certain dealings between the parties and unfinished litigation in the Court of Appeal of New South Wales, the respondent should be restrained from seeking a sequestration order against Mr Carantinos's estate. This is made plain by the fact that Mr Carantinos's claim for relief in this Court is advanced, as his written submissions reveal, on the following bases:
 
 
 (i) The applicant sought an undertaking that the respondent would not enforce a judgment entered in the Supreme Court of New South Wales by enforcement proceedings including bankruptcy proceedings. The respondent agreed to provide an undertaking on condition that the applicant verified accounts of dealings between the parties. The applicant did so without complaint by the respondent. Notwithstanding the agreement, the respondent purported to serve a bankruptcy notice and present a creditor's petition. 
 (ii) The judgment debt forms part of the dealings between the parties, which is the subject of the taking of accounts, and an appeal to the Court of Appeal. The decision of the Court of Appeal is presently reserved. 
 (iii) The respondent chose to serve a bankruptcy notice at an address known to be a business address of the applicant without recourse to his home address or the address of his then and present legal advisors.

6 It is not in dispute that the Federal Magistrates Court has jurisdiction in respect of the justiciable controversy between the parties concerning the respondent's entitlement to obtain a sequestration order in respect of Mr Carantinos's estate. Indeed, the Federal Court and the Federal Magistrates Court have concurrent jurisdiction in bankruptcy (s 27 of the Bankruptcy Act ).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>