<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Esco Corporation v PAC Mining Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1018 (4 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1018.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Esco Corporation v PAC Mining Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 640</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/640.html</AustLII>
<text>1 When I delivered my reasons for judgment in this matter on 12 May 2008, I directed that the parties consult with a view to agreeing upon Short Minutes of Order giving effect to my reasons, and that, if the parties could not agree, then competing Short Minutes of Order should be sent to my chambers with brief reasons: see Esco Corporation v PAC Mining Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 640.

2 I have had the benefit of both written and oral submissions by the parties in relation to the appropriate form of orders. From these submissions, several matters have arisen which require determination.

3 The first point of dispute between the parties concerns the definition of the term "Infringing Articles", which is used in both competing Short Minutes of Order. The definition proposed by the applicants was that "'Infringing Articles' means the Hensley System, the PAC Mining System, the CQMS System and the CQMS Lower Wing System (and any other wear assembly that contains the essential integers of claim 1 of Jones III)." The definition proposed by the respondents was that "'Infringing Articles' means the Hensley System, the PAC Mining System, the CQMS System and the CQMS Lower Wing System". My reasons for judgment of 12 May 2008 refer to and explain the meaning of most of these "systems".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/107.html</AustLII>
<text>16 There is also a dispute in relation to costs. The respondents concede that they are bound to pay the costs of the applicants in relation to the cross-claim, on which the applicants were successful. In relation to the applicants' claim of infringement, the Court found there was infringement, but in so doing only accepted one of the applicants' three arguments on construction. The general rule is that costs should follow the event, although the Court has a discretion to award costs on an issue-by-issue basis where a litigant has succeeded only in a portion of its claim: Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association Inc (1986) ATPR 40-748 ; Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 107. I think this principle should be applied in the present case, so that the applicants receive their costs with some allowance made for the fact that they succeeded only in respect of one of the three claims in dispute. Accordingly, I consider that the respondents should pay 80% of the applicants' costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association Inc (1986) ATPR 40-748</tocase>
<text>16 There is also a dispute in relation to costs. The respondents concede that they are bound to pay the costs of the applicants in relation to the cross-claim, on which the applicants were successful. In relation to the applicants' claim of infringement, the Court found there was infringement, but in so doing only accepted one of the applicants' three arguments on construction. The general rule is that costs should follow the event, although the Court has a discretion to award costs on an issue-by-issue basis where a litigant has succeeded only in a portion of its claim: Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association Inc (1986) ATPR 40-748 ; Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 107. I think this principle should be applied in the present case, so that the applicants receive their costs with some allowance made for the fact that they succeeded only in respect of one of the three claims in dispute. Accordingly, I consider that the respondents should pay 80% of the applicants' costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Powerflex Services Pty Ltd v Data Access Corporation (1996) 67 FCR 65</tocase>
<text>17 Finally, the respondents seek a stay of certain orders pending determination of an appeal from my judgment of 12 May 2008. As a condition of this stay, the respondents are willing to give undertakings that they shall keep accurate records of sales, shall not destroy any records in relation to their business, shall not dispose of or encumber any assets otherwise than in the ordinary course of business, and shall execute any application for leave to appeal and appeal with due expedition: cf Powerflex Services Pty Ltd v Data Access Corporation (1996) 67 FCR 65 at 67. In addition, the respondents undertake to pay to the applicants such amount as the Court thinks fit as compensation for any damage that the applicants may suffer as a consequence of a stay being granted, and to provide, if required by the Court, a bank guarantee in the sum of $500,000 as security for this undertaking as to compensation.

18 Relevant to the application for a stay, the respondents adduced evidence from Mr Meyers to the effect that the respondents employ about 400 people in Australia. He says that the manufacture and supply of wear assemblies is an important part of the respondents' business and a significant revenue contributor. Some of the relevant assemblies, he notes, have been supplied by the respondents for more than ten years, and that supply currently goes to every major coal producer in Australia. Mr Meyers says that if a stay is not granted, customers using the respondents' dragline and excavator lips will not be able to source alternative wear assemblies to fit their existing buckets and lips; the delay in supply of wear assemblies will have consequences for the respondents' customers' capacity to meet their contractual obligations; the employment of the 10% of the respondents' employees who are involved in the manufacture and sale of the respondents' wear assemblies may be jeopardised; and the respondents' relationship with customers will be damaged. There was some cross-examination of Mr Meyers, but it did not materially diminish the content or effect of his evidence.

19 Under O 52 r 17 of the Federal Court Rules , the Court has the power to stay the execution of a judgment pending an appeal from that judgment. There is a prima facie assumption that the judgment the subject of the appeal is correct and that the Court should not deprive a person of the fruits of victory by granting a stay. It is not necessary for the party seeking the stay to show that special or exceptional circumstances exist, but the Court must be satisfied that a sound reason has been presented to warrant exercise of the discretion: see Powerflex 67 FCR at 66; Re Middle Harbour Investments Ltd (In liq) (unreported, New South Wales Court of Appeal, 15 December 1976).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Middle Harbour Investments Ltd (In liq) (unreported, New South Wales Court of Appeal, 15 December 1976)</tocase>
<text>19 Under O 52 r 17 of the Federal Court Rules , the Court has the power to stay the execution of a judgment pending an appeal from that judgment. There is a prima facie assumption that the judgment the subject of the appeal is correct and that the Court should not deprive a person of the fruits of victory by granting a stay. It is not necessary for the party seeking the stay to show that special or exceptional circumstances exist, but the Court must be satisfied that a sound reason has been presented to warrant exercise of the discretion: see Powerflex 67 FCR at 66; Re Middle Harbour Investments Ltd (In liq) (unreported, New South Wales Court of Appeal, 15 December 1976).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>