<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tran v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1826 (2 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1826.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd (1986) 162 CLR 162</tocase>
<text>11 In relation to the language ability of the appellant his Honour found:
 
&#8226; Reference to the IELTS test in the Tribunal's reasons for decision merely indicated the Tribunal's awareness of the test as an alternative form of assessment, and inferences open upon the presentation of such evidence. In any event the Tribunal noted there was no such evidence and that the Tribunal only had available before it the appellant's evidence comprising his Diplomas.
 
&#8226; The Tribunal had carefully considered the evidence provided by the appellant in relation to his Diplomas. It noted that written assignments were not produced, but assessment was undertaken by "tick a box" multiple-choice assessment. The appellant was not required to attend class and listen to lectures conducted in English.
 
&#8226; Classes given as part of the course of study for the Diplomas were by correspondence, although the appellant had attended some classes where he communicated with tutors in Vietnamese and English.
 
&#8226; The fact that the appellant was dissatisfied with the Tribunal's determinations on questions of fact does not amount to a jurisdictional error or error of law and it is not appropriate for a court to review the merits of a Tribunal's determination ( Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd (1986) 162 CLR 162).

12 In relation to valuation of assets of the appellant his Honour found:
 
&#8226; Section 359A of the Act does not require the thought processes, subjective appraisals or determinations of the Tribunal to be provided to the appellant for comment.
 
&#8226; Facts or findings as to credibility are the function of the primary decision-maker.
 
&#8226; Although the issue of pre-and post-application values of property was determined by the Tribunal arbitrarily, the issue was decided in favour of the appellant. This is ultimately a question of fact for the Tribunal.

13 Accordingly his Honour dismissed the application.

14 The appellant filed a Notice of Appeal on 6 December 2007. During the course of oral submissions on 21 May 2008 before me, an issue of contention arose as to whether the Tribunal had made findings of fact unsupported by evidence in relation to the assessment of the appellant's English language ability, whether the appellant had attended his Diploma courses part-time, and whether the courses were conducted in English or Vietnamese (TS 12 21 May 2008). The appellant had not raised these issues before the Federal Magistrate and did not include such grounds in the Notice of Appeal filed 6 December 2007. Once these issues were raised in oral submissions, however, the appellant foreshadowed a desire to seek leave to file an Amended Notice of Appeal so as to include further grounds. I adjourned the matter to allow the appellant time to prepare an Amended Notice of Appeal and to allow both parties the opportunity to prepare amended submissions in the event that leave to file the Amended Notice of Appeal was granted.

15 On 24 June 2008 the matter returned for hearing and the appellant applied for leave to file an Amended Notice of Appeal. After hearing from both parties:
 
&#8226; I was not persuaded that the appellant's new legal arguments presented in the Amended Notice of Appeal had a reasonable prospect of success; and
 
&#8226; I considered that no sufficient explanation by the appellant was offered as to why the new ground of appeal was not raised before the Federal Magistrate.

16 However I also considered that allowing the appellant to amend his Notice of Appeal would cause limited (if any) prejudice to the respondent (indeed, Counsel for the first respondent stated at this hearing that she was in a position to answer the new ground of appeal).

17 On balance, I decided it was in the interest of justice that the appellant be granted leave to file his Amended Notice of Appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>S157/2002 v Commonwealth (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<text>23 The only basis upon which an appeal lies from a privative clause decision within the meaning of s 474 of the Act is jurisdictional error of the Tribunal: S157/2002 v Commonwealth (2003) 211 CLR 476. An error in the factual findings of the Tribunal, or the weighing of facts by the Tribunal, is not a jurisdictional error.

24 In this case there is considerable overlap between the appellant's grounds of appeal and submissions in relation to those grounds of appeal. After considering the grounds of appeal and the submissions of both parties I have formed the view that the appellant's grounds of appeal are without substance for the following reasons:

25 Section 359A specifically provides for procedural fairness in the framework of the Act as follows:
 359A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal (1) Subject to subsections (2) and (3), the Tribunal must: 
 
 (a) give to the applicant, in the way that the Tribunal considers appropriate in the circumstances, clear particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the decision that is under review; and
 (b) ensure, as far as is reasonably practicable, that the applicant understands why it is relevant to the review, and the consequences of it being relied on in affirming the decision that is under review; and
 (c) invite the applicant to comment on or respond to it.
 
 ... 
 
 (4) This section does not apply to information: 
 
 (a) that is not specifically about the applicant or another person and is just about a class of persons of which the applicant or other person is a member; or
 (b) that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application for review; or
 (ba) that the applicant gave during the process that led to the decision that is under review, other than such information that was provided orally by the applicant to the Department; or
 (c) that is non-disclosable information.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26</tocase>
<text>22 The Minister was represented by Ms Wheatley of Counsel. A summary of her submissions is as follows:
 Ground 1 
 
&#8226; Pursuant to s 359A of the Act, the Tribunal need only give the appellant particulars of information it considers would be the reason or part of the reason for affirming the decision. This does not extend to "information" encompassing the Tribunal's thought processes, determination, subjective appraisals, or relate to the existence of doubts, inconsistencies or absence of evidence ( SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26). 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal considered the information given by the appellant in relation to property valuations and decided not to place any weight on it. Such an approach is open to the Tribunal ( Tran v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1229 at [55] ).
 
&#8226; The appellant was invited by the Tribunal to provide further information supported by documentation in accordance with s 359A(2) of the Act.
 
&#8226; The real estate valuations of the appellant were given to the Tribunal for the purposes of the review. Section 359A(4)(b) of the Act specifically excludes information, given for the purposes of the application for review, from the operation of s 359A.
 Ground 2 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal did consider the appellant's advanced diplomas and also considered the other available evidence before it. The decision the Tribunal made was open to it in light of:
 
 o the appellant's reliance on an interpreter at the hearing;
 
 o the fact that, when an interpreter was not used, the appellant was hesitant and had difficulty answering questions in English;
 
 o the courses of study upon which the appellant relied were conducted by correspondence;
 
 o the fact that the appellant communicated with tutors in those courses in English and Vietnamese; and
 
 o the fact that the appellant did not claim to have produced any written assignments in English.
 
&#8226; In relation to the asset valuations, the Tribunal did consider and take into account the real estate properties and valuations but determined not to place weight on those valuations. The weight to be attributed to such valuations was an issue for the Tribunal ( Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Limited [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24). 
 Ground 3 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal did not misunderstand the questions it was to ask itself; rather it identified the correct issues and considered all of the evidence before it.
 
&#8226; The PAM policy guidelines as to functional ability in English and "better than functional ability" provide that either educational qualifications or the IELTS test results may be regarded as sufficient in deciding whether the appellant has better than functional English. The Tribunal merely adverted to the IELTS test as an alternative assessment.
 Ground 4 
 
&#8226; The findings of the Tribunal in relation to the part-time study and mode of delivery were open to the Tribunal.
 
&#8226; A finding that the appellant undertook part-time study was open to the Tribunal upon the evidence. The facts before the Tribunal were that the appellant studied by correspondence, completing 12 subjects over two years while undertaking full-time work (seven days a week).
 
&#8226; A finding that the appellant communicated with his tutors in both English and Vietnamese was open to the Tribunal on the evidence. The appellant at the Tribunal hearing stated that his tutors spoke with him in both languages and assessment was mostly by way of "tick the box" answers.

26 "Information" in s 359A of the Act has only a limited scope (see SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 at [22] ). Considering a similar legislative provision in SZBYR [2007] HCA 26 , Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ at [18] said that "information":
 does not encompass the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes or determinations...nor does it extend to identified gaps, defects or lack of detail or specificity in evidence or to conclusions arrived at by the tribunal in weighing up the evidence by reference to those gaps, etc.

27 The appellant's first ground of appeal related to the Tribunal's consideration of real estate valuations provided by the appellant. However in its statement of decision and reasons it is clear that the Tribunal carefully considered all the evidence relating to the assets claimed by the appellant. In upholding the delegate's decision to refuse the grant of a visa to the appellant, the Tribunal noted, inter alia :
 
&#8226; the fact that the property valuations provided by the appellant were not supported by evidence; and
 
&#8226; that the valuations currently provided were inconsistent with the valuations provided in 2003.

28 The appellant in ground 1 does not identify the information upon which it is said the Tribunal should have invited comment. After consideration of the evidence, the Tribunal was of the view that little weight should be given to the valuations provided by the appellant. Inconsistencies and disbelief of the appellant's evidence are not, for the purposes of s 359A of the Act, "information" which must be provided by the Tribunal to the appellant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Tran v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2007] FMCA 1929</tocase>
<text>37 As far as the second ground of appeal relates to real estate valuations, the learned Federal Magistrate found in Tran [2007] FMCA 1929 at [33] that it was clear from the reasons of the Tribunal that it did take into account the property valuations provided by the appellant. The weight given to those valuations however is an issue for the Tribunal ( Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Limited [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24).

38 The appellant raised issue with the Tribunal's decision relating to the value of the property at 93-95 Nguyen Cu Trinh Street. It appears from the evidence that the appellant held the property at 95 Nguyen Cu Trinh Street at the time of the application, but that the adjoining building No 93 was acquired after the application. The appellant's evidence was that the property at No 95 was worth $200,000 but that the combined worth of the two properties was $1,207,242. The Federal Magistrate noted that the Tribunal had divided the then value of 93-95 Nguyen Cu Trinh Street in half for the purposes of its consideration of the appellant's case. His Honour found that, while the value attributed to the properties by the Tribunal for the purposes of the application may have been decided arbitrarily, the Tribunal clearly decided the case in favour of the appellant. This is because No 93 had been acquired after the commencement of the application accordingly the Tribunal strictly did not need to take the value of that property into account. The Federal Magistrate found that the decision of the Tribunal in relation to these properties had no effect on the decision adverse to the appellant ( Tran [2007] FMCA 1929 at [33]).

41 This ground of appeal overlaps with the second ground in relation to the language ability of the appellant. Burnett FM said at [14]:
 However, the Applicant's interpretation of the Tribunal's decision on this point is in my view incorrect. It is clear from the Tribunal's decision that its reference to the IELTS test was merely to indicate its awareness of an alternative form of assessment available to it and the inferences open on the presentation of evidence of that kind. In the result however the Tribunal only had available before it the Applicant's evidence comprising the advanced diplomas. (Tran v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2007] FMCA 1929)

42 In my view, it cannot be inferred from the fact that the Tribunal mentioned the absence of an IELTS test that the Tribunal had concluded the appellant had only "functional English" because of the absence of an IELTS test. The Tribunal merely noted that the appellant did not present results of an IELTS test. The Tribunal mentioned the IELTS test because it is a consideration for which there is provision under the policy.

43 This ground of appeal is not substantiated.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Wyse v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2006] FMCA 1362</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2006/1362.html</AustLII>
<text>21 At the hearing the appellant was represented by Mr Nguyen of Counsel. A summary of the appellant's submissions are as follows:
 Ground 1 
 
&#8226; By not giving the appellant the opportunity to respond to adverse findings in relation to property valuations, the Tribunal failed to comply with the requirements in s 359A(1)(c) of the Act.
 
&#8226; By not placing due weight on the appellant's assets, the overall points score was affected which lead to the Tribunal affirming the decision of the delegate.
 Ground 2 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal failed to properly consider the evidence as to the appellant's English ability. The Tribunal accepted that the appellant achieved two Advanced Diplomas but did not award the appellant 30 points for achieving "better than functional English" as provided for in policy. The fact that the appellant exercised his right to use an interpreter at the hearing was an irrelevant consideration.
 
&#8226; The real estate valuations of the appellant were given no weight by the Tribunal and not taken into account. The Tribunal divided the value of the 93-95 Nguyen Cu Trinh Street property in half without giving any reasons. If the property were not divided in half, the appellant would have received 15 points under the Schedule to the Act. The appellant was not given the opportunity to provide further evidence or comment on the real estate valuations. The decision of the Tribunal is contrary to the authority in Wyse v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2006] FMCA 1362. 
 Ground 3 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal failed to recognise that the two Diplomas of the appellant were evidence of "better than functional English". By commenting on the appellant's failure to take an IELTS test, the Tribunal made a preference as to the type of evidence it would accept and imposed a requirement that an IELTS test be completed.
 Ground 4 
 
&#8226; The Tribunal made an error of fact that led it to misapply the law. The Tribunal concluded the appellant completed Advanced Diplomas on a part-time basis and the instructions were in Vietnamese. In fact the courses were completed on a full-time basis and instructions were in English. The factual errors led the Tribunal to conclude the appellant had "functional English".

39 Further, I agree with Ms Wheatley that the principles articulated in Wyse [2006] FMCA 1362 have no application in the context of these proceedings, as that case involved a different type of visa, a different policy and different requirements.

40 I do not consider this ground of appeal substantiated.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>