<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>BRGAG of 2008 v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1733 (18 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1733.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>BRGAG OF 2008 v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FMCA 722</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/722.html</AustLII>
<text>1 The appellant appeals to this Court from a decision of Jarret FM dated 5 June 2008 ( BRGAG OF 2008 v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FMCA 722). In that case his Honour dismissed an application for review of a decision of the Refugee Review Tribunal (the Tribunal) dated 29 January 2008. The Tribunal had affirmed a decision of a delegate of the Minister dated 16 October 2008 wherein the delegate refused the grant of a protection (class XA) visa to the appellant pursuant to the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) (the Act).

2 The appellant is a citizen of the Republic of Indonesia. He arrived in Australia on 26 August 2007 and applied for a protection (class XA) visa on 20 September 2007. The appellant claims that he is at risk of being persecuted by the Indonesian authorities.

3 The appellant claims that prior to 1998 he had a very close relationship with the Soeharto government. He claims that after 1998 he fell out of favour with the new Indonesian government because of that relationship.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/10.html</AustLII>
<text>22 In relation to the third ground of appeal, his Honour noted that the Tribunal considered the claims of the appellant relating to being beaten by police, imprisoned for one month and the possibility of further prosecution, and that the Tribunal found that these claims were unsubstantiated. As the appellant did not attend the Tribunal hearing, the Tribunal was unable to consider any additional facts relating to the assertions of the appellant. To the extent that the appellant seeks to re-agitate the facts before the Tribunal, this is not the role of the Court: NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10 at [10] .

23 I do not consider the grounds of appeal substantiated. In my view the appropriate order is that the appeal be dismissed, with costs.

 I certify that the preceding twenty-three (23) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Collier. 

 Associate:
Dated: 18 November 2008

 The Appellant appeared in person. 
 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Mr S Maycock of Clayton Utz 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: The Second Respondents did not appear 

 Date of Hearing: 18 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 November 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1733.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>S157/2002 v Commonwealth (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<text>19 The only basis upon which an appeal lies from a privative clause decision within the meaning of s 474 of the Act is jurisdictional error of the Tribunal: S157/2002 v Commonwealth (2003) 211 CLR 476. In this case I do not consider that the appellant has established either jurisdictional error in the decision of the Tribunal, or appellable error in the decision of the learned Federal Magistrate.

20 In relation to the first ground of appeal it is clear from the decision record of the Tribunal that the Tribunal did consider the appellant's claims and whether the appellant had a well founded fear of persecution. As the appellant did not attend the Tribunal hearing or submit any further material the Tribunal was unable to consider further information. It is not for the Tribunal to make a case for the appellant rather it is for the applicant before the Tribunal to make his or her case for consideration by the Tribunal.

21 In relation to the second ground of appeal I consider that there is little to distinguish this ground from the first ground of appeal to the extent that the appellant submits that the Tribunal did not give proper consideration to his case. I have nothing to add to my conclusion in relation to the first ground of appeal.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>