<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Repatriation Commission v Money [2008] FCA 118 (4 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/118.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327</tocase>
<text>7 In forming this opinion, the Repatriation Commission is required to decide the matter to its reasonable satisfaction; s 120(4). This requires the Commission to ask itself whether it was satisfied on the balance of probabilities; Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327. Section 120 does not impose an onus of proof on the applicant for a pension or on the Commission; s 120(6). Nevertheless, the Commission can only reach the requisite state of satisfaction if two conditions are fulfilled; s 120B(3). First, the material before the Commission must raise a connection between the disease and some particular service rendered by the person. Secondly, where there is a Statement of Principles in force concerning that disease, that Statement of Principles must uphold the contention that the disease is, on the balance of probabilities, connected with the service.

8 Statements of Principles are determined by the Repatriation Medical Authority; s 196B(1). They set out the factors that must be present and must be related to service before it can be said that, on the balance of probabilities, a disease can be connected with the service; s 196B(3). Subsection 196B(14)(d) states that a factor causing or contributing to a disease is related to service if:
 
 
 (d) it was contributed to in a material degree by, or was aggravated by, that service; ...

9 The Authority has determined a Statement of Principles, Instrument No. 16 of 1998, for IFA. This Statement of Principles holds that, in order for IFA to be connected with the circumstances of defence service, there must have been an "inability to obtain appropriate clinical management" for the condition; see clause 5(a). This applies only where IFA was contracted before or during service (although not arising out of that service), but was materially contributed to or aggravated by that service; see clause 6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Somerset v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 1399</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1399.html</AustLII>
<text>38 The applicant cited Somerset v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 1399 as authority for the proposition that failure to diagnose may not necessarily constitute an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. However, in Somerset Greenwood J plainly left open the possibility that it may do so; see [36]. Somerset is distinguishable on the grounds that, in that case, there was no basis for believing that the veteran was suffering from the disease during his period of service. In contrast, the expert opinion of Dr Waring is that there was adequate evidence that Mr Money had IFA "at least as early as 30 April 1979". As indicated above at [27], Dr Musk was inclined to a similar view. In Repatriation Commission v Wedekind [2000] FCA 649 , Kenny J was prepared at [17] to assume, without deciding, that the Tribunal may reasonably have been satisfied that diagnostic failure could lead to an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. Given that a beneficial approach is called for in dealing with this legislation ( Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80) , it seems to me that a person in Mr Money's position may well be prevented from obtaining appropriate clinical management of a condition by lack of awareness that they suffer from it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Wedekind [2000] FCA 649</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/649.html</AustLII>
<text>38 The applicant cited Somerset v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 1399 as authority for the proposition that failure to diagnose may not necessarily constitute an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. However, in Somerset Greenwood J plainly left open the possibility that it may do so; see [36]. Somerset is distinguishable on the grounds that, in that case, there was no basis for believing that the veteran was suffering from the disease during his period of service. In contrast, the expert opinion of Dr Waring is that there was adequate evidence that Mr Money had IFA "at least as early as 30 April 1979". As indicated above at [27], Dr Musk was inclined to a similar view. In Repatriation Commission v Wedekind [2000] FCA 649 , Kenny J was prepared at [17] to assume, without deciding, that the Tribunal may reasonably have been satisfied that diagnostic failure could lead to an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. Given that a beneficial approach is called for in dealing with this legislation ( Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80) , it seems to me that a person in Mr Money's position may well be prevented from obtaining appropriate clinical management of a condition by lack of awareness that they suffer from it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1246.html</AustLII>
<text>38 The applicant cited Somerset v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 1399 as authority for the proposition that failure to diagnose may not necessarily constitute an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. However, in Somerset Greenwood J plainly left open the possibility that it may do so; see [36]. Somerset is distinguishable on the grounds that, in that case, there was no basis for believing that the veteran was suffering from the disease during his period of service. In contrast, the expert opinion of Dr Waring is that there was adequate evidence that Mr Money had IFA "at least as early as 30 April 1979". As indicated above at [27], Dr Musk was inclined to a similar view. In Repatriation Commission v Wedekind [2000] FCA 649 , Kenny J was prepared at [17] to assume, without deciding, that the Tribunal may reasonably have been satisfied that diagnostic failure could lead to an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management. Given that a beneficial approach is called for in dealing with this legislation ( Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80) , it seems to me that a person in Mr Money's position may well be prevented from obtaining appropriate clinical management of a condition by lack of awareness that they suffer from it.

41 The applicant submits that the correct construction in this matter is that adopted in Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80 , namely, that as a matter of practical reality, "inability" requires barriers to obtaining appropriate clinical management. The applicant submits that it could not be said that the same outcome would have resulted if the Tribunal had considered this meaning. I do not think that the applicant has been able to establish this. As Burchett J expressed it in Baxter Healthcare Pty Limited v Comptroller-General of Customs (1997) 72 FCR 467 at 469, the issue "turns on whether the Tribunal in reality mistook its legal task, or whether it merely strayed into a measure of obscurity in the statement of its reasons, the actual meaning of which can nevertheless be ascertained by some perseverance, and being ascertained, reveals no error".

42 The Tribunal clearly found that there was an inability to obtain appropriate clinical management; it expressly states so in [82] of its reasons. Although the Tribunal made no express findings as to why the identified systemic failures in the naval medical system presented a barrier to Mr Money receiving appropriate clinical management, it is implicit in its reasons that Mr Money was reliant upon the Navy's medical system during his period of service. As a matter of practical reality, a person in Mr Money's position could not reasonably have been expected to take steps to obtain medical care beyond that offered by the Navy; see Brew at 88. The applicant has not demonstrated that the Tribunal applied an incorrect construction.

43 In addressing the question of whether the inability to obtain appropriate clinical management had aggravated Mr Money's IFA, Dr Waring expressed slightly different opinions. In the earlier report (13 April 2004) Dr Waring discussed the usual form of treatment in the 1970s which was usually high dose prednisolone, an immunosuppressant. He said that it was "serendipitously appropriate" that Mr Money was not given this treatment because more recent studies have "not demonstrated any benefit from prednisolone therapy for the interstitial lung disease that has been diagnosed on lung biopsy". He added:
 
 Having said this, the majority of chest physicians still consider a trial of prednisolone therapy, especially in young otherwise fit patients, who are likely to tolerate the drug relatively well. 
 [Emphasis added]

44 Dr Waring also commented that the naturally slow progression of Mr Money's disease would not have been expected if it had been diagnosed in the 1970s, and added that, in retrospect, this slow progress meant that the side effects of prednisolone therapy would have out-weighed any benefit he might have received had he been given this treatment. He summarised his view by saying that "the lack of appropriate clinical management may have, but probably has not aggravated his condition". [Original emphasis]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Baxter Healthcare Pty Limited v Comptroller-General of Customs (1997) 72 FCR 467</tocase>
<text>41 The applicant submits that the correct construction in this matter is that adopted in Brew v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 1246 ; (1999) 94 FCR 80 , namely, that as a matter of practical reality, "inability" requires barriers to obtaining appropriate clinical management. The applicant submits that it could not be said that the same outcome would have resulted if the Tribunal had considered this meaning. I do not think that the applicant has been able to establish this. As Burchett J expressed it in Baxter Healthcare Pty Limited v Comptroller-General of Customs (1997) 72 FCR 467 at 469, the issue "turns on whether the Tribunal in reality mistook its legal task, or whether it merely strayed into a measure of obscurity in the statement of its reasons, the actual meaning of which can nevertheless be ascertained by some perseverance, and being ascertained, reveals no error".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Collins v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1981] FCA 147 ; (1981) 36 ALR 598</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1981/147.html</AustLII>
<text>50 In Collins v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1981] FCA 147 ; (1981) 36 ALR 598 , Fox, Deane and Morling JJ said at 601:
 
 An appellant who attacks a conclusion of the Tribunal because of deficiency of proof said to amount to error of law must show, if he is to succeed, that there was no material before the Tribunal upon which the conclusion could properly be based.

51 The applicant argues that there was no material before the Tribunal capable of supporting a finding that there were barriers to Mr Money obtaining appropriate clinical management for his IFA. As discussed above, I am of the view that a failure to diagnose is sufficient to create a barrier to obtaining appropriate clinical management, and the evidence in this case is that a diagnosis could have been made in 1979.

52 The applicant submits that there was no material before the Tribunal capable of supporting the finding that Mr Money did not receive appropriate clinical management. This submission is founded on the equation of appropriate management with appropriate treatment and the contemporary absence of any effective treatment; two contentions which I have rejected above. In any event, there was expert evidence before the Tribunal that Mr Money did not receive appropriate clinical management. Dr Waring gave this opinion in his letter to the departmental medical officer dated 13 April 2004 and in his report dated 8 March 2005. Both of these reports are discussed in the context of the first ground of appeal. That discussion shows that there was considerable evidence on the point and that this 'no evidence' ground must fail.

53 The applicant claims that the Tribunal was required to find whether any inability to obtain appropriate clinical management was related to Mr Money's service in one of the ways set out in s 196B(14). The applicant further claims that the Tribunal failed to make such a finding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>54 The Tribunal's discussion of the applicable law includes, at [28], an explicit acknowledgement that the "relationship to service must be one of the relationships prescribed in s 196B(14) of the Act". As noted above, one of those relationships is that prescribed by s 196B(14)(a), which states that a factor contributing to a disease (here, inability to obtain appropriate clinical management) can be related to service if it "resulted from an occurrence that happened while the person was rendering that service". In its reasons, the Tribunal explicitly found that one of the circumstances of Mr Money's service and therefore an occurrence during his service was that "the Navy's medical system, on this particular occasion, failed to deliver appropriate clinical management" to Mr Money. Additional examples of the "systems failure in the medical management structure that the Navy had in place in relation to this applicant's disease at that time" were given by the Tribunal and are described above at [26] et seq. Bearing in mind that the Tribunal's reasons should "not be scrutinised upon over-zealous judicial review by seeking to discern whether some inadequacy may be gleaned from the way in which the reasons are expressed" ( Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 per Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ at 272), it is clear that the Tribunal has found that Mr Money's inability to obtain appropriate clinical management for his IFA resulted from occurrences while he was serving in the Navy.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Federal Broom Company Pty Limited v Semlitch (1964) 110 CLR 626</tocase>
<text>55 The applicant submits that the Tribunal was in error in considering that the issue was governed by the decision of the High Court in Federal Broom Company Pty Limited v Semlitch (1964) 110 CLR 626. Alternatively, it submits that if Federal Broom were applicable, it would require the Tribunal to turn its mind to whether Mr Money's inability to obtain appropriate clinical management was a state of affairs to which he would not otherwise have been exposed - presumably if he had not been in the Navy at the relevant time. The applicant submits that a similar comparative exercise is required by Johnston v Commonwealth [1982] HCA 54 ; (1982) 150 CLR 331 at 337-8. In my view, it is clear that the Tribunal did consider this issue. Implicit in the finding that the naval doctor's "clinical management fell short of the level required" is the finding that other doctors would be capable of meeting that standard. Mr Money could self-evidently not have been subject to a systemic failure of the Navy's medical management structure if he had not been serving in the Navy. Accordingly, this ground must fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnston v Commonwealth [1982] HCA 54 ; (1982) 150 CLR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/54.html</AustLII>
<text>55 The applicant submits that the Tribunal was in error in considering that the issue was governed by the decision of the High Court in Federal Broom Company Pty Limited v Semlitch (1964) 110 CLR 626. Alternatively, it submits that if Federal Broom were applicable, it would require the Tribunal to turn its mind to whether Mr Money's inability to obtain appropriate clinical management was a state of affairs to which he would not otherwise have been exposed - presumably if he had not been in the Navy at the relevant time. The applicant submits that a similar comparative exercise is required by Johnston v Commonwealth [1982] HCA 54 ; (1982) 150 CLR 331 at 337-8. In my view, it is clear that the Tribunal did consider this issue. Implicit in the finding that the naval doctor's "clinical management fell short of the level required" is the finding that other doctors would be capable of meeting that standard. Mr Money could self-evidently not have been subject to a systemic failure of the Navy's medical management structure if he had not been serving in the Navy. Accordingly, this ground must fail.

58 The applicant argues that there was no evidence before the Tribunal that any inability to obtain appropriate clinical management had contributed materially to, or aggravated, Mr Money's IFA. The applicant submits that the evidence does not demonstrate that Mr Money's defence service made his IFA worse than it otherwise would have been; Johnston v Commonwealth [1982] HCA 54 ; (1982) 150 CLR 331 at 338.

59 I have already held that a factor not being mentioned in the Statement of Principles is not inconsistent with it being a factor that aggravates a disease, though it cannot of itself be a factor that creates a connection with defence service. Dr Waring's report refers to Mr Money's exposure to poor atmospheric conditions while serving in submarines, notes that if his IFA had been correctly diagnosed it would have been reasonable to recommend that he no longer serve in submarines, and states that it is likely that his continued exposure could have exacerbated his condition. The Tribunal relied on this evidence; see [73]. There was material before the Tribunal upon which it could base its conclusion that Mr Money's condition was aggravated by the failure to diagnose it. It is not for this Court to substitute its opinion as to the appropriate weight that should be given to that evidence. That is a task for the Tribunal. It is sufficient for this Court to note that there was some real evidence for it to reject this 'no evidence' claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Bendy (1989) 10 AAR 323</tocase>
<text>60 The applicant drew the Court's attention to the requirement that mere de minimus aggravation of IFA would not suffice, given the requirements of clause 6 of the Statement of Principles; see Repatriation Commission v Bendy (1989) 10 AAR 323 at 330. It could not, however, point to any evidence that the aggravation identified by the expert would have been de minimus . This ground must fail.

61 The Tribunal found that Mr Money's service in submarines " could (via the fumes that he had to inhale), have aggravated his IFA" [emphasis added]. The applicant argues that the Tribunal here misconceived its task, which is to decide to its reasonable satisfaction whether the fumes aggravated Mr Money's IFA, as required by s 120(4).

62 The Tribunal has failed to express its satisfaction on the balance of probabilities that Mr Money's submarine service aggravated his IFA. The Tribunal's treatment of this topic nonetheless implies that it was satisfied to the appropriate standard on this point. In any event, even if this implication cannot be drawn, the Tribunal identified other aggravating factors, primarily smoking. The Tribunal laid out the measures that could have been taken to protect Mr Money's lung capacity, but which were not instituted:
 
 The prophylactic measures appropriate to the applicant's disease are: 
 
 
 &#8226; making sure that the applicant has his yearly flu vaccine and five yearly pneumococcal vaccine, and having antibiotics at hand so he could promptly start taking them at the start of infection, and therefore not be delayed waiting for doctor's appointments etc; 
 &#8226; advising him to stop smoking; 
 &#8226; keeping him under long term surveillance; 
 &#8226; regular monitoring of his lung function by non invasive testing; and 
 &#8226; explaining the importance of losing weight to the patient. 
 

 The Tribunal said that these measures "would have protected [Mr Money's] spare lung capacity that was being inexorably eroded".</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>