<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Newcrest Mining Limited v Apache Northwest Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1663 (7 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1663.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Newcrest Mining Limited v Apache Northwest Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1527</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1527.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 17 October 2008 I ordered that Apache Northwest Pty Ltd ("Apache") give preliminary discovery of certain classes of documents to Newcrest Mining Limited ("Newcrest"): see Newcrest Mining Limited v Apache Northwest Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1527. A verified list of documents was to be filed and served on or before 30 October 2008.

2 Apache applied for leave to appeal from this decision. On 30 October 2008 Middleton J varied my order by extending, until 14 November 2008, the period within which Apache was required to file and serve its verified list of documents.

3 When I made the order for preliminary discovery I foreshadowed that it might be necessary, at a later time, for the matter to return to Court to deal with consequential issues such as confidentiality. Apache subsequently advised the Court that it considered that it would be necessary for a confidentiality regime to be put in place to deal with commercially sensitive documents. An issue also arose as to which party should bear the costs of preliminary discovery.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cappuccio v Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [1999] FCA 1188</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1188.html</AustLII>
<text>6 The conventional approach to costs orders in this area was explained by Burchett J in Cappuccio v Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [1999] FCA 1188 at [3] - [4] where his Honour said that:
 "3. ... I have a discretion as to just what I should do in respect of costs, and it seems to me that the costs order which would be appropriate in a case like this depends very much on the consequences of the discovery obtained. If the applicant for preliminary discovery uncovers enough to enable that applicant to bring proceedings which are successful, there may be much to be said for the proposition that the costs of the preliminary discovery should form part of the costs of the action. On the other hand, if the applicant proceeds, brings an action, fails, and is ordered to pay the costs of that action, there seems to be every reason why, generally speaking, the costs of the preliminary discovery should be included in the costs payable to the respondent. 4. There may, of course, be cases where there are special reasons to vary the normal rule that costs follow the event. In this particular case, having listened to the arguments of both sides, each of whom seeks a costs order, I have come to the conclusion that the appropriate order, in the event that a case is brought for substantive relief, is that the costs of this application be at the discretion of the tribunal which hears the substantive application. In all the circumstances, I order that, if a substantive application is brought by the applicants against the respondent bank within six weeks of today's date, the costs be dealt with in the way I have indicated."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1864.html</AustLII>
<text>7 A different approach was taken by Gyles J in C7 Pty Ltd v Foxtel Management Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1864. C7 had sought preliminary discovery of documents. The application was opposed but C7 was largely successful. His Honour expressed the view (at [50]) that an application pursuant to Order 15A of the Federal Court Rules was a discrete application and that he should deal with the costs issue. In reaching this decision his Honour was influenced by the fact that, despite the fact that C7 had been successful, the relief which it obtained was offered prior to the hearing. He was also concerned that the respondent would be out of pocket, awaiting "some indefinite future event" because it was required to undertake the expense of providing the preliminary discovery.

8 In my opinion, in the circumstances of the present case, it is appropriate to make a conventional order. Apache opposed the making of any order relating to preliminary discovery. Moreover, orders of the conventional kind will not expose Apache to an indefinite delay in recovering its costs, at least no more delay than would attend recovery of the costs of discovery in an ordinary proceeding. Apache's interests will be protected by an order that Newcrest pay its costs in the event that no proceeding is commenced in this Court within six weeks of Newcrest undertaking inspection of the discovered documents. Even if Newcrest commences a proceeding in a Court other than this Court Apache will be entitled to recover its costs of providing discovery once the six week period has elapsed.
 I certify that the preceding eight (8) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tracey. 

 Associate:

Dated: 7 November 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr C Archibald 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Blake Dawson 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: Ms B Murray (Solicitor) 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Malleson Stephen Jaques 

 Date of Hearing: 7 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 7 November 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1663.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>