<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Alphapharm Pty Ltd v H Lundbeck A/S (No 2) [2008] FCA 1036 (10 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1036.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler , unreported, Emmett J, 27 May 1997</tocase>
<text>10 Alphapharm and Arrow accept that, upon the appropriate undertakings being given by Lundbeck, there should be a stay in relation to revocation of claim 5 of the Patent since there is some doubt as to the Court's power to order re-instatement: see Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler , unreported, Emmett J, 27 May 1997; Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495 at [4]; Imperial Chemical Industries plc v E I Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co (2002) 58 IPR 227 at [11]. I agree that there should be a stay in relation to claim 5. I note that in Doric v Lockwood above, Hely J observed (at [4]) that it is usual for an order for revocation of a patent to be stayed pending an appeal against the order.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495</tocase>
<text>10 Alphapharm and Arrow accept that, upon the appropriate undertakings being given by Lundbeck, there should be a stay in relation to revocation of claim 5 of the Patent since there is some doubt as to the Court's power to order re-instatement: see Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler , unreported, Emmett J, 27 May 1997; Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495 at [4]; Imperial Chemical Industries plc v E I Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co (2002) 58 IPR 227 at [11]. I agree that there should be a stay in relation to claim 5. I note that in Doric v Lockwood above, Hely J observed (at [4]) that it is usual for an order for revocation of a patent to be stayed pending an appeal against the order.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Imperial Chemical Industries plc v E I Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co (2002) 58 IPR 227</tocase>
<text>10 Alphapharm and Arrow accept that, upon the appropriate undertakings being given by Lundbeck, there should be a stay in relation to revocation of claim 5 of the Patent since there is some doubt as to the Court's power to order re-instatement: see Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler , unreported, Emmett J, 27 May 1997; Doric Products Pty Ltd v Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd (2002) 54 IPR 495 at [4]; Imperial Chemical Industries plc v E I Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co (2002) 58 IPR 227 at [11]. I agree that there should be a stay in relation to claim 5. I note that in Doric v Lockwood above, Hely J observed (at [4]) that it is usual for an order for revocation of a patent to be stayed pending an appeal against the order.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Woolworths Ltd v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 52 ; (2006) 150 FCR 134</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/52.html</AustLII>
<text>17 On the question of the Court's power to order reinstatement, in contending that the Full Court would have that power, Alphapharm relies on Woolworths Ltd v BP plc [2006] FCAFC 52 ; (2006) 150 FCR 134 ( Woolworths ) at [30] [48] per Sundberg and Bennett JJ. Lundbeck contends that Woolworths is distinguishable. That case concerned s 68(1)(b) of the Trade Marks Act 1995 (Cth) (TM Act), in circumstances in which a trade mark had been registered pursuant to the order of the primary Judge and the issue was whether the Court, in its appellate jurisdiction, had power to order removal of the mark. There are some differences between s 192 of the Act and s 68(1)(b) of the TM Act.

18 Lundbeck points out that there has been no judicial determination of the Court's power to order reinstatement of an entry in the Register where the Court has ordered removal of particulars of an extension of term and the order for rectification of the Register has been implemented.

19 I will not explore the present question. It suffices to say that while I suspect that it would be within the implied power of the Court to order reinstatement, there is some doubt which is not clearly removed by Woolworths .

20 There should be a stay in relation to removal of the extension of the term. The potential hardship to Lundbeck if there is no stay, it succeeds in its appeal, and the Court is found to lack power to order reinstatement, far exceeds the hardship to Alphapharm if there is a stay, it successfully resists Lundbeck's appeal, and the appeal is not determined until after 13 June 2009.

21 As a condition of getting the stay, the Lundbeck parties must give to the Court the usual undertaking as to damages, an undertaking to prosecute their appeal expeditiously, and related undertakings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986] ATPR 40-748</tocase>
<text>22 Section 43 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) gives the Court a broad discretion to award costs. In Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) ATPR 40-748 , Toohey J stated (at 2):
 
 1. Ordinarily, costs follow the event and a successful litigant receives his costs in the absence of special circumstances justifying some other order: Ritter v. Godfrey (1920) 2 K.B. 47.
 
 2. Where a litigant has succeeded only upon a portion of his claim, the circumstances may make it reasonable that he bear the expense of litigating that portion upon which he has failed: Forster v. Farquhar (1893) 1 Q.B. 564.
 
 3. A successful party who has failed on certain issues may not only be deprived of the costs of those issues but may be ordered as well to pay the other party's costs of them. In this sense, "issue" does not mean a precise issue in the technical pleading sense but any disputed question of fact or of law: Cretazzo v. Lombardi (1975) 13 S.A.S.R. 4 at 12.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/107.html</AustLII>
<text>23 Even if "the event" is easily identified, it will not always be just that costs follow the event: see Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 107. The notion of costs following the event is not straightforward in the present case.

24 Generally speaking, in the Revocation Proceeding, Lundbeck succeeded in defending the Patent against the attack by Alphapharm. Claim 5 was held invalid, but overall this did not assume great importance. Lundbeck succeeded on its cross-claim for infringement but only to a minor extent, and otherwise Alphapharm succeeded on that cross-claim.

25 Through the Arrow Proceeding, Arrow joined cause with Alphapharm in the attack on the Patent. There was no claim that Arrow had infringed the Patent.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>