<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>TS Production LLC v Drew Pictures Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1329 (27 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1329.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/655.html</AustLII>
<text>10 Neither counsel's argument really addressed the substantive merits of an appeal against Sundberg J's judgment, apart from Mr Rebikoff noting the bare fact that Judge Conlon reached the same choice of law conclusion as Sundberg J. Implicit in Mr Rebikoff's case was the contention that because of the lack of "substantial injustice" to the applicant, supposing Sundberg J to be wrong (see D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398), there was no need to go to the other limb of the D&eacute;cor test and show that his Honour's order was "attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being considered by the Full Court". The lack of substantial injustice was so clear that the application could, and should, be disposed of by a single judge on that ground alone.

11 In theory one can envisage cases where the presence or absence of either substantial injustice or sufficient doubt is so clear and obvious that the application should be disposed of on that ground alone. Such circumstance may in itself point against any departure from the presumption in the Rules that the application be heard before a single judge. The present case is not such a one. As already mentioned, there is, arguably at least, the possibility of substantial injustice being suffered by the applicant.

12 As to sufficient doubt, the point, as I have said, has not been addressed in detail. All I can say is that his Honour's reserved judgment of 81 paragraphs carefully reviews the evidence and authorities. The question for me is not whether it is attended by doubt, sufficient or otherwise, but whether the application should be heard by a Full Court. Sundberg J's judgment deals with substantial legal issues which are appropriate for resolution by a Full Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Optiver Australia Pty Ltd v Tibra Trading Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 133</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/133.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Experience shows that, in cases like the present one, it is not really practicable to separate out the leave issue of whether there the decision below is "attended with sufficient doubt" from the substantive merits. Often the merits of the proposed appeal are argued no less fully than would have been the case were leave not an issue: Optiver Australia Pty Ltd v Tibra Trading Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 133 at [28] .

14 It would seem to be a very inefficient and wasteful course for there to be a separate hearing before a single judge, and if leave were granted, a subsequent hearing before a Full Court. Notwithstanding the complexity of the matter which resulted in, I am told, written submissions of some 40 pages on each side, his Honour disposed of the hearing in less than a day. One would expect that a Full Court dealing with the leave application would be able to deal with the hearing of the matter in a similar time.

15 Related to the question of efficiency is the matter of timing. There is a possibility, although it certainly cannot be guaranteed, that the leave application and appeal could be heard before a Full Court in either the first week or the last week of the coming November sittings. However, these sittings are already extremely full. Alternatively, and still less is this the subject of any promise, a Full Court might be convened before November.

16 If the application for leave were to be heard before a single judge, the hearing may not occur immediately and the judge might have to reserve his or her decision. While of course if leave were refused that would be the end of the matter, if leave were granted the passage of time may have made it impossible to secure a hearing date for the appeal in the November sittings or earlier. In the meantime, the parties would have to go ahead with their preparations for the US trial which conceivably could be heard before the hearing and disposition of the appeal.

17 I think that in all the circumstances the most efficient and fairest course is to order that the application for leave to appeal be heard by a Full Court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>