<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Fig Tree Developments Ltd v Australian Property Custodian Holdings Ltd [2008] FCA 1041 (27 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1041.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brookfield v Yevad Products Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1376</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1376.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Prime highlights rightly, in my respectful submission, that the fact that it has prepared a supplementary list does not, in any way, lead to a conclusion that one should not regard the presumption of conclusivity as still present. In this regard it points to observations made by inter alia Branson J in Brookfield v Yevad Products Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1376. In turn, those particular submissions are contested by Fig Tree.

14 O 15, r 8 of the Federal Court Rules provides as follows:
 Order for particular discovery Where, at any stage of the proceeding, it appears to the Court from evidence or from the nature or circumstances of the case or from any document filed in the proceeding that there are grounds for a belief that some document or class of document relating to any matter in question in the proceeding may be or may have been in the possession, custody or power of a party, the Court may order that party: 
 
 (a) to file any affidavit stating whether that document or any document of that class is or has been in his possession, custody or power and, if it has been but is not then in his possession, custody or power, when he parted with it and what has become of it; and 
 (b) to serve the affidavit on any other party.

15 I emphasise in the terms of O 15 r 8 the words "grounds for a belief" and "may be or may have been". It is true that one does not lightly go behind a discovery affidavit. Prima facie, such an affidavit is conclusive, but that prima facie position may be displaced in the circumstances described in O 15 r 8. Even if displaced, there remains a discretion to exercise. Would it, for example, be unduly oppressive to order the filing of a further affidavit having regard to the potential utility to the party complaining of the document or category of documents? More generally, is it in the interests of justice so to order?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chanel Ltd v F.W. Woolworth and Co Ltd (1981) 1 WLR 485</tocase>
<text>32 And later and by reference to a judgment of Buckley LJ in Chanel Ltd v F.W. Woolworth and Co Ltd (1981) 1 WLR 485:
 An order or undertaking to the court expressed to be until further order by implication gives a right to the party bound by the order or undertaking to apply to the court to have the order or undertaking discharged or modified if good grounds for doing so are shown.

33 The explanation was, he said, that it was not an attempt to modify the contract implicit in the order or undertaking. It was an application in accordance with the contract and, as such, the exercise of an express right reserved by the contract to the party bound by the terms of the order or undertaking. Prime developed at some length a submission that, having seen the manuals which are presently confidential exhibits, there was nothing confidential about them. Fig Tree, at some length, contested this. The consent orders incorporated an agreed position in respect of the manuals. Liberty to apply was reserved to work out questions concerning the operation of those orders. I do not read the reservation of liberty to apply as a reservation of or an invitation to raise questions concerning the confidentiality of the manuals.

34 It is quite apparent from the material read before me that the orders made by consent in November last year obviated, for reasons which were thought good at the time, any contest concerning an issue in relation to the confidentiality of such documents. I see no reason not to hold Prime to its bargain concerning the status of those manuals. Particularly that is so having regard to the relative proximity of the hearing of the application to the date of trial and the length of time which has elapsed since November last year. It also seems to me that there will not be any unjust inhibition of Prime's forensic position if the present position with respect to those manuals is maintained.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fylas Pty Ltd and Vynal Pty Ltd (1992) 2 Qd R 593</tocase>
<text>31 The orders made on 28 November 2007 envisaged liberty to apply. There is a very helpful passage in respect of the position which obtains in relation to orders which have been made by consent in the judgment of McPherson J in his then capacity as Senior Puisne Judge of the Supreme Court of Queensland in Fylas Pty Ltd and Vynal Pty Ltd (1992) 2 Qd R 593 at 599 and also 601. The whole passage is too lengthy conveniently to set out in reasons delivered ex tempore. I do, though, highlight the following observations made by his Honour by reference to authority:
 The position is more complex where the order is made or the undertaking is given in consequence of an agreement between the parties or as an element in such an agreement. For a long time the rule has been that, "The contract of the parties is not the less a contract, and subject to the incidence of a contract because there is superadded the command of a Judge."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gray and Associated Book Publishers (Aust) Pty Limited [2002] FCA 1045</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1045.html</AustLII>
<text>47 In Gray and Associated Book Publishers Aust Pty Limited [2002] FCA 1045 , 23 August 2002, one aspect of an interlocutory controversy before Branson J was self indulged masking out seemingly, in that case, on the basis of an asserted private right of confidentiality. Her Honour observed at para 9:
 The rules of the Federal Court provide no basis for "a claim of irrelevance" in respect of a portion of a document that falls within the terms of an order for discovery. However, it is clear that the power of the court to order that a discovered document be produced for inspection by another party is a discretionary power (see order 15, rule 11). Further, order, 15 rule 5 relevant provides "the court shall not make an order under this order for the filing or service of any list of documents or affidavit or other documents or for the production of any document, unless satisfied that the orders are necessary at the time when the order is made." What is "necessary" within the meaning of order 15, rule 5 is that which is reasonably necessary in the interests of a fair trial and of the fair disposition of the case (Trade Practices Commission v CC (NSW) Pty Limited (1995) 58 FCR 426 at 436-437 Lindgren J).

49 I respectfully agree. As in Gray , Fig Tree did not obtain the agreement of Prime to the masking of portions of its discovered documents, nor did it seek relief from the Court from its prima facie obligations to allow full inspection of its discovered documents. Should that practice now, nonetheless, be authorised by the Court? I share with Mackenzie J, whose concern is evidenced in Menkens v Wintour [2007]) 2 QdR 40, the view that it is salutary to keep in mind another passage from McLelland CJ in Telstra, in which his Honour emphasises a need for caution in exercising a discretion to allow parts of a document to be concealed. As the Chief Judge stated in that case:
 There is a serious risk that too assiduous a marking of documents on the ground of irrelevance will create gaps affecting the ready comprehensibility of the remaining portions of the document and of the context in which those portions appear. If for this, or any other, reason, masking on the grounds of alleged irrelevance would detract from a proper understanding of the meaning and significance of the admittedly relevant parts of the document, then such masking is not justified.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Interchase Corporation Ltd in Liquidation v Grosvenor Hill Qld (Pty Ltd) No 2 (1999) 1 Qd R 163</tocase>
<text>38 The rules require a description to be adequate so as to:
 ...facilitate the production of a particular document for which the privilege has been claimed in the event, for example, of a cessor of the privilege (though for example publication dehors the proceedings) or should the court production upon a ruling that the privilege does not in fact attach : Interchase Corporation Ltd in Liquidation v Grosvenor Hill Qld (Pty Ltd) No 2 (1999) 1 QR 163 at 170.

39 A party seeking disclosure is not entitled to have such a description as would enable the formation of a prima facie view as to the correctness of the claim of privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Koompahtoo Local Aboriginal Land Council v Sanpine Pty Limited [2007] HCA 61 ; (2007) 241 ALR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/61.html</AustLII>
<text>43 The detail of Fig Tree's submissions as to why no such discovery should be ordered appears at para 61 of its outline. Again, the exigencies of the moment do not conveniently admit of setting that out in full. It seems to me that discovery should not be ordered in respect of this category because:
 
1. no arguable basis for the discovery of such documents as an aid to construction has been made out; and
 
2. in relation to the repudiation controversy the test an objective one - what the conduct would convey to a reasonable person in the position of the other party : Koompahtoo Local Aboriginal Land Council v Sanpine Pty Limited [2007] HCA 61 ; (2007) 241 ALR 88 at para 44.

44 Having regard to what is there said, the arguments advanced on behalf of Prime as to the relevance of the documents in this particular category are not persuasive. This aspect of the application fails.

45 Fig Tree has arrogated to itself the ability, without Court order, to mask out portions of discovered documents. Mr Tomlinson, in exhibits to his affidavit has given examples of what has been done in this regard. There are many documents indeed which have been masked out. How the masking out was done is explained in an affidavit of Ms Freyling, a solicitor in the employ of Minter Ellison, the solicitors for Fig Tree. She and two others, respectively described as a graduate and a research clerk (each presumably, therefore, not a solicitor), were involved in a process of masking out. Sometimes in cases thought to be doubtful, advice was taken from a more senior practitioner within the firm. Ms Freyling swears, and it is worth recording that she was not cross examined in this regard, that some 90 to 95 per cent of masking out was on the basis of "relevance" with the balance being privilege.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kyocera Mita Australia Pty Ltd v Mitronics Corporation Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 242</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/242.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In Kyocera Mita Australia Pty Ltd v Mitronics Corporation Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 242 , Stone J dismissed an application for an order which would have required a defendant to provide a list which specifically identified each document in respect of which a claim for privilege was advanced. Her Honour observed at paragraph 13:
 I do not propose to make the order sought by Kyocera. The categories have been identified not by description of the legal privilege that is claimed but by description of the documents themselves. The discovery has been verified by affidavit. In the circumstances, I am of the view that the costs involved in a matter that has been going for such a long period of time as this far outweigh any benefit from identifying and describing the documents individually in the way Kyocera seeks.

41 While the practice adopted by Fig Tree may not, at least to some, be an exemplar of perfection, it adequately recites in paras 1 to 3 of Pt 2 of Sch 1, the grounds upon which privilege is claimed in those parts of the documents in Pt 1 of Sch 1. A solicitor has certified that list. The observations made by Stone J seem to me to be apposite in the circumstances of this case. In particular, I am not satisfied that the costs of striving for any further precision at this stage of the proceedings are warranted. This aspect of Prime's notice of motion fails.

42 There has been discovery of certain documents falling into this category. What is controversial is whether there should be discovery of:
 Correspondence passing between Fig Tree and SCV which relate to the coming into existence of the assignment agreement between them, ie, an agreement which was made on 30 May 2007, much as the correspondence, which has flowed between solicitors on this subject.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/66.html</AustLII>
<text>22 It seems to me, though, having regard to the terms of the announcement, that any privilege in so much of any advice from senior counsel as is referred to in that announcement has been waived by Prime. I take the relevant principle from a passage in the reasons for judgment of Gleeson CJ and Gaudron, Gummow and Callinan JJ in Mann v Carnell [1999] HCA 66 ; (1999) 201 CLR 1 at page 13 at para 29: 
 Waiver may be express or implied. Disputes as to implied waiver usually arise from the need to decide whether particular conduct is inconsistent with the maintenance of the confidentiality which the privilege is intended to protect. When an affirmative answer is given to such a question, it is sometimes said that waiver is "imputed by operation of law" 37 . This means that the law recognises the inconsistency and determines its consequences, even though such consequences may not reflect the subjective intention of the party who has lost the privilege. . . . What brings about the waiver is the inconsistency, which the courts, where necessary informed by considerations of fairness, perceive, between the conduct of the client and maintenance of the confidentiality; not some overriding principle of fairness operating at large.

23 Their Honours continued at page 15:
 Disclosure by a client of confidential legal advice received by the client, which may be for the purpose of explaining or justifying the client's actions, or for some other purpose, will waive privilege if such disclosure is inconsistent with the confidentiality which the privilege serves to protect. Depending upon the circumstances of the case, considerations of fairness may be relevant to a determination of whether there is such inconsistency.

24 There is certainly a temporal element in the word "following" which appears in the media release. In context, though, my opinion is that there is not only such an element. It also seems to me that it carries with it an indication that the course of action described and position taken is in conformity with senior counsel's advice. Why else, one asks rhetorically in a matter such as this with its evident seriousness in a public announcement, does one make such a reference to senior counsel? It is, of course, the case that senior counsel's advice to Prime may have ranged much more widely than that described in the media release. I can see no waiver of any such wider ranging advice apparent on the face of that media release.

25 It is conceivable, therefore, that there may well be, at least prima facie , some residual privilege claim available. I propose, therefore, to order that a further affidavit of documents be provided in respect of the category four documents. In so ordering I reserve expressly such claims of privilege in respect of documents within that category as may be just. Those claims will obviously be subject to the conclusions which I have reached in respect of waiver.

26 Category 9 is described in the schedule. It is not necessary to set out its terms in detail. That is because the fate of the application in respect of category 9 seems to me, correctly with respect, as was submitted by counsel on behalf of Fig Tree to turn on the outcome of category 1. There will, therefore, be an order for a further affidavit in respect of category 9.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Menkens v Wintour [2007] 2 Qd R 40</tocase>
<text>49 I respectfully agree. As in Gray , Fig Tree did not obtain the agreement of Prime to the masking of portions of its discovered documents, nor did it seek relief from the Court from its prima facie obligations to allow full inspection of its discovered documents. Should that practice now, nonetheless, be authorised by the Court? I share with Mackenzie J, whose concern is evidenced in Menkens v Wintour [2007]) 2 QdR 40, the view that it is salutary to keep in mind another passage from McLelland CJ in Telstra, in which his Honour emphasises a need for caution in exercising a discretion to allow parts of a document to be concealed. As the Chief Judge stated in that case:
 There is a serious risk that too assiduous a marking of documents on the ground of irrelevance will create gaps affecting the ready comprehensibility of the remaining portions of the document and of the context in which those portions appear. If for this, or any other, reason, masking on the grounds of alleged irrelevance would detract from a proper understanding of the meaning and significance of the admittedly relevant parts of the document, then such masking is not justified.

56 It is submitted that there is no utility demonstrated in requiring the provision for inspection of complete documents; I respectfully disagree. I have already voiced agreement with concerns voiced by Mackenzie J and made reference to a risk that I apprehend is present.

57 It may very well be that in relation to many of those 2005 documents that this particular risk, presently apprehended, proves to be unfounded. If so, though, that will be wisdom of hindsight. At present, it seems to me that Prime has been presented, in a way the nature and extent of which it is not possible, on the materials to hand, fully to judge, with, at least, some and probably many documents which have about them a quality of sterility and depravation of context so far as their meaning is concerned. There is, in my opinion, forensic utility in the ordinary position prevailing. That Fig Tree may incur further expense in the provision of unmasked copies is a consideration, but it is outweighed by the considerations that I have mentioned.

58 A concern also that I have is that, at this stage, one ought not encourage what I regard as a practice which is irregular. Irregular, in the sense that no Court order and, for that matter, no prior agreement was sought. I am concerned also, though, that Fig Tree should not be deprived of just claims of privilege in respect of its discovered documents. I therefore propose to order that such of the masked documents as are subject to a claim for privilege be excluded from production, save for that Fig Tree must produce the documents which it has discovered in its lists. I reserve liberty to apply in respect of any dispute as to the validity of a claim for privilege. Subject, though, to that, I propose to order that unmasked copies of Fig Tree's discovered documents be produced for inspection.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>