<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hannaford (trading as Torrens Valley Orchards) v Australian Farmlink Pty Ltd ACN 087 011 541 [2008] FCA 1591 (24 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1591.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Telecommunications Products Case , Cour de Cassation (France), 2 April 2008</tocase>
<text>5 The oral character of the contract(s) apart, two further factors have complicated the resolution of this matter. The first is the real uncertainty as to the legal context in which the question of characterisation of the parties' relationship is to be addressed. If the matter is properly to be regarded as one of sale and resale, the vendor-purchaser relationship between TVO and Farmlink would be subject to the Sale of Goods Act 1895 (SA) and the resale relationship between Farmlink and Freshmart, but not Mak, probably to the Sale of Goods (Vienna Convention) Act 1986 (SA). This latter matter, though, has not been addressed by the parties and has not been the subject of evidence to the extent that it might raise questions as to the law of Singapore and Hong Kong respectively: see United Nations Convention on Contracts for the International Sale of Goods , Art 1 ("CISG"). Singapore has ratified the CISG and it is in force in that country. Though the CISG was in force in China, but not in Hong Kong, at the time of the "hand over" to China, China has apparently not taken the necessary steps to have the CISG apply to Hong Kong. The Cour de Cassation in France has, in consequence, recently concluded that the CISG was not applicable to Hong Kong: see Telecommunications Products Case , Cour de Cassation, 2 April 2008; and see generally Schroeter UG, "The Status of Hong Kong and Macao under the United Nations Convention on Contracts for the International Sale of Goods" (2004) 16 Pace International Law Review 307. If, on the other hand, the relationship of TVO and Farmlink is that of principal and agent, TVO's relationship with Freshmart, but not with Mak, was subject probably to the provisions of the Sale of Goods (Vienna Convention) Act . I mention this for the following reason. The CISG, but not the domestic Sale of Goods Act , has a developed regime for a buyer (i) to notify a seller of lack of conformity with the quality required by the contract: see CISG Arts 35, 39 and 44 and see Schlechtriem and Schwenzer (eds), Commentary on the UN Convention on International Sale of Goods at 411 ff and 460 ff (2 nd English ed, 2005); and (ii) to effect a price reduction for non-conformity: CISG Art 50 and Schlechtriem and Schwenger at 596 ff. I note this because both Farmlink and Mak effected price reductions. The evidence on whether they were negotiated or not is controversial.

6 The second complicating factor relates to those price reductions. It is clear from the evidence that, at presently relevant times, quality problems of varying severity were prevalent in both the domestic and overseas sales of cherries generally and that, in respect of overseas sales, exporters routinely passed on price reductions to Australian suppliers in response to this phenomenon. The evidence both of TVO's dealings with other exporters, and of its dealings with Farmlink since the 2000/2001 cherry season, illustrate this practice. The significance, if any, of it in the characterisation of the parties' relationship and in the terms of it has been vigorously debated before me.

7 I have in the event concluded that Farmlink was not TVO's agent. It was a purchaser for resale. The individual purchases in respect of each consignment to Singapore and Hong Kong were for agreed prices. Because quality defects were a recurrent concern and because Freshmart and Mak effected price reductions (whether or not, at least in Freshmart's case, in reliance upon Art 50 of the CISG), the individual sales by TVO took place in a context in which reductions in the "purchase price" payable by Freshmart and Mak were to be anticipated in some degree for quality defects. I am not satisfied, though, that in passing on price reductions Farmlink had any contractual right so to do. Formally it may have had rights against TVO under the Sale of Goods Act (eg s 14 and s 52) for which it may have been entitled to claim damages for breach of warranty in respect of particular individual contracts or to set off such a breach in diminution or extinction of the price.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/50.html</AustLII>
<text>8 Mr Hannaford's routine acceptance of reductions (at least those said to be made for quality reasons) in the purchase price owing to him was, in my view, a reasonable and sensible business response to a recurrent phenomenon in an ongoing business relationship in a market for perishables. As I observed in GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at [230] :
 ... notwithstanding their contract, parties in an ongoing business relationship ... commonly "regulate their relationships in accordance with what they consider is fair and reasonable or commercially necessary at particular points in time rather than by reference to a priori rights and duties arising under a contract": Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd [v Digital Equipment Corporation (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11, 110] at 11,117. 
Such "mutual accommodation" may, or may not, over time evidence a contract variation. In the present case as pleaded it did not. Mr Hannaford was not obliged to accept whatever price reduction Farmlink had accepted from, or perhaps even agreed with, Freshmart and Mak. He retained his right to renegotiate his contract with Farmlink and was entitled to insist that price reductions ascribed to quality defects were reasonable and legitimate, ie were in fact made for reasons of quality and were ones for which he bore the responsibility.

9 (i) Anthony Hannaford. Mr Hannaford is, apparently, the biggest cherry grower in South Australia. He commenced his own business in 1985 and registered the business name Torrens Valley Orchards several years later. During the 2003/2004 cherry season he owned and he still owns three orchards in the Adelaide Hills. After an early dealing with Mr Plummer in the late 1980s, he recommenced dealings with Mr Plummer and Ms Churchill in the mid-nineties about which time, or perhaps a little later, he commenced supplying them with cherries.

10 (ii) Heather Churchill. Ms Churchill has been involved in the export industry since the mid to late 1980s. She moved to South Australia in 1993 and took up a position as export coordinator with an apple exporter, South Australian Horticultural Export Co. While working in that position she met Mr Plummer who, in 1999, offered her a position with Australian Farmlink Pty Ltd, a new business which he was involved in starting up. As export manager, her responsibilities were to find market sales for produce, to arrange for its export and delivery and to discharge all the associated accounting and administrative functions. She was responsible to the directors of Farmlink. The overseas markets with which she had dealings included Singapore, Malaysia, Thailand, Taiwan, Hong Kong, the UK and some Pacific islands. Her evidence was that although Farmlink dealt with a variety of products for export, during the cherry season she concentrated 100 per cent on cherries. Ms Churchill remained the export manager of Farmlink until 2006.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hawkins v Clayton [1988] HCA 15 ; (1988) 164 CLR 539</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/15.html</AustLII>
<text>43 I am quite conscious of the foundation that both a prior course of dealing between parties and practices and usages thereby established between them can provide (a) for the drawing of inferences as to the actual terms on which the parties have contracted and (b) for the imputation of implied terms in their contract: for the difference between inference and imputation, see Hawkins v Clayton [1988] HCA 15 ; (1988) 164 CLR 539 at 570-571 and 573. This is evidenced both in the provisions of international instruments such as the CISG Art 9: see Schlechtriem and Schwenzer at 141 ff; see also Unidroit Principles of International Commercial Contracts 2004 , Arts 1.9 and 5.1.2; and in the domestic laws of common law countries: see eg Uniform Commercial Code , SS1-303; Restatement of Contracts , Second , SS223; Farnsworth on Contracts , SS7.13 (3 rd ed, 2004); Furmston (ed), The Law of Contract at [3.18] (2 nd ed, 2003); Cheshire and Fifoot, Law of Contract at [10.18] and [10.29] (9 th Aust ed, 2008). I equally accept that it may well have been the case, as I will later suggest, that some at least of the terms upon which TVO and Farmlink actually intended to contract in the 2003/2004 season were to be inferred from their prior course of dealings. But that is not the question on which I must rule.

44 The amendment sought to be made at such a late stage is not one which I consider should be permitted. It is yet another variant on the term initially proposed the variation seemingly being a response to accommodate questioning during final submissions. It is of such a character that it ought to have been the subject of evidence both of Ms Churchill and of Mr Hannaford. It raises quite a spectrum of different issues to those raised by what had been pleaded by the respondents. And it embodies an exception the provenance of which relates only to evidence in the 2003/2004 season and not to "past dealings". It is simply far too late in the day to permit this amendment to be made, the more so because I consider the proposal itself to be uncertain in scope and ambiguous in content.

45 I will in any event later suggest both that the term itself attributes a character and a consequence to past dealings which I do not consider is reasonably suggested by them and that important aspects of Ms Churchill's decisions in 2003/2004 in relation to purchase discounts had no reflection at all in the prior course of dealing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fraser-Ramsay (New Zealand) Ltd v De Renzy (1912) 32 NZLR 553</tocase>
<text>46 Notwithstanding that the relationships of principal and agent and seller and buyer are mutually exclusive, the one being a fiduciary relationship, the other a "commercially adverse relationship": Bowstead &amp; Reynolds on Agency at [1-032] (18 th ed, 2006); the distinction between them in cases where sales or purchases have been effectuated by an intermediary can be a fine one not easy to draw: see Atiyah, The Sale of Goods at 28 (10 th ed, 2001). Unsurprisingly, courts have emphasised that decided cases are for the most part of limited assistance given the quite fact (and agreement) specific nature of the inquiry to be made: see eg Fraser-Ramsay (New Zealand) Ltd v De Renzy (1912) 32 NZLR 553 at 575; see generally, Dal Pont, Law of Agency at [2.3] (2 nd ed, 2008); the more so when, as in the present matter, the contract in question (whether of agency or sale) is an oral one: cf Mercantile International Group plc v Chuan Soon Huat Industrial Group Ltd [2002] EWCA Civ 288 at [30] - [31] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Mercantile International Group plc v Chuan Soon Huat Industrial Group Ltd [2002] EWCA Civ 288</tocase>
<text>46 Notwithstanding that the relationships of principal and agent and seller and buyer are mutually exclusive, the one being a fiduciary relationship, the other a "commercially adverse relationship": Bowstead &amp; Reynolds on Agency at [1-032] (18 th ed, 2006); the distinction between them in cases where sales or purchases have been effectuated by an intermediary can be a fine one not easy to draw: see Atiyah, The Sale of Goods at 28 (10 th ed, 2001). Unsurprisingly, courts have emphasised that decided cases are for the most part of limited assistance given the quite fact (and agreement) specific nature of the inquiry to be made: see eg Fraser-Ramsay (New Zealand) Ltd v De Renzy (1912) 32 NZLR 553 at 575; see generally, Dal Pont, Law of Agency at [2.3] (2 nd ed, 2008); the more so when, as in the present matter, the contract in question (whether of agency or sale) is an oral one: cf Mercantile International Group plc v Chuan Soon Huat Industrial Group Ltd [2002] EWCA Civ 288 at [30] - [31] .

51 (i) As an agent for sale ordinarily acts on behalf of its principal: but cf in relation to a broker selling in its own name: Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd [1973] 2 Lloyd's Rep 404 at 408; Jackson Securities Ltd v Cheesman (1986) 4 NSWLR 484 at 489-490; is it apparent from the facts that the seller has actually conferred on the intermediary an authority to negotiate and/or to sell on the seller's behalf thus bringing into existence direct contracts between the seller and the third party buyer: Mercantile International Group plc at [30]-[34]?

52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].

185 The evidence, in my view, simply cannot sustain a conclusion that Farmlink acted on TVO's behalf in a "representative": cf Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society at 48-50; or "fiduciary": cf Restatement of Agency , Second , SS1.01; capacity in selling its cherries. Farmlink was a purchaser buying for the purposes of resale. It is significant in this that (i) the parties agreed in advance the prices at which TVO would sell its cherries they were not simply indicative prices (I will refer below to the significance in this of purchase discounts); (ii) while the consignments were into markets with which TVO had some, albeit rudimentary knowledge, they were simply two of the overseas markets into which TVO cherries were consigned by exporters in the 2003/2004 season; (iii) Farmlink, in contrast, was knowledgeable about, and experienced in, those two markets at that time: cf Witt at 18-19; (iv) TVO did not assume responsibility for the export or the costs associated with the export this was at Farmlink's expense: cf Witt at 18-19 and Farmlink, not TVO, bore responsibility for misadventures happening to the cherries after delivery to it; (v) TVO was not in a position to exercise practical control over Farmlink (other than by refusing orders); (vi) TVO was unaware of Farmlink's price; (vii) while Mr Hannaford doubtless understood that Farmlink would obtain its own return on the sales (howsoever this was done), there was nothing unusual about his having no interest in that matter as his relationship with Farmlink did not otherwise point to an agency relationship: cf Mercantile International Group plc at [5] and [36]; and (ix) TVO happened to know the Singapore buyer was a company with which Mr Koh was associated but did not know the identity of the Hong Kong buyer. In short, having regard to the context in which they dealt with each other, the relationship they formed in the making and filling of orders was that of seller and buyer for resale. The contrary inference that TVO appointed Farmlink its agent for sale is neither a reasonable, nor the most probable, deduction from the known facts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611</tocase>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1958/16.html</AustLII>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.

53 (iii) It may be apparent from the circumstances and context of the supplier's and intermediary's dealing, that, on sales to a third party buyer it was reasonably to be expected that the intermediary was to answer to that buyer for the quality of the goods sold: cf International Harvester Co ; Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-032].

54 (iv) Two duties stemming from a finding of agency are that the agent (a) must keep its principal's property separate from its own; and (b) must keep an accurate account of all transactions entered into on its principal's behalf: see generally Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [6-088] ff; Dal Pont, Ch 13. It has been suggested on occasion that these consequences may be indicative of an agency (at least if they have been expressly or impliedly agreed by the parties): cf Benjamin's Sale of Goods at [1-049] (7 th ed, 2006). For present purposes I merely note those agency obligations. I will make further reference to them after having outlined how Farmlink actually dealt with TVO in relation to the proceeds of sale received from the Singaporean and Hong Kong buyers and in relation to keeping accounts of the sales made by Farmlink.

179 Under the shadow of the principles to which I earlier referred and of the decisions of International Harvester Co , Ex parte White; In re Neville and Witt in particular, the factual matters upon which TVO relies primarily for this conclusion are: (i) the transaction between TVO and Farmlink was at a firm price; (ii) the documentation all reflected a sale from TVO to Farmlink; (iii) Farmlink set the price for the overseas sale and kept its sale price and margin a secret; (iv) Farmlink engaged all the freight forwarders and paid the freight costs itself; (v) Farmlink never accounted to TVO in a way which showed the total amount received, its margin and amounts paid for freight, etc; (vi) Farmlink issued invoices to its overseas customers; (vii) Farmlink alone knew the identity and location of its overseas customers; (viii) Farmlink identified itself as the shipper on the bills of lading and airway bills; (ix) Farmlink negotiated the changes in price without checking or obtaining instructions from TVO or Mr Hannaford; and (x) significantly in the year that there was insurance, the insured was Farmlink, the consignee's interest was noted, but there was no recording of TVO having any interest in the cherries.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552</tocase>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130</tocase>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967)</tocase>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1931/53.html</AustLII>
<text>47 Before identifying those factors which have been found to be of varying significance as indicators of, variously, agency or sale, it is appropriate, first, to refer generally to a number of relatively uncontroversial propositions of agency law. In so doing, I repeat for convenience in part what I said in South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club Ltd v News Ltd (2000) 177 ALR 611 at [131] ff.
 
(1) Those definitions of agency that take the principal and agent relationship itself as their particular focus: contrast International Harvester Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Carrigan's Hazeldene Pastoral Co [1958] HCA 16 ; (1958) 100 CLR 644 at 652; emphasise that that relationship "can only be established by the consent of the principal and the agent": Garnac Grain Co Inc v HMF Faure &amp; Fairclough Ltd [1968] AC 1130 at 1137; see, for example, Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Restatement of Agency, Third , SS1.01; 3 Am Jur 2d, "Agency", SS15.
 
(2) The consents so given need not necessarily be to a relationship that the parties understand, or even accept, to be that of principal and agent: Branwhite v Worcester Works Finance Ltd [1969] 1 AC 552 at 587. It is sufficient if "they have agreed to what amounts in law to such a relationship": Garnac Grain Co Inc at 1137; Nichols v Arthur Murray Inc 56 Cal Rptr 728 (1967) at 730-731; Restatement of Agency, Second, SS1 comment.
 
(3) Though there is no uniformly agreed definition of agency: see the discussion in Fisher, Agency Law at 8-11 (2000); the two whose authoritative character has resulted in their wide citation are those of the Restatement of Agency, Third, SS1.01 and of Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001] (the latter being based upon the Restatement provision). The Restatement's definition is that:
 
 
 
 SS1.01 Agency is the fiduciary relationship that arises when one person (a "principal") manifests assent to another person (an "agent") that the agent shall act on the principal's behalf and subject to the principal's control, and the agent manifests assent or otherwise consents so to act.
 
 
 

 Bowstead &amp; Reynolds' definition is that: 
 
 
 
 [1-001] Agency is the fiduciary relationship which exists between two persons, one of whom expressly or impliedly manifests assent that the other should act on his behalf so as to affect his relations with third parties, and the other of whom similarly manifests assent so to act or so acts pursuant to the manifestation. 
 
 
 

 The necessary consents apart, the required characteristic of the relationship is that one party acts on behalf of, and is authorised to act on behalf of, the other. This "representative" characteristic must be able to be discerned in the factual relation of the parties: Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd v The Producers and Citizens Co-operative Assurance Co of Australia Ltd [1931] HCA 53 ; (1931) 46 CLR 41 at 48-50.
 
(4) Though the characteristic of "control" is accentuated in the Restatement's definition: see comment f to SS1.01; its significance is far more muted in Anglo-Australian law: see South Sydney District Rugby League Football Club at [136]. Thus, it is commented in Bowstead &amp; Reynolds (at [1-017]) that:
 
 
 It might seem therefore that control is not a significant feature of the internal relationship, except in so far as the relationship by definition posits a person, the principal, giving authority, and the agent's duty to obey instructions if he wishes to continue as agent. Nevertheless, if the principal gives up all control of his supposed agent the relationship is only doubtfully one of agency. 
 

 I will return to the significance of the presence or absence of control later in these reasons.

185 The evidence, in my view, simply cannot sustain a conclusion that Farmlink acted on TVO's behalf in a "representative": cf Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society at 48-50; or "fiduciary": cf Restatement of Agency , Second , SS1.01; capacity in selling its cherries. Farmlink was a purchaser buying for the purposes of resale. It is significant in this that (i) the parties agreed in advance the prices at which TVO would sell its cherries they were not simply indicative prices (I will refer below to the significance in this of purchase discounts); (ii) while the consignments were into markets with which TVO had some, albeit rudimentary knowledge, they were simply two of the overseas markets into which TVO cherries were consigned by exporters in the 2003/2004 season; (iii) Farmlink, in contrast, was knowledgeable about, and experienced in, those two markets at that time: cf Witt at 18-19; (iv) TVO did not assume responsibility for the export or the costs associated with the export this was at Farmlink's expense: cf Witt at 18-19 and Farmlink, not TVO, bore responsibility for misadventures happening to the cherries after delivery to it; (v) TVO was not in a position to exercise practical control over Farmlink (other than by refusing orders); (vi) TVO was unaware of Farmlink's price; (vii) while Mr Hannaford doubtless understood that Farmlink would obtain its own return on the sales (howsoever this was done), there was nothing unusual about his having no interest in that matter as his relationship with Farmlink did not otherwise point to an agency relationship: cf Mercantile International Group plc at [5] and [36]; and (ix) TVO happened to know the Singapore buyer was a company with which Mr Koh was associated but did not know the identity of the Hong Kong buyer. In short, having regard to the context in which they dealt with each other, the relationship they formed in the making and filling of orders was that of seller and buyer for resale. The contrary inference that TVO appointed Farmlink its agent for sale is neither a reasonable, nor the most probable, deduction from the known facts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd [1973] 2 Lloyd's Rep 404</tocase>
<text>51 (i) As an agent for sale ordinarily acts on behalf of its principal: but cf in relation to a broker selling in its own name: Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd [1973] 2 Lloyd's Rep 404 at 408; Jackson Securities Ltd v Cheesman (1986) 4 NSWLR 484 at 489-490; is it apparent from the facts that the seller has actually conferred on the intermediary an authority to negotiate and/or to sell on the seller's behalf thus bringing into existence direct contracts between the seller and the third party buyer: Mercantile International Group plc at [30]-[34]?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jackson Securities Ltd v Cheesman (1986) 4 NSWLR 484</tocase>
<text>51 (i) As an agent for sale ordinarily acts on behalf of its principal: but cf in relation to a broker selling in its own name: Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd [1973] 2 Lloyd's Rep 404 at 408; Jackson Securities Ltd v Cheesman (1986) 4 NSWLR 484 at 489-490; is it apparent from the facts that the seller has actually conferred on the intermediary an authority to negotiate and/or to sell on the seller's behalf thus bringing into existence direct contracts between the seller and the third party buyer: Mercantile International Group plc at [30]-[34]?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285</tocase>
<text>52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361</tocase>
<text>52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203</tocase>
<text>52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397</tocase>
<text>52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].

179 Under the shadow of the principles to which I earlier referred and of the decisions of International Harvester Co , Ex parte White; In re Neville and Witt in particular, the factual matters upon which TVO relies primarily for this conclusion are: (i) the transaction between TVO and Farmlink was at a firm price; (ii) the documentation all reflected a sale from TVO to Farmlink; (iii) Farmlink set the price for the overseas sale and kept its sale price and margin a secret; (iv) Farmlink engaged all the freight forwarders and paid the freight costs itself; (v) Farmlink never accounted to TVO in a way which showed the total amount received, its margin and amounts paid for freight, etc; (vi) Farmlink issued invoices to its overseas customers; (vii) Farmlink alone knew the identity and location of its overseas customers; (viii) Farmlink identified itself as the shipper on the bills of lading and airway bills; (ix) Farmlink negotiated the changes in price without checking or obtaining instructions from TVO or Mr Hannaford; and (x) significantly in the year that there was insurance, the insured was Farmlink, the consignee's interest was noted, but there was no recording of TVO having any interest in the cherries.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566</tocase>
<text>52 (ii) Often interlocking factors of some significance are (a) by whom is the sale price to the third party set? and (b) how is the intermediary remunerated/rewarded for the sale to the third party? If the intermediary is remunerated by commission pre-arranged with the seller this will ordinarily indicate an agency relationship: eg Weiner v Harris [1910] 1 KB 285; although in exceptional circumstances a buyer for resale may be paid what is described, or is misdescribed, as a commission: eg Gannow Engineering Co Ltd v Richardson [1930] NZLR 361 ; Jackson v Royal Bank of Scotland [2000] EWCA Civ 203 at [17] - [18] . In the absence of fully informed consent, it would be a breach of fiduciary duty for an agent to profit on the sale of its principal's property by, for example, marking up the principal's stipulated sale price and retaining the difference. That an intermediary so acts may itself be indicative that the parties relationship was that of seller and buyer for resale and not agency for sale: Ex parte White; In re Nevill (1870) LR 6 Ch App 397. Nonetheless, a principal may agree to an agent deriving its remuneration from a mark-up on the price the principal stipulates it is to receive from the sale: eg Ex parte Bright; In re Smith (1879) 10 Ch D 566. In Mercantile International Group plc in circumstances in which the agreements between the parties pointed unambiguously to an agency relationship, it was held that that conclusion was unaffected by the circumstances that the principal knew that the intermediary charged more to purchasers than it confirmed to the principal; the principal did not mind nor care to know the detail of the matter, but was satisfied to get the price it stipulated; and the principal was content that the intermediary should keep for itself an undefined margin, it obtaining no remuneration by way of commission or otherwise from the principal: at [5] and [36].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd </tocase>
<text>51 (i) As an agent for sale ordinarily acts on behalf of its principal: but cf in relation to a broker selling in its own name: Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd [1973] 2 Lloyd's Rep 404 at 408; Jackson Securities Ltd v Cheesman (1986) 4 NSWLR 484 at 489-490; is it apparent from the facts that the seller has actually conferred on the intermediary an authority to negotiate and/or to sell on the seller's behalf thus bringing into existence direct contracts between the seller and the third party buyer: Mercantile International Group plc at [30]-[34]?

55 There are two final matters to which I should refer. First, while the relationships of agency and sale are mutually exclusive, it is not uncommon for an intermediary to be the agent of its seller-principal but to be a principal vis-&agrave;-vis a third party on the sale to it: see eg Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd at 408; Aluminium Industrie Vaassen BV v Romalpa Aluminium Ltd [1976] 1 WLR 676. As was said by Roskill LJ in Romalpa (at 690):
 I see no difficulty in the contractual concept that, as between the defendants and their sub-purchasers, the defendants sold as principals, but that, as between themselves and the plaintiffs, those goods which they were selling as principals within their implied authority from the plaintiffs were the plaintiffs' goods which they were selling as agents for the plaintiffs to whom they remained fully accountable. 
As will be seen, the respondents seek to draw some comfort from this.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Aluminium Industrie Vaassen BV v Romalpa Aluminium Ltd [1976] 1 WLR 676</tocase>
<text>55 There are two final matters to which I should refer. First, while the relationships of agency and sale are mutually exclusive, it is not uncommon for an intermediary to be the agent of its seller-principal but to be a principal vis-&agrave;-vis a third party on the sale to it: see eg Bailey &amp; Co Ltd v Balholm Securities Ltd at 408; Aluminium Industrie Vaassen BV v Romalpa Aluminium Ltd [1976] 1 WLR 676. As was said by Roskill LJ in Romalpa (at 690):
 I see no difficulty in the contractual concept that, as between the defendants and their sub-purchasers, the defendants sold as principals, but that, as between themselves and the plaintiffs, those goods which they were selling as principals within their implied authority from the plaintiffs were the plaintiffs' goods which they were selling as agents for the plaintiffs to whom they remained fully accountable. 
As will be seen, the respondents seek to draw some comfort from this.

74 To anticipate matters, the applicant's contention is that the above documentation clearly indicated that each transaction involved a sale by TVO to Farmlink with a re-sale to the overseas buyer. Farmlink, in contrast, contends that the documentation is consistent with its having acted as an agent for sale vis-&agrave;-vis TVO and as a seller vis-&agrave;-vis the overseas buyers, hence its reliance upon Romalpa at 690.

75 Consistent with her practice in earlier seasons, Ms Churchill arranged a pre-season planning meeting at PBVO on 30 October 2003 with growers (including Mr Hannaford) with whom she hoped to deal and who may have been interested in exporting some cherries. Apart from having a wrap-up of the previous season, the agenda referred, amongst other matters, to crop expectations, ie volume, size, quality and timing, to export market potential and to packaging requirements. The agenda did not refer to price unsurprisingly in my view given that the meeting was almost two months in advance of when exporting might be expected to commence and about a month before picking. It is Ms Churchill's evidence that price probably was not discussed at that meeting: "Not that early, no". I would note that the Cherry Export Marketing Strategy she faxed to TVO on 2 December 2003 made no mention of price and, in a fax to Freshmart of the same date suggesting an export "Program for Singapore", she gave only indicative prices as it was "too early for the real prices".

76 At some time, though, it is clear that the growers told Ms Churchill what prices per kilo they wanted for cherries (categorised by size), such that there was, according to Ms Churchill, an understanding between not just Farmlink and TVO, but all the growers that "this was the sort of price they would want to go out to the market to return, and that's what they expected". It is equally clear that she calculated her own export strategy referred to below on the basis of those prices. Those prices were (i) $7.00/kg for 24-26mm fruit; (ii) $9.00/kg for 26-28mm fruit; (iii) $11.00/kg for 28mm fruit; and (iv) there was about a $1.00 premium on 500gm punnets. Farmlink and TVO later agreed several changes to these prices as actual consignments were made. It also is alleged that Farmlink made unauthorised changes on occasion, ie changes not negotiated with TVO.

184 The issue that remains is: what was the true character of the TVO-Farmlink relationship? As I have earlier indicated, while the relationships of agency and sale are mutually exclusive, it is not uncommon for an intermediary to be the agent of its seller-principal but to be a principal vis-&agrave;-vis a third party on a sale to it: see above [55]. In my view the present is not one such case. And it is, in any event, far removed from the reservation of title clause type of case exemplified by Romalpa on which the respondents' rely.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Natwest Wholesale Australia Pty Ltd [1987] HCA 30 ; (1987) 163 CLR 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/30.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Such orders were effected usually by TVO delivering the packaged cherries to PBVO or, on occasion, to freight forwarders retained and paid for by Farmlink. It is agreed between the parties that, if the relationship between TVO and Farmlink was that of sale and purchase, such delivery was an unconditional appropriation such that property passed to Farmlink: see Sale of Goods Act , s 18 rule 5(1) ; Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Natwest Wholesale Australia Pty Ltd [1987] HCA 30 ; (1987) 163 CLR 236 ; Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA v Charles Twigg &amp; Co Ltd [1957] 1 Lloyd's Rep 240. When making a delivery TVO usually faxed what it called a "dispatch docket" to Farmlink. This handwritten document, which made no reference to price, was for present purposes the only document of significance generated by TVO for delivery to Farmlink in any season. Mr Hannaford's explanation for the absence of a price on the dispatch docket was that: 
 We didn't put a price on because sometimes the price can vary a little bit and this was one reason for creating these documents was for our own internal records as well to keep track of our sales for our own viewpoint but there was very often a price variation to do with cost of freight [or] the fact if they were in punnets or gift boxes, there may be some variation to the agreed price.

187 Being a contract for the sale of goods, each order filled was subject to the provisions of the Sale of Goods Act . As I earlier noted, it is agreed in light of my sale finding that property in the cherries passed in respect of each consignment when the goods were appropriated to the contract and this occurred on delivery: see Sale of Goods Act , s 18 rule 5 ; Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) at 255; Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA . The individual orders equally were subject to the provisions of s 14 of the Act as to implied conditions as to quality and fitness. Though it has not been the subject of contest by TVO, I am prepared to assume without deciding that, with the subject matter of the contract being perishables and it being a known purpose of the individual orders that the cherries were intended to travel to, variously, Singapore and Hong Kong for resale, it was an implied condition of each order filled that the cherries were, at the time of sale, in such a condition that they would still be fit for human consumption at the end of their shipment unless "that condition is unnaturally changed" after delivery to the first buyer, ie Farmlink: Sale of Goods Act , s 14(a) ; Kemp Ltd v Tolland (trading as James Tolland &amp; Co) [1956] 2 Lloyd's Rep 681 at 684-685; Benjamin's Sale of Goods at [11-067], but see also [11-060] and [11-062] as it is contended by TVO that Farmlink had an opportunity to inspect prior to shipment. I will refer to this later in these reasons: see [235]. The corollary of this condition was that Farmlink bore responsibility for unnatural changes in the cherries' condition occurring after delivery to it and until delivery to the overseas buyers: Kemp at 684-685.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA v Charles Twigg &amp; Co Ltd [1957] 1 Lloyd's Rep 240</tocase>
<text>70 Such orders were effected usually by TVO delivering the packaged cherries to PBVO or, on occasion, to freight forwarders retained and paid for by Farmlink. It is agreed between the parties that, if the relationship between TVO and Farmlink was that of sale and purchase, such delivery was an unconditional appropriation such that property passed to Farmlink: see Sale of Goods Act , s 18 rule 5(1) ; Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Natwest Wholesale Australia Pty Ltd [1987] HCA 30 ; (1987) 163 CLR 236 ; Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA v Charles Twigg &amp; Co Ltd [1957] 1 Lloyd's Rep 240. When making a delivery TVO usually faxed what it called a "dispatch docket" to Farmlink. This handwritten document, which made no reference to price, was for present purposes the only document of significance generated by TVO for delivery to Farmlink in any season. Mr Hannaford's explanation for the absence of a price on the dispatch docket was that: 
 We didn't put a price on because sometimes the price can vary a little bit and this was one reason for creating these documents was for our own internal records as well to keep track of our sales for our own viewpoint but there was very often a price variation to do with cost of freight [or] the fact if they were in punnets or gift boxes, there may be some variation to the agreed price.

187 Being a contract for the sale of goods, each order filled was subject to the provisions of the Sale of Goods Act . As I earlier noted, it is agreed in light of my sale finding that property in the cherries passed in respect of each consignment when the goods were appropriated to the contract and this occurred on delivery: see Sale of Goods Act , s 18 rule 5 ; Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) at 255; Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA . The individual orders equally were subject to the provisions of s 14 of the Act as to implied conditions as to quality and fitness. Though it has not been the subject of contest by TVO, I am prepared to assume without deciding that, with the subject matter of the contract being perishables and it being a known purpose of the individual orders that the cherries were intended to travel to, variously, Singapore and Hong Kong for resale, it was an implied condition of each order filled that the cherries were, at the time of sale, in such a condition that they would still be fit for human consumption at the end of their shipment unless "that condition is unnaturally changed" after delivery to the first buyer, ie Farmlink: Sale of Goods Act , s 14(a) ; Kemp Ltd v Tolland (trading as James Tolland &amp; Co) [1956] 2 Lloyd's Rep 681 at 684-685; Benjamin's Sale of Goods at [11-067], but see also [11-060] and [11-062] as it is contended by TVO that Farmlink had an opportunity to inspect prior to shipment. I will refer to this later in these reasons: see [235]. The corollary of this condition was that Farmlink bore responsibility for unnatural changes in the cherries' condition occurring after delivery to it and until delivery to the overseas buyers: Kemp at 684-685.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>WK Witt (WA) Pty Ltd v Metters Ltd [1967] WAR 15</tocase>
<text>171 On 26 March 2004, Farmlink was sent a solicitor's letter on Mr Hannaford's behalf concerning Farmlink's conduct "in acting as the agent" for TVO in relation to the export of its cherries during January 2004. Some reliance, necessarily slight: see [47](2) above and WK Witt (WA) Pty Ltd v Metters Ltd [1967] WAR 15 at 18; is placed upon this characterisation of the relationship. Reliance equally is placed upon a discovered TVO table relating to the exports to Hong Kong in which the heading: "Expected Price" and "Expected Amount" have been altered by hand to "Agreed Price" and "Agreed Amount". Mr Hannaford could not identify the handwriting. Farmlink relies on this as evidence of attempted reconstruction of events to support TVO's sale of goods claim.

172 Evidence on quality control apart (which is considered below), there is a deal of material before me to which I need make no, or only slight, reference. Though much has been said of the Australian market in general and of TVO's dealing with Woolworths and Coles in particular, I do not consider that the evidence on that market or on those dealings has any significant probative value either in characterising the TVO-Farmlink relationship or in resolving the quality questions raised. I would note in particular that it is accepted by TVO that their sales to local wholesale markets are conducted through agents; and that both Woolworths and Coles conduct their own inspections based on their own specifications and reject cherries that do not meet the specifications. No question of rejection has arisen in this matter although evidence was put on of three rejections by Woolworths of entire deliveries in January 2004. Equally, I draw from Dr Brown's evidence that risks to the maintenance of the cool chain for cherries transported in the domestic freight system are of a different order to those presented by export freight.

173 I equally have not had regard to evidence concerning TVO's dealings with other exporters and in particular Jayfresh "J" in other years. The bare detail of financial outcomes devoid of context and circumstance, I consider to be likely to mislead and therefore to prejudice.

179 Under the shadow of the principles to which I earlier referred and of the decisions of International Harvester Co , Ex parte White; In re Neville and Witt in particular, the factual matters upon which TVO relies primarily for this conclusion are: (i) the transaction between TVO and Farmlink was at a firm price; (ii) the documentation all reflected a sale from TVO to Farmlink; (iii) Farmlink set the price for the overseas sale and kept its sale price and margin a secret; (iv) Farmlink engaged all the freight forwarders and paid the freight costs itself; (v) Farmlink never accounted to TVO in a way which showed the total amount received, its margin and amounts paid for freight, etc; (vi) Farmlink issued invoices to its overseas customers; (vii) Farmlink alone knew the identity and location of its overseas customers; (viii) Farmlink identified itself as the shipper on the bills of lading and airway bills; (ix) Farmlink negotiated the changes in price without checking or obtaining instructions from TVO or Mr Hannaford; and (x) significantly in the year that there was insurance, the insured was Farmlink, the consignee's interest was noted, but there was no recording of TVO having any interest in the cherries.

185 The evidence, in my view, simply cannot sustain a conclusion that Farmlink acted on TVO's behalf in a "representative": cf Bowstead &amp; Reynolds at [1-001]; Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society at 48-50; or "fiduciary": cf Restatement of Agency , Second , SS1.01; capacity in selling its cherries. Farmlink was a purchaser buying for the purposes of resale. It is significant in this that (i) the parties agreed in advance the prices at which TVO would sell its cherries they were not simply indicative prices (I will refer below to the significance in this of purchase discounts); (ii) while the consignments were into markets with which TVO had some, albeit rudimentary knowledge, they were simply two of the overseas markets into which TVO cherries were consigned by exporters in the 2003/2004 season; (iii) Farmlink, in contrast, was knowledgeable about, and experienced in, those two markets at that time: cf Witt at 18-19; (iv) TVO did not assume responsibility for the export or the costs associated with the export this was at Farmlink's expense: cf Witt at 18-19 and Farmlink, not TVO, bore responsibility for misadventures happening to the cherries after delivery to it; (v) TVO was not in a position to exercise practical control over Farmlink (other than by refusing orders); (vi) TVO was unaware of Farmlink's price; (vii) while Mr Hannaford doubtless understood that Farmlink would obtain its own return on the sales (howsoever this was done), there was nothing unusual about his having no interest in that matter as his relationship with Farmlink did not otherwise point to an agency relationship: cf Mercantile International Group plc at [5] and [36]; and (ix) TVO happened to know the Singapore buyer was a company with which Mr Koh was associated but did not know the identity of the Hong Kong buyer. In short, having regard to the context in which they dealt with each other, the relationship they formed in the making and filling of orders was that of seller and buyer for resale. The contrary inference that TVO appointed Farmlink its agent for sale is neither a reasonable, nor the most probable, deduction from the known facts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gibson Motorsport Merchandise Pty Ltd v Forbes [2006] FCAFC 44 ; (2006) 149 FCR 569</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/44.html</AustLII>
<text>177 By way of preface to my own conclusions, I should make the following general observations. The relationships of TVO and Farmlink, and of Farmlink and Freshmart and Mak respectively, were clearly interdependent ones as the evidence of the process of making and filling orders reveals. It was open to Farmlink to choose to so structure its relationship with TVO or for that matter with Freshmart or Mak in a manner which obliged it to act in the interests either of TVO in the sale of cherries or of Freshmart or Mak in their purchase. It equally was open to Farmlink to choose to structure its relationships with TVO and the overseas buyers in a manner which, while requiring cooperation with, and some level of trust in, them, served its own several interests: cf Gibson Motorsport Merchandise Pty Ltd v Forbes [2006] FCAFC 44 ; (2006) 149 FCR 569 at [17] . In my view, Farmlink chose the latter course. This was clearly manifest in its price agreement with TVO and in its seller-purchaser relationship with the overseas buyers. There was nothing fiduciary about it.

178 The rival contentions of the parties can be simply put. TVO's case is that an overarching (or framework) conditional contract was entered into in or about December 2003 under which it agreed that, if it accepted an order or orders to sell cherries to Farmlink, it would do so at the prices that the parties had previously agreed. That agreement was effectuated in the individual orders filled by TVO.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Carminco Gold &amp; Resources Ltd v Findlay &amp; Co Stockbrokers (Underwriters) Pty Ltd (2007) 243 ALR 472</tocase>
<text>182 The documentation passing between Farmlink and Freshmart and Mak respectively admits of no other conclusion, the more so given the international trading context in which the dealings occurred. It is, in my view, most improbable that the overseas buyers would reasonably have committed themselves to a contractual arrangement with a principal of whose actual identity or circumstances they may have been unaware, especially where the goods in question were perishables of a type that were apt to give rise to some level of quality issue during periodic dealings over a season: on the distinction between unidentified and undisclosed principals, see Carminco Gold &amp; Resources Ltd v Findlay &amp; Co Stockbrokers (Underwriters) Pty Ltd (2007) 243 ALR 472. The view I take of Farmlink's contracts with Freshmart and Mak is that they were ones to which TVO was a stranger. If the prices in those contracts were to be re-negotiated for reasons of quality defects, market conditions or whatever, that was to be by the contracting parties alone. Likewise if claims for defects in quality permissible under the applicable law against the seller were to be made they were to be made against Farmlink.

183 The final comment I would make on Farmlink's relationship with the overseas buyers is that it would have been obvious to them that Farmlink was not the grower of the cherries Freshmart and Mak purchased. It was an exporter. But there is nothing in the evidence reasonably to suggest that Farmlink was acting, or was purporting to act, in the overseas sales in a "representative" capacity: cf above [47](3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Palette Shoes Pty Ltd v Krohn [1937] HCA 37 ; (1937) 58 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/37.html</AustLII>
<text>186 I would add, because it is a matter relied upon by the respondents, that I do not derive any assistance from the manner in which Farmlink received payments from its buyers and "accounted" to TVO. If it was an agent, then, subject to how its accounting to TVO was (or was taken in the circumstances to have been) agreed, the manner in which it held the proceeds of sale of its principal's property (ie in its own trading account) may itself have constituted a breach of trust: see Palette Shoes Pty Ltd v Krohn [1937] HCA 37 ; (1937) 58 CLR 1 at 30; but cf The "Tiiskeri" [1983] 2 Lloyd's Rep 658 at 663 ff. For understandable reasons, I have not been addressed on this. However, if, as I have held, Farmlink was receiving the purchase price for its consignments from its purchaser and then was settling with its own seller, there was nothing unusual in the manner of its so doing. I would add that it may well have been the case that the timing of its settlement was an implied actual term of their framework contract (the bulk of orders being settled en bloc at the end of the season).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The "Tiiskeri" [1983] 2 Lloyd's Rep 658</tocase>
<text>186 I would add, because it is a matter relied upon by the respondents, that I do not derive any assistance from the manner in which Farmlink received payments from its buyers and "accounted" to TVO. If it was an agent, then, subject to how its accounting to TVO was (or was taken in the circumstances to have been) agreed, the manner in which it held the proceeds of sale of its principal's property (ie in its own trading account) may itself have constituted a breach of trust: see Palette Shoes Pty Ltd v Krohn [1937] HCA 37 ; (1937) 58 CLR 1 at 30; but cf The "Tiiskeri" [1983] 2 Lloyd's Rep 658 at 663 ff. For understandable reasons, I have not been addressed on this. However, if, as I have held, Farmlink was receiving the purchase price for its consignments from its purchaser and then was settling with its own seller, there was nothing unusual in the manner of its so doing. I would add that it may well have been the case that the timing of its settlement was an implied actual term of their framework contract (the bulk of orders being settled en bloc at the end of the season).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Kemp Ltd v Tolland (trading as James Tolland &amp; Co) [1956] 2 Lloyd's Rep 681</tocase>
<text>187 Being a contract for the sale of goods, each order filled was subject to the provisions of the Sale of Goods Act . As I earlier noted, it is agreed in light of my sale finding that property in the cherries passed in respect of each consignment when the goods were appropriated to the contract and this occurred on delivery: see Sale of Goods Act , s 18 rule 5 ; Gamer's Motor Centre (Newcastle) at 255; Carlos Federspiel &amp; Co SA . The individual orders equally were subject to the provisions of s 14 of the Act as to implied conditions as to quality and fitness. Though it has not been the subject of contest by TVO, I am prepared to assume without deciding that, with the subject matter of the contract being perishables and it being a known purpose of the individual orders that the cherries were intended to travel to, variously, Singapore and Hong Kong for resale, it was an implied condition of each order filled that the cherries were, at the time of sale, in such a condition that they would still be fit for human consumption at the end of their shipment unless "that condition is unnaturally changed" after delivery to the first buyer, ie Farmlink: Sale of Goods Act , s 14(a) ; Kemp Ltd v Tolland (trading as James Tolland &amp; Co) [1956] 2 Lloyd's Rep 681 at 684-685; Benjamin's Sale of Goods at [11-067], but see also [11-060] and [11-062] as it is contended by TVO that Farmlink had an opportunity to inspect prior to shipment. I will refer to this later in these reasons: see [235]. The corollary of this condition was that Farmlink bore responsibility for unnatural changes in the cherries' condition occurring after delivery to it and until delivery to the overseas buyers: Kemp at 684-685.

195 I would add, though it does not strictly arise given my amendment ruling, that I have great reservations about whether what we know about (a) past purchase discounts passed on; (b) the explanations for, and contexts of, them (we know nothing of the causes of the alleged defects: cf Kemp ); (c) the fact that the only catastrophic discounts (in the 2001/2002 season) gave rise to insurance claims which ameliorated the loss; and (d) the usually small to moderate amounts for discounts in past years revealed in the material before me, would be sufficient to justify inferring a term committing Mr Hannaford to accept a quality discount passed on to him, assuming such a term could be formulated intelligibly.

196 I should make this additional comment about prior dealings. It is clear that Mr Hannaford appears to have accepted as of course some level of price discounts during the preceding years of dealing with Farmlink. It is unsurprising that he did so given the perishable nature of cherries and the known factors that could produce defects even in well run orchards and packing sheds which he clearly considered TVO to be. To repeat what he frankly conceded:
 I mean, there is always some things that happen during the season. There are quite often some issues, some problems. Maybe it is our fault. Maybe some cherries snuck through the system and so there are, from time to time there are some issues, either fair or unfair, that can result in some discounts, yes.

197 Parties to a sales contract are, as a matter of party autonomy, quite entitled to agree a regime of some form which would permit a buyer unilaterally to discount the price paid for the goods purchased because of some quality defect in them. As I earlier noted, the CISG contains such a regime: see also Sale of Goods Act (1979) (UK), s 48C(1)(a) and Benjamin's Sale of Goods (at [19-203]). Benjamin's Sale of Goods (at [12-129]) notes that this "special remedy of reduction of the price" is one which may lead to a monetary award different from what an award of damages would produce.

212 No expert evidence was called in relation to these shipments. Ms Churchill, in passing the discounts on, appears simply to have assumed without inquiry that the alleged defects were caused by circumstances for which TVO was responsible. Given the view I take of the TVO-Farmlink contract, this was a matter for Farmlink to prove, not assume, if it was to secure a reduction in price: see Kemp . In any event, the evidence of the complaints made by Mr Koh does not establish the truth of what he alleged, let alone justify the discounts applied. I say this while acknowledging that, if the Farmlink-Freshmart contracts were subject to the provisions of the CISG, Mr Koh's emails may have provided the trigger to unilateral price reductions in the Farmlink-Freshmart contract, under Art 50 of the Convention.

213 Purchase discounts, allegedly for quality reasons, were applied to ten of the eleven consignments to Hong Kong. As to five of these orders 4020, 4035, 4036, 3038 and 4039 there is no evidence at all of any quality problems with them. There were no written complaints from Mak; no emails; and no Marinasia reports. Absent such evidence, Farmlink could proffer no reasonable basis for its accepting a purchase reduction let alone for passing it on to TVO. In any event the circumstances surrounding at least order 4020 excite a real suspicion that this order, and possibly some orders other than the above (eg order 4023), were discounted in whole or in part for reasons unrelated to quality as such. Mak, as I earlier indicated, had been caught on a falling market.

214 Of the remaining five orders, order 4023 elicited a belated email quality complaint and photographs from Mak on 9 January 2004; the remaining orders 4017 (the sea shipment), 4028, 4037 and 4041 resulted initially in emails and photographs alleging quality issues and subsequently in each instance, a Marinasia Report. I would emphasise that all five of these orders were total losses. The price discount in each instance exceeded TVO's agreed price and resulted in a nil return to Farmlink as well. In what follows I am concerned only with these five orders. The discounts applied to the other five orders were clearly not appropriately substantiated.

220 Fourthly, there is evidence, relied upon by each side when to its own advantage, both of cherries included in the consignments in question being picked from the same sub-block at the same time as those accepted by Woolworths and Coles and of such cherries being rejected by Woolworths and Coles. It is understandable that TVO would rely upon the former of these particularly in light of Devlin J's comment in Kemp (at 687) on the relevance of sales of the same commodity to other purchasers without complaint, when searching for causes of defects. The most that I consider should be said generally of the comparison of export and domestic consignments is that the domestic picture for comparable quality cherries does not match that from Hong Kong. However, I place little reliance upon this in relation to the five orders under consideration for the reason that the evidence on which to base the comparability of cherries going to Woolworths and Coles and to the export market does not for the most part permit meaningful and in the case of order 4028 any comparison: see Schedule 3 to the Schedules Brief.

221 The only expert evidence called by the respondents was that of Dr Brown. The instructions Farmlink's solicitors gave to Dr Brown are not unimportant in understanding his report and the significance to be attributed to it. They include:
 On the basis of the assumptions we have asked you to accept, we seek your written report and opinion as to possible causes for the condition and quality of the cherries as observed, commented on and photographed by Freshmart in Singapore and Mr Thomas Kwan, Managing Director of Marinasia (Hong Kong) limited to whether their condition and quality could possibly have been caused during: 1. the growing and/or; 2. the picking and/or; 3. the packing and/or; 
 
 4. the storing of the cherries prior to their transport from the premises of the packer to the warehouses in Australia from where they were shipped or airfreighted overseas. 
 
 
If you are of the view that there are possible causes for the observations, comments and photos made and taken in Singapore and Hong Kong during the above stages, can you identify them and explain how they could possibly occur. We realise that some if not all of the observations and comments could have been due to causes during the export stage, but we do not seek your opinion on this issue, except to ask you to identify any observations or comments as to condition or quality that could not possibly have been caused during the export stage, and if so, for the reasons why not.

222 The applicant's counsel, again for understandable reasons, focussed upon the last paragraph quoted and has submitted that it constituted an admission made in circumstances such that it can be treated as having been made by Farmlink under s 87 of the Evidence Act . Before dealing with that submission, I would note that Dr Brown indicated in his report that he did "not cover possible causes of the fruit deterioration that may have occurred during transport, shipment and receival". 
 The alleged admission

237 Even if, which is not the case, Farmlink was defending TVO's claim for its sale price on the basis of breach of a s 14 warranty or was suing for such a breach, I am satisfied that, on the material before me, it would be unsuccessful in either case. As I have already indicated, TVO's warranties of quality and fitness address the condition of its cherries at the time of sale to Farmlink, albeit that condition must be such that they would be fit for consumption on delivery overseas (unless their condition had been changed through causes for which TVO was not responsible: Kemp at 684-685).

238 The evidence clearly suggests potential causes contributing in whole or in part to the losses on the five orders in question for which, variously, TVO, Farmlink and Mak would, if made out, be separately responsible. And there is Farmlink's problem. The state of the evidence in relation to these five orders could not reasonably justify a finding that TVO was alone responsible for the total losses, bearing in mind that Farmlink would bear the onus of proof of that: Kemp at 685. This said, I am satisfied in relation to order 4041 in particular that a cause of defects in the cherries in that shipment could have been a matter for which TVO bore responsibility.

239 The Marinasia reports and the circumstances of three of the four surveys (orders 4028, 4037 and 4041) on which they were based are quite incapable of sustaining the burden of proving TVO's sole responsibility, the more so in relation to the three mentioned because of the unexplained delays in shipment or inspection and of the circumstances of the inspection (ie at Mak's store). There are, in consequence, real grounds for apprehending that the losses were caused or contributed to by causes for which either, or both, Farmlink and Mak were responsible, eg possible inappropriate storage during delays in air shipment (cf Dr Brown's evidence) and breaks in the cool chain through exposure to warm and humid conditions in Hong Kong. Equally, there are unresolved questions surrounding order 4017 (the sea shipment): eg was the vent setting altered? Farmlink packed the container, but did it break the cool chain after delivery to it?

240 The reports, moreover, while purporting to describe the condition and appearance of the cherries, do not address the causes thereof. While those causes ought to have been of some concern to Ms Churchill for the purposes of Farmlink's own contractual obligations to Mak, they should have been of vital concern to her if Farmlink was to ascribe sole responsibility for the losses to TVO under its contract with Farmlink. The evidence does not suggest that Ms Churchill questioned or probed the Marinasia reports or Mak in any way. TVO's responsibility for the loss seems to have been assumed and Mak's assertion of total losses accepted without question. And for the purposes of this proceeding, Farmlink has relied upon them. Mak was not called to give evidence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>BICC plc v Burndy Corporation [1985] 1 Ch 232</tocase>
<text>207 My conclusion in effect necessitates that the applicant must succeed in his claim to be paid the purchase price. Farmlink has not set up as a defence the seller's breach of the implied condition of quality and fitness: see BICC plc v Burndy Corporation [1985] 1 Ch 232 at 247; Sutton, Sales and Consumer Law at [22.24] ff (4 th ed, 1995). That breach is only relied upon in justification of the price discounts applied: FAD 8.2 and 10.3. While a cross-claim for damages for breach of the implied condition has been pleaded, it has not been prosecuted: see "The Cross-Claim" below. In the circumstances Farmlink can only be said to have persisted in a "self-help" remedy which lost any semblance of justification when TVO insisted on its strict legal rights.

208 It is not strictly necessary for me to deal with these matters given the view I have taken of the TVO-Farmlink contract and of the defence and cross-claim pleaded by the respondents. However, because they loomed large in the evidence adduced, though not so much so in submissions, I will state briefly my own views on them.

209 By way of preface to what I have to say, I should indicate that it is necessary to deal separately with quality issues as they relate to Singapore and Hong Kong consignments respectively.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flowers Case , Saarbr&uuml;cken Provincial Court of Appeal, 3 June 1998, CISG-online 354, http://cisgw3.law.pace.edu/cases/980603g 1 .html</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Futuretronics International Pty Ltd v Gadzhis [1992] 2 VR 217</tocase>
<text>247 My conclusion on the contract claim makes it strictly unnecessary to consider directly the misleading or deceptive conduct claim against Farmlink or to discuss (inevitably at some length: see Cheshire and Fifoot at [11.118]) the interaction of s 51A and s 52 of the TP Act and contractual promises: see eg Futuretronics International Pty Ltd v Gadzhis [1992] 2 VR 217. It is necessary, though, to deal with the claims as they relate to each of the natural person respondents, Ms Churchill, Mr Plummer and Mr Koh. Though claims are made against all three under the TP Act (via s 75B), the Fair Trading Act 1987 (SA) s 54 and the Misrepresentation Act 1971 (SA) s 7, I will as a matter of convenience deal only with the TP Act claims given the view I take of the actual allegations made against the respondents individually. I would add that the TP Act claims against Ms Churchill provide in substance the foundation of the claims against Farmlink on whose behalf she was acting at all relevant times: see TP Act s 84(2).

248 It needs to be said at the outset that the claims, understandably, have been formulated against the contingency of fact findings quite different from those I have made. While it is necessary for the reason I gave above briefly to consider them, I recognise that those findings have rendered these claims superfluous.

249 There are three categories of representation alleged to have been made by Ms Churchill to Mr Hannaford and on which he is said to have relied, which constituted misleading or deceptive conduct. These were as follows:
 
 
 (i) In representing that Farmlink could sell TVO's cherries into Hong Kong and Singapore such that TVO would receive the agreed prices, Ms Churchill impliedly represented that Farmlink had reasonable grounds to make that representation: FASC paras 14-16, ("the negotiations representations");
 (ii) In a sequence of telephone conversations with Mr Hannaford after cherry consignments had commenced, she misled him in the following four respects (FASC paras 13.7.3 13.7.6, 17 and 18): 
 
 
 
 
 (a) from about 23 December 2003, Mr Hannaford and Ms Churchill had daily telephone conversations in relation to the ordering, delivery and sale of TVO's cherries. In those conversations Ms Churchill said words to the effect that everything was going "all right", when she had no reasonable basis to make such a representation; 
 (b) on about 4 January 2004, Mr Hannaford, in one such telephone conversation said to Ms Churchill words to the effect that he had heard from China that he was going to lose significantly and get nothing from dealing in the Hong Kong market. Ms Churchill said words to the effect that as far as she knew everything was all right, when she had no or no reasonable basis to make such a representation; 
 (c) on about 6 January 2004 Mr Hannaford in a telephone conversation asked Churchill words to the effect whether the Chinese market had crashed. Churchill said words to the effect that it had not but it was "a bit weak", with a "bit of oversupply" which should clear quickly when she had no or no reasonable basis to say the market was only "a bit weak" or only "bit over supplied" and would clear quickly but should have said that there was no or no reasonable prospect of TVO obtaining the Agreed Prices; 
 (d) after 6 January 2004, Mr Hannaford continued to have regular telephone conversations with Ms Churchill. Ms Churchill did not advise Mr Hannaford in those conversations of any difficulties with selling TVO cherries in the Hong Kong market, save and except for saying there were allegedly problems with the quality of cherries in one shipment. 
 
 
 
 
 It is alleged that in making the representations in (a) to (d) above, Ms Churchill impliedly represented that TVO would receive the agreed prices but she knew or should have known from and after 29 December 2003 that Farmlink was unable to sell TVO's cherries into the Hong Kong market and from and after 8 January 2004 that it was unable to sell TVO's cherries into the Singapore market at prices such that it could pay or TVO would receive the Agreed Prices and should have known at least from and after the last-mentioned dates that the market for cherries in Hong Kong and Singapore had crashed or become very poor or grim: ("the market representations").
 (iii) Finally, it is pleaded that (FASC para 19) Farmlink was, by Ms Churchill and its directors Mr Koh and Mr Plummer, silent as to the difficulties in fact being experienced in selling TVO's cherries in Hong Kong and Singapore markets at prices such that it could pay to TVO the Agreed Prices or at all. That silence, in the context of the relationship between TVO and Farmlink and the representations in (i) above made during negotiations constituted misleading and deceptive conduct or conduct which was likely to mislead or deceive": ("silence").

254 Thirdly, by virtue of s 51A(2) where a corporation makes a representation as to a future matter and does not have reasonable grounds for making it, the representation is taken to be misleading: CCP Australian Airships Ltd v Primus Telecommunications Pty Ltd (2005) ATPR 40-042. The onus is on the representor to adduce evidence of reasonable grounds: Futuretronics International Pty Ltd.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd (1982) 42 ALR 177</tocase>
<text>252 First, misleading or deceptive conduct is conduct which in the circumstance does lead, or is capable of leading, a person into error or, in non-disclosure cases, which fails to disabuse a person of his or her error: Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd (1982) 42 ALR 177 at 200; Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 at 198.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/44.html</AustLII>
<text>252 First, misleading or deceptive conduct is conduct which in the circumstance does lead, or is capable of leading, a person into error or, in non-disclosure cases, which fails to disabuse a person of his or her error: Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd (1982) 42 ALR 177 at 200; Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 at 198.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Elders Trustee and Executor Co Ltd v EG Reeves Pty Ltd [1987] FCA 332 ; (1987) 78 ALR 193</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1987/332.html</AustLII>
<text>253 Secondly, a statement of opinion (ie of a belief or judgment) will not be misleading or deceptive or be likely to be so merely because it misinforms or is likely to do so: Elders Trustee and Executor Co Ltd v EG Reeves Pty Ltd [1987] FCA 332 ; (1987) 78 ALR 193 at 242. It may be otherwise if the opinion was not in fact held, or had implicit in it the representation that it was reasonably based on a substratum of fact which was incorrect: RAIA Insurance Brokers Ltd v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd [1993] FCA 92 ; (1993) 41 FCR 164 ; Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 ; Cheshire and Fifoot at [11.116].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>RAIA Insurance Brokers Ltd v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd [1993] FCA 92 ; (1993) 41 FCR 164</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/92.html</AustLII>
<text>253 Secondly, a statement of opinion (ie of a belief or judgment) will not be misleading or deceptive or be likely to be so merely because it misinforms or is likely to do so: Elders Trustee and Executor Co Ltd v EG Reeves Pty Ltd [1987] FCA 332 ; (1987) 78 ALR 193 at 242. It may be otherwise if the opinion was not in fact held, or had implicit in it the representation that it was reasonably based on a substratum of fact which was incorrect: RAIA Insurance Brokers Ltd v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd [1993] FCA 92 ; (1993) 41 FCR 164 ; Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 ; Cheshire and Fifoot at [11.116].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/3.html</AustLII>
<text>253 Secondly, a statement of opinion (ie of a belief or judgment) will not be misleading or deceptive or be likely to be so merely because it misinforms or is likely to do so: Elders Trustee and Executor Co Ltd v EG Reeves Pty Ltd [1987] FCA 332 ; (1987) 78 ALR 193 at 242. It may be otherwise if the opinion was not in fact held, or had implicit in it the representation that it was reasonably based on a substratum of fact which was incorrect: RAIA Insurance Brokers Ltd v FAI General Insurance Co Ltd [1993] FCA 92 ; (1993) 41 FCR 164 ; Murphy v Overton Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 3 ; (2004) 216 CLR 388 ; Cheshire and Fifoot at [11.116].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>CCP Australian Airships Ltd v Primus Telecommunications Pty Ltd (2005) ATPR 40-042</tocase>
<text>254 Thirdly, by virtue of s 51A(2) where a corporation makes a representation as to a future matter and does not have reasonable grounds for making it, the representation is taken to be misleading: CCP Australian Airships Ltd v Primus Telecommunications Pty Ltd (2005) ATPR 40-042. The onus is on the representor to adduce evidence of reasonable grounds: Futuretronics International Pty Ltd.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Demagogue Pty Ltd v Ramensky [1992] FCA 557 ; (1992) 39 FCR 31</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/557.html</AustLII>
<text>255 Fourthly, silence, ie non-disclosure of a relevant fact or matter, can constitute misleading or deceptive conduct in circumstances in which one party is reasonably entitled to expect disclosure of the existence of that fact or matter if known to the other with whom it is dealing: see Demagogue Pty Ltd v Ramensky [1992] FCA 557 ; (1992) 39 FCR 31 ; Hughes Aircraft Systems International v Airservices Australia (1997) 76 FCR 151 at 198-201.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hughes Aircraft Systems International v Airservices Australia (1997) 76 FCR 151</tocase>
<text>255 Fourthly, silence, ie non-disclosure of a relevant fact or matter, can constitute misleading or deceptive conduct in circumstances in which one party is reasonably entitled to expect disclosure of the existence of that fact or matter if known to the other with whom it is dealing: see Demagogue Pty Ltd v Ramensky [1992] FCA 557 ; (1992) 39 FCR 31 ; Hughes Aircraft Systems International v Airservices Australia (1997) 76 FCR 151 at 198-201.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Watson v Foxman (1995) 49 NSWLR 315</tocase>
<text>260 Of the representations alleged in this category, the first in conversations from 23 December Ms Churchill said words to the effect that everything was going "all right" to Mr Hannaford does not warrant serious individual consideration. The pleading is devoid of detail and of context and is quite unilluminating: cf the observations of McLelland CJ in Eq in Watson v Foxman (1995) 49 NSWLR 315 at 318-319. The submissions have not ameliorated this.

261 The representations alleged to have been made in phone conversations around 4 and 6 January 2004 relating to the China market cannot stand in light of my earlier findings. I have rejected Mr Hannaford's evidence as to the timing of the operative conversations and I have accepted Ms Churchill's evidence as to their substance. They occurred on 3 and 7 January and resulted in Mr Hannaford's agreement to two price reductions. These conclusions necessarily must lead to my rejection of both of these allegations of misleading or deceptive conduct. More significantly, I have found that at the relevant times Ms Churchill did make Mr Hannaford aware of the market conditions in the China market.

262 The final representation of this category was that after 6 January 2004 Ms Churchill had regular telephone conversations with Mr Hannaford but did not advise him of any difficulties with selling TVO cherries in the Hong Kong market save for saying there were allegedly problems with the quality of cherries in one shipment. An allegation so broadly cast is not only unsatisfactory, it is contradicted by a body of evidence. I will not reiterate that evidence here other than to note that I have found that on 7 January, Ms Churchill communicated the substance of Mak's "serious decline" email to Mr Hannaford; probably on 7 January he agreed to cancel a shipment; the next morning he suggested a price reduction to which Mak agreed on 9 January; on 9 January two separate quality complaints were made by Mak, these being the first such complaint made by Mak; and notwithstanding the above, Mr Hannaford agreed to Farmlink's "Mud Map" of 10 January proposing four air freight shipments to Hong Kong. Whatever might be said from this time onwards about the adequacy or otherwise of Ms Churchill's investigation of the quality complaints made, the burden of the complaint that she did not advise of any difficulties with selling in the Hong Kong market is not made out.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>