<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Intel Corporation v Unwired Group Ltd [2008] FCA 1927 (11 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1927.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>AMEV-UDC Finance Ltd v Austin [1986] HCA 63 ; (1986) 162 CLR 170</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/63.html</AustLII>
<text>75 But, before dismissing this aspect of the proceedings entirely, if I were otherwise minded to accede to Intel's arguments, I am of opinion that I should give Unwired one further opportunity to set out in its pleadings the necessary material facts. I do that because it seems to me that this area of the law is one which is undergoing development. As Allsop P observed, it is not the function of single judges or full or appellate courts to depart from decisions of the High Court. However, in O'Dea v Allstates Leasing Systems (WA) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 3 ; (1983) 152 CLR 359 the High Court overruled its earlier decision in Lamson Store Service Co Ltd v Russell Wilkins &amp; Sons Ltd [1906] HCA 87 ; (1906) 4 CLR 672. That had been recently applied by the Court in IAC (Leasing) Ltd v Humphrey [1972] HCA 1 ; (1972) 126 CLR 131. The reformulation of the law as to penalties which commenced with O'Dea 152 CLR 349 and continued with AMEV-UDC Finance Ltd v Austin [1986] HCA 63 ; (1986) 162 CLR 170 may not yet be at an end, albeit it that, as Allsop P noted, it may not be at the stage that Brereton J had suggested.

76 Recently, in Gumland Property Holdings Pty Ltd v Duffy Bros Fruit Market (Campbelltown) Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 10 ; (2008) 244 ALR 1 , Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Heydon, Crennan and Kiefel JJ discussed the issue of relief against penalties and forfeiture in a cognate way. They referred to AMEV [1986] HCA 63 ; 162 CLR 170 and discussed the interplay which that and subsequent decisions had identified as developing between penalties and forfeitures.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/243.html</AustLII>
<text>63 The purpose of case management and the docket system adopted by this Court is to enable both the parties and the Court to be informed, from the outset of the case each of the parties intends to advance and to identify the real issues in dispute. This is so that directions can be crafted to enable the efficient management of the litigation, with a view to focusing on and allowing those issues to be tried, and, at the same time, eliminating irrelevant matters quickly and efficiently: White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [3] - [4] per Allsop J (applied by Heydon JA in Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116 at 128-129 [28]-[32], Mason P and Young CJ in Eq agreeing); Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159 at [29] per Allsop J; Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361 at [15] per myself; Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243 at [160] - [162] per Allsop P, with whom Beazley and Campbell JJA agreed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>BP Refinery Westernport Pty Limited v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/UKPCHCA/1977/1.html</AustLII>
<text>35 It is not so obvious that it goes without saying, that the redemption premium amount would not be payable to Intel or a note holder if an irremediable event of default had occurred but Unwrited still remained ready, willing and able to continue the WiMAX roll out. And that term is capable of being construed as contradicting the express terms of the deed poll which express no qualification to Unwired's obligation to pay the redemption premium amount under cll 6.2, 6.3 and 9.4 if an irremediable event of default occurrs (such as the de-listing of Unwired as a consequence of a successful takeover offer): BP Refinery Westernport Pty Limited v Shire of Hastings [1977] HCA 40 ; (1977) 180 CLR 266 at 282-283.

36 Accordingly, I am of opinion that Unwired's contentions in pars 43, 50(e) and 54 of its amended defence, that terms should be implied or construed qualifying Intel's entitlement to call for payment of the redemption premium amount, are untenable and have no reasonable prospect of success.

37 Unwired's next group of implied terms or construction arguments sought to interpolate into the deed poll or overall transaction an obligation of Intel to act reasonably and in good faith when exercising its contractual rights to seek payment of the redemption premium amount, in the event of a change in control of Unwired, when Unwired remained ready, willing and able to implement the WiMAX roll out (Amended Defence pars 44, 50(f)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/50.html</AustLII>
<text>39 In GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 208-209 [920] Finn J, himself an advocate of the implication or importation into all contracts of a duty of good faith and fair dealing, recognised that there was no consensus in Australian law as to whether such a term, or duty, should be included in all contracts. The High Court left that question open in Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289 at 301 [40] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gumland Property Holdings Pty Ltd v Duffy Bros Fruit Market (Campbelltown) Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 10 ; (2008) 244 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/10.html</AustLII>
<text>76 Recently, in Gumland Property Holdings Pty Ltd v Duffy Bros Fruit Market (Campbelltown) Pty Ltd [2008] HCA 10 ; (2008) 244 ALR 1 , Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Heydon, Crennan and Kiefel JJ discussed the issue of relief against penalties and forfeiture in a cognate way. They referred to AMEV [1986] HCA 63 ; 162 CLR 170 and discussed the interplay which that and subsequent decisions had identified as developing between penalties and forfeitures.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>IAC (Leasing) Ltd v Humphrey [1972] HCA 1 ; (1972) 126 CLR 131</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/1.html</AustLII>
<text>75 But, before dismissing this aspect of the proceedings entirely, if I were otherwise minded to accede to Intel's arguments, I am of opinion that I should give Unwired one further opportunity to set out in its pleadings the necessary material facts. I do that because it seems to me that this area of the law is one which is undergoing development. As Allsop P observed, it is not the function of single judges or full or appellate courts to depart from decisions of the High Court. However, in O'Dea v Allstates Leasing Systems (WA) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 3 ; (1983) 152 CLR 359 the High Court overruled its earlier decision in Lamson Store Service Co Ltd v Russell Wilkins &amp; Sons Ltd [1906] HCA 87 ; (1906) 4 CLR 672. That had been recently applied by the Court in IAC (Leasing) Ltd v Humphrey [1972] HCA 1 ; (1972) 126 CLR 131. The reformulation of the law as to penalties which commenced with O'Dea 152 CLR 349 and continued with AMEV-UDC Finance Ltd v Austin [1986] HCA 63 ; (1986) 162 CLR 170 may not yet be at an end, albeit it that, as Allsop P noted, it may not be at the stage that Brereton J had suggested.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd v Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 406</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2007/406.html</AustLII>
<text>67 Lastly, the parties are at issue as to the plea in pars 74 and 75 of the amended defence, that Unwired's obligation to pay the redemption premium amount is a penalty. In argument, Unwired accepted that it was seeking to rely on a novel argument that the occurrence of an event, namely, the change of control or de-listing, although not a breach of contract for which it was responsible, could still operate as a penalty. It sought to rely upon a recent, but even more recently, reversed, decision of Brereton J in the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd v Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 406. That was reversed in Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd v Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 310.

68 After an extensive examination of the authorities, Brereton J concluded that a penalty was a contractual obligation to pay, forfeit or suffer the retention of a sum of money or property, agreed in advance to be payable, forfeited or retainable by one party to the other upon or in default of the occurrence of an event, which could be seen as a matter of substance to have been treated by the parties as lying within the area of obligation of the first party (in the sense that it was the first party's responsibility to see to it that the event did not happen) and where the stipulated payment is out of proportion or unrelated to the damage which might be sustained by the other party by reason of a particular occurrence of default: Integral [2007] NSWSC 406 at [74] .

69 Allsop P, with whom Giles and Ipp JJA agreed, apparently in obiter dicta, concluded that Brereton J's "thoughtful" reasons highlighted a potential tension between different approaches in the field, but that the weight of existing authority limited the doctrine of penalties within narrow and clear boundaries. Allsop P said that it was the function of the High Court, and not the Court of Appeal of the Supreme Court of New South Wales or a judge at first instance, to expand that field: Interstar [2008] NSWCA 310 at [159] - [160] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd v Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 310</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/310.html</AustLII>
<text>67 Lastly, the parties are at issue as to the plea in pars 74 and 75 of the amended defence, that Unwired's obligation to pay the redemption premium amount is a penalty. In argument, Unwired accepted that it was seeking to rely on a novel argument that the occurrence of an event, namely, the change of control or de-listing, although not a breach of contract for which it was responsible, could still operate as a penalty. It sought to rely upon a recent, but even more recently, reversed, decision of Brereton J in the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd v Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 406. That was reversed in Interstar Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd v Integral Home Loans Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 310.

69 Allsop P, with whom Giles and Ipp JJA agreed, apparently in obiter dicta, concluded that Brereton J's "thoughtful" reasons highlighted a potential tension between different approaches in the field, but that the weight of existing authority limited the doctrine of penalties within narrow and clear boundaries. Allsop P said that it was the function of the High Court, and not the Court of Appeal of the Supreme Court of New South Wales or a judge at first instance, to expand that field: Interstar [2008] NSWCA 310 at [159] - [160] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Maniotis v JH Lever &amp; Co Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 7</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/7.html</AustLII>
<text>64 In Maniotis v JH Lever &amp; Co Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 7 at [72] , Finn, Emmett and Bennett JJ said:
 "In the efficient and proper conduct of civil litigation, even civil litigation hard fought between parties, it should always be recognised that, in the propounding of issues for trial, the parties should take steps to ensure that all relevant parties to the dispute are cognisant of what the issues are. Quietly leaving footprints in correspondence or directions hearings to be uncovered some time later in an attempt to reveal that a matter was always in issue is a practice that must be firmly discouraged. Where it is evident, or indeed suspected, that the other side is proceeding on the basis of a misconception or has not appreciated something, common sense will, as a general rule, mandate that a party ensure that the other is not proceeding on a misconception or that the other does appreciate something that has been said. No one's interests are advanced by litigation proceeding on assumptions which are seen or suspected to be false. The only consequence of keeping issues hidden or not clearly identifying them is to disrupt the business of the court leading to the waste of valuable public resources and to lead to the incurring of unnecessary costs by the parties, costs which ultimately have to be borne by someone: see White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [4] ." (emphasis in original)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116</tocase>
<text>63 The purpose of case management and the docket system adopted by this Court is to enable both the parties and the Court to be informed, from the outset of the case each of the parties intends to advance and to identify the real issues in dispute. This is so that directions can be crafted to enable the efficient management of the litigation, with a view to focusing on and allowing those issues to be tried, and, at the same time, eliminating irrelevant matters quickly and efficiently: White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [3] - [4] per Allsop J (applied by Heydon JA in Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116 at 128-129 [28]-[32], Mason P and Young CJ in Eq agreeing); Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159 at [29] per Allsop J; Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361 at [15] per myself; Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243 at [160] - [162] per Allsop P, with whom Beazley and Campbell JJA agreed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NT Power Generation v Power Water Authority [2004] HCA 48 ; (2004) 219 CLR 90</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/48.html</AustLII>
<text>65 I am of opinion that Unwired's allegations as to what the markets are, have been pleaded so as, at least, to reflect the economy of expression, with which the High Court was able to deal with allegations of market in NT Power Generation v Power Water Authority [2004] HCA 48 ; (2004) 219 CLR 90 at 112 [58] . The nature of a finance market and the width of possible markets which are raised by the letter of 23 August 2005 and Unwired's explanatory memorandum to its shareholders in explanation of this transaction will require close and careful attention, including in relation to issues of markets and market definition. It will be necessary to revisit carefully the further pleadings on these points.

66 However, Unwired's allegations of a contravention of s 46 are arguable and I am not satisfied that they should be dismissed at this time. But, I have real concerns as to their long-term sustainability, having regard to what is written in the letter of 23 August 2005 and the explanatory memorandum. For the moment, I think that the best course is to strike out pars 117-129 with leave to re-plead, so that Unwired can give some clarity to the overall nature of the contravention on which it relies. This is even though, as I have said, it may be perfectly legitimate for it to have pleaded some of those allegations in the form currently expressed. However, the whole pleading of this part of the amended defence should receive attention in a cognate way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>O'Dea v Allstates Leasing Systems (WA) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 3 ; (1983) 152 CLR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/3.html</AustLII>
<text>75 But, before dismissing this aspect of the proceedings entirely, if I were otherwise minded to accede to Intel's arguments, I am of opinion that I should give Unwired one further opportunity to set out in its pleadings the necessary material facts. I do that because it seems to me that this area of the law is one which is undergoing development. As Allsop P observed, it is not the function of single judges or full or appellate courts to depart from decisions of the High Court. However, in O'Dea v Allstates Leasing Systems (WA) Pty Ltd [1983] HCA 3 ; (1983) 152 CLR 359 the High Court overruled its earlier decision in Lamson Store Service Co Ltd v Russell Wilkins &amp; Sons Ltd [1906] HCA 87 ; (1906) 4 CLR 672. That had been recently applied by the Court in IAC (Leasing) Ltd v Humphrey [1972] HCA 1 ; (1972) 126 CLR 131. The reformulation of the law as to penalties which commenced with O'Dea 152 CLR 349 and continued with AMEV-UDC Finance Ltd v Austin [1986] HCA 63 ; (1986) 162 CLR 170 may not yet be at an end, albeit it that, as Allsop P noted, it may not be at the stage that Brereton J had suggested.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ringrow Pty Limited v BP Australia Pty Limited [2005] HCA 71 ; (2005) 224 CLR 656</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/71.html</AustLII>
<text>72 In Ringrow Pty Ltd v BP Australia Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 71 ; (2005) 224 CLR 656 at 666 [22] , Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ said that in assessing extravagance and oppressiveness, it is necessary to be able to compare the price to be paid, and the value of what is to be transferred as a result of the claimed penalty having become payable. I do not think that Unwired's pleading does articulate, in that way, a clear basis for asserting that a penalty would be incurred by it. I am of opinion that it is necessary to plead more than the merely formulaic words contained in par 74 of Unwired's amended defence.

73 If this point is to be articulated, even in circumstances where ultimately it might have to be struck out, it should be done in a pleading that clearly raises whatever is the triable issue which Unwired ultimately seeks to use to defend itself from liability to pay this amount as a penalty. For these reasons, pars 74 and 75 are not sufficient, in themselves, to bring out the novel claim that Unwired wishes to make and should be struck out.

74 I am concerned that the caution expressed by Allsop P should not be ignored. On the other hand, courts have to be mindful that when a party wishes to raise a test case, at least the elements for the test should be stated clearly in the pleadings. In this way, ultimately, it will be possible to apply the test, as to whether the redemption premium amount is a penalty, assessed on the conventional basis which, as a judge at first instance, I would ordinarily be obliged to apply, or by using some other test to determine whether the proceedings should be dismissed under s 31A , or otherwise stuck out as untenable. The arguments which Intel has put are significant. They carry the weight not only of the previous understanding of the common law of contract but also the operation of the document penalties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/5.html</AustLII>
<text>39 In GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 50 ; (2003) 128 FCR 1 at 208-209 [920] Finn J, himself an advocate of the implication or importation into all contracts of a duty of good faith and fair dealing, recognised that there was no consensus in Australian law as to whether such a term, or duty, should be included in all contracts. The High Court left that question open in Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289 at 301 [40] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1361.html</AustLII>
<text>63 The purpose of case management and the docket system adopted by this Court is to enable both the parties and the Court to be informed, from the outset of the case each of the parties intends to advance and to identify the real issues in dispute. This is so that directions can be crafted to enable the efficient management of the litigation, with a view to focusing on and allowing those issues to be tried, and, at the same time, eliminating irrelevant matters quickly and efficiently: White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [3] - [4] per Allsop J (applied by Heydon JA in Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116 at 128-129 [28]-[32], Mason P and Young CJ in Eq agreeing); Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159 at [29] per Allsop J; Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361 at [15] per myself; Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243 at [160] - [162] per Allsop P, with whom Beazley and Campbell JJA agreed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Toll (FCGT) Pty Limited v Alphapharm Pty Limited [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The deed poll is not, in itself, a contract between legal persons. But it is a commercial document intended to be the foundation of a contractual relationship embodied in the notes when issued. The ordinary principles of construction of contracts should be applied to the provisions of the deed poll, as well as to the transaction overall. These principles require the rights of the parties to be determined objectively, without reference to their subjective beliefs or understandings about what rights or liabilities would govern their relationship. What matters is what each party, by words and conduct, would have led a reasonable person in the position of the other party to believe. In this context, the role of the Court is to ascertain the common intention of the parties in the commercial matrix in which they contracted. This process involves discerning, in context, what a reasonable person would understand from the language in which the parties expressed their agreement, having regard to the objective surrounding circumstances with the purpose and the object of a transaction: Toll (FGCT) Pty Limited v Alphapharm Pty Limited [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 179 [40] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ. The commercial purpose of a contract is, in essence, the purpose attributable to a reasonable person in the position of the parties who is aware of what was known at the time to both of them about the genesis of the transaction, its background, context and the market in which they were operating.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1159.html</AustLII>
<text>63 The purpose of case management and the docket system adopted by this Court is to enable both the parties and the Court to be informed, from the outset of the case each of the parties intends to advance and to identify the real issues in dispute. This is so that directions can be crafted to enable the efficient management of the litigation, with a view to focusing on and allowing those issues to be tried, and, at the same time, eliminating irrelevant matters quickly and efficiently: White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [3] - [4] per Allsop J (applied by Heydon JA in Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116 at 128-129 [28]-[32], Mason P and Young CJ in Eq agreeing); Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159 at [29] per Allsop J; Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361 at [15] per myself; Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243 at [160] - [162] per Allsop P, with whom Beazley and Campbell JJA agreed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1333.html</AustLII>
<text>63 The purpose of case management and the docket system adopted by this Court is to enable both the parties and the Court to be informed, from the outset of the case each of the parties intends to advance and to identify the real issues in dispute. This is so that directions can be crafted to enable the efficient management of the litigation, with a view to focusing on and allowing those issues to be tried, and, at the same time, eliminating irrelevant matters quickly and efficiently: White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [3] - [4] per Allsop J (applied by Heydon JA in Nowlan v Marson Transport Pty Ltd (2001) 53 NSWLR 116 at 128-129 [28]-[32], Mason P and Young CJ in Eq agreeing); Visible Results Properties Inc v Sushi Train (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1159 at [29] per Allsop J; Snowy Mountains Organic Dairy Products Pty Ltd v Wholefoods Pty [2006] FCA 1361 at [15] per myself; Baulderstone Hornibrook Engineering Pty Ltd v Gordian Runoff Ltd [2008] NSWCA 243 at [160] - [162] per Allsop P, with whom Beazley and Campbell JJA agreed.

64 In Maniotis v JH Lever &amp; Co Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 7 at [72] , Finn, Emmett and Bennett JJ said:
 "In the efficient and proper conduct of civil litigation, even civil litigation hard fought between parties, it should always be recognised that, in the propounding of issues for trial, the parties should take steps to ensure that all relevant parties to the dispute are cognisant of what the issues are. Quietly leaving footprints in correspondence or directions hearings to be uncovered some time later in an attempt to reveal that a matter was always in issue is a practice that must be firmly discouraged. Where it is evident, or indeed suspected, that the other side is proceeding on the basis of a misconception or has not appreciated something, common sense will, as a general rule, mandate that a party ensure that the other is not proceeding on a misconception or that the other does appreciate something that has been said. No one's interests are advanced by litigation proceeding on assumptions which are seen or suspected to be false. The only consequence of keeping issues hidden or not clearly identifying them is to disrupt the business of the court leading to the waste of valuable public resources and to lead to the incurring of unnecessary costs by the parties, costs which ultimately have to be borne by someone: see White v Overland [2001] FCA 1333 at [4] ." (emphasis in original)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Zhu v Treasurer of New South Wales [2004] HCA 56 ; (2004) 218 CLR 530</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/56.html</AustLII>
<text>33 But, in construing a deed poll, just as with any contract, it is important to avoid it making commercial nonsense or working commercial inconvenience. This approach enables the court to give a construction to the deed poll and other transaction documents which a reasonable person in the position of the parties would have understood them to have intended by the words they chose in the context in which they engaged: Zhu v Treasurer of New South Wales [2004] HCA 56 ; (2004) 218 CLR 530 at 559 [82] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Callinan and Heydon JJ. The circumstances known to both Unwired and Intel at the time the deed poll was made and the overall transaction was entered into, included an awareness that each had conflicting aims and had made compromises which were expressed in the executed documents.

34 As the letter of 23 August 2005 recognised, the final form of the documents involved counterbalancing the possibilities of the note holder earning the various potential rates of return in different circumstances, all of which were, at that time, uncertain future events. I am of opinion that it is not reasonable or necessary to imply any term of the kind asserted by Unwired to give business efficacy to the deed poll or transaction.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>