<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Business &amp; Research Management Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1652 (14 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1652.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Arthur Murray (NSW) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1965] HCA 58 ; (1965) 114 CLR 314</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1965/58.html</AustLII>
<text>78 Central to the concept of derivation is the proposition that there must be a gain in the sense of an amount which has 'come home' to the taxpayer, i.e. it is available for the taxpayer's separate use, benefit and disposal: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Montgomery [1999] HCA 34 ; (1999) 198 CLR 639 at [65] and [117]-[118]; Commissioner of Taxes (SA) v Executor Trustee and Agency Co of South Australia (' Carden ') [1938] HCA 69 ; (1938) 63 CLR 108 at 155; Arthur Murray (NSW) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1965] HCA 58 ; (1965) 114 CLR 314 at 318; Eisner v Macomber [1919] USSC 118 ; (1920) 252 US 189 at 207 applied in Montgomery at [117]. That is, receipt of itself is not sufficient to constitute a gain or an amount as income derived: Arthur Murray at 318.

79 In order to determine whether a receipt has come home the enquiry is focused upon the general understanding among practical business people as to whether the receipt has come home for the separate use, benefit and disposal of the taxpayer: Arthur Murray at 318; Montgomery at [117].

81 A receipt will not come home where the amount received is affected by a legal or equitable restriction affecting the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of the recipient: Arthur Murray at 318; Barratt v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 271 ; (1992) 36 FCR 222 at 231; RW Parsons, Income Taxation in Australia : Principles of Income, Deductibility and Tax Accounting , Law Book Company, Sydney (1985) at [11.49]. For example, where the receipt is affected by a constructive trust (see, MacFarlane v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1986) 13 FCR 356) or where the recipient is not the beneficial object of the receipt (see The Countess of Bective v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1932) 47 CLR 417 at 424).

82 Further, even where there is no legal or equitable restriction affecting the receipt, the receipt may not come home where: 
 
(a) the practical 'realities' prevent the taxpayer from the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of a gain because the obligor cannot meet their legal or contractual obligations to the taxpayer (see Prior at 13); or
 
(b) it would be unsound from a business or legal perspective, to recognise the receipt as income because the receipt did not give a 'substantially correct reflex of the taxpayer's true income': see Carden at 145; Arthur Murray at 318; Ballarat Brewing Company Limited v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1951] HCA 35 ; (1951) 82 CLR 364 at 368, 369.

90 The consequence is that BARM derived income represented by the management fees payable pursuant to the Syndicate Deeds (subject to the operation of the ' Arthur Murray principle' discussed below) at the time at which the management fees became due to it by Participants; so understood, neither the time at which the payment obligation was discharged, nor the mode by which the payment obligation was discharged, were matters which affected the derivation by BARM of the income represented by the management fees.

94 The present state of authority recognises only a very limited class of cases in that payments may be actually received by a taxpayer, but only derived as income at later points in time. The relevant class of cases are those coming within the principle recognised in Arthur Murray .

95 It is not disputed here that, to the extent that BARM received management fees in one year that related in part to the provision by it of management services in the next year, the principle recognised in Arthur Murray would apply to defer the derivation of that part of the management fees until the later year, when the services in connection with those management fees were actually performed. Indeed, that is how it returned the income represented by the management fees.

96 The present case is, however, an attempt by BARM in reliance on Arthur Murray , to advance a broader proposition, namely, that notwithstanding:
 
(i) the incurring by Participants of debts in favour of BARM in respect of management fees; and
 
(ii) the discharge of those debts by delivery of the bills to BARM;
 
there was no derivation of income by BARM in respect of the management fees.

97 Unlike Arthur Murray , the foundation for this broader proposition does not relate to the time of performance by BARM of the management services. Rather, it rests on the following circumstances:
 
(a) BARM's conduct in entering into commercial transactions (i.e. loans) that were distinct and separate from the provision of the management services;
 
(b) the utilisation of the consideration received by BARM from Participants in respect of management fees in making those loans to PGF; and
 
(c) the circumstance that, by agreement with the borrower (PGF), BARM had limited or restricted its ability to enforce repayment of the loans.

98 The Commissioner submitted that the flaw in BARM's argument is that it attempts to conflate, for taxation purposes, the consequences of distinct and separate transactions being:
 
(i) the arrangement under which BARM provided management services to the Participants; and
 
(ii) the arrangement under which BARM made loans to PGF.

99 The first of those arrangements resulted in BARM agreeing to perform management activities which constituted the provision of services in the ordinary course of the business that it carried on and that resulted in the Participants discharging their payment obligations to it.

108 The argument underlying alternative (2) involves the deferral of derivation of income represented by the management fees to the time BARM receives payments of interest and repayments of principal on the deposit with PGF. For an accruals basis taxpayer, the point of derivation of such income would normally be, as the Commissioner contended, when the management fees fell due, subject of course to the principle that comes out of Arthur Murray that, even if received, there will be no derivation until the receipt is earned. As indicated in [95] above, that latter principle was observed in the way in which BARM returned the income represented by the management fees.

109 The argument for deferral to the time BARM receives payments of interest and repayments of principal on the deposit with PGF is said to '... look to realities' to use the words of Rich J in Prior at 13. What it effectively asserts is that BARM should be treated as a cash basis taxpayer in respect of such income and then only for the amount of money received. Reliance for this argument is placed on the process of reasoning in Arthur Murray , albeit for a very different principle, Prior and Barratt . I deal with each of these cases below.

112 Whatever else it might support, nothing was said in Arthur Murray which supports the argument underlying alternative (2). Arthur Murray was a case stated by Barwick CJ in five pending appeals from decisions of the Board of Review. The facts relevant to the only question that had to be formally answered were few and simple. They are recited in the judgment of the Court in the following terms at 316:
 'In the relevant years the company carried on a business of giving courses of tuition in dancing for fees of varying amounts per hour. What the case describes as basic courses of tuition available consisted of 5, 15 or 30 hours of private tuition to be taken by appointment within a year, though some students contracted for a course of 1,200 hours' tuition to be taken at any time during the student's lifetime. Payment for a course of lessons was often made in advance, either in the form of a lump sum or by instalments, a variable discount being allowed for immediate payment. For example, the fee for a lifetime course of 1,200 hours was [sterling]3,300, reducible to [sterling]3,000 for immediate payment. The student was given no contractual right to a refund in the event of his not completing the course--indeed the form of contract in general use denied any such right--though in practice refunds were sometimes given. In the company's books, fees were credited immediately upon their being received to an account styled "Unearned deposits--Untaught Lessons Account", and from that account amounts corresponding with lessons taught were periodically transferred to the credit of an account styled "Earned Tuition Account". The company made up its income tax returns on the footing that fees received in advance of tuition formed no part of its assessable income at the moment of receipt, but became such as and when earned by the giving of the lessons. The Commissioner, on the other hand, made the relevant assessments upon the view that fees received in advance of tuition possessed the character of assessable income in the company's hands from the moment of receipt, so that in respect of a given year of income there was no need to distinguish between fees for which lessons had been given during the year and fees for which at the end of the year the lessons still remained to be given. The question to be decided is, in effect, whether on the facts as stated it is open to the Justice hearing the appeals to uphold the Commissioner's view.'

113 The Court answered that question 'no' by declaring that on the facts appearing in the case stated the conclusion is not open that a receipt of fees for a specified number of dancing lessons to be given over a period subsequent to the receipt is a derivation of assessable income. In the course of their reasons, the Court said at 320:
 'Nothing in the Act is contradicted or ignored when a receipt of money as a prepayment under a contract for future services is said not to constitute by itself a derivation of assessable income. On the contrary, if the statement accords with ordinary business concepts in the community--and we are bound by the case stated to accept that it does--it applies the provisions of the Act according to their true meaning.'

114 Earlier in their reasons, the Court had said at 318:
 'As Dixon J. observed in Carden's Case: "Speaking generally, in the assessment of income the object is to discover what gains have during the period of account come home to the taxpayer in a realized or immediately realizable form". The word "gains" is not here used in the sense of the net profits of the business, for the topic under discussion is assessable income, that is to say gross income. But neither is it synonymous with "receipts". It refers to amounts which have not only been received but have "come home" to the taxpayer; and that must surely involve, if the word "income" is to convey the notion it expresses in the practical affairs of business life, not only that the amounts received are unaffected by legal restrictions, as by reason of a trust or charge in favour of the payer--not only that they have been received beneficially--but that the situation has been reached in which they may properly be counted as gains completely made, so that there is neither legal nor business unsoundness in regarding them without qualification as income derived.'

117 In my view, there is no process of reasoning in, or principle coming out of, Arthur Murray which supports the argument underlying alternative (2). And this would be the case whether BARM is an accruals basis or cash basis taxpayer, assuming of course that the principle coming out of Arthur Murray applies equally to both. While Arthur Murray concerned an accruals basis taxpayer, there seems to be no reason why the principle does not equally apply to a cash basis taxpayer.

118 Prior concerned a cash basis taxpayer who, during his lifetime, was a member of a partnership which was dissolved by a deed. His sole co-partner had borrowed money from him on his private account and the deceased had lent money to the partnership. An account was made up of the dealings between them on the dissolution and the result was shown as leaving the co-partner indebted to the deceased in the sum of [sterling]8,388, which included a sum of [sterling]2,535 made up of two amounts:
 
(1) [sterling]1,462 interest, said to be owing at 13 August 1932 by the co-partner on his personal account.
 
(2) [sterling]1,073 interest, said to be the deceased's half share of the interest owing to him by the partnership at the time.
 
By the deed, he undertook a personal liability to the deceased for the amount and secured it over a certain property already mortgaged, for part of the sum. The property was actually worth only [sterling]3,295 and by reason of his financial position the co-partner was unable to pay even the arrears of interest included in the sum and no payment had ever been made in respect of the sum.

119 The Commissioner contended that the interest referred to represented interest derived by the deceased during the account period ended 30 June 1932 but capitalised by means of the deed dated the 13 August 1932 affecting the dissolution of the partnership. Under the deed, the interest had been carried to the capital account.

126 In conclusion, my view is that, consistent with BARM being an accruals basis taxpayer, the income represented by the management fees was derived by BARM when those fees fell due; or, in the case of fees which related to the provision of services in a year of income after the year in which the fees fell due, consistent with the principle that comes out of Arthur Murray , in the year of income in which those services were provided. That is, as I understand the evidence, how BARM returned the income represented by the management fees. Even if BARM were to be taxed on the management fee income as a cash basis taxpayer, and as indicated in [111] above, I do not think such a basis is appropriate, that would only defer derivation to the date of delivery of the bills of exchange or, in the case of fees which related to the provision of services in a year of income after the year in which the fees were received, consistent with the principle that comes out of Arthur Murray , in the year of income in which these services were provided.

127 Moreover, in the absence of evidence that the money value of the bills at the time of delivery to BARM was less than their face value, no deferral would also result in a reduction in the quantum of the amount derived.

128 BARM's position in relation to Issue 1 cannot be sustained; and it follows that its position in relation to Issue 2 must also fail.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ballarat Brewing Company Limited v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1951] HCA 35 ; (1951) 82 CLR 364</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1951/35.html</AustLII>
<text>82 Further, even where there is no legal or equitable restriction affecting the receipt, the receipt may not come home where: 
 
(a) the practical 'realities' prevent the taxpayer from the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of a gain because the obligor cannot meet their legal or contractual obligations to the taxpayer (see Prior at 13); or
 
(b) it would be unsound from a business or legal perspective, to recognise the receipt as income because the receipt did not give a 'substantially correct reflex of the taxpayer's true income': see Carden at 145; Arthur Murray at 318; Ballarat Brewing Company Limited v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1951] HCA 35 ; (1951) 82 CLR 364 at 368, 369.

83 This is illustrated by the approach to income recognition in the area of insurance. It is accepted that, in an appropriate case, the aggregate of insurance premiums received by an insurer in a year of income does not give a substantially correct reflex of that insurer's income because of the contingencies affecting those premiums: see Sun Insurance Office v Clark (1912) AC 443 at 452-4, 456 and 460, 461, approved in Ballarat Brewing and Carden .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Barratt v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 271 ; (1992) 36 FCR 222 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/271.html</AustLII>
<text>81 A receipt will not come home where the amount received is affected by a legal or equitable restriction affecting the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of the recipient: Arthur Murray at 318; Barratt v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 271 ; (1992) 36 FCR 222 at 231; RW Parsons, Income Taxation in Australia : Principles of Income, Deductibility and Tax Accounting , Law Book Company, Sydney (1985) at [11.49]. For example, where the receipt is affected by a constructive trust (see, MacFarlane v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1986) 13 FCR 356) or where the recipient is not the beneficial object of the receipt (see The Countess of Bective v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1932) 47 CLR 417 at 424).

89 In respect of an accruals basis taxpayer, the time of derivation will normally be the time when a recoverable debt arises: Barratt at 231.2; Henderson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1970] HCA 62 ; (1968) 119 CLR 612 at 650.6.

103 The Commissioner submitted that it is a fundamental defect in BARM's argument that it impermissibly seeks to make derivation of the income amount (the debt/payment in respect of management services) dependent upon the capacity to recover the capital asset arising from investment of the income (the debt owing by PGF). Apart from the illogicality of the contended dependence, it is relevant to note that even if there had been an impediment to recovery of the debt on income account, that would not lead to the result that it would not have been derived as income. In Barratt at 232, Gummow J (Northrop and Drummond JJ agreeing) drew attention to the distinction between:
 
(a) the situation where a debt has not come into existence, with the result that income will not have been derived (an example of which was Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Australian Gas Light Co (1983) 74 FLR 13); and 
 
(b) the situation where a debt has come into existence, but there is an impediment to recovery. Accordingly, statutory prohibitions against recovery of fees for medical services pursuant to s 35(2) of the Medical Practitioners Act 1938 (NSW) were only impediments to enforcement that did not lead to the result that taxpayers assessable on an accruals basis had not derived the fees as income.

109 The argument for deferral to the time BARM receives payments of interest and repayments of principal on the deposit with PGF is said to '... look to realities' to use the words of Rich J in Prior at 13. What it effectively asserts is that BARM should be treated as a cash basis taxpayer in respect of such income and then only for the amount of money received. Reliance for this argument is placed on the process of reasoning in Arthur Murray , albeit for a very different principle, Prior and Barratt . I deal with each of these cases below.

124 Barratt was concerned with whether an accruals basis of tax accounting was appropriate for a partnership of medical practitioners carrying on a pathology practice where the partnership required the use of large and expensive equipment and laboratory, courier and clerical services which were provided by service entities associated with the partners. A Full Court of this Court held that it was and dismissed the taxpayer's appeal. The principal judgment was given by Gummow J with whom Northrop and Drummond JJ agreed but, with respect, it does not shine any light on the appropriateness of the principle put forward by BARM that is alternative (2).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brogden v Metropolitan Railway (1877) 2 AC 666</tocase>
<text>57 The authorities support the proposition that an agreement may be implied from the acts and conduct of the parties even where the strictures of offer and acceptance cannot be strictly proven: see Brogden v Metropolitan Railway (1877) 2 AC 666 at 672, 678, 679, 686, 689, 698; Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corp (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 B.P.R 11,110 at 11,117; Pobjie Agencies v Vinidex Tubemakers (2000) Aust Contract R 90-112 at [21]-[32]; see also Vroon v Foster's Brewing Group Ltd [1994] 2 VR 32 at 67.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Dunn (1989) 85 ALR 244</tocase>
<text>125 Expert accounting evidence was called by BARM in support of the argument underlying alternative (2) from Professor Robert Walker, the Professor of Accounting in the Faculty of Economics and Business at the University of Sydney. The Commissioner relied on expert accounting evidence from Mr Wayne Lonergan to deny the appropriateness of any financial accounting treatment consistent with the argument underlying alternative (2). With respect to both experts, I did not find their evidence provided me with any constructive assistance in resolving the issues raised by BARM's arguments. In any event, as Davies J observed in Commissioner of Taxation v Dunn (1989) 85 ALR 244 at 252:
 '... ordinary accounting principles and practices are not determinative of the issue, they are relevant and may be influential, as Dixon J in Carden's case (at 152) and Barwick CJ, Kitto and Taylor JJ in Arthur Murray (at 318) pointed out ...'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxes (SA) v Executor Trustee and Agency Co of South Australia [1938] HCA 69 ; (1938) 63 CLR 108</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/69.html</AustLII>
<text>78 Central to the concept of derivation is the proposition that there must be a gain in the sense of an amount which has 'come home' to the taxpayer, i.e. it is available for the taxpayer's separate use, benefit and disposal: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Montgomery [1999] HCA 34 ; (1999) 198 CLR 639 at [65] and [117]-[118]; Commissioner of Taxes (SA) v Executor Trustee and Agency Co of South Australia (' Carden ') [1938] HCA 69 ; (1938) 63 CLR 108 at 155; Arthur Murray (NSW) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1965] HCA 58 ; (1965) 114 CLR 314 at 318; Eisner v Macomber [1919] USSC 118 ; (1920) 252 US 189 at 207 applied in Montgomery at [117]. That is, receipt of itself is not sufficient to constitute a gain or an amount as income derived: Arthur Murray at 318.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1958/62.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Eisner v Macomber [1919] USSC 118 ; (1920) 252 US 189</tocase>
<text>78 Central to the concept of derivation is the proposition that there must be a gain in the sense of an amount which has 'come home' to the taxpayer, i.e. it is available for the taxpayer's separate use, benefit and disposal: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Montgomery [1999] HCA 34 ; (1999) 198 CLR 639 at [65] and [117]-[118]; Commissioner of Taxes (SA) v Executor Trustee and Agency Co of South Australia (' Carden ') [1938] HCA 69 ; (1938) 63 CLR 108 at 155; Arthur Murray (NSW) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1965] HCA 58 ; (1965) 114 CLR 314 at 318; Eisner v Macomber [1919] USSC 118 ; (1920) 252 US 189 at 207 applied in Montgomery at [117]. That is, receipt of itself is not sufficient to constitute a gain or an amount as income derived: Arthur Murray at 318.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Equuscorp Pty Ltd v Glengallan Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 55 ; (2004) 218 CLR 471 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/55.html</AustLII>
<text>92 While the Commissioner's primary submission is that the mode of discharge of payment of the management fees is irrelevant to the issue of derivation by BARM, the mode of discharge adopted (utilising bills of exchange) had the consequence that payments in the amounts shown on the bills of exchange (i.e. full payment of the management fees instalments) are to be taken as having been made to BARM on the dates on which the bills of exchange were delivered to it: Howland-Rose at [128] [130]; Equuscorp Pty Ltd v Glengallan Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 55 ; (2004) 218 CLR 471 at [44] [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1996) 61 FCR 489</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/5.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Montgomery [1999] HCA 34 ; (1999) 198 CLR 639</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/34.html</AustLII>
<text>78 Central to the concept of derivation is the proposition that there must be a gain in the sense of an amount which has 'come home' to the taxpayer, i.e. it is available for the taxpayer's separate use, benefit and disposal: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Montgomery [1999] HCA 34 ; (1999) 198 CLR 639 at [65] and [117]-[118]; Commissioner of Taxes (SA) v Executor Trustee and Agency Co of South Australia (' Carden ') [1938] HCA 69 ; (1938) 63 CLR 108 at 155; Arthur Murray (NSW) Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1965] HCA 58 ; (1965) 114 CLR 314 at 318; Eisner v Macomber [1919] USSC 118 ; (1920) 252 US 189 at 207 applied in Montgomery at [117]. That is, receipt of itself is not sufficient to constitute a gain or an amount as income derived: Arthur Murray at 318.

79 In order to determine whether a receipt has come home the enquiry is focused upon the general understanding among practical business people as to whether the receipt has come home for the separate use, benefit and disposal of the taxpayer: Arthur Murray at 318; Montgomery at [117].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].

104 There is much force in BARM's contention that alternative (1) does not involve taxation by reference to economic equivalence. Generally speaking, that doctrine has been relied on to seek re-characterisation of a receipt or outgoing where there is more than one way to achieve the desired economic result and the taxpayer chooses the way which is the most tax effective. Anti-avoidance provisions aside, the courts have consistently rejected the doctrine of taxation by reference to economic equivalence, that is, by reference to the ways in which the transaction could or might have been done, as an aid to characterisation. As was said in the joint judgment of Gaudron, McHugh, Kirby and Hayne JJ in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Orica Ltd [1998] HCA 33 ; (1998) 194 CLR 500 at [70] :
 '[L]ittle or no guidance is offered by considering what other transactions the taxpayer might have made to achieve a commercial result substantially the same as the commercial result said to flow from the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement. No doubt the taxpayer might have taken the amount of $62,309.546 which it paid to MMBW and instead of paying it to MMBW under the Principal Assumption Agreement have invested it in Commonwealth Bonds maturing at or about the same time as its debentures were to mature. If it had done that it would have derived income which it might then have applied in satisfaction of most, if not all, of its liabilities to debenture holders. Similarly, it might have invested the same amount as it paid to MMBW on more speculative investments and it might then have obtained returns greater than the amount necessary to pay the debenture holders. Examination of those other transactions does not reveal whether or when the taxpayer derived income as a result of the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement. In particular, the characterisation of the gains or receipts obtained in accordance with hypothetical transactions of the kind described is of little, if any, assistance in characterising the nature of the benefits identified as flowing from the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement.' 
In many ways, this is no more than an echo of what was said over twenty years before by Sir Nigel Bowen in Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v F C of T (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 386 387:
 'His Honour appears to have considered that he could approach the characterisation of the receipts in the hands of the taxpayer by treating them as if they were received by Bellambi or the Bellambi group. On the other hand, if they were treated as received by Federal, his Honour thought that they were received by Federal just as much as compensation for the contraction of the contract to supply coke as if the payee had been the parent rather than the subsidiary. One may have some sympathy with an approach of this kind. However, in taxation matters, the court is obliged to have regard to the actual facts and not to their equivalents. In cases where it is appropriate the court may apply a statutory provision such as s 260 to get rid of a contract, agreement or arrangement and deal with the case in disregard of that element, but, where there is no statutory warrant for doing so, the court cannot disregard certain of the facts or re-arrange the facts or decide the case according to its view of the substance of the matter. It is not legitimate to disregard the separateness of different corporate entities or to decide liability to tax upon the basis of the substantial economic or business character of what was done.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Australian Gas Light Co (1983) 74 FLR 13 </tocase>
<text>103 The Commissioner submitted that it is a fundamental defect in BARM's argument that it impermissibly seeks to make derivation of the income amount (the debt/payment in respect of management services) dependent upon the capacity to recover the capital asset arising from investment of the income (the debt owing by PGF). Apart from the illogicality of the contended dependence, it is relevant to note that even if there had been an impediment to recovery of the debt on income account, that would not lead to the result that it would not have been derived as income. In Barratt at 232, Gummow J (Northrop and Drummond JJ agreeing) drew attention to the distinction between:
 
(a) the situation where a debt has not come into existence, with the result that income will not have been derived (an example of which was Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Australian Gas Light Co (1983) 74 FLR 13); and 
 
(b) the situation where a debt has come into existence, but there is an impediment to recovery. Accordingly, statutory prohibitions against recovery of fees for medical services pursuant to s 35(2) of the Medical Practitioners Act 1938 (NSW) were only impediments to enforcement that did not lead to the result that taxpayers assessable on an accruals basis had not derived the fees as income.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Orica Ltd [1998] HCA 33 ; (1998) 194 CLR 500</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/33.html</AustLII>
<text>104 There is much force in BARM's contention that alternative (1) does not involve taxation by reference to economic equivalence. Generally speaking, that doctrine has been relied on to seek re-characterisation of a receipt or outgoing where there is more than one way to achieve the desired economic result and the taxpayer chooses the way which is the most tax effective. Anti-avoidance provisions aside, the courts have consistently rejected the doctrine of taxation by reference to economic equivalence, that is, by reference to the ways in which the transaction could or might have been done, as an aid to characterisation. As was said in the joint judgment of Gaudron, McHugh, Kirby and Hayne JJ in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Orica Ltd [1998] HCA 33 ; (1998) 194 CLR 500 at [70] :
 '[L]ittle or no guidance is offered by considering what other transactions the taxpayer might have made to achieve a commercial result substantially the same as the commercial result said to flow from the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement. No doubt the taxpayer might have taken the amount of $62,309.546 which it paid to MMBW and instead of paying it to MMBW under the Principal Assumption Agreement have invested it in Commonwealth Bonds maturing at or about the same time as its debentures were to mature. If it had done that it would have derived income which it might then have applied in satisfaction of most, if not all, of its liabilities to debenture holders. Similarly, it might have invested the same amount as it paid to MMBW on more speculative investments and it might then have obtained returns greater than the amount necessary to pay the debenture holders. Examination of those other transactions does not reveal whether or when the taxpayer derived income as a result of the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement. In particular, the characterisation of the gains or receipts obtained in accordance with hypothetical transactions of the kind described is of little, if any, assistance in characterising the nature of the benefits identified as flowing from the making of the Principal Assumption Agreement.' 
In many ways, this is no more than an echo of what was said over twenty years before by Sir Nigel Bowen in Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v F C of T (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 386 387:
 'His Honour appears to have considered that he could approach the characterisation of the receipts in the hands of the taxpayer by treating them as if they were received by Bellambi or the Bellambi group. On the other hand, if they were treated as received by Federal, his Honour thought that they were received by Federal just as much as compensation for the contraction of the contract to supply coke as if the payee had been the parent rather than the subsidiary. One may have some sympathy with an approach of this kind. However, in taxation matters, the court is obliged to have regard to the actual facts and not to their equivalents. In cases where it is appropriate the court may apply a statutory provision such as s 260 to get rid of a contract, agreement or arrangement and deal with the case in disregard of that element, but, where there is no statutory warrant for doing so, the court cannot disregard certain of the facts or re-arrange the facts or decide the case according to its view of the substance of the matter. It is not legitimate to disregard the separateness of different corporate entities or to decide liability to tax upon the basis of the substantial economic or business character of what was done.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/25.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].

91 Nor did the use to which the bills of exchange were put by BARM affect the derivation by it of income represented by the management fees: see G.P. International Pipecoaters .

101 The High Court noted in G.P. International Pipecoaters at 136 137:
 'The question in this appeal is the character of the establishment costs as receipts in the hands of the taxpayer 'Whether or not a particular receipt is income depends upon its quality in the hands of the recipient': Scott v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1966] HCA 48 ; [(1996) 117 CLR 514] , per Windeyer J. The relevant question is not the character of the expenditure by SECWA A receipt may be income in the hands of a payee whether or not it is expenditure of a capital nature by the payer. Nor is the relevant question the nature of the expenditure made by the taxpayer in the construction of the plant. A taxpayer may apply income in the acquisition of a capital asset or, conversely, apply a capital receipt to discharge a liability of a non-capital nature. As Cozens-Hardy MR observed in Hudson's Bay Co v Stevens: '... if the money is otherwise liable to income tax it cannot escape taxation by reason of its being applied to a capital purpose'. And thus a receipt may be income although the recipient is bound to apply it for the purpose of discharging a capital liability: Mersey Docks v Lucas [(1883) 8 App Cas 891, at 904, 909-910; Commissioners of Inland Revenue v Corporation of London (as Conservators of Epping Forest) [(1953) 34 TC 293, at 329]. The Commissioner and the taxpayer both treated the cost of constructing the plant as capital expenditure, but the question is not whether that was an expenditure of capital nor whether the plant was used for the purpose of producing assessable income so that depreciation of the plant was deductible under s 54 of the Act. The relevant question is whether the receipt of the establishment costs was income in the taxpayer's hands. It is necessary to keep that question steadily in mind and not to confuse the character of the receipt with the nature of the asset acquired by application of the moneys received. The appellant's argument was, in substance, that the plant was a capital asset, that the moneys expended in its construction were an expenditure of a capital nature by the taxpayer and that, as those moneys were received for the purpose of expenditure on the construction of the plant, their receipt was a receipt of capital. The first two steps may be accepted but the final step assumes that, when money is received for the purpose of its being expended by the recipient, the. character of the receipt is necessarily determined by the character of its proposed expenditure by the recipient. That assumption is erroneous and, even if the establishment costs were received for the purpose of expenditure on the construction of the plant, it does not necessarily follow that their receipt was a receipt of capital. Before turning to the character of the receipt, it is desirable first to consider the means by which the character of expenditure may be determined.' (emphasis added)

102 The taxation consequences of the loans to PGF must be addressed independently of the taxation consequences of the provision of management services. The loans to PGF were transactions that:
 
(a) had to be evaluated separately as coming within the capital gains regimes under the ITAA 1936 and the ITAA 1997: and
 
(b) represented a use of the consideration received from Participants in respect of management fees, by way of investment for income earning purposes;
 
(c) had the result that BARM incurred capital losses to the extent that there existed limited recourse provisions which had the consequences that loans to PGF were not repaid in full.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Henderson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1970] HCA 62 ; (1968) 119 CLR 612</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1970/62.html</AustLII>
<text>89 In respect of an accruals basis taxpayer, the time of derivation will normally be the time when a recoverable debt arises: Barratt at 231.2; Henderson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1970] HCA 62 ; (1968) 119 CLR 612 at 650.6.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Howland-Rose and Ors v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2002] FCA 246 ; (2002) 118 FCR 61 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/246.html</AustLII>
<text>15 In the course of its submission, BARM noted that in Howland-Rose and Ors v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2002] FCA 246 ; (2002) 118 FCR 61 , Conti J dealt with the tax position of four participants in BPS, in what amounted to a test case for BPS and the subsequent Budplans. His Honour held that the participants were not entitled to allowable deductions under s 51(1) of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth) ('ITAA 1936 ' ) in respect of the 'management fees' or 'research fees' paid by them. A review of his Honour's reasons does not indicate than any issue arose in that case as to the quantum of the outgoings claimed to be incurred; only their characterisation in terms of the section of the statute.

16 BPS was established by a prospectus dated 5 December 1995 ('Prospectus') and a trust deed dated the same date between BARM, ATTORI, ARG and each participant ('the Trust Deed'), once he or she signed the 'Principal Deed' referred to below.

17 Participants in BPS executed the following documents:
 
(1) an application form that is found at page 56 of the Prospectus ('Application Form');
 
(2) the Principal Deed that is found at pages 57 and 58 of the Prospectus ('Principal Deed'), to which were annexed a copy of the Budplan Syndicate Deed, at pages 46-51 of the Prospectus ('Syndicate Deed') and a Loan Agreement between PGF and the participant, at pages 52 54 of the Prospectus ('Loan Agreement');
 
 (3) in some or all cases, an alternative loan agreement between the participant and PGF ('Alternative Loan Agreement').

92 While the Commissioner's primary submission is that the mode of discharge of payment of the management fees is irrelevant to the issue of derivation by BARM, the mode of discharge adopted (utilising bills of exchange) had the consequence that payments in the amounts shown on the bills of exchange (i.e. full payment of the management fees instalments) are to be taken as having been made to BARM on the dates on which the bills of exchange were delivered to it: Howland-Rose at [128] [130]; Equuscorp Pty Ltd v Glengallan Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 55 ; (2004) 218 CLR 471 at [44] [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Integrated Computer Services Pty Limited v Digital Equipment Corp (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11,110</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Investment Merchant Finance Corporation Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1971] HCA 35 ; (1971) 125 CLR 249</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/35.html</AustLII>
<text>105 On the other hand, contrary to the submission in [73] and [74] above, BARM's alternative (1) does require a disregard of the legal relationships created by the relevant instruments; it requires a conflation of separate transactions, albeit financially dependent separate transactions, and taxation by reference to the end economic result of that conflation. That is equally impermissible. While not directly in point, it has a resonance with the alternative argument that was put to the High Court in Investment Merchant Finance Corporation Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1971] HCA 35 ; (1971) 125 CLR 249 where the assessment in question was sought to be upheld on the footing that the transaction, as a whole , was the carrying out of a profit-making scheme for the purposes of s 26(a) of the ITAA 1936, and that, in determining the profit derived from the scheme, the dividend received should be brought into account rather than being treated as itself, assessable income in accordance with s 44 of the ITAA 1936: in particular, see Menzies J at 262. That alternative argument was rejected by all members of the Court.

106 Of course, there will be cases where the Parliament mandates such treatment. The example that comes most readily to mind is the consolidation regime in Part III 90 of the ITAA 1997.

107 Alternative (1), rather than avoiding a 'blinkered' view of the transaction as submitted by BARM, does just that by requiring a 'closing of the eyes' to the separate transactions that took place. Contentions that alternative (1) recognises the reality of the transaction, as a whole, elides what that involves conflation of separate, albeit financially dependent, transactions, and taxation by reference to the end economic result. Like taxation by reference to economic equivalence, it must be rejected.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MacFarlane v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1986) 13 FCR 356 </tocase>
<text>81 A receipt will not come home where the amount received is affected by a legal or equitable restriction affecting the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of the recipient: Arthur Murray at 318; Barratt v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 271 ; (1992) 36 FCR 222 at 231; RW Parsons, Income Taxation in Australia : Principles of Income, Deductibility and Tax Accounting , Law Book Company, Sydney (1985) at [11.49]. For example, where the receipt is affected by a constructive trust (see, MacFarlane v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1986) 13 FCR 356) or where the recipient is not the beneficial object of the receipt (see The Countess of Bective v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1932) 47 CLR 417 at 424).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Permanent Trustee Co of New South Wales v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1940) 6 ATD 5 </tocase>
<text>80 That enquiry proceeds by reference to the 'realities' that affect the taxpayer's separate use, benefit and disposal of the receipt rather than merely the legal form of, or legal entitlements arising from, the receipt itself: Permanent Trustee Co of New South Wales v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (' Prior ') (1940) 6 ATD 5 at 13.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pobjie Agencies v Vinidex Tubemakers (2000) Aust Contract R 90-112</tocase>
<text>57 The authorities support the proposition that an agreement may be implied from the acts and conduct of the parties even where the strictures of offer and acceptance cannot be strictly proven: see Brogden v Metropolitan Railway (1877) 2 AC 666 at 672, 678, 679, 686, 689, 698; Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corp (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 B.P.R 11,110 at 11,117; Pobjie Agencies v Vinidex Tubemakers (2000) Aust Contract R 90-112 at [21]-[32]; see also Vroon v Foster's Brewing Group Ltd [1994] 2 VR 32 at 67.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030</tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sun Insurance Office v Clark (1912) AC 443</tocase>
<text>83 This is illustrated by the approach to income recognition in the area of insurance. It is accepted that, in an appropriate case, the aggregate of insurance premiums received by an insurer in a year of income does not give a substantially correct reflex of that insurer's income because of the contingencies affecting those premiums: see Sun Insurance Office v Clark (1912) AC 443 at 452-4, 456 and 460, 461, approved in Ballarat Brewing and Carden .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Countess of Bective v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1932) 47 CLR 417</tocase>
<text>81 A receipt will not come home where the amount received is affected by a legal or equitable restriction affecting the separate use, benefit or enjoyment of the recipient: Arthur Murray at 318; Barratt v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 271 ; (1992) 36 FCR 222 at 231; RW Parsons, Income Taxation in Australia : Principles of Income, Deductibility and Tax Accounting , Law Book Company, Sydney (1985) at [11.49]. For example, where the receipt is affected by a constructive trust (see, MacFarlane v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1986) 13 FCR 356) or where the recipient is not the beneficial object of the receipt (see The Countess of Bective v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1932) 47 CLR 417 at 424).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>61 The question of whether a contract was entered into or, if so, what the terms of that contract were, is not resolved by inadmissible assertions as to subjective beliefs, intentions or desires. Questions of formation of contract are dealt with on the objective theory of contract. As was recently restated by the High Court in Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 179:
 'This Court, in Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 78 ALJR 1045 , has recently reaffirmed the principle of objectivity by which the rights and liabilities of the parties to a contract are determined. It is not the subjective beliefs or understandings of the parties about their rights and liabilities that govern their contractual relations. What matters is what each party by words and conduct would have led a reasonable person in the position of the other party to believe.'

62 The Commissioner submitted in the present case:
 
(a) There is no evidence of any negotiations in relation to a deposit agreement. It is not self-evident what the terms of such an agreement would have been had there been any negotiation.
 
(b) Athough Mr Lear proposed a deposit agreement (with unidentified terms), Mr Gallagher did not want to impose any 'legal restrictions as to how it uses its money'.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vroon v Foster's Brewing Group Ltd [1994] 2 VR 32</tocase>
<text>57 The authorities support the proposition that an agreement may be implied from the acts and conduct of the parties even where the strictures of offer and acceptance cannot be strictly proven: see Brogden v Metropolitan Railway (1877) 2 AC 666 at 672, 678, 679, 686, 689, 698; Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corp (Aust) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 B.P.R 11,110 at 11,117; Pobjie Agencies v Vinidex Tubemakers (2000) Aust Contract R 90-112 at [21]-[32]; see also Vroon v Foster's Brewing Group Ltd [1994] 2 VR 32 at 67.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 </tocase>
<text>71 In determining whether an amount paid or payable to the taxpayer has the character of income, it is necessary:
 
(a) to have regard to the quality of the amount in the hands of the taxpayer and not to the character of the expenditure to the payer : Federal Commissioner of Taxation v McNeil [2007] HCA 5 ; (2007) 229 CLR 656 at [20] and [55]; G.P. International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136;
 
(b) to have regard to the whole of the surrounding circumstances or factual matrix, and not just to the contract under which the amount is paid or payable: Federal Coke Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1977) 34 FLR 375 at 385; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 53;
 
(c) as an elaboration of the previous paragraph, to consider the substance rather than the form of the transaction, particularly where an amount is paid as part of a wider, composite transaction: Dickenson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1958] HCA 62 ; (1958) 98 CLR 460 at 482, 491; Reuter v Federal Commissioner of Taxation 93 ATC 5030 at 5036 5037; Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Broken Hill Pty Co Ltd (2000) 45 ATR 507 at [50]; Macquarie Finance Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2004) 57 ATR 115 at [61], [64] per Hill J, on appeal [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [109] [111] per French J, [169] [170] and [187] per Hely J, and [251] [253] per Gyles J; Customs &amp; Excise Commissioners v Diners Club Ltd [1989] 1 WLR 1196 at 1207; see also Barclays Mercantile Business Finance Ltd v Mawson [2005] 1 AC 684; and
 
(d) to disregard the labels used by the parties: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Krakos Investments Pty Ltd (1995) 61 FCR 489 at 495; Vincent v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2002) 124 FCR 350 at [64] [72].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>