<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Duffy v Construction, Forestry, Mining &amp; Energy Union [2008] FCA 1804 (28 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1804.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cruse v Construction, Forestry, Mining &amp; Energy Union [2008] FCA 1267</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1267.html</AustLII>
<text>35 As was said in Cruse v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2008] FCA 1267 at [18] :
 Intention to coerce requires intent to exert pressure that would in a practical sense negate choice: see National Tertiary Education Industry Union at 143. Negation of choice can be contrasted with a desire to influence, persuade or induce. The question will be, as Weinberg J said in National Tertiary Education Industry Union at 143, whether "a person is left with a realistic choice as to whether or not to comply". 
The objective of the organisers in their 24 October 2005 discussion with Mr Noble was to "influence, persuade or induce". Vaughan was left with a realistic choice not to comply and did not comply.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cahill v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (No 2) [2008] FCA 1292</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1292.html</AustLII>
<text>19 The workers did not take industrial action as such. They were called off the job by Mr Fahnle. However, the organisers, on behalf of the Union, imposed a ban on the performance of work on the site after the meeting between the organisers and some of the workers on the morning of 20 October 2005. The bans on the concreting works lasted until 8.00 am the next day. The bans on earthworks lasted until the afternoon of the next day. Bans of that sort constitute "building industrial action" under s 36(1) of the Act : see Cahill v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (No 2) [2008] FCA 1292 at [58] , per Kenny J.

20 Counsel for the Union contended that the application was not pleaded so as to encompass any ban but only a ban which would constitute a restriction on the performance of work in accordance with the National Building and Construction Industry Award 2000 . Counsel referred to cl 12.1.2 of the Award which provides:
 Any direction issued by an employer shall be consistent with the employer's responsibilities to provide a safe and healthy working environment.

21 As the organiser's claims included the issue of the safety of working on the site in the absence of a site contamination report, counsel submitted that the bans did not involve a restriction on the performance of work in accordance with the Award. He observed that Mr Fahnle was, in effect, the agent of the employer of the workers in his capacity as site manager.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Seven Network (Operations) Ltd v Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia [2001] FCA 456 ; (2001) 109 FCR 378</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/456.html</AustLII>
<text>36 Further, "intent to coerce" must carry with it the exertion of pressure which involves conduct that is "unlawful, illegitimate and unconscionable": see Seven Network (Op erations) Ltd v Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia [2001] FCA 456 ; (2001) 109 FCR 378 at [41] per Merkel J. Mr Noble admitted in the concluding portion of his cross-examination that the conduct of the organisers was not of that sort.

37 Counsel for the applicant submitted that, at the 24 October 2005 meeting, the organisers told Mr Noble that, unless Vaughan employed a Union nominated shop steward, the bans on earthworks would remain in place. There are two problems with that submission. First, there were no operative bans on earthworks on the site on 24 October 2005. Second, the cross-examination of Mr Noble revealed that the " only threat" (emphasis added) was that if the Union did not have on site a safety representative/shop steward that it knew and trusted then organisers would need to visit the site to catch Vaughan if it did something wrong. Mr Noble also conceded that the organisers were not threatening to do anything "over and above their powers as union officials". Action "over and above" their powers would include the maintenance of unlawful bans. In any event there was no negation of choice for Vaughan if it did not accede to the demand for a Union nominated safety officer/steward as earthworks and concreting works had been completed by 24 October 2005. No operative or relative bans could have been maintained as a matter of practical reality. This aspect of the application is also without merit.

38 During the course of the evidence, the applicant applied for the admission of the evidence of a previous representation made by a person. The Court admitted the evidence under s 63 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth). The evidence consisted of a recording and transcript of an ABCC inspector's interview of Mr Dougas. Mr Dougas was not available to give evidence "about an asserted fact", that is, the events of 20 October 2005, because he had relied on his privilege against liability to a civil penalty under s 128(1)(b) of the Evidence Act and the Court, under s 128(5) , did not require him to give that evidence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>