<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lim v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations (No 2) [2008] FCA 1752 (21 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1752.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Aban v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1991] FCA 385 ; (1991) 31 FCR 93</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/385.html</AustLII>
<text>45 A delegation is not revoked when the office of the delegator passes to a new holder ( Aban v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1991] FCA 385 ; (1991) 31 FCR 93 at 98 per Morling, Jenkinson and Heerey JJ). The effect of a delegation is to confer upon the delegate an authority which he or she must exercise in accordance with the requirement of the statute but with his or her own independent discretion. It is not a relationship of principal and agent ( Kelly v Watson (1985) 10 FCR 305 at 318 per Neaves J). In Kelly Neaves J was considering whether a delegation continued to have operative effect notwithstanding the vacation of office of a particular permanent head who had executed the instrument of delegation. Justice Neaves was of the view (at 318) that clear and unambiguous language would be required before construing a statute to produce the result that the delegation ceased to operate when a delegator ceased to hold office (see also Johnson v Veterans' Review Board (2002) 71 ALD 16 at [31] [32] per Mansfield J). There is nothing in the Act or the SS Administration Act to suggest that the relevant delegations should cease with the holding of office of the delegator.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Brown v West [1990] HCA 7 ; (1990) 169 CLR 195</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/7.html</AustLII>
<text>37 The misstatement of the identity of the contracting party or of the employer of Mr Ptok and Ms Dean, as a mistake in naming the source of the power to enter into the Lim Activity Agreements, does not affect the validity of those agreements ( Brown v West [1990] HCA 7 ; (1990) 169 CLR 195 at 203).

38 Mr Lim also seems to contend that, whether or not the employees of WorkDirections Australia were exercising a power available as delegates of the Secretary, they were not entitled to sign without stating that it was on behalf of or as delegated by the Secretary. In this regard, Mr Lim contends that, while delegates may make decisions without revealing the source of their power, they cannot enter into agreements without indicating that they are doing so as delegates. Mr Lim says that his agreements were with a private contractor and that the Act has no application. Rather, he says, the Lim Activity Agreements are commercial contracts to which the common law applies. In a subsequent submission, Mr Lim stated that the failure to include any reference to the Secretary in the Lim Activity Agreements constitutes an ' operative mistake of law ', thereby rendering the agreements void.

39 Each Lim Activity Agreement states that it is ' an Activity Agreement under the Social Security Act 1991 '. Each states that it refers to activities necessary to receive income support payments from Centrelink. Mr Lim could not have believed that the Lim Activity Agreements were private arrangements. He could have been under no misapprehension that the agreements were under the Act and had consequences under the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnson v Veterans' Review Board (2002) 71 ALD 16</tocase>
<text>45 A delegation is not revoked when the office of the delegator passes to a new holder ( Aban v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1991] FCA 385 ; (1991) 31 FCR 93 at 98 per Morling, Jenkinson and Heerey JJ). The effect of a delegation is to confer upon the delegate an authority which he or she must exercise in accordance with the requirement of the statute but with his or her own independent discretion. It is not a relationship of principal and agent ( Kelly v Watson (1985) 10 FCR 305 at 318 per Neaves J). In Kelly Neaves J was considering whether a delegation continued to have operative effect notwithstanding the vacation of office of a particular permanent head who had executed the instrument of delegation. Justice Neaves was of the view (at 318) that clear and unambiguous language would be required before construing a statute to produce the result that the delegation ceased to operate when a delegator ceased to hold office (see also Johnson v Veterans' Review Board (2002) 71 ALD 16 at [31] [32] per Mansfield J). There is nothing in the Act or the SS Administration Act to suggest that the relevant delegations should cease with the holding of office of the delegator.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kelly v Watson (1985) 10 FCR 305</tocase>
<text>45 A delegation is not revoked when the office of the delegator passes to a new holder ( Aban v Minister for Immigration, Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1991] FCA 385 ; (1991) 31 FCR 93 at 98 per Morling, Jenkinson and Heerey JJ). The effect of a delegation is to confer upon the delegate an authority which he or she must exercise in accordance with the requirement of the statute but with his or her own independent discretion. It is not a relationship of principal and agent ( Kelly v Watson (1985) 10 FCR 305 at 318 per Neaves J). In Kelly Neaves J was considering whether a delegation continued to have operative effect notwithstanding the vacation of office of a particular permanent head who had executed the instrument of delegation. Justice Neaves was of the view (at 318) that clear and unambiguous language would be required before construing a statute to produce the result that the delegation ceased to operate when a delegator ceased to hold office (see also Johnson v Veterans' Review Board (2002) 71 ALD 16 at [31] [32] per Mansfield J). There is nothing in the Act or the SS Administration Act to suggest that the relevant delegations should cease with the holding of office of the delegator.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lim v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 1058</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1058.html</AustLII>
<text>8 The respondent challenged the competency of the appeal on the ground that it did not disclose a question of law as required by s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) ('the AAT Act'). That objection to competency came before Branson J who accepted that the notice of appeal did not identify a question of law capable of constituting the subject matter of the purported appeal ( Lim v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 1058). Her Honour concluded at [12] that the:
 ... factual assertion that Mr Lim had made arrangements, apparently after breaching one of his agreements, to attend at WorkDirections on an extra day in a later week does not itself constitute a question of law. Nor does it by implication raise a question of law the answer to which could throw doubt on the correctness of the decision of the Tribunal. The references in the notice of appeal to the law of "attendance" and "reasonable excuse" do not assist Mr Lim in this regard.

9 However, her Honour gave consideration to any questions of law that Mr Lim could reasonably expect to be able to obtain leave to include in his notice of appeal were he to apply to amend the document. Her Honour said at [15]:
 However, it seems to me that it is at least arguable that none of the agreements between Mr Lim and WorkDirections is "a Newstart Activity Agreement between the Secretary and the person" within the meaning of s 624 of [the Act]. In particular I consider it arguable that the Secretary has not approved a form of Newstart Activity Agreement for an agreement between a person and a party other than Centrelink. It may also be arguable that the authority of the Secretary to delegate all or any of the Secretary's powers under [the Act] is insufficient to alter the requirements of s 605(4) that a Newstart Activity Agreement be between the person and the Secretary. I do not mean thereby to suggest that the Secretary could not delegate his or her power to sign such an agreement. However, the agreements entered into by Mr Lim do not purport to be agreements between him and the Secretary. They purport to be agreements between him and WorkDirections.

10 Mr Lim filed an amended notice of appeal on 25 July 2008 and a further amended notice of appeal on 20 August 2008. In the further amended notice of appeal the questions of law raised are:
 
 1. Whether it was open to the Tribunal to be satisfied that the agreements entered into by Mr Lim were Newstart Activity agreements within the meaning of s 624 of [the Act] . 
 
 2. Whether it was open to the Tribunal to proceed hearing when the respondent (Secretary, DEWR) was not the same person who purported to have activity agreement with Mr Lim within the meaning of s 624 of [the Act] .

11 The ground stated in the further amended notice of appeal is ' covering up the truth and deceiving the court process '. I do not propose to deal with this ground further. Nothing was raised that would support any such conclusion.

12 The findings of fact that Mr Lim asks the Court to make are:
 
 
 1. Agreements which Mr Lim signed are not approved by the Secretary s 234 instrument. Agreements which Mr Lim signed are purported to be agreement between Mr Lim and Workdirections. 
 
 2. The newstart agreement was purported between Mr Lim and the Secretary of liberal govt. At the AAT hearing, the solicitor of respondent represent Miss Lisa Paul, Secretary of labour govt. Miss Paul was not privity to the newstart agreement with Mr Lim.

49 Although the respondent was unsuccessful in the objection to competency of the appeal, it was Branson J, not Mr Lim or his notice of appeal, that disclosed an arguable case.

50 While the respondent has established the validity of the Lim Activity Agreements and Mr Lim's application is to be dismissed, it was only after a series of attempts to validate the agreements and errors that were identified by Mr Lim and by the Court. In the circumstances, I note that the respondent has not sought an order as to costs and I will make no order as to costs. 

 I certify that the preceding fifty (50) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 


 Associate:

Dated: 21 November 2008

 The Applicant was self-represented 
 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 8 October 2008, 6 November 2008 
 
 Date of last written submissions: 13 November 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 21 November 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1752.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Luan v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 72</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/72.html</AustLII>
<text>40 As was the case for the Departmental Officer in Luan v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 72 , an employee of WorkDirections Australia could only exercise the power to sign an agreement that resulted in Centrelink payments if delegated by the Secretary to do so. The Lim Activity Agreements are written agreements in a form approved by the Secretary. That approved form provides not for the signature of the Secretary but for the signature of the Employment Service Provider/Customer Service Adviser. This was the format of the Lim Activity Agreements.

41 The fact that the agreements were signed by employees of WorkDirections Australia, as delegates of the Secretary, does not preclude the agreements being between the Secretary and Mr Lim, despite the fact that the WorkDirections Australia employees did not indicate the source of power to enter into the agreements. Nor does it otherwise preclude the agreements being Newstart Activity Agreements within s 605(4).

42 The Lim Activity Agreements are agreements between the person (Mr Lim) and the Secretary for the purposes of ss 605(4) and 624 of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>