<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Scottsdale Homes No 3 Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1958 (16 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1958.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Creevey v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 19 ACSR 456</tocase>
<text>15 So far as the adjournment of an application for the winding up of company under s 440A is concerned, the authority which has proved influential is a decision of the Queensland Court of Appeal, Creevey v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 19 ACSR 456. Mr McPherson J, with whose judgment Pincus and Davies JJ agreed, remarked at page 457:
 It is evident from the terms of that subsection [440A(2)] that before it applies, the court must be satisfied not only that there is an administration, but also, as the subsection says, that it is in the interests of the company's creditors for the company to continue under administration rather than be wound up. The judge in the present case was not satisfied that it was in the creditor's interests for the administration to continue and it is his decision to that effect that is challenged here. The question of whether an administration should continue, rather than that there be a winding up, is obviously closely related to the further question of whether the creditors could hope to get more by way of payment of their debts from one form of process or administration than from the other. In order to satisfy the court of the matter referred to in s 440A(2) of the Corporations Law, one would expect that there would have to be some persuasive evidence to enable it to be seen that there were assets which, if realized under one form of administration rather than the other, would produce a larger dividend, or at least an accelerated dividend for the creditors.

16 It is possible that in a liquidation of the company, a domino effect might occur, whereby related company loans are called up successively. Whether or not that would lead to a better return to creditors than a continuance of the administration and something of a "wait and see" approach in relation to the proposed refinancing and consequential repayment, is a moot point indeed. The only particular recovery in prospect to which the administrator points in his later affidavit is that of the two preferential payments. That would yield a recovery well short of 100 cents in the dollar for the creditors.

17 What came to be proposed on behalf of the administrators after Mr Quinlivan's affidavit was read, were orders in the following terms:
 
1. The application for winding up be adjourned until 12 February 2009.
 
2. The convening period described by section 439A be extended to 13 February 2009.
 
3. A direction that the meeting of creditors held pursuant to section 439A be held no earlier than 14 February 2009.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>