<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Priestley v Godwin [2008] FCA 1179 (16 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1179.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/1.html</AustLII>
<text>18 In Rossetto at [45] I referred to the test in s 31A and observed that it provides ' a more flexible and arguably less stringent test than that of Dey and General Steel', referring to Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125. In Rossetto at [46] I concluded that, by either test, I was satisfied that the cause of action in that case could not succeed and was liable to be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2000) 205 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/63.html</AustLII>
<text>20 Mr Priestley then submits that my decision to refuse his first application for recusal was incorrect, as failing to apply the common law test in Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy [2000] HCA 63 ; (2000) 205 CLR 337. He submits that I made an error of law.

21 Mr Priestley points to Ebner at 363 where Gaudron J noted that the test with respect to the appearance of bias is ' "whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question [he or she] is required to decide" ' (citing Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488 at [11] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Mr Priestley says that it is necessary for me first to test his application for my recusal in the way described by the Court in Ebner and to consider the history of the proceedings and all relevant facts and circumstances as a whole to decide whether a perception of bias has arisen.

24 I am fully aware of the test in Ebner and my consideration of Mr Priestley's submissions regarding a reasonable apprehension of bias was in accordance with that test. I do not consider that this ground supports a basis for me to recuse myself. Accordingly, this application for recusal is refused.

25 Mr Priestley makes a further application for me to recuse myself and submits that I had ' not disclosed all relevant circumstances regarding [my] decision to continue hearing this matter '. He argues that I have not complied with the Guide to Judicial Conduct 2007 at paragraph 3.5(f). That paragraph provides that if a judge decides to sit, the reasons for that decision should be recorded in open court, as should the disclosure of all relevant circumstances.

26 The reasons for my decision on applications 1 and 2 have been recorded. Mr Priestley submits that the "relevant circumstances" that require disclosure are the circumstances surrounding my participation as a rule making judge and the process by which O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules was passed.

27 The respondents submit that the rule exists and has been made. The respondents say that the matters that go beyond this fact, such as who actually drafted the rule, are irrelevant.

28 I do not consider that this application contains grounds that support a basis for recusal. Accordingly, this application for recusal is refused.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>18 In Rossetto at [45] I referred to the test in s 31A and observed that it provides ' a more flexible and arguably less stringent test than that of Dey and General Steel', referring to Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125. In Rossetto at [46] I concluded that, by either test, I was satisfied that the cause of action in that case could not succeed and was liable to be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488</tocase>
<text>21 Mr Priestley points to Ebner at 363 where Gaudron J noted that the test with respect to the appearance of bias is ' "whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question [he or she] is required to decide" ' (citing Johnson v Johnson (2000) 201 CLR 488 at [11] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Mr Priestley says that it is necessary for me first to test his application for my recusal in the way described by the Court in Ebner and to consider the history of the proceedings and all relevant facts and circumstances as a whole to decide whether a perception of bias has arisen.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Laws v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal [1990] HCA 31 ; (1990) 170 CLR 70</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/31.html</AustLII>
<text>14 In any event, where the basis for the alleged apprehension of bias applies to all judges of the Court, the doctrine of necessity applies so that a judge of this Court has to hear the application. The doctrine of necessity permits a member of a court who has some interest in the subject matter of the litigation to sit on a case where no judge without such an interest is available to sit ( Laws v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal [1990] HCA 31 ; (1990) 170 CLR 70 per Mason CJ and Brennan J at 88).

15 Accordingly, this application for recusal is refused.

16 After I determined that I would not recuse myself on the ground of bias and/ or reasonable apprehension of bias, Mr Priestley seeks to raise an additional ground as to why I should recuse myself, namely, my role as a rule making judge of this Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Priestley v Godwin [2008] FCA 835</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/835.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The respondents in each proceeding have filed and served notices of objections to competency. When the notices came on for hearing before Gyles J, Mr Priestley raised a constitutional issue ('the constitutional issue'). Accordingly, Gyles J did not proceed with the hearing but ordered that s 78B notices be served ( Priestley v Godwin [2008] FCA 835 (' Priestley ') at [3]).

3 Mr Priestley challenges the constitutional validity of s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ('the Act') and O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules which was made in furtherance of that section. Mr Priestley's primary submission is that the judges of the Federal Court were influenced by Parliament to replace the former test in the Federal Court Rules of "no reasonable cause of action" made, he says, under the Court's inherent jurisdiction, with the statutory test contained in s 31A, thereby compromising the independence of the Court.

4 On 11 June 2008 the constitutional issue was listed for hearing on 16 July 2008, before me. On 14 July 2008 Mr Priestley sent a letter to my Chambers requesting that the hearing be ' adjourned for a time and date to be determined by the Federal Court '. The basis for this request was ' the commencement of proceedings in the High Court ' for an order to show cause. I declined to adjourn the hearing and the matter came before me on 16 July 2008.

5 Mr Priestley presses his application for an adjournment, on the basis that he has filed an application in the High Court. That application relates to his objection to any judge of the Federal Court, or any judge that participated in the making of O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules , sitting on his matter. The application to the High Court also relates to the decision of Stone J in Priestley not to recuse herself. Mr Priestley has joined me as a defendant in the High Court proceedings, filed before the first return of these proceedings before me, on the basis of bias and/ or reasonable apprehension of bias.

6 The respondents neither consent to nor oppose the application for adjournment. Although proceedings have been filed in the High Court, no application has been made to remove this matter to the High Court. The proceedings are before me for hearing. The Court has set aside the time for that hearing and the parties are present. The respondents are represented by counsel and solicitors. I see no sufficient reason to adjourn the matter because Mr Priestley has brought an application in the High Court. That application relates, in part, to a prior aspect of these proceedings, specifically Stone J's refusal to recuse herself, and an anticipatory claim concerning me.

7 The application for an adjournment is refused.

8 Mr Priestley has made four applications that I recuse myself from hearing the matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rossetto v Meriton Apartments Proprietary Limited [2006] FCA 1290</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1290.html</AustLII>
<text>17 Mr Priestley submits that I am disqualified from hearing this matter by reason of my specific interest in O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules . Mr Priestley submits that I have made comments in a judgment regarding s 31A of the Act and that I have therefore considered and applied s 31A. He submits that this is a further ground for a reasonable apprehension of bias. He says that in Rossetto v Meriton Apartments Proprietary Limited [2006] FCA 1290 I made comments to the effect that s 31A is a valid law of the Commonwealth and that this shows that there is a reasonable apprehension of bias on my part.

18 In Rossetto at [45] I referred to the test in s 31A and observed that it provides ' a more flexible and arguably less stringent test than that of Dey and General Steel', referring to Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 and General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125. In Rossetto at [46] I concluded that, by either test, I was satisfied that the cause of action in that case could not succeed and was liable to be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Webb v The Queen [1994] HCA 30 ; (1994) 181 CLR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1994/30.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Mr Priestley submits that I should recuse myself from hearing this matter due to a reasonable apprehension of bias. Mr Priestley points to Deane J's statement in Webb v The Queen [1994] HCA 30 ; (1994) 181 CLR 41 at 74 where his Honour noted that one of the categories of disqualification by reason of appearance of bias was ' disqualification by interest... where some direct or indirect interest in the proceedings, whether pecuniary or otherwise, gives rise to a reasonable apprehension of prejudice '. Mr Priestley submits that I have an interest in the proceedings and that I am biased as a rule making judge of the Federal Court.

10 Further, it is Mr Priestley's submission that there is no judge presently sitting on the Federal Court who can sit on his case, either because that judge was also a rule making judge with respect to the impugned rule, or because the judge has applied s 31A of the Act. Although judges have been appointed to the bench since O 20 r 5 was passed, Mr Priestley submits that these judges are also biased as they have applied s 31A of the Act in their judgments. Mr Priestley says that would give rise to a reasonable apprehension of bias on the part of that judge because he or she has therefore been influenced by Parliament.

11 Mr Priestley proffers two alternatives to myself or any other judge of the Court hearing his matter. He submits that the matter could be referred to the High Court under s 40 of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) ('the Judiciary Act ') and that he could apply for a writ of prohibition and ask the High Court to issue s 78B notices in order for the High Court to examine the constitutional validity of s 31A of the Act. The other alternative Mr Priestley proffers is that Parliament appoint a new judge to the Federal Court to sit on his case.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>