<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bing! Software Pty Ltd v Bing Technologies Pty Limited (No 1) [2008] FCA 1760 (25 November 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1760.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Anakin Pty Ltd v Chatswood BBQ King Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1517</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1517.html</AustLII>
<text>118 In relation to the claim of the applicant in para 4 of the Amended Application although it is open to the Court to order a change of corporate name in appropriate circumstances (as, for example, was ordered by the Court in Anakin Pty Ltd v Chatswood BBQ King Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1517) I do not consider these appropriate circumstances. As I have already explained, in my view the undertaking of the first respondent and the order I propose to make adequately address issues raised by the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson and Eclar Investments Pty Ltd (1981) 55 FLR 1</tocase>
<text>31 Further, it is clear that in considering whether the competing marks are substantially identical within s 120(1) of the Act a comparison must be undertaken of the registered trade mark and the whole of the respondent's mark, and not merely part of it: Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson and Eclar Investments Pty Ltd (1981) 55 FLR 1 at 8.

32 As I noted earlier in this judgment, the applicant's registered trade mark is as follows:

33 The respondents use "bing" in a number of ways, including the following:
 
and
 
and
 




and
 Bing 
and</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson (1983) 66 FLR 216</tocase>
<text>35 The fact that both marks include the same word does not conclusively mean that the marks are "substantially identical": Marc A Hammond Pty Ltd v Papa Carmine Pty Ltd (1973) 28 FLR 160; Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson (1983) 66 FLR 216. Indeed, the fact that the Bing Trade Mark is written in capital letters, and the first respondent's mark is not, suggests that the two marks are not substantially identical: SAP Australia Pty Ltd v Sapient Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1821 ; (1999) 169 ALR 1 at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/22.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In addition to these principles, it is also clear that:
 
&#8226; In order to determine whether there has been any contravention of s 52 it is necessary to determine whether or not the conduct complained of amounted to a representation which has or would be likely to lead to a misconception arising in the minds of that section of the public to whom the conduct has been directed: Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22 at [34] .
 
&#8226; Whether or not there is the requirement of some exclusive reputation as an element in the common law tort of passing off, there is no such requirement in relation to Pt V of the TPA. The question is not whether an applicant has shown a sufficient reputation in a particular get-up or name. The question is whether the use of the particular get-up or name by an alleged wrongdoer in relation to his product is likely to mislead or deceive persons familiar with the claimant's product to believe that the two products are associated, having regard to the state of knowledge of consumers in Australia of the claimant's product: Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359 at 419; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [39] .
 
&#8226; Where the relevant conduct involves representations to the public at large or to a section thereof, such as prospective purchasers of a product the respondent markets or proposes to market, the issue is one of identifying the "ordinary" or "reasonable" members of that class of prospective purchasers: Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45 at 84-85.
 
&#8226; It is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of the class of prospective purchasers: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 85. This excludes erroneous or fanciful assumptions: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 86.
 
&#8226; Where a transitory association between the names of two products in the mind of a member of the public is immediately dispelled upon a comparison of those products, this brief association will generally be of no significance and therefore will not give rise to misleading conduct or deception: Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [53] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Home Loans Ltd t/as Aussie Home Loans v Phillips [1998] FCA 181 ; (1998) 40 IPR 392</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/181.html</AustLII>
<text>82 While the respective trade marks of both parties feature the word "bing" there is absolutely no evidence that in doing so the first respondent represented any relationship with the applicant, that the first respondent's service was in any way related to the products and services provided by the applicant, or that the first respondent's service had, for example, uses or benefits which it did not have. While not conclusive, I also consider that the substantial differences between the products and service offered by the applicant and the service offered by the first respondent militate against the application of s 53 (cf Australian Home Loans Ltd t/as Aussie Home Loans v Phillips [1998] FCA 181 ; (1998) 40 IPR 392).

83 This finding is further supported by the absence of evidence before me that either the applicant or its products have a reputation from which the first respondent would be able to benefit (cf Australian Home Loans Ltd t/as Aussie Home Loans v Phillips [1998] FCA 181 ; (1998) 40 IPR 392 ; Mark Foys Pty Ltd v TVSN (Pacific) Ltd [2000] FCA 1626). Other than evidence of a small number of inquiries temporarily confusing the applicant with the first respondent, there is no evidence that the applicant or its products and service are sufficiently well-known that a substantial number of members of the public, or even a substantial number of members of those sections of the public which are likely to engage either with the applicant or respondent, would be misled in terms of ss 53(c) or 53 (d) TPA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v FS Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/51.html</AustLII>
<text>39 The concept of "deceptive similarity" in the context of trade marks was described by Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 415 as follows:
 On the question of deceptive similarity a different comparison must be made from that which is necessary when substantial identity is in question. The marks are not now to be looked at side by side. The issue is not abstract similarity, but deceptive similarity. Therefore the comparison is the familiar one of trade mark law. It is between, on the one hand, the impression based on recollection of the plaintiff's mark that persons of ordinary intelligence and memory would have; and, on the other hand, the impressions that such persons would get from the defendant's television exhibitions. To quote Lord Radcliffe again: "The likelihood of confusion or deception in such cases is not disproved by placing the two marks side by side and demonstrating how small is the chance of error in any customer who places his order for goods with both the marks clearly before him... It is more useful to observe that in most persons the eye is not an accurate recorder of visual detail, and that marks are remembered rather by general impressions or by some significant detail than by any photographic recollection of the whole": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co at 106. And in Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v FS Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said "In deciding this question, the marks ought not, of course, to be compared side by side. An attempt should be made to estimate the effect or impression produced on the mind of potential customers by the mark or device for which the protection of an injunction is sought. The impression or recollection which is carried away and retained is necessarily the basis of any mistaken belief that the challenged mark or device is the same" (at 658)...(at 416). The deceptiveness that is contemplated must result from similarity; but the likelihood of deception must be judged not by the degree of similarity alone, but by the effect of that similarity in all the circumstances.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>British Telecommunications PLC v One In A Million Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 289</tocase>
<text>119 In relation to the order sought by the applicant in para 5 of the Amended Application, namely that the first respondent transfer the registration of the domain name www.bing.com , I make the following observations:
 
&#8226; The first respondent, apparently in good faith, acquired the domain name from the United States for the not inconsiderable sum of $US25,000. An order in the nature of that sought by the applicant, which would deprive the first respondent of that asset, is not lightly entertained by the Court.
 
&#8226; While it may be commonplace for companies in Australia to use a ".com" or ".com.au" domain name, the first respondent's domain name is registered in the United States. An order that the first respondent transfer an international domain name to remedy infringement of an Australian trade mark which trade mark is territorial in its operation would in my view require extraordinary circumstances.
 
&#8226; The applicant has relied on a number of cases in support of its application for an order that the first respondent be ordered to transfer the domain name, namely the English Court of Appeal case British Telecommunications PLC v One In A Million Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 289 and the High Court of New Zealand case Oggi Advertising Ltd v McKenzie (1998) 44 IPR 661. Further, Hill J ordered transfer of a domain name in CSR Ltd v Resource Capital Australia Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; (2003) 128 FCR 408. However each of those cases involved cybersquatting, defined by The Australian Concise Oxford Dictionary as "the practice of registering names, especially well-known company or brand names, as Internet domains, in the hope of reselling them at a profit", and which practice is, as Hill J noted in CSR Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; 128 FCR 408 , conduct somewhat suggestive of criminality and fraud. The facts in each of those cases were very different from those in the case before me.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359</tocase>
<text>71 In addition to these principles, it is also clear that:
 
&#8226; In order to determine whether there has been any contravention of s 52 it is necessary to determine whether or not the conduct complained of amounted to a representation which has or would be likely to lead to a misconception arising in the minds of that section of the public to whom the conduct has been directed: Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22 at [34] .
 
&#8226; Whether or not there is the requirement of some exclusive reputation as an element in the common law tort of passing off, there is no such requirement in relation to Pt V of the TPA. The question is not whether an applicant has shown a sufficient reputation in a particular get-up or name. The question is whether the use of the particular get-up or name by an alleged wrongdoer in relation to his product is likely to mislead or deceive persons familiar with the claimant's product to believe that the two products are associated, having regard to the state of knowledge of consumers in Australia of the claimant's product: Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359 at 419; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [39] .
 
&#8226; Where the relevant conduct involves representations to the public at large or to a section thereof, such as prospective purchasers of a product the respondent markets or proposes to market, the issue is one of identifying the "ordinary" or "reasonable" members of that class of prospective purchasers: Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45 at 84-85.
 
&#8226; It is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of the class of prospective purchasers: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 85. This excludes erroneous or fanciful assumptions: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 86.
 
&#8226; Where a transitory association between the names of two products in the mind of a member of the public is immediately dispelled upon a comparison of those products, this brief association will generally be of no significance and therefore will not give rise to misleading conduct or deception: Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [53] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/12.html</AustLII>
<text>71 In addition to these principles, it is also clear that:
 
&#8226; In order to determine whether there has been any contravention of s 52 it is necessary to determine whether or not the conduct complained of amounted to a representation which has or would be likely to lead to a misconception arising in the minds of that section of the public to whom the conduct has been directed: Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22 at [34] .
 
&#8226; Whether or not there is the requirement of some exclusive reputation as an element in the common law tort of passing off, there is no such requirement in relation to Pt V of the TPA. The question is not whether an applicant has shown a sufficient reputation in a particular get-up or name. The question is whether the use of the particular get-up or name by an alleged wrongdoer in relation to his product is likely to mislead or deceive persons familiar with the claimant's product to believe that the two products are associated, having regard to the state of knowledge of consumers in Australia of the claimant's product: Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359 at 419; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [39] .
 
&#8226; Where the relevant conduct involves representations to the public at large or to a section thereof, such as prospective purchasers of a product the respondent markets or proposes to market, the issue is one of identifying the "ordinary" or "reasonable" members of that class of prospective purchasers: Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45 at 84-85.
 
&#8226; It is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of the class of prospective purchasers: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 85. This excludes erroneous or fanciful assumptions: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 86.
 
&#8226; Where a transitory association between the names of two products in the mind of a member of the public is immediately dispelled upon a comparison of those products, this brief association will generally be of no significance and therefore will not give rise to misleading conduct or deception: Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [53] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Colbeam Palmer Ltd v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/50.html</AustLII>
<text>104 I have found that both the first respondent and Mr Cranitch infringed the registered trade mark of the applicant under the Act , but that the applicant has not substantiated its claims in relation to breach of the TPA or passing off. Accordingly, I now turn to the applicant's claims for injunctive and associated relief and damages. In this respect I note that, in closing submissions, the applicant elected to seek an award of damages rather than an account of profits pursuant to s 126(b) of the Act and in accordance with the principles in Colbeam Palmer Ltd v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25 at 32.

105 On 11 March 2008 the first respondent gave an undertaking in Court through its counsel, Mr Crowe SC. Any consideration of relief which would have been available to the applicant must be carried out in light of this undertaking.

106 The undertaking was in the following terms:
 MR CROWE: Your Honour, while Mr Cranitch is coming to the courtroom, I have instructions from the first respondent to offer an undertaking to the court to give an undertaking to the court that the first respondent in relation to all references to the software, the subject of these proceedings, will not use the word "BING!" when directly referring to that software in any documentation, on websites, or otherwise. To make that plain it is not offering to change its name, but it is offering an undertaking that it will not refer to the software itself as BING! or any other combination of words using the word "BING!". (TS 86 ll 18-25)

117 In relation to the claim of the applicant in para 3 of the Amended Application, I consider that the undertaking given by the first respondent and the actions of the respondents to date and as anticipated by Mr Cranitch's affidavit of 12 March 2008 answer that claim adequately. As I propose to make an order in terms of that undertaking, in my view an order for delivery up and destruction as sought by the applicant is not warranted (cf Colbeam [1968] HCA 50 ; 122 CLR 25 at 39 per Windeyer J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Community First Credit Union Ltd v Khan (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, 30 August 1995)</tocase>
<text>115 It is not in dispute that the undertaking given by the first respondent in Court through its Counsel is enforceable by order of the Court: O 35 r 11 Federal Court Rules . Indeed courts have, on occasion, declined to grant injunctions in circumstances where an undertaking given by one of the parties is adequate to protect the rights of the other (for example Simos J in Community First Credit Union Ltd v Khan (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, 30 August 1995)). However it is also recognised that, in a proper case, a party may insist upon an injunction notwithstanding an undertaking which has been given (cf Phillimore and Pickford LJJ in Winkle &amp; Co Ltd v Gent &amp; Son (1914) 31 RPC 473 at 479, 480).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Crazy Ron's Communications Pty Limited v Mobileworld Communications Pty Limited [2004] FCAFC 196 ; (2004) 209 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/196.html</AustLII>
<text>30 These principles are well settled and have been applied on numerous occasions by the Full Court of the Federal Court (for example, Starr Partners Pty Limited v Dev Prem Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 42 ; Crazy Ron's Communications Pty Limited v Mobileworld Communications Pty Limited [2004] FCAFC 196 ; (2004) 209 ALR 1).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>CSR Ltd v Resource Capital Australia Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; (2003) 128 FCR 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/279.html</AustLII>
<text>119 In relation to the order sought by the applicant in para 5 of the Amended Application, namely that the first respondent transfer the registration of the domain name www.bing.com , I make the following observations:
 
&#8226; The first respondent, apparently in good faith, acquired the domain name from the United States for the not inconsiderable sum of $US25,000. An order in the nature of that sought by the applicant, which would deprive the first respondent of that asset, is not lightly entertained by the Court.
 
&#8226; While it may be commonplace for companies in Australia to use a ".com" or ".com.au" domain name, the first respondent's domain name is registered in the United States. An order that the first respondent transfer an international domain name to remedy infringement of an Australian trade mark which trade mark is territorial in its operation would in my view require extraordinary circumstances.
 
&#8226; The applicant has relied on a number of cases in support of its application for an order that the first respondent be ordered to transfer the domain name, namely the English Court of Appeal case British Telecommunications PLC v One In A Million Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 289 and the High Court of New Zealand case Oggi Advertising Ltd v McKenzie (1998) 44 IPR 661. Further, Hill J ordered transfer of a domain name in CSR Ltd v Resource Capital Australia Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; (2003) 128 FCR 408. However each of those cases involved cybersquatting, defined by The Australian Concise Oxford Dictionary as "the practice of registering names, especially well-known company or brand names, as Internet domains, in the hope of reselling them at a profit", and which practice is, as Hill J noted in CSR Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; 128 FCR 408 , conduct somewhat suggestive of criminality and fraud. The facts in each of those cases were very different from those in the case before me.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co (1951) 68 RPC 103</tocase>
<text>29 In The Shell Company of Australia Ltd v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Ltd (1963) 109 CLR 407 , Windeyer J considered "substantial identity" in terms of trade marks. His Honour said:
 In considering whether marks are substantially identical they should, I think, be compared side by side, their similarities and differences noted and the importance of these assessed having regard to the essential features of the registered mark and the total impression of resemblance or dissimilarity that emerges from the comparison. "The identification of an essential feature depends", it has been said, "partly on the Court's own judgment and partly on the burden of the evidence that is placed before it": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co (1951) 68 RPC 103 at p 106. Whether there is substantial identity is a question of fact: see Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 per Latham CJ...and Ex parte O'Sullivan; Re Craig (1944) SR (NSW) 291 per Jordan CJ, where the meaning of the expression was considered.

39 The concept of "deceptive similarity" in the context of trade marks was described by Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 415 as follows:
 On the question of deceptive similarity a different comparison must be made from that which is necessary when substantial identity is in question. The marks are not now to be looked at side by side. The issue is not abstract similarity, but deceptive similarity. Therefore the comparison is the familiar one of trade mark law. It is between, on the one hand, the impression based on recollection of the plaintiff's mark that persons of ordinary intelligence and memory would have; and, on the other hand, the impressions that such persons would get from the defendant's television exhibitions. To quote Lord Radcliffe again: "The likelihood of confusion or deception in such cases is not disproved by placing the two marks side by side and demonstrating how small is the chance of error in any customer who places his order for goods with both the marks clearly before him... It is more useful to observe that in most persons the eye is not an accurate recorder of visual detail, and that marks are remembered rather by general impressions or by some significant detail than by any photographic recollection of the whole": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co at 106. And in Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v FS Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said "In deciding this question, the marks ought not, of course, to be compared side by side. An attempt should be made to estimate the effect or impression produced on the mind of potential customers by the mark or device for which the protection of an injunction is sought. The impression or recollection which is carried away and retained is necessarily the basis of any mistaken belief that the challenged mark or device is the same" (at 658)...(at 416). The deceptiveness that is contemplated must result from similarity; but the likelihood of deception must be judged not by the degree of similarity alone, but by the effect of that similarity in all the circumstances.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Enzed Holdings Ltd v Wynthea Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 373 ; (1984) 57 ALR 167</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/373.html</AustLII>
<text>123 In relation to assessment of damages in such cases, in Enzed Holdings Ltd v Wynthea Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 373 ; (1984) 57 ALR 167 at 183 the Full Court observed as follows:
 The principle is clear. If the court finds damage has occurred it must do its best to quantify the loss even if a degree of speculation and guess work is involved. Furthermore, if actual damage is suffered, the award must be for more than nominal damages. We should add that we can see no reason why this principle should not apply in cases under the Trade Practices Act as well as in cases at common law. We emphasize, however, that the principle applies only when the court finds that loss or damage has occurred. It is not enough for a plaintiff merely to show wrongful conduct by the defendant. (emphasis added)

125 In claiming that damages "at large" should be awarded the applicant relied in part on the decision of Jessup J in Review Australia Pty Ltd v Innovative Lifestyle Investments Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 74. However:
 
&#8226; I consider that Review Australia [2008] FCA 74 is distinguishable from this case. In Review Australia Jessup J accepted that the market presence of the respondents' product did bring about some minor dilution of the applicant's reputation for originality (at [30]). In my view there is some evidence of minor and short-lived confusion of a small number of consumers, but no evidence that there has been any dilution of the applicant's reputation in any respect by the market presence of the first respondent. There is, for example, no evidence (unlike in Review Australia ) that any value placed by the applicant on its goods and services has been diminished by the activities of the respondents. I make this observation particularly in light of the completely different activities of the parties and the markets in which they operate.
 
&#8226; In the absence of demonstration by the applicant of any damage, the principles articulated by the Full Court in Enzed Holdings [1984] FCA 373 ; 57 ALR 167 which I have outlined earlier in this judgment militate against an award of damages.
 
&#8226; Although the applicant relies on evidence of Associate Professor Alpert to the effect that, on the balance of probabilities, the use by the respondents of the mark "bing" has caused a diminution in the value of the applicant's trade mark, I accord the witness' evidence no weight in relation to this issue because:
 
 
 o I am not satisfied that Associate Professor Alpert is an expert on valuation of trademarks or intellectual property law. Associate Professor Alpert's expert report dated 21 December 2007 concerned an overview of key issues from a marketing/branding/consumer behaviour perspective, which area appears to be his area of expertise (Introduction para (c) to report);
 o considering the witness' expert report and the contents thereof, I draw the inference that, prior to the hearing, he had not directed his mind to the question of monetary valuation of the trade mark in question. Indeed in referring to "brand values" in his report, Associate Professor Alpert appeared to equate the term with brand aspects rather than any financial concept (note, for example, TS 137 ll 34-44, TS 138 ll 1-4);
 o Associate Professor Alpert's evidence in relation to possible diminution in the value of the applicant's trade mark was theoretical, highly qualified, and not particularly helpful. I refer in particular to: 
 
 
 
 
 &#9642; the fact that, in response to a question from Mr Franklin SC as to whether the witness had any experience in assessing the value of the trade mark, the witness replied: 
 
 
 
 
 
 Not quantitatively, but in what we teach, marketing branding is essential, and we stress the value of the brand. (TS 132 ll 4-6) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 &#9642; the witness merely agreed that he was able to give the Court "opinions as to the general proposition that a brand is a valuable asset" (TS 132 ll 8-10) and that "these situations can be complex" (TS 132 ll 13-15);
 &#9642; in response to a question from Mr Franklin SC as to whether Associate Professor Alpert was able to give the Court expert advice on possible causes of diminution and the value of brand, the witness replied: "I'd like to think so, yes" (TS 132 ll 18);
 &#9642; the witness merely agreed that, assuming that one has a valuable brand that is protected by a registered trademark or a de facto monopoly, one of the reasons that that value might diminish is if someone uses the same or a similar brand in the same market (TS 132 ll 30-33). 
 
 
 
 
 In noting this evidence I intend no criticism of the witness who was endeavouring to be of assistance. However, in my view, the evidence raises not only serious questions as to the witness' expertise in relation to the issue of value of the relevant brand, but also serious doubts as to its probity.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Erven Warnink Besloten Vennootschop v J Townend and Sons (Hull) Ltd (1979) AC 731</tocase>
<text>85 In order to substantiate a claim in passing off the applicant must show:
 
1) A misrepresentation.
 
2) Made by a trader in the course of trade.
 
 
 3) To prospective customers of his or ultimate consumers of goods or services supplied by him.
 4) Which is calculated to injure the business or goodwill of another trader (in the sense that this is a reasonably foreseeable consequence); and
 5) Which causes actual damage to a business or goodwill of a trader by whom the action is brought or (in a quia timet action) will probably do so. 
 

(Lord Diplock in Erven Warnink Besloten Vennootschop v J Townend and Sons (Hull) Ltd (1979) AC 731 at 742; cf Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414 at 443-444 and Re Conagra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ex parte O'Sullivan; Re Craig (1944) SR (NSW) 291</tocase>
<text>29 In The Shell Company of Australia Ltd v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Ltd (1963) 109 CLR 407 , Windeyer J considered "substantial identity" in terms of trade marks. His Honour said:
 In considering whether marks are substantially identical they should, I think, be compared side by side, their similarities and differences noted and the importance of these assessed having regard to the essential features of the registered mark and the total impression of resemblance or dissimilarity that emerges from the comparison. "The identification of an essential feature depends", it has been said, "partly on the Court's own judgment and partly on the burden of the evidence that is placed before it": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co (1951) 68 RPC 103 at p 106. Whether there is substantial identity is a question of fact: see Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 per Latham CJ...and Ex parte O'Sullivan; Re Craig (1944) SR (NSW) 291 per Jordan CJ, where the meaning of the expression was considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fencott v Miller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/12.html</AustLII>
<text>97 Section 75B reflects the intention of Parliament to bring to account natural persons whose conduct brings about the contravention of the law by a corporation: Fencott v Miller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 at 583; Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd v Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd (2001) FCA 1228 at [75] . However because s 75B imports the requirements of the criminal law ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661) , in order to establish accessorial liability pursuant to s 75B the applicant must establish the following:
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person has aided and abetted the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person was aware or ought to have been aware of the facts which gave rise to the contravention of the TPA, and intentionally participated in the contravention ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661) ; and
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person was knowingly concerned in a contravention the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person had actual knowledge of the essential elements of the contravention and intentional participation in it ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/49.html</AustLII>
<text>29 In The Shell Company of Australia Ltd v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Ltd (1963) 109 CLR 407 , Windeyer J considered "substantial identity" in terms of trade marks. His Honour said:
 In considering whether marks are substantially identical they should, I think, be compared side by side, their similarities and differences noted and the importance of these assessed having regard to the essential features of the registered mark and the total impression of resemblance or dissimilarity that emerges from the comparison. "The identification of an essential feature depends", it has been said, "partly on the Court's own judgment and partly on the burden of the evidence that is placed before it": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co (1951) 68 RPC 103 at p 106. Whether there is substantial identity is a question of fact: see Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 per Latham CJ...and Ex parte O'Sullivan; Re Craig (1944) SR (NSW) 291 per Jordan CJ, where the meaning of the expression was considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/181.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Relevant principles in the context of claimed breach of s 52 , as explained by the Full Court in SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 at 14, include the following:
 
&#8226; Initial confusion is sufficient and it is not necessary for confusion to induce or be likely to induce a transaction. Conduct which misleads a customer so that, under some mistaken impression of a trader's connection or affiliation, he or she opens negotiations or invites approaches may be misleading or deceptive even if the true position emerges before the transaction is concluded.
 
&#8226; However, each case depends on its own facts and conduct may not be misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive, notwithstanding that it may engender temporary and commercially irrelevant error (cf Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [56] ; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [41] ).
 
&#8226; Characterisation of conduct as "misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive" involves a judgment of a notional cause and effect relationship between the conduct and putative consumer's state of mind.

71 In addition to these principles, it is also clear that:
 
&#8226; In order to determine whether there has been any contravention of s 52 it is necessary to determine whether or not the conduct complained of amounted to a representation which has or would be likely to lead to a misconception arising in the minds of that section of the public to whom the conduct has been directed: Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22 at [34] .
 
&#8226; Whether or not there is the requirement of some exclusive reputation as an element in the common law tort of passing off, there is no such requirement in relation to Pt V of the TPA. The question is not whether an applicant has shown a sufficient reputation in a particular get-up or name. The question is whether the use of the particular get-up or name by an alleged wrongdoer in relation to his product is likely to mislead or deceive persons familiar with the claimant's product to believe that the two products are associated, having regard to the state of knowledge of consumers in Australia of the claimant's product: Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359 at 419; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [39] .
 
&#8226; Where the relevant conduct involves representations to the public at large or to a section thereof, such as prospective purchasers of a product the respondent markets or proposes to market, the issue is one of identifying the "ordinary" or "reasonable" members of that class of prospective purchasers: Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45 at 84-85.
 
&#8226; It is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of the class of prospective purchasers: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 85. This excludes erroneous or fanciful assumptions: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 86.
 
&#8226; Where a transitory association between the names of two products in the mind of a member of the public is immediately dispelled upon a comparison of those products, this brief association will generally be of no significance and therefore will not give rise to misleading conduct or deception: Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [53] .

76 To that extent I consider that any brief association between the two trade marks in the mind of a member of the public would generally be of no significance, and that a significant number of members of the general public, in fact or by inference, have not been misled or would likely not be misled by the first respondent's use of the trade mark "bing" for the purposes of s 52 TPA (cf Hansen [2008] FCAFC 181 at [46] - [48] ).

77 Accordingly, I consider that the applicant's claim against the first respondent for breach of s 52 TPA fails.

78 In para 15 of the Amended Statement of Claim, the applicant specifically pleaded that, by reason of the first respondent's conduct, the first respondent had contravened and/or threatened and intended to continue to contravene the provisions of s 53 TPA because the first respondent:
 
&#8226; had represented and/or threatened to represent that its business is operated by or under the authority of the applicant whereas its business was not operated by or under the authority of the applicant;
 
&#8226; had represented and/or threatened to represent that its business is operated under or with the sponsorship and/or approval of the applicant whereas its business is not operated with the sponsorship and/or approval of the applicant;
 
&#8226; has represented and/or threatens to represent that the products offered for sale, sold and supplied by the first respondent are offered for sale, sold and supplied by or under the authority of the applicant, whereas such products are not offered for sale, sold, or supplied by or under the authority of the applicant; and
 
&#8226; has represented and/or threatened to represent that the products offered for sale, sold or supplied by the first respondent are offered for sale, sold or supplied under or with the sponsorship and/or approval of the applicant whereas such products were not offered for sale, sold or supplied with the sponsorship or approval of the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/210.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Further, it is clear that:
 
&#8226; The concept in s 10 of the allegedly infringing trade mark being "likely" to deceive or cause confusion does not import a requirement that it be more probable than not that the mark has that effect. The probability of deception or confusion must be finite and non-trivial. There must be a "real tangible danger of its occurring": Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 380.
 
&#8226; A trade mark is likely to cause confusion if the result of its use will be that a number of persons are caused to wonder whether it might not be the case that the two products or closely related products and services come from the same source. It is enough if the ordinary person entertains a reasonable doubt: Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 382.
 
&#8226; Deceptive similarity must be judged by the standards of "ordinary" people keeping in mind the likelihood that they may have only an imperfect recollection of the registered mark: Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215 at 220.
 
&#8226; Deceptiveness flows not only from the degree of similarity itself between the marks, but also from the effect of that similarity considered in relation to the circumstances of the goods, the prospective purchasers and the market covered by the monopoly attached to the registered trade mark: NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26 at 67, cf Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 416.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/170.html</AustLII>
<text>70 Relevant principles in the context of claimed breach of s 52 , as explained by the Full Court in SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 at 14, include the following:
 
&#8226; Initial confusion is sufficient and it is not necessary for confusion to induce or be likely to induce a transaction. Conduct which misleads a customer so that, under some mistaken impression of a trader's connection or affiliation, he or she opens negotiations or invites approaches may be misleading or deceptive even if the true position emerges before the transaction is concluded.
 
&#8226; However, each case depends on its own facts and conduct may not be misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive, notwithstanding that it may engender temporary and commercially irrelevant error (cf Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [56] ; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [41] ).
 
&#8226; Characterisation of conduct as "misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive" involves a judgment of a notional cause and effect relationship between the conduct and putative consumer's state of mind.

71 In addition to these principles, it is also clear that:
 
&#8226; In order to determine whether there has been any contravention of s 52 it is necessary to determine whether or not the conduct complained of amounted to a representation which has or would be likely to lead to a misconception arising in the minds of that section of the public to whom the conduct has been directed: Astrazeneca Pty Ltd v GlaxoSmithKline Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 22 at [34] .
 
&#8226; Whether or not there is the requirement of some exclusive reputation as an element in the common law tort of passing off, there is no such requirement in relation to Pt V of the TPA. The question is not whether an applicant has shown a sufficient reputation in a particular get-up or name. The question is whether the use of the particular get-up or name by an alleged wrongdoer in relation to his product is likely to mislead or deceive persons familiar with the claimant's product to believe that the two products are associated, having regard to the state of knowledge of consumers in Australia of the claimant's product: Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Limited (2007) 159 FCR 359 at 419; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [39] .
 
&#8226; Where the relevant conduct involves representations to the public at large or to a section thereof, such as prospective purchasers of a product the respondent markets or proposes to market, the issue is one of identifying the "ordinary" or "reasonable" members of that class of prospective purchasers: Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; [2000] 202 CLR 45 at 84-85.
 
&#8226; It is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of the class of prospective purchasers: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 85. This excludes erroneous or fanciful assumptions: Campomar [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at 86.
 
&#8226; Where a transitory association between the names of two products in the mind of a member of the public is immediately dispelled upon a comparison of those products, this brief association will generally be of no significance and therefore will not give rise to misleading conduct or deception: Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [53] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>King v Milpurrurru (1996) 66 FCR 474</tocase>
<text>68 As the conduct of the first respondent infringed the applicant's trade mark, in my view it is clear that Mr Cranitch had procured or directed that conduct, and accordingly is similarly liable for such infringement (cf also King v Milpurrurru (1996) 66 FCR 474).

69 In both written and oral submissions the applicant emphasised that, so far as concerned a cause of action under the TPA, its primary claim related to alleged breach of s 52. The applicant in the amended statement of claim claimed that the first respondent had, inter alia , contravened s 52 TPA on the basis of the same conduct on which the applicant alleged infringement of its trade mark.

102 Had I found that the first respondent had engaged in passing off, then in order for tortious liability to be imposed on Mr Cranitch it would have been necessary to establish that Mr Cranitch had conferred on the first respondent his authority to engage in the relevant conduct: King v Milpurrurru 66 FCR 474 at 480-481, 494; Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231 at 245-246; Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54 at 73; Microsoft Corporation v Tyn Electronics Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 63 IPR 137 at 145.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Marc A Hammond Pty Ltd v Papa Carmine Pty Ltd (1973) 28 FLR 160</tocase>
<text>35 The fact that both marks include the same word does not conclusively mean that the marks are "substantially identical": Marc A Hammond Pty Ltd v Papa Carmine Pty Ltd (1973) 28 FLR 160; Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson (1983) 66 FLR 216. Indeed, the fact that the Bing Trade Mark is written in capital letters, and the first respondent's mark is not, suggests that the two marks are not substantially identical: SAP Australia Pty Ltd v Sapient Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1821 ; (1999) 169 ALR 1 at 11.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mark Foys Pty Ltd v TVSN (Pacific) [2000] FCA 1626 ; (2000) 104 FCR 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1626.html</AustLII>
<text>80 In order for the applicant to substantiate its case under s 53 , the applicant needs to establish that, by the use of the confusingly or deceptively similar name and mark ("bing"), the first respondent has represented that it has the necessary connection with the applicant such that a substantial number of members of the public will believe that the first respondent or its services has the sponsorship or approval of the applicant ( 10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shosana Pty Ltd (1987) 79 ALR 299 at 301-302; Mark Foys Pty Ltd v TVSN (Pacific) [2000] FCA 1626 ; (2000) 104 FCR 61 at 77-78).

83 This finding is further supported by the absence of evidence before me that either the applicant or its products have a reputation from which the first respondent would be able to benefit (cf Australian Home Loans Ltd t/as Aussie Home Loans v Phillips [1998] FCA 181 ; (1998) 40 IPR 392 ; Mark Foys Pty Ltd v TVSN (Pacific) Ltd [2000] FCA 1626). Other than evidence of a small number of inquiries temporarily confusing the applicant with the first respondent, there is no evidence that the applicant or its products and service are sufficiently well-known that a substantial number of members of the public, or even a substantial number of members of those sections of the public which are likely to engage either with the applicant or respondent, would be misled in terms of ss 53(c) or 53 (d) TPA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231</tocase>
<text>66 In considering the liability of a director of a company for conduct of the company which has infringed the intellectual property rights of a third party, Lindgren J in Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231 explained:
 The "procured or directed" test, sometimes referred to as the "authorised, procured or directed" test, focuses attention on the relationship between the director's intention and the particular corporate conduct which the law characterises as tortious. What seems to underlie this test is the notion that, necessarily, companies can engage in tortious conduct only through human beings, and, at least ordinarily, where a particular human being involved and responsible to an appropriate extent can be identified, he should, as a matter of policy, be liable... (at 243-244)

67 In my view it is clear on the evidence that:
 
&#8226; Mr Cranitch is the managing director and Chief Executive Officer of the first respondent, and is in effective control of the first respondent;
 
&#8226; Mr Cranitch did the relevant background searches prior to the first respondent using the word "bing" in relation to its services (Cranitch affidavit paras 47-55);
 
&#8226; the decision to use "bing" in relation to the services of the first respondent was made by Mr Cranitch (Cranitch affidavit paras 42-46).

102 Had I found that the first respondent had engaged in passing off, then in order for tortious liability to be imposed on Mr Cranitch it would have been necessary to establish that Mr Cranitch had conferred on the first respondent his authority to engage in the relevant conduct: King v Milpurrurru 66 FCR 474 at 480-481, 494; Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231 at 245-246; Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54 at 73; Microsoft Corporation v Tyn Electronics Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 63 IPR 137 at 145.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54</tocase>
<text>62 In ascertaining whether software is "incidental" to its internet postal service as submitted by the first respondent, it is useful to test the first respondent's hypothesis in this way. Computer hardware cannot properly function without the benefit of software. Yet it could scarcely be said in relation to a computer that software loaded on to a computer hard drive was "incidental" to the computer itself, merely because the software allowed the computer to operate in certain ways. This is clear from the many cases involving claims of infringement of trade mark with respect to software (for example, Microsoft Corporation v PC Club Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1522 and Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54).

102 Had I found that the first respondent had engaged in passing off, then in order for tortious liability to be imposed on Mr Cranitch it would have been necessary to establish that Mr Cranitch had conferred on the first respondent his authority to engage in the relevant conduct: King v Milpurrurru 66 FCR 474 at 480-481, 494; Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231 at 245-246; Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54 at 73; Microsoft Corporation v Tyn Electronics Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 63 IPR 137 at 145.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Microsoft Corporation v PC Club Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1522</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1522.html</AustLII>
<text>62 In ascertaining whether software is "incidental" to its internet postal service as submitted by the first respondent, it is useful to test the first respondent's hypothesis in this way. Computer hardware cannot properly function without the benefit of software. Yet it could scarcely be said in relation to a computer that software loaded on to a computer hard drive was "incidental" to the computer itself, merely because the software allowed the computer to operate in certain ways. This is clear from the many cases involving claims of infringement of trade mark with respect to software (for example, Microsoft Corporation v PC Club Australia Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1522 and Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Microsoft Corporation v Tyn Electronics Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 63 IPR 137</tocase>
<text>102 Had I found that the first respondent had engaged in passing off, then in order for tortious liability to be imposed on Mr Cranitch it would have been necessary to establish that Mr Cranitch had conferred on the first respondent his authority to engage in the relevant conduct: King v Milpurrurru 66 FCR 474 at 480-481, 494; Microsoft Corporation v Auschina Polaris Pty Ltd (1996) 71 FCR 231 at 245-246; Microsoft Corporation v Ezy Loans Pty Ltd (2005) 62 IPR 54 at 73; Microsoft Corporation v Tyn Electronics Pty Ltd (in liq) (2005) 63 IPR 137 at 145.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>MID Sydney Pty Ltd v Australian Tourism Co Ltd (1998) 90 FCR 236</tocase>
<text>50 The respondents cite in support of their case MID Sydney Pty Ltd v Australian Tourism Co Ltd (1998) 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 , both of which are authorities for the proposition that, when comparing services, one should focus primarily on a comparison of the totality of the two services rather than the individual aspects of those services (cf comments in Davison M, Monotti A and Wiseman L, Australian Intellectual Property Law (Cambridge University Press, 2008) p 105). This contention is superficially attractive, however in my view falters on closer examination.

54 In considering the principles articulated in MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 I am of the view that the facts of the case before me do not support an application of those principles.

55 In MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 (so far as material in the present case) the appellant was the registered proprietor of the trade mark "The Chifley Tower", registered for services in class 36 described as " leasing of office and retail space; building and property management ". The respondents proposed to use the word "Chifley" in relation to hotel-related services. The Full Court accepted that the hotel business entailed "management" of hotel properties. However the Court did not accept that hotel-related services therefore were "property management" services within the meaning of class 36. As the Court observed:
 The conduct of an hotel business includes the accommodation of guests, the operation of restaurants and bars (including compliance with the liquor licensing law) and the provision of conference and business facilities and of other services normally offered by hoteliers. These activities cannot ordinarily be described as "property management services". To elaborate on what might be thought an obvious proposition about the ordinary use of language is often not profitable. But the ordinary meaning of property management services - and this is supported by Mr Garnett's evidence about his own business activities - would not encompass the occupation of a property under contract with, or licence or lease from, its owner or lessee in order to manage a business, for the benefit of both the manager and the owner or lessee, conducted on that property. (at 242)

56 Later their Honours continued:
 It was suggested that, if a manager provided services falling within the description "property management services", those services did not lose that character because they formed part of an overall business having features other than the provision of property management services. Certainly it is true that a provider of property management services is no less such a provider because it provides, in the course of its business, other services as well. But where, in this case, services are performed which are incidental to the conduct of the hotel business, it is not correct, in our view, to conclude that Touraust is using the word "Chifley" (or a sign incorporating it) in relation to property management services. (at 242-243)

57 So far as concerns the software provided by the first respondent to its customers bearing the moniker "bing", in my view that software is a "good" which is both severable from the internet postal service, and would in other circumstances be capable of being the subject of a registered trade mark in its own right within Class 9. Similarly, distributing and updating that software are "services" within classes 35 and 42. The software supplied by the first respondent, and the services provided by the first respondent in support thereof, are not, to draw an analogy with MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 , goods or services which lose their features as software because they form part of an overall broader service. The software remains software, which requires distribution and updating, no matter that it is used in connection with the first respondent's internet postal service.

60 In dismissing the appeal before it the Full Court observed that there was some force in the respondent's contention that the trial judge erred, favourably to the appellants, in finding that the respondent's use of "Sapient" was in relation to the same services as the services in respect of which the second appellant's trade mark was registered. Their Honours continued:
 While Sapient Australia provides instruction to its customers on how to use the software solutions it has specifically designed and implemented for them, the provision of that instruction is no more than an incident to the provision of the more broadly based consulting service. Sapient Australia is simply not engaged in the general activity of providing education and training in computer software. Its trade is quite different: see MID Sydney Pty Ltd v Australian Tourism Co Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 561 at 565-8. In the light of the conclusion we have reached it is not necessary to consider whether we should depart from his Honour's finding on this point... (at 11) (emphasis added)

113 Mr Crowe SC submitted that, if the first respondent could not successfully rely on MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 prior to the provision of the undertaking, it could do so following the provision of the undertaking (cf TS 174 ll 28-37). In my view this is not strictly the case. As I have already observed, I do not consider that MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 applies because I consider that the software is not "incidental" to the provision of the internet postal service in the sense used in MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1. However if the software provided by the first respondent does not bear the mark "bing", I do not see how the applicant's trade mark is infringed through the first respondent continuing to call itself "bing" in relation to provision of an internet postal service, which (according to Mr Cranitch's affidavit of 12 March 2008) uses a software called "Easymail". I do not accept that the applicant has a monopoly in the use of the name "bing" as a trade mark in respect of any service, including services which are not the subject of the applicant's registered trade mark, simply because the service requires a person using it to use any form of software. Such a proposition, in my view, takes the applicant's statutory monopoly beyond that sanctioned by the Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/73.html</AustLII>
<text>85 In order to substantiate a claim in passing off the applicant must show:
 
1) A misrepresentation.
 
2) Made by a trader in the course of trade.
 
 
 3) To prospective customers of his or ultimate consumers of goods or services supplied by him.
 4) Which is calculated to injure the business or goodwill of another trader (in the sense that this is a reasonably foreseeable consequence); and
 5) Which causes actual damage to a business or goodwill of a trader by whom the action is brought or (in a quia timet action) will probably do so. 
 

(Lord Diplock in Erven Warnink Besloten Vennootschop v J Townend and Sons (Hull) Ltd (1979) AC 731 at 742; cf Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414 at 443-444 and Re Conagra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302.)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Munday v Carey (1905) 22 RPC 273</tocase>
<text>124 In this case the applicant has not established any damage by way of loss of sales, loss of reputation or, indeed, any impact whatsoever adverse or otherwise on the value of its trade mark or otherwise, from the conduct of the first respondent. I have already observed several times throughout this judgment that the activities and customer base of each of the applicant and the first respondent are completely removed from the other. There is scant evidence as to the reputation of the applicant, including in relation to its registered trade mark, and no evidence that its reputation has been affected. Any confusion between the services offered by the applicant and the first respondent was demonstrated to be short-lived and immediately resolved on inquiry. I consider this to be a case where the applicant has shown wrongful conduct by the respondents, but not substantiated any damage arising from that conduct. Accordingly, there is no evidence to warrant compensatory damages or even nominal damages in the absence of quantification of damages (cf The Sanitas Company Ltd v Condy (1887) 4 RPC 530 ; Munday v Carey (1905) 22 RPC 273 ; Paramount Pictures Corporation v Hasluck (2006) 70 IPR 293 at 302).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26</tocase>
<text>40 Further, it is clear that:
 
&#8226; The concept in s 10 of the allegedly infringing trade mark being "likely" to deceive or cause confusion does not import a requirement that it be more probable than not that the mark has that effect. The probability of deception or confusion must be finite and non-trivial. There must be a "real tangible danger of its occurring": Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 380.
 
&#8226; A trade mark is likely to cause confusion if the result of its use will be that a number of persons are caused to wonder whether it might not be the case that the two products or closely related products and services come from the same source. It is enough if the ordinary person entertains a reasonable doubt: Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 382.
 
&#8226; Deceptive similarity must be judged by the standards of "ordinary" people keeping in mind the likelihood that they may have only an imperfect recollection of the registered mark: Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215 at 220.
 
&#8226; Deceptiveness flows not only from the degree of similarity itself between the marks, but also from the effect of that similarity considered in relation to the circumstances of the goods, the prospective purchasers and the market covered by the monopoly attached to the registered trade mark: NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26 at 67, cf Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 416.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Oggi Advertising Ltd v McKenzie (1998) 44 IPR 661</tocase>
<text>119 In relation to the order sought by the applicant in para 5 of the Amended Application, namely that the first respondent transfer the registration of the domain name www.bing.com , I make the following observations:
 
&#8226; The first respondent, apparently in good faith, acquired the domain name from the United States for the not inconsiderable sum of $US25,000. An order in the nature of that sought by the applicant, which would deprive the first respondent of that asset, is not lightly entertained by the Court.
 
&#8226; While it may be commonplace for companies in Australia to use a ".com" or ".com.au" domain name, the first respondent's domain name is registered in the United States. An order that the first respondent transfer an international domain name to remedy infringement of an Australian trade mark which trade mark is territorial in its operation would in my view require extraordinary circumstances.
 
&#8226; The applicant has relied on a number of cases in support of its application for an order that the first respondent be ordered to transfer the domain name, namely the English Court of Appeal case British Telecommunications PLC v One In A Million Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 289 and the High Court of New Zealand case Oggi Advertising Ltd v McKenzie (1998) 44 IPR 661. Further, Hill J ordered transfer of a domain name in CSR Ltd v Resource Capital Australia Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; (2003) 128 FCR 408. However each of those cases involved cybersquatting, defined by The Australian Concise Oxford Dictionary as "the practice of registering names, especially well-known company or brand names, as Internet domains, in the hope of reselling them at a profit", and which practice is, as Hill J noted in CSR Ltd [2003] FCA 279 ; 128 FCR 408 , conduct somewhat suggestive of criminality and fraud. The facts in each of those cases were very different from those in the case before me.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Paramount Pictures Corporation v Hasluck (2006) 70 IPR 293</tocase>
<text>124 In this case the applicant has not established any damage by way of loss of sales, loss of reputation or, indeed, any impact whatsoever adverse or otherwise on the value of its trade mark or otherwise, from the conduct of the first respondent. I have already observed several times throughout this judgment that the activities and customer base of each of the applicant and the first respondent are completely removed from the other. There is scant evidence as to the reputation of the applicant, including in relation to its registered trade mark, and no evidence that its reputation has been affected. Any confusion between the services offered by the applicant and the first respondent was demonstrated to be short-lived and immediately resolved on inquiry. I consider this to be a case where the applicant has shown wrongful conduct by the respondents, but not substantiated any damage arising from that conduct. Accordingly, there is no evidence to warrant compensatory damages or even nominal damages in the absence of quantification of damages (cf The Sanitas Company Ltd v Condy (1887) 4 RPC 530 ; Munday v Carey (1905) 22 RPC 273 ; Paramount Pictures Corporation v Hasluck (2006) 70 IPR 293 at 302).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Conagra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/159.html</AustLII>
<text>85 In order to substantiate a claim in passing off the applicant must show:
 
1) A misrepresentation.
 
2) Made by a trader in the course of trade.
 
 
 3) To prospective customers of his or ultimate consumers of goods or services supplied by him.
 4) Which is calculated to injure the business or goodwill of another trader (in the sense that this is a reasonably foreseeable consequence); and
 5) Which causes actual damage to a business or goodwill of a trader by whom the action is brought or (in a quia timet action) will probably do so. 
 

(Lord Diplock in Erven Warnink Besloten Vennootschop v J Townend and Sons (Hull) Ltd (1979) AC 731 at 742; cf Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd [1984] HCA 73 ; (1984) 156 CLR 414 at 443-444 and Re Conagra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302.)

86 The applicant is not required to establish proof of an intention to deceive as a necessary ingredient in the cause of action: Conagra [1992] FCA 159 ; 33 FCR 302 at 308.

87 Applying principles relevant to the tort of passing off to the facts of this case, for the following reasons I do not consider that the applicant has substantiated its claim in respect of passing off.

88 First, I have already found that the first respondent's use of the word "bing" did not constitute conduct in breach of ss 52 and 53 TPA. Similarly I do not consider that the first respondent's conduct amounted to a misrepresentation in terms of the applicant's claim for passing off.

89 Second, I do not consider that the evidence has established a sufficient reputation in the applicant in relation to the mark "BING!" such that a substantial number of persons would recognise relevant products or services under that mark as emanating from a single source rather I consider that evidence is scant as to the applicant's reputation in commerce including in relation to the Bing Trade Mark.

90 Third, in light of my finding as to the applicant's reputation, and the complete divergence between the businesses of the parties and their prospective customers, I do not consider that the applicant has established a likelihood of injury to its business from the use of "bing" by the first respondent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd v Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd (2001) FCA 1228</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1228.html</AustLII>
<text>97 Section 75B reflects the intention of Parliament to bring to account natural persons whose conduct brings about the contravention of the law by a corporation: Fencott v Miller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 at 583; Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd v Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd (2001) FCA 1228 at [75] . However because s 75B imports the requirements of the criminal law ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661) , in order to establish accessorial liability pursuant to s 75B the applicant must establish the following:
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person has aided and abetted the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person was aware or ought to have been aware of the facts which gave rise to the contravention of the TPA, and intentionally participated in the contravention ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661) ; and
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person was knowingly concerned in a contravention the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person had actual knowledge of the essential elements of the contravention and intentional participation in it ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661).

98 In this case I consider that, had the applicant substantiated its claims against the first respondent with ss 52 and 53 TPA, Mr Cranitch similarly would have been personally liable pursuant to s 75B. I form this view because:
 
&#8226; the applicant has pleaded actual knowledge by Mr Cranitch of the relevant contraventions of the TPA in the Amended Statement of Claim;
 
&#8226; earlier in this judgment I described the relationship of Mr Cranitch to the first respondent and his management role with the first respondent. In my view it is clear that Mr Cranitch, in his role as managing director, secretary and Chief Executive Officer of the first respondent, and in effective control of the first respondent through an associated company, was the ultimate decision-maker of the first respondent and to that extent had actual knowledge through his personal involvement in conduct of the first respondent (cf Red Bull Australia (2001) FCA 1228 at [75] ).

99 As is clear from para 16A Amended Statement of Claim the applicant claims that the conduct of the first respondent had been carried out by Mr Cranitch. In para 16C Amended Statement of Claim the applicant claims further that Mr Cranitch was a person "involved in the said passing off". The applicant submitted that the activities of Mr Cranitch in:
 
&#8226; making the decision to change the brand from "EasyMail" and looking for a new name;
 
&#8226; conducting all negotiations with the seller of bing.com;
 
&#8226; conducting background inquiries which revealed the existence of the applicant's registered trade mark;
 
formed the basis for a finding that Mr Cranitch was jointly and severally liable with the first respondent.

100 Second, the applicant has pleaded that the conduct of the first respondent took place at the direction of and with the authority of Mr Cranitch, pursuant to a plan or design devised by Mr Cranitch (para 16A Amended Statement of Claim), and that Mr Cranitch has, inter alia , been knowingly concerned in or a party to the conduct of the first respondent (para 16B Amended Statement of Claim). Accordingly the pleadings support a claim by the applicant alleging liability of Mr Cranitch in respect of tortious conduct for which the first respondent is liable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1020.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Further, it is clear that:
 
&#8226; The concept in s 10 of the allegedly infringing trade mark being "likely" to deceive or cause confusion does not import a requirement that it be more probable than not that the mark has that effect. The probability of deception or confusion must be finite and non-trivial. There must be a "real tangible danger of its occurring": Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 380.
 
&#8226; A trade mark is likely to cause confusion if the result of its use will be that a number of persons are caused to wonder whether it might not be the case that the two products or closely related products and services come from the same source. It is enough if the ordinary person entertains a reasonable doubt: Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 382.
 
&#8226; Deceptive similarity must be judged by the standards of "ordinary" people keeping in mind the likelihood that they may have only an imperfect recollection of the registered mark: Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215 at 220.
 
&#8226; Deceptiveness flows not only from the degree of similarity itself between the marks, but also from the effect of that similarity considered in relation to the circumstances of the goods, the prospective purchasers and the market covered by the monopoly attached to the registered trade mark: NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26 at 67, cf Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 416.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Spillers Ltd's Trade Mark Application (1953) 70 RPC 51</tocase>
<text>47 The inquiry in s 120(1) as to whether use of a trade mark concerns goods or services in respect of which a trade mark is registered is simple, involving a comparison between the registered mark used notionally, fairly and normally in respect of any goods and services, with the alleged infringer's actual use. Resolution of the inquiry is a question of fact: Re Spillers Ltd's Trade Mark Application (1953) 70 RPC 51; cf Wal-Mart Stores Inc v Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 596.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Review Australia Pty Ltd v Innovative Lifestyle Investments Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 74</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/74.html</AustLII>
<text>121 The applicant conceded in this case that it had not lead evidence establishing any actual loss of sales revenue arising from the conduct of the first respondent, but instead claimed damages "at large" as awarded in Review Australia Pty Ltd v Innovative Lifestyle Investments Pty Lt d [2008] FCA 74. Damages sought by the applicant were in the sum of $50,000, representing:
 
&#8226; damages on the basis of notional royalty;
 
&#8226; diminution in the value of the applicant's trade mark; and
 
&#8226; loss of reputation.

122 The applicant submitted in this case that factors of assistance to the Court in determining an award of damages at large included:
 
&#8226; the amount of time and effort the applicant had spent developing its reputation;
 
&#8226; that the respondent had had the benefit of using the applicant's asset, namely the Bing trade mark;
 
&#8226; the fact that the respondent had paid $25,000 for the www.bing.com domain name, which was an unlawful use of the applicant's property; and
 
&#8226; the fact that the first respondent pays the owner of the copyright in the first respondent's software the sum of $300,000 per annum.

125 In claiming that damages "at large" should be awarded the applicant relied in part on the decision of Jessup J in Review Australia Pty Ltd v Innovative Lifestyle Investments Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 74. However:
 
&#8226; I consider that Review Australia [2008] FCA 74 is distinguishable from this case. In Review Australia Jessup J accepted that the market presence of the respondents' product did bring about some minor dilution of the applicant's reputation for originality (at [30]). In my view there is some evidence of minor and short-lived confusion of a small number of consumers, but no evidence that there has been any dilution of the applicant's reputation in any respect by the market presence of the first respondent. There is, for example, no evidence (unlike in Review Australia ) that any value placed by the applicant on its goods and services has been diminished by the activities of the respondents. I make this observation particularly in light of the completely different activities of the parties and the markets in which they operate.
 
&#8226; In the absence of demonstration by the applicant of any damage, the principles articulated by the Full Court in Enzed Holdings [1984] FCA 373 ; 57 ALR 167 which I have outlined earlier in this judgment militate against an award of damages.
 
&#8226; Although the applicant relies on evidence of Associate Professor Alpert to the effect that, on the balance of probabilities, the use by the respondents of the mark "bing" has caused a diminution in the value of the applicant's trade mark, I accord the witness' evidence no weight in relation to this issue because:
 
 
 o I am not satisfied that Associate Professor Alpert is an expert on valuation of trademarks or intellectual property law. Associate Professor Alpert's expert report dated 21 December 2007 concerned an overview of key issues from a marketing/branding/consumer behaviour perspective, which area appears to be his area of expertise (Introduction para (c) to report);
 o considering the witness' expert report and the contents thereof, I draw the inference that, prior to the hearing, he had not directed his mind to the question of monetary valuation of the trade mark in question. Indeed in referring to "brand values" in his report, Associate Professor Alpert appeared to equate the term with brand aspects rather than any financial concept (note, for example, TS 137 ll 34-44, TS 138 ll 1-4);
 o Associate Professor Alpert's evidence in relation to possible diminution in the value of the applicant's trade mark was theoretical, highly qualified, and not particularly helpful. I refer in particular to: 
 
 
 
 
 &#9642; the fact that, in response to a question from Mr Franklin SC as to whether the witness had any experience in assessing the value of the trade mark, the witness replied: 
 
 
 
 
 
 Not quantitatively, but in what we teach, marketing branding is essential, and we stress the value of the brand. (TS 132 ll 4-6) 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 &#9642; the witness merely agreed that he was able to give the Court "opinions as to the general proposition that a brand is a valuable asset" (TS 132 ll 8-10) and that "these situations can be complex" (TS 132 ll 13-15);
 &#9642; in response to a question from Mr Franklin SC as to whether Associate Professor Alpert was able to give the Court expert advice on possible causes of diminution and the value of brand, the witness replied: "I'd like to think so, yes" (TS 132 ll 18);
 &#9642; the witness merely agreed that, assuming that one has a valuable brand that is protected by a registered trademark or a de facto monopoly, one of the reasons that that value might diminish is if someone uses the same or a similar brand in the same market (TS 132 ll 30-33). 
 
 
 
 
 In noting this evidence I intend no criticism of the witness who was endeavouring to be of assistance. However, in my view, the evidence raises not only serious questions as to the witness' expertise in relation to the issue of value of the relevant brand, but also serious doubts as to its probity.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c40">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>SAP Australia Pty Ltd v Sapient Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1821 ; (1999) 169 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1821.html</AustLII>
<text>35 The fact that both marks include the same word does not conclusively mean that the marks are "substantially identical": Marc A Hammond Pty Ltd v Papa Carmine Pty Ltd (1973) 28 FLR 160; Angove's Pty Ltd v Johnson (1983) 66 FLR 216. Indeed, the fact that the Bing Trade Mark is written in capital letters, and the first respondent's mark is not, suggests that the two marks are not substantially identical: SAP Australia Pty Ltd v Sapient Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1821 ; (1999) 169 ALR 1 at 11.

46 In reply, the respondents submitted in summary:
 
&#8226; The applicant fixes upon the fact that the first respondent provides, as part of its postal service, software to customers. To accept the applicant's case would be to accept that it has a monopoly in the use of the name "bing" as a trade mark in respect of any service which provides software even though the provision of that software is ancillary to the actual service acquired by customers. This approach has been rejected by the courts.
 
&#8226; Although the first respondent is actually engaged in the provision of postal services , the applicant is trying to elevate those services to that of provision of computer software, relying upon the incidental use of that software in the conduct of the first respondent's business. That is an incorrect approach and contrary to binding authority on this Court.
 
&#8226; This case is very similar to that in SAP Australia Pty Ltd v Sapient Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 1821 ; (1999) 169 ALR 1. 
 
&#8226; The applicant is trying to distract the court by the fact that the services or goods offered by the parties might have some features in common. The Court should not be distracted by the fact that, in part, the services or goods provided by the first respondent involves the provision of software to its customers.
 
&#8226; In any event, on the morning of the second day of the trial the first respondent provided an open undertaking to the Court that it would not use the word "bing" either by itself or in combination with any other words in directly referring to the software it provides to its customers.

50 The respondents cite in support of their case MID Sydney Pty Ltd v Australian Tourism Co Ltd (1998) 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 , both of which are authorities for the proposition that, when comparing services, one should focus primarily on a comparison of the totality of the two services rather than the individual aspects of those services (cf comments in Davison M, Monotti A and Wiseman L, Australian Intellectual Property Law (Cambridge University Press, 2008) p 105). This contention is superficially attractive, however in my view falters on closer examination.

54 In considering the principles articulated in MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 I am of the view that the facts of the case before me do not support an application of those principles.

58 The respondents also submitted that the facts of this case parallel those in SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1. In SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 the first appellant, a subsidiary of a German company (the second appellant), had traded in Australia since 1989, and distributed computer software products of the second appellant in Australia. The first appellant had also established a training college under the name "Sapient College". The second appellant had registered in Australia the trade marks SAP and SAPIENT COLLEGE in respect of Class 41:
 Education; providing of training; cultural activities; the foregoing including post graduate, further and advanced education and training in business, business management, management, business administration, computers, computer peripherals and computer software, information technology, intellectual property, telecommunications, science and technology, medical technology and science, technology management, stress management and therapy, personal development, lifestyle, relaxation and remedial techniques.

59 The respondent was incorporated in Australia in 1998 and provided custom-designed computer systems for clients and some ancillary training. The appellants alleged infringement by the respondent of the registered trade marks, misleading or deceptive conduct in contravention of s 52 TPA, and passing off. The action at first instance was dismissed.

61 Where the analogy between these proceedings and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 breaks down is that while the Full Court accepted in SAP Australia that "broadly based consulting services" could include supplementary training as an adjunct to the provision of custom designed computer systems for clients, in this case it does not follow that software provided by the first respondent is no more than an incident to the provision of its service. As I noted earlier, the software used by the first respondent is a product in its own right the copyright therein is owned by a third party, and the first respondent has exclusive distribution rights (TS 66 ll 12-13). The first respondent provides the software even though, as Mr Cranitch conceded during cross-examination, the first respondent has some clients who do not use the software, but send to the first respondent documents in the form of PDF files, word documents and publisher documents (TS 71 ll 40-41). The software and associated services are an important part of the first respondent's internet postal service.

70 Relevant principles in the context of claimed breach of s 52 , as explained by the Full Court in SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1 at 14, include the following:
 
&#8226; Initial confusion is sufficient and it is not necessary for confusion to induce or be likely to induce a transaction. Conduct which misleads a customer so that, under some mistaken impression of a trader's connection or affiliation, he or she opens negotiations or invites approaches may be misleading or deceptive even if the true position emerges before the transaction is concluded.
 
&#8226; However, each case depends on its own facts and conduct may not be misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive, notwithstanding that it may engender temporary and commercially irrelevant error (cf Knight v Beyond Properties Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 170 at [56] ; Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181 at [41] ).
 
&#8226; Characterisation of conduct as "misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive" involves a judgment of a notional cause and effect relationship between the conduct and putative consumer's state of mind.

113 Mr Crowe SC submitted that, if the first respondent could not successfully rely on MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 prior to the provision of the undertaking, it could do so following the provision of the undertaking (cf TS 174 ll 28-37). In my view this is not strictly the case. As I have already observed, I do not consider that MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 applies because I consider that the software is not "incidental" to the provision of the internet postal service in the sense used in MID Sydney 90 FCR 236 and SAP Australia [1999] FCA 1821 ; 169 ALR 1. However if the software provided by the first respondent does not bear the mark "bing", I do not see how the applicant's trade mark is infringed through the first respondent continuing to call itself "bing" in relation to provision of an internet postal service, which (according to Mr Cranitch's affidavit of 12 March 2008) uses a software called "Easymail". I do not accept that the applicant has a monopoly in the use of the name "bing" as a trade mark in respect of any service, including services which are not the subject of the applicant's registered trade mark, simply because the service requires a person using it to use any form of software. Such a proposition, in my view, takes the applicant's statutory monopoly beyond that sanctioned by the Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c41">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1955/15.html</AustLII>
<text>40 Further, it is clear that:
 
&#8226; The concept in s 10 of the allegedly infringing trade mark being "likely" to deceive or cause confusion does not import a requirement that it be more probable than not that the mark has that effect. The probability of deception or confusion must be finite and non-trivial. There must be a "real tangible danger of its occurring": Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 380.
 
&#8226; A trade mark is likely to cause confusion if the result of its use will be that a number of persons are caused to wonder whether it might not be the case that the two products or closely related products and services come from the same source. It is enough if the ordinary person entertains a reasonable doubt: Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 382.
 
&#8226; Deceptive similarity must be judged by the standards of "ordinary" people keeping in mind the likelihood that they may have only an imperfect recollection of the registered mark: Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215 at 220.
 
&#8226; Deceptiveness flows not only from the degree of similarity itself between the marks, but also from the effect of that similarity considered in relation to the circumstances of the goods, the prospective purchasers and the market covered by the monopoly attached to the registered trade mark: NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26 at 67, cf Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 416.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c42">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Starr Partners Pty Limited v Dev Prem Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 42</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/42.html</AustLII>
<text>30 These principles are well settled and have been applied on numerous occasions by the Full Court of the Federal Court (for example, Starr Partners Pty Limited v Dev Prem Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 42 ; Crazy Ron's Communications Pty Limited v Mobileworld Communications Pty Limited [2004] FCAFC 196 ; (2004) 209 ALR 1).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c43">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 30 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/157.html</AustLII>
<text>101 To the extent that the applicant contends that Mr Cranitch is jointly liable with the first respondent for passing off, I would not consider the claim of the applicant substantiated by the evidence even had I considered the activities of the first respondent constituted passing off. Although it was clear from the evidence that Mr Cranitch was significantly involved in the activities of the first respondent and the development of the first respondent's trade mark, all activities of the first respondent in connection with its trade mark were carried out by the first respondent. I can identify no basis for asserting that Mr Cranitch himself passed off the first respondent's services as being those of the applicant or as being in any other way associated with the applicant. Involvement by Mr Cranitch in relation to management of the first respondent, and Mr Cranitch's involvement in decision-making in relation to development of the first respondent's "bing" trade mark, do not, in my view, amount to passing off (cf observations of the Full Court in Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 30 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 at 399).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c44">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Sanitas Company Ltd v Condy (1887) 4 RPC 530</tocase>
<text>124 In this case the applicant has not established any damage by way of loss of sales, loss of reputation or, indeed, any impact whatsoever adverse or otherwise on the value of its trade mark or otherwise, from the conduct of the first respondent. I have already observed several times throughout this judgment that the activities and customer base of each of the applicant and the first respondent are completely removed from the other. There is scant evidence as to the reputation of the applicant, including in relation to its registered trade mark, and no evidence that its reputation has been affected. Any confusion between the services offered by the applicant and the first respondent was demonstrated to be short-lived and immediately resolved on inquiry. I consider this to be a case where the applicant has shown wrongful conduct by the respondents, but not substantiated any damage arising from that conduct. Accordingly, there is no evidence to warrant compensatory damages or even nominal damages in the absence of quantification of damages (cf The Sanitas Company Ltd v Condy (1887) 4 RPC 530 ; Munday v Carey (1905) 22 RPC 273 ; Paramount Pictures Corporation v Hasluck (2006) 70 IPR 293 at 302).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c45">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>The Shell Company of Australia Ltd v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Ltd (1963) 109 CLR 407</tocase>
<text>29 In The Shell Company of Australia Ltd v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Ltd (1963) 109 CLR 407 , Windeyer J considered "substantial identity" in terms of trade marks. His Honour said:
 In considering whether marks are substantially identical they should, I think, be compared side by side, their similarities and differences noted and the importance of these assessed having regard to the essential features of the registered mark and the total impression of resemblance or dissimilarity that emerges from the comparison. "The identification of an essential feature depends", it has been said, "partly on the Court's own judgment and partly on the burden of the evidence that is placed before it": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co (1951) 68 RPC 103 at p 106. Whether there is substantial identity is a question of fact: see Fraser Henleins Pty Ltd v Cody [1945] HCA 49 ; (1945) 70 CLR 100 per Latham CJ...and Ex parte O'Sullivan; Re Craig (1944) SR (NSW) 291 per Jordan CJ, where the meaning of the expression was considered.

39 The concept of "deceptive similarity" in the context of trade marks was described by Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 415 as follows:
 On the question of deceptive similarity a different comparison must be made from that which is necessary when substantial identity is in question. The marks are not now to be looked at side by side. The issue is not abstract similarity, but deceptive similarity. Therefore the comparison is the familiar one of trade mark law. It is between, on the one hand, the impression based on recollection of the plaintiff's mark that persons of ordinary intelligence and memory would have; and, on the other hand, the impressions that such persons would get from the defendant's television exhibitions. To quote Lord Radcliffe again: "The likelihood of confusion or deception in such cases is not disproved by placing the two marks side by side and demonstrating how small is the chance of error in any customer who places his order for goods with both the marks clearly before him... It is more useful to observe that in most persons the eye is not an accurate recorder of visual detail, and that marks are remembered rather by general impressions or by some significant detail than by any photographic recollection of the whole": de Cordova v Vick Chemical Co at 106. And in Australian Woollen Mills Ltd v FS Walton &amp; Co Ltd [1937] HCA 51 ; (1937) 58 CLR 641 Dixon and McTiernan JJ said "In deciding this question, the marks ought not, of course, to be compared side by side. An attempt should be made to estimate the effect or impression produced on the mind of potential customers by the mark or device for which the protection of an injunction is sought. The impression or recollection which is carried away and retained is necessarily the basis of any mistaken belief that the challenged mark or device is the same" (at 658)...(at 416). The deceptiveness that is contemplated must result from similarity; but the likelihood of deception must be judged not by the degree of similarity alone, but by the effect of that similarity in all the circumstances.

40 Further, it is clear that:
 
&#8226; The concept in s 10 of the allegedly infringing trade mark being "likely" to deceive or cause confusion does not import a requirement that it be more probable than not that the mark has that effect. The probability of deception or confusion must be finite and non-trivial. There must be a "real tangible danger of its occurring": Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 380.
 
&#8226; A trade mark is likely to cause confusion if the result of its use will be that a number of persons are caused to wonder whether it might not be the case that the two products or closely related products and services come from the same source. It is enough if the ordinary person entertains a reasonable doubt: Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd [1955] HCA 15 ; (1954) 91 CLR 529 at 594-595; Registrar of Trade Marks v Woolworths Ltd [1999] FCA 1020 ; (1999) 93 FCR 365 at 382.
 
&#8226; Deceptive similarity must be judged by the standards of "ordinary" people keeping in mind the likelihood that they may have only an imperfect recollection of the registered mark: Johnson &amp; Johnson v Kalnin [1993] FCA 210 ; (1993) 114 ALR 215 at 220.
 
&#8226; Deceptiveness flows not only from the degree of similarity itself between the marks, but also from the effect of that similarity considered in relation to the circumstances of the goods, the prospective purchasers and the market covered by the monopoly attached to the registered trade mark: NSW Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-Operative Company Ltd (1989) 14 IPR 26 at 67, cf Windeyer J in Shell 109 CLR 407 at 416.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c46">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wal-Mart Stores Inc v Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 596</tocase>
<text>47 The inquiry in s 120(1) as to whether use of a trade mark concerns goods or services in respect of which a trade mark is registered is simple, involving a comparison between the registered mark used notionally, fairly and normally in respect of any goods and services, with the alleged infringer's actual use. Resolution of the inquiry is a question of fact: Re Spillers Ltd's Trade Mark Application (1953) 70 RPC 51; cf Wal-Mart Stores Inc v Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 596.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c47">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wingate Marketing Pty Ltd v Levi Strauss &amp; Co (1994) 121 ALR 191</tocase>
<text>34 In considering the Bing Trade Mark and the respondents' varied uses of "bing" side by side, an obvious similarity is that the trade marks of both the applicant and the first respondent include the word "bing". It is also not in dispute that both parties pronounce the word "bing" in the same way, which is relevant in considering the similarity or otherwise of the marks (Gummow J in Wingate Marketing Pty Ltd v Levi Strauss &amp; Co (1994) 121 ALR 191 at 229).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c48">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Winkle &amp; Co Ltd v Gent &amp; Son (1914) 31 RPC 473</tocase>
<text>115 It is not in dispute that the undertaking given by the first respondent in Court through its Counsel is enforceable by order of the Court: O 35 r 11 Federal Court Rules . Indeed courts have, on occasion, declined to grant injunctions in circumstances where an undertaking given by one of the parties is adequate to protect the rights of the other (for example Simos J in Community First Credit Union Ltd v Khan (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, 30 August 1995)). However it is also recognised that, in a proper case, a party may insist upon an injunction notwithstanding an undertaking which has been given (cf Phillimore and Pickford LJJ in Winkle &amp; Co Ltd v Gent &amp; Son (1914) 31 RPC 473 at 479, 480).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c49">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yeatman v L Homberger &amp; Co (1912) 29 RPC 645</tocase>
<text>114 The first respondent's undertaking obviously does not address any past conduct which may have infringed the applicant's trade mark. However, other than continuing to call itself "bing" in relation to provision of internet postal services where the mark "bing" does not appear on any software or in any documentary references to software, and which in my view constitutes neither infringement of the applicant's trade mark nor misrepresentation in terms of the TPA or passing off, the applicant has not demonstrated conduct of the first respondent having an on-going effect for which the undertaking provided is not an answer in terms of the applicant's contentions regarding use of the trade mark and software (contrast, for example, Yeatman v L Homberger &amp; Co (1912) 29 RPC 645). I consider that the terms of the undertaking provided by the first respondent are adequate to protect any rights of the applicant has in relation to this matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c50">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/65.html</AustLII>
<text>97 Section 75B reflects the intention of Parliament to bring to account natural persons whose conduct brings about the contravention of the law by a corporation: Fencott v Miller [1983] HCA 12 ; (1983) 152 CLR 570 at 583; Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd v Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd (2001) FCA 1228 at [75] . However because s 75B imports the requirements of the criminal law ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661) , in order to establish accessorial liability pursuant to s 75B the applicant must establish the following:
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person has aided and abetted the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person was aware or ought to have been aware of the facts which gave rise to the contravention of the TPA, and intentionally participated in the contravention ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661) ; and
 
&#8226; in circumstances where the applicant contends that a person was knowingly concerned in a contravention the applicant must demonstrate that the relevant person had actual knowledge of the essential elements of the contravention and intentional participation in it ( Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; 158 CLR 661).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c51">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shosana Pty Ltd (1987) 79 ALR 299</tocase>
<text>80 In order for the applicant to substantiate its case under s 53 , the applicant needs to establish that, by the use of the confusingly or deceptively similar name and mark ("bing"), the first respondent has represented that it has the necessary connection with the applicant such that a substantial number of members of the public will believe that the first respondent or its services has the sponsorship or approval of the applicant ( 10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shosana Pty Ltd (1987) 79 ALR 299 at 301-302; Mark Foys Pty Ltd v TVSN (Pacific) [2000] FCA 1626 ; (2000) 104 FCR 61 at 77-78).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>