<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Devere Holdings Pty Ltd v Lopez [2008] FCA 1091 (24 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1091.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd v Phillip Morris Inc (1981) 148 CLR 170 </tocase>
<text>7 The proposed appeal concerns a point of practice and procedure. There is an important distinction between the exercise of the discretion to grant leave to appeal in such a case and one which involves determining a substantive right: D&eacute;cor Corporation at 400. In so finding, the Court was reflecting the warning reaffirmed by the High Court in Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd v Phillip Morris Inc (1981) 148 CLR 170 at 177 that a tight rein should be kept on such appeals. That warning has been echoed many times by this Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Custom Credit Holdings Ltd v Creighton Investments Pty Ltd (Unreported NSWSC, 7 March 1985, BC8500943) </tocase>
<text>27 The applicants submit that the value of a benefit is not relevant when determining if conduct was ratified, and that what is important is the adoption or acceptance of the validity of an act done: Custom Credit Holdings Ltd v Creighton Investments Pty Ltd (Unreported NSWSC, 7 March 1985, BC8500943) at 25 per Clarke J. They also submit that a detriment that gives rise to an estoppel does not need to be valued: Hornsby Shire Council v Yifta Pty Ltd (Unreported, NSWSC, 17 March 1993, BC9301992) at 24 per Young J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/70.html</AustLII>
<text>9 It is trite that particulars constitute the details of a statement of a party's case sufficiently clear to allow the opponent a fair opportunity to meet it: Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658 at 664.

10 Paragraph 18 of the statement of claim alleges that the consideration which Devere gave for the transfer of the Andonys' undivided one-third share of the Land was at most $45,000. Paragraph 5 of the defence denies this allegation but then pleads that the consideration comprised the benefits accruing to the Andonys under and pursuant to what are described as the First Agreement or alternatively the November 2000 Agreement.

11 The particulars of para 5 of the defence which were ordered are as follows: 
 Particulars of all of the benefits alleged to have accrued to each of Mr Andony and Mrs Andony under and pursuant to 
 
 (a) the First Agreement;
 (b) the November 2000 Agreement; 
 
 by identifying in respect of each and every benefit: 
 
 (c) the nature of the benefit; 
 (d) the monetary value of the benefit; 
 (e) when and how the benefit was accrued to each of Mr Andony and Mrs Andony;
 (f) by whom the benefit was provided.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/655.html</AustLII>
<text>6 The general approach to such an application is to consider whether the decision is attended with sufficient doubt to warrant its reconsideration and whether substantial injustice would result if leave were not granted, supposing that the decision was wrong: D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397 at 398-9.

7 The proposed appeal concerns a point of practice and procedure. There is an important distinction between the exercise of the discretion to grant leave to appeal in such a case and one which involves determining a substantive right: D&eacute;cor Corporation at 400. In so finding, the Court was reflecting the warning reaffirmed by the High Court in Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd v Phillip Morris Inc (1981) 148 CLR 170 at 177 that a tight rein should be kept on such appeals. That warning has been echoed many times by this Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hornsby Shire Council v Yifta Pty Ltd (Unreported, NSWSC, 17 March 1993, BC9301992)</tocase>
<text>27 The applicants submit that the value of a benefit is not relevant when determining if conduct was ratified, and that what is important is the adoption or acceptance of the validity of an act done: Custom Credit Holdings Ltd v Creighton Investments Pty Ltd (Unreported NSWSC, 7 March 1985, BC8500943) at 25 per Clarke J. They also submit that a detriment that gives rise to an estoppel does not need to be valued: Hornsby Shire Council v Yifta Pty Ltd (Unreported, NSWSC, 17 March 1993, BC9301992) at 24 per Young J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Verge v Devere Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] FMCA 591</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/591.html</AustLII>
<text>12 The applicants submit that the error below was the finding that, in para 5 of their defence, they had put the "consideration" for the sale, the "benefits" comprising the consideration, and the "benefits accruing" under both the "First Agreement", alternatively the "November 2000 Agreement" in issue and, accordingly, must provide the detailed particulars demanded by the Trustees: Verge v Devere Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] FMCA 591 at [23] and [24].

13 The applicant submits that it is the Trustees who bear the onus of proving each of the elements of s 120(1) of the Act which renders void, relevantly, a transfer of property where "the transferee gave consideration of less value than the market value of the property". In particular they submit that the Trustees must plead and prove:
 
 
 (a) the consideration that Devere gave to the Andonys; 
 
 (b) the value of that consideration; and 
 
 (c) the market value of the Andonys' undivided one third interest in the Land.

14 The applicants contend that whilst paragraph 5 denies the allegation that the consideration was $45,000 and pleads what the consideration actually was, it does not answer an allegation by the Trustees that the identified consideration pleaded in para 18 of the statement of claim had a particular value and then assert that it had a different value. It merely puts in issue, the applicants say, the threshold element to the Trustees' claim by asserting, in effect, that the transaction was wider than is alleged by the Trustees in para 18 of the statement of claim. In summary, the applicants' defence is that there was additional consideration, not that there was additional consideration of some particular value.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>