<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Green v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 125 (20 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/125.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Capital Territory v Alphaone Pty Ltd (1994) 49 FCR 576</tocase>
<text>38 In my view, there was no obligation on the part of Tribunal to inform Mr Green of its views regarding his credibility and the weight which it was prepared to give his evidence. The Tribunal's conclusion as to his credibility was part of its reasoning and thought processes in relation to the determination of the whole matter, and thus was not required to be put to Mr Green: see Commissioner for the Australian Capital Territory Revenue v Alphaone Pty Ltd (1994) 49 FCR 576 at 591-592. Although it was for the Tribunal to weigh Mr Green's evidence and in so doing form a view as to his credibility, the reasoning involved in this task did not need to be signalled.

39 Secondly, it is said that the Tribunal ought to have sought further evidence from persons who made statements but were not called to give oral evidence. The Tribunal observed in its reasons at [66] that:
 
 'It was notable that none of the people most closely involved with the applicant his father, his son, his step-mother, his sister and his de facto gave evidence at the hearing. [His son] and [his de facto] apparently attended the hearing, however.'

40 There was no requirement, in my view, that the Tribunal seek further evidence from these persons. If Mr Green wished to adduce evidence from these persons, he had a full opportunity to do so. Given that Mr Green chose not to call them, it is not appropriate to expect the Tribunal to seek any further evidence on the basis that they may be able to provide some useful information.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/8.html</AustLII>
<text>41 Although the observation of the Tribunal at [66] concerning Mr Green's failure to call certain witnesses could be construed adversely to Mr Green's case, there is no indication that those persons could have provided material to assist his case. On the other hand, however, having regard to the fact that the Tribunal's proceedings are inquisitorial in nature and the observations in Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 at 308 are not applicable, there is no indication in this case that any particular adverse inference was drawn or suggested on the basis of the fact that the witnesses did not give evidence orally and that the omission to ask them to do so rested with Mr Green (and not on the Tribunal).

42 Finally, it is said that there were three findings of fact made by the Tribunal for which there was no evidentiary basis. This submission relies on an interpretation of the Tribunal's reasons at [109]:
 
 'The applicant has an aunt (his father's sister) in England, though he says he does not remember her. While his aunt could not necessarily be expected to welcome the applicant into her home, it is not improbable that she would be able to give him some guidance on becoming re-established in the United Kingdom. The skills he has developed as a painter would be as useful to him there as they are here, and indeed the larger market might be to his advantage. He has no business ties within Australia. Nothing in the evidence suggests that he would be unable to obtain [the drug facilitating his rehabilitation] in the United Kingdom and thereby continue his drug rehabilitation.'

43 When closely examined, it is apparent that each of the views expressed by the Tribunal at [109] is in tentative and speculative terms and that they are not expressed as findings of fact. The general effect of the observations is that there is simply no evidence to support findings to the contrary. So far as the observation in relation to Mr Green's aunt is concerned, this is a general statement which does not appear to have been given any particular weight. The statements in this paragraph really amount on their face to an expression of views which were open to the Tribunal in the circumstances of this case.

44 I therefore do not consider that there was any failure by the Tribunal to provide procedural fairness in this case.

45 For the reasons which I have given above in relation to the need to consider mitigating factors pursuant to paragraph 2.8 of the Direction, this application is granted and the matter is remitted to the Tribunal for determination in accordance with these reasons. As the second respondent filed a submitting appearance, it is appropriate that the costs of the application are borne by the first respondent.

 I certify that the preceding forty-five (45) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tamberlin. 


 Associate:

Dated: 20 February 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: Ms S. Higgins 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Ebsworth &amp; Ebsworth Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms B. Nolan 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 25 January 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 February 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/125.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rokobatini v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 1238 ; (1999) 90 FCR 583</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1238.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Section 499(1) of the Act provides that the Minister may give written directions to a person or body having functions or powers under the Act if the directions are about the performance of those functions or the exercise of those powers. Section 499(2A) mandates that the relevant person or body (which includes the Tribunal: see Rokobatini v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 1238 ; (1999) 90 FCR 583 at 591 (per Katz J)) must comply with such a direction. The power of the Minister under s 499(1) is limited by s 499(2), which provides that a direction must be consistent with the Act and regulations promulgated pursuant to it.

10 On 23 August 2001, pursuant to s 499(1), the Minister issued Direction No 21 entitled Visa Refusal and Cancellation under section 501 ("the Direction"). Part 2 of the Direction concerns the exercise of the discretion under s 501(2) once a decision has been made that the character test is not satisfied, a matter which is conceded by Mr Green in this case. Part 2 provides that, when exercising the discretion, "decision-makers must have regard to" three primary considerations, namely, the protection of the Australian community, the expectations of the Australian community and, if relevant, the best interests of any children involved. Other considerations, which are not "primary considerations" and are not mandatory, include the effects on the visa-holder's family, evidence of rehabilitation, the likelihood of breaching or evading obligations under a legal or other ongoing matter, the duration of the proposed stay in Australia and whether the visa is permanent or temporary.

11 Paragraph 2.5 of the Direction identifies three factors which are relevant to the protection of the Australian community. They are the seriousness and nature of the conduct, the likelihood of recidivism and whether visa cancellation would provide general deterrence.

12 Of importance to this case is the process laid down by the Direction for considering "the seriousness and the nature of the conduct of a non-citizen". Paragraph 2.6 outlines what the Minister views as serious offences, and paragraph 2.7 states that the sentence imposed for a crime is an appropriate indicator of the seriousness of the offender's conduct against the community. Paragraph 2.8 then provides that decision-makers must take into account certain mitigating considerations:
 
 'When exercising discretion, decision-makers must also take the following factors into account as relevant considerations: 
 
 
 
 (a) any relevant factors provided by the non-citizen as mitigating factors ; 
 
 
 
 (b) the offence is not classified as an offence in Australia. ... 
 
 
 
 (c) a lighter sentence would be incurred in Australia for a similar offence; or 
 
 
 
 (d) the non-citizen has been pardoned' 
 
 (Emphasis added.)

13 The Tribunal's reasons comprehensively set out at [10]-[76] the chronology of facts and the evidence relevant to this matter. The Tribunal summarised Mr Green's personal history, detailed his criminal record in Australia since 1978, and described the events leading up to the cancellation of his visa by the Minister and his detention on 16 August 2005.

14 The Tribunal's reasons summarised the evidence led by Mr Green, most of which pertained to Mr Green's explanation of his personal history, how and why he came to possess a criminal record, and also some mitigating circumstances. His reasons, in short, were that he had led a life of few opportunities, and that he had unfortunately been surrounded by "bad kids, then bad adults". The Tribunal described Mr Green's time in prison, and noted his evidence which stated that he was not a "vicious outlaw type of criminal", but rather more of the "Robin Hood" type. The Tribunal also discussed Mr Green's developing drug addiction, and the crimes he committed to support that addiction, as well as the rehabilitation which Mr Green had sought in art and family.

15 The Tribunal found Mr Green's evidence unsatisfactory in certain respects. It concluded at [53] that although Mr Green's evidence should not "be entirely discarded, his tendency towards exaggeration and opportunistic fabrication dictates a certain caution in evaluating it." An observation as to the need for caution in this context does not mean that Mr Green's evidence was rejected out of hand.

16 After making this finding, the Tribunal addressed the psychological and other evidence before it. Several psychological assessments of Mr Green were before the Tribunal and, although they appeared to "differ in material respects", the Tribunal found at [64]:
 
 'It is difficult to derive much assistance from this part of the evidence, other than to conclude that the applicant has psychological problems, whether produced by drug abuse, incarceration, an unhappy childhood or a combination of all three. He has not to date been able to shake off anti-social or self-destructive patterns of behaviour but is not a hopeless case. He could be rehabilitated and his development of his artistic capacities, as well as his [drug rehabilitation] program are positive steps, as is the possibility of employment and of continuing his relationship with [a female friend].'

17 The Tribunal then summarised other evidence provided by friends and family of Mr Green, which detailed various matters of personal concern, including the likelihood of Mr Green obtaining employment after his release from prison, continuing an intimate relationship with a female friend, and succeeding in an artistic career.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>