<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Luck v Chief Executive Officer of Centrelink (includes corrigendum dated 20 March 2009) [2008] FCA 1879 (10 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1879.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen [1984] FCA 176 ; (1984) 3 FCR 344</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/176.html</AustLII>
<text>When an application for an extension of time to commence a proceeding under the ADJR Act is made the Court has an unfettered discretion. There is a large number of potentially relevant considerations which, depending upon the circumstances, may need to be balanced in determining how the discretion should be exercised. Many of these were collected by Wilcox J in his judgment in Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen [1984] FCA 176 ; (1984) 3 FCR 344 at 348-9.

I am prepared to assume, in Ms Luck's favour that she did not make timely applications because of ignorance of her legal rights and because of health problems. She has also been occupied with a good deal of litigation in this Court and elsewhere. I am also prepared to assume that the respondents would suffer no prejudice were an extension of time to be granted.

On the other hand, it is necessary to have regard to the considerable delay involved and the merits of the principal application. The factor which, however, weighs most heavily against the granting of an extension of time is that the two decisions which are the subject of the objections to competency were both expressed to be operative for only twelve months and three months respectively. Their effect is spent. Any attempt to deal with the alleged failure to make a decision to review the second decision would, for the same reason, serve no useful purpose. No useful purpose would be served at this stage by quashing these decisions or declaring them to be null and void. The June 2008 decision, in respect of which a timely application was made, was in substantially the same terms as the two spent decisions. Ms Luck relies on the same grounds to challenge all three decisions. She will not, therefore, be deprived of the opportunity of testing the legal validity of the restrictions placed on her in relation to her dealings with Centrelink.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>