<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Burton v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 1464 (2 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1464.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Citizenship v Le [2007] FCA 1318 ; (2007) 164 FCR 151</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1318.html</AustLII>
<text>24 It is well-established that the Tribunal has no general obligation to initiate enquiries or to make out an applicant's case for him or her: Minister for Immigration and Citizenship v Le [2007] FCA 1318 ; (2007) 164 FCR 151 at [60] per Kenny J. Her Honour observed that there is authority for the proposition that in certain "rare or exceptional circumstances", a failure by the Tribunal to enquire may render the decision manifestly unreasonable in the Wednesbury sense.

26 The seminal authority for the principle that a failure to enquire may, in exceptional circumstances, invalidate a decision is Prasad v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs [1985] FCA 47 ; (1985) 6 FCR 155. Kenny J referred to this in Le at [64].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S154/2002 [2003] HCA 60 ; (2003) 201 ALR 437</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/60.html</AustLII>
<text>31 However, it seems to me that a failure to "test" the later evidence by questioning the witness cannot be equated with a failure to gather factual material of the kind contemplated by the principle stated in Prasad . This is borne out by the observations of Gummow and Heydon JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S154/2002 (2003) 3"> [2003] HCA 60 ; 201 ALR 437 at [57] .

32 Their Honours pointed out in Applicant S154/2002 that the rule in Browne v Dunn has no application to proceedings in an administrative tribunal; the tribunal member conducting an enquiry is not an adversarial cross-examiner, but an inquisitor who is obliged to be fair. In my view it follows that, ordinarily, there can be no duty to use the Tribunal's powers to test one side's assertions as against the other's.

33 This was especially so in the present case where the circumstances relating to the actual marriage ceremony, including the short time the parties had known each other, raised doubts about its genuineness. Moreover, the Tribunal found that Mrs Burton was not a credible witness.

34 There was evidence before the Tribunal that Mr Vikash Burton sponsored his wife's application for a spouse visa and that his wife ultimately became an Australian citizen on 20 March 2007. There was also evidence that Mr Vikash Burton and his wife have a daughter, born in Australia in March 2003. It also appears that they have another child who is also an Australian citizen, although the name and birth date do not appear in the material.

35 The grant of citizenship to Vikash's wife has the result that, at the time of the decision by the Tribunal, her visa was no longer liable to cancellation under s 140(2) of the Act.

36 Accordingly, there was no error in the approach taken by the Tribunal, namely that the appellant's son would be free to lodge a spouse visa application to return to Australia.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SGLB [2004] HCA 32 ; (2004) 207 ALR 12</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/32.html</AustLII>
<text>25 On the other hand there is also authority for the view that the provisions of the Act on which the appellant relied, in particular the power under s 363(3)(a) , to summon persons to give evidence, do not impose any duty on the Tribunal to exercise that power: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SGLB [2004] HCA 32 ; (2004) 207 ALR 12 at [43] (with respect to s 426 of the Act).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Prasad v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs [1985] FCA 47 ; (1985) 6 FCR 155</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1985/47.html</AustLII>
<text>26 The seminal authority for the principle that a failure to enquire may, in exceptional circumstances, invalidate a decision is Prasad v Minister for Immigration &amp; Ethnic Affairs [1985] FCA 47 ; (1985) 6 FCR 155. Kenny J referred to this in Le at [64].

27 The effect of what Wilcox J said in Prasad at 169-170 is that there may be Wednesbury unreasonableness where it is obvious that there is material that is readily available to the decision-maker that is likely to be of critical importance in relation to a central issue for determination.

28 In my view, this principle does not extend to the present case because all that occurred was that competing versions of the facts were advanced by different parties.

29 It is true that the prior inconsistent statements of the "repudiators" included sworn statutory declarations which were retracted, without any apparent explanation, in unsworn statements and that they were not "tested" in the witness box.

30 Indeed, Mr Burton's statements were apparently not even signed (though the Tribunal's reasons provide conflicting information on this point) and consisted only of two handwritten undated statements received by the Tribunal in May 2003 and July 2003.

31 However, it seems to me that a failure to "test" the later evidence by questioning the witness cannot be equated with a failure to gather factual material of the kind contemplated by the principle stated in Prasad . This is borne out by the observations of Gummow and Heydon JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S154/2002 (2003) 3"> [2003] HCA 60 ; 201 ALR 437 at [57] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>