<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Insurance News Pty Ltd (ACN 128 480 973) v JEM Nominees Pty Ltd (ACN 005 304 049) trading as Insurance News Australia [2008] FCA 1966 (19 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1966.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brookfield Communications Inc v West Coast Entertainment Corporation [1999] USCA9 74 ; 174 F3d 1036 (1999)</tocase>
<text>12 Although there is no precise finding to this effect the Federal Magistrate appears to accept that the words "insurance" and "news" and "Australia" were words which are "descriptive" rather than "distinctive". It would be surprising if any other result ensued because they are self-evidently descriptive words. Although more than one descriptive word is combined, each component retains its descriptive significance in relation to the services at issue; the combination results in a composite that is itself descriptive: see Brookfield Communications Inc v West Coast Entertainment Corporation [1999] USCA9 74 ; 174 F3d 1036 (1999); Finance Express v Nowcom Corporation 564 FSupp2d 1160 (2008).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>connect.com.au Pty Ltd v GoConnect Australia Pty Ltd (2000) 178 ALR 348</tocase>
<text>13 Moreover, the Federal Magistrate's comparison of the two domain names by substituting "company" for "com" and "Australia" for "au" is misplaced. The ".com" top-level domain signifies the sites' commercial nature, and the ".au" signifies where the domain is registered: see connect.com.au Pty Ltd v GoConnect Australia Pty Ltd (2000) 178 ALR 348 ; Prime Publishers Inc v American-Republican Inc 160 FSupp2d 266 (2001). The Federal Magistrate's commentary about the similarity in capitalisation of the website names is also not significant as web addresses are not capital-sensitive.

17 In connect.com.au Pty Ltd, Emmett J observed at [57] that for a descriptive name to become distinctive, "a very substantial amount of use in the relevant market would be necessary for it to acquire any secondary meaning". At [58] his Honour said:
 ...where a descriptive trade name is used there will always be the possibility of confusion...[and] where a descriptive trade name is used it will be difficult for that name to become distinctive of a particular business. Application to like businesses would not ordinarily mislead the public: see Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Ltd (1978) 140 CLR 216.

18 At [60] Emmett J earlier said:
 "There is a price to be paid for the advantages flowing from the possession of an eloquently descriptive trade name. Because it is descriptive it is equally applicable to any business of a like kind. Its very descriptiveness ensures that it is not distinctive of any particular business and hence its application to other like businesses will not ordinarily mislead the public." 
See also the discussion at [61] regarding possible confusion by the public where "descriptive words are used by two traders as part of their respective trade names", even where the trade names include differentiating words.

20 At 228 - 229 in the Hornsby Building case, Stephen J (with whom Jacobs J agreed) referred to the use of descriptive words in a business name as not entitling a claim for a monopoly in these words. At 229, his Honour referred to the concept stressed by Emmett J in connect.com.au Pty Ltd that "(t)here is a price to be paid for the advantages flowing from the possession of an eloquently descriptive trade name".
 
See also Barwick CJ at 221 (with whom Aickin J agreed).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Dodds Family Investments Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Lane Industries Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (2003) 26 IPR 261</tocase>
<text>19 Similar observations have been made by Stephen J at 228 in the Hornsby Building case and by a Full Court of this Court in Dodds Family Investments Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Lane Industries Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (2003) 26 IPR 261.

20 At 228 - 229 in the Hornsby Building case, Stephen J (with whom Jacobs J agreed) referred to the use of descriptive words in a business name as not entitling a claim for a monopoly in these words. At 229, his Honour referred to the concept stressed by Emmett J in connect.com.au Pty Ltd that "(t)here is a price to be paid for the advantages flowing from the possession of an eloquently descriptive trade name".
 
See also Barwick CJ at 221 (with whom Aickin J agreed).

21 I also note that in Dodds Family Investments at 269, the Full Court said:
 The causative connection is reputation, an association in the minds of consumers between the originator's designation and its goods or services. Merely descriptive words will not ordinarily effect such an association: per Gummow, French, Hill JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Finance Express v Nowcom Corporation 564 FSupp2d 1160 (2008)</tocase>
<text>12 Although there is no precise finding to this effect the Federal Magistrate appears to accept that the words "insurance" and "news" and "Australia" were words which are "descriptive" rather than "distinctive". It would be surprising if any other result ensued because they are self-evidently descriptive words. Although more than one descriptive word is combined, each component retains its descriptive significance in relation to the services at issue; the combination results in a composite that is itself descriptive: see Brookfield Communications Inc v West Coast Entertainment Corporation [1999] USCA9 74 ; 174 F3d 1036 (1999); Finance Express v Nowcom Corporation 564 FSupp2d 1160 (2008).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information (1978) 140 CLR 216</tocase>
<text>10 At [17], by reference to the High Court's judgment in Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Pty Ltd (1978) 140 CLR 216 , his Honour noted, correctly, that "...a party is not able to obtain a monopoly over a name which is not distinctive but rather descriptive."

11 At [63], his Honour referred to the names of the websites as using "common words". At [64] he referred to "the descriptive nature of the words".

17 In connect.com.au Pty Ltd, Emmett J observed at [57] that for a descriptive name to become distinctive, "a very substantial amount of use in the relevant market would be necessary for it to acquire any secondary meaning". At [58] his Honour said:
 ...where a descriptive trade name is used there will always be the possibility of confusion...[and] where a descriptive trade name is used it will be difficult for that name to become distinctive of a particular business. Application to like businesses would not ordinarily mislead the public: see Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Ltd (1978) 140 CLR 216.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Prime Publishers Inc v American-Republican Inc 160 FSupp2d 266 (2001)</tocase>
<text>13 Moreover, the Federal Magistrate's comparison of the two domain names by substituting "company" for "com" and "Australia" for "au" is misplaced. The ".com" top-level domain signifies the sites' commercial nature, and the ".au" signifies where the domain is registered: see connect.com.au Pty Ltd v GoConnect Australia Pty Ltd (2000) 178 ALR 348 ; Prime Publishers Inc v American-Republican Inc 160 FSupp2d 266 (2001). The Federal Magistrate's commentary about the similarity in capitalisation of the website names is also not significant as web addresses are not capital-sensitive.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/181.html</AustLII>
<text>22 Although the Federal Magistrate, at [65], considered the names of the two websites and the get-up of those sites in combination provided the requisite confusion, this finding is at odds with his Honour's earlier observation at [11] that the two sites are not strikingly similar. So much is evident, at least, when it is remembered that one site is a free service and another a subscriber based service thereby lessening possible confusion. As described by the Federal Magistrate the appearance of the two websites is not sufficiently similar to give rise to confusion on the basis of appearance alone or in combination with the names. The fact that some interested people may be confused between the two sites is an insufficient basis to establish a reasonable likelihood of an appreciable or relevant confusion. That is especially so where there is no finding as to whether the number of possible confused people was significant or otherwise. See Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 181.

23 Having regard to the foregoing it is apparent that JEM's claim under the Act should not have succeeded. The lack of a finding about whether the words insurance, news and Australia - had acquired a distinctive meaning through extensive use is fatal to JEM's ability to maintain the orders it secured below. His Honour did not deal with the claim made by JEM under the tort of "passing off". Rather, his Honour found it unnecessary due to his finding that the respondents succeeded under the TPA. It may be likely that no such claim could be established. In any event, the parties consider, and I agree, that no different result would ensue concerning the passing off claim. 
The appeal should be allowed, the operative orders below set aside and the appellants should have their costs of the appeal and of the proceeding below.

 I certify that the preceding twenty-three (23) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Marshall. 


 Associate:

Dated: 19 December 2008

 Solicitor for the Appellants: Mahoneys Solicitors 
 
 Counsel for the Appellants: Mr G McGowan SC with Mr P Ehrlich 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Davis Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms S Gatford 

 Date of Hearing: 17 December 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 December 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1966.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>