<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Envestra Limited (ACN 078 551 685) v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 249 (7 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/249.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Murry [1998] HCA 42 ; (1998) 193 CLR 605</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/42.html</AustLII>
<text>29 As senior counsel for both parties acknowledged, the resolution of their dispute depends upon the proper construction of s 705 - 70 of the ITAA 1997. In Commissioner of Taxation v Murry [1998] HCA 42 ; (1998) 193 CLR 605 Kirby J at 632 referred to authorities indicating that taxation statutes should generally not be narrowly construed. His Honour said that each case must depend upon its own statutory language and apparent statutory purposes. Neither party on this appeal suggested any particular policy behind s 705 - 70 which helpfully informed its construction in the present circumstances.

30 It is not disputed by the Commissioner that Envestra, and ESL and EQL, could have elected on or before 1 July 2002 (or, indeed, at any time until the formal adoption of the financial accounts of ESL and EQL respectively for the financial year ended 30 June 2003) under s 334(5) of the Corporations Act to apply the 1999 AASB 1020 to the statement of the financial position of ESL and EQL or to the consolidated financial statements of Envestra and its group. Had they done so, it is also common ground that the deferred tax liabilities of ESL and EQL measured in accordance with the 1999 AASB 1020 would have been liabilities of ESL and EQL under s 705 - 70 (1) of the ITAA for the purpose of working out the allocable cost amount of each of ESL and EQL joining the Envestra consolidated group. There is no apparent policy behind Pt 3 - 90 of the ITAA 1997, or in particular s 705 - 70 , which suggests such an outcome would be inappropriate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chu Kheng Lim v Minister for Immigration Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1992] HCA 64 ; (1992) 176 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/64.html</AustLII>
<text>31 But does the word "can" in s 705 - 70 (1) in its context mean that the possible adoption of the 1999 AASB 1020 by Envestra, ESL and EQL at 30 June 2002 (or until their financial accounts to 30 June 2003 were approved by their directors) enlivens s 705 - 70 (1)? Or does the word "can" in its context have some different meaning and function? It is a trite starting point, recognised by those rhetorical questions that it is desirable, where possible, to give meaning to every word used in a statute: Chu Kheng Lim v Minister for Immigration Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1992] HCA 64 ; (1992) 176 CLR 1 at 12-13; Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 29 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 382.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 29 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/29.html</AustLII>
<text>31 But does the word "can" in s 705 - 70 (1) in its context mean that the possible adoption of the 1999 AASB 1020 by Envestra, ESL and EQL at 30 June 2002 (or until their financial accounts to 30 June 2003 were approved by their directors) enlivens s 705 - 70 (1)? Or does the word "can" in its context have some different meaning and function? It is a trite starting point, recognised by those rhetorical questions that it is desirable, where possible, to give meaning to every word used in a statute: Chu Kheng Lim v Minister for Immigration Local Government and Ethnic Affairs [1992] HCA 64 ; (1992) 176 CLR 1 at 12-13; Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority [1998] HCA 29 ; (1998) 194 CLR 355 at 382.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Price v Civil Service Commission [1978] 1 All ER 1228</tocase>
<text>33 Accounting standards of the AASB are not totally prescriptive. They may contain provisions which require or permit matters of judgment, and matters of choice. The use of the words "can or must" can therefore readily function as alternatives in relation to the AASB accounting standards which in fact apply in the determination of the accounting liabilities of a joining entity at the joining date. Some standards will direct the recognition of a particular accounting liability, and some will permit of a judgment or discretion as to whether a particular accounting liability is recognised. I do not think it is necessary to look to accounting standards which might have, but in fact did not, apply at the relevant time to give meaning and function to the word "can" in s 705 - 70 (1). Indeed, if that were contemplated by that provision, it would have been more appropriate to use words such as "could have been" or "may have been" as well as "can or must" in that provision. I think the use of the present tense points only to accounting standards which in fact apply in the determination of the accounting liabilities of the joining entity at the joining time. Although in a quite different context, I note that the expression "can comply" in s 1 of the Sex Discrimination Act 1975 (UK) and in s 1 of the Race Relations Act 1976 (UK) has been given a practical operative meaning rather than one which encompasses what is theoretically possible: Price v Civil Service Commission [1978] 1 All ER 1228; and Mandla (Sewa Singh) v Dowell Lee [1983] 2 AC 548 per Lord Fraser at 565-566 respectively.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Mandla (Sewa Singh) v Dowell Lee [1983] 2 AC 548</tocase>
<text>33 Accounting standards of the AASB are not totally prescriptive. They may contain provisions which require or permit matters of judgment, and matters of choice. The use of the words "can or must" can therefore readily function as alternatives in relation to the AASB accounting standards which in fact apply in the determination of the accounting liabilities of a joining entity at the joining date. Some standards will direct the recognition of a particular accounting liability, and some will permit of a judgment or discretion as to whether a particular accounting liability is recognised. I do not think it is necessary to look to accounting standards which might have, but in fact did not, apply at the relevant time to give meaning and function to the word "can" in s 705 - 70 (1). Indeed, if that were contemplated by that provision, it would have been more appropriate to use words such as "could have been" or "may have been" as well as "can or must" in that provision. I think the use of the present tense points only to accounting standards which in fact apply in the determination of the accounting liabilities of the joining entity at the joining time. Although in a quite different context, I note that the expression "can comply" in s 1 of the Sex Discrimination Act 1975 (UK) and in s 1 of the Race Relations Act 1976 (UK) has been given a practical operative meaning rather than one which encompasses what is theoretically possible: Price v Civil Service Commission [1978] 1 All ER 1228; and Mandla (Sewa Singh) v Dowell Lee [1983] 2 AC 548 per Lord Fraser at 565-566 respectively.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 82</tocase>
<text>34 The significance of tense in the construction of s 23(g)(iii) of the ITAA 1936 was discussed by the Full Court of this Court in Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 82 , especially per Lockhart J at 89 and per Beaumont J at 116. Of course, that case addressed a quite different context, so it merely provides an indication that tense may be a significant indicator to the proper construction of a taxation statute. See also Brookton Co-op Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441 per Mason J at 451 and per Aickin J at 461-469.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brookton Co-op Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/28.html</AustLII>
<text>34 The significance of tense in the construction of s 23(g)(iii) of the ITAA 1936 was discussed by the Full Court of this Court in Cronulla Sutherland Leagues Club Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 82 , especially per Lockhart J at 89 and per Beaumont J at 116. Of course, that case addressed a quite different context, so it merely provides an indication that tense may be a significant indicator to the proper construction of a taxation statute. See also Brookton Co-op Society Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (Cth) [1981] HCA 28 ; (1981) 147 CLR 441 per Mason J at 451 and per Aickin J at 461-469.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>