<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXQY v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 207 (3 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/207.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/263.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The other ground which was argued was that the Tribunal had erred by failing to consider whether the appellant had been persecuted by reason of her membership of a particular social group. This ground was not raised expressly before the Tribunal nor was material presented by the appellant which made it necessary for the Tribunal to consider and determine the issue. Even if it be assumed, in the appellant's favour, that a particular social group of the kind identified by counsel existed, the Tribunal's findings that the appellant had not been subject to conduct which amounted to persecution means that she does not satisfy the Convention definition of a "refugee". If she was not persecuted the question of the reason for any alleged persecution does not arise. It cannot, therefore, be said that the Tribunal's failure to deal with the issue meant that a claim which might have been dispositive of the application had been ignored: see NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [63] . In any event this was not a ground that was argued before the Federal Magistrate. I note also that, when asked by the Tribunal whether she knew of any other women who had a similar problem to her in Thailand, she answered that she did not.

22 The appeal should be dismissed with costs.
 I certify that the preceding twenty-two (22) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Tracey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 3 March 2008


 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr J A Patel 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Ms E Latif 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Clayton Utz 
 
 Date of Hearing: 3 March 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 March 2008 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/207.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>