<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tasman Group Services Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [2008] FCA 23 (29 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/23.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Emu Bay Railway Co Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1944] HCA 28 ; (1944) 71 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1944/28.html</AustLII>
<text>32 With the SBC loans there was not a condition precedent to the coming into existence of the liability, as was the case in Emu Bay Railway Co Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1944] HCA 28 ; (1944) 71 CLR 596. The loan agreements, under which money was advanced, stipulated dates for repayment and created unconditional obligations, notwithstanding that such obligations were extended from time to time: cf Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citylink Melbourne Limited (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [134]. Prior to the sale of share agreement, there was no suggestion that SBC's rights would be abandoned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citylink Melbourne Limited (2006) 228 CLR 1</tocase>
<text>32 With the SBC loans there was not a condition precedent to the coming into existence of the liability, as was the case in Emu Bay Railway Co Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1944] HCA 28 ; (1944) 71 CLR 596. The loan agreements, under which money was advanced, stipulated dates for repayment and created unconditional obligations, notwithstanding that such obligations were extended from time to time: cf Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Citylink Melbourne Limited (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [134]. Prior to the sale of share agreement, there was no suggestion that SBC's rights would be abandoned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Spassked v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2003] FCAFC 282 ; (2003) 136 FCR 441</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/282.html</AustLII>
<text>41 The applicant relied on Spassked v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2003] FCAFC 282 ; (2003) 136 FCR 441 at [128] where Gyles J said that the parent-subsidiary relationship in that case was such that the loans were "purely intra-group arrangements with no external aspect" and many of the companies involved had "no external role at all". Thus the requisite connection or relationship between the outgoing and the earning of assessable income "was not to be inferred but must be positively established". However, in the present case SBAF certainly had an external role. It was a trading entity in its own right, albeit an unsuccessful one, and used the borrowed funds for working capital to pay the expenses of its business.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>GP International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/25.html</AustLII>
<text>42 The relevant taxpayer is the applicant. The focus is upon it and the use to which it put the borrowed funds. The Court is not concerned with SBC's purpose in advancing funds: GP International Pipecoaters Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 136-137.

43 I conclude the answer to Issue 2 is: yes.

44 Section 245 - 35 (1) provides that a debt is forgiven if the debtor's obligation to pay the debt "is released or waived, or is otherwise extinguished".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Craine v Colonial Mutual Fire Insurance Co Ltd [1920] HCA 64 ; (1920) 28 CLR 305</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1920/64.html</AustLII>
<text>51 In my opinion, the words of s 245-35(1) cannot be read down so as to require some express forgiveness. Waiver, for example, may be by conduct; it is an intentional act done with knowledge whereby a person abandons a right by acting in a manner inconsistent with that right: Craine v Colonial Mutual Fire Insurance Co Ltd [1920] HCA 64 ; (1920) 28 CLR 305 at 326, Grundt v Great Boulder Gold Mines Ltd [1937] HCA 58 ; (1937) 59 CLR 641 at 658. The expression "or otherwise extinguished" is wide and would cover an agreement, enforceable in equity, not to set up the cause of action in debt: McDermott v Black [1940] HCA 4 ; (1940) 63 CLR 161. SBAF was of course a party to the sale of shares agreement. After settlement of the sale of shares agreement and SBC's receipt of the purchase price from Tasman Group there is no way in which SBC could have recovered the debts previously owing by SBAF.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Grundt v Great Boulder Gold Mines Ltd [1937] HCA 58 ; (1937) 59 CLR 641</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/58.html</AustLII>
<text>51 In my opinion, the words of s 245-35(1) cannot be read down so as to require some express forgiveness. Waiver, for example, may be by conduct; it is an intentional act done with knowledge whereby a person abandons a right by acting in a manner inconsistent with that right: Craine v Colonial Mutual Fire Insurance Co Ltd [1920] HCA 64 ; (1920) 28 CLR 305 at 326, Grundt v Great Boulder Gold Mines Ltd [1937] HCA 58 ; (1937) 59 CLR 641 at 658. The expression "or otherwise extinguished" is wide and would cover an agreement, enforceable in equity, not to set up the cause of action in debt: McDermott v Black [1940] HCA 4 ; (1940) 63 CLR 161. SBAF was of course a party to the sale of shares agreement. After settlement of the sale of shares agreement and SBC's receipt of the purchase price from Tasman Group there is no way in which SBC could have recovered the debts previously owing by SBAF.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McDermott v Black [1940] HCA 4 ; (1940) 63 CLR 161</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1940/4.html</AustLII>
<text>51 In my opinion, the words of s 245-35(1) cannot be read down so as to require some express forgiveness. Waiver, for example, may be by conduct; it is an intentional act done with knowledge whereby a person abandons a right by acting in a manner inconsistent with that right: Craine v Colonial Mutual Fire Insurance Co Ltd [1920] HCA 64 ; (1920) 28 CLR 305 at 326, Grundt v Great Boulder Gold Mines Ltd [1937] HCA 58 ; (1937) 59 CLR 641 at 658. The expression "or otherwise extinguished" is wide and would cover an agreement, enforceable in equity, not to set up the cause of action in debt: McDermott v Black [1940] HCA 4 ; (1940) 63 CLR 161. SBAF was of course a party to the sale of shares agreement. After settlement of the sale of shares agreement and SBC's receipt of the purchase price from Tasman Group there is no way in which SBC could have recovered the debts previously owing by SBAF.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sandell v Porter [1966] HCA 28 ; (1966) 115 CLR 666</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1966/28.html</AustLII>
<text>66 Mr Meredith, correctly in my view, identified the debtor's capacity to pay as a function of the resources which would be available, including assets which the debtor could realise in a reasonable time frame, and taking into account other liabilities. This approach is consistent with the classic definition of solvency in Sandell v Porter [1966] HCA 28 ; (1966) 115 CLR 666 at 670.

67 I would therefore not accept Mr Hodgkinson's going concern basis.

68 Mr Hodgkinson argued that a creditor valuing a debt in its own hands on a going concern basis will apply any payment against its oldest debt first. Therefore, he said, on Mr Meredith's figures, totalling SBC advances outstanding prior to each new advance meant that the distribution would be insufficient to repay any further advance after 31 January 1997.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>