<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Maher v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2008] FCA 205 (29 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/205.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Get Motor Cycles Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1078</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1078.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Matters relevant to whether security should be provided include whether the application for security is brought promptly, the strength of the applicant's case, whether the applicant is impecunious, whether any impecuniosity was caused by the respondent, whether the application for security is oppressive, and whether the applicant is in substance a plaintiff in the proceeding. See generally Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Get Motor Cycles Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1078.

7 I am satisfied the application for security was brought promptly.

14 The word "oppressive" is used in this area to describe an application for security that is used merely to deny an impecunious applicant a right to litigate. See Jianshe Southern at [27]. As a general rule poverty is not a bar to a litigant at first instance. However the position is different as to appeals. In Skyring v Sweeney [1999] FCA 61 at [6] Spender J said:
 
 Impecuniosity ought not to be a bar to a person prosecuting at first instance a claim, but the position on appeal seems to me to be fundamentally different. In effect, in the absence of an order for security for costs in the circumstances of this case, Mr Skyring, in effect, is given a free hit, and that seems to me to be intrinsically unfair. 
 

See also Moore v Macks [2007] FCA 509 at [20] to [21].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Maher v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2007] FCA 560</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/560.html</AustLII>
<text>8 I have read the Federal Magistrate's decision the subject of the appeal and the amended notice of appeal. Many of the grounds are not available grounds of appeal or are of such generality and so wanting in particularity that they are impossible to assess. The complaint about the Magistrate's construction of Order 36 of the Federal Court Rules was rejected by Tracey J in Maher v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2007] FCA 560 at [9] .

9 There is no material before me to support the claim that the Magistrate denied the applicant procedural fairness.

10 The complaint that the respondent's demand for payment should have been on behalf of all parties jointly entitled to costs, and that each should have been named in the notice for that purpose, was dealt with by the Magistrate at [32] to [35] of his reasons. On the evidence before him the Magistrate found that the respondent was authorised to collect all of the costs on behalf of the other parties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Skyring v Sweeney [1999] FCA 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/61.html</AustLII>
<text>14 The word "oppressive" is used in this area to describe an application for security that is used merely to deny an impecunious applicant a right to litigate. See Jianshe Southern at [27]. As a general rule poverty is not a bar to a litigant at first instance. However the position is different as to appeals. In Skyring v Sweeney [1999] FCA 61 at [6] Spender J said:
 
 Impecuniosity ought not to be a bar to a person prosecuting at first instance a claim, but the position on appeal seems to me to be fundamentally different. In effect, in the absence of an order for security for costs in the circumstances of this case, Mr Skyring, in effect, is given a free hit, and that seems to me to be intrinsically unfair. 
 

See also Moore v Macks [2007] FCA 509 at [20] to [21].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Moore v Macks [2007] FCA 509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/509.html</AustLII>
<text>14 The word "oppressive" is used in this area to describe an application for security that is used merely to deny an impecunious applicant a right to litigate. See Jianshe Southern at [27]. As a general rule poverty is not a bar to a litigant at first instance. However the position is different as to appeals. In Skyring v Sweeney [1999] FCA 61 at [6] Spender J said:
 
 Impecuniosity ought not to be a bar to a person prosecuting at first instance a claim, but the position on appeal seems to me to be fundamentally different. In effect, in the absence of an order for security for costs in the circumstances of this case, Mr Skyring, in effect, is given a free hit, and that seems to me to be intrinsically unfair. 
 

See also Moore v Macks [2007] FCA 509 at [20] to [21].</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>