<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Mayne Industries Pty Ltd v Advanced Engineering Group Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 27 (23 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/27.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/273.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The respondent says the 1995 Act by introducing the notion of a 'shape' within the definition of 'sign' in s 6 of the Act and thus within the definition of a 'trade mark' in s 17 of the Act as a ' sign used, or intended to be used, to distinguish goods or services dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods or services so dealt with or provided by any other person ' did not bring about the radical change of providing that a registered trade mark would have the effect of restricting access to functional features or innovations. The respondent says the trade mark law of this country recognises a continuing fundamental distinction between a shape, whether expressed in part or the entirety of the goods the subject of the registration, that has an element of 'functional significance' and a shape which bears no functional significance. The respondent says, consistent with observations in Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494, were the 1995 Act to enable a registered trade mark to give the owner a monopoly over functional features (and thus suit for infringement of such a registered trade mark) it would indeed have made a radical change to trade mark law and nothing in the Act or in the discussions that preceded it suggest that such a result was intended. Therefore, it follows, it is said, that in the context of contended infringement, once the evidence demonstrates that the shape serves some functional significance, use of the shape (the trade mark) cannot be use as a trade mark. In such a case, it is said the shape adopted in the respondent's goods and consequential use of the shape in brochures and advertising material does not differentiate or distinguish the goods as a badge of origin of the user as a purveyor of those goods but serves to identify (distinguish) the content or features of the goods themselves. In other words, the respondent uses the shape to say in trade 'these are the goods that I sell' not 'know me as the seller or purveyor of these goods by this shape' (although, for trade mark use purposes, the seller need not be specifically identified).

10 The applicant says the respondent has misunderstood the true context in which issues of functionality were discussed Kenman Kandy and related authorities. In this case, the trade mark has been accepted by the Registrar and has been registered. The applicant is the registered owner of a valid shape mark which is not the subject of a challenge or cross-claim for cancellation or rectification of the Register on grounds of lack of distinctiveness . The applicant says that discussions in the authorities of whether a trade mark application is to be rejected if it consists of a shape expressed in the relevant goods so as to achieve a particular technical result or by reason of the nature of the goods or some other functional feature, do not inform in any determinative sense, whether a registered trade mark (assessed in accordance with s 41 of the Act throughout the application stage) is infringed by use of the trade mark or a substantially identical trade mark. In assessing whether the registered trade mark has been infringed for the purposes of s 120(1) of the Act, the applicant says that all the circumstances of use are examined to answer this orthodox question: has the respondent made use of the mark as a 'badge of origin' in the sense that the use indicates a connection in the course of trade between the goods and the user of the sign? Further, the applicant says the S loop, although it in part serves a purpose of catching a wire, the bottom section of the S shape (that is, the lower U-shape of the S loop), serves no functional purpose at all. Secondly, other shapes also catch the wires of a fence and the respondent's fence dropper need not incorporate the S loop, that is, need not use the applicant's trade mark, in order to function as a dropper incorporating a shaped catch. The applicant, in submissions, put it this way, ' ... it must have something that engages on the intermediate wire, but it doesn't have to have that shape. That is our case.'

11 The applicant says that, in fact, the respondent recognises by reliance upon contentions of the applicant's own witnesses, Mr Sachs, and Mr Bailey, that the applicant's article, the fence dropper, has become, through extensive use, well known and is distinguished in the relevant trade by the three dimensional S loop, that is, by the sign comprising the trade mark. The applicant says that a three dimensional shape mark that performs an aspect of function may, as in the case of this mark, distinguish the goods (fence droppers) in the applicant and although a mark may have a functional element, there is no point of principle derived from the authorities that a shape mark cannot serve as a bade of origin by a respondent to distinguish its goods from those of others. The question is whether, contextually, it has been so used by the respondent. An analogue in relation to word marks is a mark that contains a descriptive element which, nevertheless, in the context of contended infringing use, might be seen to serve as a badge of origin. A question will inevitably arise as to whether the use of words containing a descriptive element might make it difficult to demonstrate that the words have been used to distinguish the goods of the respondent, and that difficulty is likely to be all the more pronounced where the mark is a three dimensional shape forming part of the goods.

12 That question will require consideration in these reasons.

65 In Kenman Kandy, Stone J observed that:
 
 The 'inherent form' of goods, in my view, can only refer to those aspects of form that have functional significance. Were the 1995 Act to enable the registration of a trade mark that would give the owner a monopoly over functional features, it would indeed have made a radical change to trade mark law. [137]

66 The respondent's current brochure being the only brochure now used by the respondent (exhibit GS3 to the affidavit of Serisier - exhibit 12 in the proceeding) is endorsed on the back and front with a photograph of the dropper prominently displaying a fence wire engaged in the loop, other depictions of an installed dropper and a photograph of many droppers spread out enabling the loop to be plainly seen. None of these uses constitute use of the shape as a trade mark, nor does importing and offering for sale a dropper that contains an S loop constitute use as a trade mark. Although the earlier brochures of the respondent depicting the exploded view, in situ, of the shape of the S loop (thereby giving particular emphasis to the feature) and descriptive references to the ' unique loop ' impressionistically suggest use of the shape as a distinguishing feature of the goods in the course of trade going to origin, the references are ultimately properly seen as a reference to the configuration of the goods as goods that owe the shape of the S loop to an essential function of the article, that is, the nature of the goods themselves and the capacity of the loop to catch, fix and secure intermediate wires of a fence. There is a circularity involved when the shape in the goods is such an important functional part of the dropper that a user necessarily illustrates the S shape of the catch in the course of trade to convey the features of the dropper. Such use has all the appearance of selecting the shape as a distinguishing feature of the respondent's dropper as a badge of origin. However, such use is not use of the shape as a badge of origin, but rather a statement of the essential functional feature of the S loop inherent in the goods in the sense contemplated in Philips v Remington (supra) per Burchett J; Hill and Branson JJ agreeing and in Kenman Kandy (supra) per French J [45] and Stone JJ [137] and [140].

81 A shape when formed is capable of describing something, as the shape is capable of conveying information. A continuous line drawn around a centre point where each point on the line is equidistant from that point, describes a shape in a particular plane. The name given to that shape is a circle and the shape when formed is commonly understood as describing a circle. A shape might take form in two dimensions or when the shape is to be applied to or embodied in an article, the shape will take form in three dimensions. A three dimensional shape to be embodied in goods is capable of describing those goods by that shape. That shape might also find expression in an analogue for the shape such as an alphabetic analogue like 'S shape' or 'S dropper' that sufficiently approximates the features of the shape that it becomes the name, by that analogue, of the article. In Philips Electronics N V v Remington Consumer Products (1998) 40 IPR 279 at 292 , Jacob J observed that: 'A picture of an article is equivalent to a description of it both convey information. If the picture is simply of an artefact which traders might legitimately wish to manufacture then to my mind it is just like the common word for it' . In that case, Jacob J was considering a question of capacity to distinguish. However those observations as they relate to the capacity of an image to convey information and thus describe an artefact or article are relevant to this issue. A picture is simply a two-dimensional image of the three dimensional article reflecting features of shape. His Honour's observation was adopted in Koninklijke Philips v Remington (supra) at p 101 [12], per Burchett J; Hill and Branson JJ agreeing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited [1961] HCA 75 ; (1963) 109 CLR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1961/75.html</AustLII>
<text>44 The applicant says these considerations are made more pronounced by the respondent's reliance on the distinctiveness of the S loop and the use of Mr Bailey's evidence in another forum, tendered by the respondent as part of exhibit 17 in these proceedings that the ' S shape applied to the wire capturing feature has become synonymous with the products of Mayne Industries in the marketplace '. The applicant says such a powerful statement of acquired distinctiveness supports an inference that the respondent's use in the manner identified is use of a distinctive shape mark, as a trade mark. The applicant contends the shape mark has been ' thrown on ' to the respondent's advertisements to distinguish its droppers from others in the sense contemplated in the well-known passage from the judgment of Kitto J in The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited [1961] HCA 75 ; (1963) 109 CLR 407 at 424-425 and used ' to make the goods more arresting of appearance and more attractive and thus to distinguish them from the goods of other traders ' which is the ' primary function ' of the mark ( Coca-Cola Company v All-Fect Distributors Ltd [1999] FCA 1721 ; (1999) 96 FCR 107 at 118 per Black CJ, Sundberg and Finkelstein JJ). Coca-Cola v All-Fect recognised that a two-dimensional mark used in relation to goods can function as a trade mark even though it has become part of the goods. The 1995 Act makes it plain that a three-dimensional shape registered as a shape trade mark for embodiment in an article or part of an article, can operate as a trade mark and it follows, it is said, that use of the shape in the respondent's articles in circumstances of pronounced distinctiveness and the factors identified at [38]-[44] operates as trade mark use.

60 Section 120 of the Act expressly incorporates the notion previously implied ( The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited (supra)) in both s 58(1) and s 62(1) of the Trade Marks Act 1955 (Cth) ('the 1955 Act') that infringing use of a mark is limited to use ' as a trade mark '. Use as a trade mark is use of the mark as a badge of origin in the sense that use indicates a connection in the course of trade between goods and the person who applies the mark to the goods. ( Coca-Cola v All-Fect (supra); Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Limited v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Limited (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 341 per Lockhart J and 351 per Gummow J). The registered owner of the trade mark has, subject to Part 3 of the Act, the exclusive rights to use the trade mark (and authorise others to use the trade mark) in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered (s 20(1))). Section 120(1) provides relevantly, that a person infringes a registered trade mark if the person uses, as a trade mark, a sign that is substantially identical with the trade mark in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered. A trade mark is a sign used or intended to be used, to distinguish goods dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods so dealt with or provided by any other person (s 17) and a sign includes a shape (s 6). Section 7(4) provides that use of a trade mark in relation to goods means use of the trade mark upon or in physical or other relation to the goods. Accordingly, has the respondent used, as a trade mark, the three dimensional sign in relation to goods by importation, sale and promotion of articles, embodying the shape, to distinguish those goods in the course of trade from the goods of others?

62 Similarly, a trade mark that comprises a three-dimensional shape for embodiment in goods or a part of goods where the shape serves in part a functional purpose might be thought to still serve as a badge of origin. Since the goods, or a part of the goods, take the form of the shape serving that functional purpose, it would be difficult to demonstrate that use of the shape of the goods serves the primary function of a badge of origin. Such use is very likely to convey something of the functional attributes of the goods, much akin, by analogy, to the use of the oil drop man to identify the qualities of the Shell Petrol in Shell v Esso (supra). Where the goods embody the shape, a seller of goods bearing the shape, might find it difficult to describe or illustrate the goods without reference to the shape in much the same way that Tansing ( Musidor BV v Tansing (1994) 52 FCR 363) found it necessary in the course of trade in unauthorised recordings of the Rolling Stones to use the trade mark ' Rolling Stones ' to describe the content of the goods being sold. Similarly, how might Disney Enterprises Inc describe an animated cinematic version of ' The Hunchback of Notre Dame ' without using the words ' The Hunchback of Notre Dame ' notwithstanding the registration of that title as a trade mark for entertainment services ( Christodoulou (supra)). Where the trade mark comprises a shape which is demonstrated to involve a substantial functional element in the goods, references to the shape are almost certainly references to the nature of the goods themselves rather than use of the shape as a trade mark.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Coca-Cola Company v All-Fect Distributors Ltd [1999] FCA 1721 ; (1999) 96 FCR 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/1721.html</AustLII>
<text>44 The applicant says these considerations are made more pronounced by the respondent's reliance on the distinctiveness of the S loop and the use of Mr Bailey's evidence in another forum, tendered by the respondent as part of exhibit 17 in these proceedings that the ' S shape applied to the wire capturing feature has become synonymous with the products of Mayne Industries in the marketplace '. The applicant says such a powerful statement of acquired distinctiveness supports an inference that the respondent's use in the manner identified is use of a distinctive shape mark, as a trade mark. The applicant contends the shape mark has been ' thrown on ' to the respondent's advertisements to distinguish its droppers from others in the sense contemplated in the well-known passage from the judgment of Kitto J in The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited [1961] HCA 75 ; (1963) 109 CLR 407 at 424-425 and used ' to make the goods more arresting of appearance and more attractive and thus to distinguish them from the goods of other traders ' which is the ' primary function ' of the mark ( Coca-Cola Company v All-Fect Distributors Ltd [1999] FCA 1721 ; (1999) 96 FCR 107 at 118 per Black CJ, Sundberg and Finkelstein JJ). Coca-Cola v All-Fect recognised that a two-dimensional mark used in relation to goods can function as a trade mark even though it has become part of the goods. The 1995 Act makes it plain that a three-dimensional shape registered as a shape trade mark for embodiment in an article or part of an article, can operate as a trade mark and it follows, it is said, that use of the shape in the respondent's articles in circumstances of pronounced distinctiveness and the factors identified at [38]-[44] operates as trade mark use.

60 Section 120 of the Act expressly incorporates the notion previously implied ( The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited (supra)) in both s 58(1) and s 62(1) of the Trade Marks Act 1955 (Cth) ('the 1955 Act') that infringing use of a mark is limited to use ' as a trade mark '. Use as a trade mark is use of the mark as a badge of origin in the sense that use indicates a connection in the course of trade between goods and the person who applies the mark to the goods. ( Coca-Cola v All-Fect (supra); Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Limited v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Limited (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 341 per Lockhart J and 351 per Gummow J). The registered owner of the trade mark has, subject to Part 3 of the Act, the exclusive rights to use the trade mark (and authorise others to use the trade mark) in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered (s 20(1))). Section 120(1) provides relevantly, that a person infringes a registered trade mark if the person uses, as a trade mark, a sign that is substantially identical with the trade mark in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered. A trade mark is a sign used or intended to be used, to distinguish goods dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods so dealt with or provided by any other person (s 17) and a sign includes a shape (s 6). Section 7(4) provides that use of a trade mark in relation to goods means use of the trade mark upon or in physical or other relation to the goods. Accordingly, has the respondent used, as a trade mark, the three dimensional sign in relation to goods by importation, sale and promotion of articles, embodying the shape, to distinguish those goods in the course of trade from the goods of others?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Limited v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Limited (1991) 30 FCR 326</tocase>
<text>60 Section 120 of the Act expressly incorporates the notion previously implied ( The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Esso Standard Oil (Australia) Limited (supra)) in both s 58(1) and s 62(1) of the Trade Marks Act 1955 (Cth) ('the 1955 Act') that infringing use of a mark is limited to use ' as a trade mark '. Use as a trade mark is use of the mark as a badge of origin in the sense that use indicates a connection in the course of trade between goods and the person who applies the mark to the goods. ( Coca-Cola v All-Fect (supra); Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Limited v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Limited (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 341 per Lockhart J and 351 per Gummow J). The registered owner of the trade mark has, subject to Part 3 of the Act, the exclusive rights to use the trade mark (and authorise others to use the trade mark) in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered (s 20(1))). Section 120(1) provides relevantly, that a person infringes a registered trade mark if the person uses, as a trade mark, a sign that is substantially identical with the trade mark in relation to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered. A trade mark is a sign used or intended to be used, to distinguish goods dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods so dealt with or provided by any other person (s 17) and a sign includes a shape (s 6). Section 7(4) provides that use of a trade mark in relation to goods means use of the trade mark upon or in physical or other relation to the goods. Accordingly, has the respondent used, as a trade mark, the three dimensional sign in relation to goods by importation, sale and promotion of articles, embodying the shape, to distinguish those goods in the course of trade from the goods of others?

61 The answer to that question requires examination of the purpose and nature of the impugned use, the relevant context, the way the trade mark has been adopted or applied in relation to goods and the use of brochures, catalogues and advertisements ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 347). A part of that contextual analysis involves an assessment of whether use of the trade mark might be illustrative or descriptive of the goods rather than use as a trade mark. In that context, the extent to which a three dimensional shape for the goods or a part of the goods serves function is an important element in the determination of whether use is distinctive of commercial origin or illustrative or descriptive of the embodied shape of the goods. Use of the trade mark must be demonstrated to be use that serves the primary function of a trade mark ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 348 and 349; Christodolou v Disney Enterprises Inc [2005] FCA 1401 ; (2005) 66 IPR 595). A word trade mark that contains a descriptive element may nevertheless still serve as a badge of origin as language does not necessarily convey only one idea ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling ) although the descriptive element may make it difficult to demonstrate that the words serve the primary function of distinguishing the goods. ( Wellness Pty Ltd v Pro-Bio Living Waters Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 242 per Bennett J [29]).

105 Section 122(1) of the Act like s 64(1) of the 1955 Act, assumes infringing conduct on the part of the respondent that is excused when the person uses a sign in good faith to indicate one or more of the identified characteristics. Section 64(1)(b) contemplated use in good faith by a person 'of a description of the character or quality of his goods' whereas s 122(1)(b)(i) concerns use in good faith to indicate a broader range of characteristics. The essential concern going to good faith in s 122(1) is that the use be honest. Something less than fraudulent intention in the common law sense will suffice to prevent use being in good faith ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling (supra), per Gummow J at p 356). There must be however, identified conduct on the part of the respondent that demonstrates use of the sign in circumstances where Mr Hastie has engaged in conscious and deliberate acts to undermine the registered owner or the integrity of the trade mark. Has the respondent sought to undermine the trade mark by the 'assiduous efforts of an infringer? ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling per Gummow J at p 355 adopting the phrase used by Windeyer J in Re Bali Brassiere Co Inc Registered Trade Mark: An Application by v Berlei Limited [1968] HCA 72 ; (1968) 118 CLR 128 at 133). A conscious decision to try and render generic, a trade mark which on advice from reputable patent and trade mark attorneys would be infringed by use is an example ( Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Ltd (1990) 96 ALR 277 at 311 per Hill J). In that case, the decision by Johnson &amp; Johnson to use the trade mark was made with 'full knowledge' of the registration with advice that use would constitute infringement of the mark; and in circumstances where use was part of an international strategy to undermine the mark by rendering it generic. Since those ulterior motives subsisted, the use was found not to be honest. In this case, Mr Hastie had worked with and had been responsible for manufacturing S shaped wire droppers since 1978. He knew of the licence agreement between National Nail and Cyclone and knew that the improved dropper was the subject of a patent in New Zealand. He knew that royalties had been paid under the licence until the expiry of the prolongation period of the patent in New Zealand in 1986. Before entering the New Zealand market in 1996, Mr Hastie sought advice as to the patent position in that country. He understood that any patent had expired for the S shaped dropper. He assumed that there was no patent protection for it in Australia. He sought advice in 1996 from patent attorneys and he says he at least asked about the position in Australia. There is no independent written advice to Mr Hastie going to the position in Australia. I accept that Mr Hastie assumed in 2003 that there was no patent on foot in Australia but that he did not seek advice in 2003 as to the intellectual property position in Australia concerning the S dropper.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Christodolou v Disney Enterprises Inc [2005] FCA 1401 ; (2005) 66 IPR 595</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2005/1401.html</AustLII>
<text>61 The answer to that question requires examination of the purpose and nature of the impugned use, the relevant context, the way the trade mark has been adopted or applied in relation to goods and the use of brochures, catalogues and advertisements ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 347). A part of that contextual analysis involves an assessment of whether use of the trade mark might be illustrative or descriptive of the goods rather than use as a trade mark. In that context, the extent to which a three dimensional shape for the goods or a part of the goods serves function is an important element in the determination of whether use is distinctive of commercial origin or illustrative or descriptive of the embodied shape of the goods. Use of the trade mark must be demonstrated to be use that serves the primary function of a trade mark ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 348 and 349; Christodolou v Disney Enterprises Inc [2005] FCA 1401 ; (2005) 66 IPR 595). A word trade mark that contains a descriptive element may nevertheless still serve as a badge of origin as language does not necessarily convey only one idea ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling ) although the descriptive element may make it difficult to demonstrate that the words serve the primary function of distinguishing the goods. ( Wellness Pty Ltd v Pro-Bio Living Waters Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 242 per Bennett J [29]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wellness Pty Ltd v Pro-Bio Living Waters Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 242</tocase>
<text>61 The answer to that question requires examination of the purpose and nature of the impugned use, the relevant context, the way the trade mark has been adopted or applied in relation to goods and the use of brochures, catalogues and advertisements ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 347). A part of that contextual analysis involves an assessment of whether use of the trade mark might be illustrative or descriptive of the goods rather than use as a trade mark. In that context, the extent to which a three dimensional shape for the goods or a part of the goods serves function is an important element in the determination of whether use is distinctive of commercial origin or illustrative or descriptive of the embodied shape of the goods. Use of the trade mark must be demonstrated to be use that serves the primary function of a trade mark ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling at 348 and 349; Christodolou v Disney Enterprises Inc [2005] FCA 1401 ; (2005) 66 IPR 595). A word trade mark that contains a descriptive element may nevertheless still serve as a badge of origin as language does not necessarily convey only one idea ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling ) although the descriptive element may make it difficult to demonstrate that the words serve the primary function of distinguishing the goods. ( Wellness Pty Ltd v Pro-Bio Living Waters Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 242 per Bennett J [29]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Musidor BV v Tansing (1994) 52 FCR 363</tocase>
<text>62 Similarly, a trade mark that comprises a three-dimensional shape for embodiment in goods or a part of goods where the shape serves in part a functional purpose might be thought to still serve as a badge of origin. Since the goods, or a part of the goods, take the form of the shape serving that functional purpose, it would be difficult to demonstrate that use of the shape of the goods serves the primary function of a badge of origin. Such use is very likely to convey something of the functional attributes of the goods, much akin, by analogy, to the use of the oil drop man to identify the qualities of the Shell Petrol in Shell v Esso (supra). Where the goods embody the shape, a seller of goods bearing the shape, might find it difficult to describe or illustrate the goods without reference to the shape in much the same way that Tansing ( Musidor BV v Tansing (1994) 52 FCR 363) found it necessary in the course of trade in unauthorised recordings of the Rolling Stones to use the trade mark ' Rolling Stones ' to describe the content of the goods being sold. Similarly, how might Disney Enterprises Inc describe an animated cinematic version of ' The Hunchback of Notre Dame ' without using the words ' The Hunchback of Notre Dame ' notwithstanding the registration of that title as a trade mark for entertainment services ( Christodoulou (supra)). Where the trade mark comprises a shape which is demonstrated to involve a substantial functional element in the goods, references to the shape are almost certainly references to the nature of the goods themselves rather than use of the shape as a trade mark.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Koninklijke Philips Electrics NV and Another v Remington Products Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 876 ; (2000) 100 FCR 90</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/876.html</AustLII>
<text>15 The respondent also pleaded and contended throughout the proceedings, until the point was abandoned in addresses, that the elements of s 24(1) of the Act were made out on the footing that the registered trade mark consists of a sign that, after the date of registration of the trade mark, has become 'generally accepted' within the relevant trade as the sign that describes or is the name of an article. As a result, s 24(1) has the effect of enlivening a limitation under s 24(2) of the Act on the exclusive rights of the registered owner to use or authorise others to use the sign in relation to the article and by operation of s 24(2)(b), the registered owner ' is taken to have ceased to have those exclusive rights from the day determined by the court under subsection (4). ' Subsection (4) provides that ' a prescribed court may determine the day on which a sign first became generally accepted within the relevant trade as the sign that describes or is the name of the article ... '. Although the respondent contends that the trade mark consists of a sign that has become generally accepted in the relevant trade as the sign that describes a fence dropper containing an S loop, the respondent says it cannot satisfy the temporal element and show that the sign became so 'generally accepted' after the date of registration of the trade mark. Accordingly, a defence in reliance upon s 24 of the Act has been abandoned.

16 The respondent relies upon a defence under s 25 of the Act on the footing that the trade mark contains a sign (the S loop shape) that describes a fence dropper that was formerly exploited by the applicant (or its predecessors in title) under a patent lodged on 9 October 1968 under the Patents Act 1952 (Cth) for a term of 16 years which expired on 9 October 1984. Thus, s 25(1)(a) and (b) are satisfied. The respondent says, consistent with s 25(1)(c) of the Act, the evidence demonstrates that ' the sign is the only commonly known way to describe or identify the article ... '. The respondent says that since the trade mark consists of the sign, the registered owner by reason of s 25(2)(a) and (b) does not have any exclusive rights to use or authorise others to use the sign in relation to the article and is taken to have ceased to have those rights from the end of the period of 2 years after the patent expired or ceased.

17 Section 25 is in these terms:
 
 25 Trade mark relating to article etc formerly manufactured under patent 
 
 (1) This section applies if: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) a registered trade mark consists of, or contains, a sign that describes or is the name of: 
 
 
 
 (i) an article or substance that was formerly exploited under a patent; or 
 (ii) a service that was formerly provided as a patented process; and 
 
 
 (b) it is at least 2 years since the patent has expired or ceased; and 
 
 
 
 
 (c) the sign is the only commonly known way to describe or identify the article, substance or service. 
 
 
 
 
 (2) If the trade mark consists of the sign, the registered owner: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) does not have any exclusive rights to use, or authorise other persons to use, the trade mark in relation to: 
 
 
 
 (i) the article or substance or other goods of the same description; or 
 (ii) the service or other services of the same description; and 
 
 
 
 (b) is taken to have ceased to have those exclusive rights from the end of the period of 2 years after the patent expired or ceased. 
 
 
 
 
 (3) If the trade mark contains the sign, the registered owner: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) does not have any exclusive rights to use, or authorise other persons to use, the sign in relation to: 
 
 
 
 (i) the article or substance or other goods of the same description; or 
 (ii) the service or other services of the same description; and 
 
 
 
 (b) is taken to have ceased to have those exclusive rights from the end of the period of 2 years after the patent expired or ceased.

18 The applicant says s 25 of the Act has no application because as a matter of orthodox language a trade mark consisting of or containing a three dimensional shape sign cannot 'describe' an article (formerly exploited under a patent) as only words can do that and the trade mark is not a word mark. Further, if the sign describes anything at all, it describes the S loop in the fence dropper which is only a part of an article not the article for the purposes of s 25(1) of the Act. If, however, s 25 does apply, the sign is not the 'only commonly known way' to describe the article. The applicant says the evidence shows other commonly known ways of 'describing' or 'identifying' the article.

19 The respondent also relies upon s 122 of the Act which provides for classes of conduct that 'in spite of s 120' do not constitute infringing conduct. The respondent says, consistent with s 122(1)(b)(i) that it has depicted the 'unique loop' in good faith to indicate the kind, quality, or intended purpose of the respondent's fence dropper or the characteristic of the respondent's dropper of effecting 'constituent, efficient securing loop(s)'. The respondent also relies upon s 122(1)(c) of the Act on the footing that the respondent has used the trade mark in good faith to indicate the intended purpose of goods. The applicant says the respondent has used the trade mark as a badge of origin not as an indication of those identified characteristics, and, in any event, the respondent did not do so in 'good faith.'

20 The respondent brings a cross-claim as a person aggrieved.

63 In Koninklijke Philips Electrics NV and Another v Remington Products Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 876 ; (2000) 100 FCR 90, the Full Court considered in the context of contended infringement of a two dimensional device mark for the configuration of three rotary shaving heads arranged in an equilateral triangle and a second two dimensional device mark (described as a three dimensional mark because the depiction was said to represent a three dimensional appearance) whether dealing (manufacture, importation and sale) in goods having that shape, being a functional shape depicted in each of the two dimensional device marks, constituted use of the mark ' upon, or in physical or other relation to the goods ', the subject of the registration. In addressing that question, the Court was considering marks depicting a configuration for rotary shaving heads forming part of an electric shaver that had been popular for over 30 years and a configuration of rotary heads that ' although not the only way in which to make an efficient rotary electric shaver, it is one of the best ways to do so and this model has proved extremely successful '. In respect of the second two dimensional mark, the applicants had incorporated within the registration a so-called ' disclaimer ' to the effect that 'registration of the mark would neither confer nor recognise any right to use its features as a design applied to an article of manufacture. Burchett J with whom Hill and Branson JJ agreed, concluded that a shape that goods possess because of their nature and the need for a particular functional or technical result, could not operate as a trade mark ([12]-[22]), that is:
 
 ... merely to produce and deal in goods having the shape, being a functional shape, of something depicted by a trade mark (here the marks do depict, one more completely than the other, a working part of a triple rotary shaver) is not to engage in a 'use' of the mark 'upon, or in physical or other relation to the goods'. [12].
 

And: 
 
 The alternative ways of using a trade mark in relation to goods do not include simply using the goods themselves as a trade mark. [12].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Smith Kline and French Laboratories (Aust) Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [1967] HCA 42 ; (1967) 116 CLR 628</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1967/42.html</AustLII>
<text>64 Having regard to Smith Kline and French Laboratories (Aust) Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [1967] HCA 42 ; (1967) 116 CLR 628 at 639-640 and an acceptance of the proposition put by Lehane J at first instance in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167 that the 1995 Act's introduction of shape signs (although intended to effect the result that a shape trade mark would find embodiment in goods or a part of goods), did not bring about a radical change of long accepted principle concerning functional use, Burchett J concluded that there has been no abandonment of the idea that goods have an existence, as goods , and a shape trade mark has an existence in relation to goods. As a result, the shape of goods (or of a part of goods) embodied by reason of the nature of the goods or a technical or functional result to be achieved by the goods could not distinguish the goods of one trade source from similar goods of another. [15]. The shape might distinguish or differentiate the goods as goods but not the trade source. Dealing in goods of that shape is thus use of the goods not use of the shape of those goods as a trade mark. Burchett J observed at [16]:
 
 The special cases where a shape of the goods may be a mark are cases falling within, not without, the principle he expounded [Windeyer J in Smith Kline]. For they are cases where the shape that is a mark is 'extra', added to the inherent form of the particular goods as something distinct which can denote origin. The goods can still be seen as having, in Windeyer J's words, 'an existence independently of the mark' which is imposed upon them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/1999/816.html</AustLII>
<text>64 Having regard to Smith Kline and French Laboratories (Aust) Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [1967] HCA 42 ; (1967) 116 CLR 628 at 639-640 and an acceptance of the proposition put by Lehane J at first instance in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167 that the 1995 Act's introduction of shape signs (although intended to effect the result that a shape trade mark would find embodiment in goods or a part of goods), did not bring about a radical change of long accepted principle concerning functional use, Burchett J concluded that there has been no abandonment of the idea that goods have an existence, as goods , and a shape trade mark has an existence in relation to goods. As a result, the shape of goods (or of a part of goods) embodied by reason of the nature of the goods or a technical or functional result to be achieved by the goods could not distinguish the goods of one trade source from similar goods of another. [15]. The shape might distinguish or differentiate the goods as goods but not the trade source. Dealing in goods of that shape is thus use of the goods not use of the shape of those goods as a trade mark. Burchett J observed at [16]:
 
 The special cases where a shape of the goods may be a mark are cases falling within, not without, the principle he expounded [Windeyer J in Smith Kline]. For they are cases where the shape that is a mark is 'extra', added to the inherent form of the particular goods as something distinct which can denote origin. The goods can still be seen as having, in Windeyer J's words, 'an existence independently of the mark' which is imposed upon them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Campamor Sociedad, Limitada &amp; Anor v Nike International Limited &amp; Anor [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/12.html</AustLII>
<text>72 Sections 24 and 25 of the 1995 Act are based on s 56 of the 1955 Act which owes its formulation in substantial part to s 15 of the United Kingdom Trade Marks Act 1938. Section 56(1) of the 1955 Act provided that the registration of a trade mark did not become invalid by reason only of the use, after the date of registration, of a word or words which the trade mark contained or of which it consisted, as the name or description of an article. As to invalidity, the Court in Campamor Sociedad, Limitada &amp; Anor v Nike International Limited &amp; Anor [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Callinan JJ, approved the view of Taylor J in F H Faulding &amp; Co Ltd v Imperial Chemical Industries of Australia and New Zealand Ltd [1964] HCA 38 ; (1965) 112 CLR 537 at 560-561 that s 56 operated as a provision intended to define exhaustively what manner of use after registration of a registered word trade mark would operate to invalidate the mark. Section 56(2)(b) of the 1955 Act provided that where an article was formerly manufactured under a patent, a period of two years had elapsed since the patent ceased or expired and the word which the trade mark contained or of which it consisted, was the only practicable name or description of the article, particular consequences arose. They were these. If the trade mark consisted solely of that word, the registration of the trade mark 'so far as regards registration in respect of the article ... or of any goods of the same description, ... shall be deemed for the purposes of s 22 to be an entry wrongly remaining in the Register' (s 56(3)). Section 22(1) of the 1955 Act provided that a prescribed Court 'may, on the application of a person aggrieved or the Registrar, order the rectification of the Register by [among other things] the expunging or amendment of an entry wrongly made in or remaining in the Register'. If, however, the trade mark contained that word and other matter, s 56(4) provided that a prescribed Court, in deciding whether the trade mark ought to remain in the Register in relation to the article or any goods of the same description, 'may, in the case of a decision in favour of the trade mark remaining in the Register, require as a condition that the proprietor shall disclaim any right to the exclusive use of that word in relation to that article or to any goods of the same description ... but no such disclaimer affects any rights of the proprietor of the trade mark except such as arise out of the registration of the trade mark in respect of which the disclaimer is made'. Section 56(5) contained a provision which had the effect of deeming rights of the registered owner to have ceased. That provision was in these terms:
 
 (5) For the purposes of any other legal proceedings relating to the trade mark - 
 
 
 
 
 (a) if the trade mark consists solely of that word, all rights of the registered proprietor to the exclusive use of the trade mark; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) if the trade mark contains that word and other matter, all rights of the registered proprietor to the exclusive use of that word, 
 
 
 
 
 in relation to the article ... or to any goods of the same description ... shall be deemed to have ceased on the date at which the use mentioned in paragraph (a) of sub-section (2) first became well-known and established, or at the expiration of the period of two years mentioned in paragraph (b) of that sub-section.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>F H Faulding &amp; Co Ltd v Imperial Chemical Industries of Australia and New Zealand Ltd [1964] HCA 38 ; (1965) 112 CLR 537</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/38.html</AustLII>
<text>72 Sections 24 and 25 of the 1995 Act are based on s 56 of the 1955 Act which owes its formulation in substantial part to s 15 of the United Kingdom Trade Marks Act 1938. Section 56(1) of the 1955 Act provided that the registration of a trade mark did not become invalid by reason only of the use, after the date of registration, of a word or words which the trade mark contained or of which it consisted, as the name or description of an article. As to invalidity, the Court in Campamor Sociedad, Limitada &amp; Anor v Nike International Limited &amp; Anor [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Callinan JJ, approved the view of Taylor J in F H Faulding &amp; Co Ltd v Imperial Chemical Industries of Australia and New Zealand Ltd [1964] HCA 38 ; (1965) 112 CLR 537 at 560-561 that s 56 operated as a provision intended to define exhaustively what manner of use after registration of a registered word trade mark would operate to invalidate the mark. Section 56(2)(b) of the 1955 Act provided that where an article was formerly manufactured under a patent, a period of two years had elapsed since the patent ceased or expired and the word which the trade mark contained or of which it consisted, was the only practicable name or description of the article, particular consequences arose. They were these. If the trade mark consisted solely of that word, the registration of the trade mark 'so far as regards registration in respect of the article ... or of any goods of the same description, ... shall be deemed for the purposes of s 22 to be an entry wrongly remaining in the Register' (s 56(3)). Section 22(1) of the 1955 Act provided that a prescribed Court 'may, on the application of a person aggrieved or the Registrar, order the rectification of the Register by [among other things] the expunging or amendment of an entry wrongly made in or remaining in the Register'. If, however, the trade mark contained that word and other matter, s 56(4) provided that a prescribed Court, in deciding whether the trade mark ought to remain in the Register in relation to the article or any goods of the same description, 'may, in the case of a decision in favour of the trade mark remaining in the Register, require as a condition that the proprietor shall disclaim any right to the exclusive use of that word in relation to that article or to any goods of the same description ... but no such disclaimer affects any rights of the proprietor of the trade mark except such as arise out of the registration of the trade mark in respect of which the disclaimer is made'. Section 56(5) contained a provision which had the effect of deeming rights of the registered owner to have ceased. That provision was in these terms:
 
 (5) For the purposes of any other legal proceedings relating to the trade mark - 
 
 
 
 
 (a) if the trade mark consists solely of that word, all rights of the registered proprietor to the exclusive use of the trade mark; or 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) if the trade mark contains that word and other matter, all rights of the registered proprietor to the exclusive use of that word, 
 
 
 
 
 in relation to the article ... or to any goods of the same description ... shall be deemed to have ceased on the date at which the use mentioned in paragraph (a) of sub-section (2) first became well-known and established, or at the expiration of the period of two years mentioned in paragraph (b) of that sub-section.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>EOS (Aust) Pty Ltd v Expo Tomei Pty Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 277</tocase>
<text>75 Section 87(1) confers a discretion on the Court to order cancellation of the registration of the trade mark. That discretion is to be exercised according to its terms and, where appropriate, settled principle. The discretion is to be exercised subject to s 87(2) which identifies circumstances in which the Court might decide not to make an order. Similarly, the Court might by s 89 of the Act decide 'not to grant an application under s 87' and therefore refuse to make an order which, is itself, an exercise of the discretion, if the registered owner satisfies the Court that the ground relied on by the applicant 'has not arisen through any act or fault of the registered owner'. In terms, the discretion must not only be exercised taking account of s 87(2) and s 89 but having regard to the effect of s 25 on the right of the registered owner of the trade mark. It seems to me that all these matters must be weighed carefully in the balance to determine whether the Court ought to cancel the registration of a trade mark and, in consequence, extinguish rights conferred by the Act on the registered owner. The discretion is a true discretion in the sense that all the matters going to s 25 (the circumstances of this case) must be considered, the particular circumstances of the applicant, any relevant s 87(2) factors, the conduct of the registered owner and the effect upon the rights of the registered owner brought about by the operation of s 25. Some of these factors will weigh heavily as s 25, for example, has the applied effect of declaring that the registered owner has no exclusive rights. In that sense, the discretion may seem facultative only ( EOS (Aust) Pty Ltd v Expo Tomei Pty Ltd (1998) 42 IPR 277, per Branson J). However, the Court is required to determine whether an order ought to be made or refused taking account of the identified considerations. Although those considerations are more limited than the reference in s 22(1)(b) of the 1955 Act which conditioned the discretion as 'subject to the Act', s 87(1) requires the Court to consider particular matters or circumstances by drawing within s 87(1) the specific matters, facts and circumstances contained in s 87(2) and s 89. Moreover, an order for cancellation of the registration of a trade mark is one of and perhaps the most significant intervention a Court might make in granting remedial orders inter-parties or on the application of the Registrar. That suggests that the Court is required to consider and weigh (within the bounds identified by the section) whether an order ought to be made in all the relevant circumstances. Accordingly, the term 'may' in s 87(1) ought not to be read as 'must upon the application of s 25 but subject to subsection (2) and section 89, order' etc. The power conferred on the Court in respect of cancellation under s 87(1) involves the exercise of a discretion as much as s 22 of the 1955 Act involved the exercise of a discretion in relation to expungement ( Campomar v Nike (supra) [87], p 80, the Court).

76 Section 87(2) like s 87(1) contemplates the application of either s 24 or s 25 in relation to a trade mark and uses the language 'because the trade mark contains a sign' and then sets out alternatives that fulfil the content of the application of either s 24 or s 25. The first alternative relates to the circumstances engaging s 24, namely, 'because the trade mark contains a sign that (a) has become generally accepted within the relevant trade as the sign that describes or is the name of an article ...'. The second relates to the circumstances engaging s 25, namely 'because the trade mark contains a sign that describes or is the name of an article that was formerly exploited under a patent'. In either case, the Court may decide not to make an order under s 87(1) and allow the trade mark to remain on the Register in respect of the article or goods of the same description subject to any condition or limitation the Court may impose. Section 25 of the 1995 Act maintains the distinction evident in s 56 of the 1955 Act between a trade mark that contains subject matter (a word or words in s 56) and one that consists of that subject matter. Differential consequences arise for each. Section 87(1) is predicated upon the application of s 25 which applies in the circumstances set out in s 25(1). Section 87(2) so far as s 25 is concerned, addresses a circumstance where s 25 applies because the trade mark contains a sign rather than consists of the sign and secondly, because the trade mark describes or is the name of an article. Section 87(2) does not also require for its operation that the sign is the only commonly known way to describe or identify the article. Once s 25 applies according to its terms, the discretion in s 87(1) is enlivened. Subject to its terms, the exercise of the discretion must take into account whether an order ought not to be made in the case of a trade mark containing a sign that describes or is the name of an article formerly exploited under a patent. Since the trade mark in this case consists of the sign rather than 'contains' a sign (among other elements) s 87(2) has no operation for the purposes of s 87(1).

77 Are the elements of s 25(1)(a), (b) and (c) satisfied?

78 The trade mark's legislation of the Commonwealth has been evolving over time and now comprehends any shape, colour, sound or scent as a possible trade mark. Section 25 must be given a purposive construction consistent with the evolution of the Act to contemporary circumstances. The elements of s 25(1) on the facts of this case, are these.

79 The trade mark consists of the sign as it is the entirety of the trade mark.

80 The sign is a shape.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Bali Brassiere Co Inc Registered Trade Mark: An Application by v Berlei Limited [1968] HCA 72 ; (1968) 118 CLR 128</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/72.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The respondent says the 1995 Act by introducing the notion of a 'shape' within the definition of 'sign' in s 6 of the Act and thus within the definition of a 'trade mark' in s 17 of the Act as a ' sign used, or intended to be used, to distinguish goods or services dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods or services so dealt with or provided by any other person ' did not bring about the radical change of providing that a registered trade mark would have the effect of restricting access to functional features or innovations. The respondent says the trade mark law of this country recognises a continuing fundamental distinction between a shape, whether expressed in part or the entirety of the goods the subject of the registration, that has an element of 'functional significance' and a shape which bears no functional significance. The respondent says, consistent with observations in Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494, were the 1995 Act to enable a registered trade mark to give the owner a monopoly over functional features (and thus suit for infringement of such a registered trade mark) it would indeed have made a radical change to trade mark law and nothing in the Act or in the discussions that preceded it suggest that such a result was intended. Therefore, it follows, it is said, that in the context of contended infringement, once the evidence demonstrates that the shape serves some functional significance, use of the shape (the trade mark) cannot be use as a trade mark. In such a case, it is said the shape adopted in the respondent's goods and consequential use of the shape in brochures and advertising material does not differentiate or distinguish the goods as a badge of origin of the user as a purveyor of those goods but serves to identify (distinguish) the content or features of the goods themselves. In other words, the respondent uses the shape to say in trade 'these are the goods that I sell' not 'know me as the seller or purveyor of these goods by this shape' (although, for trade mark use purposes, the seller need not be specifically identified).

64 Having regard to Smith Kline and French Laboratories (Aust) Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [1967] HCA 42 ; (1967) 116 CLR 628 at 639-640 and an acceptance of the proposition put by Lehane J at first instance in Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV &amp; Anor v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 816 ; (1999) 91 FCR 167 that the 1995 Act's introduction of shape signs (although intended to effect the result that a shape trade mark would find embodiment in goods or a part of goods), did not bring about a radical change of long accepted principle concerning functional use, Burchett J concluded that there has been no abandonment of the idea that goods have an existence, as goods , and a shape trade mark has an existence in relation to goods. As a result, the shape of goods (or of a part of goods) embodied by reason of the nature of the goods or a technical or functional result to be achieved by the goods could not distinguish the goods of one trade source from similar goods of another. [15]. The shape might distinguish or differentiate the goods as goods but not the trade source. Dealing in goods of that shape is thus use of the goods not use of the shape of those goods as a trade mark. Burchett J observed at [16]:
 
 The special cases where a shape of the goods may be a mark are cases falling within, not without, the principle he expounded [Windeyer J in Smith Kline]. For they are cases where the shape that is a mark is 'extra', added to the inherent form of the particular goods as something distinct which can denote origin. The goods can still be seen as having, in Windeyer J's words, 'an existence independently of the mark' which is imposed upon them.

105 Section 122(1) of the Act like s 64(1) of the 1955 Act, assumes infringing conduct on the part of the respondent that is excused when the person uses a sign in good faith to indicate one or more of the identified characteristics. Section 64(1)(b) contemplated use in good faith by a person 'of a description of the character or quality of his goods' whereas s 122(1)(b)(i) concerns use in good faith to indicate a broader range of characteristics. The essential concern going to good faith in s 122(1) is that the use be honest. Something less than fraudulent intention in the common law sense will suffice to prevent use being in good faith ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling (supra), per Gummow J at p 356). There must be however, identified conduct on the part of the respondent that demonstrates use of the sign in circumstances where Mr Hastie has engaged in conscious and deliberate acts to undermine the registered owner or the integrity of the trade mark. Has the respondent sought to undermine the trade mark by the 'assiduous efforts of an infringer? ( Johnson &amp; Johnson v Sterling per Gummow J at p 355 adopting the phrase used by Windeyer J in Re Bali Brassiere Co Inc Registered Trade Mark: An Application by v Berlei Limited [1968] HCA 72 ; (1968) 118 CLR 128 at 133). A conscious decision to try and render generic, a trade mark which on advice from reputable patent and trade mark attorneys would be infringed by use is an example ( Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd v Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Ltd (1990) 96 ALR 277 at 311 per Hill J). In that case, the decision by Johnson &amp; Johnson to use the trade mark was made with 'full knowledge' of the registration with advice that use would constitute infringement of the mark; and in circumstances where use was part of an international strategy to undermine the mark by rendering it generic. Since those ulterior motives subsisted, the use was found not to be honest. In this case, Mr Hastie had worked with and had been responsible for manufacturing S shaped wire droppers since 1978. He knew of the licence agreement between National Nail and Cyclone and knew that the improved dropper was the subject of a patent in New Zealand. He knew that royalties had been paid under the licence until the expiry of the prolongation period of the patent in New Zealand in 1986. Before entering the New Zealand market in 1996, Mr Hastie sought advice as to the patent position in that country. He understood that any patent had expired for the S shaped dropper. He assumed that there was no patent protection for it in Australia. He sought advice in 1996 from patent attorneys and he says he at least asked about the position in Australia. There is no independent written advice to Mr Hastie going to the position in Australia. I accept that Mr Hastie assumed in 2003 that there was no patent on foot in Australia but that he did not seek advice in 2003 as to the intellectual property position in Australia concerning the S dropper.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Currie v Dempsey [1967] 69 SR NSW 116</tocase>
<text>112 The right to obtain relief for infringement seems to me to be necessarily bound up with the grant of exclusive rights conferred by s 20(1). Since the grant of those exclusive rights is expressly subject to s 25 of the Act which, if satisfied, meets head on the exclusive rights conferred by s 20(1), it seems to me that proof of the subsistence of the exclusive rights is an essential element of the cause of action. In other words, the allegation made by the respondent is a denial of an essential ingredient in a cause of action and once raised and an evidential onus discharged, the persuasive onus falls upon the applicant. The structure of ss 20(1), 25 and 120(1) seem to fall within the general rule Walsh JA had in mind in Currie v Dempsey [1967] 69 SR NSW 116 at 125; [1967] 2 NSWR 532 when his Honour said:
 
 But, if recourse is had to the rules of pleading, the fixing of the burden of proof is not always to be tested simply by asking which party is alleging the affirmative. In Purkess v Crittenden it was said that the proposition there quoted from Phipson on evidence, 10 th Ed, par. 92, has been frequently acknowledged. The proposition was that the expression 'the burden of proof' as applied to judicial proceedings, 'has two distinct and frequently confused meanings: (1) the burden of proof as a matter of law and pleading the burden, as it has been called, of establishing a case, whether by preponderance of evidence, or beyond reasonable doubt; and (2) the burden of proof in the sense of introducing evidence'. The author went on to say, and this was also approved in the case last cited, that the burden of proof in the first sense is always stable, but the burden of proof in the second sense may shift constantly. 
 
 In my opinion, the burden of proof in the first sense lies on a plaintiff, if the fact alleged (whether affirmative or negative in form) is an essential element in his cause of action, e.g., if its existence is a condition precedent to his right to maintain the action. 
 
 The onus is on the defendant, if the allegation is not a denial of an essential ingredient in the cause of action, but is one which, if established, will constitute a good defence, that is, an 'avoidance' of the claim which, prima facie, the plaintiff has.

113 The respondent seeks to avoid the plaintiff's claim by demonstrating that s 25 applies with the result that the applicant does not have any exclusive rights. Whilst it is, of course, true that the respondent seeks to avoid the plaintiff's claim in that way, the matters raised by the respondent having regard to s 20 and s 25 are properly characterised as a denial of an essential ingredient in the cause of action. Although s 120(1) does not speak in terms of the exclusive rights of the registered owner of the trade mark, the right to obtain relief is predicated upon and is conferred in support of the exclusive rights of the registered owner. If the registered owner, by operation of s 25, does not have any exclusive rights, it would be an odd notion that the registered owner could seek and obtain relief in respect of the use by a respondent of a substantially identical trade mark. Accordingly, it seems to me that once the respondent puts the elements of s 25 in issue and adduces evidence of those matters, the persuasive onus falls upon the applicant.

114 In any event, in this matter the parties agree that the disposition of the controversy does not in any sense turn upon the discharge of the burden of proof wherever it lies. There is an abundance of evidence going to the question in controversy and the findings I have made are supported by a clear body of evidence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>