<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Fitzpatrick v Keelty [2008] FCA 35 (31 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/35.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bryant v Commonwealth Bank of Australia (1997) FCR 545</tocase>
<text>40 The meaning of s 60(4)(a) was also considered by the Full Court of the Federal Court in Bryant v Commonwealth Bank of Australia (1997) 75 FCR 545. O'Loughlin and Merkel JJ concluded that (at 564):
 
 ... Mr Bryant's causes of action, as pleaded in his statement of claim, are essentially claims which are referable to his financial and property rights. That is not to deny him his right to allege "personal injury or wrong done to" him or members of his family. But if the injury that was suffered or the wrong done arose as a direct result of the alleged infringements of his financial or property rights, as was the case in Faulkner v Bluett , then "the primary and substantial right of action is direct pecuniary loss to the property or estate of the bankrupt". (at 119) To apply the language of Handley JA in Manningell v Hewlett to Mr Bryant's circumstances his claims for stress and suffering were "consequential upon alleged breaches" of duty said to be owed to him by the Bank as a mortgagee or secured creditor and were not claims "without reference to [his] rights of property", within the principle stated by Dixon J in Cox v Journeaux .

41 The Court concluded that the loss complained of arose from direct pecuniary loss to the bankrupt's property.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cox v Journeaux (No 2) [1935] HCA 48 ; (1935) 52 CLR 713</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1935/48.html</AustLII>
<text>39 Subsection 60(5) provides that "action" means any civil proceedings whether at law or in equity. The test as to the meaning of the words "personal injury or wrong done to the bankrupt" is whether the damages or part of them are to be estimated by immediate reference to pain felt by the bankrupt in respect of his mind, body or character and without reference to his rights of property: see Cox v Journeaux (No 2) [1935] HCA 48 ; (1935) 52 CLR 713 at 721 per Dixon J.

42 The respondents have in effect submitted that in determining whether s 60(4) applies to the proceedings, the proper approach is to regard the proceedings as stemming from the termination of the applicant's employment. The respondents rely upon Pelechowski v NSW Land and Housing Commission [2000] FCA 233 in support of the proposition that s 60(4) does not apply to such proceedings . In Pelechowski , a judicial registrar had dismissed an application by the applicant for relief, finding that there was no substance in the application and that the applicant had been guilty of serious misconduct. Madgwick J concluded that proceedings for unlawful termination of employment under the WRA did not fall within the Cox test and thus s 60(4) did not apply, because an essential element of the proceeding was that one's economic relations with one's former employer had been disrupted and property rights were at the heart of such proceedings. His Honour's reasons were delivered ex tempore. His Honour noted that the applicant had principally sought reinstatement, that the relief sought was essentially of an economic nature, and that the application did not appear to have made any claim for compensation in the way of damages for personal injury. I am bound to follow this judgment unless I conclude it is plainly wrong. I have not reached that view.

47 His Honour said (at 55 - 56): 
 
 ... the words ["wrong done to the bankrupt"] cannot be taken in isolation. They must, in accordance with the ordinary canons of construction, be read in the context in which they appear. The meaning of the expression, taken from that context, has been explained in numerous cases. In Australia, the classic expression is that contained in the judgment of Dixon J in Cox v Journeaux ... 
 
 Applying that test to the present case, the action brought by the claimant cannot be categorised as he submits. Although it is true that the claimant contends that a "wrong" has been done to him and that he has suffered hurt and even "defamation"... these contentions are irrelevant to the task of identifying, for the purpose of s 60(4)(a) of the Act, the nature of the action exempted from the stay. The exemption is limited to those cases where it has been considered appropriate to sever the personal interests of the person subsequently made bankrupt from his property, and to reserve to him the prosecution of and benefits derived from such litigation as not being legitimately entitlements of the creditors. ...

48 His Honour went on to take into account, in characterising the proceedings, the fact that the "wrong" was "the very source of the financial problems which have led to his bankruptcy" and that the proceedings involved "the very essence of the subject matter to which s 60(2) is addressed" (at 56). In the present proceedings, there is nothing to suggest that the applicant's bankruptcy was connected in any way with the "personal injury" or "wrongs" of which the applicant now complains. However, his Honour's preceding observations concerning the nature of cases in which the exemption in s 60(4) applies are of general application.

49 An issue which has arisen in a number of cases is whether it is possible to sever or separate certain causes of action which would fall within s 60(4) from other aspects of the proceedings. In Byrant , Lockhart J (at 548-549) discussed a number of cases where there were mixed causes of action, some of which were found to have vested in the trustee and others not. From the cases considered by Lockhart J, his Honour distilled the principle that a claim for damages for injury to personal and mental health will not fall within the exemption in s 60(4) where the claim cannot be made without reference to the bankrupt's rights of property.

54 The respondents submit that to the extent that the applicant has raised claims in negligence which may fall within the Cox test, the proceedings have no reasonable prospect of success. The respondents cited Tame v New South Wales; Annetts v Australian Stations Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 35 ; (2002) 211 CLR 317 in support of the proposition that an investigating officer does not owe a duty of care to a person whose conduct is under investigation because it is inconsistent with a police officer's duty. Investigators in internal disciplinary investigations also do not owe a duty of care to the employee being investigated: see State of New South Wales v Paige [2002] NSWCA 235 ; (2002) 60 NSWLR 371. The respondents also submit that there is no suggestion in the material filed by the applicant that the actions complained of occurred outside any officer's course of duty, and that the actions should therefore be dealt with in accordance with the authorities cited. The respondents also submit that to the extent that the applicant seeks damages for psychological injury, damages for negligence are not available for psychological injury falling short of a recognised psychiatric disorder: see Tame v State of New South Wales . The applicant has not pleaded any relevant psychiatric disorder.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Daemar v Industrial Commission of New South Wales and Another ( No 2 ) (1990) 99 ALR 789</tocase>
<text>37 The respondents submit that as a result of the deemed abandonment of the proceedings, the stay provided by s 60(2) continues to operate, referring to the discussion by Ipp J in Stobbart v Mocnaj (1996) 16 WAR 318 at 323. The effect of the deemed abandonment of the proceedings, where the applicant may not continue the proceedings in his own name, is that the proceedings are stayed: Daemar v Industrial Commission of New South Wales and Another (No 2) (1990) 99 ALR 789, per Kirby P at 790.

38 The respondents submit that neither of the proceedings fall within the description in s 60(4) (an action in respect of any personal injury or wrong) and thus neither may be continued by the bankrupt. The respondents also submit that to the extent that it could be said that the applicant has identified causes of action which individually fall within s 60(4)(a) , those causes of action have not been properly pleaded and should be struck out or dismissed. The respondents identified the latter causes of action as potentially being:
 
&#8226; Causes of action for damages and other remedies for injuries allegedly done to the applicant and members of his family;
 
&#8226; Unlawful detention and deprivation of liberty;
 
&#8226; Unlawful interference with and possession of personal property; and
 
&#8226; Damages for injury to credit, character and reputation (defamation).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Daemar v Industrial Commission of New South Wales and Others (1988) 79 ALR 591</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fitzpatrick v Keelty [2007] FCA 1658</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1658.html</AustLII>
<text>30 The applicant is a bankrupt, pursuant to orders of the Federal Magistrates Court of 22 May 2007: see Kidney v Fitzpatrick [2007] FCMA 943. An application to set aside the bankruptcy notice had earlier been dismissed by the Federal Magistrates Court: see Fitzpatrick v Kidney [2007] FMCA 942. An appeal from those orders, and certain related orders, was dismissed by a judge of this Court (Madgwick J) on 19 September 2007: see Fitzpatrick v Keelty [2007] FCA 1658. His Honour did not "order a stay or injunction or do anything else of the kind that would prevent the ordinary operation of s 60 of the [Bankruptcy] Act" (see [38] of his Honour's reasons). Other orders had also been made by the Federal Magistrates Court on 3 August 2007 in the context of an application for annulment, which were somewhat unusual: see Fitzpatrick v Kidney [2007] FMCA 1422. The effect of the orders was to make an order for annulment, but to stay the operation of that order for 28 days and subject the annulment to the fulfilment of certain conditions. There has been no suggestion that the conditions the subject of the orders of 3 August 2007 have been satisfied.

31 Section 60 of the Bankruptcy Act relevantly concerns the stay of legal proceedings commenced by a person who subsequently becomes a bankrupt. The section provides:
 
 
 (1) ... 
 (2) An action commenced by a person who subsequently becomes a bankrupt is, upon his or her becoming a bankrupt, stayed until the trustee makes election, in writing, to prosecute or discontinue the action. 
 (3) If the trustee does not make such an election within 28 days after notice of the action is served upon him or her by a defendant or other party to the action, he or she shall be deemed to have abandoned the action. 
 (4) Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, a bankrupt may continue, in his or her own name, an action commenced by him or her before he or she became a bankrupt in respect of: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) any personal injury or wrong done to the bankrupt, his or her spouse or a member of his or her family; or 
 
 
 
 (b) the death of his or her spouse or of a member of his or her family. 
 
 
 (4A) ... 
 
 
 (5) In this section, action means any civil proceeding, whether at law or in equity.

32 Prior to the hearing before me, an affidavit was filed by the respondents' solicitor, Ms Harvey, sworn 28 August 2007, deposing that the trustee had been served with notice of the two proceedings on 27 July 2007. The trustee was asked to advise of his election to prosecute or discontinue each of the actions within 28 days. Ms Harvey deposed that no response had been received. Accordingly, the proceedings are deemed abandoned pursuant to s 60(3). The issue is whether the applicant can continue any part of the proceedings in his own name pursuant to s 60(4).

33 At the time of the hearing of the present motions on 31 August 2007, the appeal to this Court (which led to the judgment of Madgwick J of 19 September 2007) was awaiting hearing. At the hearing before me, both parties made submissions concerning the effect of the orders of the Federal Magistrates Court. After Madgwick J's judgment was given, the parties were provided with an opportunity to make written submissions concerning the effect of that judgment on the present proceedings. Submissions were received from the applicant and the respondents.

34 The applicant's submissions, made both orally at the hearing and in written form afterwards, primarily concern the propriety and legality of the Federal Magistrate's orders of 3 August 2007. However, these proceedings do not involve a challenge to the Federal Magistrate's orders, nor were those orders challenged in the proceedings before Madgwick J: see his Honour's reasons at [33].

35 The applicant also submitted, at the hearing, that the sequestration order has no effect on these proceedings. He indicated that he relied upon s 60(4) , although he did not elaborate on these submissions, other than to make allegations of impropriety and illegality of the various orders made by the Federal Magistrates Court.

36 The applicant's written submissions on the bankruptcy issue provided post-hearing are lengthy and contain numerous allegations of impropriety and corruption variously relating to the creditor, the trustee, the respondents' solicitors, the Federal Magistrates by whom the relevant orders were made and the judge of this Court dismissing the appeal, and the processes involved. In terms of the effect of the applicant's bankruptcy, the applicant submits that it would not be appropriate for me to adjudicate on the proceedings he has brought in this Court until "all such complaints and allegations [concerning the bankruptcy action] have been subjected to full and proper independent inquiry/investigation in the interests of justice and, the integrity of our judicial system".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hamilton v Young [2007] QSC 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2007/1.html</AustLII>
<text>50 The Supreme Court of Queensland recently considered the issue of severance of claims under s 60(4) in Hamilton v Young [2007] QSC 160. The Court in Hamilton considered the issue of whether a claim for damages for the cost of raising an unplanned child can be characterised as claim for damages for "personal injury or wrong". The Court was not asked to stay the part of the bankrupt's claim for personal injuries, but was asked to stay that part of her action claiming damages for the cost of raising her child. Douglas J (at [11]) considered that the word "wrong" in s 60(4) identified a personal tort affecting the person or feelings of the bankrupt, and not, as in the circumstances in Hamilton , the loss to her of property caused by the expense of bringing up her child.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Pelechowski v NSW Land &amp; Housing Commission [2000] FCA 233</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2000/233.html</AustLII>
<text>42 The respondents have in effect submitted that in determining whether s 60(4) applies to the proceedings, the proper approach is to regard the proceedings as stemming from the termination of the applicant's employment. The respondents rely upon Pelechowski v NSW Land and Housing Commission [2000] FCA 233 in support of the proposition that s 60(4) does not apply to such proceedings . In Pelechowski , a judicial registrar had dismissed an application by the applicant for relief, finding that there was no substance in the application and that the applicant had been guilty of serious misconduct. Madgwick J concluded that proceedings for unlawful termination of employment under the WRA did not fall within the Cox test and thus s 60(4) did not apply, because an essential element of the proceeding was that one's economic relations with one's former employer had been disrupted and property rights were at the heart of such proceedings. His Honour's reasons were delivered ex tempore. His Honour noted that the applicant had principally sought reinstatement, that the relief sought was essentially of an economic nature, and that the application did not appear to have made any claim for compensation in the way of damages for personal injury. I am bound to follow this judgment unless I conclude it is plainly wrong. I have not reached that view.

43 Interestingly, in Pelechowski , the applicant had been an employee of the Department of Housing. His Honour noted that "[t]hose economic relations [with one's former employer] depend upon contract, or perhaps in the case of a public servant, a statutory relationship, but nevertheless of a contractual or quasi-contractual kind, that is to say, property rights are at the heart of the proceedings" (at [5]). His Honour's view therefore was that insofar as termination proceedings were concerned, no distinction was to be made between those employed pursuant to statute and other employees in the context of s 60(4).

51 The respondents were unable to point to any authorities concerning s 60(4) in which a question concerning or relating to the termination of employment arose in the context of proceedings for judicial review. In any event, I am satisfied that the judicial review proceedings the applicant has brought bear the same general character as the proceedings considered in Pelechowski and Daemar . In my opinion, all the "decisions" which the applicant seeks to challenge (leaving aside whether they are amenable to review) directly arise from or are incidental to the termination of his employment and do not fall within the exception in s 60(4).

52 As noted at [38], the respondents submit that certain causes of action which the applicant may be seeking to raise in one or both of the two proceedings and which may fall within s 60(4) should be dealt with in accordance with the respondents' motions (that is, that they be struck out or dismissed). The ability for the applicant to continue these causes of action also depends upon these actions being severed from those parts of the proceedings which do not fall within s 60(4). I propose to deal with those causes of action on the assumption that they can be treated, individually, as falling within s 60(4), as the respondents' submissions appeared to accept. I am satisfied that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting that part of the proceedings concerning those causes of action and that judgment should be given for the respondents.

53 One of these potential actions is defamation. The pleadings filed by the applicant refer in a general sense to damage to his character and reputation and to "defamation", as well as more specifically in relation to the contents of the reports and statements made by the respondents' solicitor in Court. As the respondents have submitted, the applicant has not particularised the statements, other than in the case of the alleged statements of the solicitor in relation to which he has provided more detail. He has not particularised the effect of any statements on his reputation. As the respondents have submitted, even if statements made by the solicitor were defamatory, the express defence of absolute privilege may well apply. I am satisfied that to the extent that the applicant has raised a cause of action in defamation there is no reasonable prospect of successful prosecution.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>