<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Winspear v Mackinnon [2008] FCA 322 (11 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/322.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Colgate-Palmolive Company v Cussons Pty Limited (1993) 46 FCR 225</tocase>
<text>4 The defendants resist the plaintiff's claim for indemnity costs. They contend, correctly, that the usual course is that costs are payable on a party and party basis, unless the circumstances of the case warrant a departure from that normal course; see Colgate-Palmolive Company v Cussons Pty Limited (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 233, per Sheppard J and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1844 at [3] and [17], per Gray J.

5 The categories of cases in which indemnity costs may be granted are not closed. The overriding consideration is the justice of the particular case. This includes the recognition that there are circumstances which justify the order of indemnity costs, including when a party unreasonably causes another party to incur costs; see Colgate-Palmolive at 233 and Leahy Petroleum at [17].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1844</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1844.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The defendants resist the plaintiff's claim for indemnity costs. They contend, correctly, that the usual course is that costs are payable on a party and party basis, unless the circumstances of the case warrant a departure from that normal course; see Colgate-Palmolive Company v Cussons Pty Limited (1993) 46 FCR 225 at 233, per Sheppard J and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1844 at [3] and [17], per Gray J.

5 The categories of cases in which indemnity costs may be granted are not closed. The overriding consideration is the justice of the particular case. This includes the recognition that there are circumstances which justify the order of indemnity costs, including when a party unreasonably causes another party to incur costs; see Colgate-Palmolive at 233 and Leahy Petroleum at [17].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>J Corp Pty Ltd v Australian Builders Labourers Federated Union of Workers, West Australia Branch (No 2) (1993) 46 IR 301</tocase>
<text>8 After the conclusion of the evidence, the defendants persisted "in what should on proper consideration be seen to be a hopeless case": see J Corp Pty Ltd v Australian Builders Labourers Federated Union of Workers, West Australia Branch (No 2) (1993) 46 IR 301 at 303 per French J. This is particularly so when they had about two weeks to reflect on their position before coming to Court on the final day of the hearing to present their submissions. In those circumstances, I consider that the plaintiff should have her costs with respect to the hearing on 28 November 2007 paid on an indemnity basis. Indeed, ultimately, counsel for the defendants did not oppose that course. There is no reason to depart from the usual order that costs follow the event in respect of the balance of the proceedings.

9 The remaining issue requiring resolution is which of the defendants should pay the plaintiff's costs. The plaintiff contends that it should be the first and second defendants. The defendants submit that it should be the first defendant only. I agree with the later submission. The first defendant was the key decision maker for the defendants. The second defendant is an elderly lady and her actions as a director of the third and fourth defendants were influenced by the first defendant. The evidence bears out that he decided, without reference to the second defendant, to deny the plaintiff her correct entitlement to shares in the third and fourth defendants.

10 As each party has had some degree of success in the matters requiring resolution today, no order will be made concerning the costs of today's hearing.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>