<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZDFZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 390 (2 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/390.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In reaching the conclusion that there is jurisdictional error, it is recognised that an error of fact does not of itself normally constitute error of law, let alone jurisdictional error: Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35 6 per Brennan J. In a context where there are competing facts, the weight to be ascribed to particular pieces of evidence is a matter entrusted by the legislature to the Tribunal for resolution. Mere disagreement with the ultimate finding of fact made does not expose error of law. And what may be described as " illogical or irrational " inferences drawn from the facts before the Tribunal may often be an unhelpful characterisation of the reasoning process and may amount to no more than a conclusion that a Court may have reached a different factual conclusion: cf Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 [2003] HCA 30 at [8] [9] per Gleeson CJ; [2003] HCA 30 ; 198 ALR 59. See also: NACB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 at [22] [30] per Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Commissioner for ACT Revenue v Alphaone Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1074 ; (1994) 49 FCR 576</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1074.html</AustLII>
<text>9 That obligation, it is considered, is not confined to an obligation to advise an applicant " of any adverse conclusion which has been arrived at ". In Commissioner for ACT Revenue v Alphaone Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1074 ; (1994) 49 FCR 576 at 591 2, Northrop, Miles and French JJ in an oft-cited passage observed:
 
 Where the exercise of a statutory power attracts the requirement for procedural fairness, a person likely to be affected by the decision is entitled to put information and submissions to the decision-maker in support of an outcome that supports his or her interests. That entitlement extends to the right to rebut or qualify by further information, and comment by way of submission, upon adverse material from other sources which is put before the decision-maker. It also extends to require the decision-maker to identify to the person affected any issue critical to the decision which is not apparent from its nature or the terms of the statute under which it is made. The decision-maker is required to advise of any adverse conclusion which has been arrived at which would not obviously be open on the known material. Subject to these qualifications however, a decision-maker is not obliged to expose his or her mental processes or provisional views to comment before making the decision in question. ...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>NACB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/235.html</AustLII>
<text>40 In reaching the conclusion that there is jurisdictional error, it is recognised that an error of fact does not of itself normally constitute error of law, let alone jurisdictional error: Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35 6 per Brennan J. In a context where there are competing facts, the weight to be ascribed to particular pieces of evidence is a matter entrusted by the legislature to the Tribunal for resolution. Mere disagreement with the ultimate finding of fact made does not expose error of law. And what may be described as " illogical or irrational " inferences drawn from the facts before the Tribunal may often be an unhelpful characterisation of the reasoning process and may amount to no more than a conclusion that a Court may have reached a different factual conclusion: cf Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 [2003] HCA 30 at [8] [9] per Gleeson CJ; [2003] HCA 30 ; 198 ALR 59. See also: NACB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 at [22] [30] per Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 [2003] HCA 30</tocase>
<text>40 In reaching the conclusion that there is jurisdictional error, it is recognised that an error of fact does not of itself normally constitute error of law, let alone jurisdictional error: Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35 6 per Brennan J. In a context where there are competing facts, the weight to be ascribed to particular pieces of evidence is a matter entrusted by the legislature to the Tribunal for resolution. Mere disagreement with the ultimate finding of fact made does not expose error of law. And what may be described as " illogical or irrational " inferences drawn from the facts before the Tribunal may often be an unhelpful characterisation of the reasoning process and may amount to no more than a conclusion that a Court may have reached a different factual conclusion: cf Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Applicant S20/2002 [2003] HCA 30 at [8] [9] per Gleeson CJ; [2003] HCA 30 ; 198 ALR 59. See also: NACB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 235 at [22] [30] per Tamberlin, Emmett and Weinberg JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Cohen [2001] HCA 10 , 177 ALR 473</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/10.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The Respondent Minister opposes the grant of relief. He seeks to define, and confine, the " issues " to be addressed for the purposes of s 425(1) as those defined by the delegate's decision initially refusing to grant the protection visa and thereafter to rely on the adverse findings of credit as made by the reconstituted Tribunal. That Tribunal, it is submitted by the Minister, made its own findings of fact which were open to it and, if there be any error, such errors it is submitted are errors of fact which normally do not give rise to jurisdictional error: SZINP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1747 at [26] , [29]; VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231 at [77] . See also: Waterford v Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77 per Brennan J; Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Cohen [2001] HCA 10 at [36] , [2001] HCA 10 ; 177 ALR 473 per McHugh J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SFGB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 231 , 77 ALD 402</tocase>
<text>42 But what does matter is whether such an error, when it does occur, can be characterised as a jurisdictional error. In the present circumstances it is considered that it can. In SFGB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 231 , 77 ALD 402 Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ observed:
 
 [19] ... If the Tribunal makes a finding and that finding is a critical step in its ultimate conclusion and there is no evidence to support that finding then this may well constitute a jurisdictional error ...
 

And, in SZDTZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1824 Greenwood J reviewed some of the authorities (including SFGB ) and concluded:
 
 [31] The central matter is this.
 
 [32] A determination of the Tribunal as to a state of satisfaction or otherwise, of the relevant criteria or criterion in question, that is based upon a finding of fact or inferences drawn from facts, not based on logical or rational grounds, will give rise to an error of jurisdiction if there is no evidence to support the finding or no proper basis for drawing the inference; or, if there be some evidence, although inadequate, reliance by the Tribunal upon that inadequate evidence gives rise to an inference that the Tribunal has misconceived the test or is not, in reality, satisfied of the requisite matters, as a result of which there has been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of the power conferred upon the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 , 228 CLR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>10 " Considerable care ", however, needs to be exercised in effecting a dichotomy between an " adverse conclusion ... which would not obviously be open on the known material" and " mental processes ": SZBEL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 at [31] , [2006] HCA 63 ; 228 CLR 152 at 162. Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ there referred to the argument then being advanced seeking to advance such a dichotomy and then applying that dichotomy to the facts before the Court. Their Honours observed:
 
 [31] Stated in this way, the argument seeks to elucidate the content of the requirements of procedural fairness by setting up a dichotomy. There are two reasons to exercise considerable care in approaching the problem in that way. First, it is far from clear that the two categories that are identified (conclusions not obviously open on the known material, and mental processes of decision-making) encompass all possible kinds of case that may fall for consideration. Secondly, there is a very real risk that focusing upon these two categories will distract attention from the fundamental principles that are engaged. 

 Their Honours continued:
 
 [33] The Act defines the nature of the opportunity to be heard that is to be given to an applicant for review by the Tribunal. The applicant is to be invited "to give evidence and present arguments relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review" (s 425(1) (emphasis added)). The reference to "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review" is important.
 
 [34] Those issues will not be sufficiently identified in every case by describing them simply as whether the applicant is entitled to a protection visa. The statutory language "arising in relation to the decision under review" is more particular. The issues arising in relation to a decision under review are to be identified having regard not only to the fact that the Tribunal may exercise (s 415) all the powers and discretions conferred by the Act on the original decision-maker (here, the Minister's delegate), but also to the fact that the Tribunal is to review that particular decision, for which the decision-maker will have given reasons.
 
 [35] The Tribunal is not confined to whatever may have been the issues that the delegate considered. The issues that arise in relation to the decision are to be identified by the Tribunal. But if the Tribunal takes no step to identify some issue other than those that the delegate considered dispositive, and does not tell the applicant what that other issue is, the applicant is entitled to assume that the issues the delegate considered dispositive are "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review". That is why the point at which to begin the identification of issues arising in relation to the decision under review will usually be the reasons given for that decision. And unless some other additional issues are identified by the Tribunal (as they may be), it would ordinarily follow that, on review by the Tribunal, the issues arising in relation to the decision under review would be those which the original decision-maker identified as determinative against the applicant.

11 The Appellant in the present appeal has pursued a course whereby his application has been rejected by the delegate and thereafter considered by the Refugee Review Tribunal on two occasions -- the first being its decision in February 2004; the second being that of the reconstituted Tribunal in October 2006.

12 The delegate concluded in part as follows:
 
 3.2.4 I accept that the applicant may have been a supporter of a political party in Bangladesh that is currently opposed to the present BNP led government. ...
 
 3.2.5 ... The information above indicates that merely belonging to an opposition party does not attract persecution in Bangladesh.
 

These and other findings led the delegate to conclude that the now Appellant did not have a real chance of being persecuted should he return to Bangladesh.

19 First, it is not considered that " the issues arising in relation to the decision under review " are to be defined in all cases by the decision of the delegate. Their Honours in SZBEL did observe:
 
 ... But if the Tribunal takes no step to identify some issue other than those that the delegate considered dispositive, and does not tell the applicant what that other issue is, the applicant is entitled to assume that the issues the delegate considered dispositive are "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review"....
 

 The issues which a delegate considers dispositive of the application may well be the issues which an applicant has to confront and answer when an appeal is lodged with the tribunal, eg SZJKU v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 308 at [37] [45] per Emmett J. But the object of s 425 is to ensure that an applicant is given an opportunity " to give evidence and present arguments ", being evidence and argument " relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review ". And that is an obligation imposed upon the tribunal hearing the application before it, whether it be the tribunal initially hearing the application or any subsequent tribunal.

24 To give the terms of s 425(1) the width of operation that naturally follows from the terminology employed by the Parliamentary draftsman does not transgress the qualifications recognised by their Honours in SZBEL , supra , namely that there are many ways in which a tribunal may indicate to an applicant that it questions the account being given and that there is no requirement upon a tribunal to give a " running account " of the evidence.

25 As to the former qualification, their Honours in SZBEL observed:
 
[47] ... there may well be cases, perhaps many cases, where either the delegate's decision, or the Tribunal's statements or questions during a hearing, sufficiently indicate to an applicant that everything he or she says in support of the application is in issue. That indication may be given in many ways. It is not necessary (and often would be inappropriate) for the Tribunal to put to an applicant, in so many words, that he or she is lying, that he or she may not be accepted as a witness of truth, or that he or she may be thought to be embellishing the account that is given of certain events. The proceedings are not adversarial and the Tribunal is not, and is not to adopt the position of, a contradictor. But where, as here, there are specific aspects of an applicant's account, that the Tribunal considers may be important to the decision and may be open to doubt, the Tribunal must at least ask the applicant to expand upon those aspects of the account and ask the applicant to explain why the account should be accepted.

26 Rather than narrowly confining the identification of those matters which may constitute " issues " to which s 425(1) applies, it is considered that their Honours were there recognising that the " issues " arising in relation to a decision may be many and various and were recognising that there had to be a practical manner in which tribunal members could extend to an applicant an opportunity to " give evidence and present arguments " in relation to those " specific matters " that may assume importance.

27 Third, reliance by the Respondent Minister in the current appeal upon the adverse findings made by the reconstituted Tribunal is also not considered persuasive. The obligation imposed by s 425 upon a Tribunal is to extend the invitation there set forth. If that invitation has not been extended, and it should have been, it matters not that the Tribunal has thereafter proceeded in a manner which necessarily involves it in making factual findings. Indeed, the importance of s 425 is to ensure that the process of making those findings of fact is a process informed by, or at least assisted by, the evidence and arguments presented by an applicant.

28 If the application of s 425 is not to be confined in the narrow manner being urged by the First Respondent, it remains to consider whether the reconstituted Tribunal did in fact put the now Appellant on notice that some " specific " issues which had previously been resolved in his favour remained matters in respect to which it had reservations. It remains to consider whether the reconstituted Tribunal did in fact extend to the Appellant a meaningful opportunity " to give evidence and present arguments " in respect to those " specific " issues.

29 It is considered that the reconstituted Tribunal did not give the Appellant such an opportunity. The manner in which the Tribunal as reconstituted discharged its task of giving the Appellant such an opportunity was a matter for it. But the failure of the Tribunal to extend the opportunity emerges because nowhere in the transcript of the proceedings is there any indication given to the Appellant that he could not proceed upon the basis that he was, in summary, a person with a long record of political activities and a person who remained politically active.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZDTZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1824</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1824.html</AustLII>
<text>42 But what does matter is whether such an error, when it does occur, can be characterised as a jurisdictional error. In the present circumstances it is considered that it can. In SFGB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 231 , 77 ALD 402 Mansfield, Selway and Bennett JJ observed:
 
 [19] ... If the Tribunal makes a finding and that finding is a critical step in its ultimate conclusion and there is no evidence to support that finding then this may well constitute a jurisdictional error ...
 

And, in SZDTZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1824 Greenwood J reviewed some of the authorities (including SFGB ) and concluded:
 
 [31] The central matter is this.
 
 [32] A determination of the Tribunal as to a state of satisfaction or otherwise, of the relevant criteria or criterion in question, that is based upon a finding of fact or inferences drawn from facts, not based on logical or rational grounds, will give rise to an error of jurisdiction if there is no evidence to support the finding or no proper basis for drawing the inference; or, if there be some evidence, although inadequate, reliance by the Tribunal upon that inadequate evidence gives rise to an inference that the Tribunal has misconceived the test or is not, in reality, satisfied of the requisite matters, as a result of which there has been only a purported, rather than a real, exercise of the power conferred upon the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZINP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1747</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1747.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The Respondent Minister opposes the grant of relief. He seeks to define, and confine, the " issues " to be addressed for the purposes of s 425(1) as those defined by the delegate's decision initially refusing to grant the protection visa and thereafter to rely on the adverse findings of credit as made by the reconstituted Tribunal. That Tribunal, it is submitted by the Minister, made its own findings of fact which were open to it and, if there be any error, such errors it is submitted are errors of fact which normally do not give rise to jurisdictional error: SZINP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1747 at [26] , [29]; VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231 at [77] . See also: Waterford v Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77 per Brennan J; Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Cohen [2001] HCA 10 at [36] , [2001] HCA 10 ; 177 ALR 473 per McHugh J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZJKU v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 308</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/308.html</AustLII>
<text>19 First, it is not considered that " the issues arising in relation to the decision under review " are to be defined in all cases by the decision of the delegate. Their Honours in SZBEL did observe:
 
 ... But if the Tribunal takes no step to identify some issue other than those that the delegate considered dispositive, and does not tell the applicant what that other issue is, the applicant is entitled to assume that the issues the delegate considered dispositive are "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review"....
 

 The issues which a delegate considers dispositive of the application may well be the issues which an applicant has to confront and answer when an appeal is lodged with the tribunal, eg SZJKU v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 308 at [37] [45] per Emmett J. But the object of s 425 is to ensure that an applicant is given an opportunity " to give evidence and present arguments ", being evidence and argument " relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review ". And that is an obligation imposed upon the tribunal hearing the application before it, whether it be the tribunal initially hearing the application or any subsequent tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/231.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The Respondent Minister opposes the grant of relief. He seeks to define, and confine, the " issues " to be addressed for the purposes of s 425(1) as those defined by the delegate's decision initially refusing to grant the protection visa and thereafter to rely on the adverse findings of credit as made by the reconstituted Tribunal. That Tribunal, it is submitted by the Minister, made its own findings of fact which were open to it and, if there be any error, such errors it is submitted are errors of fact which normally do not give rise to jurisdictional error: SZINP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1747 at [26] , [29]; VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231 at [77] . See also: Waterford v Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77 per Brennan J; Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Cohen [2001] HCA 10 at [36] , [2001] HCA 10 ; 177 ALR 473 per McHugh J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Waterford v Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/25.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The Respondent Minister opposes the grant of relief. He seeks to define, and confine, the " issues " to be addressed for the purposes of s 425(1) as those defined by the delegate's decision initially refusing to grant the protection visa and thereafter to rely on the adverse findings of credit as made by the reconstituted Tribunal. That Tribunal, it is submitted by the Minister, made its own findings of fact which were open to it and, if there be any error, such errors it is submitted are errors of fact which normally do not give rise to jurisdictional error: SZINP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1747 at [26] , [29]; VWFP and VWFQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 231 at [77] . See also: Waterford v Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77 per Brennan J; Re Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Cohen [2001] HCA 10 at [36] , [2001] HCA 10 ; 177 ALR 473 per McHugh J.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>