<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Yang v American International Assurance Company (Australia) Ltd [2008] FCA 39 (12 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/39.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/18.html</AustLII>
<text>71 The High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 discussed the concept of unconscionable conduct as used in s 51AA of the Act. Gleeson CJ at 62 accepted that 'special disadvantage' meant a disabling circumstance seriously affecting the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment in that party's own best interests. Gleeson CJ (referring to the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [2002] FCAFC 4 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301) said in Berbatis [2003] HCA 18 ; 214 CLR 51 at 64:
 
 A person is not in a position of relevant disadvantage, constitutional, situational, or otherwise, simply because of inequality of bargaining power. Many, perhaps even most, contracts are made between parties of unequal bargaining power, and good conscience does not require parties to contractual negotiations to forfeit their advantages, or neglect their own interests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leelee Pty Ltd and Anor (2000) ATPR 41-742</tocase>
<text>74 Section 51AC commenced operation on 1 July 1998 and as such the applicants can only rely on their claim under this section in relation to the events alleged to have taken place after this time. Pursuant to s 51AC(6)(b) of the Act the Court is entitled to take into account circumstances existing prior to the commencement of the section but is not entitled to take into account alleged conduct prior to the commencement of the section in determining post commencement breaches: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leelee Pty Ltd and Anor (2000) ATPR 41-742 at [72]-[92].

75 Section 51AC(3) of the Act sets out a non-exhaustive list of factors to which a court may have regard in determining whether a corporation has contravened s 51AC(1). They include the relative strengths of the bargaining positions of the supplier and the business consumer as defined and whether, as a result of the supplier's conduct, the business consumer was required to comply with conditions not reasonably necessary for the protection of the legitimate interests of the supplier. Other factors include the capacity of the business consumer to understand documents relating to the supply or possible supply of goods or services and whether any undue influence or pressure was exerted on, or unfair tactics used against, the business consumer. Also relevant is the extent to which the supplier unreasonably failed to disclose to the business consumer any intended conduct that might affect the interests of the business consumer and the risk involved. The extent to which the supplier was willing to negotiate the terms and conditions of any contract for the supply of goods or services with the business consumer and the extent to which the supplier and the business consumer acted in good faith are also relevant factors.

76 The relevant conduct for the purposes of s 51AC(1)(a) relied upon by the applicants must be in connection with the supply or possible supply of services to a person. For the applicants to succeed in a claim within this section the services provided by AIA to the applicants must be identified.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [2002] FCAFC 4 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/62.html</AustLII>
<text>71 The High Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v CG Berbatis Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2003] HCA 18 ; (2003) 214 CLR 51 discussed the concept of unconscionable conduct as used in s 51AA of the Act. Gleeson CJ at 62 accepted that 'special disadvantage' meant a disabling circumstance seriously affecting the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment in that party's own best interests. Gleeson CJ (referring to the decision of the Full Court of this Court in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Samton Holdings Pty Ltd and Others [2002] FCAFC 4 ; (2002) 117 FCR 301) said in Berbatis [2003] HCA 18 ; 214 CLR 51 at 64:
 
 A person is not in a position of relevant disadvantage, constitutional, situational, or otherwise, simply because of inequality of bargaining power. Many, perhaps even most, contracts are made between parties of unequal bargaining power, and good conscience does not require parties to contractual negotiations to forfeit their advantages, or neglect their own interests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio and Another [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/14.html</AustLII>
<text>72 In The Commercial Bank of Australia Limited v Amadio and Another [1983] HCA 14 ; (1983) 151 CLR 447 Mason J referred to the underlying general principle applicable where one party takes unfair or unconscientious advantage of an opportunity created by the special disadvantage of another. Mason J said at 462: 
 
 I qualify the word "disadvantage" by the adjective "special" in order to disavow any suggestion that the principle applies whenever there is some difference in the bargaining power of the parties and in order to emphasise that the disabling condition or circumstance is one which seriously affects the ability of the innocent party to make a judgment as to his own best interests, when the other party knows or ought to know of the existence of that condition or circumstance and of its effect on the innocent party.

73 Section 51AC of the Act proscribes unconscionable conduct in business transactions. The relevant prohibition is found in s 51AC(1)(a): 
 
 A corporation must not, in trade or commerce, in connection with: 
 
 
 (a) the supply or possible supply of goods or services to a person (other than a listed public company); 
 ... 
 
 
 engage in conduct that is, in all the circumstances, unconscionable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/22.html</AustLII>
<text>91 The Court is also guided by the observations of the High Court of Australia in Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118 at [31] where the High Court referred to the preference for courts to make findings on the basis of contemporary materials, objectively established facts and the apparent logic of events rather than on the appearances of witnesses at the hearing.

92 The detail contained in the affidavits provided by Mr Yang is carefully constructed and suggests recent invention in English. The same observation can be made of the other witnesses for the applicants. In this case the translation from Mandarin to English and the grammatical and semantic nuances lost in that process engender too much scope for uncertainty and do not establish the precision necessary for a finding of misrepresentation. The claimed representations by Ms Chen and Ms Lin were allegedly made to Mr Yang in Mandarin. The Court is not satisfied that any representations were made by them as alleged.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ingot Capital Investments Pty Ltd and Others v Macquarie Equity Capital Markets Ltd and Others (No 6) (2007) 63 ACSR 1</tocase>
<text>89 The Court is required to distil from the facts a version of the events which it considers is established by the evidence. In doing so the Court refers to the observations of McLelland CJ in Watson v Foxman and Others (1995) 49 NSWLR 315 at 318-9, cited with approval in Lahoud &amp; Ors. v Lahoud &amp; Anor. [2006] NSWCA 169 at [91] . With regards to allegations of misleading and deceptive conduct claimed to be within s 52 of the Act, his Honour said at 318: 
 
 ... it is ordinarily necessary for that party to prove to the reasonable satisfaction of the court: (1) what the alleged conduct was; and (2) circumstances which rendered the conduct misleading. Where the conduct is the speaking of words in the course of a conversation, it is necessary that the words spoken be proved with a degree of precision sufficient to enable the court to be reasonably satisfied that they were in fact misleading in the proved circumstances. 

See also Ingot Capital Investments Pty Ltd and Others v Macquarie Equity Capital Markets Ltd and Others (No 6) (2007) 63 ACSR 1 at 107.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lahoud &amp; Ors. v Lahoud &amp; Anor. [2006] NSWCA 169</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2006/169.html</AustLII>
<text>89 The Court is required to distil from the facts a version of the events which it considers is established by the evidence. In doing so the Court refers to the observations of McLelland CJ in Watson v Foxman and Others (1995) 49 NSWLR 315 at 318-9, cited with approval in Lahoud &amp; Ors. v Lahoud &amp; Anor. [2006] NSWCA 169 at [91] . With regards to allegations of misleading and deceptive conduct claimed to be within s 52 of the Act, his Honour said at 318: 
 
 ... it is ordinarily necessary for that party to prove to the reasonable satisfaction of the court: (1) what the alleged conduct was; and (2) circumstances which rendered the conduct misleading. Where the conduct is the speaking of words in the course of a conversation, it is necessary that the words spoken be proved with a degree of precision sufficient to enable the court to be reasonably satisfied that they were in fact misleading in the proved circumstances. 

See also Ingot Capital Investments Pty Ltd and Others v Macquarie Equity Capital Markets Ltd and Others (No 6) (2007) 63 ACSR 1 at 107.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Legione and Another v Hateley [1983] HCA 11 ; (1983) 152 CLR 406 at 444</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1983/11.html</AustLII>
<text>137 The second basis upon which the applicants claim unconscionable conduct on the part of AIA is in relation to the events leading up to the resignation of Mr Yang on 30 January 2002. AIA accepts that a strict application of legal rights may be unconscionable if exercised harshly, oppressively or capriciously: see Legione and Another v Hateley [1983] HCA 11 ; (1983) 152 CLR 406 at 444. However there is nothing to suggest that the effective termination (by resignation) of Mr Yang was exercised by AIA harshly, oppressively or capriciously. The dishonesty of Mr Yang in relation to the issue of the receipts in respect of Mr Xu's policies, the false completion of the application forms for Mr Xu, the false representations to the AIA clerk on 5 December 2001, the false alteration of the receipt presented to AIA and the false versions of events given to Mr Chinnery in January 2002 together with the choice of resignation offered to Mr Yang, support a conclusion that the cessation of Mr Yang's agency was not in any way brought about by the unconscionable conduct of AIA but rather by the conduct of Mr Yang himself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Moukhayber v Camden Timber and Hardware Co Pty Ltd [2002] NSWCA 58</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2002/58.html</AustLII>
<text>93 The only alleged oral representations made in English were made by Mr Juneau to Mr Yang. The Court is guided by the judgment of Heydon JA in Moukhayber v Camden Timber and Hardware Co Pty Ltd [2002] NSWCA 58 where his Honour said (at [29]) 'the risks of misunderstanding...were doubtless increased by the plaintiff's lack of skill in speaking English' . Given Mr Yang's very limited grasp of the English language, the Court is not satisfied that the alleged representations of Mr Juneau were in fact made.

94 The representation alleging indemnity by AIA to Mr Yang and the evidence in support of such alleged representation lacks the required precision to constitute a representation. In summary the Court is not satisfied on the balance of probabilities that any representations were made to Mr Yang by Ms Lin, Ms Chen or by Mr Juneau as alleged.

95 The terms relied upon by Mr Yang as constituting part of the representations, namely ' security for life' and ' guaranteed for life' , exemplify the language difficulties and imprecision associated with the representations alleged in these proceedings. Identical words are contained in AIA's brochures but in an entirely different context to that claimed by Mr Yang. Such phrases are published by AIA in brochures for the benefit of clients, not for its agents. The brochure entitled 'Security for Life' states, inter alia, 'AIA has the strength and international resources to provide "Security for Life" to its much valued customers' . The brochure published solely for use by agents entitled 'A Career for Life' states, inter alia, 'In Australia, we give our clients 'Security for Life' we will always be there to help them when they need us no matter where they might be' . The brochure does not suggest that the term 'security for life' was to be interpreted as applying to agents. Rather it clearly applies to 'clients' .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Louth v Diprose [1992] HCA 61 ; (1992) 175 CLR 621</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/61.html</AustLII>
<text>70 For conduct to be actionable as unconscionable under s 51AA it must be unconscionable under the unwritten law. The requirements of a finding of unconscionability in equity were described by the High Court in Louth v Diprose [1992] HCA 61 ; (1992) 175 CLR 621. At 637 Deane J said:
 
 It has long been established that the jurisdiction of courts of equity to relieve against unconscionable dealing extends generally to circumstances in which (i) a party to a transaction was under a special disability in dealing with the other party to the transaction with the consequence that there was an absence of any reasonable degree of equality between them and (ii) that special disability was sufficiently evident to the other party to make it prima facie unfair or "unconscionable" that that other party procure, accept or retain the benefit of, the disadvantaged party's assent to the impugned transaction in the circumstances in which he or she procured or accepted it. Where such circumstances are shown to have existed, an onus is cast upon the stronger party to show that the transaction was fair, just and reasonable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Queensland Aggregates Pty. Ltd. and Another v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 57 FLR 314</tocase>
<text>138 As discussed above, for the applicants to succeed in a claim under s 51AC of the Act the services provided by AIA to the applicants must be in connection with the supply or possible supply of services to the applicants. The Court accepts AIA's submission that the principal 'right' acquired by the applicants under the various agreements is the right to be paid remuneration in the form of commissions and other benefits. In Queensland Aggregates Pty. Ltd. and Another v Trade Practices Commission (1981) 57 FLR 314 at 319 the Full Court held that a payment of money does not comprise a supply of services under the Act. Such 'right' to remuneration is not a connecting factor for the purposes of s 51AC(1)(a) of the Act. Accordingly the requirements of s 51AC have not been met.

139 As such the applicants have not made out their claim under either ss 51A, 51AA or 51AC of the Act and the Court dismisses the application with costs.


 I certify that the preceding one hundred and thirty-nine (139) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Cowdroy. 


 Associate:

Dated: 12 March 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: I. G. Archibald 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Accentro Legal 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: M.A. Jones 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Ebsworth &amp; Ebsworth 
 
 Dates of Hearing: 27 31 August, 3 6 September, 10 14 September, 19 21 September, 4 6 December 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 12 March 2008 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/39.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Watson v Foxman and Others (1995) 49 NSWLR 315</tocase>
<text>89 The Court is required to distil from the facts a version of the events which it considers is established by the evidence. In doing so the Court refers to the observations of McLelland CJ in Watson v Foxman and Others (1995) 49 NSWLR 315 at 318-9, cited with approval in Lahoud &amp; Ors. v Lahoud &amp; Anor. [2006] NSWCA 169 at [91] . With regards to allegations of misleading and deceptive conduct claimed to be within s 52 of the Act, his Honour said at 318: 
 
 ... it is ordinarily necessary for that party to prove to the reasonable satisfaction of the court: (1) what the alleged conduct was; and (2) circumstances which rendered the conduct misleading. Where the conduct is the speaking of words in the course of a conversation, it is necessary that the words spoken be proved with a degree of precision sufficient to enable the court to be reasonably satisfied that they were in fact misleading in the proved circumstances. 

See also Ingot Capital Investments Pty Ltd and Others v Macquarie Equity Capital Markets Ltd and Others (No 6) (2007) 63 ACSR 1 at 107.

90 McLelland CJ in Foxman 49 NSWLR 315 also observed at 319 that 'in the absence of some reliable contemporaneous record or other satisfactory corroboration' an applicant who relies upon spoken words as a basis for an allegation of misrepresentation or unconscionable conduct may encounter 'serious difficulties of proof' .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>