<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Windsor v Sydney Medical Service Cooperative Ltd [2008] FCA 348 (17 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/348.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jobbins v Capel Corporation Limited and Another [1989] FCA 538 ; (1989) 25 FCR 226</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1989/538.html</AustLII>
<text>31 Order 11 rule 16 of the Federal Court Rules permits the Court to strike out a pleading (in whole or in part) where no reasonable cause of action is disclosed; where the pleading has a tendency to cause embarrassment or is otherwise an abuse of process such as where an action is time barred: Jobbins v Capel Corporation Limited and Another [1989] FCA 538 ; (1989) 25 FCR 226. It is an abuse of process to bring a proceeding which can clearly be seen to be foredoomed to fail: Walton v Gardiner [1993] HCA 77 ; (1993) 177 CLR 378 at 393.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Walton v Gardiner [1993] HCA 77 ; (1993) 177 CLR 378</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/77.html</AustLII>
<text>31 Order 11 rule 16 of the Federal Court Rules permits the Court to strike out a pleading (in whole or in part) where no reasonable cause of action is disclosed; where the pleading has a tendency to cause embarrassment or is otherwise an abuse of process such as where an action is time barred: Jobbins v Capel Corporation Limited and Another [1989] FCA 538 ; (1989) 25 FCR 226. It is an abuse of process to bring a proceeding which can clearly be seen to be foredoomed to fail: Walton v Gardiner [1993] HCA 77 ; (1993) 177 CLR 378 at 393.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wardley Australia Limited and Another v The State of Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/55.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The respondent submits that the cause of action founded upon a contravention of s 52 of the TPA is doomed to fail in that it is time barred: s 82(2) and Schedule 1, item 21 of the Trade Practices Amendment Act (No 1) 2001 (Cth). Ms Windsor seeks damages under s 82 and s 87. In the case of any cause of action which had not expired as at 26 July 2001, that action must be commenced within six years of the date upon which the cause of action accrued. Ms Windsor's case appears to be that she was induced to enter into a contract on the basis of representations made in contravention of the TPA. That contract (putting aside the question of parties) was made on 8 January 2001: see para 4 of her statement of claim. Proceedings were commenced on 28 February 2007. The cause of action accrued when the loss was ascertained (the date of entry into the contract) or was reasonably ascertainable (on 13 January 2001, when the representations were first shown to be false): see Wardley Australia Limited and Another v The State of Western Australia [1992] HCA 55 ; (1992) 175 CLR 514 as to the date of accrual of the cause of action. As such, the cause of action is time barred.

24 The respondent submits that it is not clear from the pleading whether Ms Windsor contends that the representations were rendered misleading or deceptive by reason of the fact that the contract did not contain terms consistent with the representations. Ms Windsor does not expressly plead that the representations were false, misleading or deceptive. If the case propounded by Ms Windsor is that the contract did contain terms consistent with the representations, Ms Windsor did not suffer loss by reason of the representations, but rather by reason of a breach of contract. Conversely, if Ms Windsor's case is that the contract did not contain those terms, the cause of action plainly accrued when she entered into a bargain devoid of those terms or when the representations were first shown to be false.

25 Ms Windsor submits that the respondent's arguments that her claim is doomed to fail because it is time barred is fatally flawed in that it incorrectly assumes that all causes of action occurred before 28 February 2001.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>