<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Russell v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 343 (14 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/343.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Krampel Newman Partners Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2001] FCA 976 ; (2001) 113 FCR 306</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/976.html</AustLII>
<text>9 In Krampel Newman Partners Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2001] FCA 976 ; (2001) 113 FCR 306 at 312, [15] , Ryan J concluded that s 14ZZN of the TAA does not evince an intention contrary to the effect of s 23 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), which is that the singular includes the plural. I respectfully agree. Thus, there is nothing in s 14ZZN of the TAA which forbids the inclusion in the form of initiating application which is lodged with this Court of appeals against more than one objection decision.

10 Krampel Newman concerned objection decisions each of which related to objections against income tax assessments. Does it make any difference here that one of the primary tax liabilities is in respect of income tax and the other is in respect of a net amount for the purposes of the GST Act ? In my opinion it does not, for the following additional reasons.

11 Another feature of s 14ZZN is that it makes indifferent, generic provision for an appeal in respect of whatever constitutes an "appealable objection decision", as defined. That definition is to be found in s 14ZQ of the TAA. The effect of that definition is that, subject to an exception that is of no present relevance, an "appealable objection decision" is any "objection decision", another term defined by s 14ZQ. That definition, in turn, directs one to s 14ZY(2) of the TAA. Again subject to an exception of no present relevance, the effect of that subsection is that an "objection decision" is any decision of the Commissioner in respect of a "taxation objection". "Taxation objection", too, is a defined term (again, s 14ZQ) and that definition provides that a "taxation objection" has the meaning given in s 14ZL. I have already made some reference above to s 14ZL. It suffices to add that the effect of s 14ZL(2) is that an objection to which Part IVC of the TAA applies is a "taxation objection".

12 By this circuitous path the position reached is that each of the objection decisions with which Mr Russell is dissatisfied and to which he refers in the application he filed may be the subject of an appeal to this court under s 14ZZN of the TAA. Each is an "appealable objection decision". There is nothing in s 14ZZN which explicitly mandates that an "appeal" lodged with the Court is competent only if it concerns one or more assessments in respect of the same type of taxation liability.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1958/2.html</AustLII>
<text>13 There is also good reason not to imply any such intention. In Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32 , at 40-41 Dixon CJ noted, albeit as he acknowledged without at the time a judicial decision to that effect, that it was generally assumed that " under the Constitution liability for tax could not be imposed upon a subject without leaving open to him some judicial process by which he could show that he was not taxable or not taxable in the sum assessed ". As Dawson J later noted in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168 , at 222, the general assumption to which Sir Owen Dixon referred did receive later judicial recognition: (His Honour referred to MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1984] HCA 20 ; (1984) 158 CLR 622 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678 at 684 ; Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462 at 467). Section 14ZZN of the TAA therefore serves the important constitutional end of expressly providing for recourse by the person affected to the judicial power of the Commonwealth for a challenge to an administratively assessed taxation liability. Section 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) counsels that Acts should be read and construed subject to the Constitution and so as not to exceed Commonwealth legislative power. Section 14ZZN provides for a fixed time limit within which to engage this constitutionally necessary right of challenge. In the face of language that did not expressly forbid the practice and whose language was broad enough on its face to permit it, it would be a strong thing to discern by implication a prohibition as to joinder which would foreclose by a technicality of form such an important and necessary right.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/23.html</AustLII>
<text>13 There is also good reason not to imply any such intention. In Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32 , at 40-41 Dixon CJ noted, albeit as he acknowledged without at the time a judicial decision to that effect, that it was generally assumed that " under the Constitution liability for tax could not be imposed upon a subject without leaving open to him some judicial process by which he could show that he was not taxable or not taxable in the sum assessed ". As Dawson J later noted in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168 , at 222, the general assumption to which Sir Owen Dixon referred did receive later judicial recognition: (His Honour referred to MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1984] HCA 20 ; (1984) 158 CLR 622 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678 at 684 ; Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462 at 467). Section 14ZZN of the TAA therefore serves the important constitutional end of expressly providing for recourse by the person affected to the judicial power of the Commonwealth for a challenge to an administratively assessed taxation liability. Section 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) counsels that Acts should be read and construed subject to the Constitution and so as not to exceed Commonwealth legislative power. Section 14ZZN provides for a fixed time limit within which to engage this constitutionally necessary right of challenge. In the face of language that did not expressly forbid the practice and whose language was broad enough on its face to permit it, it would be a strong thing to discern by implication a prohibition as to joinder which would foreclose by a technicality of form such an important and necessary right.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1984)158 CLR 622</tocase>
<text>13 There is also good reason not to imply any such intention. In Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32 , at 40-41 Dixon CJ noted, albeit as he acknowledged without at the time a judicial decision to that effect, that it was generally assumed that " under the Constitution liability for tax could not be imposed upon a subject without leaving open to him some judicial process by which he could show that he was not taxable or not taxable in the sum assessed ". As Dawson J later noted in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168 , at 222, the general assumption to which Sir Owen Dixon referred did receive later judicial recognition: (His Honour referred to MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1984] HCA 20 ; (1984) 158 CLR 622 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678 at 684 ; Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462 at 467). Section 14ZZN of the TAA therefore serves the important constitutional end of expressly providing for recourse by the person affected to the judicial power of the Commonwealth for a challenge to an administratively assessed taxation liability. Section 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) counsels that Acts should be read and construed subject to the Constitution and so as not to exceed Commonwealth legislative power. Section 14ZZN provides for a fixed time limit within which to engage this constitutionally necessary right of challenge. In the face of language that did not expressly forbid the practice and whose language was broad enough on its face to permit it, it would be a strong thing to discern by implication a prohibition as to joinder which would foreclose by a technicality of form such an important and necessary right.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/36.html</AustLII>
<text>13 There is also good reason not to imply any such intention. In Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32 , at 40-41 Dixon CJ noted, albeit as he acknowledged without at the time a judicial decision to that effect, that it was generally assumed that " under the Constitution liability for tax could not be imposed upon a subject without leaving open to him some judicial process by which he could show that he was not taxable or not taxable in the sum assessed ". As Dawson J later noted in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168 , at 222, the general assumption to which Sir Owen Dixon referred did receive later judicial recognition: (His Honour referred to MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1984] HCA 20 ; (1984) 158 CLR 622 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678 at 684 ; Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462 at 467). Section 14ZZN of the TAA therefore serves the important constitutional end of expressly providing for recourse by the person affected to the judicial power of the Commonwealth for a challenge to an administratively assessed taxation liability. Section 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) counsels that Acts should be read and construed subject to the Constitution and so as not to exceed Commonwealth legislative power. Section 14ZZN provides for a fixed time limit within which to engage this constitutionally necessary right of challenge. In the face of language that did not expressly forbid the practice and whose language was broad enough on its face to permit it, it would be a strong thing to discern by implication a prohibition as to joinder which would foreclose by a technicality of form such an important and necessary right.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/61.html</AustLII>
<text>13 There is also good reason not to imply any such intention. In Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Brown [1958] HCA 2 ; (1957-1958) 100 CLR 32 , at 40-41 Dixon CJ noted, albeit as he acknowledged without at the time a judicial decision to that effect, that it was generally assumed that " under the Constitution liability for tax could not be imposed upon a subject without leaving open to him some judicial process by which he could show that he was not taxable or not taxable in the sum assessed ". As Dawson J later noted in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Richard Walter Pty Ltd [1995] HCA 23 ; (1994-1995) 183 CLR 168 , at 222, the general assumption to which Sir Owen Dixon referred did receive later judicial recognition: (His Honour referred to MacCormick v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1984] HCA 20 ; (1984) 158 CLR 622 ; Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Truhold Benefit Pty. Ltd. [1985] HCA 36 ; (1985) 158 CLR 678 at 684 ; Air Caledonie International v The Commonwealth [1988] HCA 61 ; (1988) 165 CLR 462 at 467). Section 14ZZN of the TAA therefore serves the important constitutional end of expressly providing for recourse by the person affected to the judicial power of the Commonwealth for a challenge to an administratively assessed taxation liability. Section 15A of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) counsels that Acts should be read and construed subject to the Constitution and so as not to exceed Commonwealth legislative power. Section 14ZZN provides for a fixed time limit within which to engage this constitutionally necessary right of challenge. In the face of language that did not expressly forbid the practice and whose language was broad enough on its face to permit it, it would be a strong thing to discern by implication a prohibition as to joinder which would foreclose by a technicality of form such an important and necessary right.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Peerless Marine Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] AATA 765 ; (2006) 63 ATR 1303</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2006/765.html</AustLII>
<text>14 Moreover, the prospect that out of a single investigation by the Commissioner's staff there might emerge controversies in respect of both a GST and an income tax liability is by no means remote. The present case apart, in Peerless Marine Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] AATA 765 ; (2006) 63 ATR 1303 what emerged from the one investigation was a controversy as to whether the taxpayer was carrying on a business such that it was entitled to allowable deductions for expenditure incurred in the construction of what was alleged to be a prototype for a class of luxury motor cruiser and a related GST controversy as to whether, in respect of that same expenditure, it was entitled to input tax credits. The taxpayer elected to challenge the objection decisions in the Administrative Appeals Tribunal ("Tribunal") rather than in this Court and the Tribunal heard and determined the GST and income tax controversies together. Had it sought to appeal those decisions, s 14ZZN of the TAA would have permitted the joinder of those appeals in the one application, in my opinion. A construction of s 14ZZN which would facilitate such joinder has about it such an obvious convenience and practicality that it is to be preferred to one which would not.

15 Thus, the mere fact that Mr Russell has chosen to join in the one form of application appeals in respect of both income tax and GST assessments and related administrative penalty assessments does not, of itself render any of the appeals incompetent.

16 That is not to say that the adoption of such a course binds the Court to hear each of the appeals together. On some occasions it may be convenient to hear and determine a GST appeal together with an income tax appeal; on other occasions it may not be. Order 52B r 3 incorporates by reference, inter alia, the directions hearing provision made by O 52A r 13. Questions as to whether there ought to be separate hearings would be apt subjects for determination at a directions hearing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Seal and Edgelaw v Kingston [1908] 2 KB 579</tocase>
<text>37 Were a partner's liability for GST only joint, the Commissioner's submission might have some attraction. Under the general law of partnership (and prior to the death of any of the partners) every partner in a firm is liable jointly with the other partners for all debts and obligations of the firm incurred while a partner: s 12(1) of the Partnership Act 1891 (Qld). The rules of court provide that, subject to any grant of leave to the contrary, where an applicant claims relief to which any other person is entitled jointly with him, all persons so entitled shall be parties with him: O 6, r 3(1) of the Federal Court Rules . Further, O 42 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules permits a claim brought by two or more persons claiming as partners to be brought in the name of the partnership. When so brought any party may apply on notice to be furnished with the names and places of residence of those who were partners at the time when the cause of action arose: O 42 r 3 of the Federal Court Rules . It is possible for a partner to institute proceedings in the name of the partnership without the prior consent of his fellow partners but, if such a course of action is taken, the court may direct that the proceeding be stayed until that partner has given his fellow partners a full indemnity, together with security in respect of costs: Seal and Edgelaw v Kingston [1908] 2 KB 579, at 582.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Sutherland v Gustar (Inspector of Taxes) [1994] Ch 304</tocase>
<text>38 As it happens, in Sutherland v Gustar (Inspector of Taxes) [1994] Ch 304 , an analogous controversy arose in the United Kingdom in respect of the competency of the purported institution of an appeal by one partner, against the wishes of his fellow partners (who had reached an agreement satisfactory to them with the Inspector of Taxes), in respect of a joint assessment of the partnership to income tax which had been confirmed by the general commissioners. Under the then applicable legislation in the United Kingdom, a partner's liability to income tax was joint. The then Vice Chancellor, Sir Donald Nicholls, who delivered the judgement of the Court of Appeal (Nicholls V-C, Leggatt and Henry LJJ) identified the problem raised in that case in a way which resonates in the present:
 
 "[Partners] do not always have the same interest in challenging an assessment. What is important to one partner may not matter to another. Similar divergences of interest, and differences of view about what is the best course for the partnership, can and do arise regarding other aspects of partnership business. Here, as elsewhere in the law, the courts evolved practical solutions. In the context of litigation, the courts devised procedures which protect a would-be plaintiff partner by permitting him to go ahead with court proceedings but also protect the partners who do not wish to become embroiled in the proceedings. The traditional means used to achieve this end was for the minority partner to be permitted to bring the proceedings in the name of the partnership. Every partner is an agent of the firm, a principle now enshrined in section 5 of the Partnership Act 1890 (53 &amp; 54 Vict. c. 39). But the other partners had to be protected by an adequate indemnity." [1994] Ch at 310."

39 Section 5 of the Partnership Act 1890 (UK) finds its local analogue in s 8 of the Partnership Act 1891 (Qld).

40 The Court of Appeal solved the problem thus posed by construing the statutory procedural code for the institution of taxation appeals in a way which enabled any person assessed to tax to institute an appeal in respect of the assessment irrespective of whether he had been assessed alone or jointly with others. In the case of an appeal against a joint assessment, Their Lordships opined:
 
 "In the latter case, in contemplation of law the notice of appeal is given on behalf of all those assessed in the sense, but only in the sense, that the notice effectually triggers an appeal against the joint assessment. This does not enable the person giving the notice then to conduct the appeal as though he were acting for all the partners. He has authority only to act and speak for himself, unless his co-partners authorise him to act for them. If they do not, and if they wish to pursue a different line, they may do so. But an appeal against the joint assessment having been set in motion, they, along with the partner who gave the notice of appeal, are appellants for the purposes of the Act of 1970. Accordingly, notice of the hearing must be given to them, and their concurrence is needed if the appeal is to be settled or abandoned pursuant to section 54." [1994] Ch at 312.

41 Primacy must, of course, be given to the language of the applicable Australian legislation. Nonetheless, were liability in respect of a GST assessment joint, there would, with respect, be much to commend in the adoption of a similar approach to that adopted in Sutherland v Gustar to the construction of the right to appeal to this Court against an objection decision conferred by s 14ZZ of the TAA on a "person dissatisfied" and in related practice and procedure. The "person dissatisfied" with the Commissioner's objection decision in respect of a GST assessment might well, for just the reasons identified by the Court of Appeal in Sutherland v Gustar , be but one of a number of partners.

42 Yet a partner's liability in respect of GST and any related administrative penalty is not just joint, but rather joint and several. Within Schedule 1 to the TAA, s. 444-30 provides, materially:
 
 " 444-30 Partnerships 
 
 
 
 (1) Obligations that are imposed under this Schedule or an indirect tax law on a partnership are imposed on each partner, but may be discharged by any of the partners. 
 (2) The partners are jointly and severally liable to pay any amount that is payable under this Schedule or an indirect tax law by the partnership."

43 Prior to the introduction of this provision into Schedule 1 the now repealed provisions formerly found in ss 50(1) and 50(2) of the TAA made identical provision in respect of the GST liability of partners. It would seem incongruous in these circumstances to construe the right of appeal conferred by s 14ZZ of the TAA as being dependent upon the consent of each partner or even to require that each other partner be given notice of a challenge to an objection decision by one of them.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>