<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hansen Beverage Company v Bickfords (Australia) Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 406 (31 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/406.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shoshana Pty Ltd (Sue Smith Case) (1987) 79 ALR 299</tocase>
<text>44 In 10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shoshana Pty Ltd (Sue Smith Case) (1987) 79 ALR 299 , the Full Court adopted the approach that for an applicant to establish a case for contravention of s 52 of the TPA, it must prove a 'significant' or 'substantial' proportion of persons within the relevant market would likely be misled or deceived. This was adopted in National Exchange Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission (2004) 61 IPR 420 (per Jacobson and Bennett JJ at [70]-[71]). Whilst there may be some view to the contrary (see .au Domain Administration Ltd v Domain Names Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 424 ; (2004) 207 ALR 521 , [25]-[26] per Finkelstein J), I will proceed to approach the question of the operation of the TPA by requiring it to be established that a significant or substantial proportion of persons who would be potential customers within Australia would be likely to be misled. Whilst some may consider this approach puts a greater burden than that considered by Hill J to be required, I am inclined to consider that the difference in approach is a matter of expression and not one of quantitative substance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Arnotts Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 97 ALR 555</tocase>
<text>147 In Arnotts Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1990) 97 ALR 555 , Lockhart, Wilcox and Gummow JJ stated at 604 that:
 
 ...it is not very profitable - at least in this court to spend time in determining whether a particular survey is hearsay evidence. Even if it is, ordinarily the court will have a discretion under O 33, r 3 [a substantially equivalent provision to s 190(3)] to permit the evidence to be adduced. To call the persons who responded to the survey will almost always result in appreciable expense and delay. Given the existence of a discretion, it seems more sensible to concentrate attention upon the necessity for, and reliability of, the survey evidence, rather than to worry about its compliance with rules regarding hearsay evidence which were developed before this type of problem arose.

148 Their Honours went on in Arnotts 97 ALR 555 to point out that modern market survey techniques, if undertaken by experienced and professional people, are highly likely to be accurate. That approach is a sensible one, and allows a trial judge to assess for herself or himself whether the strict application of the hearsay rule would undermine common sense or justice.

149 However, in the present circumstances, the evidence of Mr Alford is effectively required, as opinion evidence, to validate the statistical approach. I do not consider that in the circumstances, where the issue of exposure of a television audience is and has always been a matter that is or could be expected to be in issue, proper opinion evidence should not be before the Court. It is not for Bickfords to cross-examine Mr Alford to test his approach or his basis of opinion Mr Alford needed to prepare this himself for the Court.

150 I do accept that Mr Alford was sufficiently expert and professional in the collection of the relevant ratings data. I am not saying that Mr Alford's sampling methods are necessarily flawed. However, the issue in this case of the number of viewers of the television shows is one which (along with other exposures) has been in contention since the beginning of the proceeding. Hansen has had ample opportunity to comply with the Evidence Act , and without this compliance, I cannot be satisfied as to the probative value of the opinion evidence in its current form.

151 The matter to which the evidence relates is genuinely in dispute, namely the specific number of people watching a particular television show or the reach or exposure of the particular television show. In view of the potential importance of the issue and of the evidence, I do not consider that there would be unnecessary expense or delay involved in requiring adherence to the Evidence Act . The central issue in this case is reputation, and exposure of the MONSTER ENERGY mark to young male adults and other potential customers in Australia.

152 When one looks at the matter from this point of view, and specifically in light of the nature of the opinion evidence that must necessarily be relied upon, and not just raw data, I do not consider I should receive such evidence in the exercise of my discretion under s 190(3).

153 In any event, as I have said, even accepting the reach of the television programs as contended for by Hansen, I do not consider that their impact has been such to give rise to the awareness necessary in the target market or any other potential customers in Australia.

154 Whilst then there is no specific evidence as to the exact extent of television exposures, I do accept that there must be some exposure to extreme sports followers within the target demographic and to potential customers in Australia, although this cannot be quantified. However, I would be prepared to infer that many people, particularly those with an interest in a particular sport, would view these television programs in Australia.

155 The summary of the television exposures is undertaken by reference to various events occurring outside Australia, although it is to be evaluated in light of my previous observations and views as to quality and impression.

156 I turn first to motocross and supercross events. Hansen gave evidence that it has sponsored motocross/supercross athletes since 2003. Some of these athletes competed in the AMA supercross championships, which consist of weekly races between January and May each year held at different locations around the US. Hansen set out each occurrence of broadcasting of these championships in Australia. In summary, the evidence included that ESPN broadcasted the event for between one and two hours on many days in January, February, March, April, May and December in 2004, 2005, and 2006.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>ASIC v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2005/417.html</AustLII>
<text>129 Bickfords contended that the documents in the three exhibits do not fall under the business records exception on the basis that they are not business records, but rather products of the business , in the sense considered by Sperling J in Roach v Page (No 15) [2003] NSWSC 939. Similarly, Bickfords submitted that the records were not internal ones and as such, as set out in ASIC v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320 , they could not be regarded as business records under s 69. Additionally, Bickfords argued, the representations were prepared in contemplation of litigation and did not therefore fall within the business records exception.

133 The records referred to in s 69(1) of the Evidence Act are the documents a business generates in the course of, or for the purpose of the business, not documents which it may have or keep as the product of that business. The concept of a business record is an internal record, kept in an organised form accessible in the usual course of business, actually recording the business activities themselves and does not include the product of the business itself: see Sperling J in Roach v Page [2003] NSWSC 939 ; ASIC v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320 at [180] - [182] per Austin J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>.au Domain Administration Ltd v Domain Names Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 424 ; (2004) 207 ALR 521</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/424.html</AustLII>
<text>44 In 10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shoshana Pty Ltd (Sue Smith Case) (1987) 79 ALR 299 , the Full Court adopted the approach that for an applicant to establish a case for contravention of s 52 of the TPA, it must prove a 'significant' or 'substantial' proportion of persons within the relevant market would likely be misled or deceived. This was adopted in National Exchange Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission (2004) 61 IPR 420 (per Jacobson and Bennett JJ at [70]-[71]). Whilst there may be some view to the contrary (see .au Domain Administration Ltd v Domain Names Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 424 ; (2004) 207 ALR 521 , [25]-[26] per Finkelstein J), I will proceed to approach the question of the operation of the TPA by requiring it to be established that a significant or substantial proportion of persons who would be potential customers within Australia would be likely to be misled. Whilst some may consider this approach puts a greater burden than that considered by Hill J to be required, I am inclined to consider that the difference in approach is a matter of expression and not one of quantitative substance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 70 ; (2007) 239 ALR 662</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/70.html</AustLII>
<text>140 It is important that opinion evidence sets out the process of reasoning so that the opinion satisfies the requirements of s 79. As the Full Court said in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 70 ; (2007) 239 ALR 662 at [108] [109]:
 
 Further, unless a witness states in his or her evidence in chief the grounds and reasoning that have led to the opinion, the opinion is valueless. Before the Court can assess the value of an opinion, it must know the facts on which it is based. If the opinion is based on irrelevant facts or facts that are clearly not going to be proved, the opinion is likely to be valueless. It should not be for a cross-examiner to endeavour to elicit the facts or assumptions upon which an opinion is expressed, and it would be unfair to leave such matters to the cross-examiner. Except in a straightforward, uncomplicated case, where the facts are admitted or otherwise readily identified, opinion evidence would normally be rejected under s 135 if the facts or assumptions upon which the opinion is based are not expressly stated. 
 
 It is for the Court to judge the reliability of, and the weight to be given to, particular evidence. Opinion evidence, like any other evidence, must be comprehensible and reach conclusions that are rationally based. The process of inference or reasoning that leads to conclusions ought to be stated or revealed in a way that enables the conclusions to be tested and a judgment to be made about their reliability and the weight that should be given to them. If not, the opinion evidence would normally be rejected under s 135.

141 Apart from the information contained in the exhibits to the affidavit, Mr Alford's opinion evidence was significant in that it purported to give evidence as to the processing, checking for quality and validating the use of the data in the final television ratings database. There was no evidence as to who did this, or how various 'standard statistical methods' were adopted by him or the nature of the 'publicity and reliable demographic information' referred to by him. Ms Inglis-Clark did not provide this information, even if this could be relied upon to support Mr Alford's material. Mr Alford's evidence is more than a view expressed about business or professional practice, and cannot be equated to that, of say, a valuer who relies upon his own experience and observation in the giving of evidence.

142 In the case of Mr Alford's evidence, it being opinion evidence, the requirements of s 79 of the Evidence Act needed to be complied with and, in my view, they have not been.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd (1980) 32 ALR 387</tocase>
<text>52 I am of the view that the correct date at which Hansen's reputation should be assessed is the point at which the relevant Bickfords' product became available to consumers: in April/May 2006. Before this date, there was no possibility that a consumer could be misled or deceived under s 52 of the TPA. In relation to the passing off claim, Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd (1980) 32 ALR 387 established that the relevant date is the date of commencement by the respondent of the conduct complained of again, April/May 2006. No importance in this proceeding attaches to whether the month of April or May 2006 is specifically nominated as the relevant date.

53 Even if the correct date is the date when the impugned conduct was threatened, the relevant date would still be April/May 2006 in the circumstances of this case.

54 The meeting between Mr Hukowskyj of Bickfords and Jessica Brown of Coles on 29 November 2005 involved no threat of passing off or contravention of the TPA because Bickfords was still considering its options, and if Bickfords were to proceed with the MONSTER branding its intention was then 'to secure licensed rights to the MONSTER brand in Australasia'. That is to say, rather than threatening to pass off its product as Hansen's in November 2005, Bickfords had in mind to sell its product under licence from Hansen.

55 As to the proposed 12 January 2006 date, Bickfords relies upon an advertisement in the Australian Trade Marks Journal of acceptance of Bickfords' MONSTER ENERGY trade mark application and Mr Hukowskyj's presentation to Ms Brown of Coles.

56 In Bickfords' submissions in relation to the trade mark application it was stated:
 
 It is to be noted that it is a requirement of a valid trade mark application for an unused mark that it be based on a definite and present intention to use the mark as a trade mark in the immediate future.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Colorado Group Ltd v Strandbags Group Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 160 ; (2006) 67 IPR 628</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/160.html</AustLII>
<text>49 There was some dispute between the parties as to the relevant date at which Hansen's reputation should be assessed. Bickfords contented that the relevant date is when the impugned conduct commenced, or whenever the passing off was first threatened, whichever is earlier. Bickfords relied on the decision of Finkelstein J in Colorado Group Ltd v Strandbags Group Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 160 ; (2006) 67 IPR 628 , and argued that the impugned conduct commenced no later than 29 November 2005, being the date when Mr Hukowskyj of Bickfords met with Jessica Brown of Coles and first raised the concept of supplying a 440 mL energy drink product to Coles. At that time, Bickfords had lodged applications for registration of the MONSTER and MONSTER ENERGY names.

50 Alternatively, Bickfords argued that the relevant date should be at least 12 January 2006, by which time Bickfords had presented mock up cans to Coles and the Trade Marks Office had publicly advertised the acceptance of Bickfords' MONSTER ENERGY trade mark application.

51 Hansen, on the other hand, looks to the date on which the Bickfords products were available to consumers, namely late April or early May 2006, arguing that consumers could not be misled or deceived until the Bickfords product was available for purchase. Hansen also submitted that, in any event, Bickfords may not now retract from its defence, in which the earliest date pleaded was April 2006. Hansen dismissed Bickfords' argument concerning the publication of the acceptance of Bickfords' MONSTER ENERGY trade mark application on the basis that there was no evidence that Bickfords was proposing to use those marks other than in accordance with its plan to obtain a licence from Hansen.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Compafina Bank v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [1982] 1 NSWLR 409</tocase>
<text>135 Other authorities were relied upon by Hansen, but I do not consider they take the matter any further or specifically address the issue of the tender of the documents in the three exhibits, being extracts obtained by Hansen effectively of statistical information produced and created by and in the possession of OzTAM: see for example Compafina Bank v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [1982] 1 NSWLR 409 ; R W Miller &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Krupp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 32 NSWLR 152; Shoshana Pty Ltd v 10 th Cantanae Pty Ltd (1987) 11 IPR 249; and Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (1990) 93 ALR 657 .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>ConAgra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/159.html</AustLII>
<text>29 In ConAgra Inc v McCain Foods (Aust) Pty Ltd [1992] FCA 159 ; (1992) 33 FCR 302 the Full Court considered a case having some similarities with the present proceeding.

30 Both parties rely on the Full Court authority of ConAgra . It is useful to first refer to the salient facts of that case: 
 
&#8226; the applicant ConAgra had marketed its HEALTHY CHOICE frozen dinner product in the United States from January 1989 and had achieved sales of HEALTHY CHOICE products from January 1989 to March 1991 amounting to $US458,210,000, accounting for 7.6% of the overall frozen food, dinner and entr&eacute;e market in the United States;
 
&#8226; ConAgra had obtained trade mark registration of HEALTHY CHOICE in the United States;
 
&#8226; ConAgra had spent very substantial sums of money on advertising its HEALTHY CHOICE product in the United States;
 
&#8226; ConAgra had not manufactured its HEALTHY CHOICE products other than in the United States, but had sold the products in Canada and Central America;
 
&#8226; McCain had been manufacturing and marketing frozen food dinners in Australia;
 
&#8226; in October 1989, the Australian marketing director of McCain travelled to the United States and Canada and noticed ConAgra's HEALTHY CHOICE product in supermarkets, obtained five examples of the packaging, took them back to Australia and reported to McCain senior management that ' The ... product 'Healthy Choice' (low cholesterol) is getting very favourable comments in the US. We should look closely at this one.'; 
 
&#8226; from May 1990, McCain conducted market research and product development for its own HEALTHY CHOICE product;
 
&#8226; in July 1990, McCain applied for trade mark registration in Australia for HEALTHY CHOICE together with the McCain logo;
 
&#8226; in February 1991, McCain launched three varieties of its HEALTHY CHOICE product in Australia; and
 
&#8226; on 8 April 1991, ConAgra commenced proceedings against McCain in the Federal Court claiming that McCain's adoption of the name and get-up of ConAgra's products amounted to passing off or breach of ss 52 or 53 (c) of the TPA.

31 At first instance Hill J found that McCain's packaging suggested, to a person familiar with the ConAgra product, that there is a relationship of some kind between ConAgra and McCain or their respective products. However, both at first instance and on appeal to the Full Court, ConAgra failed to establish that McCain's sale of its HEALTHY CHOICE product in Australia amounted to passing off or breach of s 52 or s 53(c) of the TPA because ConAgra was unable to establish that there was a substantial or sufficiently substantial number of persons in Australia who were aware of ConAgra's products and for whom HEALTHY CHOICE would have signified ConAgra's product.

32 ConAgra's evidence of reputation included affidavits from ten people who had some recent connection with the United States. Some were United States citizens visiting or residing in Australia and others were Australian citizens who had spent time in the United States. To varying degrees, each deponent recognised ConAgra's HEALTHY CHOICE product. It was ultimately found that no extrapolation of any value could be made from those deponents to the Australian population in general (including foreign citizens in Australia) whether as likely buyers of frozen foods or as likely to be aware of ConAgra's product in the United States.

34 It was submitted by Bickfords that in the present case a proper analysis of the admissible evidence leads to a similar conclusion as reached by the trial judge and Full Court in ConAgra , to the effect that, at the time Bickfords launched its MONSTER ENERGY product:
 
&#8226; there was not a sufficiently substantial number of persons in Australia who were aware of Hansen's MONSTER ENERGY product and for whom MONSTER would have signified Hansen's product;
 
&#8226; what Bickfords really set out to do was to adopt the name and get-up of Hansen's MONSTER ENERGY product, without contravening the law, not because it wanted to have its product confused with that of Hansen, but because it was most impressed by the striking success of Hansen's product in the United States and sought to adopt it for its own products in Australia as a good idea and one likely to succeed here; and
 
&#8226; such conduct does not amount to fraud but, in any event, a finding of fraud cannot improve Hansen's case if it cannot prove its claimed reputation.

35 On the other hand, Hansen submitted that the Court ought to find that the exposure relied upon in fact generated a substantial reputation in the MONSTER ENERGY mark in Australia. Hansen submits that the Court ought to so find on the basis:
 
&#8226; of the extent of the exposure apparent from the evidence summarised in the form of the Schedules of Exposure before the Court;
 
&#8226; that the strategy referred to above was in fact successfully implemented;
 
&#8226; of evidence of the state of knowledge of members of the public; 
 
&#8226; of evidence of the efforts made by persons other than Bickfords to become involved in the distribution of the Hansen product in Australia; and
 
&#8226; of Bickfords' own conduct and research.

36 It is clear from the principles stated in ConAgra that it is not necessary in a passing off case for an applicant to establish actual trade in the jurisdiction but, rather, it is sufficient if the applicant establishes a reputation in the jurisdiction.

37 Justice Lockhart stated in ConAgra 33 FCR at 343 that:
 
 ... it is still necessary for a plaintiff to establish that his goods have the requisite reputation in the particular jurisdiction, that there is a likelihood of deception among consumers and a likelihood of damage to his reputation. But reputation within the jurisdiction may be proved by a variety of means including advertisements on television or radio, or in magazines and newspapers within the forum. It may be established by showing constant travel of people between other countries and the forum, and that people within the forum (whether residents there or persons simply visiting there from other countries) are exposed to the goods of the overseas owner ... 
 
 Certainly the law of passing off does not confer protection on the owners of goods who have no reputation in a particular jurisdiction, otherwise they would have an international monopoly with respect to the name, get-up or mark applied to their goods (and services) and may never intend to exploit it in the particular jurisdiction. It is the likelihood of deception among consumers and of damage to reputation that are the critical requirements to establish a case of passing off and they prevent any such unauthorised international monopoly being granted to a plaintiff. A quia timet injunction is a good illustration of this point for, in most cases, while such an injunction will be granted where the plaintiff has at the time of action no relevant business connection with the particular jurisdiction but has a reputation there and has established a likelihood of deception amongst consumers, he must go on to establish a likelihood of damage to his reputation and that he intends to establish in some way his business or sell his goods in that jurisdiction.

38 Justice Lockhart considered the existence of modern mass advertising, commenting at 342:
 
 It is no longer valid, if it ever was, to speak of a business having goodwill or reputation only where the business is carried on. Modern mass advertising through television (which reaches by satellite every corner of the globe instantaneously), radio, newspapers and magazines reaches people in many countries of the world. The international mobility of the world population increasingly brings human beings, and therefore potential consumers of goods and services, closer together and engenders an increasing and more instantaneous awareness of international commodities. This is an age of enormous commercial enterprises, some with budgets larger than sovereign states, who advertise their products by sophisticated means involving huge financial outlay. Goods and services are often preceded by their reputation abroad. They may not be physically present in the market of a particular country, but are well known there because of the sophistication of communications which are increasingly less limited by national boundaries, and the frequent travel of residents of many countries for reasons of business, pleasure or study.

39 As to the extent of the reputation required, his Honour said at 346:
 
 I said earlier that if a plaintiff establishes that it has a reputation in the jurisdiction then that would be sufficient to allow it to maintain an action in passing off. I have already discussed the various ways by which that reputation may be achieved, but it remains to define the extent or scope of reputation required. In my opinion the plaintiff must prove that there are within the jurisdiction in which the defendant is carrying on business a substantial number of persons who are aware of the plaintiff's product ... This was the test adopted by the primary judge (at 485 6) and in my opinion correctly. Further, it does not matter whether the persons within the relevant jurisdiction who are aware of the plaintiff's product, are resident or visitors from anywhere in the world. 
 
 The reason for the requirement of a substantial number of persons is in my opinion that the reputation of a plaintiff in the forum is the source of his potential business there; his goods are known to people there who are his potential customers. For him to have in a practical and business sense a sufficient reputation in the forum requires something more than a reputation among a small number of persons, although the size and extent of the class may vary according to the circumstances of the case. Also, the law seeks to promote local competition and innovation and does not extend its protection to persons whose goods are not sufficiently known in the forum.

40 Justice French, at 377, said that:
 
 It is essential to the cause of action in passing off that the applicant's goods or services have a reputation with a substantial number of persons who would be potential customers were those goods or services to be marketed within the jurisdiction.

41 As to what is meant by the term 'substantial', his Honour said at 380:
 
 The term "substantial" is evaluative and relative to such factors as the size and distribution of the population of prospective consumers.

42 In relation to the operation of the TPA, Lockhart J (at 353) referred to the observation of Hill J that the threshold under the TPA may well be lower than it is for passing off, namely that a not insignificant number of persons could be misled. Justice Lockhart did not need to determine whether the threshold was different. Justice Gummow referred (at 372) to 'a reputation with a substantial number of persons who would be potential customers', but did not separately discuss the position under the TPA.

43 Justice French observed at 377 that the trial judge had used the term 'a not insignificant number of persons' to identify the threshold of public awareness of the applicant's mark or get up which, under the TPA, was required for the applicant to succeed. His Honour said (at 381) of the word 'insignificant':
 
 That word is normative but not for that reason inappropriate. Attention must be paid to the policy of the relevant provision which, as the heading to Pt V and many of its provisions indicate, is one of consumer protection. If the similarity complained of is commercially irrelevant having regard to the number of people who know of it, then it can be concluded that the use of the name and/or get-up complained of is not misleading or deceptive.

45 I make one further observation in relation to legal principle to be derived from ConAgra . In the absence of the establishment of reputation in Australia, fraud will not avail Hansen in its attempt to prove a case of passing off. Fraud may well be relevant in determining the relief Hansen would be entitled to, if reputation were otherwise established, or as an element in establishing the requisite misrepresentation (see ConAgra 33 FCR at 345 per Lockhart J).

46 Nevertheless, relevantly to this proceeding, deliberate copying may not always evidence an intention to deceive so as to constitute fraud in the relevant sense.

47 Justice Lockhart took the following view of McCain's deliberate adoption of the name and get-up of ConAgra's product, at 352:
 
 Merely to imitate the name of another trader or his product or his get-up does not establish a case of fraud. That appears clearly from the Pub Squash case. I have the distinct impression from my reading of the evidence in this case that what the respondent really set out to do was to apply to its own product and packaging so much of the name of the appellant's product "Healthy Choice" and get-up of its packaging as it could do, without contravening the law, not because it wanted to have its product confused with that of the appellant, but because it was most impressed by the striking success of the appellant's frozen food products in the United States and sought to adopt it for its own products in Australia as a good idea and one likely to succeed here. Nevertheless it seems the respondent wanted to sell its own product as a distinctive McCain product. ... As reputation in Australia has not been established by the appellant, for the reasons I gave earlier, the finding of fraud does not ultimately avail the appellant.

48 Justice Gummow viewed McCain's conduct similarly, at 374:
 
 ... like Lockhart J, my impression from the evidence is that there is much to be said for the view that [McCain] acted as it did, not to filch [ConAgra's] market or prospective market in Australia, but because it was impressed by the success of [ConAgra's] product in the United States and thought that a similar product was likely to succeed here. That would not amount to fraud in the required sense. Deliberate copying does not necessarily indicate fraud.

77 This can only be done through appropriate evidence. The Court must be satisfied, on the balance of probabilities, as to the existing reputation. As Gummow J reminded us, caution must be taken in treating findings found at an interlocutory level as if they would be findings which would suffice to establish reputation at trial (see ConAgra 33 FCR at 354).

231 Evidence was introduced by Bickfords in response to Hansen's claim, relevantly directed to Bickfords' own development and marketing of its product and mark. In view of my conclusion that Hansen has not demonstrated sufficient reputation to be entitled to the relief sought, it is not necessary for me to deal with these aspects of this evidence. The evidence relevant to the cross-claim I will deal with separately. However, it is convenient to make certain observations now that the Court has heard the evidence and received submissions by the parties, particularly on the question of fraud in the required sense as discussed by Lockhart and Gummow JJ in ConAgra .

232 Mr Kotses and Mr Bell gave evidence on behalf of Bickfords and were cross-examined. As I indicated previously, Mr Bell was Bickfords' Marketing Manager, and was asked by Mr Kotses to consider a brand for a new energy drink. An attack was made upon their evidence by Hansen.

233 One thing is clear which I accept from the evidence of Mr Kotses and Mr Bell, and the objective evidence; they both thought that Hansen did not have sufficient reputation in Australia in the MONSTER brand. The fact that Mr Kotses may have been aware that Hansen products were being promoted to young customers, and that he was probably aware that the Hansen mark was shown on pay TV, does not mean that he thought the mark MONSTER ENERGY had sufficient reputation in Australia. I accept his evidence in this regard when he says that he considered the public was not aware of Hansen's MONSTER ENERGY product in Australia prior to April/May 2006. Accordingly, by definition, Bickfords did not want to misrepresent the established reputation and goodwill of Hansen in Australia, as it was thought that none had thus far been established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McCormick &amp; Company Inc v McCormick [2000] FCA 1335 ; (2000) 51 IPR 102</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1335.html</AustLII>
<text>78 The evidence necessary or sufficient to establish reputation to found a case for passing off and contravention of the TPA will depend upon various factors (see eg Natural Waters of Viti Limited v Dayals (Fiji) Artesian Waters Limited (2007) 71 IPR 571 at [58]-[59]). Reputation may be inferred from a high volume of sales and extensive advertising, without any other direct evidence (see in a different context, Kenny J in McCormick &amp; Company Inc v McCormick [2000] FCA 1335 ; (2000) 51 IPR 102 at [86] - [88] . In this proceeding, there are no sales or direct advertising or promotion of Hansen's product in Australia. Rather, the evidence relied upon is that of exposure to persons in Australia through the marketing strategy adopted by Hansen to reach its target demographic primarily in other countries.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>National Exchange Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission (2004) 61 IPR 420</tocase>
<text>44 In 10th Cantanae Pty Ltd v Shoshana Pty Ltd (Sue Smith Case) (1987) 79 ALR 299 , the Full Court adopted the approach that for an applicant to establish a case for contravention of s 52 of the TPA, it must prove a 'significant' or 'substantial' proportion of persons within the relevant market would likely be misled or deceived. This was adopted in National Exchange Pty Ltd v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission (2004) 61 IPR 420 (per Jacobson and Bennett JJ at [70]-[71]). Whilst there may be some view to the contrary (see .au Domain Administration Ltd v Domain Names Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 424 ; (2004) 207 ALR 521 , [25]-[26] per Finkelstein J), I will proceed to approach the question of the operation of the TPA by requiring it to be established that a significant or substantial proportion of persons who would be potential customers within Australia would be likely to be misled. Whilst some may consider this approach puts a greater burden than that considered by Hill J to be required, I am inclined to consider that the difference in approach is a matter of expression and not one of quantitative substance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Natural Waters of Viti Limited v Dayals (Fiji) Artesian Waters Limited (2007) 71 IPR 571</tocase>
<text>78 The evidence necessary or sufficient to establish reputation to found a case for passing off and contravention of the TPA will depend upon various factors (see eg Natural Waters of Viti Limited v Dayals (Fiji) Artesian Waters Limited (2007) 71 IPR 571 at [58]-[59]). Reputation may be inferred from a high volume of sales and extensive advertising, without any other direct evidence (see in a different context, Kenny J in McCormick &amp; Company Inc v McCormick [2000] FCA 1335 ; (2000) 51 IPR 102 at [86] - [88] . In this proceeding, there are no sales or direct advertising or promotion of Hansen's product in Australia. Rather, the evidence relied upon is that of exposure to persons in Australia through the marketing strategy adopted by Hansen to reach its target demographic primarily in other countries.

79 No expert evidence concerning the reputation of Hansen's product in Australia, nor any survey evidence as to the reputation in and public recognition of the Hansen product in Australia, was sought to be led by any party, although such evidence would be potentially admissible: see Natural Waters (2007) 71 IPR at [30].

80 As I have said, reliance has been placed by Hansen upon a strategy 'to lay a foundation' in Australia (for instance) before the Hansen product is launched. Whilst the young male adult is accepted as the target market or the main potential customer, the initial focus of the strategy is upon those who are involved in or watch extreme sports, which sports have an international focus and appeal. No direct evidence has been led as to the number of persons who fall within the potential extreme sports target customers, nor as to the number of persons who fall within the potential young male adult target customers, although there is some indication on the evidence tendered by Bickfords that there were some 1.01 million males in Australia aged between 18 and 24 over the relevant period. The Court has been asked not only to accept that the strategy of targeting extreme sports has been successful but, more importantly, has extended to the potential young male adult customers that are the potential target market through the technique of 'word of mouth' marketing described previously. I am not persuaded on the evidence that over the relevant period the foundation laid has reached the level of establishing the required reputation in the Hansen mark in Australia.

81 In this proceeding, I have taken into account not only the number of references to the get-up of Hansen's product, but also the context in which they appear, so as to evaluate properly the evidence presented and the effect it may have on the potential customers targeted, namely young male adults. Where, as in this proceeding, the get-up is striking and distinct, a reputation may be more readily and quickly obtained, but the Court cannot assume this has occurred in a market where the product has not been sold or directly advertised. It may be that in these circumstances potential customers will not necessarily associate any get-up, packaging, or design with the Hansen product. It will all depend upon the extent of the customers' own interests (say in a particular extreme sport) and his or her own previous exposure to the product.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>R v Wood (1982) 76 Cr App Rep 23</tocase>
<text>123 In R v Wood (1982) 76 Cr App Rep 23 , the Lord Chief Justice rejected an argument that where a computer is used in the course of the production of final figures, those figures were hearsay, finding at 27 that:
 
 This computer was rightly described as a tool. It did not contribute its own knowledge. It merely did a sophisticated which could have been done manually by the chemist and was in fact done by the chemists using the computer programmed by Mr Kellie whom the Crown called as a witness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Roach v Page (No 15) [2003] NSWSC 939</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2003/939.html</AustLII>
<text>129 Bickfords contended that the documents in the three exhibits do not fall under the business records exception on the basis that they are not business records, but rather products of the business , in the sense considered by Sperling J in Roach v Page (No 15) [2003] NSWSC 939. Similarly, Bickfords submitted that the records were not internal ones and as such, as set out in ASIC v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320 , they could not be regarded as business records under s 69. Additionally, Bickfords argued, the representations were prepared in contemplation of litigation and did not therefore fall within the business records exception.

133 The records referred to in s 69(1) of the Evidence Act are the documents a business generates in the course of, or for the purpose of the business, not documents which it may have or keep as the product of that business. The concept of a business record is an internal record, kept in an organised form accessible in the usual course of business, actually recording the business activities themselves and does not include the product of the business itself: see Sperling J in Roach v Page [2003] NSWSC 939 ; ASIC v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320 at [180] - [182] per Austin J.

136 Hansen contended that the contrast between the OzTAM reports and publications considered by Sperling J in Roach v Page was 'stark'. Hansen contended that it was not the function of OzTAM business to publish books, newspapers or other publications for wider dissemination for advertising or promotional purposes.

137 However, the fact is that the actual documents sought to be tendered in the three exhibits are the very documents the OzTAM business is providing as part of the product of its business to third parties. They were in fact purchased by Hansen's solicitors for the purposes of tendering in this proceeding. The fact that these documents may not be widely disseminated, or that their purpose is not to advertise, does not mean that the principle expressed by Sperling J does not apply to the tender of the documents in question.

138 Accordingly, I consider that the documents in the three exhibits are not admissible as business records. I do not need to consider whether the representations relied upon were prepared in contemplation of litigation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Rook v Maynard [1993] TASSC 137 ; (1993) 126 ALR 150</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//tas/supreme_ct/1993/137.html</AustLII>
<text>121 Hansen relied on Rook v Maynard [1993] TASSC 137 ; (1993) 126 ALR 150 , a case dealing with the common law rules of evidence, where Wright J considered the admissibility of data obtained from a computer program which traced the user's identification number, stating at 157 that:
 
 once the trace was applied to the respondent's log-on identification, the process then undertaken by the trace was entirely mechanical in that the peregrinations through the data base by that computer user were automatically traced throughout the system and were recorded and stored for retrieval in report form as soon as the trace print-out was called for.

122 His Honour found that the computer output from this process was not hearsay as it did not contain a human element.

124 The evidence which was being considered in these cases was data which had meaning only by virtue of its analysis or recording by a computer; that is, the computer was performing a function which produced data helpful to the court. Although, in Rook , the user had to log on before the computer would begin its tracing function, it was not this logging on which was the fact sought to be proved in that case. Rather, it was that the computer had undertaken certain functions, which were able to be proved by data resulting from the computer program itself.

125 In the present case what Hansen is ultimately seeking to prove by the tender is the audience reach, but derived from some data that a certain number of people in the sample homes pressed the button when near the television, thereby representing that they were 'in the room where the television was on'. I do not accept that Hansen can avoid this conclusion by asserting that it does not rely on the OzTAM data for the purpose of showing certain people were in the room at the relevant time. Undoubtedly, Hansen seeks to prove the estimated audience sizes for a particular program derived by statistical methods from the data, but such data is not automatically recorded by the meters without the human intervention of deliberately pressing the button to show a person or persons are in the room where the television is on. When the people are in the room they intend to, and do, make the representation to assert the existence of this fact, the existence of which needs to be proved to form the basis of the statistical analysis. It seems to me that the necessary reliance by Hansen on the data derived from the sample homes must involve the representation (as defined broadly in s 3 and the dictionary in the Schedule to the Evidence Act ) by a person that the person was in the room on the relevant occasion, namely when the television is operating.

126 This is the previous representation (as broadly defined) which, under s 59 of the Evidence Act , makes the source data hearsay which is then used to calculate the audience reach. It is not because the OzTAM computer processes the information that the data is hearsay, it is because the original makers of the representation (the people pressing the buttons) are not giving the evidence themselves. The fact that the source data which is fed into the OzTAM system by the users is then processed using a computer program is not germane to the question of whether the underlying evidence which has been put to the Court in this instance is hearsay or not.

127 Hansen submitted that, in the event I found that the OzTAM data was hearsay, the evidence forms part of the business records of OzTAM because the reports in question are 'the very things constituting the business activities of OzTAM' and are therefore admissible in any event. Hansen pointed to various authorities, including a number concerning market survey evidence, to support its proposition.

128 It is important to recall that I am considering the documents in the three exhibits, which are extracts, specially obtained by Hansen for the purpose of the proceeding, of the statistical analysis that is generated on an ongoing basis by OzTAM.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R W Miller &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Krupp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 32 NSWLR 152</tocase>
<text>135 Other authorities were relied upon by Hansen, but I do not consider they take the matter any further or specifically address the issue of the tender of the documents in the three exhibits, being extracts obtained by Hansen effectively of statistical information produced and created by and in the possession of OzTAM: see for example Compafina Bank v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [1982] 1 NSWLR 409 ; R W Miller &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Krupp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 32 NSWLR 152; Shoshana Pty Ltd v 10 th Cantanae Pty Ltd (1987) 11 IPR 249; and Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (1990) 93 ALR 657 .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Shoshana Pty Ltd v 10 th Cantanae Pty Ltd (1987) 11 IPR 249</tocase>
<text>135 Other authorities were relied upon by Hansen, but I do not consider they take the matter any further or specifically address the issue of the tender of the documents in the three exhibits, being extracts obtained by Hansen effectively of statistical information produced and created by and in the possession of OzTAM: see for example Compafina Bank v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [1982] 1 NSWLR 409 ; R W Miller &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Krupp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 32 NSWLR 152; Shoshana Pty Ltd v 10 th Cantanae Pty Ltd (1987) 11 IPR 249; and Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (1990) 93 ALR 657 .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Supetina Pty Ltd v Lombok Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 376 ; (1984) 5 FCR 439</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/376.html</AustLII>
<text>134 To the extent that Spender J decided in Supetina Pty Ltd v Lombok Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 376 ; (1984) 5 FCR 439 a principle to the contrary, with respect, I do not regard that view to be correct. His Honour did not have had the advantage of the analysis undertaken in the authorities to which I have just referred.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (1990) 93 ALR 657</tocase>
<text>135 Other authorities were relied upon by Hansen, but I do not consider they take the matter any further or specifically address the issue of the tender of the documents in the three exhibits, being extracts obtained by Hansen effectively of statistical information produced and created by and in the possession of OzTAM: see for example Compafina Bank v ANZ Banking Group Ltd [1982] 1 NSWLR 409 ; R W Miller &amp; Co Pty Ltd v Krupp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1991) 32 NSWLR 152; Shoshana Pty Ltd v 10 th Cantanae Pty Ltd (1987) 11 IPR 249; and Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (1990) 93 ALR 657 .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Walton v R [1989] HCA 9 ; (1989) 166 CLR 283</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/9.html</AustLII>
<text>146 I appreciate that the hearsay rule is not to be applied inflexibly. Chief Justice Mason, in Walton v R [1989] HCA 9 ; (1989) 166 CLR 283 , in so regarding the hearsay rule stated that:
 
 (w)hen the dangers which the [hearsay] rule seeks to prevent are not present or are negligible in the circumstances of a given case there is no basis for a strict application of the rule. 

Justice Deane made similar comments.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>