<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hastie Group Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 444 (7 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/444.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd [1997] HCA 2 ; (1995) 187 CLR 384</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/2.html</AustLII>
<text>31 In CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd [1997] HCA 2 ; (1995) 187 CLR 384 , Brennan CJ, Dawson, Toohey and Gummow JJ, with whom Gaudron J agreed on this point, said at 408:
 
 'It is well settled that at common law, apart from any reliance upon s 15AB of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), the court may have regard to reports of law reform bodies to ascertain the mischief which a statute is intended to cure. Moreover, the modern approach to statutory interpretation (a) insists that the context be considered in the first instance, not merely at some later stage when ambiguity might be thought to arise, and (b) uses "context" in its widest sense to include such things as the existing state of the law and the mischief which, by legitimate means such as those just mentioned, one may discern the statute was intended to remedy. Instances of general words in a statute being so constrained by their context are numerous. In particular, as McHugh JA pointed out in Isherwood v Butler Pollnow Pty Ltd , if the apparently plain words of a provision are read in the light of the mischief which the statute was designed to overcome and of the objects of the legislation, they may wear a very different appearance. Further, inconvenience or improbability of result may assist the court in preferring to the literal meaning an alternative construction which, by the steps identified above, is reasonably open and more closely conforms to the legislative intent.'

32 In HP Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553 Hill J, with whom Stone J and Allsop J agreed, said at [44]:
 
 'It is clear, both having regard to the modern principles of interpretation as enunciated by the High Court in cases such as CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd [1997] HCA 2 ; (1997) 187 CLR 384 and s 15AA of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) that the Court will prefer an interpretation of a statute which would give effect to the legislative purpose, as opposed to one that would not. This requires the Court to identify that purpose, both by reference to the language of the statute itself and also any extrinsic material which the Court is authorised to take into account.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Envestra Limited (ACN 078 551 685) v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 249</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/249.html</AustLII>
<text>3 Effective 1 July 2002, Australia introduced a consolidation regime to allow a wholly owned group of resident entities to consolidate their tax position rather than be treated as separate entities. The consolidation regime is principally contained in Pt 3 - 90 of the ITAA 97, comprising Divs 700 to 721. The only judicial consideration of these provisions of which I am aware is the very recent decision of Mansfield J in Envestra Limited (ACN 078 551 685) v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 249 (unreported) on 7 March 2008 that concerned a discrete aspect of the tax cost setting rules and has no connection with the issues in the present case. By the time of the introduction of the consolidation regime, the measures quarantining the franking surpluses of a corporate tax entity on it ceasing to be an exempting entity and becoming a former exempting entity were embodied in Div 208 of Pt 3 - 6 of the ITAA 97. Subdivision 709-B of Pt 3 - 90 of the ITAA 97 modifies the operation of Div 208 in relation to consolidated groups in a number of different ways, depending on the status of the head company and its subsidiary member at the joining time.

4 This case involves a consideration of the provisions of Div 208 of Pt 3 - 6 as modified by the provisions of Subdiv 709-B of Pt 3 - 90 of the ITAA 97. Although this interaction has been the subject of academic and other writings, for example, see Stephen Barkoczy, "Consolidation and Imputation" (2003) 6(1) Journal of Australian Taxation 78, it certainly has not been the subject of any judicial consideration before now.

5 I do not propose to set out the description of the 'scheme' as it appears in the notice of private ruling; merely the salient features necessary for an understanding of the dispute between the applicants and the Commissioner, and its resolution.

6 On 10 April 1979, Austral Refrigeration Pty Limited ('Austral Refrigeration') was incorporated in NSW. From this time to 20 May 2002, it was effectively owned (not less than 95%) by non-residents.

7 From 13 May 1997 to 20 May 2002, Austral Refrigeration was taken to be an exempting company by virtue of s 160APHBA of the ITAA 36 by the enactment on 16 July 1999 of the Taxation Laws Amendment Act (No 2) 1999 (Cth) (Act No 93 of 1999).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>HP Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/126.html</AustLII>
<text>30 On a purely textual analysis of the relevant provisions, I am of the view that either argument is reasonably tenable, although I have a marginal preference for the applicants' argument. On the other hand, having regard to the principles of construction more recently enunciated by the High Court of Australia ( CIC Insurance Limited v Bankstown Football Club Limited [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297) , followed by Full Courts of this Court ( HP Mercantile Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553) , not only with respect to taxation statutes but statutes generally, it would be inappropriate to confine oneself to a purely textual analysis. This is not to say that recourse may not be made to a textual analysis where there is a lack of guidance as to legislative policy from legitimate sources or where that policy as identified is incapable of manifestation through the text of the statute: Cf. Reliance Carpet Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (2007) 160 FCR 449. But that is not this case.

32 In HP Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553 Hill J, with whom Stone J and Allsop J agreed, said at [44]:
 
 'It is clear, both having regard to the modern principles of interpretation as enunciated by the High Court in cases such as CIC Insurance Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd [1997] HCA 2 ; (1997) 187 CLR 384 and s 15AA of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) that the Court will prefer an interpretation of a statute which would give effect to the legislative purpose, as opposed to one that would not. This requires the Court to identify that purpose, both by reference to the language of the statute itself and also any extrinsic material which the Court is authorised to take into account.'</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Peabody v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 463 ; 92 ATC 4585</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/463.html</AustLII>
<text>2 It is not unusual for there to be a significant lag between the date from which major changes to Australia's taxation system are legislatively introduced and the time that such changes are first considered by the Courts. For example, it was not until 1992 that this Court had the opportunity to consider the provisions of Part IVA introduced into the Income Tax Assessment Act 1936 (Cth) ('the ITAA 36') some 11 years earlier and their application to an impugned scheme: Peabody v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; 92 ATC 4 ,585. The changes involved in this case are no exception. In 1987, Australia introduced an imputation system (Pt IIIAA of the ITAA 36) for the taxation of companies and their shareholders in replacement of the classical system which had hitherto existed. Subsequent changes were made to the provisions of Pt IIIAA of the ITAA 36 prior to their embodiment in Pt 3 - 6 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1997 (Cth) ('the ITAA 97'), however I am not aware of any judicial consideration of these provisions as originally enacted or as changed. One of these changes was the insertion of Div 2A (and 1AA) by Act No 93 of 1999. Relevantly, and in short, this change introduced, effective 13 May 1997, measures designed to curb the unintended usage of franking credits through franking credit trading schemes by, inter alia, quarantining the franking surpluses of companies on their ceasing to be effectively owned by non-residents. This was done through various concepts, including the concept of an exempting company (s 160APHBA) a company effectively owned (not less than 95%) by prescribed persons (non-residents) (ss 160APHBB and 160APHBF); and the concept of a former exempting company - a company that had ceased to be an exempting company and is not again an exempting company (subs 160APHBE(1)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Reliance Carpet Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (2007) 160 FCR 449</tocase>
<text>30 On a purely textual analysis of the relevant provisions, I am of the view that either argument is reasonably tenable, although I have a marginal preference for the applicants' argument. On the other hand, having regard to the principles of construction more recently enunciated by the High Court of Australia ( CIC Insurance Limited v Bankstown Football Club Limited [1997] HCA 10 ; (1997) 187 CLR 297) , followed by Full Courts of this Court ( HP Mercantile Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553) , not only with respect to taxation statutes but statutes generally, it would be inappropriate to confine oneself to a purely textual analysis. This is not to say that recourse may not be made to a textual analysis where there is a lack of guidance as to legislative policy from legitimate sources or where that policy as identified is incapable of manifestation through the text of the statute: Cf. Reliance Carpet Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (2007) 160 FCR 449. But that is not this case.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>