<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tasmanian Perpetual Trustees Ltd v Jordan [2008] FCA 464 (10 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/464.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Award Simplification Case (1997) 75 IR 272</tocase>
<text>16 Counsel also argued that I should look at the earlier award in 1965 which was "simplified": see Award Simplification Case (1997) 75 IR 272. I agree with counsel for TPT that it would not be proper to have regard to such factors in a context where no evidence of such matters was raised in the court below. The learned Magistrate noted at [5] that there was no dispute about the facts. The dispute concerned the correct interpretation of the relevant terms of the Award. The history of the earlier award would be a matter of fact, provable by evidence.

17 The appeal will be allowed and the orders made on 15 October 2007 set aside. In place of those orders it is ordered that the respondent's application No. LNG6 of 2007 be dismissed. Leave is granted to the parties to file written submissions as to costs within seven days.

 I certify that the preceding seventeen (17) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 10 April 2008

 Counsel for the Appellant: J Bourke 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: W Friend 

 Date of Hearing: 2 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 10 April 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/464.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>City of Wanneroo v Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Unions [2006] FCA 813</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/813.html</AustLII>
<text>5 His Honour noted that there was no dispute about the facts. His Honour cited a number of authorities on the construction of awards: Short v FW Hercus Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 51 ; (1993) 40 FCR 511 at 520; Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 181 at 184 and City of Wanneroo v Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Unions [2006] FCA 813 at [57] . In the latter case French J referred to an observation in his earlier decision City of Wanneroo v Holmes (1989) 30 IR 362 at 380:
 Awards, whether made by consent or otherwise, should make sense according to the basic conventions of the English language. They bind the parties on pain of pecuniary penalties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>City of Wanneroo v Holmes (1989) 30 IR 362</tocase>
<text>5 His Honour noted that there was no dispute about the facts. His Honour cited a number of authorities on the construction of awards: Short v FW Hercus Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 51 ; (1993) 40 FCR 511 at 520; Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 181 at 184 and City of Wanneroo v Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Unions [2006] FCA 813 at [57] . In the latter case French J referred to an observation in his earlier decision City of Wanneroo v Holmes (1989) 30 IR 362 at 380:
 Awards, whether made by consent or otherwise, should make sense according to the basic conventions of the English language. They bind the parties on pain of pecuniary penalties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>Jordan v Tasmanian Perpetual Trustees Limited [2007] FMCA 1511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/1511.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The Award provides in cl 18.1.1 for a "general entitlement" to thirteen weeks of long service leave "on completing" fifteen years of continuous service and seven weeks of such leave "on completing" each period of eight years of continuous service after the first fifteen years. At the time he retired Mr Fitzgerald had completed three years of an eight year period of service. Was he entitled to pro rata payment in lieu of long service leave for that three year period? O'Sullivan FM answered that question in the affirmative: Jordan v Tasmanian Perpetual Trustees Limited [2007] FMCA 1511. TPT now appeals.

3 The respondent to the appeal, the applicant in the court below, is a Workplace Inspector under s 167(2) of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth).

4 The relevant provisions of the Award are as follows.
 18. LONG SERVICE LEAVE 18.1 Entitlement to long service leave 18.1.1 General entitlement 
 
 Subject to 18.1.2, an employee is entitled to:
 
 18.1.1(a) thirteen weeks of long service leave on ordinary pay on completing fifteen years of continuous service with one employer; and
 
 18.1.1(b) seven weeks of long service leave on ordinary pay on completing each period of eight years of continuous service with that employer after the first fifteen years of continuous service with that employer. 
 
 18.1.2 Entitlement if service commenced before 1 March 1965 
 
 An employee whose continuous service commenced before 1 March 1965 is entitled to an amount of long service leave equal to:
 
 18.1.2(a) 1/80 of the period of his or her continuous service with one employer completed prior to 1 March 1965; plus
 
 18.1.2(b) 1/60 of the period of his or her continuous service with that employer completed subsequent to 28 February 1965; less
 
 18.1.2(c) any long service leave which has already been granted to and taken by the employee. 
 
 18.2 Payment in lieu of long service leave if employment stops after fifteen years 18.2.1 Entitlement to payment in lieu 
 
 If an employee becomes entitled to long service leave in accordance with 18.1, and that leave is not taken, the employee is entitled to payment in lieu of leave if his or her employment ends. 
 
 18.2.2 Entitlement 
 
 The employee is entitled to payment in lieu of long service leave equal to:
 
 18.2.2(a) 1/80 of the period of his or her continuous service with that employer prior to 1 March 1965; and
 
 
 18.2.2(b) 1/60 of the period of his or her continuous service with that employer subsequent to 28 February 1965. 
 
 18.3 Entitlement to long service leave if employment stops after ten years 18.3.1 Between ten and fifteen years' continuous service 
 
 This section only applies if an employee's employment is ended for any reason other than dismissal for serious and wilful misconduct and the employee has completed at least ten, but less than fifteen, years of continuous service with one employer. 
 
 18.3.2 Entitlement 
 
 The employee is entitled to an amount of long service leave equal to:
 
 18.3.2(a) 1/80 of the period of his or her continuous service with that employer completed prior to 1 March 1965; and
 
 18.3.2(b) 1/60 of the period of his or her continuous service with that employer completed subsequent to 28 February 1965. 
 
 18.4 What happens if the employee dies before leave is taken 
 
 If an employee dies before taking all the long service leave to which he or she is entitled, the employee's employer must pay to the employee's personal representative the full amount of the long service leave entitlement still owed to the employee (if any).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Short v FW Hercus Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 51 ; (1993) 40 FCR 511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/51.html</AustLII>
<text>5 His Honour noted that there was no dispute about the facts. His Honour cited a number of authorities on the construction of awards: Short v FW Hercus Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 51 ; (1993) 40 FCR 511 at 520; Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 181 at 184 and City of Wanneroo v Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Unions [2006] FCA 813 at [57] . In the latter case French J referred to an observation in his earlier decision City of Wanneroo v Holmes (1989) 30 IR 362 at 380:
 Awards, whether made by consent or otherwise, should make sense according to the basic conventions of the English language. They bind the parties on pain of pecuniary penalties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 181</tocase>
<text>5 His Honour noted that there was no dispute about the facts. His Honour cited a number of authorities on the construction of awards: Short v FW Hercus Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 51 ; (1993) 40 FCR 511 at 520; Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 181 at 184 and City of Wanneroo v Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Unions [2006] FCA 813 at [57] . In the latter case French J referred to an observation in his earlier decision City of Wanneroo v Holmes (1989) 30 IR 362 at 380:
 Awards, whether made by consent or otherwise, should make sense according to the basic conventions of the English language. They bind the parties on pain of pecuniary penalties.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>