<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>St George Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 453 (11 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/453.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australia &amp; New Zealand Savings Bank v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 493 ; (1993) 42 FCR 535</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/493.html</AustLII>
<text>59 That the process of characterisation is approached from a practical and business point of view does not provide licence to ignore the legal relationship actually formed by the terms of the transaction. Subject to considerations of sham (not relevant here) and to considerations that the legal form agreed on may have been varied or may be incomplete (also not relevant here), the process of characterisation, from a practical and business point of view, is one that is directed to the legal rights and obligations created by the parties in their transaction (here, in the constituent documents). This was made clear in the judgments of Gibbs ACJ and Stephen and Aickin JJ in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v South Australia Battery Makers Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 32 ; (1978) 140 CLR 645 at 659-660 and 662, respectively. It is also made clear in the reasons of the Full Court in CityLink Melbourne Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 272 ; (2004) 141 FCR 69 at [40] - [45] ; and in the reasons of Hill J (with whom Davies and Heerey JJ agreed) in Australia &amp; New Zealand Savings Bank v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 493 ; (1993) 42 FCR 535 at 560.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BP Australia Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1965] UKPCHCA 2 ; (1965) 112 CLR 386</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/UKPCHCA/1965/2.html</AustLII>
<text>57 To similar effect, see the judgment of the Privy Council in BP Australia Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1965] UKPCHCA 2 ; (1965) 112 CLR 386 at 397 and 399.

58 It is clear that the character of the advantage sought by the making of the expenditure is the chief, if not critical, factor in determining the character of what was paid: The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428 at 454; GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 137; Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141 at 147-149; Commissioner of Taxation v CityLink Melbourne Limited [2006] HCA 35 ; (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [1] , [3], [76], [77] and [148]; and BP Australia 112 CLR at 394 and 398.

61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>CityLink Melbourne Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 272 ; (2004) 141 FCR 69</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/272.html</AustLII>
<text>58 It is clear that the character of the advantage sought by the making of the expenditure is the chief, if not critical, factor in determining the character of what was paid: The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428 at 454; GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 137; Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141 at 147-149; Commissioner of Taxation v CityLink Melbourne Limited [2006] HCA 35 ; (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [1] , [3], [76], [77] and [148]; and BP Australia 112 CLR at 394 and 398.

59 That the process of characterisation is approached from a practical and business point of view does not provide licence to ignore the legal relationship actually formed by the terms of the transaction. Subject to considerations of sham (not relevant here) and to considerations that the legal form agreed on may have been varied or may be incomplete (also not relevant here), the process of characterisation, from a practical and business point of view, is one that is directed to the legal rights and obligations created by the parties in their transaction (here, in the constituent documents). This was made clear in the judgments of Gibbs ACJ and Stephen and Aickin JJ in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v South Australia Battery Makers Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 32 ; (1978) 140 CLR 645 at 659-660 and 662, respectively. It is also made clear in the reasons of the Full Court in CityLink Melbourne Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 272 ; (2004) 141 FCR 69 at [40] - [45] ; and in the reasons of Hill J (with whom Davies and Heerey JJ agreed) in Australia &amp; New Zealand Savings Bank v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 493 ; (1993) 42 FCR 535 at 560.

63 Equally impermissible is to recast the transaction entered between the parties and substitute an economic equivalent: CityLink Melbourne 141 FCR at 40 and Commissioner of Taxation v Myer Emporium Ltd [1987] HCA 18 ; (1986) 163 CLR 199 at 217. Some of the submissions of the Commissioner tended towards such an approach. It is not permissible, for instance, to take as the subject of characterisation what is "really happening", being the payment of money by SGB, nominally as "interest", but in truth as the payment to capital securities holder of their dividend. That is not the legal relationship that has been lawfully set up. The payment to be the subject of characterisation is the payment of interest on the Debenture under the Indenture. The task is to decide, from a business and practical perspective, giving weight to the nature of the rights and obligations of the parties created by the relevant transaction documents, and placing the Indenture and the rights and obligations arising therefrom in their complete relevant legal and business context, whether the outgoings of interest bear the character of capital or revenue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1953/68.html</AustLII>
<text>58 It is clear that the character of the advantage sought by the making of the expenditure is the chief, if not critical, factor in determining the character of what was paid: The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428 at 454; GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 137; Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141 at 147-149; Commissioner of Taxation v CityLink Melbourne Limited [2006] HCA 35 ; (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [1] , [3], [76], [77] and [148]; and BP Australia 112 CLR at 394 and 398.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Asiamet (No 1) Resources Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 73 ; (2004) 137 FCR 146</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/73.html</AustLII>
<text>62 At times, the submissions put on behalf of SGB appeared to combine the undoubtedly correct (at least at a sufficient level of generality) propositions that the contractual and legal rights must be analysed and that the separateness of corporate entities must be recognised: The Federal Coke Company v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 15 ALR 449 at 459 per Bowen CJ and Commissioner of Taxation v Asiamet (No 1) Resources Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 73 ; (2004) 137 FCR 146 at [148] - [165] , in aid of a different objective, that is to have the interest payable under the Debenture analysed by reference primarily, if not wholly, to the rights and obligations created under the Indenture, without regard to the whole of the surrounding arrangement. Such an approach is impermissible. It ignores the essential requirement to view the legal rights and obligations created by the parties, and payments and outgoings made thereunder, in their whole legal and commercial context, in order that the characterisation, from a business and practical point of view, of the payment or outgoing by reference to the relevant legal relationship can be undertaken. Legal form is the subject of the characterisation; it is not the sole source of the answer to that process of characterisation: cf Parsons RW op cit [2.421]-[2.422]. The requirement to look at the whole legal and business context is not denied by what was said by Deane and Sheppard JJ in Ure v Federal Commission of Taxation (1981) 34 ALR 237 at 249, as appeared to be put by SGB.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42</tocase>
<text>61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Indooroopilly Children Services (Qld) Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 325</tocase>
<text>99 It is unnecessary to decide this aspect of the case. The parties, however, fully argued the relevant issues. I was invited by the Commissioner to provide my reasons on the issues argued even if they were not necessary for my decision. After initially submitting that I should not do so, SGB put submissions to the effect of those put by the Commissioner in this respect. I have given careful consideration to complying with the request of the parties to discuss Division 974 even if it is not necessary for a decision. I have come to the view that I should not, for three reasons. First, no separate body of facts needs to be found for the assistance of a Full Court, should I be found to have erred in my earlier analysis. Secondly, however detailed and concluded my views, they would not be essential for the reasoning underlying the orders made. They would, as obiter dicta , lack a degree of authority. Subject to conforming with the law of Australia as laid out by Parliament and as interpreted and declared by the courts as the judicial branch of government: (see Commissioner of Taxation v Indooroopilly Children Services (Qld) Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 325) it is for the Commissioner and the ATO to administer the revenue legislation as they interpret it. There has been public comment made by the Commissioner, the ATO, and others, apparently doubting elements of these basal governmental separations, responsibilities and functions discussed in Indooroopilly 158 FCR 325. This is not the place to enter that debate. It is, however, appropriate to recognise that courts decide cases and, in so doing, declare the law, including the meaning and effect of laws of the Parliament. To the extent that my views on Division 974 would be clearly obiter dicta, they may create an unnecessary impediment to the administration of the revenue legislation if they are not part of the ratio decidendi of the decision. Thirdly, the business community and capital markets, likewise, will have my views that are not part of the ratio decidendi affecting questions of advice and judgment in circumstances where the views of the Commissioner and the ATO can be sought by ruling or assessment, and, thereafter, be directly and specifically tested and ruled upon in a way binding on both the revenue and the taxpayer.

100 I should add that I have come to these views having had the benefit of the thorough and careful submission of counsel for both sides (for which I express my gratitude) and having considered these submissions in considerable detail.

101 As to the evidence requiring a ruling I set out my rulings and my reasons (in brief).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Myer Emporium Ltd [1987] HCA 18 ; (1986) 163 CLR 199</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/18.html</AustLII>
<text>63 Equally impermissible is to recast the transaction entered between the parties and substitute an economic equivalent: CityLink Melbourne 141 FCR at 40 and Commissioner of Taxation v Myer Emporium Ltd [1987] HCA 18 ; (1986) 163 CLR 199 at 217. Some of the submissions of the Commissioner tended towards such an approach. It is not permissible, for instance, to take as the subject of characterisation what is "really happening", being the payment of money by SGB, nominally as "interest", but in truth as the payment to capital securities holder of their dividend. That is not the legal relationship that has been lawfully set up. The payment to be the subject of characterisation is the payment of interest on the Debenture under the Indenture. The task is to decide, from a business and practical perspective, giving weight to the nature of the rights and obligations of the parties created by the relevant transaction documents, and placing the Indenture and the rights and obligations arising therefrom in their complete relevant legal and business context, whether the outgoings of interest bear the character of capital or revenue.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v South Australia Battery Makers Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 32 ; (1978) 140 CLR 645</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/32.html</AustLII>
<text>59 That the process of characterisation is approached from a practical and business point of view does not provide licence to ignore the legal relationship actually formed by the terms of the transaction. Subject to considerations of sham (not relevant here) and to considerations that the legal form agreed on may have been varied or may be incomplete (also not relevant here), the process of characterisation, from a practical and business point of view, is one that is directed to the legal rights and obligations created by the parties in their transaction (here, in the constituent documents). This was made clear in the judgments of Gibbs ACJ and Stephen and Aickin JJ in Federal Commissioner of Taxation v South Australia Battery Makers Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 32 ; (1978) 140 CLR 645 at 659-660 and 662, respectively. It is also made clear in the reasons of the Full Court in CityLink Melbourne Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCAFC 272 ; (2004) 141 FCR 69 at [40] - [45] ; and in the reasons of Hill J (with whom Davies and Heerey JJ agreed) in Australia &amp; New Zealand Savings Bank v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] FCA 493 ; (1993) 42 FCR 535 at 560.

82 The conclusion that I have reached is supported by South Australian Battery Makers [1978] HCA 32 ; 140 CLR 645. As Gibbs ACJ said at 655:
 
 If on the other hand one advantage sought by the outgoings was the acquisition of a capital asset (the land and buildings), the fact that the payments were called 'rent', and were made periodically, would not necessarily prevent them from being in part outgoings of a capital nature.

83 There, the capital advantage was not obtained by the taxpayer; here it was. The benefit of the arrangement and integrated structure of which the Indenture and Debenture were an integral and integrated part inured to the benefit of SGB by the strengthening of the capital structure of SGB and its group in a manner that was acceptable to the RBA. The advantage sought and obtained by the interest payments was the assistance in the creation and maintenance of that business capital structure for the long-term structural benefit of SGB.

84 Division 974 was introduced into the 1997 Act by the Debt/Equity Act. The Debt/Equity Provisions sought to set out a statutory regime for the treatment of the deductibility of returns on financial interests issued by a company. In particular, these provisions sought to identify new rules governing what is an equity interest and what is a debt interest for tax purposes, based on the economic substance of the rights and obligations of the arrangement, rather than their legal form. A premise underlying the rationale of the provisions was the likely deductibility of interest on what is a debt in legal form.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Federal Coke Company v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 15 ALR 449</tocase>
<text>62 At times, the submissions put on behalf of SGB appeared to combine the undoubtedly correct (at least at a sufficient level of generality) propositions that the contractual and legal rights must be analysed and that the separateness of corporate entities must be recognised: The Federal Coke Company v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 15 ALR 449 at 459 per Bowen CJ and Commissioner of Taxation v Asiamet (No 1) Resources Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 73 ; (2004) 137 FCR 146 at [148] - [165] , in aid of a different objective, that is to have the interest payable under the Debenture analysed by reference primarily, if not wholly, to the rights and obligations created under the Indenture, without regard to the whole of the surrounding arrangement. Such an approach is impermissible. It ignores the essential requirement to view the legal rights and obligations created by the parties, and payments and outgoings made thereunder, in their whole legal and commercial context, in order that the characterisation, from a business and practical point of view, of the payment or outgoing by reference to the relevant legal relationship can be undertaken. Legal form is the subject of the characterisation; it is not the sole source of the answer to that process of characterisation: cf Parsons RW op cit [2.421]-[2.422]. The requirement to look at the whole legal and business context is not denied by what was said by Deane and Sheppard JJ in Ure v Federal Commission of Taxation (1981) 34 ALR 237 at 249, as appeared to be put by SGB.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/25.html</AustLII>
<text>58 It is clear that the character of the advantage sought by the making of the expenditure is the chief, if not critical, factor in determining the character of what was paid: The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428 at 454; GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 137; Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141 at 147-149; Commissioner of Taxation v CityLink Melbourne Limited [2006] HCA 35 ; (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [1] , [3], [76], [77] and [148]; and BP Australia 112 CLR at 394 and 398.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>applied</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Hallstroms Proprietary Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1946] HCA 34 ; (1946) 72 CLR 634</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1946/34.html</AustLII>
<text>56 In Hallstroms Proprietary Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1946] HCA 34 ; (1946) 72 CLR 634 , Dixon J incorporated his reasons in Sun Newspapers 61 CLR at 359-363 and elaborated upon them saying the following at 646, 647 and 648:
 
 As a prefatory remark it may be useful to recall the general consideration that the contrast between the two forms of expenditure corresponds to the distinction between the acquisition of the means of production and the use of them; between establishing or extending a business organization and carrying on the business; between the implements employed in work and the regular performance of the work in which they are employed; between an enterprise itself and the sustained effort of those engaged in it. 
 
 ... 
 
 What is an outgoing of capital and what is an outgoing on account of revenue depends on what the expenditure is calculated to effect from a practical and business point of view, rather than upon the juristic classification of the legal rights, if any, secured, employed or exhausted in the process. 
 
 [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Heather v P-E Consulting Group Ltd [1973] Ch 189</tocase>
<text>54 By and large, the parties were not in disagreement about the governing legal principles. The disagreement, however, came in the characterisation called for by those principles. At times, there appeared to be a difference between the parties based on the posited distinctions, first, between legal form and business substance, and secondly, between the loan or non-loan character of the Debenture. Neither such distinction is determinative. The relevant distinction is in the words of s 8-1: capital or in the nature of capital (juxtaposed against the contrary concept inherent in the context of s 8-1(2): that of revenue outgoing). Ultimately, however, the difference between the parties can be found in the process of characterisation of the legal relationship created among the parties, set in the full business and legal context of that relationship. Minds may differ in the conclusions reached in that exercise. That is almost inevitable in such a process of characterisation when the facts are not sufficiently obvious as to answer the question themselves: cf Heather v P-E Consulting Group Ltd [1973] Ch 189.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760</tocase>
<text>61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>John Fairfax &amp; Sons Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1959] HCA 4 ; (1959) 101 CLR 30</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/4.html</AustLII>
<text>53 There was no issue about s 8-1(1). It should be noted at the outset that this concession by the Commissioner did not provoke an argument on behalf of SGB that this led to the satisfaction of s 8-1(2). There was no debate or discussion as to the true nature of the "negative limbs" of s 8-1(2) and whether they operate only by way of contradistinction to illustrate what is not included, from the outset, in the "positive limbs" of s 8-1(1), or as true exceptions: Macquarie Finance Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [104] : SA Battery Makers Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1976) 28 FLR 451 at 463; and Parsons, RW Income Tax in Australia (1985, Law Book Co Sydney) at [5.12]. The argument proceeded, in substance, on the basis that s 8-1(2) was a true exception, an approach which has judicial support: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1999) 197 CLR 459 at 468 [24] and John Fairfax &amp; Sons Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1959] HCA 4 ; (1959) 101 CLR 30 at 34, and which accords more with a plain reading of the text of the statute.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1170.html</AustLII>
<text>61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.

64 Before examining the relevant aspects of the overall arrangement to answer this question, it is necessary to say something about the submissions about interest and deductibility. The expression of views by the judges in cases as to the usual approach to interest in this context should be seen for what they are, and are not. They are the discussion of the kinds of consideration discussed by Dixon J in Sun Newspapers and Hallstroms Case in the context of interest on a loan. Thus, it can be accepted that, ordinarily, interest will be an allowable deduction under s 8-1, if incurred in the course of an income-producing activity or business: Texas Co (Australasia) Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1940] HCA 9 ; (1940) 63 CLR 382 at 468 and Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-70 [27]. This acceptance does not lay down some independent rule to be engaged and analysed beyond the characterisation enquiry discussed earlier. Rather, interest is usually deductible because, usually, it is a recurrent or periodic payment securing an advantage not of an enduring kind, but the use by the borrower of money during the term of the loan: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-470 [27]. But, as was noted in the same paragraph, "there may be particular circumstances where it is proper to regard the purpose of interest payments as something other than the raising or maintenance of the borrowing and thus, potentially, of a capital nature." To this passage there was footnoted Parsons RW op cit [6.11]. The possibilities referred to by Professor Parsons in that paragraph do not form an exhaustive universe of non-deductible interest. See also the discussion by Hill J at first instance in Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation 210 ALR at [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Macquarie Finance Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/205.html</AustLII>
<text>53 There was no issue about s 8-1(1). It should be noted at the outset that this concession by the Commissioner did not provoke an argument on behalf of SGB that this led to the satisfaction of s 8-1(2). There was no debate or discussion as to the true nature of the "negative limbs" of s 8-1(2) and whether they operate only by way of contradistinction to illustrate what is not included, from the outset, in the "positive limbs" of s 8-1(1), or as true exceptions: Macquarie Finance Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [104] : SA Battery Makers Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1976) 28 FLR 451 at 463; and Parsons, RW Income Tax in Australia (1985, Law Book Co Sydney) at [5.12]. The argument proceeded, in substance, on the basis that s 8-1(2) was a true exception, an approach which has judicial support: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1999) 197 CLR 459 at 468 [24] and John Fairfax &amp; Sons Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1959] HCA 4 ; (1959) 101 CLR 30 at 34, and which accords more with a plain reading of the text of the statute.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/62.html</AustLII>
<text>58 It is clear that the character of the advantage sought by the making of the expenditure is the chief, if not critical, factor in determining the character of what was paid: The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1953] HCA 68 ; (1953) 89 CLR 428 at 454; GP International Pipecoaters Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 25 ; (1990) 170 CLR 124 at 137; Mount Isa Mines Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 62 ; (1992) 176 CLR 141 at 147-149; Commissioner of Taxation v CityLink Melbourne Limited [2006] HCA 35 ; (2006) 228 CLR 1 at [1] , [3], [76], [77] and [148]; and BP Australia 112 CLR at 394 and 398.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352</tocase>
<text>61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SA Battery Makers Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1976) 28 FLR 451</tocase>
<text>53 There was no issue about s 8-1(1). It should be noted at the outset that this concession by the Commissioner did not provoke an argument on behalf of SGB that this led to the satisfaction of s 8-1(2). There was no debate or discussion as to the true nature of the "negative limbs" of s 8-1(2) and whether they operate only by way of contradistinction to illustrate what is not included, from the outset, in the "positive limbs" of s 8-1(1), or as true exceptions: Macquarie Finance Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [104] : SA Battery Makers Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1976) 28 FLR 451 at 463; and Parsons, RW Income Tax in Australia (1985, Law Book Co Sydney) at [5.12]. The argument proceeded, in substance, on the basis that s 8-1(2) was a true exception, an approach which has judicial support: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1999) 197 CLR 459 at 468 [24] and John Fairfax &amp; Sons Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1959] HCA 4 ; (1959) 101 CLR 30 at 34, and which accords more with a plain reading of the text of the statute.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1999) 197 CLR 459</tocase>
<text>53 There was no issue about s 8-1(1). It should be noted at the outset that this concession by the Commissioner did not provoke an argument on behalf of SGB that this led to the satisfaction of s 8-1(2). There was no debate or discussion as to the true nature of the "negative limbs" of s 8-1(2) and whether they operate only by way of contradistinction to illustrate what is not included, from the outset, in the "positive limbs" of s 8-1(1), or as true exceptions: Macquarie Finance Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 205 ; (2005) 146 FCR 77 at [104] : SA Battery Makers Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1976) 28 FLR 451 at 463; and Parsons, RW Income Tax in Australia (1985, Law Book Co Sydney) at [5.12]. The argument proceeded, in substance, on the basis that s 8-1(2) was a true exception, an approach which has judicial support: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1999) 197 CLR 459 at 468 [24] and John Fairfax &amp; Sons Pty Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [1959] HCA 4 ; (1959) 101 CLR 30 at 34, and which accords more with a plain reading of the text of the statute.

64 Before examining the relevant aspects of the overall arrangement to answer this question, it is necessary to say something about the submissions about interest and deductibility. The expression of views by the judges in cases as to the usual approach to interest in this context should be seen for what they are, and are not. They are the discussion of the kinds of consideration discussed by Dixon J in Sun Newspapers and Hallstroms Case in the context of interest on a loan. Thus, it can be accepted that, ordinarily, interest will be an allowable deduction under s 8-1, if incurred in the course of an income-producing activity or business: Texas Co (Australasia) Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1940] HCA 9 ; (1940) 63 CLR 382 at 468 and Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-70 [27]. This acceptance does not lay down some independent rule to be engaged and analysed beyond the characterisation enquiry discussed earlier. Rather, interest is usually deductible because, usually, it is a recurrent or periodic payment securing an advantage not of an enduring kind, but the use by the borrower of money during the term of the loan: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-470 [27]. But, as was noted in the same paragraph, "there may be particular circumstances where it is proper to regard the purpose of interest payments as something other than the raising or maintenance of the borrowing and thus, potentially, of a capital nature." To this passage there was footnoted Parsons RW op cit [6.11]. The possibilities referred to by Professor Parsons in that paragraph do not form an exhaustive universe of non-deductible interest. See also the discussion by Hill J at first instance in Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation 210 ALR at [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>applied</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Sun Newspapers Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation; Associated Newspapers Limited v The Federal Commis s ioner of Taxation [1938] HCA 73 ; (1938) 61 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/73.html</AustLII>
<text>55 The starting point for analysis is the judgment of Dixon J (as he then was) in Sun Newspapers Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation; Associated Newspapers Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1938] HCA 73 ; (1938) 61 CLR 337 at 359-363. A number of passages in that classic analysis at 359, 360, 361, 362 and 363 are worthy of repetition here:
 
 The distinction between expenditure and outgoings on revenue account and on capital account corresponds with the distinction between the business entity, structure, or organization set up or established for the earning of profit and the process by which such an organization operates to obtain regular returns by means of regular outlay, the difference between the outlay and returns representing profit or loss. The business structure or entity or organization may assume any of an almost infinite variety of shapes and it may be difficult to comprehend under one description all the forms in which it may be manifested. In a trade or pursuit where little or no plant is required, it may be represented by no more than the intangible elements constituting what is commonly called goodwill, that is, widespread or general reputation, habitual patronage by clients or customers and an organized method of serving their needs. At the other extreme it may consist in a great aggregate of buildings, machinery and plant all assembled and systematized as the material means by which an organized body of men produce and distribute commodities or perform services. But in spite of the entirely different forms, material and immaterial, in which it may be expressed, such sources of income contain or consist in what has been called a "profit-yielding subject," the phrase of Lord Blackburn in United Collieries Ltd. v. Inland Revenue Commissioners ... As general conceptions it may not be difficult to distinguish between the profit-yielding subject and the process of operating it. In the same way expenditure and outlay upon establishing, replacing and enlarging the profit-yielding subject may in a general way appear to be of a nature entirely different from the continual flow of working expenses which are or ought to be supplied continually out of the returns or revenue . ... But the practical application of such general notions is another matter. The basal difficulty in applying them lies in the fact that the extent, condition and efficiency of the profit-yielding subject is often as much the product of the course of operations as it is of a clear and definable outlay of work or money by way of establishment, replacement or enlargement . ... But for the same or a like reason it is even harder to maintain the distinction in relation to the intangible elements forming so important a part of many profit-yielding subjects. For example, a profitable enterprise such as the sale of a patent medicine may depend almost entirely on advertisement. In the beginning the goodwill may have been established by a great initial outlay upon a widespread advertising campaign carried out upon a scale which it was not intended to maintain or repeat. The outlay might properly be considered to be of a capital nature. On the other hand the goodwill may have been gradually established by continual advertisement over a period of years growing in extent as it proved successful. In that case the expenditure upon advertising might be regarded as an ordinary business outgoing on account of revenue. 

 ... 
 
 In the attempt, by no means successful, to find some test or standard by the application of which expenditure or outgoings may be referred to capital account or to revenue account the courts have relied to some extent upon the difference between an outlay which is recurrent, repeated or continual and that which is final or made "once for all", and to a still greater extent upon a distinction to be discovered in the nature of the asset or advantage obtained by the outlay. If what is commonly understood as a fixed capital asset is acquired the question answers itself. But the distinction goes further. The result or purpose of the expenditure may be to bring into existence or procure some asset or advantage of a lasting character which will enure for the benefit of the organization or system or "profit-earning subject." It will thus be distinguished from the expenditure which should be recouped by circulating capital or by working capital. 

 ... 
 
 But the idea of recurrence and the idea of endurance or continuance over a duration of time both depend on degree and comparison. As to the first it has been said it is not a question of recurring every year or every accounting period; but "the real test is between expenditure which is made to meet a continuous demand, as opposed to an expenditure which is made once for all" ... By this I understand that the expenditure is to be considered of a revenue nature if its purpose brings it within the very wide class of things which in the aggregate form the constant demand which must be answered out of the returns of a trade or its circulating capital and that actual recurrence of the specific thing need not take place or be expected as likely. Thus, in Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Ltd. v. Dale ... the establishment and reorganization of agencies formed part of the class of things making the continuous or constant demand for expenditure, but the given transaction was of a magnitude and precise description unlikely again to be encountered. Recurrence is not a test, it is no more than a consideration the weight of which depends upon the nature of the expenditure. 
 
 ... 
 
 There are, I think, three matters to be considered, (a) the character of the advantage sought, and in this its lasting qualities may play a part, (b) the manner in which it is to be used, relied upon or enjoyed, and in this and under the former head recurrence may play its part, and (c) the means adopted to obtain it; that is, by providing a periodical reward or outlay to cover its use or enjoyment for periods commensurate with the payment or by making a final provision or payment so as to secure future use or enjoyment. 
 
[emphasis added; footnotes omitted]

56 In Hallstroms Proprietary Limited v The Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1946] HCA 34 ; (1946) 72 CLR 634 , Dixon J incorporated his reasons in Sun Newspapers 61 CLR at 359-363 and elaborated upon them saying the following at 646, 647 and 648:
 
 As a prefatory remark it may be useful to recall the general consideration that the contrast between the two forms of expenditure corresponds to the distinction between the acquisition of the means of production and the use of them; between establishing or extending a business organization and carrying on the business; between the implements employed in work and the regular performance of the work in which they are employed; between an enterprise itself and the sustained effort of those engaged in it. 
 
 ... 
 
 What is an outgoing of capital and what is an outgoing on account of revenue depends on what the expenditure is calculated to effect from a practical and business point of view, rather than upon the juristic classification of the legal rights, if any, secured, employed or exhausted in the process. 
 
 [emphasis added]

60 Thus, it is not helpful to ascertain the subject matter for characterisation otherwise than by (subject to sham etc) straightforward analysis of the legal relationship of the parties and the ascertainment from that analysis of the legal context and character of the payment. The conclusions drawn from that analysis will, of course, be relevant to the central task assessing, from a practical business point of view, the true business character of the outgoing by reference to the notions of capital and revenue illuminated by Dixon J in Sun Newspapers and Hallstroms Case.

64 Before examining the relevant aspects of the overall arrangement to answer this question, it is necessary to say something about the submissions about interest and deductibility. The expression of views by the judges in cases as to the usual approach to interest in this context should be seen for what they are, and are not. They are the discussion of the kinds of consideration discussed by Dixon J in Sun Newspapers and Hallstroms Case in the context of interest on a loan. Thus, it can be accepted that, ordinarily, interest will be an allowable deduction under s 8-1, if incurred in the course of an income-producing activity or business: Texas Co (Australasia) Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1940] HCA 9 ; (1940) 63 CLR 382 at 468 and Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-70 [27]. This acceptance does not lay down some independent rule to be engaged and analysed beyond the characterisation enquiry discussed earlier. Rather, interest is usually deductible because, usually, it is a recurrent or periodic payment securing an advantage not of an enduring kind, but the use by the borrower of money during the term of the loan: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-470 [27]. But, as was noted in the same paragraph, "there may be particular circumstances where it is proper to regard the purpose of interest payments as something other than the raising or maintenance of the borrowing and thus, potentially, of a capital nature." To this passage there was footnoted Parsons RW op cit [6.11]. The possibilities referred to by Professor Parsons in that paragraph do not form an exhaustive universe of non-deductible interest. See also the discussion by Hill J at first instance in Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation 210 ALR at [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Texas Co (Australasia) Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1940] HCA 9 ; (1940) 63 CLR 382</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1940/9.html</AustLII>
<text>64 Before examining the relevant aspects of the overall arrangement to answer this question, it is necessary to say something about the submissions about interest and deductibility. The expression of views by the judges in cases as to the usual approach to interest in this context should be seen for what they are, and are not. They are the discussion of the kinds of consideration discussed by Dixon J in Sun Newspapers and Hallstroms Case in the context of interest on a loan. Thus, it can be accepted that, ordinarily, interest will be an allowable deduction under s 8-1, if incurred in the course of an income-producing activity or business: Texas Co (Australasia) Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1940] HCA 9 ; (1940) 63 CLR 382 at 468 and Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-70 [27]. This acceptance does not lay down some independent rule to be engaged and analysed beyond the characterisation enquiry discussed earlier. Rather, interest is usually deductible because, usually, it is a recurrent or periodic payment securing an advantage not of an enduring kind, but the use by the borrower of money during the term of the loan: Steele v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation 197 CLR at 469-470 [27]. But, as was noted in the same paragraph, "there may be particular circumstances where it is proper to regard the purpose of interest payments as something other than the raising or maintenance of the borrowing and thus, potentially, of a capital nature." To this passage there was footnoted Parsons RW op cit [6.11]. The possibilities referred to by Professor Parsons in that paragraph do not form an exhaustive universe of non-deductible interest. See also the discussion by Hill J at first instance in Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation 210 ALR at [47].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ure v Federal Commission of Taxation (1981) 34 ALR 237</tocase>
<text>62 At times, the submissions put on behalf of SGB appeared to combine the undoubtedly correct (at least at a sufficient level of generality) propositions that the contractual and legal rights must be analysed and that the separateness of corporate entities must be recognised: The Federal Coke Company v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 15 ALR 449 at 459 per Bowen CJ and Commissioner of Taxation v Asiamet (No 1) Resources Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 73 ; (2004) 137 FCR 146 at [148] - [165] , in aid of a different objective, that is to have the interest payable under the Debenture analysed by reference primarily, if not wholly, to the rights and obligations created under the Indenture, without regard to the whole of the surrounding arrangement. Such an approach is impermissible. It ignores the essential requirement to view the legal rights and obligations created by the parties, and payments and outgoings made thereunder, in their whole legal and commercial context, in order that the characterisation, from a business and practical point of view, of the payment or outgoing by reference to the relevant legal relationship can be undertaken. Legal form is the subject of the characterisation; it is not the sole source of the answer to that process of characterisation: cf Parsons RW op cit [2.421]-[2.422]. The requirement to look at the whole legal and business context is not denied by what was said by Deane and Sheppard JJ in Ure v Federal Commission of Taxation (1981) 34 ALR 237 at 249, as appeared to be put by SGB.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/5.html</AustLII>
<text>61 It is also essential to recognise that the above analysis of characterisation requires "both a wide survey and an exact scrutiny of the taxpayer's activities": Western Gold Mines (NL) v Commissioner of Taxation (WA) [1938] HCA 5 ; (1938) 59 CLR 729 at 740. That is, one examines the whole business context of what was done: BP Australia 112 CLR at 399; National Australia Bank Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 80 FCR 352 at 362; Commissioner of Taxation v Cooling (1990) 22 FCR 42 at 52-53 (Hill J); and Macquarie Finance Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2004] FCA 1170 ; (2004) 210 ALR 508 (Hill J) at [64]. Relevant also here is the close interconnection of all the constituent documents in the integrated international commercial transaction: cf Inland Revenue Commissioner v Europa Oil (NZ) Ltd [1971] AC 760 at 774-775.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>