<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v PRK Corporation Limited [2008] FCA 403 (28 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/403.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1678.html</AustLII>
<text>26 Mr Bannon submitted that this construction of s 45(2)(b)(ii) of the TP Act was supported by several matters.
 
 
 &#8226; First, s 45(4) of the TP Act, a deeming provision, assumes that a corporation which is potentially the subject of an allegation that it has contravened s 45(2)(b)(ii) must have been party to the original arrangement.
 &#8226; Secondly, the definition of ' give effect to ' in s 4 of the TP Act also appears to be drafted on the assumption that only a party to the arrangement can do an act in pursuance of or in accordance with a provision of the arrangement.
 &#8226; Thirdly, the authorities indicate that a corporation can give effect to a provision in an arrangement independently of that corporation's motive. It would create an unrealistic burden on corporations (so Mr Bannon argued) if their conduct could give effect to an anti-competitive provision in an arrangement without the corporation being a party to the arrangement or realising that its actions constitute a contravention of the TP Act: Tradestock Pty Ltd v TNT (Management) Pty Ltd (1978) 32 FLR 420, at 432, per Smithers J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 , at [294], per Merkel J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd v Peat Marwick Hungerfords [1997] HCA 8 ; (1997) 188 CLR 241</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/8.html</AustLII>
<text>28 It is sometimes appropriate to decide a pure question of law on a strike out motion: Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd v Peat Marwick Hungerfords [1997] HCA 8 ; (1997) 188 CLR 241. But the authorities do not suggest that a court is bound to do so ( Morgan v Union Shipping (Nz) Ltd [2001] NSWSC 325 , at [9], per Sperling J and authorities cited there). Mr Bannon did not submit otherwise.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Morgan v Union Shipping (Nz) Ltd [2001] NSWSC 325</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/325.html</AustLII>
<text>28 It is sometimes appropriate to decide a pure question of law on a strike out motion: Esanda Finance Corporation Ltd v Peat Marwick Hungerfords [1997] HCA 8 ; (1997) 188 CLR 241. But the authorities do not suggest that a court is bound to do so ( Morgan v Union Shipping (Nz) Ltd [2001] NSWSC 325 , at [9], per Sperling J and authorities cited there). Mr Bannon did not submit otherwise.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/213.html</AustLII>
<text>65 None of the Patrick Respondents is an individual. Mr Bathurst, however, argued that the problems identified by Mr Hutley are even more acute so far as Mr Burgess and other individual respondents are concerned. He also pointed out that there is no allegation that Mr Burgess was aware of the precise material facts and circumstances constituting the contraventions of s 45(2): see Rural Press Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2002] FCAFC 213 ; (2002) 118 FCR 236 , at 283 [162], per curiam.

66 In answer to these submissions, Mr Burnside used the pleaded allegations of accessorial liability against Mr Burgess to illustrate the argument. Mr Burnside contended that a number of specific allegations are made about the extent of Mr Burgess' knowledge of relevant matters. In response to a question, Mr Burnside stated that the case against Mr Burgess does not depend on which of the P&amp;O Respondents happened to be a party to the pleaded arrangements, or to have given effect to the provisions of the pleaded arrangements.

67 I expressed the view ( Ts 136 ) that if this was the ACCC's case, the Statement of Claim should be amended to make it quite clear. The pleading should explicitly allege that by reason of specific matters known to Mr Burgess, he aided and abetted, or was knowingly concerned in, any contraventions that might be established against either or both of the P&amp;O Respondents. The pleading should also identify unambiguously the matters known to Mr Burgess and the other individual respondents that are said to show that each was aware of the material facts and circumstances constituting the contraventions of s 45(2) of the TP Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tradestock Pty Ltd v TNT (Management) Pty Ltd (1978) 32 FLR 420</tocase>
<text>26 Mr Bannon submitted that this construction of s 45(2)(b)(ii) of the TP Act was supported by several matters.
 
 
 &#8226; First, s 45(4) of the TP Act, a deeming provision, assumes that a corporation which is potentially the subject of an allegation that it has contravened s 45(2)(b)(ii) must have been party to the original arrangement.
 &#8226; Secondly, the definition of ' give effect to ' in s 4 of the TP Act also appears to be drafted on the assumption that only a party to the arrangement can do an act in pursuance of or in accordance with a provision of the arrangement.
 &#8226; Thirdly, the authorities indicate that a corporation can give effect to a provision in an arrangement independently of that corporation's motive. It would create an unrealistic burden on corporations (so Mr Bannon argued) if their conduct could give effect to an anti-competitive provision in an arrangement without the corporation being a party to the arrangement or realising that its actions constitute a contravention of the TP Act: Tradestock Pty Ltd v TNT (Management) Pty Ltd (1978) 32 FLR 420, at 432, per Smithers J; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1678 , at [294], per Merkel J.

29 In the present case, I do not think it appropriate to attempt to resolve the question of law presented by Mr Bannon on behalf of AAT. The contention is arguable, but its correctness is by no means self-evident. The authorities recognise, for example, that the expression ' in accordance with ' in the definition of ' give effect to ' in s 4 of the TP Act :
 
 'are intended to cover the situation where what is done is or may be done for reasons other than to implement the understanding.' 
 

 Tradestock v TNT, at 432. In other words, the expression indicates that a corporation may give effect to an arrangement otherwise than by implementing it. The statutory language may suggest, therefore, that a corporation can give effect to a provision of an arrangement even though it is not party to the arrangement.

30 In any event, the question of construction raised by AAT ultimately may be resolved by reference to the particular facts of the case which, of course have not yet been found. AAT is not in the same situation as a third party which has no involvement with an alleged arrangement but which subsequently does something that happens to be connected to the goals sought to be achieved by the parties to the arrangement. The ACCC alleges that the very point of the two of the pleaded arrangements was to allow the Patrick Respondent and the P&amp;O Corporations to utilise AAT as the vehicle for carrying into effect the anti-competitive elements of the arrangement. AAT may well be in quite a different position to a third party that had no prior knowledge of the arrangement and was never intended to have any particular role to play in implementing the anti-competitive provisions of the arrangement.

31 For these reasons, it is not appropriate to resolve the question of law raised by AAT on the strike out application. The question is arguable and should be resolved at the trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/65.html</AustLII>
<text>61 The Patrick Respondents point out that the Statement of Claim alleges that each of the Patrick Respondents aided and abetted and was knowingly concerned in the contraventions of each of the others. They submit that the Statement of Claim fails to plead material facts, including the knowledge of the essential elements of the contravention and intentional participation: Yorke v Lucas [1985] HCA 65 ; (1985) 158 CLR 661. Mr Hutley, in his oral argument, pointed out that the complaint is of practical importance since Patrick is now a subsidiary of Toll, but the other four Patrick Respondents are within another corporate group.

62 Mr Hutley illustrated the point by reference to the pleading alleging contraventions by Patrick. Paragraph 260 pleads that ' in the premises ' Patrick:
 
 
 '260.1 by entering into the first arrangement, made an arrangement ... containing provisions which had the purpose ... or likely effect of substantially lessening competition in each of [twelve markets]. 
 
 and thereby contravened [s 45(2)(a)(ii) of the TP Act ]; or alternatively 
 
 260.2 aided and abetted, or was knowingly concerned in: 
 
 
 
 260.2.1 the contravention by Patrick Holdings in making the first arrangement...; 
 
 260.2.2 the contravention by Patrick Operations in making the first arrangement ...; 
 
 260.2.3 the contravention by Patrick Operations No 2 in making the first arrangement...'.

63 The pleadings follow a similar pattern in relation to Patrick's alleged contravention of s 45(2)(b)(ii) of the TP Act and its knowing participation in the contraventions of that sub-paragraph by each of the other three named Patrick Respondents (para 261). They also follow a similar pattern in relation to the second arrangement (paras 262-263). The same form of pleading is repeated for each of those three Patrick Respondents.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>