<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tidswell Financial Services Limited (ACN 010 810 607) v Sovereign Capital Limited (ACN 085 821 218) [2008] FCA 586 (29 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/586.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>National Mutual Holdings Pty Ltd v The Sentry Corporation (1988) 19 FCR 155 </tocase>
<text>8 The principles to be applied on such motions are well accepted and are not in dispute. The discretion to make an order under s 48 is unfettered, although it must be exercised judicially and in accordance with accepted principle. As to the latter it is only necessary that I refer to the Full Court decision in National Mutual Holdings Pty Ltd v The Sentry Corporation (1988) 19 FCR 155 which has been followed repeatedly. The Court there indicated (at 162) that the discretion given should be exercised flexibly having regard to the circumstances of the particular case; the factors which the Court is entitled to take into account in considering whether one city is more appropriate than another for interlocutory or final hearings are numerous and include residence of parties and witnesses, expense to parties, the place where the cause of action arose and the convenience of the Court; the balance of convenience will be a relevant consideration, but not necessarily determinative of each case; there is no onus of proof in the strict sense on the party seeking to have the proceedings conducted or continued in another place but the Court must be satisfied that there is sound reason to direct that the proceeding be conducted or continued elsewhere; the test to be applied, ultimately is:
 ... where can the case be conducted or continued most suitably bearing in mind the interests of all the parties, the ends of justice in the determination of the issues between them, and the most efficient administration of the Court. It cannot and should not, in our opinion, be defined more closely or precisely.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Inverness Medical Switzerland GMBH v Advance Chemical Systems Pty Limited [2002] FCA 1261</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1261.html</AustLII>
<text>9 Given this test it is unsurprising that judges have observed that authorities on such motions tend not to be very helpful given the fact specific character of the question the s 48 discretion raised: see eg Inverness Medical Switzerland GMBH v Advance Chemical Systems Pty Limited [2002] FCA 1261 at [2] .

10 The matters relied upon in Mr Parker's affidavit in support of the motion are (i) the first respondent's principal place of business is at Broadbeach as is the place of residence of the majority of staff (past and present) who can be expected to be called to give evidence at trial; (ii) the legal practice conducted by Mr Parker and Mr Simmonds will be significantly affected if the trial (estimated by both sides to take two weeks) at which they necessarily must attend, is to be held in Adelaide 
(a) they are the firm's only principals;
(b) their employees are junior solicitors without open practising certificates;
 
(c) the practice consists predominantly of conveyancing and typically issues more than fifty trust cheques per week; 
 
(d) no employee of the firm has authority to execute a trust account cheque (in accordance with the Queensland Law Society Rules); and 
 
(e) the practice needs at least one of the partners to be readily accessible to clients and staff and for administrative matters.
(iii) SCL employs three persons on a full-time basis and, if these are required to give evidence in Adelaide, there would be major disruption to the business; (iv) there would be far greater costs incurred in respect of the conduct of a trial in Adelaide than in Brisbane in respect of flights, accommodation etc; (v) the respondents' documentation is located in Queensland.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Optics Online Pty Ltd v Sunland Group Ltd [2006] FCA 1389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1389.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Save for the issues arising from Mr Parker's and Mr Simmonds' professional practice, the matters relied upon by Mr Bratton in his affidavit opposing the transfer mirror in considerable degree those referred to by Mr Parker, save in one important respect. That exceptional matter, to which I earlier referred, is that Tidswell's investment was solicited by the respondent Mr Benson who sought out Mr Bratton in South Australia with the consequence that the causes of action advanced arose in that State. Of itself, this not only makes Tidswell's choice of the South Australian District Registry an appropriate one in which to file its proceedings, it also provides real reason for pause in too readily acceding to a request to transfer the proceedings to Brisbane particularly at this stage: cf Optics Online Pty Ltd v Sunland Group Ltd [2006] FCA 1389 at [8] - [9] .

12 Otherwise Mr Bratton relies upon (i) Adelaide being Tidswell's place of business; (ii) the four witnesses two lay (himself and the company's managing director) and two expert all reside in South Australia; (iii) for him and the managing director to go to Brisbane for two weeks would cause significant disruption to the day-to-day management of Tidswell's business; and (iv) Tidswell's documentation is all in Adelaide.

13 Bearing in mind that I need a sound or good reason for ordering that the proceeding be conducted in Brisbane, I do not consider that such has been made out at this stage of the proceeding particularly when one has regard to the fact that the proceeding itself was properly and appropriately instituted in South Australia.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>