<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Olivaylle Pty Limited v Flottweg GMBH &amp; Co KGAA (No 3) [2008] FCA 572 (4 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/572.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maguire v Leather [2007] QSC 164</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2007/164.html</AustLII>
<text>14 Atkins , of course, refers to, in its English origins, an English practice whereby it is traditionally the role of junior counsel to furnish an advice on evidence. In Australia, that certainly can be so but especially in more recent times, both solicitors themselves, as well as senior counsel, have an involvement in the furnishing of an advice on evidence. An example of the difficulties which can be encountered where an advice on evidence is not prepared is offered by Fryberg J in a Queensland case, Maguire v Leather , BC200705438, given on 13 July 2007, [2007] QSC 164 , see especially para 71.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Bassett v Host (1982) 1 NSWLR 206</tocase>
<text>15 In terms of general principle, it seems to me that an appropriate starting point is a decision given in the New South Wales Court of Appeal, Bassett v Host (1982) 1 NSWLR 206. That case was the subject of a subsequent appeal to the High Court, Host v Bassett (1983) 57 ALJR 681 , in which an appeal was dismissed. The passages from which I quote now from the judgments in the New South Wales Court of Appeal were not the subject of express reference in the High Court, but there is nothing in the High Court's judgment, which was confined to the more narrow issues that arose in that case, that calls into question the passages concerned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Host v Bassett (1983) 57 ALJR 681</tocase>
<text>15 In terms of general principle, it seems to me that an appropriate starting point is a decision given in the New South Wales Court of Appeal, Bassett v Host (1982) 1 NSWLR 206. That case was the subject of a subsequent appeal to the High Court, Host v Bassett (1983) 57 ALJR 681 , in which an appeal was dismissed. The passages from which I quote now from the judgments in the New South Wales Court of Appeal were not the subject of express reference in the High Court, but there is nothing in the High Court's judgment, which was confined to the more narrow issues that arose in that case, that calls into question the passages concerned.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Betts v Whittingslowe (1944) SASR 163</tocase>
<text>19 The circumstances in which witnesses can be called even after a party has closed its case are many and varied. Some singular examples show just how far the extent of the discretionary power to permit the calling of a witness after the closing of a case can reach. In that regard, note might usefully be taken of two South Australian cases. The first, Betts v Whittingslowe (No. 1) (1944) SASR 163 is a decision of then Chief Justice, Napier CJ. His Honour, at page 163, held that:
 Until the issues of fact and law have been finally determined by verdict or judgment, a trial judge has an inherent right to open a trial or to admit fresh evidence.

20 In the course of his judgment the Chief Justice, at page 163, did observe that:
 A trial should not be reopened merely to permit a party to fortify evidence adduced in the first instance by calling witnesses who might easily have been made available if due diligence had been shown.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jingellic Minerals NL v Beach Petroleum NL (1991) 55 SASR 424</tocase>
<text>21 More recently in time, Zelling J, then an acting justice of the South Australian Supreme Court, in Jingellic Minerals NL v Beach Petroleum NL (1991) 55 SASR 424 , also had occasion to consider the subject of the calling of a witness after the closing of a case. The circumstances there were rather singular in the sense that it became apparent that counsel in that case had not appreciated that a particular issue was material to the determination of the proceeding before the court. The application was made after the close of the case. His Honour held that a judge had power to reopen a case and to do so even in respect of a case where he had given judgment, but before orders had been sealed, if the interests of justice required such a course. His Honour counselled that such applications are to be kept in strict bounds. He added at page 425:
 Justice, however, is a protean concept and has moreover to be administered having regard to the rights and interests of both sides so that the application of the admitted jurisdiction to a given set of facts is not free of difficulty. There must be on the cases some specific cause which triggers the use of the remedial jurisdiction.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>State of Queensland v JL Holdings (1996/1997) [1997] HCA 1 ; 189 CLR 146</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/1.html</AustLII>
<text>22 More recently in time the High Court has had occasion in State of Queensland v JL Holdings (1996/1997) [1997] HCA 1 ; 189 CLR 146 to consider the place of case management systems in the obtaining of justice according to law. Their Honours cite two authorities which, in my opinion, have pertinence in the context of the present application. At page 152 their Honours cite with approval what they describe as a well known passage in the judgment of Bowen LJ in Cropper v Smith (1884) 26 Ch D 700 at 710, where his Lordship said:
 Now, I think it is a well established principle that the object of courts is to decide the rights of the parties and not to punish them for mistakes they make in the conduct of their cases by deciding otherwise than in accordance with their rights. Speaking for myself and in conformity with what I have heard laid down by the other division of the Court of Appeal and by myself as a member of it, I know of no kind of error or mistake which, if not fraudulent or intended to over reach, the court ought not to correct if it can be done without injustice to the other party. Courts do not exist for the sake of discipline but for the sake of deciding matters in controversy and I do not regard such amendment as a matter of favour or of grace.

24 Their Honours continue in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that they did not regard the passages that they cited from Sali v SPC as sanctioning any departure from Cropper v Smith and accepted in cases such as Clough and Rogers v Frog (1974) 48 ALJR 481. They continue, by way of observation, that:
 Sali v SPC was a case concerning the refusal of an adjournment in relation to which proper principles of case management have a particular relevance. 
And I considered they had just such relevance in refusing the application made by Olivaylle in December.

25 It is also observed by Dawson, Gaudron and McHugh JJ in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that:
 Case management is not an end in itself. It is an important and useful aid for ensuring the prompt and efficient disposal of litigation but it ought always to be borne in mind, even in changing times, that the ultimate aim of a court is the attainment of justice and no principle of case management can be allowed to supplant that aim. 
Those are observations reflect the views of an ultimate appellant court. Obviously enough, their application will differ in the context of particular cases and especially will differ in relation to an application of this nature, made in the course of a trial, in terms of whether prejudice will be occasioned to an opposing party. It must be said that in this court the reception of Queensland v JL Holdings has not been, with the very greatest of respect, an entirely subordinate one. In this regard and in the very particular context of the case before his Honour, in Black and Decker Australasia Pty Limited v GMCA Pty Limited [2007] FCA 1623 on 23 October 2007, Finkelstein J observed at para 3 that a state of affairs whereby case management directions were overlooked had as one of its chief causes what his Honour described as "the chilling effect" of the High Court's decision in Queensland v JL Holdings .

26 With the very greatest respect, I do not regard Queensland v JL Holdings as having a chilling effect. It seems to me that there is a need not to confuse the particular principle enunciated in JL Holdings with the outcome in particular cases. In terms of principle and in the context of this particular case, the most material consideration in my opinion is, is there prejudice and, if so, what is its nature and extent and having regard to that, what impact does that have on the discretion to permit the reception of some or all of the contents of Mr Lorenz's affidavit as evidence in the trial?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cropper v Smith (1884) 26 Ch D 700</tocase>
<text>22 More recently in time the High Court has had occasion in State of Queensland v JL Holdings (1996/1997) [1997] HCA 1 ; 189 CLR 146 to consider the place of case management systems in the obtaining of justice according to law. Their Honours cite two authorities which, in my opinion, have pertinence in the context of the present application. At page 152 their Honours cite with approval what they describe as a well known passage in the judgment of Bowen LJ in Cropper v Smith (1884) 26 Ch D 700 at 710, where his Lordship said:
 Now, I think it is a well established principle that the object of courts is to decide the rights of the parties and not to punish them for mistakes they make in the conduct of their cases by deciding otherwise than in accordance with their rights. Speaking for myself and in conformity with what I have heard laid down by the other division of the Court of Appeal and by myself as a member of it, I know of no kind of error or mistake which, if not fraudulent or intended to over reach, the court ought not to correct if it can be done without injustice to the other party. Courts do not exist for the sake of discipline but for the sake of deciding matters in controversy and I do not regard such amendment as a matter of favour or of grace.

24 Their Honours continue in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that they did not regard the passages that they cited from Sali v SPC as sanctioning any departure from Cropper v Smith and accepted in cases such as Clough and Rogers v Frog (1974) 48 ALJR 481. They continue, by way of observation, that:
 Sali v SPC was a case concerning the refusal of an adjournment in relation to which proper principles of case management have a particular relevance. 
And I considered they had just such relevance in refusing the application made by Olivaylle in December.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sali v SPC Limited (1993) 67 ALJR 841</tocase>
<text>23 Their Honours also cite at pages 153 and 154 a passage from an earlier High Court decision Sali v SPC Ltd (1993) 67 ALJR 841 at 849, where in that case Toohey and Gaudron JJ had observed:
 The contemporary approach to court administration has introduced another element into the equation or, more accurately, has put another consideration onto the scales. The view that the conduct of litigation is not merely a matter for the parties but is also one for the court and the need to avoid disruptions of the court's lists with the consequent inconvenience to the court and prejudice to the interests of other litigants waiting to be heard are pressing concerns to which a court may have regard.

24 Their Honours continue in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that they did not regard the passages that they cited from Sali v SPC as sanctioning any departure from Cropper v Smith and accepted in cases such as Clough and Rogers v Frog (1974) 48 ALJR 481. They continue, by way of observation, that:
 Sali v SPC was a case concerning the refusal of an adjournment in relation to which proper principles of case management have a particular relevance. 
And I considered they had just such relevance in refusing the application made by Olivaylle in December.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Clough and Rogers v Frog (1974) 48 ALJR 481</tocase>
<text>24 Their Honours continue in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that they did not regard the passages that they cited from Sali v SPC as sanctioning any departure from Cropper v Smith and accepted in cases such as Clough and Rogers v Frog (1974) 48 ALJR 481. They continue, by way of observation, that:
 Sali v SPC was a case concerning the refusal of an adjournment in relation to which proper principles of case management have a particular relevance. 
And I considered they had just such relevance in refusing the application made by Olivaylle in December.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Black and Decker Australasia Pty Limited v GMCA Pty Limited [2007] FCA 1623</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1623.html</AustLII>
<text>25 It is also observed by Dawson, Gaudron and McHugh JJ in Queensland v JL Holdings at page 154 that:
 Case management is not an end in itself. It is an important and useful aid for ensuring the prompt and efficient disposal of litigation but it ought always to be borne in mind, even in changing times, that the ultimate aim of a court is the attainment of justice and no principle of case management can be allowed to supplant that aim. 
Those are observations reflect the views of an ultimate appellant court. Obviously enough, their application will differ in the context of particular cases and especially will differ in relation to an application of this nature, made in the course of a trial, in terms of whether prejudice will be occasioned to an opposing party. It must be said that in this court the reception of Queensland v JL Holdings has not been, with the very greatest of respect, an entirely subordinate one. In this regard and in the very particular context of the case before his Honour, in Black and Decker Australasia Pty Limited v GMCA Pty Limited [2007] FCA 1623 on 23 October 2007, Finkelstein J observed at para 3 that a state of affairs whereby case management directions were overlooked had as one of its chief causes what his Honour described as "the chilling effect" of the High Court's decision in Queensland v JL Holdings .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Urban Transport Authority of New South Wales v Nweiser (1992) 28 NSWLR 471</tocase>
<text>27 Before departing from questions of principle I should also make reference to another decision of the New South Wales Court of Appeal, Urban Transport Authority of New South Wales v Nweiser (1992) 28 NSWLR 471 to which I was very helpfully referred by counsel. The leading judgment in the Court of Appeal in that case is that of Clarke J with whom Mahoney and Meagher JJ agreed. There are passages which appear at pages 475 and 476 which are pertinent to the discretion I have to exercise in this case. It suffices for present purposes if I note, by reference to what is an accurate summary of them in the head note, that a failure to lead evidence from a witness whom it is afterwards desired to call, even where such failure to due to a deliberate decision taken for tactical reasons, can not be a decisive ground for a court to refuse to exercise its discretion to grant an application by a party to re-open its case, albeit that is, an important factor.

28 Strictly speaking, the Respondent has not closed its case although, as I have mentioned, there were directions which required the identification of the Respondent's evidence in-chief by affidavit filed pre-trial, subject to a grant of leave.

29 In the context of this case, there is no doubt whatsoever that there is, to say the least, a degree of forensic embarrassment to Olivaylle in the application that is now made on behalf of Flottweg. It is quite apparent from the opening of the Applicant's case, as well as from passages in the cross examination of, especially, Dr Paterson, that aspects of the Applicant's case have been cast by reference to a predicated absence of Mr Lorenz from the witness box. "Predicated" in the sense that no affidavit from him was served by or on behalf of Flottweg until 2 April. Olivaylle also identifies and draws attention to the lateness of the application and the fact that Mr Lorenz's affidavit is not short, and it highlights and emphasises the prejudice I have mentioned.

30 Mr Lorenz's affidavit seems to me to have three broad subject areas:
 
(i) his in-house involvement in the issuing of quotes and the conduct of correspondence related thereto with Dr Paterson, including conversations by telephone with Dr Paterson; 
 
(ii) a visit which he made to Australia in September 2004 to meet Dr Paterson and Messrs Nieuwkerk, de Moya and Carey to discuss the project; and then a further visit that he made to Australia in May of 2006 which involved his attendance on 1 and 2 May at the Olivaylle site of operation. 
 
The latter involved his observation of the line. In his affidavit at para 40, he purports to give an opinion in respect of the performance of that line.

31 On behalf of Flottweg, attention is directed to the court's overriding obligation to achieve justice between both parties. The point is also developed that some of the forensic advantage may depend on the interpretation of a particular email authored by Mr Lorenz on 28 January 2004 which is page 196 in the exhibits to the affidavit of Mr de Moya, (which became document 26 on the court file).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>