<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 (10 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/5.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2035</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/2035.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The ACCC commenced these proceedings on 1 November 2006 alleging contraventions by various parties of s 45 of the Act and the Code. The alleged contraventions involved price fixing in the provision of educational consultancy services to overseas students of Korean origin. The proceedings were commenced against Kokos, Chad Kim, IAE, Young Gil Pae, Sang-Hong Jung and Rebekah Cabalt. Study Overseas Now Pty Ltd (Study Overseas Now) was joined as a respondent to the proceedings subsequently. On 17 August 2007 the ACCC was given leave to serve on Mr Seow Bing Yeo, a director of that company, a notice of motion seeking his joinder, such service to be effected out of the jurisdiction in Japan through a diplomatic channel. For the reasons set out in Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2035 , that latter requirement was dispensed with and an order for substituted service made.

5 The corporate respondents and Sang-Hong Jung are each said to have been in the business of providing educational consultancy services to students of Korean origin. The services allegedly involved providing information to students about courses in secondary and tertiary education institutions in Western Australia and arranging for their enrolment at institutions of their choice. The corporate respondents and Ms Jung are said to have been remunerated by commissions paid by the institutions.

6 The corporate respondents and Ms Jung are said to have made oral and written agreements in 2004 and 2005 under which they agreed not to offer or accept discounted tuition fees. Any party to the agreements that offered or agreed to accept a discounted tuition fee would be referred to a 'Council of Korean Agency' comprising representatives of each of the parties to the agreement. Such parties would be banned from enrolling students in the relevant institutions for a period of three months. It was alleged that copies of the written agreement were sent to a number of educational institutions. The ACCC alleged that the conduct of the corporate respondents and Ms Jung was in contravention of s 45 of the Act and of the Code. The other natural person respondents were said to have been involved in the contraventions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR 41-515</tocase>
<text>51 The ACCC set out in its submissions a non-exhaustive list of the principles and factors relevant to the determination of pecuniary penalties. They were: 
(a) The nature and extent of the contravening conduct.
(b) The amount of loss or damage caused. 
(c) The circumstances in which the conduct took place. 
(d) The size of the contravening company.
 
 (e) The degree of power it has, as evidenced by its market share and ease of entry into the market.
 (f) The deliberateness of the contravention and the period over which it extended. 
 (g) Whether the contravention arose out of the conduct of senior management or at a lower level. 
 (h) Whether the company has a corporate culture conducive to compliance with the Act as evidenced by educational programs and disciplinary or other corrective measures in response to an acknowledged contravention. 
 (i) Whether the company has shown a disposition to cooperate with the authorities responsible for the enforcement of the Act in relation to the contravention. 
 (j) Whether the respondents have engaged in similar conduct in the past.
 (k) The financial position of the respondents. 
 (l) The deterrent effect of the proposed penalty. 


The ACCC referred to Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR 41-515. Although there has been repeated discussion in later cases of the factors relevant to the quantum of pecuniary penalties, I am satisfied that the above list is sufficiently comprehensive. It is to be applied by reference to the general principle that the purpose of pecuniary penalties is to deter the contravenor and others from future contraventions of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (2007) ATPR 42-140</tocase>
<text>48 Save for the orders sought against Mr Chad Kim in relation to the alleged attempted contravention of the Code, the declaratory orders sought are within the power of the Court to make. There may be a question about their utility given that these reasons set out the findings of fact and the contraventions which underpin the injunctive relief which has been granted and the pecuniary penalties which are to be imposed. However, as Nicholson J pointed out in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (2007) ATPR 42-140 at [6] such declarations: 
 
 1. Are an appropriate vehicle to record the Court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (1993) 41 FCR 89 at 100; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Chen [2003] FCA 897 ; (2003) 132 FCR 309 at [36] .
 2. Serve to vindicate the ACCC's claim that the respondents contravened the Act: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Goldy Motors (2000) 23 ATPR 41-801 at [34].
 3. May be of assistance to the ACCC in the future in carrying out the duties conferred upon it by the Act: Goldy Motors 23 ATPR at [34].
 4. Are of assistance in clarifying the law: Goldy Motors 23 ATPR at [34]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Chaste Corporation Pty Ltd (in liq) [2005] FCA 1212 at [146] .
 5. May inform consumers of the dangers arising from a respondent's contravening conduct: Chen 132 FCR at [48]; and 
 6. May deter corporations from contravening the Act: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Midland Brick Co Pty Ltd (2004) 207 ALR 329 at [22]. 


In that case in considering the appropriateness of declaratory relief, Nicholson J observed that the declarations sought, by consent, were directed to the determination of legal controversies and not to answering abstract or hypothetical questions. The matters in issue had been identified, particularised and admitted by the respondents. The ACCC as a public body charged with enforcing the Act had a real interest in seeking the relief and the respondents were in the position of a proper contradictor in that they had a true interest in opposing the declarations sought. So much is true in this case.

49 In the circumstances of this case however, there is a question affecting the appropriateness of making the declarations sought at this time. There are other parties to these proceedings who are named in the declarations and against whom these proceedings are still pending. Although the declaratory orders are sought only against the first to fourth respondents, they involve formal declarations of the involvement of other respondents. True it is that the declarations are in personam as between the ACCC and the first to fourth respondents severally. They would not give rise to any issue estoppel against other parties any more than would the findings of fact based upon admissions made by the first to fourth respondents. Those findings of fact have been made only as against the first to fourth respondents.

50 In my opinion it is undesirable that the Court should, at this time, make formal declarations naming other respondents as parties to the contravening conduct. The question of declaratory relief will be stood over with liberty to the ACCC to apply for orders at an appropriate time in the terms sought. Apart from the declaration sought against Mr Chad Kim in relation to the alleged attempt to contravene the Code, the declaratory orders proposed are otherwise appropriate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076</tocase>
<text>51 The ACCC set out in its submissions a non-exhaustive list of the principles and factors relevant to the determination of pecuniary penalties. They were: 
(a) The nature and extent of the contravening conduct.
(b) The amount of loss or damage caused. 
(c) The circumstances in which the conduct took place. 
(d) The size of the contravening company.
 
 (e) The degree of power it has, as evidenced by its market share and ease of entry into the market.
 (f) The deliberateness of the contravention and the period over which it extended. 
 (g) Whether the contravention arose out of the conduct of senior management or at a lower level. 
 (h) Whether the company has a corporate culture conducive to compliance with the Act as evidenced by educational programs and disciplinary or other corrective measures in response to an acknowledged contravention. 
 (i) Whether the company has shown a disposition to cooperate with the authorities responsible for the enforcement of the Act in relation to the contravention. 
 (j) Whether the respondents have engaged in similar conduct in the past.
 (k) The financial position of the respondents. 
 (l) The deterrent effect of the proposed penalty. 


The ACCC referred to Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd (1996) ATPR 41-515. Although there has been repeated discussion in later cases of the factors relevant to the quantum of pecuniary penalties, I am satisfied that the above list is sufficiently comprehensive. It is to be applied by reference to the general principle that the purpose of pecuniary penalties is to deter the contravenor and others from future contraventions of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>