<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>ConnectEast Management Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 557 (29 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/557.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/26.html</AustLII>
<text>8 Nor does the language of the section suggest that, where there is more than one trust higher than the status-seeking trust, the higher trusts must be of the same level. The only requirement is that they be "of a higher level" than the status-seeking trust. For example, suppose trust A is on level (a). Since the section contemplates that there could be relevant trusts on as many as three levels higher, there could be a situation where trust B is on level (b), trust C is on level (c) and trust D is on level (d). Of each of trusts B, C and D it can be said that it is on a "higher" level than A's, that is to say on a level which has the quality or characteristic of being higher than (a).

9 At first blush, it may seem odd that the section provides that, where there is more than one trust, each must have fixed entitlements to all of the income and capital of the status-seeking trust. How can two or more each be entitled to all the income and capital?

10 The answer is to be found in the words "directly or indirectly". A fixed entitlement may be held indirectly where there is entitlement via interposed companies, partnerships or trusts: s 272-20. Thus, to take the example above, if trust B owns 100 percent of trust A and in turn trust C owns 100 per cent of trust B, and trust D owns 100 per cent of trust C, each of B, C and D has a fixed entitlement to all of the income and capital of A. In the case of B, it has its entitlement directly; each of C and D has its entitlement indirectly.

15 The ordinary and grammatical meaning of the section is as submitted by the Commissioner. The result could not be said to be arbitrary or capricious. To confer the benefit of the higher status only where the status-seeking subsidiary is wholly owned by the trust of that higher status is a rational legislative objective. That objective has been achieved in the language of the statute, which admits of only one meaning. The merits or otherwise of the objective are not a matter for the Court: Cooper Brookes (Wollongong) Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1981] HCA 26 ; (1981) 147 CLR 297 at 304-305.

16 The appeal will be dismissed with costs, including reserved costs.

 I certify that the preceding sixteen (16) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 29 April 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: T F Bathurst QC and S H P Steward 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: P J Hanks QC and S Sharpley 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 21 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 29 April 2008 


 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/557.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>