<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Riley v Repatriation Commission [2008] FCA 531 (21 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/531.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/51.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Where a claim relates to operational service, as the applicant's claim did, the standard of proof to be applied to the question whether an injury or disease is war-caused is prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) of the Act. Those provisions are applied in the manner explained by the High Court in Byrnes v Repatriation Commission [1993] HCA 51 ; (1993) 177 CLR 564 at 571 and may be summarised as follows:
 
(1) The threshold question is posed by subs 120(3) namely, whether the whole of the material before the decision-maker raises a reasonable hypothesis connecting the veteran's injury or disease with the circumstances of his service. The question whether the material raises a reasonable hypothesis of that kind does not involve the finding of any facts relating to the veteran's service or relating to any connection between that service and the relevant injury or disease.
 
(2) If the material does raise such a reasonable hypothesis, the decision-maker proceeds to the question posed by subs 120(1) namely, is the decision-maker satisfied beyond reasonable doubt that the facts required to connect the veteran's injury or disease with his service were not present or were displaced by other facts. It is only at this stage that the Tribunal finds any facts.

12 Subsection 120(3) 'is affected by s 120A'; and, according to subs 120A(1), s 120A applies to a claim under Part II of the Act made on or after 1 June 1994 that relates to operational service rendered by a veteran. The applicant's claim was such a claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/83.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal focuses on the alleged failure of the Tribunal to approach the question whether the applicant's CP was war-caused in the manner prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) and 120A(3) of the Veterans' Entitlements Act 1986 (Cth) ('the Act'), as explained in the authorities, including Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750 ; Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353 ; Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; and Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83. In particular, the applicant contends that the Tribunal erred in law by:
 
(1) Treating clinical onset of CP as requiring the contemporaneous diagnosis of CP ground 4(i);
 
(2) impermissible fact-finding at the reasonable hypothesis stage that one of the elements required to raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting CP with the applicant's war service (clinical onset of CP within six months of direct trauma to the patella) did not occur within the prescribed time ground 4(ii); and
 
(3) rejecting the alternative hypothesis (of inability to obtain appropriate clinical management in Vietnam for pre-existing CP) on the basis of impermissible fact-finding that the applicant's CP did not have its clinical onset until after his operational service grounds 4(iii) and 4(iv).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/398.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal focuses on the alleged failure of the Tribunal to approach the question whether the applicant's CP was war-caused in the manner prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) and 120A(3) of the Veterans' Entitlements Act 1986 (Cth) ('the Act'), as explained in the authorities, including Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750 ; Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353 ; Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; and Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83. In particular, the applicant contends that the Tribunal erred in law by:
 
(1) Treating clinical onset of CP as requiring the contemporaneous diagnosis of CP ground 4(i);
 
(2) impermissible fact-finding at the reasonable hypothesis stage that one of the elements required to raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting CP with the applicant's war service (clinical onset of CP within six months of direct trauma to the patella) did not occur within the prescribed time ground 4(ii); and
 
(3) rejecting the alternative hypothesis (of inability to obtain appropriate clinical management in Vietnam for pre-existing CP) on the basis of impermissible fact-finding that the applicant's CP did not have its clinical onset until after his operational service grounds 4(iii) and 4(iv).

33 The Tribunal then referred to the meaning of 'clinical onset' considered by the Full Court in Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 , referring to the analysis of the Tribunal in Re Robertson v Repatriation Commission (1998) 50 ALD 668 , in which Senior Member Dwyer concluded at 670 that:
 '... there is a clinical onset of a disease, either when a person becomes aware of some feature or symptom which enables a doctor to say the disease was present at that time, or when a finding is made on investigation which is indicative to a doctor of the disease being present at that time.' 
and noted this analysis was specifically endorsed by Branson J in Cornelius at [26].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353</tocase>
<text>3 The appeal focuses on the alleged failure of the Tribunal to approach the question whether the applicant's CP was war-caused in the manner prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) and 120A(3) of the Veterans' Entitlements Act 1986 (Cth) ('the Act'), as explained in the authorities, including Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750 ; Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353 ; Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; and Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83. In particular, the applicant contends that the Tribunal erred in law by:
 
(1) Treating clinical onset of CP as requiring the contemporaneous diagnosis of CP ground 4(i);
 
(2) impermissible fact-finding at the reasonable hypothesis stage that one of the elements required to raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting CP with the applicant's war service (clinical onset of CP within six months of direct trauma to the patella) did not occur within the prescribed time ground 4(ii); and
 
(3) rejecting the alternative hypothesis (of inability to obtain appropriate clinical management in Vietnam for pre-existing CP) on the basis of impermissible fact-finding that the applicant's CP did not have its clinical onset until after his operational service grounds 4(iii) and 4(iv).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Robertson v Repatriation Commission (1998) 50 ALD 668</tocase>
<text>33 The Tribunal then referred to the meaning of 'clinical onset' considered by the Full Court in Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 , referring to the analysis of the Tribunal in Re Robertson v Repatriation Commission (1998) 50 ALD 668 , in which Senior Member Dwyer concluded at 670 that:
 '... there is a clinical onset of a disease, either when a person becomes aware of some feature or symptom which enables a doctor to say the disease was present at that time, or when a finding is made on investigation which is indicative to a doctor of the disease being present at that time.' 
and noted this analysis was specifically endorsed by Branson J in Cornelius at [26].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/750.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal focuses on the alleged failure of the Tribunal to approach the question whether the applicant's CP was war-caused in the manner prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) and 120A(3) of the Veterans' Entitlements Act 1986 (Cth) ('the Act'), as explained in the authorities, including Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750 ; Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353 ; Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; and Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83. In particular, the applicant contends that the Tribunal erred in law by:
 
(1) Treating clinical onset of CP as requiring the contemporaneous diagnosis of CP ground 4(i);
 
(2) impermissible fact-finding at the reasonable hypothesis stage that one of the elements required to raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting CP with the applicant's war service (clinical onset of CP within six months of direct trauma to the patella) did not occur within the prescribed time ground 4(ii); and
 
(3) rejecting the alternative hypothesis (of inability to obtain appropriate clinical management in Vietnam for pre-existing CP) on the basis of impermissible fact-finding that the applicant's CP did not have its clinical onset until after his operational service grounds 4(iii) and 4(iv).

33 The Tribunal then referred to the meaning of 'clinical onset' considered by the Full Court in Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 , referring to the analysis of the Tribunal in Re Robertson v Repatriation Commission (1998) 50 ALD 668 , in which Senior Member Dwyer concluded at 670 that:
 '... there is a clinical onset of a disease, either when a person becomes aware of some feature or symptom which enables a doctor to say the disease was present at that time, or when a finding is made on investigation which is indicative to a doctor of the disease being present at that time.' 
and noted this analysis was specifically endorsed by Branson J in Cornelius at [26].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/391.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appeal focuses on the alleged failure of the Tribunal to approach the question whether the applicant's CP was war-caused in the manner prescribed by subss 120(1) and (3) and 120A(3) of the Veterans' Entitlements Act 1986 (Cth) ('the Act'), as explained in the authorities, including Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750 ; Meehan v Repatriation Commission (2002) 35 AAR 353 ; Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; and Hardman v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCAFC 83. In particular, the applicant contends that the Tribunal erred in law by:
 
(1) Treating clinical onset of CP as requiring the contemporaneous diagnosis of CP ground 4(i);
 
(2) impermissible fact-finding at the reasonable hypothesis stage that one of the elements required to raise a reasonable hypothesis connecting CP with the applicant's war service (clinical onset of CP within six months of direct trauma to the patella) did not occur within the prescribed time ground 4(ii); and
 
(3) rejecting the alternative hypothesis (of inability to obtain appropriate clinical management in Vietnam for pre-existing CP) on the basis of impermissible fact-finding that the applicant's CP did not have its clinical onset until after his operational service grounds 4(iii) and 4(iv).

13 Subsection 120A(3) of the Act relevantly provides that a hypothesis connecting a person's injury or disease with the circumstances of any particular service rendered by the person is reasonable only if there is in force a Statement of Principles that upholds the hypothesis. That is, the hypothesis raised by the material will only be reasonable if the hypothesis is consistent with, or fits the template of, the Statement of Principles: see Deledio at 96, endorsing the observations of Heerey J at first instance in Deledio v Repatriation Commission (1997) 47 ALD 261 at 275.

14 The method by which subss 120(1), 120(3) and 120A(3) are applied was explained in Deledio at 97 98, to which the Tribunal referred at [33] [35]. The threshold question remains whether the material before the decision-maker points to an hypothesis of connection between (in the case of a claim in respect of a veteran's injury or disease) the injury or disease and the particular circumstances of the veteran's service. Subsection 120A(3) adds the additional requirement that the hypothesis must be upheld by the SoP made under subs 196B(2) of the Act for the kind of injury suffered or disease contracted by the veteran.

26 Consistent with the first step in Deledio at 97, the Tribunal considered all the material before it and found at [33] of its reasons that that material '... raises a reasonable hypothesis connecting Mr Riley's CP with his war service within the meaning of subs 120(3) of the Act'.

27 The Tribunal then proceeded to the second Deledio step and found at [34] that there is an SoP in force in respect of the relevant injury, which it identified as Instrument No. 33 of 2001.

28 The Tribunal then turned to the third Deledio step in 'determining whether the relevant hypothesis complies with one or more of the factors referred to in the relevant SoP'. The Tribunal at [35] said:
 'This step involves considering all of the material before me, but without making any findings of fact at this stage of the process. If the evidence taken as a whole does not fit within the relevant SoP factors, then any hypothesis would not be reasonable: section 120A(3). The claim would therefore not be successful.'

29 The Tribunal then proceeded to 'determine' when the clinical onset (or clinical worsening) of the condition occurred because, in its words '... in respect of all of the relevant factors with the exception of factor 5(h) it is essential ...' (at [36]).

30 At [37] the Tribunal reasoned that because the precise dates of the incidents in Vietnam are unclear, the most generous interpretation of the date of the incidents, being the date the applicant ceased operational service in May 1967, the clinical onset (or worsening) would need to have occurred by November 1967.

44 The applicant's complaint appears to be with the Tribunal's use of the expression 'determine' in [36] of its reasons. He suggests that the expression 'determine' means that the Tribunal embarked on impermissible fact-finding. I do not agree. I agree with the Commission's short answer, that the Tribunal was simply acknowledging that, in terms of the third step in Deledio , it was required to 'form an opinion' and that the expression 'determine', in the context of the Tribunal's understanding that its task was not to find facts (at [35]), meant no more than forming an opinion.

45 The Tribunal, at [45] (second) and [46] (second) of its reasons, was doing no more than setting out the process by which it formed the opinion that the hypotheses were not reasonable by reference to factors 5(a), 5(b) and 5(e) of the SoP. It was not, despite the use of the word 'find' in [46] (second), involved in an exercise in fact-finding, specifically, as to the time when the applicant experienced clinical onset of his CP, outside the process of forming that opinion.

46 Nor was the Tribunal involved in resolving possible conflicts in the evidence because there were none. The Tribunal's non-acceptance of the evidence of Dr Giblin referred to at [45] (second) of its reasons was not by way of preferring the evidence of another practitioner; rather, it was by reference to the accepted definition of clinical onset referred to in [33] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/192.html</AustLII>
<text>15 In Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 , a Full Court (Black CJ, Drummond and Kenny JJ) said that the function of the Statement of Principles is to prescribe the essential content of what is a reasonable hypothesis, for subs 120(3) purposes, capable of connecting the particular kind of injury, disease or death with the circumstances of the veteran's particular service. In order to satisfy subss 120(3) and 120A(3) of the Act, an hypothesis relied on by a dependent of a veteran to support a pension claim must be supported by material pointing to each element that the Statement of Principles makes essential for the hypothesis to be reasonable. The Court said at [57] [58]:
 'Whatever the situation may have been in relation to claims before 1 June 1994, the effect of s 120A(3) (where there is an SoP under s 196B(2)) is that a hypothesis is reasonable only if it is upheld by the SoP. Pursuant to s 196B(2), the SoP must set out "the factors that must as a minimum exist" and "which of those factors must be related to service". The result is that, where it applies, the SoP prescribes the essential content of what is a reasonable hypothesis, for s 120(3) purposes, capable of connecting the particular kind of injury, diseases or death with the circumstances of a veteran's particular service. In order to satisfy ss 120(3) and 120A(3), a hypothesis relied on by a veteran to support a pension claim must be supported by material pointing to each element that the SoP makes essential for the hypothesis to be reasonable. In order for Mr Hill to succeed, the hypothesis raised by the material before the Tribunal had to fit the template set out in the PTSD SoP. ...' (Emphasis added)

16 At the time of the decision and of the Tribunal's decision, there was in force a Statement of Principles concerning CP, No. 33 of 2001 ('the SoP'). Clause 4 of the SoP provides that one of the factors set out in cl 5 of the SoP must be related to any relevant service rendered by the person.

17 The applicant relied on factors 5(a), (b) and (h) in the SoP (presumably for both knees):
 '(5)(a) "suffering direct trauma to the patella of the affected knee within the six months immediately before the clinical onset of chondromalacia patellae;" (5)(b) "suffering an injury to the affected knee resulting in meniscal damage or permanent ligamentous instability within the six months immediately before the clinical onset of chondromalacia patella ..." (5)(h) "inability to obtain appropriate clinical management for chondromalacia patellae."' 
In the alternative, the applicant relied on factor 5(e) in relation to his right knee:
 '(5)(e) "suffering direct trauma to the patella of the affected knee within the six months immediately before the clinical worsening of chondromalacia patellae ..."'</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>