<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIBR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 502 (21 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/502.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Abebe v The Comonwealth [2004] HCA 32 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/32.html</AustLII>
<text>35 The first respondent further submits that any weight to be given by the Tribunal to evidence was a matter for the Tribunal: Abebe v The Comonwealth [2004] HCA 32 ; (1999) 197 CLR 510 at [197] .

36 Finally, the first respondent submits that there was no error in the way in which the Federal Magistrate dealt with the issue of s 425 and that the appellant was properly on notice of the issue in relation to the tenant generally.

37 The first respondent's contention that the grounds of appeal raise matters not raised before the Federal Magistrate must be accepted. The sole issue before the Federal Magistrate was whether there had been compliance with s 425 by the Tribunal putting to the appellant conflicting statements in the Amnesty International Report. The Federal Magistrate ruled against the appellant on that sole ground. The appellant has not made that ruling the subject matter of this appeal.

44 Insofar as it is submitted that the Tribunal was in error in determining the absence of fear on the part of the appellant, that was a matter for the Tribunal and not for this Court. The weight that the Tribunal put upon the evidence for the purpose of determining that issue was also for the Tribunal and not for this Court: Abebe [2004] HCA 32 ; 197 CLR 510.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>45 The second ground seems to be a complaint going peculiarly to the merits or to the weight which the Tribunal put upon the evidence which gave rise to the Tribunal's ultimate decision, disguised as it were as a complaint of bias. Insofar as it is a complaint about the merits, that is not a matter for this Court: Attorney-General v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35-36; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham (2000) 168 ALR 407 at [67]. Insofar as it is a complaint of apprehended bias or bias, there is simply no evidence to support a claim of prejudgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/28.html</AustLII>
<text>38 A party is not entitled to raise new grounds which were deliberately or by inadvertence not put to the Court from which the appeal is brought: Metwally v University of Wollongong [1985] HCA 28 ; (1985) 60 ALR 68 at 71.

39 If the appellant were entitled to raise these new grounds, it would mean that this Court would have to sit, as it were, as the Court at first instance to determine whether these new grounds would give rise to the relief sought in the application before the Federal Magistrate. Parliament has given the responsibility for hearing these applications exclusively to the Federal Magistrates Court. The parties, whether they are represented or unrepresented, ought to articulate all of their complaints in relation to the Tribunal's reasons in the Federal Magistrates Court so that that Court can make the appropriate findings and reach a considered decision on all aspects of the Tribunal's decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham (2000) 168 ALR 407</tocase>
<text>45 The second ground seems to be a complaint going peculiarly to the merits or to the weight which the Tribunal put upon the evidence which gave rise to the Tribunal's ultimate decision, disguised as it were as a complaint of bias. Insofar as it is a complaint about the merits, that is not a matter for this Court: Attorney-General v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35-36; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Durairajasingham (2000) 168 ALR 407 at [67]. Insofar as it is a complaint of apprehended bias or bias, there is simply no evidence to support a claim of prejudgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZKMS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/499.html</AustLII>
<text>40 To allow the appellant to articulate these grounds on appeal would be to allow the appellant to treat this Court as a Court at first instance. Such a course of action is unsatisfactory, not only for this Court but also for the High Court which would hear any application for special leave from this decision. It would put the High Court, as it were, in a position of hearing applications for special leave from a court of first instance: SZKMS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 499.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VUAX v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/158.html</AustLII>
<text>41 However, authority seems to suggest that I need to consider whether the grounds have merit before I determine whether I should give leave for the appellant to raise the matters: VUAX v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 158.

42 The Tribunal considered the question of a well-founded fear of persecution conventionally. The Tribunal said:
 
 Fourth, an applicant's fear of persecution for a Convention reason must be a "well-founded" fear. This adds an objective requirement to the requirement that an applicant must in fact hold such a fear. A person has a "well-founded fear" of persecution under the Convention if they have genuine fear founded upon a "real chance" of persecution for a Convention stipulated reason. A fear is well-founded where there is a real substantial basis for it but not if it is merely assumed or based on mere speculation. A "real chance" is one that is not remote or insubstantial or a far-fetched possibility. A person can have a well-founded fear of persecution even though the possibility of the persecution occurring is well below 50 per cent.

43 The Tribunal stated the correct test which it applied to the facts. It found that the appellant did not have a genuine fear of persecution. That being the case, the appellant could not satisfy the test of well-founded fear of persecution as determined by the authorities.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>