<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Alphapharm Pty Ltd v H Lundbeck A/S (includes corrigendum dated 27 June 2008) [2008] FCA 559 (24 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/559.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1937/63.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Advanced Building Systems Pty Ltd v Ramset Fasteners (Aust) Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 19 ; (1998) 194 CLR 171</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/19.html</AustLII>
<text>In determining whether what is claimed fits the description of a "manner of manufacture", one must confine one's attention to the face of the specification: Philips v Mirabella at 663-664; Advanced Building Systems Pty Ltd v Ramset Fasteners (Aust) Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 19 ; (1998) 194 CLR 171 (Ramset) at [38] ; CCOM Pty Ltd v Jiejing Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1168 ; (1994) 51 FCR 260 ( CCOM v Jiejing ) at 291). The notion of a manner of manufacture does not incorporate considerations of novelty or inventiveness which are dealt with independently and comprehensively in s 18(1)(b), s 7, and the definitions of "prior art base" and "prior art information" in Sch 1: see Ramset at [30]-[34] (dealing with s 100 of the 1952 Act).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Aktiebolaget H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 59 ; (2002) 212 CLR 411</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/59.html</AustLII>
<text>The effect of these provisions is that the Patent can be revoked under the Act only on a ground of invalidity that would have been available under the 1952 Act. In any case where a relevant ground of invalidity under the 1952 Act is narrower than the corresponding ground under the Act, the patentee has the benefit of the narrower ground and is not to be worse off than if the 1952 Act had continued to operate: NV Philips Gloeilampenfabrieken v Mirabella International Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 404 ; (1993) 44 FCR 239 at 250 ff per Lockhart J, with whom Northrop J agreed and with whom Burchett J agreed on this point; ICI Chemicals &amp; Polymers Ltd v Lubrizol Corporation Inc (2000) 106 FCR 214 ( Lubrizol ) at [22] [24]; Aktiebolaget H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 1303 ; (2000) 51 IPR 375 at [8] [10]. Professors Banwell and Davies

In Minnesota v Beiersdorf at 292-295 and in Aktiebolaget H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 59 ; (2002) 212 CLR 411 ( Astra ) at [57] it was held in relation to s 100(1)(e) of the 1952 Act that publications are not to be taken into account unless their content was part of common general knowledge at the priority date. Accordingly, the issue is not whether it was obvious to conduct a literature search of a particular kind with a view to acquiring information, but whether the information that would have been obtained from the search had already entered the body of common general knowledge: Minnesota v Beiersdorf at 295; Astra at [45]. No question arises in this case regarding the results of a routine literature search.

Alphapharm submits: 
 
 415. ... Professor Montgomery articulates a series of opinions regarding the efficacy of citalopram vs (+) citalopram on the basis of his interpretation of reports or articles, which in turn report the results of certain clinical studies (most of which were conducted by or on behalf of Lundbeck). 
 

 
 
 416. No person has given evidence regarding the conduct of those studies, the underlying data concerning the studies has not been provided and there has been no disclosure of primary documents that might reveal (for instance) the aims, objectives or methodology of those studies. The authors of the Journal Articles relied upon have not given evidence. As submitted above, Alphapharm was able to call the pooled studies seriously into question, on the basis of limited material. 
 

 
 
 417. The Journal Articles themselves constitute reports of selected information taken from and summarized as the results from clinical studies. Further, there is no evidence as to the existence of other unpublished studies the results of which may be unhelpful to the Lundbeck arguments. Professor Montgomery does not refer to the underlying data, but relies on the results as reported in the Articles. 
 

 
 
 418. The Journal Articles themselves are at times opaque as to the studies upon which their conclusions are based ... Further, not all of the studies upon which the Montgomery expert evidence is based were published. 
 

 
 
 419. Accordingly, the basis upon which Professor Montgomery has expressed his opinions is hearsay evidence which cannot be admitted as evidence of the truth of its contents. 
 

 
 
 420. Alphapharm submits that, in the absence of proof of that factual basis, the evidence of Professor Montgomery in this regard is inadmissible.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Angiotech Pharmaceuticals v Conor [2007] EWCA Civ 5 ; [2007] RPC 20</tocase>
<text>I am aware of the observations made by the English Court of Appeal in relation to the High Court's judgment in Astra in Angiotech Pharmaceuticals v Conor [2007] EWCA Civ 5 ; [2007] RPC 20 at [39] [45] which were quoted by Kitchin J in Generics v Lundbeck at [73]. Those observations are of no relevance to my task.

Astra also stands as authority for the following propositions:

While the evidence that was before Kitchin J in Generics v Lundbeck was clearly different from that which was before me, I assume that the evidence of the course of experimentation that was followed at Lundbeck was similar. In any event, his Lordship's summary (at [154]) accords with my findings on the evidence in the present case: 
 
 Assuming the skilled person decided to embark upon the task of trying to obtain the individual enantiomers there was no real dispute between the parties that he would initially choose to attempt to resolve the final molecules. Only if this failed might he then consider alternative methods such as using enantiomerically pure precursors. But here his anxiety would be that subsequent reaction steps might result in the production of an enantiomerically impure final product. As I shall explain, scientists at Lundbeck attempted to resolve citalopram by classical resolution techniques using diastereoisomers, by using new resolving agents, by attempting to resolve derivatives and by using techniques of asymmetric synthesis, all over the period 1980 to 1988. In addition, they attempted to resolve citalopram using analytical chiral HPLC from 1983 to 1987. None of these techniques were successful. The claimants accepted that citalopram is not easily resolved by making diastereoisomers. However, they submitted the skilled addressee would not regard failure in relation to this molecule as the end of road. I accept that this was so. But the work Lundbeck undertook illustrates that the road to which the claimants referred was long and uncertain. 
 

 The Product Claims

The word "routine" that has become a common feature in formulations of the obviousness test in Australia (see [180] above) is more comfortably applicable to discussions of methods than products. However, the "matter of routine" test can be applied to product claims. The question to be asked is whether it would have been a matter of routine for those skilled in the art to adopt the goal of obtaining the enantiomers of citalopram for use of one of them as a drug for the treatment of depression.

In Astra , the High Court described (at [53]) the reformulation of the "Cripps question" by Graham J in Olin at 187-188. Their Honours stated that that approach should be accepted. Adapting that test to the circumstances of the present product claims, I would state the test as follows: 
 
 Would the hypothetical addressee or team as at 14 June 1988, equipped with the Australian Citalopram Patent and possessed of the common general knowledge within the field at that time, adopt as a matter of routine the aim of obtaining the (+)-enantiomer of citalopram in the expectation that it might well produce a useful alternative to, or a better drug than, citalopram? 
 

 
While I think that the hypothetical addressee or team in 1988 would have recognised the possibility of an advantage in obtaining the enantiomers because of the possibility of the therapeutic benefits of the racemate being found to reside in one of them, I do not think that the goal of obtaining the enantiomers would have been adopted as a matter of routine, as is required for the Australian test of obviousness to be satisfied.
 The Joint Report

Again, a convenient starting point is the Joint Report.

Professors Banwell and Davies were asked: "What were the motivations (chemically and academically, but excluding regulatory) for obtaining the enantiomers of a known racemate?"</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler (1997) 39 IPR 29</tocase>
<text>Alphapharm submits that it is no more permissible to read in the word "pure" than it was to read the qualifier "drainage" into the claims in the patent specification in Atlantis Corporation Pty Ltd v Schindler (1997) 39 IPR 29 ( Atlantis ). The invention in that case was entitled in the complete specification "Drainage Cell" and was stated to relate to "the provision of adequate drainage by artificial means" and to have particular application in the area of landscape gardening". However, the claims simply described a rigid cell structure.

A Full Court of this Court held that the claims were unambiguous and were simply in respect of the rigid structure without any limitation by reference to the purpose of "drainage".

In my view, the facts in Atlantis are distinguishable. There was no question in Atlantis of whether the object was claimed an object in its own right. Quite apart from: the expert evidence that, where no purity is specified in relation to a compound, chemists read in a 95% purity criterion; and the references to "individual", "pure", separated" and "isolated" elsewhere in the Patent, 
I would have understood an unqualified reference to (+)-citalopram, whether in the open literature or in a patent, to refer to that compound when other than merely part of the unresolved racemate.

Alphapharm draws attention to the fact that both Professors Banwell and Davies said that from the formula for the racemic mixture (citalopram) they could deduce the formulae for the (+)-enantiomer and the (-)-enantiomer. I do not think this fact to be persuasive as to how claim 1 is properly to be construed.

Alphapharm draws attention to the Patent's title as it existed prior to amendment and to the terms of overseas Escitalopram Patents.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Beecham Group Ltd v Bristol Laboratories Ltd (1977) 1B IPR 665</tocase>
<text>In Beecham Group Ltd v Bristol Laboratories Ltd (1977) 1B IPR 665 ( Beecham) , the plaintiff alleged infringement of patents for a pharmaceutical compound by the importation, offering for sale and sale in the United Kingdom of the antibiotic, Hetacillin. The plaintiff held four patents relating to a new class of semi-synthetic penicillins and to methods for their manufacture. One such penicillin was Ampicillin, a valuable antibiotic. The clinical effectiveness of Hetacillin was due entirely to Ampicillin, of which it was an acetone derivative. In the presence of water, as and when administered as an antibiotic, Hetacillin would revert into Ampicillin by a reversible chemical reaction.

The Lundbecks rely on a passage from the speech of Lord Diplock, the whole of the paragraph being as follows (p 710): 
 
 I have already expressed my opinion that the pith and marrow doctrine is applicable to claims for new products as well as to new processes; and I agree with the Court of Appeal that the relationship of hetacillin to ampicillin provides a clear case for its application. It was argued that what is claimed in the patents as an essential feature of the class of products to which ampicillin belongs is the presence of an amino group in the alpha position, and that this feature is absent in hetacillin. This is literally true at the time of importation and sale but it ceases to be true as soon as hetacillin is put to use for the only purpose for which it is intended. The substitution for the postulated amino group of the variant incorporated in hetacillin is evanescent and reversible and for all practical purposes of use can be regarded as the equivalent of the amino group in ampicillin. In the apt phrase used by the Court of Appeal, it is the reproduction of the substance ampicillin, albeit temporarily masked. 
 

His Lordship was addressing a product claim. In the imported hetacillin, there was a substituent for the amino group in the alpha position, but the substitution of the variant was "evanescent and reversible" and could be regarded as the equivalent of the amino group in the alpha position in the patented drug ampicillin.

The Lundbecks draw an analogy with the bromo-diol's performance of the function of the cyano-diol.

Wootten J was of the view (at 532) that a proper and convenient way to test the matter was to ask whether the sale of monensin sodium in Australia by another person would be an infringement of the patent. After referring to Beecham , his Honour held (at 534) that "the mere conversion of monensic acid to monensin sodium with the retention of substantially the same molecular structure and the same therapeutic effects, and involving only the use of a simple and well understood process, would fall within the 'pith and marrow' doctrine".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH v Commissioner of Patents [2001] FCA 647 ; (2001) 112 FCR 595</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/647.html</AustLII>
<text>Lundbeck refers to three authorities as being relevant to the construction of the expression "pharmaceutical substance per se ": Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH v Commissioner of Patents [2001] FCA 647 ; (2001) 112 FCR 595 ( Boehringer ); Prejay Holdings Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2003] FCAFC 77 ; (2003) 57 IPR 424 ( Prejay ); and Pharmacia Italia SpA v Mayne Pharma Pty Ltd (2006) 69 IPR 1 ( Pharmacia ).

Boehringer is not entirely on point. The patent claims were for a container comprising an aerosol or spray composition for nasal administration. The composition comprised as its active ingredient a certain pharmaceutical substance. The primary Judge, Heerey J, held that s 70(2)(a) was not satisfied because the pharmaceutical substance itself ( per se ) was not disclosed in the complete specification and did not fall within the scope of a claim of the patent specification ( Boehringer Ingelheim International v Commissioner of Patents (2001) AIPC 91-670). His Honour examined the legislative history behind ss 70 79 and concluded that patents for new and inventive processes or new and inventive modes of treatment of old or known products are not the subject of s 70: it is only patents for new and inventive products that are. Accordingly, the expression per se showed that an extension of term is to be available only where the claim is for a pharmaceutical substance as such, not a substance forming part of a method or process.

The Full Court in Boehringer agreed (at [37]). Their Honours noted (at [39]) that the Second Reading Speech relating to the Intellectual Property Laws Amendment Bill 1997 (Cth), which inserted the relevant sections into the Act, spoke of "development of a new drug" and of the research and testing required before a "product" could enter the market. Their Honours also noted (at [40]) that the Explanatory Memorandum relating to that Bill spoke of the expression "pharmaceutical substance per se " as being usually restricted to "new and inventive substances". They considered that the expression "fall within the scope of the claim or claims of that specification" in s 70(2)(a) means "[b]e included amongst the things claimed " (at [42]).

The decision in Boehringer does not govern the present case because claims 1 to 5 are indisputably product claims, and the pharmaceutical substance per se in question is indisputably the (+)-enantiomer of citalopram.

In my view, Lundbeck seeks to draw more from the expression " per se " than was necessary in Boehringer . In Boehringer , the Court was concerned only to distinguish between a pharmaceutical substance that is the subject of a product claim (which they held to be within s 70(2)(a)) and a substance that forms part of a method or process claim (which they held not to be within s 70(2)(a)). The Court was not concerned, as I am, with a competition between two arguable "first regulatory approval dates" and with the question whether the substance the subject of a product claim in a later patent was contained in goods previously included in the ARTG.

In Prejay a Full Court of this Court followed Boehringer . All of the claims were method claims, not product claims. The Commissioner's delegate refused an application for an extension. The Full Court agreed with the delegate that a substance that is mentioned in the context of a method claim does not meet the requirement of s 70(2)(a) that the substance per se fall within the scope of a claim (at [23] [24] per Wilcox and Cooper JJ, [28] per Allsop J).

In Pharmacia , Weinberg J accepted the distinction drawn in Boehringer , but held (at [99]) that claim 1 of the patent before him did state "a claim to a new and inventive substance, and not to a novel process or method". Weinberg J was also not concerned with rival first regulatory approval dates or with the associated questions that are before me.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Borowski v Quayle [1966] VR 382</tocase>
<text>The starting point for resolution of Alphapharm's General Relevance Objection is a particular group of exceptions to the hearsay rule that were recognised under the general law as being dictated by necessity. In the Law Reform Commission's Interim Report on Evidence (ALRC No 26, 1985), the Commission described these exceptions as (a) the expert's accumulated knowledge, (b) the reported data of fellow scientists, and (c) information commonly relied upon in an industry, trade or calling (ALRC No 26 vol 1 at [131], vol 2 at [91]). The Commission cited in support: English Exporters (London) Ltd v Eldonwall Ltd [1973] 1 Ch 415 ; R v Abadom [1983] 1 WLR 126 ; Borowski v Quayle [1966] VR 382 ( Borowski ); H v Schering Chemicals Ltd [1983] 1 All ER 849 ( Schering Chemicals ); Reid v Kerr [1974] 9 SASR 367 ; Rowley v London and North Western Railway Co [1852] EngR 1037 ; (1873) LR 8 Exch 221 ; Dickins v Randerson [1901] 1 KB 437 ; R v Perryman (1907) 147 CCC Sess Pap 109 (Lawrence J). There is some overlap between the three categories.

The Commission referred, as an illustration of (b), to Borowski , in which the following passage from Wigmore on Evidence, Chadbourn JH (ed) (Little, Brown &amp; Co, Boston, 1979) vol 2 at [665b], was cited with approval: 
 
 The data of every science are enormous in scope and variety. No one professional man can know from personal observation more than a minute fraction of the data which he must every day treat as working truths. Hence a reliance on the reported data of fellow scientists, learned by perusing their reports in books and journals. The law must and does accept this kind of knowledge from scientific men...[T]o reject a professional physician or mathematician because the fact or some facts to which he testifies are known to him only upon the authority of others would be to ignore the accepted methods of professional work and to insist on finical and impossible standards.....In general, the considerations which define the (professional) are (a) a proper source of information, (b) an extent of personal observation in the general subject, enabling him to estimate the general plausibility, or probability of soundness, of the views expressed, and (c) the impossibility of obtaining information on the particular technical detail except through reported data in part or entirely. The true solution must be to trust the discretion of the trial judge, exercised in the light of the nature of the subject and the witness' equipments. The decisions show in general a liberal attitude in receiving technical testimony based on professional reading. 
 

 
In Borowski , his Honour found (at 386) that evidence given by the expert in that case: 
 
 
 ...would have been directed to matter travelling outside opinion and dependent to a degree upon knowledge based upon hearsay. But this is an area where the hearsay rule does not apply and the matter dealt with in the evidence would clearly have been admissible.

The same judge-made exception to the hearsay rule was recognised in the standard texts on evidence at that time: see, for example, D Byrne QC and JD Heydon, Cross on Evidence (3 rd Australian Edition, Butterworths, 1986) at [15.31], [17.161], citing, in addition to Borowski and Schering Chemicals , See v Milner (1980) 2A Crim R 210 (FCA); Holt v Auckland City Council [1980] 2 NZLR 124; Cuthill v State Electricity Commissioner of Victoria [1981] VR 908 at 915 (FC); Baker v Australian Asbestos Insulations Pty Ltd [1984] 3 NSWLR 595 at 607.

The Law Reform Commission dealt with the present issue under the heading "Evidence Admissible for a Non-hearsay Purpose" (ALRC No 26 Vol 1 at [685]) stating (footnotes omitted): 
 
 Under existing law hearsay evidence that is admissible for a non-hearsay purpose is not excluded, but may not be used by the court as evidence of the facts stated. This involves the drawing of unrealistic distinctions. The issue is resolved by defining the hearsay rule as preventing the admissibility of hearsay evidence where it is relevant by reason only that it would affect the court's assessment of the facts intended to be asserted. This would have the effect that evidence relevant for a non-hearsay purpose eg to prove a prior consistent or inconsistent statement, or to prove the basis of the expert's opinion will be admissible also of evidence of the facts stated: 
 

 
 
 Tender of Prior Consistent and Inconsistent Statements 
 ............... 
 

 
 
 Expert's evidence of Basis of Opinion 
 Reference has been made above to the uncertainties that exist as to the admissibility of such evidence and to the unclear exceptions which have had to be created to meet the problems created by the hearsay rule. Under the proposal, evidence by an expert of the facts on which his opinion is based will be admissible as evidence of those facts. Potential dangers have been raised. First, there is the danger that false evidence may be placed before the court. However, the expert will usually form a judgment about the accuracy of what he is told. In addition the tactical pressure on the parties to verify the facts relied upon by the expert should ensure that problems of assessment of the evidence will not arise. They will either call more direct evidence or have to face adverse comment. When assessment problems do arise, the exclusionary discretions may be used. This is similar to the present approach. Another danger suggested is that it could result in an increase in evidence adduced particularly that which is adduced in the Family Court and is of marginal relevance. As at present, the expert will do no more than adduce evidence of the basis of his opinion what he was told will be relevant to that opinion and the assessment of it. However, the relevance proposal and relevance discretion will apply and give the courts express control where now that control and its extent is unclear. It has also been suggested that parties will want to answer the allegations of marginal relevance and this will give rise to an increase in the evidence given. However, this should not occur. First the party against whom the evidence is led can object to the relevance of the facts related by the expert only those affecting his opinion will be relevant. As to such facts, that party will have to decide, as at present, whether he accepts those facts or wishes to challenge them. He would have to do this whether the evidence was admitted as the basis of the expert's opinion or to prove the facts asserted it would be a foolish party who relied on that distinction in relation to key factual elements and did not call rebutting evidence. The proposal in fact has the potential to save time and costs. At present, the party leading the expert evidence should lead non-hearsay evidence to confirm all the statements made to and relied upon by the court. If he does not, it will be open to the opposing party to argue that the opinion should be rejected the hearsay rile will lie in wait. Under the proposal he can call witnesses to confirm the key material, and leave it up to the opposing party to cross-examine the witness to raise the matters in issue. If he does not and leads evidence in rebuttal, it will be possible for the first party to call further evidence.

The result of the Commission's deliberations was s 60 of the Evidence Act . The hearsay rule itself is set out in s 59 of that Act. Section 59(1) provides: 
 
 Evidence of a previous representation made by a person is not admissible to prove the existence of a fact that the person intended to assert by the representation.

In their joint report, Uniform Evidence Law: Report of December 2005, the Australian, New South Wales and Victorian Law Reform Commissions have recognised that s 60 had the effect of excluding from the hearsay rule an expert's statement of the factual basis of his or her opinion (see [7.74] ff). The Commissions recognised (at [7.74]) that an expert relies on "statements made to him or her by others about their observations of events which are facts in issue, together with a wide range of factual information from more remote sources". The Commissions gave as illustrations: knowledge acquired by experts from reading the work of other experts and from discussion with them; the reported data of fellow experts relied upon by such persons as scientists and technical experts in giving expert opinion evidence; factual material commonly relied upon in a particular industry or trade or calling.
 
The Commissions also recognised that, through necessity, there existed those judge-made exceptions to the hearsay rule referred to at [761] above. In addition to Borowski , they cited PQ v Australian Red Cross Society [1992] 1 VR 19 ; R v Vivona (Unreported, Victorian Court of Criminal Appeal, Crockett, Tadgell and Teague JJ, 12 September 1994); R v Fazio (1997) 93 A Crim R 522. The Commissions then stated at [7.77], [7.78] (footnotes omitted):
 
 
 7.77 The proposal that became s 60 was formulated with these exceptions in mind, with the intention that s 60 would perform the role the miscellaneous common law exceptions had performed and the complication of specific exceptions for these kinds of evidence avoided. 
 

 
 
 7.78 Section 60 also applies to representations of fact unique to the particular case upon which the expert bases his or her opinion. Such evidence is hearsay at common law, but s 60 lifts the statutory hearsay rule in that situation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/316.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Burroughs Corporation (Perkins's Application ) [1974] RPC 147</tocase>
<text>Alphapharm submits that in relation to the new manner of manufacture criterion, the case is one of a "mere desideratum" (the expression "a mere method or mere idea or mere desideratum" was used in Burroughs Corporation ( Perkins's Application ) [1974] RPC 147). Senior counsel for Alphapharm frankly conceded that, in a sense, Alphapharm's submission in this respect rose no higher than its case on obviousness. Indeed, he conceded that it was more confined than that case because the character of a manner of manufacture must appear on the face of the specification, and common general knowledge cannot be taken into account as it can in the context of obviousness.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/363.html</AustLII>
<text>Lundbeck submits that it has not been accepted in this Court that an expert's opinion is inadmissible if it is based on assumed or accepted facts that are not identified and proved, citing: Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 ( Sydneywide ) at [16] per Branson J and [87] per Weinberg and Dowsett JJ); Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208 at [16] , [21] [27] per Sundberg J; Jango v Northern Territory (No 4 ) (2004) 214 ALR 608 at [19] per Sackville J; NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381 at [33] per Finkelstein J; Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719 at [7] per Heerey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>CCOM Pty Ltd v Jiejing Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1168 ; (1994) 51 FCR 260</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1168.html</AustLII>
<text>In determining whether what is claimed fits the description of a "manner of manufacture", one must confine one's attention to the face of the specification: Philips v Mirabella at 663-664; Advanced Building Systems Pty Ltd v Ramset Fasteners (Aust) Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 19 ; (1998) 194 CLR 171 (Ramset) at [38] ; CCOM Pty Ltd v Jiejing Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1168 ; (1994) 51 FCR 260 ( CCOM v Jiejing ) at 291). The notion of a manner of manufacture does not incorporate considerations of novelty or inventiveness which are dealt with independently and comprehensively in s 18(1)(b), s 7, and the definitions of "prior art base" and "prior art information" in Sch 1: see Ramset at [30]-[34] (dealing with s 100 of the 1952 Act).

What is required is that there be a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification, taken as a whole, of the invention that is claimed in the claims so that those who may wish to exploit the invention as claimed after the patent has expired will be enabled to do so: see, for example, Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5 at 11 per Fullagar J; F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; CCOM v Jiejing at 281-282; Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289 at 304; Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 ( Lockwood v Doric ) at [69].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254</tocase>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385</tocase>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/230.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents ( [1971] HCA 3 ; 1971) 123 CLR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/3.html</AustLII>
<text>What is required is that there be a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification, taken as a whole, of the invention that is claimed in the claims so that those who may wish to exploit the invention as claimed after the patent has expired will be enabled to do so: see, for example, Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5 at 11 per Fullagar J; F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; CCOM v Jiejing at 281-282; Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289 at 304; Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 ( Lockwood v Doric ) at [69].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>F Hoffmann-La Roche AG v Chiron Corporation (2000) 47 IPR 516</tocase>
<text>I note that my rulings in relation to Documents 4 and 5 are consistent with certain observations made on applications for orders for discovery by Burchett J in F Hoffmann-La Roche AG v Chiron Corporation (2000) 47 IPR 516 at [19] [21] and by Branson J in Lubrizol Corporation Inc v Imperial Chemical Industries plc [2000] FCA 1464 ; (2000) 50 IPR 526 at [33] (although, unlike the present case, those cases involved the exercise of a discretion and a balancing exercise).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/890.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428</tocase>
<text>Both parties rely on the following passage from the English Court of Appeal's judgment in General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre &amp; Rubber Co Limited [1972] RPC 457 at 485-486: 
 
 If the prior inventor's publication contains a clear description of, or clear instructions to do or make, something that would infringe the patentee's claim if carried out after the grant of the patentee's patent, the patentee's claim will have been shown to lack the necessary novelty, that is to say, it will have been anticipated. The prior inventor, however, and the patentee may have approached the same device from different starting points and may for this reason, or it may be for other reasons, have so described their devices that it cannot be immediately discerned from a reading of the language which they have respectively used that they have discovered in truth the same device; but if carrying out the directions contained in the prior inventor's publication will inevitably result in something being made or done which, if the patentee's patent were valid, would constitute an infringement of the patentee's claim, this circumstance demonstrates that the patentee's claim has in fact been anticipated.
 If, on the other hand, the prior publication contains a direction which is capable of being carried out in a manner which would infringe the patentee's claim, but would be at least as likely to be carried out in a way which would not do so, the patentee's claim will not have been anticipated, although it may fail on the ground of obviousness. To anticipate the patentee's claim the prior publication must contain clear and unmistakeable directions to do what the patentee claims to have invented : Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457, line 34, approved in BTH Co Ltd v Metropolitan Vickers Electrical Co Ltd (1928) 45 RPC 1 at 24, line 1. A signpost, however clear, upon the road to the patentee's invention will not suffice. The prior inventor must be clearly shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee. [my emphasis] 
 

 
This passage has been followed in Lubrizol at [61] and in numerous other cases.

In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre &amp; Rubber Co Limited [1972] RPC 457</tocase>
<text>Both parties rely on the following passage from the English Court of Appeal's judgment in General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre &amp; Rubber Co Limited [1972] RPC 457 at 485-486: 
 
 If the prior inventor's publication contains a clear description of, or clear instructions to do or make, something that would infringe the patentee's claim if carried out after the grant of the patentee's patent, the patentee's claim will have been shown to lack the necessary novelty, that is to say, it will have been anticipated. The prior inventor, however, and the patentee may have approached the same device from different starting points and may for this reason, or it may be for other reasons, have so described their devices that it cannot be immediately discerned from a reading of the language which they have respectively used that they have discovered in truth the same device; but if carrying out the directions contained in the prior inventor's publication will inevitably result in something being made or done which, if the patentee's patent were valid, would constitute an infringement of the patentee's claim, this circumstance demonstrates that the patentee's claim has in fact been anticipated.
 If, on the other hand, the prior publication contains a direction which is capable of being carried out in a manner which would infringe the patentee's claim, but would be at least as likely to be carried out in a way which would not do so, the patentee's claim will not have been anticipated, although it may fail on the ground of obviousness. To anticipate the patentee's claim the prior publication must contain clear and unmistakeable directions to do what the patentee claims to have invented : Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457, line 34, approved in BTH Co Ltd v Metropolitan Vickers Electrical Co Ltd (1928) 45 RPC 1 at 24, line 1. A signpost, however clear, upon the road to the patentee's invention will not suffice. The prior inventor must be clearly shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee. [my emphasis] 
 

 
This passage has been followed in Lubrizol at [61] and in numerous other cases.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Generics (UK) Ltd v H Lundbeck A/S [2007] EWHC 1040 ; [2007] RPC 32</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Glaxo Group Ltd's Patent [2004] EWHC 477 ; [2004] RPC 43</tocase>
<text>Since arriving at the conclusion expressed in the last paragraph, I have read what Kitchin J has said on the present issue in Generics v Lundbeck at [231] [237] and the passages from the authorities to which his Lordship refers, namely, Richardson-Vicks Inc's Patent [1995] RPC 568 at 581 and Glaxo Group Ltd's Patent [2004] EWHC 477 ; [2004] RPC 43 at [113] . I note that my conclusion is generally in line with those three authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>H Lundbeck A/S v Generics (UK) Ltd [2008] EWCA 311</tocase>
<text>While the reasons set out above were being proofread in preparation for delivery of judgment, the English Court of Appeal on 10 April 2008 gave judgment in H Lundbeck A/S v Generics (UK) Ltd [2008] EWCA Civ 311 , the appeal from the judgment of Kitchin J in Generics v Lundbeck previously noted. With respect, I do not think it necessary to incorporate references to their Lordships' reasons, which are, generally speaking, consistent with what I have written above.
 I certify that the preceding seven hundred and eighty-five (785) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Lindgren. 
 
Associate:
 
 
Dated: 24 April 2008
 
 
 Proceeding NSD 1120 of 2005 
 
 Counsel for the Applicant/Cross Respondent (Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mr DK Catterns QC, Mr S Burley SC and Mr JS Cooke Solicitor for the Applicant/Cross Respondent (Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent/First Cross Claimant
(H Lundbeck A/S) and for the Second Cross Claimant (Lundbeck Australia Pty Ltd): Mr D Shavin QC and Ms KJ Howard SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent/First Cross Claimant
(H Lundbeck A/S) and for the Second Cross Claimant (Lundbeck Australia Pty Ltd): Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Proceeding NSD 1870 of 2005 
 
 Counsel for the Applicant (Lundbeck Aust Pty Ltd): Mr D Shavin QC and Ms KJ Howard SC Solicitor for the Applicant (Lundbeck Aust Pty Ltd): Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent (the Secretary of the Department of Health &amp; Ageing of the Commonwealth of Australia): Mr G Kennett Solicitor for the First Respondent (the Secretary
of the Department of Health &amp; Ageing of the Commonwealth of Australia): Australian Government Solicitor Counsel for the Second Respondent
(Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mr DK Catterns QC, Mr S Burley SC
and Mr JS Cooke 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent
(Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Proceeding NSD 954 of 2006 
 
 Counsel for the Applicant
(Arrow Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd): Mr C Dimitriadis 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant
(Arrow Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd): Blake Dawson Waldron 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent (H Lundbeck A/S): Mr D Shavin QC and Ms KJ Howard SC Solicitor for the Respondent (H Lundbeck A/S): Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Proceeding NSD 1078 of 2006 
 
 Counsel for the Applicant (H Lundbeck A/S): Mr D Shavin QC and Ms KJ Howard SC 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant (H Lundbeck A/S): Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 The First Respondent (Commissioner of Patents) did not appear, having filed a submitting appearance. 
 
 
 Counsel for the Second Respondent
(Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mr DK Catterns QC, Mr S Burley SC
and Mr JS Cooke 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent
(Alphapharm Pty Ltd): Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Dates of Hearing: 11, 12, 13, 16, 17, 18, 19, 23, 24, 26 April 2007; 1, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 May 2007 
 
 Date Last Written Submission Received: 21 November 2007 
 
 Date of Judgment: 24 April 2008 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/559.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Harrington-Smith v State of Western Australia (No 2) [2003] FCA 893 ; (2003) 130 FCR 424</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/893.html</AustLII>
<text>It is necessary to distinguish between two potential meanings of the notion of a "basis rule". The expression may be used to refer to a supposed rule that evidence of expert opinion is not admissible unless the expert identifies the assumed factual basis for his or her opinion, thereby distinguishing between what is opinion and what is not. This goes to the form taken by the expert's evidence. The provisions of s 79 of the Evidence Act tend to have the practical effect of requiring attention to the form that expert evidence takes: HG v The Queen [1999] HCA 2 ; (1999) 197 CLR 414 at [39] per Gleeson CJ. As I noted in Harrington-Smith v State of Western Australia (No 2) [2003] FCA 893 ; (2003) 130 FCR 424 at [25] , in the absence of a distinction between opinion and assumed factual basis, the Court may not be able to be satisfied:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HG v The Queen [1999] HCA 2 ; (1999) 197 CLR 414</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/2.html</AustLII>
<text>It is necessary to distinguish between two potential meanings of the notion of a "basis rule". The expression may be used to refer to a supposed rule that evidence of expert opinion is not admissible unless the expert identifies the assumed factual basis for his or her opinion, thereby distinguishing between what is opinion and what is not. This goes to the form taken by the expert's evidence. The provisions of s 79 of the Evidence Act tend to have the practical effect of requiring attention to the form that expert evidence takes: HG v The Queen [1999] HCA 2 ; (1999) 197 CLR 414 at [39] per Gleeson CJ. As I noted in Harrington-Smith v State of Western Australia (No 2) [2003] FCA 893 ; (2003) 130 FCR 424 at [25] , in the absence of a distinction between opinion and assumed factual basis, the Court may not be able to be satisfied:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1</tocase>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date

In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1658.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>In re Adamson (1960) 275 F 2d 952</tocase>
<text>I note that if In re Adamson (1960) 275 F2d 952 is authority for the proposition that a patent for a racemate necessarily anticipates a claimed invention of either of its enantiomers, I respectfully disagree. Conclusion on novelty

Alphapharm's attack on the Patent on the ground that the invention lacked novelty fails. SECTION E OBVIOUSNESS 
 Relevant law</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>In re O'Farrell [1988] USCAFED 411 ; (1988) 853 F 2d 894 at 903)</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jango v Northern Territory (No 4) (2004) 214 ALR 608</tocase>
<text>Lundbeck submits that it has not been accepted in this Court that an expert's opinion is inadmissible if it is based on assumed or accepted facts that are not identified and proved, citing: Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 ( Sydneywide ) at [16] per Branson J and [87] per Weinberg and Dowsett JJ); Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208 at [16] , [21] [27] per Sundberg J; Jango v Northern Territory (No 4 ) (2004) 214 ALR 608 at [19] per Sackville J; NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381 at [33] per Finkelstein J; Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719 at [7] per Heerey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/58.html</AustLII>
<text>What is required is that there be a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification, taken as a whole, of the invention that is claimed in the claims so that those who may wish to exploit the invention as claimed after the patent has expired will be enabled to do so: see, for example, Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5 at 11 per Fullagar J; F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; CCOM v Jiejing at 281-282; Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289 at 304; Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 ( Lockwood v Doric ) at [69].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 235 ALR 202</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/21.html</AustLII>
<text>The history of the emergence of obviousness or lack of inventive step as a distinct ground of invalidity has been recently traced by the High Court in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 235 ALR 202 ( Lockwood v Doric (No 2) ) at [38] [49], and by a Full Court of this Court in Ajinomoto Co Inc v NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 34 at [63] [91]. I need not discuss that history.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lubrizol Corporation Inc v Imperial Chemical Industries plc [2000] FCA 1464 ; (2000) 50 IPR 526</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1464.html</AustLII>
<text>The effect of these provisions is that the Patent can be revoked under the Act only on a ground of invalidity that would have been available under the 1952 Act. In any case where a relevant ground of invalidity under the 1952 Act is narrower than the corresponding ground under the Act, the patentee has the benefit of the narrower ground and is not to be worse off than if the 1952 Act had continued to operate: NV Philips Gloeilampenfabrieken v Mirabella International Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 404 ; (1993) 44 FCR 239 at 250 ff per Lockhart J, with whom Northrop J agreed and with whom Burchett J agreed on this point; ICI Chemicals &amp; Polymers Ltd v Lubrizol Corporation Inc (2000) 106 FCR 214 ( Lubrizol ) at [22] [24]; Aktiebolaget H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 1303 ; (2000) 51 IPR 375 at [8] [10]. Professors Banwell and Davies

Both parties rely on the following passage from the English Court of Appeal's judgment in General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre &amp; Rubber Co Limited [1972] RPC 457 at 485-486: 
 
 If the prior inventor's publication contains a clear description of, or clear instructions to do or make, something that would infringe the patentee's claim if carried out after the grant of the patentee's patent, the patentee's claim will have been shown to lack the necessary novelty, that is to say, it will have been anticipated. The prior inventor, however, and the patentee may have approached the same device from different starting points and may for this reason, or it may be for other reasons, have so described their devices that it cannot be immediately discerned from a reading of the language which they have respectively used that they have discovered in truth the same device; but if carrying out the directions contained in the prior inventor's publication will inevitably result in something being made or done which, if the patentee's patent were valid, would constitute an infringement of the patentee's claim, this circumstance demonstrates that the patentee's claim has in fact been anticipated.
 If, on the other hand, the prior publication contains a direction which is capable of being carried out in a manner which would infringe the patentee's claim, but would be at least as likely to be carried out in a way which would not do so, the patentee's claim will not have been anticipated, although it may fail on the ground of obviousness. To anticipate the patentee's claim the prior publication must contain clear and unmistakeable directions to do what the patentee claims to have invented : Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457, line 34, approved in BTH Co Ltd v Metropolitan Vickers Electrical Co Ltd (1928) 45 RPC 1 at 24, line 1. A signpost, however clear, upon the road to the patentee's invention will not suffice. The prior inventor must be clearly shown to have planted his flag at the precise destination before the patentee. [my emphasis] 
 

 
This passage has been followed in Lubrizol at [61] and in numerous other cases.

I note that my rulings in relation to Documents 4 and 5 are consistent with certain observations made on applications for orders for discovery by Burchett J in F Hoffmann-La Roche AG v Chiron Corporation (2000) 47 IPR 516 at [19] [21] and by Branson J in Lubrizol Corporation Inc v Imperial Chemical Industries plc [2000] FCA 1464 ; (2000) 50 IPR 526 at [33] (although, unlike the present case, those cases involved the exercise of a discretion and a balancing exercise).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Makita (Australia) Pty Ltd v Sprowles (2001) 52 NSWLR 705</tocase>
<text>Alphapharm relies on a passage from the well-known judgment of Heydon JA (as his Honour then was) in Makita (Australia) Pty Limited v Sprowles (2001) 52 NSWLR 705 ( Makita ) at [85]: 
 
 In short, if evidence tendered as expert opinion evidence is to be admissible, it must be agreed or demonstrated that there is a field of "specialised knowledge"; there must be an identified aspect of that field in which the witness demonstrates that by reason of specified training, study or experience, the witness has become an expert; the opinion proffered must be "wholly or substantially based on the witness's expert knowledge"; so far as the opinion is based on facts "observed" by the expert; they must be identified and admissibly proved by the expert, and so far as the opinion is based on "assumed" or "accepted" facts, they must be identified and proved in some other way; it must be established that the facts on which the opinion is based form a proper foundation for it; and the opinion of an expert requires demonstration or examination of the scientific or other intellectual basis of the conclusions reached: that is, the expert's evidence must explain how the field of "specialised knowledge" in which the witness is expert by reason of "training, study or experience", and on which the opinion is "wholly or substantially based", applies to the facts assumed or observed so as to produce the opinion propounded. If all these matters are not made explicit, it is not possible to be sure whether the opinion is based wholly or substantially on the expert's specialised knowledge. If the court cannot be sure of that, the evidence is strictly speaking not admissible, and, so far as it is admissible, of diminished weight.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Merck &amp; Co Inc v Arrow Pharmaceuticals Ltd [2003] FCA 1344 ; (2003) 59 IPR 226</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/1344.html</AustLII>
<text>Dr Barker decided that the decision of Wilcox J in Merck &amp; Co Inc v Arrow Pharmaceuticals Ltd [2003] FCA 1344 ; (2003) 59 IPR 226 ( Merck ) governed the issue before him. As Dr Barker understood the position, Merck produced the result that it did not matter that escitalopram was a new chemical entity having properties different from those of the racemate, citalopram, or that the registration of citalopram under its brand name Cipramil on the ARTG did not give the right to market escitalopram except as part of the racemate. All that mattered was that Cipramil did in fact "contain" escitalopram, or put another way, that escitalopram was present (to some extent) in Cipramil, and that Cipramil was included in the ARTG. It was also immaterial, according to Dr Barker, that escitalopram was not responsible for all of the activity of Cipramil.

Dr Barker concluded that since citalopram hydrobromide, marketed under the brand name Cipramil and containing escitalopram, was first registered on the ARTG on 9 December 1997, the Commissioner was required by reg 10.7(7) to amend the relevant entry in the Register to reflect the correct extension of the term of the Patent as expiring on 9 December 2012 (see [32] above).

Lundbeck complains that the Dr Barker erred in finding that the first regulatory approval date was the date on which Cipramil was registered on the ARTG, and that Dr Barker ought to have found that it was the date on which Lexapro was so registered (see [33] above). Which legislative r&eacute;gime applies?

For its part, Alphapharm relies on Merck &amp; Co Inc v Arrow Pharmaceuticals Ltd (2003) 59 IPR 226 ( Merck ). A patentee, Merck &amp; Co Inc (Merck), appealed against the Commissioner's delegate's refusal of an extension. The appeal was undefended, the respondent having withdrawn from the proceeding. Wilcox J allowed the appeal.

Sankyo Company Pty Ltd (Sankyo) had held a patent that claimed a compound of a particular formula, commonly referred to as Lovastatin. Lovastatin was entered on the ARTG. It was used for the control of cholesterol levels. Sankyo's patent expired on 19 February 2000, and no extension was sought in respect of it.

Merck applied for a patent on 3 June 1980 with priority dates in 1979 and 1980. The patent was granted on the basis of the exclusion of certain claims which related to Lovastatin.

On appeal, Wilcox J disagreed, saying (at [25]) that Merck's LHA argument was "irrefutable", and that, if only on that ground, the delegate's decision must be reversed.

His Honour stated (at [26]) that LHA was a pharmaceutical substance per se disclosed in the complete specification of the patent and falling within its claims, and that the undisputed evidence was that Mevacor contained LHA.

Wilcox J considered that it was irrelevant whether or not LHA itself was included in the ARTG: that for s 70(3)(a) purposes it was enough that it was contained in some other good (Mevacor) that was included in the ARTG (at [27]). His Honour thought that it did not matter that LHA was present in Mevacor only in minute quantities (at [28]).

Having regard to his conclusions supporting Merck's LHA argument, his Honour did not need to address its argument concerning Lovastatin, although he expressed the view that it seemed to him that the delegate had been right to reject that argument.

In Merck , as in the other cases referred to above, the question before the Court did not concern a competition between two arguable first regulatory approval dates. However, Wilcox J's construction of "containing" in s 70(3) must be applicable to the word "contain" in s 70(5). If I were to follow Wilcox J, I would hold that Cipramil "contained" (+)-citalopram. 
 Consideration of Lundbeck's "pharmaceutical substance per se " submission

The Latin expression "per se" means "by or in itself; intrinsically. Opposed to PER ACCIDENS [defined relevantly to mean "By virtue of some non-essential circumstance; contingently, indirectly"]": Oxford Dictionary of Foreign Words and Phrases (OUP, 1997). It is not every disclosure of every substance falling within the definition of "pharmaceutical substance" to which s 70(2)(a) refers. A non-essential or incidental disclosure of a pharmaceutical substance will not satisfy s 70(2)(a). The pharmaceutical substance must be of the essence of a disclosure made in the specification. This construction is consistent with the requirement that it fall within the scope of the claim or claims.

The racemate, citalopram, is the pharmaceutical substance per se disclosed in the specification of the Australian Citalopram Patent, whereas the (+)-enantiomer of that racemate is the pharmaceutical substance per se disclosed in the specification of the Patent, in each case for the purpose of s 70(2)(a). Moreover, the inclusion in the ARTG of Cipramil on 9 December 1997 clearly signified the inclusion in the ARTG of goods that consisted of or contained the pharmaceutical substance citalopram, and the inclusion of Lexapro in the ARTG on 16 September 2003 clearly signified the inclusion in the ARTG of goods that consisted of or contained the pharmaceutical substance (+)-citalopram, in each case for the purpose of s 70(3)(a). The precise question before the Court, however, is whether Cipramil was goods that contained the pharmaceutical substance (+)-citalopram for the latter purpose.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Merck Frosst Canada Inc v Canada (Minister of National Health and Welfare) (2000) 8 CPR (4 th ) 48</tocase>
<text>In the Canadian case Pfizer Canada Inc v Apotex Inc (1998) 78 CPR (3d) 3, the court stated that the doctrine of equivalents applies to compositions where there is equivalence between chemical ingredients. That approach was followed in the Canadian case Merck Frosst Canada Inc v Canada (Minister of National Health and Welfare) (2000) 8 CPR (4 th ) 48. In the later case, the court stated, quoting from the earlier one, that "basically, there is equivalence when the substituting ingredient or device 'performs substantially the same function in substantially the same way to obtain the same result'". Accordingly, the court accepted expert evidence that the chemical properties and activities of the substituted ingredient were similar to those of the ingredient that it replaced. That evidence showed that both compounds were electron withdrawing groups and would therefore allow a particular reaction to occur, resulting in the same products. Importantly, the court accepted expert evidence that "a person reasonably skilled in the art would have known of the inter-changeability of that ingredient not contained in the patent with the one that was". Accordingly, the court found infringement proved. The evidence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Meyers Taylor Pty Ltd v Vicarr Industries Ltd [1977] HCA 19 ; (1977) 137 CLR 228</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/19.html</AustLII>
<text>It is common ground that the basic test for lack of novelty in Australia is the "reverse infringement test", which was enunciated by Aickin J in the following well-known passage in Meyers Taylor Pty Ltd v Vicarr Industries Ltd [1977] HCA 19 ; (1977) 137 CLR 228 at 235: 
 
 The basic test for anticipation or want of novelty is the same as that for infringement and generally one can properly ask oneself whether the alleged anticipation would, if the patent were valid, constitute an infringement ... 
 

 
This rule is stated in Blanco White TA, Patents for Inventions and the Protection of Industrial Design (5 th ed, Stephens, London, 1983) at [4-102] as follows:
 
 
 The test for lack of novelty is essentially the same as the test for infringement; that is to say, a prior use will invalidate a claim if it was such that it would infringe that claim if carried out after the grant of the patent concerned; while a prior disclosure will invalidate if it contains a clear description of, or clear instructions to do or make, something that would infringe if carried out after grant.

Lundbeck submits that there are two elements of the reverse infringement test: first, that the alleged anticipation must disclose all of the essential features of the particular claim it is said to anticipate; and, second, that the alleged anticipation must have enabled the addressee to carry out the invention. Alphapharm submits: "The submissions of Lundbeck misapplied the doctrine of enabling disclosure, even assuming it applies in Australia". Alphapharm submits, however, that the applicability of the doctrine need not be decided because there is no dispute that the Australian Citalopram Patent "enabled" the racemate, that is, the positive enantiomer, but only with the negative enantiomer in equal proportions. Clearly, the issue of the proper construction of claim 1 discussed above directly arises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Australia) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/9.html</AustLII>
<text>The question of what was obvious is assessed from the perspective of the hypothetical non-inventive skilled addressee or team in the field of the invention, taking into account "what was known or used" (referred to as "common general knowledge"): Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Australia) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 ( Minnesota v Beiersdorf ). This position is now effectively codified in ss 7(2) and 18(1)(b) of the Act, provided s 7(3) is put to one side.

In Minnesota v Beiersdorf at 292-295 and in Aktiebolaget H&auml;ssle v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2002] HCA 59 ; (2002) 212 CLR 411 ( Astra ) at [57] it was held in relation to s 100(1)(e) of the 1952 Act that publications are not to be taken into account unless their content was part of common general knowledge at the priority date. Accordingly, the issue is not whether it was obvious to conduct a literature search of a particular kind with a view to acquiring information, but whether the information that would have been obtained from the search had already entered the body of common general knowledge: Minnesota v Beiersdorf at 295; Astra at [45]. No question arises in this case regarding the results of a routine literature search.

In Minnesota v Beiersdorf , Aickin J described the notion of common general knowledge (at 292): 
 
 The notion of common general knowledge itself involves the use of that which is known or used by those in the relevant trade. It forms the background knowledge and experience which is available to all in the trade in considering the making of new products, or the making of improvements in old, and it must be treated as being used by an individual as a general body of knowledge. 
 

 
As noted earlier, it was held in Astra that information recorded in a document, even a document widely circulated within the art, is not part of general common knowledge merely because the skilled addressee could be expected to locate it. The question is whether it is "generally accepted without question" or "generally regarded as a good basis for further action" by the bulk of those in the art: Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Tyco Electronics Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 315 ; (2002) 56 IPR 248 at [100] , quoting Blanco White TA, Patents for Inventions and the Protection of Industrial Design (5 th ed, Stephens, London, 1983) at [4-207].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Tyco Electronics Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 315 ; (2002) 56 IPR 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/315.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minnesota v Beiersdorf , Aickin J described the notion of common general knowledge (at 292): 
 
 The notion of common general knowledge itself involves the use of that which is known or used by those in the relevant trade. It forms the background knowledge and experience which is available to all in the trade in considering the making of new products, or the making of improvements in old, and it must be treated as being used by an individual as a general body of knowledge. 
 

 
As noted earlier, it was held in Astra that information recorded in a document, even a document widely circulated within the art, is not part of general common knowledge merely because the skilled addressee could be expected to locate it. The question is whether it is "generally accepted without question" or "generally regarded as a good basis for further action" by the bulk of those in the art: Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co v Tyco Electronics Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 315 ; (2002) 56 IPR 248 at [100] , quoting Blanco White TA, Patents for Inventions and the Protection of Industrial Design (5 th ed, Stephens, London, 1983) at [4-207].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>National Research Development Corporation v Commissioner of Patents [1959] HCA 67 ; (1959) 102 CLR 252</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/67.html</AustLII>
<text>In Gambro Pty Ltd v Fresenius Medical Care South East Asia Pty Ltd (2004) 61 IPR 442 ( Gambro ), Allsop J pointed out (at [353]) that it is wrong to divide up the inventive process into conception and practical implementation: it is the whole that must be considered and it suffices that there is only one inventive step involved (see also National Research Development Corporation v Commissioner of Patents [1959] HCA 67 ; (1959) 102 CLR 252 at 262).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c40">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Neolab Ltd and others v H Lundbeck AS 3 Ni 9/05 (EU) </tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c41">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/1399.html</AustLII>
<text>Lundbeck submits that it has not been accepted in this Court that an expert's opinion is inadmissible if it is based on assumed or accepted facts that are not identified and proved, citing: Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 ( Sydneywide ) at [16] per Branson J and [87] per Weinberg and Dowsett JJ); Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208 at [16] , [21] [27] per Sundberg J; Jango v Northern Territory (No 4 ) (2004) 214 ALR 608 at [19] per Sackville J; NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381 at [33] per Finkelstein J; Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719 at [7] per Heerey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c42">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56</tocase>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c43">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513</tocase>
<text>In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c44">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1524.html</AustLII>
<text>The history of the emergence of obviousness or lack of inventive step as a distinct ground of invalidity has been recently traced by the High Court in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 235 ALR 202 ( Lockwood v Doric (No 2) ) at [38] [49], and by a Full Court of this Court in Ajinomoto Co Inc v NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 34 at [63] [91]. I need not discuss that history.

Lundbeck submits that it has not been accepted in this Court that an expert's opinion is inadmissible if it is based on assumed or accepted facts that are not identified and proved, citing: Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 ( Sydneywide ) at [16] per Branson J and [87] per Weinberg and Dowsett JJ); Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208 at [16] , [21] [27] per Sundberg J; Jango v Northern Territory (No 4 ) (2004) 214 ALR 608 at [19] per Sackville J; NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381 at [33] per Finkelstein J; Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719 at [7] per Heerey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c45">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/23.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, it is clear that the earlier disclosure must be "enabling": see for example, Hill v Evans at 8 ("the antecedent statement must be such that a person of ordinary knowledge of the subject would at once perceive, understand and be able practically to apply the discovery without the necessity of making further experiments and gaining further information before the invention can be made useful"); Flour Oxidising Co Ltd v Carr &amp; Co Ltd (1908) 25 RPC 428 at 457 per Parker J ("clear and unmistakable directions so to use [the earlier apparatus]"); Acme Bedstead Co Ltd v Newlands Bros Ltd [1937] HCA 63 ; (1937) 58 CLR 689 at 707 per Dixon J; Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236 at 260-262 per Stephen and Mason JJ; Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd v Marlin Engineering Co (1990) 91 ALR 513 at 531-532 per Gummow J (the supposed anticipation must not require of the skilled but non-inventive addressee "the exercise of any inventive ingenuity and the taking of any inventive step"); Bristol-Myers Squibb Co v FH Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [2000] FCA 316 ; (2000) 97 FCR 524 at [67] per Black CJ and Lehane J ("must give a direction or make a recommendation or suggestion which will result, if the skilled reader follows it, in the claimed invention"); Imperial Chemical Industries Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2004] FCA 1658 ; (2005) 213 ALR 399 at [61] ff per Crennan J; Pfizer v Eli Lilly at [313]-[324] per French and Lindgren JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c46">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Olin Mathieson Chemical Corporation v Biorex Laboratories Limited [1970] RPC 157</tocase>
<text>The High Court also held in Astra (at [50] [53]) that obviousness was to be determined by asking whether a hypothetical non-inventive skilled addressee, equipped with the common general knowledge as at the priority date, would have taken steps towards the invention "as a matter of routine" in the expectation that they might well produce the invention or some other useful result (endorsing statements in Wellcome Foundation Ltd v V.R. Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262 ( Wellcome ) at 286 and Olin Mathieson Chemical Corporation v Biorex Laboratories Limited [1970] RPC 157 ( Olin ) at 187-188). The High Court has therefore insisted on the two elements: (1) being led as a matter of routine to the desired result; and (2) having a reasonable expectation of achieving that result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c47">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>Ortho-McNeil Pharmaceutical Inc v Mylan Laboratories Inc 348 F Supp 2d 713</tocase>
<text>My construction, independently arrived at, accords with that of District Judge Keeley in Ortho-McNeil Pharmaceutical Inc v Mylan Laboratories Inc 348 F Supp 2d 713. Her Honour had to construe a claim of "An S( )-pyridobenzoxazine compound represented by [a certain formula]". Her Honour said (at 726): 
 
 Thus, while it is certainly necessary to distinguish a new invention over the prior art, there is no indication that an inventor must use a plain-English purity limitation, as Mylan contends. Instead, an inventor may use anything that a person skilled in the relevant art would understand to limit the claim. In this case, the term "S( )" clearly and plainly limits the claim language to the levorotatory enantiomer. Those skilled in the art clearly understand the term "S( )" to affirmatively denote only the levorotatory enantiomer of a racemic compound, and not the racemic compound itself. 
 

 
Later (at 729-730) Keeley J said that those skilled in the art would have understood the claim to cover "levofloxacin with a purity that was highly, but less than 100%, optically pure". Her Honour's observations apply mutatis mutandis to the present case.

While my construction would leave unanswered the question how much "impurity" would prevent a compound from meeting the formula in claim 1 (see below), it does establish that when the compound is present only as 50% of a racemate, it does not meet the description in claim 1.

The construction outlined above is also supported by the body of the specification and a certain convention in the way in which chemists understand references to compounds, both discussed below, but does not depend on those two additional considerations. I rely on them as alternative bases for my construction if I am wrong in thinking that claim 1 is unambiguous. Rules of construction

There is a series of decisions of the various courts of the United States in which it has been accepted that unexpected superiority in effectiveness is probative of non-obviousness: see, for example, Sterling Drug Inc v Watson 135 F Supp 173 (1955) at 175-176; In re Gershon , 372 F 2d 535 (1967) at 537; In re Skoner , 517 F 2d 947 (1975) at 950; Ex parte Sohda 2002 WL 519757 at 2-3; In re Chupp , 816 F 2d 643 (1987) at 646-647; Ortho-McNeil Pharmaceutical Inc v Mylan Laboratories Inc 348 F Supp 2d 713 at 755-756.

In some of these cases it has been said that the evidence of unexpected superior clinical benefits has been admitted to counter prima facie obviousness arising from other evidence. I do not find other evidence in the present case raising a prima facie case of obviousness. In any event, this was not a basis of admissibility relied upon by Lundbeck.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c48">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pfizer Canada Inc v Apotex Inc (1998) 78 CPR (3d) 3</tocase>
<text>In the Canadian case Pfizer Canada Inc v Apotex Inc (1998) 78 CPR (3d) 3, the court stated that the doctrine of equivalents applies to compositions where there is equivalence between chemical ingredients. That approach was followed in the Canadian case Merck Frosst Canada Inc v Canada (Minister of National Health and Welfare) (2000) 8 CPR (4 th ) 48. In the later case, the court stated, quoting from the earlier one, that "basically, there is equivalence when the substituting ingredient or device 'performs substantially the same function in substantially the same way to obtain the same result'". Accordingly, the court accepted expert evidence that the chemical properties and activities of the substituted ingredient were similar to those of the ingredient that it replaced. That evidence showed that both compounds were electron withdrawing groups and would therefore allow a particular reaction to occur, resulting in the same products. Importantly, the court accepted expert evidence that "a person reasonably skilled in the art would have known of the inter-changeability of that ingredient not contained in the patent with the one that was". Accordingly, the court found infringement proved. The evidence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c49">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/224.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c50">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pharmacia Corporation v Merck &amp; Co Inc [2002] RPC 775</tocase>
<text>In so holding, the High Court rejected a less demanding "worth a try" or "obvious to try" test. Astra therefore stands for the rejection of a line of United Kingdom authority to the effect that "all of the courses of action which present themselves without the exercise of invention are obvious": Pharmacia Corporation v Merck &amp; Co Inc [2002] RPC 775 at 818 (see Astra at [54] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, Gummow and Hayne JJ). Their Honours explained that "[t]he tracing of a course of action which was complex and detailed, as well as laborious, with a good deal of trial and error, with dead ends and the retracing of steps [a description taken from the judgment of the trial Judge] [was] not the taking of routine steps to which the hypothetical formulator [would be] taken as a matter of course" (at [58]; also per Callinan J at [185]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c51">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Pharmacia Italia SpA v Mayne Pharma Pty Ltd (2006) 69 IPR 1</tocase>
<text>Lundbeck refers to three authorities as being relevant to the construction of the expression "pharmaceutical substance per se ": Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH v Commissioner of Patents [2001] FCA 647 ; (2001) 112 FCR 595 ( Boehringer ); Prejay Holdings Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2003] FCAFC 77 ; (2003) 57 IPR 424 ( Prejay ); and Pharmacia Italia SpA v Mayne Pharma Pty Ltd (2006) 69 IPR 1 ( Pharmacia ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c52">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/344.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c53">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Prejay Holdings Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2003] FCAFC 77 ; (2003) 57 IPR 424</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/77.html</AustLII>
<text>Lundbeck refers to three authorities as being relevant to the construction of the expression "pharmaceutical substance per se ": Boehringer Ingelheim International GmbH v Commissioner of Patents [2001] FCA 647 ; (2001) 112 FCR 595 ( Boehringer ); Prejay Holdings Ltd v Commissioner of Patents [2003] FCAFC 77 ; (2003) 57 IPR 424 ( Prejay ); and Pharmacia Italia SpA v Mayne Pharma Pty Ltd (2006) 69 IPR 1 ( Pharmacia ).

In Prejay a Full Court of this Court followed Boehringer . All of the claims were method claims, not product claims. The Commissioner's delegate refused an application for an extension. The Full Court agreed with the delegate that a substance that is mentioned in the context of a method claim does not meet the requirement of s 70(2)(a) that the substance per se fall within the scope of a claim (at [23] [24] per Wilcox and Cooper JJ, [28] per Allsop J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c54">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Company LLC (No 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2006) 71 IPR 46</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1787.html</AustLII>
<text>Obviousness is perhaps the most critical aspect of the Revocation Proceeding (and the Arrow Proceeding). This appears to be the first time an Australian patent relating to a single enantiomer has been challenged on the ground of obviousness (the obviousness ground was abandoned in Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Company LLC (No 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2006) 71 IPR 46 ( Ranbaxy ) as noted by Young J at [15]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c55">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Application of Eli Lilly &amp; Co [1982] 1 NSWLR 526</tocase>
<text>In Re Application of Eli Lilly &amp; Co [1982] 1 NSWLR 526, it was argued by the Commissioner in an application under s 90 of the Patents Act 1952 (Cth) for an extension of term, that the patentee had not properly exploited the invention. The patent was in respect of a pharmaceutical invention called monensic acid and a new process for producing that product. The patentee had exploited and used commercially only monensin sodium, a salt of monensic acid. The Commissioner argued that the salt was a product chemically distinct from the acid.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c56">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289</tocase>
<text>What is required is that there be a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification, taken as a whole, of the invention that is claimed in the claims so that those who may wish to exploit the invention as claimed after the patent has expired will be enabled to do so: see, for example, Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5 at 11 per Fullagar J; F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; CCOM v Jiejing at 281-282; Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289 at 304; Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 ( Lockwood v Doric ) at [69].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c57">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Richardson-Vicks Inc's Patent [1995] RPC 568</tocase>
<text>Since arriving at the conclusion expressed in the last paragraph, I have read what Kitchin J has said on the present issue in Generics v Lundbeck at [231] [237] and the passages from the authorities to which his Lordship refers, namely, Richardson-Vicks Inc's Patent [1995] RPC 568 at 581 and Glaxo Group Ltd's Patent [2004] EWHC 477 ; [2004] RPC 43 at [113] . I note that my conclusion is generally in line with those three authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c58">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/980.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c59">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Saccharin Corporation Ltd v Anglo-Continental Chemical Works Ltd (1900) 17 RPC 307</tocase>
<text>There is little case law in Australia in relation to "mechanical equivalents" and "non-essential integers" in the context of chemical formulae. In Saccharin Corporation Ltd v Anglo-Continental Chemical Works Ltd (1900) 17 RPC 307 at 319, Buckley J held that a method claim was infringed notwithstanding that changes had been made, because the same result was achieved.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c60">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/788.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties' written submissions referred to numerous authorities on the construction of patents, and, in particular, on the construction of patent claims. I need not refer to more than the following: The construction of a specification is a question of law and belongs to the Court: Hill v Evans (1862) 1A IPR 1 ( Hill v Evans ) at 3; The Court must construe the specification as it would be understood by the notional skilled addressee as at the relevant date: Hill v Evans at 3-4; D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc (1988) 13 IPR 385 ( D&eacute;cor ) at 400; Flexible Steel Lacing Co v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331 ( Flexible Steel Lacing ) at [81]; Evidence from a skilled addressee in the field of the invention as to how he or she would have understood the specification at the relevant date is relevant evidence for the purposes of s 55(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (Evidence Act): EI Dupont De Nemours &amp; Co v Imperial Chemicals Industries plc [2002] FCA 230 ; (2002) 54 IPR 304 at 320-322; Flexible Steel Lacing at [81]; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 at [21]; Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231 at [49] ; The claims must be construed in the context of the specification as a whole, and the rest of the specification may explain the background to the claims, assist in ascertaining the meaning of technical terms, or aid in the resolving of ambiguities in the construction of the claims: Clorox at [16]; Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co KG v RE Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 ( Sachtler ) at [42]; A patent specification must be given a purposive rather than a purely literal construction, and must be construed in a practical commonsense manner avoiding a too technical or narrow construction in favour of a construction under which the invention will work, as against one according to which it may not work: Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Ely Lilly &amp; Co [2005] FCAFC 224 ; (2005) 225 ALR 416 ( Pfizer v Eli Lilly ) at [249]-[250]; The hypothetical addressee of the patent is the non-inventive person skilled in the art before the priority date, and the words used in the specification and the claims are to be given the meanings that that skilled addressee would give them, both in the light of his or her own general knowledge and what is disclosed in the body of the specification: Clorox at [20]; D&eacute;cor at 391; PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41 at [170] . Professors Banwell and Davies on the meaning that the Patent claims would convey to the hypothetical skilled chemist at the priority date

Alphapharm submits that "the wording of the claims makes it clear that the relevant area has been deliberately left outside the claim", citing Sachtler at [53].

Alphapharm submits that the cross-examination of Professor Banwell established that the steps of the A process were different from the integers of Claim 6(b).

Another defence raised by Alphapharm concerns the definition of "exploit" in Schedule 1 to the Act. Section 13(1) of the Act provides that, subject to the Act, a patent gives the patentee the exclusive rights, during the term of the patent, to exploit the invention and to authorise another person to do so. Section 13(3) provides that a patent "has effect throughout the patent area". The definition of "exploit" in the Dictionary in Schedule 1 is as follows: 
 
 exploit , in relation to an invention includes:
 (a) where the invention is a product make, hire, sell or otherwise dispose of the product, offer to make, sell, hire or otherwise dispose of it, use or import it, or keep it for the purpose of doing any of those things; or
 (b) where the invention is a method or process use the method or process or do any act mentioned in paragraph (a) in respect of a product resulting from such use. 
 

 
Alphapharm submits that para (b) of the definition requires that the use of the method or process be in the "patent area". The "patent area" is defined in the Dictionary in Schedule 1 and may, for convenience, be thought of as being "Australia". 
 Consideration of the claim of infringement of the product claims (claims 1, 3 and 5)

The authorities relating to infringement were recently reviewed by Bennett J in Sachtler at [43]-[67]. Her Honour cautioned against the purported application of the "pith and marrow" or "substance of the invention" approach, untrammelled by the form of the claims (at [55]).

It is necessary for the Court to construe claim 6(b) in the light of the common general knowledge as at the priority date. How would the non-inventive person skilled in the art at that time, possessed of that common general knowledge, have understood the words of the claim?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c61">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Seyfang v G D Searle &amp; Co [1973] QB 148</tocase>
<text>This seems to me to reflect the only practicable way in which opinion evidence of the kind given by Professor Montgomery can be dealt with. In this respect, I note the statement made by Cooke J in Seyfang v G D Searle &amp; Co [1973] QB 148 at 151: 
 
 It does appear to me with the greatest respect that a system which does not permit experts to refer in their expert evidence to the publications of other experts in the same field is a system which puts peculiar difficulties in the way of proof of matters which depend on expert opinion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c62">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1958/27.html</AustLII>
<text>What is required is that there be a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification, taken as a whole, of the invention that is claimed in the claims so that those who may wish to exploit the invention as claimed after the patent has expired will be enabled to do so: see, for example, Soci&eacute;t&eacute; Des Usines Chimiques Rh&ocirc;ne-Poulenc v Commissioner of Patents [1958] HCA 27 ; (1958) 100 CLR 5 at 11 per Fullagar J; F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co AG v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; CCOM v Jiejing at 281-282; Rehm Pty Ltd v Websters Security Systems (International) Pty Ltd (1988) 11 IPR 289 at 304; Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 ( Lockwood v Doric ) at [69].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c63">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/157.html</AustLII>
<text>Lundbeck submits that it has not been accepted in this Court that an expert's opinion is inadmissible if it is based on assumed or accepted facts that are not identified and proved, citing: Sydneywide Distributors Pty Ltd v Red Bull Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 157 ; (2002) 55 IPR 354 ( Sydneywide ) at [16] per Branson J and [87] per Weinberg and Dowsett JJ); Neowarra v Western Australia (No 1) [2003] FCA 1399 ; (2003) 134 FCR 208 at [16] , [21] [27] per Sundberg J; Jango v Northern Territory (No 4 ) (2004) 214 ALR 608 at [19] per Sackville J; NutraSweet Australia Pty Ltd v Ajinomoto Co Inc [2005] FCA 1524 ; (2005) 67 IPR 381 at [33] per Finkelstein J; Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lee Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 363 ; (2006) 228 ALR 719 at [7] per Heerey J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c64">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wellcome Foundation Ltd v V.R. Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/12.html</AustLII>
<text>The High Court also held in Astra (at [50] [53]) that obviousness was to be determined by asking whether a hypothetical non-inventive skilled addressee, equipped with the common general knowledge as at the priority date, would have taken steps towards the invention "as a matter of routine" in the expectation that they might well produce the invention or some other useful result (endorsing statements in Wellcome Foundation Ltd v V.R. Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 12 ; (1981) 148 CLR 262 ( Wellcome ) at 286 and Olin Mathieson Chemical Corporation v Biorex Laboratories Limited [1970] RPC 157 ( Olin ) at 187-188). The High Court has therefore insisted on the two elements: (1) being led as a matter of routine to the desired result; and (2) having a reasonable expectation of achieving that result.

Evidence of the patentee's own lack of success in earlier attempts is probative of the inventive nature of a successful solution to a problem ( Wellcome at 287); the question of what weight is to be given to that evidence will depend on all the circumstances including the patentee's qualifications and experience in the field of the invention. Inventions that reveal an "unfelt want or need" are as likely or sometimes more likely to involve an inventive step as those that fulfil a "long-felt want" ( Wellcome at 287; Astra at [38]). Obviousness in relation to the product claims and the method claim

Obviousness means different things in relation to the product claims (claims 1 5) and the method claim (claim 6). Alphapharm criticises Lundbeck for failing to make that distinction.

In the case of the method claim, the question of obviousness assumes as the starting point the goal of obtaining the (+)-enantiomer. In relation to the product claims, on the other hand, the question is whether that goal was itself an obvious one to pursue. Common general knowledge of methods available to resolve racemates may, however, be relevant to the obviousness of the product claims. It is relevant to the question whether it was obvious to want to obtain (+)-citalopram to ask whether it was part of common general knowledge that there were or were not available straightforward, inexpensive methods of doing so that were expected to succeed.

While evidence of the efforts of the inventor and of the efforts (or absence of them) of the patentee's opponent and others is admissible as relevant to the issue of obviousness (see, for example, Wellcome at 287), the question is an objective one requiring the creation of a hypothetical person, skilled but non-inventive in the art, or a hypothetical team of such persons. The concept of common general knowledge at the priority date must be proved by evidence, and the assumption made that the hypothetical person or team was possessed of that common general knowledge.

In Wellcome, Aickin J, with whom the other members of the High Court agreed, stated (at 287): 
 
 ... not all inventions are to be classified as fulfilling a long-felt want. Those which reveal an "unfelt want" are as likely, or sometimes more likely, to involve an inventive step. 
 

 
In Astra at [38], Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, Gummow and Hayne JJ approved of this passage. However, neither Aickin J in Wellcome nor their Honours in Astra were saying that evidence of unexpected benefits is admissible. Rather, the point they were making was that evidence of previous unsuccessful attempts to satisfy a long-felt want, while admissible, might not be entitled to much weight since inventive step can be present, not only in the presence of a long-felt want and associated motivation, but also in their absence.

It seems to me that Lundbeck has set up a "straw man" to knock down. In the light of the nature of the case that Lundbeck had to counter, it was only evidence of what was commonly known and expected at the priority date that it was entitled to seek to prove. Evidence of post-priority date surprises did not fall within that description.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c65">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Wm Wrigley Jr Company v Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd (2006) 66 IPR 298</tocase>
<text>There is a principle that all that is within the scope of a claim must be useful if the claim is not to fail for inutility, or, to express the matter differently, a claim is bad if it covers means that will not produce the desired result even if a skilful person would know which means to avoid: Wm Wrigley Jr Company v Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd (2006) 66 IPR 298 at [138] and authorities there cited.

Alphapharm relies on the testimony of Professor Montgomery who was asked what the highest therapeutically useful unit dose of escitalopram was. He said that it was 20 mg of escitalopram, but that in treating obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) clinicians normally use above that level, and that unit dosages of 30 mg and 40 mg are often used in the treatment of resistant OCD.

Professor Montgomery was also asked what would be the minimum useful dose. He said that 5 mg was found to be effective in the treatment of social anxiety disorder in a very large study, but that that amount was found to be ineffective in the treatment of generalised anxiety disorder. He said that there is a general notion that one should use lower doses in the case of the elderly, and that the 5 mg dose is used for the treatment of them.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>