<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Fleming's Nurseries Pty Ltd v Hannaford [2008] FCA 591 (2 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/591.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Zee Sweet Pty Ltd v Magnom Orchards Pty Ltd [2003] VSC 486</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VICSC/2003/486.html</AustLII>
<text>16 Mr Hannaford also filed written submissions, which he developed at the hearing. Mr Hannaford contends that:
 
 
 1. The bases for the claims against him for delivery up and/or destruction of the trees are the terms of the Non-Propagation Agreements pleaded in subpars (c)(ii) of pars 11, 14, 17, 20 23 and 26 of the applicants' Further Amended Statement of Claim. As Mr Hannaford observes, he pleads that these are unenforceable since they are penalties and/or seeks relief against forfeiture. Mr Hannaford further submits that this claim, which will have to be determined before the applicants' entitlement to relief in the nature of delivery up or destruction is granted, "will require a determination of the factors which may have led to the subject clauses being inserted into the agreements and whether ... the rights sought to be granted by the clauses were extravagant or oppressive at the time of entry into the agreements". He added that "[t]he question of relief against forfeiture will require a consideration of the circumstances as at the date of the breach and will require a consideration of the effect of the proposed delivery up or destruction orders on [him]". Counsel for Mr Hannaford submits that these matters "sit ill" with a trial as to liability only since the witnesses in relation to these matters may also be witnesses in connection with damages issues. Findings regarding their credit may need to be made prior to the damages hearing if a split trial is ordered. In an amendment to his written submissions filed prior to the hearing, Mr Hannaford noted that his defence "rests significantly on his credit" and that, if unsuccessful, he would also be a likely witness in relation to assessment of damages or account of profits. He argued that, therefore, an order for a split trial would have the potential to cause embarrassment and the need for the judge hearing the trial on liability to disqualify herself from hearing the latter part of the proceeding.
 2. Zee Sweet Pty Ltd v Magnom Orchards Pty Ltd [2003] VSC 486 (" Zee Sweet ") is distinguishable.
 3. If there is an enquiry as to profits at the trial on liability, as suggested by the Notice of Motion, then issues will plainly overlap. (I note that the applicants disavowed this suggestion at the hearing.)
 4. The relief sought by the applicants includes discretionary relief such as declarations and injunctions, which ordinarily weigh against the splitting of a trial.

26 The parties did not rely at the hearing on Zee Sweet and I do not consider much turns on its conduct. It is, plainly enough, a different case from the present, although involving a similar subject matter.

27 Mr Hannaford raises the possibility that, after the trial on liability, it may be necessary to make adverse credit findings against some witnesses, who may later be required for the trial on pecuniary relief. Mr Hannaford claims and, for present purposes, I accept that his credit will be in issue on liability. Mr Hannaford places particular reliance on the evidence that he foreshadows in connection with his penalty and/or relief against forfeiture claim, which, according to him, would overlap with evidence he is likely to give at a trial on monetary relief. His counsel points out that he is a sole trader and, as such, is the person most familiar with all aspects of his business.

28 I accept that there is a risk that I might take an adverse view of Mr Hannaford's credit at the trial on liability. Whether or not Mr Hannaford will need to give evidence at a trial on monetary relief is uncertain, although I accept that he may. I accept that if I were to make adverse credit findings against him, he might perceive that he was at some disadvantage at the second stage of the proceeding. Whether or not this possibility is realised remains to be seen. I doubt, however, that any real disadvantage is likely to arise for him. The possibility of disadvantage is limited because at this second stage it is likely that much would turn on documentary business and other records and expert accountants' evidence. Notwithstanding this, I accept that the possibility that I may take an adverse view of Mr Hannaford's credit at the trial on liability, which will impact on him if he is needed to give evidence at the trial on monetary relief, is a factor tending against a split trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 ; (1999) 217 ALR 495</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/718.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The principles that govern the circumstances in which an order under O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules may be made are well established. They are discussed by Branson J in Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 ; (1999) 217 ALR 495 (" Reading ") at [7] and [8] and by French J in Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651 at [7] . Ultimately, the question is whether, in the exercise of the Court's discretion, this is an appropriate case for the departure from the ordinary course that all issues of fact and law should be determined at the one time, on the basis that it is just and convenient for the order to be made: see Reading at [9]; Tallglen Pty Ltd v Pay TV Holdings Pty Ltd (1996) 22 ACSR 130. As counsel for the applicants pointed out, the outcome of the reported decisions on O 29 r 2 turns in each instance on the nature of the case and the particular circumstances relevant to it.

18 It is customary in intellectual property cases, however, to hear and determine issues of liability separately and before issues of pecuniary relief. This is largely because it is generally thought just and convenient to so order on account of the fact that an applicant in such a case is not compelled to make an election as between damages and an account of profits at least before the evidence on liability has been received: see Reading at [9] per Branson J; Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v Bata Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230 ; Digi International Inc v Stallion Technologies Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 529 at [40] per Ambrose J; and Novartis Crop Protection Australasia Pty Ltd v Orica Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1013 at [7] - [9] per Stone J. Under s 56(3) of the PBRA, in an action for infringement, Canada is entitled to make an election for damages or an account of profits. That is, the nature of Canada's case attracts the same considerations as other intellectual property cases requiring an election between the remedies in the event that liability is established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/651.html</AustLII>
<text>17 The principles that govern the circumstances in which an order under O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules may be made are well established. They are discussed by Branson J in Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 ; (1999) 217 ALR 495 (" Reading ") at [7] and [8] and by French J in Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651 at [7] . Ultimately, the question is whether, in the exercise of the Court's discretion, this is an appropriate case for the departure from the ordinary course that all issues of fact and law should be determined at the one time, on the basis that it is just and convenient for the order to be made: see Reading at [9]; Tallglen Pty Ltd v Pay TV Holdings Pty Ltd (1996) 22 ACSR 130. As counsel for the applicants pointed out, the outcome of the reported decisions on O 29 r 2 turns in each instance on the nature of the case and the particular circumstances relevant to it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tallglen Pty Ltd v Pay TV Holdings Pty Ltd (1996) 22 ACSR 130</tocase>
<text>17 The principles that govern the circumstances in which an order under O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules may be made are well established. They are discussed by Branson J in Reading Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Mutual Provident Society [1999] FCA 718 ; (1999) 217 ALR 495 (" Reading ") at [7] and [8] and by French J in Olbers Co Ltd v Commonwealth (No 3) [2003] FCA 651 at [7] . Ultimately, the question is whether, in the exercise of the Court's discretion, this is an appropriate case for the departure from the ordinary course that all issues of fact and law should be determined at the one time, on the basis that it is just and convenient for the order to be made: see Reading at [9]; Tallglen Pty Ltd v Pay TV Holdings Pty Ltd (1996) 22 ACSR 130. As counsel for the applicants pointed out, the outcome of the reported decisions on O 29 r 2 turns in each instance on the nature of the case and the particular circumstances relevant to it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v Bata Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230</tocase>
<text>18 It is customary in intellectual property cases, however, to hear and determine issues of liability separately and before issues of pecuniary relief. This is largely because it is generally thought just and convenient to so order on account of the fact that an applicant in such a case is not compelled to make an election as between damages and an account of profits at least before the evidence on liability has been received: see Reading at [9] per Branson J; Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v Bata Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230 ; Digi International Inc v Stallion Technologies Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 529 at [40] per Ambrose J; and Novartis Crop Protection Australasia Pty Ltd v Orica Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1013 at [7] - [9] per Stone J. Under s 56(3) of the PBRA, in an action for infringement, Canada is entitled to make an election for damages or an account of profits. That is, the nature of Canada's case attracts the same considerations as other intellectual property cases requiring an election between the remedies in the event that liability is established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Digi International Inc v Stallion Technologies Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2001/442.html</AustLII>
<text>18 It is customary in intellectual property cases, however, to hear and determine issues of liability separately and before issues of pecuniary relief. This is largely because it is generally thought just and convenient to so order on account of the fact that an applicant in such a case is not compelled to make an election as between damages and an account of profits at least before the evidence on liability has been received: see Reading at [9] per Branson J; Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v Bata Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230 ; Digi International Inc v Stallion Technologies Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 529 at [40] per Ambrose J; and Novartis Crop Protection Australasia Pty Ltd v Orica Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1013 at [7] - [9] per Stone J. Under s 56(3) of the PBRA, in an action for infringement, Canada is entitled to make an election for damages or an account of profits. That is, the nature of Canada's case attracts the same considerations as other intellectual property cases requiring an election between the remedies in the event that liability is established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Novartis Crop Protection Australasia Pty Ltd v Orica Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1013</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1013.html</AustLII>
<text>18 It is customary in intellectual property cases, however, to hear and determine issues of liability separately and before issues of pecuniary relief. This is largely because it is generally thought just and convenient to so order on account of the fact that an applicant in such a case is not compelled to make an election as between damages and an account of profits at least before the evidence on liability has been received: see Reading at [9] per Branson J; Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v Bata Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230 ; Digi International Inc v Stallion Technologies Pty Ltd (2001) 53 IPR 529 at [40] per Ambrose J; and Novartis Crop Protection Australasia Pty Ltd v Orica Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1013 at [7] - [9] per Stone J. Under s 56(3) of the PBRA, in an action for infringement, Canada is entitled to make an election for damages or an account of profits. That is, the nature of Canada's case attracts the same considerations as other intellectual property cases requiring an election between the remedies in the event that liability is established.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Polaris Communications Pty Ltd v Dynamic Hearing Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 627</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/627.html</AustLII>
<text>21 I accept that, if the applicants succeed on their principal liability issues, they will have a good basis for injunctive relief. In turn, to quote Sundberg J, this would provide an "end point" to the respondents' infringing conduct and a proper foundation for a consideration of the quantum of pecuniary relief to which the applicants would be entitled: see Polaris Communications Pty Ltd v Dynamic Hearing Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 627 at [5] .

22 Any trial on liability would, of course, include a hearing and determination of the penalty and/or relief against forfeiture issues that Mr Hannaford pleads by way of Defence. On account of these claims, however, Mr Hannaford argues that the applicants exaggerate the savings in time and expense if a split trial were ordered. He maintains that the penalty and/or relief against forfeiture issues would necessitate discovery of certain of his and Fleming's Nurseries' financial records since the value (to him and to Fleming's Nurseries) of the asset (the cherry trees) subject to the so-called penalty clause is in issue. There would, so his counsel says, be a corresponding need to prepare and present financial evidence directed to these matters. Accordingly, his counsel submits that the cost to Mr Hannaford of a trial on all issues would not be appreciably greater than the cost of a trial on liability alone.

23 The applicants respond that, so far as they are concerned, the evidence as to penalties and/or relief against forfeiture is not co-terminous with the evidence as to monetary relief. They affirm that, so far as they are concerned, there would remain significant cost and time advantages with a split trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ringrow Pty Ltd v BP Australia Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 71 ; (2005) 222 ALR 306</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/71.html</AustLII>
<text>12 Apparently there will be a need for some plant DNA testing in relation to issues 1 and 2. Issues 2 and 5 also involve some questions of construction. The applicants foreshadow that they will argue that, when properly construed, the so-called penalty clause does not provide for a penalty at all but is merely intended to provide further protection against unauthorised use. Counsel for Mr Hannaford, on the other hand, states that, on the matter of penalty, Mr Hannaford wishes to adduce evidence of the value of the asset to him, the value to Fleming's Nurseries, the sum paid in respect of it, and related matters: see in this connection Ringrow Pty Ltd v BP Australia Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 71 ; (2005) 222 ALR 306 at 309-309 (citing Dunlop Pneumatic Tyre Co Ltd v New Garage and Motor Co Ltd [1914] UKHL 1 ; [1915] AC 79 at 86-87).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dunlop Pneumatic Tyre Co Ltd v New Garage and Motor Co Ltd [1914] UKHL 1 ; [1915] AC 79</tocase>
<text>12 Apparently there will be a need for some plant DNA testing in relation to issues 1 and 2. Issues 2 and 5 also involve some questions of construction. The applicants foreshadow that they will argue that, when properly construed, the so-called penalty clause does not provide for a penalty at all but is merely intended to provide further protection against unauthorised use. Counsel for Mr Hannaford, on the other hand, states that, on the matter of penalty, Mr Hannaford wishes to adduce evidence of the value of the asset to him, the value to Fleming's Nurseries, the sum paid in respect of it, and related matters: see in this connection Ringrow Pty Ltd v BP Australia Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 71 ; (2005) 222 ALR 306 at 309-309 (citing Dunlop Pneumatic Tyre Co Ltd v New Garage and Motor Co Ltd [1914] UKHL 1 ; [1915] AC 79 at 86-87).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>