<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Black &amp; Decker Inc v GMCA Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 504 (18 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/504.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Adelmann &amp; Ham Boiler Corporation v Llanrwst Foundry Co (1928) 45 RPC 413</tocase>
<text>26 GMCA submitted that both patents were but an "attempt to re-design a known tool so as to achieve impermissibly, a patent monopoly over what is really a marketing idea". The alleged invention, so the argument went, citing Maugham J in Adelmann &amp; Ham Boiler Corporation v Llanrwst Foundry Co (1928) 45 RPC 413 at 420, was simply the application of a well known and well understood piece of mechanism to achieve an obvious advantage. The mere "positioning" of the handle for a known tool in order to achieve a known result was not a manner of manufacture.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cleveland Graphite Bronze Co v Glacier Metal Co Ltd (1950) 67 RPC 149</tocase>
<text>78 Claims must be determined in a practical and common sense manner: Nesbit v Impro at 95; Minnesota Mining at 274. In Cleveland Graphite Bronze Co v Glacier Metal Co Ltd (1950) 67 RPC 149 at 154 it was said that the claims must be as precise "as the subject admits of". The fact that Dr Stark had no problems on first reading is of significance. It is not the role of an independent expert to seek out difficulties or to read a patent with, to borrow an expression from administrative law, "an eye keenly attuned to the perception of error": Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 322 ; (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287 quoted in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272. This episode reflects on Dr Stark's credibility as an independent expert. Generally I found Dr Stark lacked objectivity and detachment. He appeared keen to raise every conceivable argument in favour of the party which retained him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Colbeam Palmer Ltd v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/50.html</AustLII>
<text>147 However, statutory rights to damages or an account of profits conferred on owners or exclusive licensees of intellectual property only have effect for the period that a plaintiff in fact has the relevant status. Thus in Colbeam Palmer Ltd v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25 Windeyer J held (at 36) that an account of profits should be taken to terminate as at the date the plaintiff assigned the trade mark in question and (at 41) that the assignee, having been joined as a plaintiff, should be entitled to an account of profits from the date of assignment. Similarly in Stack v Brisbane City Council (1996) 35 IPR 296 at 302 Drummond J held that where an equitable title had been converted into legal title by assignment, the assignor would have the right to an account of profits made by the infringers in the period up to the assignment and that the assignee alone would have the right to any profits made by the infringers after that date. Likewise, if an election were made for damages the assignee
 is the proper claimant for that relief, but only as from the date its equitable ownership became converted by registration into full legal and beneficial ownership of the patent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 322 ; (1993) 43 FCR 280</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/322.html</AustLII>
<text>78 Claims must be determined in a practical and common sense manner: Nesbit v Impro at 95; Minnesota Mining at 274. In Cleveland Graphite Bronze Co v Glacier Metal Co Ltd (1950) 67 RPC 149 at 154 it was said that the claims must be as precise "as the subject admits of". The fact that Dr Stark had no problems on first reading is of significance. It is not the role of an independent expert to seek out difficulties or to read a patent with, to borrow an expression from administrative law, "an eye keenly attuned to the perception of error": Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 322 ; (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287 quoted in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272. This episode reflects on Dr Stark's credibility as an independent expert. Generally I found Dr Stark lacked objectivity and detachment. He appeared keen to raise every conceivable argument in favour of the party which retained him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1971/3.html</AustLII>
<text>32 The claims must be fairly based on the matter described in the specification: Patents Act s 40(3). The body of the specification must provide a "real and reasonably clear disclosure" of the invention claimed: F Hoffman-La Roche &amp; Co v Commissioner of Patents [1971] HCA 3 ; (1971) 123 CLR 529 at 539; Lockwood 1 at [69].

33 GMCA submits that the claims are not fairly based. It says that the claims, in particular claim 1, are not limited to power saws but extend to all manner of power tools. They do not include "essential features" in the specification, viz the reciprocation frequency and stroke length ranges. They also refer to a "plurality" of positions whereas in fact there are only two.

34 Whatever may be the position in relation to claim 1, the claims from claim 3 onwards, and in particular the critical claim 6, are clearly confined to power saws.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Foggin v Lacey (2003) 57 IPR 225</tocase>
<text>115 The principles are stated by Gummow J in Wanem Pty Ltd v John Tekiela [1990] FCA 372 ; (1990) 19 IPR 435 at 440, cited with approval by the Full Court in Foggin v Lacey (2003) 57 IPR 225 at [13]. Gummow J said:
 ...(i) first impressions are important in determining whether there is an infringement of a design, (ii) an obvious imitation is one which is not the same as the registered design but is a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences, (iii) the question must be looked at as one of substance and by examining the essential features of the design, (iv) a closer correspondence between the registered design and the alleged infringing design is necessary to satisfy the test of obvious imitation than that of fraudulent imitation, (v) precise mathematical comparisons or matters of measurements or ratios, which form no part of the mental picture which the eye conveys to the brain of shape or configuration suggested by the design, are not to be applied as the test of infringement; appearance to the eye is the critical issue, and (vi) questions of infringement must not be determined by a narrow or overly technical approach in comparison between the design and the alleged infringement, lest the registration be sapped of its worth to the registered owner.

116 As the Full Court in Foggin noted, it is for the Court to rule on the meaning of the design and question of infringement as determined by reference to the eye of the consumer.

117 My first, and continuing, impression is that product B is significantly different in appearance from the Design. In particular the shank is quite different. What is in issue here is an everyday product. To the lay person this looks like a saw, obviously not a hand saw but one with some attachment in the shape of the shank. I regard this as more important than differences in angles and proportions. Put simply, the Design shows a saw blade with a shank; product B is a saw with a different sort of shank.

118 As might be expected experts on either side gave differing views. Professor Redmond thought that the dominant aspect of the Design was the blade and that product B was "closely similar, such that it has the same appeal to the eye as the design in the (Design)". He saw the shank as an "attachment device" but the saw blade was the "core or crucial visual element". The shank was "peripheral" or "of less significance". Nevertheless I think the ordinary consumer would see a panel saw blade as a piece of metal with teeth along the bottom and a sloping top. The shank is at one end, and thus is in a literal sense peripheral, but it is, and would be seen as, an integral and distinctive part of the article.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Co Ltd [1972] RPC 457</tocase>
<text>43 In the case of an anticipation in documentary form, the document must contain "clear and unmistakable directions to do what the patentee claims to have invented": General Tire &amp; Rubber Co v Firestone Tyre and Rubber Co Ltd [1972] RPC 457 at 486.

44 Although GMCA originally pleaded some 22 anticipations, by trial these had been reduced to 13. In final submissions only seven were relied on. The general comment can be made that although some of the devices could perhaps as a matter of physical possibility be used as a jigsaw there was no clear direction that this was their intended use.

45 This device was in evidence and is also described in the Bosch 1993/94 Catalogue. It is described as a "multisaw" and is pictured as being used in panel saw mode. There are photographs of various blade accessories such as a rasp, file and various brushes and also the statement: "In addition, the Bosch jigsaw accessory range is available for the multisaw".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Grant v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 69 IPR 221</tocase>
<text>27 Much of this argument overlapped with GMCA's case on description, utility, novelty and obviousness. To the extent that it did not, it must be rejected. The alleged invention did not involve an abstract idea, like that considered in Grant v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 69 IPR 221. It concerned machines and their operation and thus "something of a corporeal and substantial nature": R v Wheeler (1819) 2 B &amp; Ald 345 at 350, cited in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 72 IPR 447 at [66] ( Lockwood 2 ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Limited v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/8.html</AustLII>
<text>31 In any case, the specification does not put forward the "major vector element" as something "contribut(ing) to the achievement of the invention". The invention is not for a method of holding a power saw; it is for a power saw capable of fulfilling different functions. As already explained, the (perhaps overly scientific) term "vector" is but a word used in describing these two functions. The specification contains quite detailed explanations and diagrams of the preferred embodiment. There is no obligation on a patentee to describe more than a single preferred form of the invention. The ground of insufficiency is not made out merely because it is said there are other ways of carrying out the invention as to which the specification is not sufficiently precise: No-Fume Ltd v Frank Pitchford &amp; Co Ltd (1935) 52 RPC 231 at 248. The test is whether the disclosure in the specification will "enable the addressee to produce something within each claim without new inventions or additions or prolonged study of matters presenting initial difficulty": Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Limited v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1 at [25] . This requirement has been satisfied.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 72 IPR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/21.html</AustLII>
<text>27 Much of this argument overlapped with GMCA's case on description, utility, novelty and obviousness. To the extent that it did not, it must be rejected. The alleged invention did not involve an abstract idea, like that considered in Grant v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 69 IPR 221. It concerned machines and their operation and thus "something of a corporeal and substantial nature": R v Wheeler (1819) 2 B &amp; Ald 345 at 350, cited in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 72 IPR 447 at [66] ( Lockwood 2 ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/58.html</AustLII>
<text>30 GMCA say that the specification "does not explain how [counsel's emphasis] the major vector element contributes to the achievement of the invention (which is said to be a useful tool)". Reliance was placed on a passage in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 at [99] ( Lockwood 1 ). However, that passage is not in point. It is in the context of a fair basing argument and says that a claim cast in the form of a consistory clause is not fairly based if other parts of the specification show that the invention is narrower than that consistory clause. The inquiry, their Honours stress, is into what the body of the specification read as a whole discloses as the invention.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/9.html</AustLII>
<text>21 Claims must be construed in a practical, common sense manner, and are valid so long as they provide a workable standard suitable to the intended use: Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 at 273; Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56 at 95.

78 Claims must be determined in a practical and common sense manner: Nesbit v Impro at 95; Minnesota Mining at 274. In Cleveland Graphite Bronze Co v Glacier Metal Co Ltd (1950) 67 RPC 149 at 154 it was said that the claims must be as precise "as the subject admits of". The fact that Dr Stark had no problems on first reading is of significance. It is not the role of an independent expert to seek out difficulties or to read a patent with, to borrow an expression from administrative law, "an eye keenly attuned to the perception of error": Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 322 ; (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287 quoted in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272. This episode reflects on Dr Stark's credibility as an independent expert. Generally I found Dr Stark lacked objectivity and detachment. He appeared keen to raise every conceivable argument in favour of the party which retained him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56</tocase>
<text>21 Claims must be construed in a practical, common sense manner, and are valid so long as they provide a workable standard suitable to the intended use: Minnesota Mining &amp; Manufacturing Co v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253 at 273; Nesbit Evans Group Australia Pty Ltd v Impro Ltd (1997) 39 IPR 56 at 95.

78 Claims must be determined in a practical and common sense manner: Nesbit v Impro at 95; Minnesota Mining at 274. In Cleveland Graphite Bronze Co v Glacier Metal Co Ltd (1950) 67 RPC 149 at 154 it was said that the claims must be as precise "as the subject admits of". The fact that Dr Stark had no problems on first reading is of significance. It is not the role of an independent expert to seek out difficulties or to read a patent with, to borrow an expression from administrative law, "an eye keenly attuned to the perception of error": Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 322 ; (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287 quoted in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272. This episode reflects on Dr Stark's credibility as an independent expert. Generally I found Dr Stark lacked objectivity and detachment. He appeared keen to raise every conceivable argument in favour of the party which retained him.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nicaro Holdings Pty ltd v Martin Engineering Co (1990) 16 IPR 545</tocase>
<text>72 It is not in dispute that GMCA has offered for sale and sold in Australia two allegedly infringing products, referred to in this case as T1 and T2. Black &amp; Decker has to show that the GMCA products take each and every essential integer of the claims relied on (claims 1 and 3 to 8 of the Standard Patent): Nicaro Holdings Pty ltd v Martin Engineering Co (1990) 16 IPR 545 at 559-560.

73 A photograph of T1:

74 The only integers in contest are those designated 1.8 and 1.9 in claim 1 of the Patent. Integer 1.8 it will be recalled is as follows (emphasis added):
 and wherein the handle is positioned such that a force applied thereto by the user in a first of the said plurality of positions comprises a major vector transmitted along a line of action extending substantially parallel to the line of linear reciprocation. 
Integer 1.9 is in the same terms save only that the word "parallel" is replaced by the word "transverse". These integers obviously relate to the operation of the device in its panel saw (integer 1.8) and jigsaw (integer 1.9) modes.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>No-Fume Ltd v Frank Pitchford &amp; Co Ltd (1935) 52 RPC 231</tocase>
<text>31 In any case, the specification does not put forward the "major vector element" as something "contribut(ing) to the achievement of the invention". The invention is not for a method of holding a power saw; it is for a power saw capable of fulfilling different functions. As already explained, the (perhaps overly scientific) term "vector" is but a word used in describing these two functions. The specification contains quite detailed explanations and diagrams of the preferred embodiment. There is no obligation on a patentee to describe more than a single preferred form of the invention. The ground of insufficiency is not made out merely because it is said there are other ways of carrying out the invention as to which the specification is not sufficiently precise: No-Fume Ltd v Frank Pitchford &amp; Co Ltd (1935) 52 RPC 231 at 248. The test is whether the disclosure in the specification will "enable the addressee to produce something within each claim without new inventions or additions or prolonged study of matters presenting initial difficulty": Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Limited v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1 at [25] . This requirement has been satisfied.

35 The reciprocation frequency and stroke length ranges are matters of guidance for the skilled addressee. They are not essential to the working of the claimed invention. As Maugham LJ said in No-Fume at 248, the specification does not have to define
 ... all the proportions, or all the dimensions, or all the temperatures, or all the materials which would give a similar or like result.

36 The preferred embodiment makes it clear that only two uses are disclosed.

37 The invention, so far is claimed in any claim, must be useful: Patents Act s 18(1)(c). This means that the invention as claimed must produce the desired result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/32.html</AustLII>
<text>113 In Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd [2005] HCA 32 ; (2005) 221 CLR 287 the High Court considered the concept of fraudulent imitation under the 1906 Act. Their Honours held (at [36]) that in order to find a fraudulent imitation it was not necessary to show that the differences between alleged infringement and design had been made to disguise the copying. In this respect their Honours at [28] qualified the statement in Malleys Limited v J W Tomlin Pty Ltd [1961] HCA 77 ; (1961) 180 CLR 120 at 127. In Polyaire their Honours at [17] accepted the submission
 that the application of a "fraudulent imitation" requires that the application of the design be with knowledge of the existence of the registration and of the absence of consent to its use, or with reason to suspect those matters, and that the use of the design produces what is an "imitation" within the meaning of para (a) [of s 30(1)]. This... is the knowledge, belief or intent which renders the conduct fraudulent. 
In a footnote to that passage their Honours say:
 See as to the permissible inference by a jury of fraud against a party who "wilfully shuts his eyes" the judgment of Lord Esher MR in English and Scottish Mercantile Investment Co Ltd v Brunton [1892] 2 QB 700 at 707-708.

114 As the submissions of Black &amp; Decker appear to accept, the knowledge, belief or intent which does or does not render the conduct fraudulent is that of the Chinese manufacturer. It is the manufacturer who is said to have "applied" the Design outside Australia. I see no reason to disbelieve the evidence of Mr Coates. It seems inherently unlikely that the Chinese manufacturer had knowledge of the Australian Designs Act; still less that the Design was registered under it. There is no basis for finding that the manufacturer had reason to suspect such registration. The onus on Black &amp; Decker to establish fraudulent imitation has not been discharged.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Wheeler (1819) 2 B &amp; Ald 345</tocase>
<text>27 Much of this argument overlapped with GMCA's case on description, utility, novelty and obviousness. To the extent that it did not, it must be rejected. The alleged invention did not involve an abstract idea, like that considered in Grant v Commissioner of Patents (2006) 69 IPR 221. It concerned machines and their operation and thus "something of a corporeal and substantial nature": R v Wheeler (1819) 2 B &amp; Ald 345 at 350, cited in Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd v Doric Products Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] HCA 21 ; (2007) 72 IPR 447 at [66] ( Lockwood 2 ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royal British Bank v Turquand (1856) 6 E &amp; B 327</tocase>
<text>144 However, s 127(1) is not mandatory. Section 127(4) provides that the section does not limit the ways in which a company may execute a document (including a deed). As to authority to execute, persons dealing with BDA, including BDI, were entitled to assume that the company's constitution had been complied with and that a director had been duly appointed and had authority to exercise the powers customarily performed by a director of a similar company: s 129(1) , (3), the statutory equivalent of the Rule in Turquand's Case ( Royal British Bank v Turquand (1856) 6 E &amp; B 327). Section 128(1) provides that a person is entitled to make the assumptions in s 129 and a person is not entitled to make an assumption under s 129 if they knew the assumption was incorrect. While there is no evidence in the present case as to the powers of a director of a similar company to BDA, the onus is on GMCA to establish the contrary. In any event, it seems inherently likely that a director of a company similar to BDA, a wholly owned subsidiary of an overseas company, would have authority to execute on the company's behalf a document of the kind executed by Ms Armstrong. A degree of informality is to be expected. The reality is that Ms Armstrong was not, in the time-honoured expression, engaged on a frolic of her own.

145 In relation to BDI, Mr Pratt was authorized, by virtue of his office, to execute the Deed. The Deed was clearly in the ordinary course of business of BDI in that it dealt with the licensing of intellectual property, which seems to have been BDI's only business.

146 Black &amp; Decker's case is that because the December 2006 Deed made the March 2006 letter of termination "null and void ab initio", the 1987 Agreement, as varied by the 2005 Deed, continued uninterrupted. As a consequence, BDA is to be treated as having the status of exclusive licensee from at least the date of the 2005 Deed (its case that such status existed from the 1987 Agreement has been rejected for the reasons already given).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stack v Brisbane City Council (1996) 35 IPR 296</tocase>
<text>147 However, statutory rights to damages or an account of profits conferred on owners or exclusive licensees of intellectual property only have effect for the period that a plaintiff in fact has the relevant status. Thus in Colbeam Palmer Ltd v Stock Affiliates Pty Ltd [1968] HCA 50 ; (1968) 122 CLR 25 Windeyer J held (at 36) that an account of profits should be taken to terminate as at the date the plaintiff assigned the trade mark in question and (at 41) that the assignee, having been joined as a plaintiff, should be entitled to an account of profits from the date of assignment. Similarly in Stack v Brisbane City Council (1996) 35 IPR 296 at 302 Drummond J held that where an equitable title had been converted into legal title by assignment, the assignor would have the right to an account of profits made by the infringers in the period up to the assignment and that the assignee alone would have the right to any profits made by the infringers after that date. Likewise, if an election were made for damages the assignee
 is the proper claimant for that relief, but only as from the date its equitable ownership became converted by registration into full legal and beneficial ownership of the patent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ullrich Aluminium Pty Ltd v Dias Aluminium Products Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 119 ; (2006) 153 FCR 437</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/119.html</AustLII>
<text>104 Section 17 of the Designs Act 1906 requires that a design be new or original to enable it to be registered. It must be "substantially novel or substantially original, having regard to the nature of the article to which the design is applied": Ullrich Aluminium Pty Ltd v Dias Aluminium Products Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 119 ; (2006) 153 FCR 437 at [3] . GMCA's expert Mr Brown considered nine prior saw blades as follows:
 (i) Canadian Patent No. 636160; (ii) US Patent No. 3,802,079; (iii) US Patent No. 2,621,689; (iv) Extract from "Popular Mechanics Encyclopaedia of Tools and Techniques" by Oldham, 1994, page 132; (v) "Power Hand Tool Handbook", pages 40 41, 1980 by Case; (vi) Bourke Patent US No. 5,755,293; (vii) Black &amp; Decker European Patent No. 0949 032; (viii) pages 94, 95 and 106 from "The Complete Book of Tools" by Jackson and Day; (ix) Disston No. 12 and D23 lightweight saws.

105 With the exception of the Disston saw blades all of these references were provided to Mr Brown by GMCA's solicitors. None of the references contain a blade with a notch at the front or the same shape as the Design. The Disston blades lack the notch at the front of the Design and any shank at the rear and an angled front edge.

106 Black &amp; Decker's expert Professor Redmond considered the references and was of the view that none were substantially similar visually to the Design. In my view none of the references showed blades which were substantially similar visually to the Design.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wanem Pty Ltd v John Tekiela [1990] FCA 372 ; (1990) 19 IPR 435</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1990/372.html</AustLII>
<text>115 The principles are stated by Gummow J in Wanem Pty Ltd v John Tekiela [1990] FCA 372 ; (1990) 19 IPR 435 at 440, cited with approval by the Full Court in Foggin v Lacey (2003) 57 IPR 225 at [13]. Gummow J said:
 ...(i) first impressions are important in determining whether there is an infringement of a design, (ii) an obvious imitation is one which is not the same as the registered design but is a copy apparent to the eye notwithstanding slight differences, (iii) the question must be looked at as one of substance and by examining the essential features of the design, (iv) a closer correspondence between the registered design and the alleged infringing design is necessary to satisfy the test of obvious imitation than that of fraudulent imitation, (v) precise mathematical comparisons or matters of measurements or ratios, which form no part of the mental picture which the eye conveys to the brain of shape or configuration suggested by the design, are not to be applied as the test of infringement; appearance to the eye is the critical issue, and (vi) questions of infringement must not be determined by a narrow or overly technical approach in comparison between the design and the alleged infringement, lest the registration be sapped of its worth to the registered owner.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>