<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hostworks Group Limited ACN 008 010 820, in the matter of Hostworks Group Limited ACN 008 010 820 [2008] FCA 64 (12 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/64.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Sonodyne International Limited (1994) 15 ACSR 494</tocase>
<text>15 It is, of course, clear that the Court's role on this application is not to pass a final view on whether the proposed scheme should be approved, either by the members at the proposed meeting, or then by the Court under s 411(4)(d). The decision must first await the will of the members to be expressed at the scheme meeting. Assuming the members support the proposed scheme, when the Court is then called upon to approve it, dissenting members or other interested parties will have the opportunity to oppose the Court's granting approval: Re Sonodyne International Limited (1994) 15 ACSR 494 at 497 per Hayne J.

16 However, the authorities indicate that, at this point, the Court should review the proposed scheme and the proposed explanatory statement, and may invite the plaintiff company to attend to any matters which seemed to the Court to require attention before the distribution of the documents.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>FT Eastment &amp; Sons Pty Ltd v Metal Roof Decking Supplies Pty Ltd (1977) 3 ACLR 69</tocase>
<text>17 In FT Eastment &amp; Sons Pty Ltd v Metal Roof Decking Supplies Pty Ltd (1977) 3 ACLR 69 at 72, Street CJ said:
 
 [T]he court will not ordinarily summon a meeting unless the scheme is of such a nature and cast in such terms, if it achieves the statutory majority at the creditor's meeting [in this case, the members' meeting] the court would be likely to approve it on the hearing of a petition which is unopposed.
 

That passage was cited with approval by the High Court in Australian Securities Commission v Marlborough Goldmines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485, and has been followed in many decisions since, including recently Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 per Robson J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Marlborough Goldmines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/15.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In FT Eastment &amp; Sons Pty Ltd v Metal Roof Decking Supplies Pty Ltd (1977) 3 ACLR 69 at 72, Street CJ said:
 
 [T]he court will not ordinarily summon a meeting unless the scheme is of such a nature and cast in such terms, if it achieves the statutory majority at the creditor's meeting [in this case, the members' meeting] the court would be likely to approve it on the hearing of a petition which is unopposed.
 

That passage was cited with approval by the High Court in Australian Securities Commission v Marlborough Goldmines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485, and has been followed in many decisions since, including recently Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 per Robson J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re NRMA Ltd [2000] NSWSC 82 ; (2000) 33 ACSR 595</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2000/82.html</AustLII>
<text>18 The Court's task when considering the convening of a proposed scheme meeting under s 411(1) of the Act was described by Santow J in Re NRMA Ltd [2000] NSWSC 82 ; (2000) 33 ACSR 595 at [3] as follows:
 
 The Court must be satisfied, at least at a prima facie level, as to the legality of what it proposed, that there has been proper disclosure with nothing misleading or deceptive in any material sense and that the scheme will, if and when approved by members, be likely then to be approved by the Court as being "so far fair and reasonable as an intelligent and honest man" may approve. It is not for the Court otherwise to be concerned with the merits of the proposal or to inhibit consideration by members so that they can form their own judgment whether to vote for or against.

19 Obviously, one focus of the Court in fulfilling that task is to ensure that there is sufficient disclosure to those who may be affected by the proposed scheme of its details and effect: see Re Central Pacific Minerals NL [2002] FCA 239. In that case, Emmett J at [9] said that, amongst the factors to which the Court should have regard in exercising its discretion whether to convene a meeting, were the acceptability of the documentation of the proposed scheme; the commercial viability and morality of the proposed scheme; the likely acceptability of the proposed scheme; the bona fides of the proposals; whether the proposal could be achieved by another method; and any objections or submissions by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC). Both Conti J in Re CSR Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 34 at 36-37 and Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [38] referred to those criteria with approval, and as conforming with the observations of Santow J in Re NRMA Limited [2000] NSWSC 82 ; 33 ACSR 595 referred to.

20 I therefore turn to consider the matters of which I had to be satisfied before making an order convening the proposed scheme meeting. The first is that there has been proper disclosure in the proposed explanatory statement as required by s 411(3) of the Act: see Re NRMA Limited [2000] NSWSC 82 ; 33 ACSR 595 at [15] - [49] . The explanatory statement must explain the effect of the proposed arrangement and set out any information that is material to the making of a decision by a member or members to approve or not to approve the proposed scheme. Section 411(3A) in effect requires a statement of all the main facts which will enable shareholders to exercise their judgment whether to support the proposed scheme. I carefully considered the proposed scheme. In my view, adopting the words in s 411(3)(a), the explanatory statement does explain the effect of the proposed scheme, including in particular stating the material interests of the directors of Hostworks, and the effect on those interests of the proposed scheme. On the material, its effect on them is no different from the effect on other members of Hostworks.

21 Section 411(3) requires the explanatory statement to set out the prescribed information, and other information that is material to the making of a decision by a member of Hostworks whether or not to agree to the proposed scheme. Regulation 5.1.01(1) of the Corporation Regulations 2001 (Cth) (the Regulations) provides that, unless ASIC otherwise allows, the explanatory statement must state the matters set out in Pt 3 of Sch 8 to the Regulations and have annexed to it the reports and copies of the documents mentioned. There is nothing to indicate that ASIC has agreed that less information than that prescribed should be provided. I considered each of the pieces of information prescribed in Pt 3 of Sch 8 to the Regulations to determine whether they are contained within the proposed explanatory statement. I will not go through them seriatim. In my view, they are each apparently covered by material in the explanatory statement.

22 In reaching that view, I was assisted by the schedule provided in the written submissions of counsel for Hostworks in which each of the requirements of ss 411 and 412 and Pt 3 of Sch 8 of the Regulations are set out and cross-referenced to the relevant parts of the explanatory memorandum or other materials. There is also evidence from Hostworks that a process of verification was undertaken in relation to each of those pieces of information to ensure that it is accurately reported in or with the explanatory memorandum.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Central Pacific Minerals NL [2002] FCA 239</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2002/239.html</AustLII>
<text>19 Obviously, one focus of the Court in fulfilling that task is to ensure that there is sufficient disclosure to those who may be affected by the proposed scheme of its details and effect: see Re Central Pacific Minerals NL [2002] FCA 239. In that case, Emmett J at [9] said that, amongst the factors to which the Court should have regard in exercising its discretion whether to convene a meeting, were the acceptability of the documentation of the proposed scheme; the commercial viability and morality of the proposed scheme; the likely acceptability of the proposed scheme; the bona fides of the proposals; whether the proposal could be achieved by another method; and any objections or submissions by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC). Both Conti J in Re CSR Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 34 at 36-37 and Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [38] referred to those criteria with approval, and as conforming with the observations of Santow J in Re NRMA Limited [2000] NSWSC 82 ; 33 ACSR 595 referred to.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re CSR Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 34</tocase>
<text>19 Obviously, one focus of the Court in fulfilling that task is to ensure that there is sufficient disclosure to those who may be affected by the proposed scheme of its details and effect: see Re Central Pacific Minerals NL [2002] FCA 239. In that case, Emmett J at [9] said that, amongst the factors to which the Court should have regard in exercising its discretion whether to convene a meeting, were the acceptability of the documentation of the proposed scheme; the commercial viability and morality of the proposed scheme; the likely acceptability of the proposed scheme; the bona fides of the proposals; whether the proposal could be achieved by another method; and any objections or submissions by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC). Both Conti J in Re CSR Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 34 at 36-37 and Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [38] referred to those criteria with approval, and as conforming with the observations of Santow J in Re NRMA Limited [2000] NSWSC 82 ; 33 ACSR 595 referred to.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1582.html</AustLII>
<text>19 Obviously, one focus of the Court in fulfilling that task is to ensure that there is sufficient disclosure to those who may be affected by the proposed scheme of its details and effect: see Re Central Pacific Minerals NL [2002] FCA 239. In that case, Emmett J at [9] said that, amongst the factors to which the Court should have regard in exercising its discretion whether to convene a meeting, were the acceptability of the documentation of the proposed scheme; the commercial viability and morality of the proposed scheme; the likely acceptability of the proposed scheme; the bona fides of the proposals; whether the proposal could be achieved by another method; and any objections or submissions by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC). Both Conti J in Re CSR Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 34 at 36-37 and Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [38] referred to those criteria with approval, and as conforming with the observations of Santow J in Re NRMA Limited [2000] NSWSC 82 ; 33 ACSR 595 referred to.

41 Under cl 7.3(a) of the Implementation Agreement, each scheme participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its shares in Hostworks which are transferred under the scheme will be free from all mortgages and encumbrances. Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207, regarded an almost identical deemed warranty clause as onerous and unreasonable and "calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty": at [21]. In Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J disagreed with the approach of Fryberg J: see at [59]-[62]. I respectfully agree with and adopt the views of Lindgren J. I share the understanding of his Honour that the purpose and effect of such a clause is simply to ensure that a scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty would be equal to the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. I note that the approach of Lindgren J has been preferred in subsequent cases, including by Robson J in Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 at [45] ; by Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [33] ; and by Gyles J in Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389 at [9] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207</tocase>
<text>26 Section 411 further requires that the Court is satisfied that the scheme can properly be described as a compromise or arrangement so as to come within its ambit. The word "arrangement" has been held to be a word of wide import, not limited by its relationship or the expression "compromise". An arrangement may extend to any subject matter which is something which a company is able to agree with its members, and is likened to a contract between a company and its members. As noted earlier, there have been a number of cases in which a scheme involving the acquisition of a company's issued capital for cash, so that the company becomes a wholly owned subsidiary of an acquiring entity, is a common use of the Pt 5.1 procedure. See also e.g. Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207; and Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd (2007) 62 ACSR 400.

41 Under cl 7.3(a) of the Implementation Agreement, each scheme participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its shares in Hostworks which are transferred under the scheme will be free from all mortgages and encumbrances. Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207, regarded an almost identical deemed warranty clause as onerous and unreasonable and "calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty": at [21]. In Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J disagreed with the approach of Fryberg J: see at [59]-[62]. I respectfully agree with and adopt the views of Lindgren J. I share the understanding of his Honour that the purpose and effect of such a clause is simply to ensure that a scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty would be equal to the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. I note that the approach of Lindgren J has been preferred in subsequent cases, including by Robson J in Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 at [45] ; by Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [33] ; and by Gyles J in Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389 at [9] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd (2007) 62 ACSR 400</tocase>
<text>26 Section 411 further requires that the Court is satisfied that the scheme can properly be described as a compromise or arrangement so as to come within its ambit. The word "arrangement" has been held to be a word of wide import, not limited by its relationship or the expression "compromise". An arrangement may extend to any subject matter which is something which a company is able to agree with its members, and is likened to a contract between a company and its members. As noted earlier, there have been a number of cases in which a scheme involving the acquisition of a company's issued capital for cash, so that the company becomes a wholly owned subsidiary of an acquiring entity, is a common use of the Pt 5.1 procedure. See also e.g. Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207; and Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd (2007) 62 ACSR 400.

31 In Re APN News Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J discussed at some length aspects of the proposed scheme then under consideration which may be described as performance risk; "no-shop" and "no-talk" restrictions; break fee; and a deemed warranty by the members of the target company. Each of those features is present in the proposed scheme. It is appropriate to consider them each in turn.

32 The performance risk concern has been raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications. They are referred to by Lindgren J in Re APN News 62 ACSR 400 at [23]. I will not repeat them. It is necessary to consider the so called "performance risk" of shareholders being left in a position, once the scheme has become effective, of their shares having been transferred to Broadcast Australia, but then facing a delay in the provision of the scheme consideration, so that their only remedy would be to sue on the Deed Poll. That risk has been overcome here by requiring the scheme consideration to be paid to Hostworks before 12 noon on the "implementation date" to be held in trust by Hostworks for the purpose of being paid to the scheme participants, that is the shareholders of Hostworks, before they are divested of their shares in Hostworks later on in the implementation date. Broadcast Australia must provide the funds to pay for the shares it is to acquire before they are transferred. A similar arrangement was satisfactory to Robson J for the purposes of authorising or directing the calling of the proposed meeting in Re Coles Group [2007] VSC 389 ; see at [38]. The Deed Poll contains a covenant on the part of Broadcast Australia to provide the scheme consideration on the implementation date in accordance with the terms of the scheme so that it ties the settlement step of payment and transfer together.

41 Under cl 7.3(a) of the Implementation Agreement, each scheme participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its shares in Hostworks which are transferred under the scheme will be free from all mortgages and encumbrances. Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207, regarded an almost identical deemed warranty clause as onerous and unreasonable and "calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty": at [21]. In Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J disagreed with the approach of Fryberg J: see at [59]-[62]. I respectfully agree with and adopt the views of Lindgren J. I share the understanding of his Honour that the purpose and effect of such a clause is simply to ensure that a scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty would be equal to the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. I note that the approach of Lindgren J has been preferred in subsequent cases, including by Robson J in Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 at [45] ; by Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [33] ; and by Gyles J in Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389 at [9] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Promentum Limited [2007] FCA 446</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/446.html</AustLII>
<text>27 
 
Generally, there is no apparent reason, at this stage, and on the material now before me, to consider that the proposed scheme is improper. The independent expert's report has assessed the offer to be fair and reasonable and in the best interests of the shareholders of Hostworks in the absence of an alternative offer on better terms. The evidence indicates that the offer made by Broadcast Australia is at the upper range of the valuation of shares in Hostworks made by the independent expert, and is considerably in excess of any listed share price in the recent past. There is nothing to suggest that the scheme works unfairly as between members of Hostworks, or that in any other respect the directors of Hostworks or others associated with it, or with Broadcast Australia, will profit to the detriment of the members of Hostworks, or that they will profit differently from the other members of Hostworks. Consequently, if the proposed scheme is supported at the proposed meeting of shareholders of Hostworks, at present, there does not appear to be any reason why the scheme then would not be approved. That seems to be a test, perhaps even put at a slightly higher level than necessary, to determine whether the proposed scheme is a proper one: see e.g. Re Promentum Limited [2007] FCA 446 at [13] ; IOR Friendly Society Ltd v IOR Group Ltd (2007) FCA 970 at [28] ; Re CCI Holdings Limited [2007] FCA 832 at [21] ; and Re Gloucester Coal Ltd [2007] FCA 1017 at [28] . Later in these reasons, I refer to particular features of the arrangement as contained in the Implementation Deed and the Deed Poll which warrant specific comment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>IOR Friendly Society Ltd v IOR Group Ltd (2007) FCA 970</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/970.html</AustLII>
<text>27 
 
Generally, there is no apparent reason, at this stage, and on the material now before me, to consider that the proposed scheme is improper. The independent expert's report has assessed the offer to be fair and reasonable and in the best interests of the shareholders of Hostworks in the absence of an alternative offer on better terms. The evidence indicates that the offer made by Broadcast Australia is at the upper range of the valuation of shares in Hostworks made by the independent expert, and is considerably in excess of any listed share price in the recent past. There is nothing to suggest that the scheme works unfairly as between members of Hostworks, or that in any other respect the directors of Hostworks or others associated with it, or with Broadcast Australia, will profit to the detriment of the members of Hostworks, or that they will profit differently from the other members of Hostworks. Consequently, if the proposed scheme is supported at the proposed meeting of shareholders of Hostworks, at present, there does not appear to be any reason why the scheme then would not be approved. That seems to be a test, perhaps even put at a slightly higher level than necessary, to determine whether the proposed scheme is a proper one: see e.g. Re Promentum Limited [2007] FCA 446 at [13] ; IOR Friendly Society Ltd v IOR Group Ltd (2007) FCA 970 at [28] ; Re CCI Holdings Limited [2007] FCA 832 at [21] ; and Re Gloucester Coal Ltd [2007] FCA 1017 at [28] . Later in these reasons, I refer to particular features of the arrangement as contained in the Implementation Deed and the Deed Poll which warrant specific comment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re CCI Holdings Limited [2007] FCA 832</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/832.html</AustLII>
<text>27 
 
Generally, there is no apparent reason, at this stage, and on the material now before me, to consider that the proposed scheme is improper. The independent expert's report has assessed the offer to be fair and reasonable and in the best interests of the shareholders of Hostworks in the absence of an alternative offer on better terms. The evidence indicates that the offer made by Broadcast Australia is at the upper range of the valuation of shares in Hostworks made by the independent expert, and is considerably in excess of any listed share price in the recent past. There is nothing to suggest that the scheme works unfairly as between members of Hostworks, or that in any other respect the directors of Hostworks or others associated with it, or with Broadcast Australia, will profit to the detriment of the members of Hostworks, or that they will profit differently from the other members of Hostworks. Consequently, if the proposed scheme is supported at the proposed meeting of shareholders of Hostworks, at present, there does not appear to be any reason why the scheme then would not be approved. That seems to be a test, perhaps even put at a slightly higher level than necessary, to determine whether the proposed scheme is a proper one: see e.g. Re Promentum Limited [2007] FCA 446 at [13] ; IOR Friendly Society Ltd v IOR Group Ltd (2007) FCA 970 at [28] ; Re CCI Holdings Limited [2007] FCA 832 at [21] ; and Re Gloucester Coal Ltd [2007] FCA 1017 at [28] . Later in these reasons, I refer to particular features of the arrangement as contained in the Implementation Deed and the Deed Poll which warrant specific comment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Gloucester Coal Ltd [2007] FCA 1017</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1017.html</AustLII>
<text>27 
 
Generally, there is no apparent reason, at this stage, and on the material now before me, to consider that the proposed scheme is improper. The independent expert's report has assessed the offer to be fair and reasonable and in the best interests of the shareholders of Hostworks in the absence of an alternative offer on better terms. The evidence indicates that the offer made by Broadcast Australia is at the upper range of the valuation of shares in Hostworks made by the independent expert, and is considerably in excess of any listed share price in the recent past. There is nothing to suggest that the scheme works unfairly as between members of Hostworks, or that in any other respect the directors of Hostworks or others associated with it, or with Broadcast Australia, will profit to the detriment of the members of Hostworks, or that they will profit differently from the other members of Hostworks. Consequently, if the proposed scheme is supported at the proposed meeting of shareholders of Hostworks, at present, there does not appear to be any reason why the scheme then would not be approved. That seems to be a test, perhaps even put at a slightly higher level than necessary, to determine whether the proposed scheme is a proper one: see e.g. Re Promentum Limited [2007] FCA 446 at [13] ; IOR Friendly Society Ltd v IOR Group Ltd (2007) FCA 970 at [28] ; Re CCI Holdings Limited [2007] FCA 832 at [21] ; and Re Gloucester Coal Ltd [2007] FCA 1017 at [28] . Later in these reasons, I refer to particular features of the arrangement as contained in the Implementation Deed and the Deed Poll which warrant specific comment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Coles Group Ltd [2007] VSC 389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSC/2007/389.html</AustLII>
<text>17 In FT Eastment &amp; Sons Pty Ltd v Metal Roof Decking Supplies Pty Ltd (1977) 3 ACLR 69 at 72, Street CJ said:
 
 [T]he court will not ordinarily summon a meeting unless the scheme is of such a nature and cast in such terms, if it achieves the statutory majority at the creditor's meeting [in this case, the members' meeting] the court would be likely to approve it on the hearing of a petition which is unopposed.
 

That passage was cited with approval by the High Court in Australian Securities Commission v Marlborough Goldmines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485, and has been followed in many decisions since, including recently Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 per Robson J.

30 There may be some difference of opinion, or perhaps only of emphasis, between the views of Robson J in Re Coles Group Ltd [2007] VSC 389 and Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (2007) 61 ACSR 266 as to whether it is necessary to consider s 411(17) at the first stage of the two stage process for the Court to direct the meeting and then, after the scheme is voted upon, to approve it. If that consideration is relevant at this point, that is whether there is a likelihood (or prospect) of s 411(17) being satisfied at first stage, I have the necessary level of satisfaction at this point and on the material referred to. The provisional view of ASIC referred to above indicates that there is a prospect of it producing to the Court the form of statement referred to in s 411(17)(b), although of course the Court then clearly is not obliged to approve the proposed scheme. Alternatively, on the information presently available to me, as I have indicated, I do not see a reason why, if the members of Hostworks at the proposed meeting of the scheme support the proposed scheme, I would not be satisfied that the scheme has not been proposed for the purpose of enabling any person to avoid the operation of any of the provisions of Chapter 6. That must necessarily be only a tentative and provisional judgment. However, it is accepted, as is now commonplace, that in circumstances such as the present, an entity such as Hostworks has a choice between following the takeover procedure in Chapter 6 in conjunction with Broadcast Australia or following the scheme of arrangement procedure supported by inter partes documentary agreements as contemplated by Pt 5.1 of Chapter 5 of the Act. Consequently, the mere choice of the procedure now being adopted is not an indication that a purpose of this procedure is to enable any person to avoid the operation of any provisions of Chapter 6. There will thus need to be some identification of which provision or provisions of Chapter 6 might relevantly operate so as to produce potentially a different outcome to that which would follow from the present procedure and an exploration of why the Pt 5.1 procedure has been used having regard to that provision or those provisions if s 411(17)(a) is to be enlivened. Such consideration may also be relevant to the discretion of the Court under s 411(17) if ASIC has provided a statement under s 411(17)(b). No such provision has presently been identified.

32 The performance risk concern has been raised in previous scheme of arrangement applications. They are referred to by Lindgren J in Re APN News 62 ACSR 400 at [23]. I will not repeat them. It is necessary to consider the so called "performance risk" of shareholders being left in a position, once the scheme has become effective, of their shares having been transferred to Broadcast Australia, but then facing a delay in the provision of the scheme consideration, so that their only remedy would be to sue on the Deed Poll. That risk has been overcome here by requiring the scheme consideration to be paid to Hostworks before 12 noon on the "implementation date" to be held in trust by Hostworks for the purpose of being paid to the scheme participants, that is the shareholders of Hostworks, before they are divested of their shares in Hostworks later on in the implementation date. Broadcast Australia must provide the funds to pay for the shares it is to acquire before they are transferred. A similar arrangement was satisfactory to Robson J for the purposes of authorising or directing the calling of the proposed meeting in Re Coles Group [2007] VSC 389 ; see at [38]. The Deed Poll contains a covenant on the part of Broadcast Australia to provide the scheme consideration on the implementation date in accordance with the terms of the scheme so that it ties the settlement step of payment and transfer together.

41 Under cl 7.3(a) of the Implementation Agreement, each scheme participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its shares in Hostworks which are transferred under the scheme will be free from all mortgages and encumbrances. Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207, regarded an almost identical deemed warranty clause as onerous and unreasonable and "calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty": at [21]. In Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J disagreed with the approach of Fryberg J: see at [59]-[62]. I respectfully agree with and adopt the views of Lindgren J. I share the understanding of his Honour that the purpose and effect of such a clause is simply to ensure that a scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty would be equal to the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. I note that the approach of Lindgren J has been preferred in subsequent cases, including by Robson J in Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 at [45] ; by Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [33] ; and by Gyles J in Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389 at [9] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Mincom Ltd (2007) 61 ACSR 266</tocase>
<text>30 There may be some difference of opinion, or perhaps only of emphasis, between the views of Robson J in Re Coles Group Ltd [2007] VSC 389 and Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (2007) 61 ACSR 266 as to whether it is necessary to consider s 411(17) at the first stage of the two stage process for the Court to direct the meeting and then, after the scheme is voted upon, to approve it. If that consideration is relevant at this point, that is whether there is a likelihood (or prospect) of s 411(17) being satisfied at first stage, I have the necessary level of satisfaction at this point and on the material referred to. The provisional view of ASIC referred to above indicates that there is a prospect of it producing to the Court the form of statement referred to in s 411(17)(b), although of course the Court then clearly is not obliged to approve the proposed scheme. Alternatively, on the information presently available to me, as I have indicated, I do not see a reason why, if the members of Hostworks at the proposed meeting of the scheme support the proposed scheme, I would not be satisfied that the scheme has not been proposed for the purpose of enabling any person to avoid the operation of any of the provisions of Chapter 6. That must necessarily be only a tentative and provisional judgment. However, it is accepted, as is now commonplace, that in circumstances such as the present, an entity such as Hostworks has a choice between following the takeover procedure in Chapter 6 in conjunction with Broadcast Australia or following the scheme of arrangement procedure supported by inter partes documentary agreements as contemplated by Pt 5.1 of Chapter 5 of the Act. Consequently, the mere choice of the procedure now being adopted is not an indication that a purpose of this procedure is to enable any person to avoid the operation of any provisions of Chapter 6. There will thus need to be some identification of which provision or provisions of Chapter 6 might relevantly operate so as to produce potentially a different outcome to that which would follow from the present procedure and an exploration of why the Pt 5.1 procedure has been used having regard to that provision or those provisions if s 411(17)(a) is to be enlivened. Such consideration may also be relevant to the discretion of the Court under s 411(17) if ASIC has provided a statement under s 411(17)(b). No such provision has presently been identified.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Re Arthur Yates and Co Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 758</tocase>
<text>33 Clauses 10.1 and 10.2 of the Implementation Agreement contain "no-shop" and "no-talk" provisions during the "exclusivity period", defined as the period from the date of the Implementation Agreement to the "sunset date" or the date when the agreement is earlier terminated. The sunset date is 31 May 2008. During that period, Hostworks is obliged to ensure that neither it nor its representatives directly or indirectly solicits or invites any discussions in relation to, or which may reasonably be expected to lead to, a competing transaction, that is defined as any expression of interest, proposal or offer by a third party to evaluate or enter into any transaction similar to the proposed scheme or by which a person would acquire an interest in 10% or more of the issued shares in Hostworks or engage in other like transactions. During the same period, under the "no-talk" provision, Hostworks is to ensure that neither it nor its representatives negotiates with any persons in relation to, or which might reasonably be expected to lead to, a competing transaction, even if it was not solicited or initiated by Hostworks in any way. It is also obliged under cl 10.3 to ensure that neither it nor any of its representatives in relation to a competing transaction, facilitates any other party undertaking due diligence investigations in relation to Hostworks, or makes any non-public information relating to Hostworks available to any such person. Because such clauses provoke obvious concerns as to the directors' potential breach of fiduciary duty or statutory obligations by entering into such agreements, cl 10.7 contains what is called "fiduciary and other carve-out" provisions. It provides that the restrictions in cl 10.2 and cl 10.3 do not apply to the extent that, in response to an approach by a third party, Hostworks informs the third party that it can only participate in negotiations or discussions with that third party if the third party proposes a competing transaction of a certain quality. If a competing transaction is then made which meets certain criteria, and if Hostworks' directors determine in good faith and acting reasonably that failing to respond to a bona fide competing transaction would "more likely than not" constitute a breach of their fiduciary or statutory obligations, they are not bound to comply with cl 10.2 or cl 10.3. Before that carve-out operates, the directors of Hostworks must be satisfied that the competing transaction is bona fide and in writing by a reputable entity, and they must have determined in good faith and acting reasonably (after independent advice) that the competing transaction is capable of being valued and completed, and is of a higher value to Hostworks and its shareholders than the proposed scheme. They must also have received written advice from Hostworks' external legal adviser that failing to respond to such a bona fide competing transaction would more likely than not constitute a breach of the independent directors' fiduciary duties or statutory obligations. In Re Arthur Yates and Co Ltd (2001) 36 ACSR 758, Santow J expressed the view that no-talk provisions should satisfy certain particular concerns, at [9] which Lindgren J in Re APN News Ltd 62 ACSR 400 at [29] described in the following terms:
 
 
 (a) it should be for no more than a reasonable period capable of precise ascertainment; 
 
 
 
 
 
 (b) while it may differentiate between actively soliciting an alternative merger proposal and simply dealing with an unsolicited one, in either case the provision should be framed so that it is subject to the overriding obligation not to breach the directors' fiduciary duties or be otherwise unlawful; and 
 
 
 
 
 
 (c) there should be adequate prominence given to the provision in the explanatory memorandum sent to shareholders.

34 I note that the Takeover Panel "Guidance Note: 7 Lock-up Devices" distinguishes between the anti-competitive effect of "no-talk" agreements and "no-shop" agreements. It identifies the former as inherently more anti-competitive at [7.30], and so considers it necessary for a "no-talk" agreement to contain an appropriate fiduciary carve out. It does not require generally that a "no-shop" agreement be similarly subject to a fiduciary carve out, because such a clause generally only prevents the target company from soliciting alternative or additional bidders or transactions, and does not prevent an interested party from bidding: at [7.31] and [7.7].

35 As I have noted, the exclusivity period will expire by no later than 31 May 2008, and the "no-talk" provision in the Implementation Agreement is subject to a carve out recognising the directors' fiduciary obligations and statutory duties. The evidence also indicated that the directors of Hostworks (other than Mr Shore who did not participate in the decision-making processes at all) considered the interests of the members of Hostworks in agreeing to those provisions, including the procuring of legal advice about them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Bolnisi Gold NL in the matter of Bolnisi Gold NL (No 2) [2007] FCA 2078</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/2078.html</AustLII>
<text>38 Clause 11 of the Implementation Agreement imposes a break fee provision. Break fees are also now a commonplace feature in proposed agreements for schemes of arrangements and in merger and takeover agreements, both in Australia and overseas. See per Lindgren J in APN News Ltd 62 ACSR 400 at [43]. As his Honour said at [44], break fees are justified by reference to the costs incurred by the offeror company; the benefit that that company confers on the members of the target company by increasing its value; and the desirability, from the viewpoint of those members, that takeover offers be made to them. His Honour then went on to consider contemporary practice in relation to break fees. There is a more lengthy discussion by his Honour of general considerations relating to break fees in Bolnisi Gold NL in the matter of Bolnisi Gold NL (No 2) [2007] FCA 2078 at [9] - [30] . It is a most helpful discussion.

39 There have been a number of orders made by the Court under s 411(1) of the Act in which the existence of provisions such as those in cl 11 of the Implementation Agreement concerning break fees have not been an obstacle to the making of orders for the convening of meetings.

40 In this case, the break fee is not payable if the members of Hostworks fail to support or approve the proposed scheme. A term to the contrary effect was removed from the Implementation Agreement by its amendment on 14 December 2007. There can therefore be no suggestion that the provision for the payment of the break fee will coerce shareholders to vote in favour of the proposed scheme. Those matters are fully explained in the draft explanatory statement. It is also fair to observe that, as reported in the Implementation Agreement, the break fee proposed is not of an inappropriate magnitude. It is identified as being $675,000, representing an estimate of Broadcast Australia's costs of and in relation to making the proposed offer. My general understanding is that that was not an unrealistic figure. It is a figure which the parties have agreed is a genuine and reasonable pre-estimate of the costs that Broadcast Australia will suffer if the proposed scheme does not proceed: cl 11.3. I note that the break fee is less than 1% of the equity value of Hostworks. To that extent, it accords with the Takeovers Panel Guidance Note 7: Lock Up Devices at [7.17]. I am not sure that it is appropriate to determine that an appropriate break fee may be fixed by reference to a percentage of the equity value of the takeover target as distinct from a genuine pre-estimate of the costs of the proposed offer. However, that is not of significance here because the break fee is less than 1% of the equity value of Hostworks. It is not necessary to take that further. There is in the circumstances no reason why that provision of the Implementation Agreement should have impeded the Court from making the order for the convening of the proposed meeting.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/federal_ct/2007/1389.html</AustLII>
<text>41 Under cl 7.3(a) of the Implementation Agreement, each scheme participant is deemed to have warranted that all of its shares in Hostworks which are transferred under the scheme will be free from all mortgages and encumbrances. Fryberg J in Re Mincom Ltd (No 3) (2007) 25 ACLC 207, regarded an almost identical deemed warranty clause as onerous and unreasonable and "calculated to catapult unsuspecting shareholders who have not read the small print of the arrangement in the schedule to the explanatory statement into a state of breach of warranty": at [21]. In Re APN News &amp; Media Ltd 62 ACSR 400, Lindgren J disagreed with the approach of Fryberg J: see at [59]-[62]. I respectfully agree with and adopt the views of Lindgren J. I share the understanding of his Honour that the purpose and effect of such a clause is simply to ensure that a scheme participant whose shares are subject to an encumbrance is not unfairly advantaged. The amount of the damages payable for breach of the warranty would be equal to the amount required to discharge the encumbrance. I note that the approach of Lindgren J has been preferred in subsequent cases, including by Robson J in Re Coles Group Limited [2007] VSC 389 at [45] ; by Lander J in Re Adelaide Bank Limited [2007] FCA 1582 at [33] ; and by Gyles J in Orion Telecommunications Ltd [2007] FCA 1389 at [9] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sovereign Life Assurance Co v Dodd [1892] 2 QB 573</tocase>
<text>43 In my view, neither of those matters is necessary. The relevant question is to determine whether either the option holders, or the three major shareholders who have granted an option over their shares in favour of Broadcast Australia, have rights which are so dissimilar as to make it impossible to consult together with a view to their common interest: see e.g. per Bowen LJ in Sovereign Life Assurance Co v Dodd [1892] 2 QB 573 at 583. Whilst not foreclosing the possibility that a dissenting shareholder might persuade me in due course that there should have been separate meetings of one or other of those classes, as well as of the other members of Hostworks excluding those three shareholders, so that the Court would not approve the scheme if the members otherwise approve it under s 411(4)(b), at this point I do not see that such separate meetings are necessary.

44 I do not regard the shareholders and the option holders as having different interests to such an extent that they could not consult together with other shareholders. The consideration payable for the cancellation of options takes into account the strike price of options. Upon exercise of the options, the option holders will receive consideration equivalent to the scheme consideration. The scheme consideration exceeds the exercise price of all the options. The only impediment to the immediate exercise of some of the options is the approval of the proposed scheme, triggering the operation of r 6.2(p) of the ESOP Rules, but I do not think that consideration renders the interests of the option holders so dissimilar from those of the shareholders of Hostworks as to preclude them from having a general common interest with the shareholders. Ultimately, they are proposed to be treated the same.

45 
 
As the price to be paid by Broadcast Australia, if it exercises its call options over some 19% of the issued capital of Hostworks, is equivalent to the scheme consideration, and because if the scheme is not approved, those call options will lapse, in my view there is no sufficient reason to consider that the present holders of those shares should constitute a separate class for the purposes of the scheme meeting. The options do not affect the rights and obligations of those shareholders in relation to Hostworks. Those option grantors will not be advantaged or disadvantaged depending upon the outcome of the scheme in relation to other members of Hostworks. Broadcast Australia does not have the ability to exercise or to control the exercise of the votes attached to those shares in Hostworks before the exercise of the options, and effectively in practice before the meeting.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>