<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Etl v Kliger Partners [2008] FCA 602 (30 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/602.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Decor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/655.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The principles are well established. A Court which is asked to grant leave to appeal from an interlocutory decision must first determine whether, in all the circumstances, the decision is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered. Secondly, it must consider whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused, supposing the decision to be wrong, see Decor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397. Mr Etl has advanced no argument at all which suggests that his Honour made any error in the exercise of his discretion to refuse the adjournment sought on 17 December 2007.

10 Even if the draft notice of appeal is to be understood as an attempt to commence an appeal from the whole of his Honour's judgment which includes the affirmation of the sequestration order, no error is established, given that the making of those orders was not opposed and no argument was directed to his Honour designed to persuade him that the Registrar had erred in making the sequestration order. Accordingly, I am not persuaded that his Honour's decision is attended by any doubt and there is, therefore, no occasion for it to be reconsidered on appeal.

11 Moreover, no substantial injustice will result for Mr Etl in the event that leave is refused because he will remain free to pursue the inquiries which he has been undertaking with a view to obtaining fresh evidence which, if it is obtained, may enable him to make application to the Court for the sequestration order to be set aside. That is a matter for the future.

12 There is, therefore, nothing to be gained by enlarging time for the filing and serving of a notice of appeal.

13 The application should be dismissed. I will hear the parties on costs.

 I certify that the preceding thirteen (13) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY. 


 Associate:

Dated: 5 May 2008

 Counsel for Applicant: Applicant appeared in person Counsel for Respondent: Mr M Barrett Solicitor for Respondent: Kliger Partners Counsel for Trustee in Bankruptcy: 
Mr A Cox Solicitor for Trustee in Bankruptcy 
Pointon Partners 

 Date of Hearing: 30 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 April 2008 

 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/602.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>