<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gordon v Commonwealth of Australia [2008] FCA 603 (6 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/603.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cosma v Qantas Airways Ltd [2002] FCA 640 ; (2002) 124 FCR 504</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/425.html</AustLII>
<text>93 "Particular employment" means the actual employment the relevant employee was required to perform pursuant to his contract of employment, not the general status of an employee in the employer's organisation: Cosma v Qantas Airways Ltd [2002] FCA 640 ; (2002) 124 FCR 504. Today the particular employment from which Mr Gordon was dismissed no longer exists.

94 On 1 May 2003 Mr Gordon entered into a contract to purchase a house at 9 Denis Drive, Riverside (a suburb of Launceston) for $142,500. He paid a deposit of $5,000. Settlement was due on 13 June 2003. The contract was subject to Westpac Bank making available a mortgage to secure a loan of $150,000.

95 After the ATO terminated his employment Mr Gordon advised Westpac accordingly. Because he then failed the bank's income test the loan application was refused. An alternative buyer was found for the property in June or July 2003. Mr Gordon's deposit was retuned, but he claims the following losses:
 Legal fees $476.52 Surveying fees $250.00 Building Inspection $330.00 Credit Card Fee $62.56 Total $1,089.08 

In addition he claims a loss of value. The property was valued by Brothers &amp; Newton Pty Ltd of Launceston in May 2007, as at May 2003, at $250,000. Apparently there was a real estate boom in Launceston.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 688 ; (2003) 201 ALR 55</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/688.html</AustLII>
<text>124 The usual practice in the Federal Court is to adopt the rate of interest applied by the Supreme Court of the State or Territory in which the Federal Court is considering the matter: GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 688 ; (2003) 201 ALR 55 at [7] . The current rate prescribed under rule 5A of the Supreme Court Rules 2000 (Tas) is 10.5 per cent.

125 The award for lost salary is for money lost progressively over the last five years. I will allow the 10.5 per cent on roughly half that amount, say $30,000, for five years, ie $15,750. The remainder of the award, $28,030, represents compensation for loss incurred five years ago. Interest on that component will be $14,715. Total interest amounts to $30,465.

126 The parties requested leave to make submissions as to costs after reasons were delivered. There will be a direction that within seven days of delivery of judgment the applicant file and serve submissions as to costs, the respondent file and serve submissions seven days thereafter and the applicant file and serve any reply within seven days. Costs will be decided on the papers.

 I certify that the preceding one hundred and twenty-six (126) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 6 May 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: B McTaggart 
 
 Solicitors for the Applicant: Ogilvie Jennings 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: B Morgan 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Dates of Hearing: 4, 5 and 6 February 2008 
 
 Date of Final Submissions 18 February 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 May 2008 

 SCHEDULE 
 Year Date Blood Pressure Reading Doctor 1997 21 November 150/93 Mee 26 November 135/85 Mee 1998 30 June 180/100 Mee 3 July 160/80 Mee 1999 20 April 150/93 Mee 2000 17 April 150/100 Cooper 18 November 150/85 Mee 28 November 150/95 Cooper 2001 23 July 135/85 Mee 2002 September/October 160/110 unknown 2003 22 April 200/110 Payne 22 April 190/105 Mee 9 May 170/105 Mee 13 May 200/125 Payne 15 May 170/110 McArdle 15 May 180/110 Cooper 19 May 170/98 Mee 28 May 170/100 McArdle 2 June 150/88 Mee 10 June 170/110 Mee 10 June 170/100 Cooper 19 June 172/100 Cooper 24 July 150/85 Mee 2004 14 January 165/110 Cooper 5 February 111/70 (ambulatory) Bishop 

 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/603.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>IW v City of Perth [1997] HCA 30 ; (1997) 191 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/30.html</AustLII>
<text>59 Anti-discrimination legislation is to be given a "fair, large and liberal" interpretation rather than one which is "literal or technical": IW v City of Perth [1997] HCA 30 ; (1997) 191 CLR 1 at 12 per Brennan CJ and McHugh J. From 28 April 2003 Mr Gordon was an "employee" of the respondent, however conditional the terms under which he was employed. He attended at the ATO Launceston office, carried out such duties as were required of him (there is nothing to suggest the contrary) and received, or became entitled to receive, a wage or salary as long as he so attended. During the period he was at the office the respondent would have owed him the common law and statutory obligations which employers owe to their employees. The respondent would have been liable to any third parties for torts committed by Mr Gordon in the course of his employment. Withdrawing an employment offer, in circumstances where Mr Gordon had already started work, and would have continued to work but for Mr Godden telling him to leave the premises that day, was within the concept of "dismissing" in s 15(2)(c).

60 Since s 15(1) make it unlawful to discriminate against a person on the grounds of disability in "determining who should be offered employment" (par (b)) or "in the terms or conditions on which employment is offered" (par (c)), it would be strange if someone like Mr Gordon who had actually started work would be in a weaker position and would have no protection against discrimination.

61 I reject the respondent's submission that Mr Gordon "commenced his employment under false pretences". The medical evaluation form ([18]-[20] above) made it clear that the doctor was not to decide whether Mr Gordon got the job. The form was quite encouraging in holding out the prospect that, if any medical problems existed, their effect on employment could quite possibly be resolved to the satisfaction of the employee. Mr Gordon was aware that Dr Payne would talk to the ATO. Mr Gordon was not to know when this would happen. In the meantime, according to Mr Godden, Mr Gordon's commencing work was somewhat accelerated, apparently on the ATO's initiative, because the training program was about to commence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>March v Stramare (E &amp; MH) Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 12 ; (1991) 171 CLR 506</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/12.html</AustLII>
<text>98 However, I do not think any amount in relation to the house purchase is properly allowable as damages by way of compensation for any loss or damage suffered because of the conduct of the respondent: s 46PO(4)(d) of the HREOC Act. There is no suggestion that the ATO was aware of, let alone encouraged, this purchase. Any loss, either by way of out of pocket expenses or loss of a chance to make a profitable investment, arose from Mr Gordon's rather precipitate decision to purchase and cannot, as a matter of commonsense, be attributed to the discriminatory conduct of the ATO: cf March v Stramare (E &amp; MH) Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 12 ; (1991) 171 CLR 506.

99 At the time of his termination Mr Gordon's ATO gross salary was $42,351.

100 Following his termination he applied for the following positions;
 22 June 2003 Deloittes Tax Analyst 30 March 2004 Tasmanian Perpetual Trustees position not advised 30 March 2004 Shadforths Stockbrokers Financial Advisor Assistance/Planner 30 March 2004 Commonwealth Bank Financial Planner 30 March 2004 SMF Funds Management Office Administrator 1 April 2004 RBF Cadet, Investments 1 April 2004 RBF Superannuation Administrator</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Malec v J C Hutton Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 20 ; (1990) 169 CLR 638</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/20.html</AustLII>
<text>106 Assessing what is likely to happen in the future, or would be likely to have happened had not something intervened, is not a matter of scientific demonstration or proof. Nor, unlike findings as to alleged past events, is it a case of all or nothing; 51 per cent probability win, 49 per cent probability lose: Malec v J C Hutton Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 20 ; (1990) 169 CLR 638 at 643. Nevertheless, the circumstances in the present case make it extremely unlikely that Mr Gordon, had it not been for the termination in May 2003, would have pursued a successful career with the ATO until retirement, let alone at the level he suggests.

107 First, without wishing to be hurtful to Mr Gordon, the inescapable fact is that, for whatever reason, he is not a high achiever. On paper his qualifications are considerable. He has an honours economics degree and an MBA from good universities. He is a qualified accountant. He has almost finished financial planning qualifications. Yet the positions he has occupied up until now could be characterised as occupying a rank and salary towards the lower end of mid-level clerical/professional jobs. Professional men or women in their mid-forties should be at or approaching their peak in terms of earnings and professional status. If they haven't got very far by this stage, things are unlikely to improve to any significant extent.

108 Secondly, in the past Mr Gordon has not displayed any particular enthusiasm for a career in taxation. He did not persist with the ATO in his earlier career (see [14] above). Perhaps more importantly, in his recent job applications, both in the public and private sectors ([100] above), only one was tax-related. The rest appear to have been for employment in the funds management industry.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Power v Aboriginal Hostels Limited [2003] FCA 1475 ; (2003) 133 FCR 254</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/1475.html</AustLII>
<text>63 In Power v Aboriginal Hostels Limited [2003] FCA 1475 ; (2003) 133 FCR 254 Selway J held that it is the imputed disability which is relevant. His Honour said at [15]-[18]:
 15 The next question is whether the appellant is unable to perform those duties 'because of his disability'. That question was not addressed by the learned Federal Magistrate. In my view the failure to address that question was an appealable error. If the question had been addressed then there are two possibilities. The first is that the 'imputed disorder' of depression is the relevant disability. Alternatively, his actual condition of an adjustment disorder (from which he seems to have recovered) is the relevant disability. 16 The appellant's submissions assumed that the relevant disability was the actual condition of the appellant at the time of his termination. On that basis the appellant submitted that he could perform the inherent requirements of the position - indeed, he was doing so for the four weeks before his employment was terminated. Consequently, he argued, s 15(4) of the DDA had no application. 17 On the other hand the respondent's submissions assumed that the relevant disability was the imputed disorder of depression, notwithstanding that the appellant was not suffering from that disability. On this basis the respondent argued that in light of the report of Dr Ducrou the appellant was unable to comply with the inherent duties of the position. 18 So far as my research reveals, there is no authority directly on point. The definition of 'disability' in s 4 of the DDA purports to be an exhaustive definition, 'unless the contrary intention appears'. There is no obvious contrary intention disclosed by s 15(4). Nor is there any obvious reason to imply one. The DDA is principally directed to the elimination as far as possible of 'discrimination against persons on the ground of disability' in relevant areas (s 3 DDA). It is not directed at achieving 'fair outcomes' as such. Consequently what is prohibited is discriminatory behaviour based upon disability. 'Imputed' disability is sufficient for this purpose. What the DDA prohibited in this case was not the dismissal of the appellant for a reason which was wrong, but the dismissal of the appellant who had a disability (albeit an imputed one) in circumstances where a person without a disability would not have been dismissed. When it is understood that the DDA is directed at the ground of discrimination (which includes imputed disability) and not 'fair outcomes' then there seems no reason to imply that 'disability' appearing in s 15(4) of the DDA does not include imputed disability.

64 Additionally to his Honour's observations, it can be said that it is likely that the word "disability" wherever it appears in s 15(4) is referring to the same thing. Where first appearing, "disability" is obviously referring to the discrimination alleged against the employer seeking to rely on the defence. If that discrimination was on the ground of imputed disability, then "disability" means imputed disability and the later expression "his or her disability" refers to the disability imputed to the employee alleging discrimination.

65 Since s 15 as a whole is setting up a norm of conduct, it is to be read as addressed to employers as at the time they are contemplating potentially discriminatory conduct. Subsections (1) and (2) tell employers what they must not do. Subsections (3) and (4) tell them in what circumstances they may lawfully do what would otherwise amount to unlawful discrimination. This suggests that what subs (4) is concerned with are circumstances known to the employer at the time. However, consistently with the philosophy of anti-discrimination legislation (see [58] above), the criterion is an objective one as is indicated by the reference to "all other factors that it is reasonable to take into account". The relevant circumstances include the nature of the imputed disability in the light of such medical investigation as may be reasonable and the availability of reasonable treatment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Purvis v New South Wales [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 217 CLR 92</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/62.html</AustLII>
<text>56 As already mentioned, hypertension is a disability. The respondent, on the advice of Dr Payne, imputed this disability to Mr Gordon. The comparator for the purposes of s 5(1) is a hypothetical person who does not have hypertension but has Mr Gordon's qualifications and experience and is applying for the position of a GST Field Officer in the Launceston office of the ATO. There can be no doubt that such a person would have got the job and would not have had the employment offer withdrawn. By withdrawing the offer of employment the respondent has treated Mr Gordon less favourably than it would have treated such a hypothetical person. It did so because of the imputed condition of hypertension, which, it considered, made him unfit for the requirements of the particular position. The respondent thus discriminated against Mr Gordon, within the meaning of s 5(1): Purvis v New South Wales [2003] HCA 62 ; (2003) 217 CLR 92 at [213] .

57 I do not accept the respondent's argument that the offer was withdrawn, not because of Mr Gordon's hypertension, but because he failed to meet one of the pre-employment conditions, viz, that he be certified fit for the duties of the position. One cannot divorce the factual base from its legal characterisation. Even if regard is had to the three other medical conditions mentioned by Dr Payne, there would still be discrimination because they are equally "disabilities" which would not be suffered by the comparator. But viewed in a practical way, the inescapable conclusion from the evidence is that the real and operative reason for withdrawing the offer was Mr Gordon's imputed hypertension.

58 The respondent contended that it did not dismiss Mr Gordon, rather that it withdrew a conditional offer of employment when the condition was not satisfied.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Waters v Public Transport Corporation [1991] HCA 49 ; (1991) 173 CLR 349</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/49.html</AustLII>
<text>62 I conclude therefore that Mr Gordon has made out a prima facie case of discrimination. Before passing to the s 15(4) defence I should note that the Act does not require an intention or motive to discriminate; cf Waters v Public Transport Corporation [1991] HCA 49 ; (1991) 173 CLR 349 at 359 per Mason CJ and Gaudron J, with whom Deane J at 382 agreed, a case under comparable Victorian legislation. There is nothing to suggest that Dr Payne, or Mr Godden and the other ATO officers, acted otherwise than in good faith.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>X v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 63 ; (1999) 200 CLR 177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/63.html</AustLII>
<text>66 Whether something is an "inherent requirement" of a particular employment depends on whether it is an essential element. The inherent requirements include at least the ability to carry out the physical tasks encompassed by the particular employment but also matters such as having regard for the safety of other employees, the general public and the employee himself: X v The Commonwealth [1999] HCA 63 ; (1999) 200 CLR 177 at [31] - [35] per McHugh J.

67 The requirements of the particular employment in question in the present case were described by Mr Godden. In 2003 GST Field Staff were organised into six teams, three each in Hobart and Launceston. The Launceston teams were based at an ATO office in that city. The office was purely a GST Field Site. No other ATO functions were performed at that site and there were no facilities for public contact. When a taxpayer had to be seen, the officers would go out to the taxpayer's place of business.

68 Launceston teams were expected to deal with clients in the North of the State down to Ross, on the North West Coast and in the North East down to Bicheno.

69 All Launceston staff were involved in field work in 2003. The work was a mixture of audit and advisory visits. The latter would be in response to a taxpayer's request for a visit. The Commissioner had given a public undertaking that the Office would contact the taxpayer within 72 hours of the initial request and complete the visit within 14 days.

70 Management was trying to maximise field time with an aim of officers spending 80 per cent of their time in the field. As it turned out, in 2003 officers in Launceston spent about 40 to 50 per cent of their time in the field, the remainder being taken up with training, team meetings, leave etc. New APS 4 staff such as Mr Gordon would have to spend more time in the field than the average because their work would have required them to spend more time doing advisory visits than audits.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>