<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Granada Tavern v Smith [2008] FCA 646 (15 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/646.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/34.html</AustLII>
<text>3 The appellants now appeal to this Court. Essentially the duress alleged was the threatened and actual deprivation of Ms Wills of weekend work. The appellants attack some of his Honour's fact finding. They say that even accepting the facts as found, a case of contravention was not made out. They say there was a misunderstanding of the principles laid down in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 at 359-362. They say the reasons given by his Honour were inadequate.

4 Ms Wills started work at the Tavern on 14 February 2005. At the time she was nineteen. She had commenced studying a course of business management at the University on a full time basis in 2004 and was still engaged in those studies. She worked predominantly as a waitress in the restaurant but occasionally in the kitchen.

5 Up until August 2006 Ms Wills worked generally three or four dinner shifts during the week and also on weekends when she was regularly rostered to work both days. She was almost always rostered to work on the Sunday lunch shift. The work roster at the Tavern for each week was written on a sheet of paper displayed on a wall between the kitchen and the bar, usually one or two weeks in advance. The employee responsible for compiling the rosters was Mr Michael Taylor. He was the head chef and had worked at the Tavern for over ten years. He was Ms Wills' immediate superior. She often spoke with Mr Taylor about the number of shifts per week that she wanted to work. She told him she needed to work four or five shifts per week or approximately fourteen hours in order to meet her financial commitments.

71 The appeal grounds can be summarised as follows:
 
&#8226; His Honour erred in finding that duress was applied in connection with an AWA (Grounds 1-8, 11);
 
&#8226; His Honour misapplied the principles laid down in Briginshaw v Briginshaw at 359-362 (Ground 9);
 
&#8226; Findings concerning Ms Wills being a "ringleader" and that her work hours changed "dramatically" were not open (Ground 10). Other errors were alleged in a "Schedule of Fact Finding Errors";
 
&#8226; His Honour failed to properly consider and deal with the appellants' submissions (Ground 12).

Ground 13, alleging that the penalties were excessive, was not pursued.

72 There were ten matters complained of under this heading.

73 "Pressure" not applied in connection with AWA . Plainly the evidence established that Mr Hibberd was keen to have AWAs signed by employees, especially because he had discovered that he did not have a valid AWA regime existing. All his dealings with Ms Wills referred to by his Honour were directed towards her signing an AWA, indeed they were concerned with little else. Prior to the AWA issue Ms Wills had virtually no contact with Mr Hibberd. The change to her weekend rosters was obviously intended to disadvantage her in the context of her resistance to signing an AWA. It is hard to see how his Honour could have come to any other conclusion.

74 It was submitted before his Honour that the respondent had to establish that the conduct of Mr Hibberd amounted to a "compulsion of the will of Ms Wills such as to have the effect of giving her no other practical alternative than to sign the AWA". There had to have been an "overbearing of the will".

85 His Honour said: 
 32 I accept, as both parties submitted, that the principles applicable in Briginshaw v Briginshaw and Another [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 ("Briginshaw") should be applied to allegations such as duress. I note that, not surprisingly, the Respondents sought to place the definition of duress, as it were, at the highest level. It was submitted (First and Second Respondents' outline of closing submission) that "clear, cogent, strong and strict proof is required" (paragraph 1). 33 The authority cited in support of that proposition as a footnote was the observation of Ryan J in Canturi at [44]. What Ryan J actually said at paragraph [44] was: 
 
 I accept that the onus of proving duress remains on the applicants and it is one which, having regard to the seriousness of the alleged contravention, has to be proved to the reasonable satisfaction of the Court in accordance with Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336. 
 
 
34 In my view it is preferable to approach an issue such as a finding of duress in accordance with what are well established principles. To seek to elevate duress to any particular level of significance is only likely to cloud the issues. While I bear well in mind the observations of the Courts as to the hesitations that should be borne in mind in considering issues both of duress generally and even more so of economic duress, it seems to me that in the ultimate the Court is faced in this instance with an alleged breach of the terms of a subsection of the Act, which is required to be proved to the satisfaction of the Court in accordance with Briginshaw principles.

86 Later at [295] his Honour said that he was satisfied of "all the above matters" (ie the matters in [292]-[294] quoted at [70] above) "to what Ryan J in Canturi described as 'the requisite degree' when referring to Briginshaw principles".

87 The complaint of the appellants on the appeal centred on his Honour's statement that the appellants "sought to place the definition of duress at its highest level" (at [32]). This was said by the appellants to manifest a misunderstanding "of the application of the Briginshaw principle to the case before him".

88 I think that all his Honour was conveying was that the appellants had submitted, as might have been expected, that duress was a serious allegation. It is inherent in the forensic process that a defendant will stress the seriousness of the charge alleged, be it civil or criminal. As counsel for the respondents submitted, correctly (and, in the light of the recent Full Court decision to be discussed hereafter, presciently), the principle in Briginshaw is simply that serious misconduct is not lightly to be found because it is not ordinarily engaged in by members of the community.

89 In any event, it may be that, if anything, his Honour's application of Briginshaw was too favourable to the appellants. I say that because the true nature and effect of Briginshaw has recently been the subject of detailed analysis by Branson J (with whom French and Jacobson JJ agreed) in Qantas Airways Ltd v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69.

90 Branson J explained that expressions like "the Briginshaw standard" and "the Briginshaw test" should be avoided because of their tendency to mislead. Her Honour cited (at [124]) the well known passage from the judgment of Dixon J in that case at 361-362:
 Fortunately... at common law no third standard of persuasion was definitely developed. Except upon criminal issues to be proved by the prosecution, it is enough that the affirmative of an allegation is made out to the reasonable satisfaction of the tribunal. But reasonable satisfaction is not a state of mind that is attained or established independently of the nature and consequence of the fact or facts to be proved. The seriousness of an allegation made, the inherent unlikelihood of an occurrence of a given description, or the gravity of the consequences flowing from a particular finding, are considerations which must affect the answer to the question whether the issue has been proved to the reasonable satisfaction of the tribunal. 
Her Honour emphasised at [125]-[126] that Dixon J was speaking of "allegations", that is to say individual allegations of material fact, rather than, for example, causes of action. Nor did Dixon J identify any particular standard; rather that the tribunal of fact, before accepting the truth of evidence of a particular allegation, should give consideration to the nature of the allegation and the likely consequences which follow should it be accepted.

94 Applying that approach to the present case, it may be doubted whether the particular allegations of fact in this case, for example that Mr Hibberd or Ms Bercheree said or did such and such or had such and such intention, really involve allegations of particular gravity. They are to be contrasted with allegations of adultery ( Briginshaw ) or fraud ( Rejfek ). The AWA regime is, or was at the time, part of a complex statutory industrial law system. Knowledge of its full ramifications amongst all employers is not self-evidently a circumstance on which courts can safely rely. Breaches of the law may well occur in ignorance. Moral opprobrium does not necessarily attach. Of course, particular factual allegations in AWA duress cases may involve allegations of reprehensible behaviour; see, for example, the conduct in Jordan . While the conduct alleged against Mr Hibberd certainly warranted the learned Magistrate's criticisms, I doubt if it could be characterised as conduct inherently unlikely to be engaged in by employers.

95 In the light of the Full Court's decision in Gama one does not say: "Contravention of s 400(5) is a serious matter; therefore the Briginshaw standard applies". Rather, the fact finder must look at the particular factual allegations. They can vary infinitely. Before reaching a finding which accepts those allegations as true (the onus of course being on the applicant), the fact finder must, amongst other things, take into account the gravity of the particular allegations: s 140(2)(c). Once the facts are fully found, including the making of inferences from primary fact, the question whether those facts fall within the statutory prescription of applying duress in connection with an AWA is a question of law: Hope v City of Bathurst [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7.

96 Gama is an important decision, not least for throwing light on an intriguing phenomenon in Australian professional legal culture. The resilience of the common law is such that in practice the Evidence Act is often overlooked. In my own experience, in the period of well over a decade since the Evidence Act was introduced Briginshaw is without fail cited in witness actions with the possible exception of patent infringement cases but I do not recall ever being referred to s 140. This is not to say it never happens, but a search of the Federal Court internal judgment database reveals only six decisions, apart from Gama , (including one in the Full Court) in which the covering list of legislation and cases cited refers to both s 140 and Briginshaw .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Canturi v Sita Coaches Pty Ltd (2002)116 FCR 276</tocase>
<text>75 Whatever may be the position in other contexts, s 400(5) does not require, as an essential element of contravention, an overbearing of the will of the employee. There can still be a contravention even if, as in the present case, the employee does not sign the AWA and thus has not had his or her will overborne. By contrast, at common law the question of duress will usually only arise where the plaintiff is seeking to avoid the consequence of some act or event allegedly produced by the duress of the defendant, such as the payment of money or the entering into a contract. In Canturi v Sita Coaches Pty Ltd (2002)116 FCR 276 at [43] Ryan J, after reviewing the authorities, stated the position as follows:
 In my view, the consensus of the authorities to which I have referred is that duress, in the relevant sense, involves the illegitimate application of pressure to induce a party to enter into an AWA, or to discourage a party from taking that course. What is illegitimate is a question of fact to be decided in the circumstances of each case which may include whether there is an existing relationship of employer and employee or some other relationship of utmost good faith between the parties to the proposed AWA. As is made clear by the last sentence in the passage from the judgment of the Full Court in Schanka [v Employment National (Administration) Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 202 ; (2000) 97 FCR 186 at [23] ] quoted at [36] above, it is not only pressure which in fact overbears the will of one party so as to result in an AWA being concluded that can amount to duress. Accordingly, I cannot accept the argument advanced on behalf of the respondents that "neither Napoli nor Canturi submitted to the alleged duress so it cannot be contended that their will was overborne, or that the conduct alleged against the respondents was illegitimate".

86 Later at [295] his Honour said that he was satisfied of "all the above matters" (ie the matters in [292]-[294] quoted at [70] above) "to what Ryan J in Canturi described as 'the requisite degree' when referring to Briginshaw principles".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Employment Advocate v Williamson [2001] FCA 1164 ; (2001) 111 FCR 20</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1164.html</AustLII>
<text>91 Her Honour pointed out that the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) contained a provision dealing with standard of proof in civil matters, viz s 140 , which is as follows:
 
 
 (1) In a civil proceeding, the court must find the case of a party proved if it is satisfied that the case has been proved on the balance of probabilities. 
 (2) Without limiting the matters that the court may take into account in deciding whether it is so satisfied, it is to take into account: 
 (a) the nature of the cause of action or defence; and 
 (b) the nature of the subject-matter of the proceeding; and 
 (c) the gravity of the matters alleged. 
 


As her Honour had noted, with the concurrence of Kenny J, in Employment Advocate v Williamson [2001] FCA 1164 ; (2001) 111 FCR 20 at [65] , s 140(2) of the Evidence Act was intended to reflect the common law position as to the strength of evidence necessary to establish satisfaction on the balance of probabilities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/22.html</AustLII>
<text>102 Generally as to the setting aside of findings of fact that rest on credibility findings by the trial judge, the position is as summarised by McHugh J in Fox v Percy [2003] HCA 22 ; (2003) 214 CLR 118 at [65] - [67] :
 65 Whether an appellate court should intervene in a decision of a trial judge who has made findings based on the credibility or demeanour of a witness is governed by the principles stated in Abalos v Australian Postal Commission. In that case, I said [at 178-9]: 
 
 [W]here a trial judge has made a finding of fact contrary to the evidence of a witness but has made no reference to that evidence, an appellate court cannot act on that evidence to reverse the finding unless it is satisfied "that any advantage enjoyed by the trial judge by reason of having seen and heard the witnesses, could not be sufficient to explain or justify the trial judge's conclusion" [ Watt (or Thomas) v Thomas [1947] AC 484 at 488].
 ...
 [W]hen a trial judge resolves a conflict of evidence between witnesses, the subtle influence of demeanour on his or her determination cannot be overlooked.
 
 
66 Mason CJ, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ, the other members of the Court, agreed with my judgment. Abalos was applied in Devries v Australian National Railways Commission [1993] HCA 78 ; [(1993) 177 CLR 472 at 479] where Brennan and Gaudron JJ and I said: 
 
 More than once in recent years, this Court has pointed out that a finding of fact by a trial judge, based on the credibility of a witness, is not to be set aside because an appellate court thinks that the probabilities of the case are against -- even strongly against -- that finding of fact. (Footnote omitted.) If the trial judge's finding depends to any substantial degree on the credibility of the witness, the finding must stand unless it can be shown that the trial judge "has failed to use or has palpably misused his advantage" [ SS Hontestroom v SS Sagaporack [1927] AC 37 at 47] or has acted on evidence which was "inconsistent with facts incontrovertibly established by the evidence" or which was "glaringly improbable" [ Brunskill [1985] HCA 61 ; (1985) 59 ALJR 842 at 844; 62 ALR 53 at 57].
 
 
67 There was nothing novel about these statements. They derived from principles in decisions of this Court and the House of Lords stretching over the best part of a century.

103 In the present case the appellants' attack on the credibility findings in respect of Ms Wills does not come near that standard of appellate review.

104 The "concentration camp" comment . It may be that Mr Hibberd was attempting to make the point that if different employees were working on different conditions he would have to ensure that people on the Award did not get such additional benefits as the AWA provided. However, the tone and context in which the term was used were very much matters for his Honour, who had the opportunity to assess the witnesses, and in particular Ms Wills.

105 The appellants say that his Honour failed to deal with submissions made as to fact and law; "little or no reference" was made to submissions by the appellants on the evidence.

106 The Federal Magistrates Court was established by the Federal Magistrates Act 1999 (Cth). One of the objects of that Act was "to enable the Federal Magistrates Court to operate as informally as possible in the exercise of judicial power": s 3(2)(a). Likewise s 42 provides:
 In proceedings before it, the Federal Magistrates Court must proceed without undue formality and must endeavour to ensure that the proceedings are not protracted.

107 His Honour's judgment, handed down expeditiously some six weeks after final submissions, extends over 51 pages. It deals in detail with the events at the Tavern in 2006. It makes clear findings of fact. It cites the appropriate legislation and authorities. It explains the reasoning which led to his Honour's decision. The appellants on reading the judgment would understand why they lost. Perhaps his Honour did not record and deal with every argument advanced on behalf of the appellants, but he was not obliged to do so.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hope v City of Bathurst [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/16.html</AustLII>
<text>95 In the light of the Full Court's decision in Gama one does not say: "Contravention of s 400(5) is a serious matter; therefore the Briginshaw standard applies". Rather, the fact finder must look at the particular factual allegations. They can vary infinitely. Before reaching a finding which accepts those allegations as true (the onus of course being on the applicant), the fact finder must, amongst other things, take into account the gravity of the particular allegations: s 140(2)(c). Once the facts are fully found, including the making of inferences from primary fact, the question whether those facts fall within the statutory prescription of applying duress in connection with an AWA is a question of law: Hope v City of Bathurst [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jordan v Mornington Inn Pty Ltd (2007) 166 IR 33</tocase>
<text>76 No legal right or legitimate expectation of Ms Wills removed or threatened . Removal or threatened removal of something which can be characterised as a legal right or legitimate expectation is not an essential element of the concept of duress under the statute. In any event, with her established pattern of weekend work, an "unwritten agreement" as Mr Taylor termed it, Ms Wills plainly did have a legitimate expectation; cf Jordan v Mornington Inn Pty Ltd (2007) 166 IR 33 at [43]. Of necessity, a legitimate expectation is something less than a legal right.

77 No actual or threatened detriment sufficient to constitute duress . The loss of shifts, particularly on weekends was, on the evidence, a serious detriment to Ms Wills. She was a student who depended on part time employment to survive.

94 Applying that approach to the present case, it may be doubted whether the particular allegations of fact in this case, for example that Mr Hibberd or Ms Bercheree said or did such and such or had such and such intention, really involve allegations of particular gravity. They are to be contrasted with allegations of adultery ( Briginshaw ) or fraud ( Rejfek ). The AWA regime is, or was at the time, part of a complex statutory industrial law system. Knowledge of its full ramifications amongst all employers is not self-evidently a circumstance on which courts can safely rely. Breaches of the law may well occur in ignorance. Moral opprobrium does not necessarily attach. Of course, particular factual allegations in AWA duress cases may involve allegations of reprehensible behaviour; see, for example, the conduct in Jordan . While the conduct alleged against Mr Hibberd certainly warranted the learned Magistrate's criticisms, I doubt if it could be characterised as conduct inherently unlikely to be engaged in by employers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd v Gold Peg International Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 117 ; (2006) 234 ALR 241</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/117.html</AustLII>
<text>108 In Kovan Engineering (Aust) Pty Ltd v Gold Peg International Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 117 ; (2006) 234 ALR 241 an issue arose as to the adequacy of the reasons of the trial judge. Weinberg J and I said:
 44 As to the second matter, the obligations of the trial judge to give adequate reasons, on the appeal Kovan relied strongly on what was said by Nettle JA (with whom Batt and Vincent JJA agreed) in Hunter v Transport Accident Commission (2005) 43 MVR 130 at [21]. While noting that the extent of the reasons will depend on the circumstances of the case, his Honour said that the reasons should deal with the "substantial" points which have been raised, include findings on "material" questions of fact and provide an "intelligible" explanation of the reasoning from evidence to findings to ultimate conclusion. Reference to the evidence should not be limited to the evidence that has been accepted and acted upon, but "ordinarily" should deal with the "substantial" points made in evidence which has been rejected and explain why it has been rejected. The judge must deal with evidence which is "relevant and cogent", arguments which are "substantial" and issues which are "significant". 45 No matter how prescriptive the principles laid down, they inevitably involve disclaimers as to any universal applicability. Moreover, the passage from Hunter would give an unbalanced view if it were not read in conjunction with the firm warnings of courts of high authority against over-lengthy judgments. These are noted by the Full Court in Expectation [Pty Ltd v PRD Realty Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 189 ; (2004) 140 FCR 17] at [83] . Of the cases there referred to, particular note should be taken of what was said by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Digi-Tech (Aust) Ltd v Brand [2004] NSWCA 58 ; (2004) 62 IPR 184 at [287] [290] and the following passage from the joint judgment of Gleeson CJ, McHugh and Gummow JJ in Whisprun Pty Ltd v Dixon [2003] HCA 48 ; (2003) 200 ALR 447 (at [62]): 
 
 ... it should not be accepted that Newman J failed, at least in a general way, to consider the matters to which the Court of Appeal referred. The fact that his Honour did not refer to these matters in his judgment is not decisive. A judge's reasons are not required to mention every fact or argument relied on by the losing party as relevant to an issue. Judgments of trial judges would soon become longer than they already are if a judge's failure to mention such facts and arguments would be evidence that he or she had not properly considered the losing party's case. 
 
 46 As the Full Court said in Expectation (at [71]), in the normal case statements by a trial judge of a general assertive nature can be accepted as encompassing a detailed consideration of the evidence. As their Honours immediately go on to say, such statements should be treated with some reserve where there has been "significant" delay between trial and judgment. After such a delay: 
 
 ... a more comprehensive statement of the relevant evidence than would normally be required should be provided by the trial judge in order to make manifest, to the parties and the public, that the delay has not affected the decision. 
 
... 48 As to the suggested obligation on the trial judge to explain why evidence or argument of the losing party has been rejected, we would refer to what was said by Schiemann LJ in Customs and Excise Commissioners v A [2003] 2 All ER 736 at [82] [83], in a passage cited with approval in Digi-Tech (at [285]): 
 
 ... judges should bear in mind that the primary function of a first instance judgment is to find facts and identify the crucial legal points and to advance reasons for deciding them in a particular way. The longer a judgment is and the more issues with which it deals the greater the likelihood that: (i) the losing party, the Court of Appeal and any future readers of the judgment will not be able to identify the crucial matters which swayed the judge; (ii) the judgment will contain something with which the unsuccessful party can legitimately take issue and attempt to launch an appeal; (iii) citation of the judgment in future cases will lengthen the hearing of those future cases because time will be taken sorting out the precise status of the judicial observation in question; and (iv) reading the judgment will occupy a considerable amount of the time of legal advisers to other parties in future cases who again will have to sort out the status of the judicial observation in question. All this adds to the cost of obtaining legal advice. 
 
 Often it is not possible to reconcile neatly all evidence and arguments. Sometimes evidence or arguments of the losing party may be valid in themselves; it is just that there seem to the trial judge to be other and more persuasive items of evidence and points of argument the other way. If the trial judge does not mention such evidence or arguments of the losing party an appellate court may take a different view. It may reverse the decision below because it finds the appellant's evidence or arguments persuasive. But that will be because the appeal court took a different view of the facts or law from that of the trial judge, not because the trial judge made a legal error in the way his or her reasons were expressed -- provided the minimum requirements identified by Schiemann LJ are satisfied.

109 The other member of the Court in Kovan , Allsop J, said:
 119 As to the discussion of the adequacy of the reasons of the primary judge, in addition to my complete agreement with Heerey and Weinberg JJ, I would only wish to make reference to what Mahoney JA said in Housing Commission of New South Wales v Tatmar Pastoral Co Pty Ltd [1983] 3 NSWLR 378 at 385 (a decision affirmed sub nom Tatmar Pastoral Co Pty Ltd v Housing Commission of New South Wales (1984) 54 ALR 155): 
 
 [I]t is the duty of the judge to state his reasons for deciding as he does and that his failure to do so may constitute an error of law ... However, such a duty does not exist in respect of every matter, of fact or of law, which was or might have been raised in the proceeding. It is not the duty of the judge to decide every matter which is raised in argument. He may decide a case in a way which does not require the determination of a particular submission: In such a case he may put it aside or, as Lord Scarman said, merely salute it in passing: R v Barnet London Borough Council; Ex parte Nilish Shah [1983] 2 AC 309 at 350. A judge will, of course, appreciate the possibility of points being taken or decided on appeal which were not taken or decided below and for this reason he may decide, and give reasons for his decision on, matters which in strictness he need not decide. 
 
 See also Soulemezis v Dudley (Holdings) Pty Ltd (1987) 10 NSWLR 247 at 269 70 and 280 1.

110 These observations apply a fortiori to the Federal Magistrates Court with its statutory mandate for informality and expedition.

111 The appeal is dismissed.

 I certify that the preceding one hundred and eleven (111) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Heerey. 


 Associate:

Dated: 15 May 2008

 Counsel for the First and Second Appellants: N Clelland SC 
 
 Counsel for the Third Appellant: G Livermore 
 
 Solicitors for the Appellants: Simmons Wolfhagen 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: J Bourke and M Felman 
 
 Solicitors for the Respondent: Clayton Utz 

 Date of Hearing: 31 March and 1 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 May 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/646.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maritime Union of Australia v Geraldton Port Authority [1999] FCA 899 ; (1999) 165 ALR 67</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/899.html</AustLII>
<text>78 Conduct was not illegitimate or unconscionable . Lawful conduct can constitute duress: Maritime Union of Australia v Geraldton Port Authority [1999] FCA 899 ; (1999) 165 ALR 67 at [367] . Characterising conduct as unconscionable involves a value judgement. His Honour was entitled to consider the relative age and power positions of the parties and the way in which Mr Hibberd exploited that position, for example by denying that Ms Wills had a pattern of weekend work. The picture of Mr Hibberd emerging from the evidence of Ms Wills, whom his Honour found to be "impressive" and "a young woman of some fortitude" (at [186]), was of a man behaving in an overbearing way to a vulnerable employee.

79 Not established that Mr Hibberd intentionally applied duress to Ms Wills in connection with an AWA . The conduct of Mr Hibberd and Ms Berechree, especially in their directions to Mr Taylor regarding the roster, was intentional conduct, plainly meant to apply pressure to Ms Wills in connection with an AWA. It had no other purpose that is apparent. Ms Wills' note, which disclosed at the very least that she was not about to sign the AWA and accept whatever Mr Hibberd was pleased to give her, was followed the next day by his directions. This was hardly a coincidence.

80 Not established Ms Wills regarded as a ringleader . This was a finding well open in the light of Ms Wills' conduct at the meetings of 7 and 27 August and Mr Hibberd's suggesting at the latter meeting that Ms Wills was acting as a bargaining agent. In any event, this is not a factual finding of critical importance. Whether or not Ms Wills was the ringleader, or seen as such by Mr Hibberd, unconscionable pressure was applied to her.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/66.html</AustLII>
<text>92 Her Honour referred to a number of authorities, including the High Court decisions in Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 and Rejfek v McElroy (1965) 112 CLR 517. In the latter case the High Court at 521 made it plain that
 the standard of proof to be applied in a case and the relationship between the degree of persuasion of the mind according to the balance of probabilities and the gravity or otherwise of the fact of whose existence the mind is to be persuaded are not to be confused. (Emphasis added by Branson J in Gama at [131].)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Qantas Airways Ltd v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/69.html</AustLII>
<text>89 In any event, it may be that, if anything, his Honour's application of Briginshaw was too favourable to the appellants. I say that because the true nature and effect of Briginshaw has recently been the subject of detailed analysis by Branson J (with whom French and Jacobson JJ agreed) in Qantas Airways Ltd v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69.

93 Gama itself was a case of alleged racial discrimination. Branson J noted the various considerations which s 140 , in the circumstances of the case, required to be taken into account. With regard to "the gravity of the matter alleged", her Honour said at [137]:
 Without wishing to diminish the significance of the factual allegations made by Mr Gama, which themselves varied in gravity, more serious allegations of racial discrimination can be brought to mind. 
Her Honour had earlier noted at [133] that 
 The legislative requirement for complaints of unlawful discrimination to be made in the first instance to the President [of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission] reflects a recognition, as it seems to me, that the practical implications of human rights principles are not always well understood by members of the Australian community. For this reason, not only may claims of discrimination lack substance but acts of discrimination may occur without the actor intending to breach those principles. For these reasons moral opprobrium may, but does not necessarily, attach to an allegation of discriminatory conduct. 
In conclusion, her Honour said at [139]:
 ...in my view, for the reasons given above, references to, for example, "the Briginshaw standard" or "the onerous Briginshaw test" and, in that context, to racial discrimination being a serious matter not lightly to be inferred, have a tendency to lead a trier of facts into error. The correct approach to the standard of proof in a civil proceeding in a federal court is that for which s 140 of the Evidence Act provides. It is an approach which recognises, adopting the language of the High Court in Neat Holdings, that the strength of the evidence necessary to establish a fact in issue on the balance of probabilities will vary according to the nature of what is sought to be proved and, I would add, the circumstances in which it is sought to be proved.

95 In the light of the Full Court's decision in Gama one does not say: "Contravention of s 400(5) is a serious matter; therefore the Briginshaw standard applies". Rather, the fact finder must look at the particular factual allegations. They can vary infinitely. Before reaching a finding which accepts those allegations as true (the onus of course being on the applicant), the fact finder must, amongst other things, take into account the gravity of the particular allegations: s 140(2)(c). Once the facts are fully found, including the making of inferences from primary fact, the question whether those facts fall within the statutory prescription of applying duress in connection with an AWA is a question of law: Hope v City of Bathurst [1980] HCA 16 ; (1980) 144 CLR 1 at 7.

96 Gama is an important decision, not least for throwing light on an intriguing phenomenon in Australian professional legal culture. The resilience of the common law is such that in practice the Evidence Act is often overlooked. In my own experience, in the period of well over a decade since the Evidence Act was introduced Briginshaw is without fail cited in witness actions with the possible exception of patent infringement cases but I do not recall ever being referred to s 140. This is not to say it never happens, but a search of the Federal Court internal judgment database reveals only six decisions, apart from Gama , (including one in the Full Court) in which the covering list of legislation and cases cited refers to both s 140 and Briginshaw .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rejfek v McElroy (1965) 112 CLR 517</tocase>
<text>92 Her Honour referred to a number of authorities, including the High Court decisions in Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 and Rejfek v McElroy (1965) 112 CLR 517. In the latter case the High Court at 521 made it plain that
 the standard of proof to be applied in a case and the relationship between the degree of persuasion of the mind according to the balance of probabilities and the gravity or otherwise of the fact of whose existence the mind is to be persuaded are not to be confused. (Emphasis added by Branson J in Gama at [131].)

94 Applying that approach to the present case, it may be doubted whether the particular allegations of fact in this case, for example that Mr Hibberd or Ms Bercheree said or did such and such or had such and such intention, really involve allegations of particular gravity. They are to be contrasted with allegations of adultery ( Briginshaw ) or fraud ( Rejfek ). The AWA regime is, or was at the time, part of a complex statutory industrial law system. Knowledge of its full ramifications amongst all employers is not self-evidently a circumstance on which courts can safely rely. Breaches of the law may well occur in ignorance. Moral opprobrium does not necessarily attach. Of course, particular factual allegations in AWA duress cases may involve allegations of reprehensible behaviour; see, for example, the conduct in Jordan . While the conduct alleged against Mr Hibberd certainly warranted the learned Magistrate's criticisms, I doubt if it could be characterised as conduct inherently unlikely to be engaged in by employers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>Smith v Granada Tavern [2007] FMCA 904</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2007/904.html</AustLII>
<text>1 Ms Emily Wills, a student at the University of Tasmania, is a casual employee at the Granada Tavern in Berriedale, a suburb of Hobart. The Tavern is owned by the first appellant (the Company), a company trading under that name. In an application brought by a Workplace Inspector, Burchardt FM in the Federal Magistrates Court found that the Company, its director the second appellant Mr Michael Hibberd, and the manager of the Tavern, the third appellant, Ms Jocelyn Berechree, had applied duress to Ms Wills in connection with an Australian Workplace Agreement (AWA) contrary to s 400(5) of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth): Smith v Granada Tavern [2007] FMCA 904.

2 His Honour imposed penalties of $24,750 on the Company, $4,950 on Mr Hibberd and $1,980 on Ms Berechree.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>