<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLQZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 717 (20 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/717.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Harrington v Rich [2008] FCAFC 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/61.html</AustLII>
<text>9 No question arises in the present Application as to whether it was filed within time; the question is whether leave should be granted or refused. Considerations relevant to the exercise of that discretion are:
 
(i) whether in all the circumstances, the judgment of the primary judge is attended by sufficient doubt as to warrant it being reconsidered by the Full Court; and 
 
(ii) whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused, supposing the decision were wrong. See: Harrington v Rich [2008] FCAFC 61 at [25] per Sackville, Emmett and Jacobson JJ.

10 In the present proceedings it is considered that leave to appeal should be refused. The judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court is not attendant with sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered. Relevant to that conclusion is a review of the reasons for decision of both the Refugee Review Tribunal and the Federal Magistrates Court.

11 The reasons for decision of the Tribunal recount the claims being made, the findings of fact which were made and the reasons for decision. Those findings include findings made adversely to the now Applicant -- but findings which were open to the Tribunal. It thus concluded, for example:
 As is set out herein, the Tribunal is satisfied the applicant has sought to at least embellish if not entirely fabricate material parts of his case. Therefore, even though the Tribunal accepts the above claim (to have been abducted) is possible, the Tribunal does not intend to give the applicant the benefit of the doubt and thus does not accept this claim. ... ... the Tribunal is not satisfied the applicant is being pursued by the Indian authorities; for the reasons he claimed or at all. The Tribunal therefore does not accept the applicant had to hide in Bangalow. ... ... ... the Tribunal is satisfied the applicant could safely relocate in India and by doing avoid a well founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1543.html</AustLII>
<text>8 The Application sought an order dispensing with compliance with Order 52, r 5(2) of the Federal Court Rules . However, in SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543 at [9] Lindgren J correctly concluded that " there is no rule providing for a time limit for the seeking of leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment of the FMCA ". His Honour further concluded that " there is an implied time limit of 21 days after the date of the interlocutory judgment ".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLQZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FMCA 194</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/194.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The Federal Magistrates Court dismissed an application to review the decision of the Tribunal on 20 February 2008: SZLQZ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FMCA 194. The Federal Magistrate dismissed the application pursuant to rule 44.12(1)(a) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 (Cth).

5 Rule 44 of the 2001 Rules provides as follows: 
 Show cause hearing (1) At a hearing of an application for an order to show cause, the Court may: (a) if it is not satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed -- dismiss the application; or (b) if it is satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed -- adjourn the proceeding and order a respondent to show cause at a final hearing why an order for the relief claimed should not be made on such of the grounds mentioned in the application as are specified by the Court; or (c) without making an order under paragraph (b), make final orders in relation to the claims for relief and grounds mentioned in the application. (2) To avoid doubt, a dismissal under paragraph (1)(a) is interlocutory. 
As rule 44.12(2) expressly provides, the dismissal of an application under rule 44.12(1)(a) is an interlocutory decision.

6 An appeal to this Court from an interlocutory decision of the Federal Magistrates Court requires leave: Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), s 24(1A). The Applicant appeared before this Court this afternoon unrepresented, although he did have the assistance of an interpreter.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>