<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLRL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 716 (20 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/716.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Applicant M171/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 220</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/220.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Although the Application for Leave to Appeal as filed in this Court on 4 March 2008 sought an order dispensing with compliance with O 52, r 5(2) of the Federal Court Rules , in SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543 at [9] Lindgren J correctly concluded that " there is no rule providing for a time limit for the seeking of leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment of the FMCA ". His Honour further concluded that " there is an implied time limit of 21 days after the date of the interlocutory judgment ". See also: Applicant M171/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 220 at [32] per Moore J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Harrington v Rich [2008] FCAFC 61</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/61.html</AustLII>
<text>7 No question arises in the present Application as to whether it was filed within time; the question is whether leave should be granted or refused. Considerations relevant to the exercise of that discretion are:
 
(i) whether in all the circumstances the judgment of the primary judge is attended by sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered by the Full Court; and 
 
(ii) whether substantial injustice would result if leave were refused, supposing the decision were wrong. See: Harrington v Rich [2008] FCAFC 61 at [25] per Sackville, Emmett and Jacobson JJ.

8 The proposed Grounds of Appeal as set out in the Draft Notice of Appeal are as follows (without alteration): 
 1. Jurisdictional error 2. Breached of procedural fairness 3. Berached of natural justice 
Particulars provided in respect of these grounds, as expressed in the Draft Notice of Appeal , state (without alteration):
 1. TRIBUNAL ASK FOR THE RE LOCATION &amp; FAILED TO SAK FOR THE INFORMATION. 2. THEY USED TELEPHONE CONFRENCE FOR ME.ITS TOO DIFFICULT FOR ME. 3. I NEED A GOOD HEARING:

9 It is considered that leave to appeal should be refused. A review of the reasons for decision of the Tribunal does not reveal any jurisdictional error, breach of procedural fairness or denial of natural justice. Nor do the reasons of the Federal Magistrates Court, albeit brief, disclose any self-evident appellable error.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1543.html</AustLII>
<text>6 Although the Application for Leave to Appeal as filed in this Court on 4 March 2008 sought an order dispensing with compliance with O 52, r 5(2) of the Federal Court Rules , in SZDGN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1543 at [9] Lindgren J correctly concluded that " there is no rule providing for a time limit for the seeking of leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment of the FMCA ". His Honour further concluded that " there is an implied time limit of 21 days after the date of the interlocutory judgment ". See also: Applicant M171/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 220 at [32] per Moore J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLRL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FMCA 196</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/196.html</AustLII>
<text>3 On 20 February 2008 the Federal Magistrates Court dismissed an application seeking review of the decision of the Tribunal: SZLRL v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FMCA 196. The Federal Magistrate dismissed the proceedings before that Court pursuant to r 44.12(1)(a) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 (Cth).

4 Rule 44.12 of the 2001 Rules provides as follows: 
 Show cause hearing (1) At a hearing of an application for an order to show cause, the Court may: (a) if it is not satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed -- dismiss the application; or (b) if it is satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed -- adjourn the proceeding and order a respondent to show cause at a final hearing why an order for the relief claimed should not be made on such of the grounds mentioned in the application as are specified by the Court; or (c) without making an order under paragraph (b), make final orders in relation to the claims for relief and grounds mentioned in the application. (2) To avoid doubt, a dismissal under paragraph (1) (a) is interlocutory. 
As r 44.12(2) expressly provides, the dismissal of an application under r 44.12(1)(a) is an interlocutory decision.

5 An appeal to this Court from an interlocutory decision of the Federal Magistrates Court requires leave: Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), s 24(1A). The Applicant appeared before this Court this afternoon unrepresented, although he did have the assistance of an interpreter.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>