<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tervonen v Finland [2008] FCA 781 (29 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/781.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/32.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).

36 The validity of the amended s 16 notice, excluding offences 55, 57 and 58, has been established by the decision of the Full Court in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 with supplementary reasons Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32. In any event, in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 , Brennan CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ said (at 539):
 "Lacking any power to review those decisions [including the giving of a s 16 notice], a s 19 magistrate must proceed on the footing that the order and the notice, if not invalid ex facie, were validly made."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/24.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).

36 The validity of the amended s 16 notice, excluding offences 55, 57 and 58, has been established by the decision of the Full Court in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 with supplementary reasons Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32. In any event, in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 , Brennan CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ said (at 539):
 "Lacking any power to review those decisions [including the giving of a s 16 notice], a s 19 magistrate must proceed on the footing that the order and the notice, if not invalid ex facie, were validly made."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/25.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/2067.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).

2 The general nature of the jurisdiction pursuant to s 21 of the Act is not in doubt it is a rehearing in which the Court reaches its own conclusions on the eligibility for surrender, although only having regard to the material before the Magistrate ( Dutton v O'Shane [2003] FCAFC 195 ; (2003) 132 FCR 352 at 386; Brock v United States of America [2007] FCAFC 3 ; (2007) 157 FCR 121 per Black CJ at [20] [24] and [29] and Rares J at [73] [80]). Tervonen challenges both satisfaction of the conditions precedent in s 19(1) and the conclusions on the merits of surrender reached by the Magistrate pursuant to s 19(2). In Tervonen [2007] FCA 2067 (at [6] [9]), I discussed the question as to how a review is to be conducted in relation to s 19(1). It is convenient to deal with the questions arising pursuant to s 19(2) in the first instance.

33 I need not repeat the discussion concerning the proper approach to this provision in a s 21 review set out in Tervonen [2007] FCA 2067 at [6] [9]. The approach most favourable to Tervonen is that the issues are to be decided on the merits. I will consider them on that basis in the first instance.

34 Section 19(1) is as follows:
 "(1) Where: 
 
 
 (a) a person is on remand under section 15;
 (b) the Attorney General has given a notice under subsection 16(1) in relation to the person;
 (c) an application is made to a magistrate by or on behalf of the person or the extradition country concerned for proceedings to be conducted in relation to the person under this section; and
 (d) the magistrate considers that the person and the extradition country have had reasonable time in which to prepare for the conduct of such proceedings; 
 
 
 
 
 the magistrate shall conduct proceedings to determine whether the person is eligible for surrender in relation to the extradition offence or extradition offences for which surrender of the person is sought by the extradition country."

35 Tervonen does not dispute that he was arrested pursuant to a provisional arrest warrant and was remanded in custody pursuant to s 15 of the Act on 4 July 2006 and then again on 8 March 2007. However, he claims that he was not on remand in relation to all of the extradition offences. That may be correct in one sense as the amended s 16 notice was served after the second remand, but I accept the submission on behalf of Finland that s 19(1) does not require that the applicant be on remand pursuant to s 15 in relation to each and every extradition offence. In any event, the point is academic in the sense that the offences which had been added after the last remand (57 and 58) are now excluded because of the decision of the Full Court as to the s 16 notice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1898.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1684.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 20 December 2007 I made orders pursuant to s 21(2)(b)(i) of the Extradition Act 1988 (Cth) (the Act) on the application of Jan Tervonen quashing an order of the second respondent made on 6 June 2007 that Tervonen was eligible for surrender to the first respondent, the Republic of Finland, for certain offences, and the consequent issue of a warrant pursuant to s 19(9) of the Act ( Tervonen v Finland [2007] FCA 2067). That decision was based upon the judgment of Rares J in Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs [2007] FCA 1684 ; (2007) 98 ALD 589 and consequent orders declaring invalid and quashing successive notices purporting to have been given pursuant to s 16 of the Act ( Tervonen v Minister for Justice and Customs (No 3) [2007] FCA 1898). That basis for the decision meant that I did not need to consider the other arguments raised on behalf of Tervonen. The Full Court allowed an appeal from the decision of Rares J ( Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 , corrected in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32). Consequently, on 6 March 2008, the Full Court allowed an appeal from my earlier decision, set aside the orders that I had made and remitted the matter to me to be determined according to law ( Republic of Finland v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 25).

20 It appears that Tervonen put a similar argument to Rares J in the proceeding challenging the validity of the s 16 notice see Tervonen [2007] FCA 1684 ; 98 ALD 589 at [33] [44]. Rares J decided that it was open to the Minister to form the relevant opinion but did not consider the correctness or otherwise of that opinion, the proceeding before him being a challenge on administrative law grounds.

21 In my opinion, it is tolerably clear in the present case that only the first three warrants would normally be regarded as being "for the arrest of the person for the offence", the other warrants being connected with coercive investigation. To borrow from Art 1 of the Treaty, it was only those warrants by which Tervonen had been charged by a competent authority with the relevant offences against the law of Finland, bearing in mind that an extradition treaty must be a treaty relating to the surrender of persons accused or convicted of offences (s 5). That conclusion is assisted by the failure of Finland to produce material to the Magistrate explaining the system as it applied to the issues in the case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Brock v United States of America [2007] FCAFC 3 ; (2007) 157 FCR 121</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/3.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The general nature of the jurisdiction pursuant to s 21 of the Act is not in doubt it is a rehearing in which the Court reaches its own conclusions on the eligibility for surrender, although only having regard to the material before the Magistrate ( Dutton v O'Shane [2003] FCAFC 195 ; (2003) 132 FCR 352 at 386; Brock v United States of America [2007] FCAFC 3 ; (2007) 157 FCR 121 per Black CJ at [20] [24] and [29] and Rares J at [73] [80]). Tervonen challenges both satisfaction of the conditions precedent in s 19(1) and the conclusions on the merits of surrender reached by the Magistrate pursuant to s 19(2). In Tervonen [2007] FCA 2067 (at [6] [9]), I discussed the question as to how a review is to be conducted in relation to s 19(1). It is convenient to deal with the questions arising pursuant to s 19(2) in the first instance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/35.html</AustLII>
<text>22 However, counsel for Finland submits that this argument is effectively foreclosed to Tervonen by the decision of the High Court in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528. There are certainly similarities between that case and this, as extradition was sought by the Republic of Austria, a civil law country as is Finland. The Full Court of this Court had held that, on the material placed before the Magistrate on behalf of the Republic of Austria, he could not properly be satisfied in terms of s 19(2)(a) and s 19(3)(a) of the Act that the duly authenticated warrant that he had before him provided for the arrest of the appellant as a person "accused" of the offences to which the warrant referred ( Kainhofer v Director of Public Prosecutions (1994) 52 FCR 341 at 359G). The Court had held that the Act and the Treaty with Austria (which appears to be similar to that in the present case) provided for the surrender of a person only if the person was "accused" or convicted of an extradition offence. Their Honours said ( Kainhofer 52 FCR at 358 359):
 "Neither the Act nor the Treaty, however, defines the circumstances in which a person is to be regarded as being "accused" of the offence or offences in respect of which surrender is sought. In the jurisprudence of this country, one would not normally speak of a person as a person who is "accused" of a criminal offence in the sense in which that expression is used in the Act unless legal proceedings for the imposition of a penalty in respect of the offence have been commenced by the laying before a magistrate or other appropriate official of an information or complaint alleging the commission of the offence or by the presentation to a court of an indictment alleging such commission or unless the person has been formally charged with the offence before an appropriate official following upon his arrest. That statement may not be exhaustive but, in any event, it would not be sufficient to establish that a person was "accused" of an offence to show only that a complaint had been made to the police alleging the commission of the offence or that the police, or other investigating body, were conducting inquiries to determine whether there was evidence of the commission of the offence sufficient to warrant the person being "accused" of the offence in the sense mentioned."

24 It is not at all clear to me what meaning is to be given to the words "for the offence" in s 19(3)(a) in the light of the decision of the High Court. The submission for Finland reduces the content of s 19(3)(a) (and so s 19(2)(a)) to mere authentication of the warrant. So far as the substance of the warrant is concerned, all that is necessary is to tick off the offences against those in relation to which extradition is sought. It is difficult to discern any reason in principle why the opinion of the Attorney-General in relation to s 16(2)(a)(i) should not be examinable by the Magistrate where appropriate and yet the opinion in relation to s 16(2)(a)(ii) and s 16(2)(b) can be dealt with on the merits by the Magistrate notwithstanding the earlier opinion of the Attorney-General. It is even more difficult to understand why a magistrate's satisfaction in relation to a provisional arrest warrant pursuant to s 12 should decide the relevant issue to the exclusion of a magistrate pursuant to s 19 where appropriate. Neither the Attorney-General nor the first Magistrate has any better means of deciding the point than would be available to a properly instructed magistrate acting pursuant to s 19. However, I can see no escape from the conclusion that the decision of the High Court in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 does have the effect as submitted on behalf of Finland.

25 On the merits of the issue, if it were open to be considered, in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 , Gummow J said (at 564):
 "The fundamental question is whether the person whose extradition is sought under Pt II is one in respect of whom there has been taken by the competent authorities in the extradition country a decision to invoke the operation of the criminal law by the taking of whatever steps are necessary to initiate what might fairly be described as a prosecution." 
The fact that his Honour did not agree with the conclusion of the Full Court in that case on that issue would not be of any significance here, as the facts here are considerably stronger than the facts in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528. There is nothing in the majority judgment in the High Court to indicate that they would have taken a different view in principle from Gummow J if the question had fallen for determination.

26 In my opinion, there is no substance to the issues raised by Tervonen concerning authentication of the warrants, bearing in mind the provisions of s 19(7) and s 19(8) of the Act and Art 8(2) of the Treaty. The original documents are in evidence.

27 It was also submitted that warrants 1, 2 and 3 were vitiated by a conflict of interest on the part of the prosecutor making the claim for those warrants as he was a victim of one of the other alleged offences, and so the warrants could not be authenticated. Even if a conflict were established, it would not affect authentication and there is no other relevant ground to oppose surrender available under s 19(2) on that basis.

36 The validity of the amended s 16 notice, excluding offences 55, 57 and 58, has been established by the decision of the Full Court in Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen [2008] FCAFC 24 with supplementary reasons Minister for Home Affairs v Tervonen (No 2) [2008] FCAFC 32. In any event, in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; 185 CLR 528 , Brennan CJ, Dawson and McHugh JJ said (at 539):
 "Lacking any power to review those decisions [including the giving of a s 16 notice], a s 19 magistrate must proceed on the footing that the order and the notice, if not invalid ex facie, were validly made."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dutton v O'Shane [2003] FCAFC 195 ; (2003) 132 FCR 352 at 386</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/195.html</AustLII>
<text>2 The general nature of the jurisdiction pursuant to s 21 of the Act is not in doubt it is a rehearing in which the Court reaches its own conclusions on the eligibility for surrender, although only having regard to the material before the Magistrate ( Dutton v O'Shane [2003] FCAFC 195 ; (2003) 132 FCR 352 at 386; Brock v United States of America [2007] FCAFC 3 ; (2007) 157 FCR 121 per Black CJ at [20] [24] and [29] and Rares J at [73] [80]). Tervonen challenges both satisfaction of the conditions precedent in s 19(1) and the conclusions on the merits of surrender reached by the Magistrate pursuant to s 19(2). In Tervonen [2007] FCA 2067 (at [6] [9]), I discussed the question as to how a review is to be conducted in relation to s 19(1). It is convenient to deal with the questions arising pursuant to s 19(2) in the first instance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Kainhofer v Director of Public Prosecutions (1994) 52 FCR 341 </tocase>
<text>22 However, counsel for Finland submits that this argument is effectively foreclosed to Tervonen by the decision of the High Court in Director of Public Prosections (Cth) v Kainhofer [1995] HCA 35 ; (1995) 185 CLR 528. There are certainly similarities between that case and this, as extradition was sought by the Republic of Austria, a civil law country as is Finland. The Full Court of this Court had held that, on the material placed before the Magistrate on behalf of the Republic of Austria, he could not properly be satisfied in terms of s 19(2)(a) and s 19(3)(a) of the Act that the duly authenticated warrant that he had before him provided for the arrest of the appellant as a person "accused" of the offences to which the warrant referred ( Kainhofer v Director of Public Prosecutions (1994) 52 FCR 341 at 359G). The Court had held that the Act and the Treaty with Austria (which appears to be similar to that in the present case) provided for the surrender of a person only if the person was "accused" or convicted of an extradition offence. Their Honours said ( Kainhofer 52 FCR at 358 359):
 "Neither the Act nor the Treaty, however, defines the circumstances in which a person is to be regarded as being "accused" of the offence or offences in respect of which surrender is sought. In the jurisprudence of this country, one would not normally speak of a person as a person who is "accused" of a criminal offence in the sense in which that expression is used in the Act unless legal proceedings for the imposition of a penalty in respect of the offence have been commenced by the laying before a magistrate or other appropriate official of an information or complaint alleging the commission of the offence or by the presentation to a court of an indictment alleging such commission or unless the person has been formally charged with the offence before an appropriate official following upon his arrest. That statement may not be exhaustive but, in any event, it would not be sufficient to establish that a person was "accused" of an offence to show only that a complaint had been made to the police alleging the commission of the offence or that the police, or other investigating body, were conducting inquiries to determine whether there was evidence of the commission of the offence sufficient to warrant the person being "accused" of the offence in the sense mentioned."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Zoeller v Federal Republic of Germany (1989) 23 FCR 282</tocase>
<text>31 Tervonen argues that at least one charge (offence 5) is barred by a time limitation in Finland and that the limitation of time in relation to offence 8 and offence 9 expired on 5 July 2007. It is submitted for Finland that that question is irrelevant as it does not arise pursuant to s 19(2). That proposition follows from the wording of the section together with the authority of the Court in Zoeller v Federal Republic of Germany (1989) 23 FCR 282 at 303. Tervonen submits that this should be qualified because Art 7(2)(d) of the Treaty requires setting out the relevant provisions of the statute creating the offence or a statement of the relevant law as to the offence including any law relating to the limitation of proceedings. It was also submitted on behalf of Finland that, certainly in relation to the first warrant, it is clear that criminal proceedings were commenced within the limitation period.

32 Whilst the effect of the Treaty when combined with s 11 of the Act may be to require production of information as to time limitations, there is nothing in the Treaty or the Act which would entitle the Magistrate to take that information into account in deciding eligibility for surrender. This may seem anomalous, but presumably the Attorney-General can take that information into account in exercising the discretions in relation to surrender pursuant to s 22 of the Act as well as the earlier discretion pursuant to s 16.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>