<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nationwide (Mercantile) Collections Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 824 (16 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/824.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Braams Group Pty Limited v Miric [2002] NSWCA 417 ; (2002) 44 ACSR 124</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2002/417.html</AustLII>
<text>19 It seems to me that this is a case which falls squarely within the principles stated by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Braams Group Pty Limited v Miric [2002] NSWCA 417 ; (2002) 44 ACSR 124. It is sufficient to refer to what was said by Stein JA at [41]-[42], [51] and [61].

20 For those reasons, the application will be dismissed.

21 I should point out that the originating process sought the injunctive relief as an interlocutory order, however, without objection by counsel for the Deputy Commissioner, Mr Johnson proceeded to seek the relief as final relief. However, as I have said, Nationwide has not made out a claim of abuse of process and I propose to dismiss the application. I order that the plaintiff pay the costs of the application. 

 I certify that the preceding twenty-one (21) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobson. 


 Associate:
Dated: 3 June 2008


 Counsel for the Plaintiff: J T Johnson 
 
 Solicitors for the Plaintiff: Sally Nash &amp; Co 
 
 Counsel for the Defendant: M L Brabazon 
 
 Solicitors for the Defendant: Australian Taxation Office Legal Services Branch 
 
 Date of Hearing: 16 May 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 16 May 2008 


 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/824.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>David Grant &amp; Co Pty Limited (Receiver Appointed) v Westpac Banking Corporation (1995) 184 CLR 265</tocase>
<text>2 Mr Johnson accepts that in light of the decision of the High Court in David Grant &amp; Co Pty Limited (Receiver Appointed) v Westpac Banking Corporation (1995) 184 CLR 265 , it is necessary for him to establish to my satisfaction that the pursuit of a winding up application in the present circumstances would amount to an abuse of process within the principles stated in Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/34.html</AustLII>
<text>2 Mr Johnson accepts that in light of the decision of the High Court in David Grant &amp; Co Pty Limited (Receiver Appointed) v Westpac Banking Corporation (1995) 184 CLR 265 , it is necessary for him to establish to my satisfaction that the pursuit of a winding up application in the present circumstances would amount to an abuse of process within the principles stated in Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>