<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Dunstan v von Doussa (No 2) [2008] FCA 827 (5 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/827.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Alexandra Private Geriatric Hospital Pty Ltd v Blewett (1985) 7 FCR 341</tocase>
<text>60 A decision may be set aside upon an application for judicial review if it is " so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it ": Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118 per Gibbs J. The test is an objective one: Alexandra Private Geriatric Hospital Pty Ltd v Blewett (1985) 7 FCR 341. Sheppard J there stated, at 357, that a court:
 ... ought not to reach the conclusion that the decision is so entirely unreasonable unless [it] is clearly of the opinion that no reasonable mind could reach it. The decision will not be vitiated just because a court itself believes that the decision is unreasonable. It must be satisfied that no person acting reasonably could arrive at such a decision. ...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 , 225 CLR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/72.html</AustLII>
<text>63 No error may be discerned in the delegate adopting that approach. There is, in any event, only limited scope for contending that a decision is unreasonable by reason of a failure to pursue inquiries: cf Luu v Renevier (1989) 91 ALR 39 ; Visa International Service Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2003] FCA 977 at [627] [628], [2003] FCA 977 ; 131 FCR 300 at 430 1 per Tamberlin J. Whatever may be the limits of an obligation upon a decision-maker to make inquiries when required to make relevant findings of fact, the obligation is even more confined when the administrative task being pursued is that of attempting to achieve a conciliated result. Only such inquiries need be undertaken by the delegate as are considered either appropriate or necessary to discharge the function of conciliation. The delegate is " not an independent arbiter charged with deciding an issue joined between adversaries " and was not bound to make his own inquiries for the purpose of forming a view about how a particular claim was to be resolved. Contrast: Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 at [26] , [2005] HCA 72 ; 225 CLR 88 at 99 per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>60 A decision may be set aside upon an application for judicial review if it is " so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it ": Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118 per Gibbs J. The test is an objective one: Alexandra Private Geriatric Hospital Pty Ltd v Blewett (1985) 7 FCR 341. Sheppard J there stated, at 357, that a court:
 ... ought not to reach the conclusion that the decision is so entirely unreasonable unless [it] is clearly of the opinion that no reasonable mind could reach it. The decision will not be vitiated just because a court itself believes that the decision is unreasonable. It must be satisfied that no person acting reasonably could arrive at such a decision. ...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dunstan v von Doussa [2008] FCA 97</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/97.html</AustLII>
<text>4 It should also be noted that an earlier interlocutory decision in these proceedings has caused to be joined the Attorney-General of the Commonwealth as the Fourth Respondent to the proceedings: Dunstan v von Doussa [2008] FCA 97. None of the remaining Respondents have taken any active part in the final hearing and each has instead filed a submitting appearance.

5 It is considered that the remaining claim for relief as made in the Further Amended Application should be dismissed.

6 The essential facts relevant to the decision not to revoke the Notice of Termination may be stated with some simplicity.

86 When the Attorney-General was joined as a party to the present proceedings, left open was this question as to whether he could seek an order for costs in the event that the Applicant was unsuccessful: Dunstan v von Doussa [2008] FCA 97 at [20] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Haneef v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1273 , 161 FCR 40</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1273.html</AustLII>
<text>54 An " improper purpose ", it has been said, " will not lightly be inferred and, by application of a presumption of regularity, will only be inferred if the evidence cannot be reconciled with the proper exercise of the power ": Industrial Equity Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649 at 672 per Gaudron J. A person challenging an exercise of power upon the basis of improper purpose has the onus of establishing that contention. Where the purpose of a decision must be ascertained by inference from other facts, there is a presumption of regularity: Haneef v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1273 at [278] , 161 FCR 40 at 88 per Spender J. An appeal has been dismissed: Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship v Haneef [2007] FCAFC 203 , 163 FCR 414.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Industrial Equity Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/46.html</AustLII>
<text>54 An " improper purpose ", it has been said, " will not lightly be inferred and, by application of a presumption of regularity, will only be inferred if the evidence cannot be reconciled with the proper exercise of the power ": Industrial Equity Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649 at 672 per Gaudron J. A person challenging an exercise of power upon the basis of improper purpose has the onus of establishing that contention. Where the purpose of a decision must be ascertained by inference from other facts, there is a presumption of regularity: Haneef v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1273 at [278] , 161 FCR 40 at 88 per Spender J. An appeal has been dismissed: Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship v Haneef [2007] FCAFC 203 , 163 FCR 414.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Jones v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission [2002] FCA 1054 , 76 ALD 424</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1054.html</AustLII>
<text>31 If attention is more specifically confined to the "Particulars" in fact provided in the Further Amended Application , there is no basis for concluding that the decision of the First Respondent was vitiated by reason of " apprehended bias ". A reasonable apprehension of bias must be " firmly established ": Re JRL; Ex parte CJL [1986] HCA 39 ; (1986) 161 CLR 342 at 352. It is not sufficient if a reasonable bystander " has a vague sense of unease or disquiet ": Jones v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission [2002] FCA 1054 at [100] per Weinberg J, [2002] FCA 1054 ; 76 ALD 424. In the present proceedings there is not even a basis upon which any such " vague sense of unease " could be supported.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Luu v Renevier (1989) 91 ALR 39</tocase>
<text>63 No error may be discerned in the delegate adopting that approach. There is, in any event, only limited scope for contending that a decision is unreasonable by reason of a failure to pursue inquiries: cf Luu v Renevier (1989) 91 ALR 39 ; Visa International Service Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2003] FCA 977 at [627] [628], [2003] FCA 977 ; 131 FCR 300 at 430 1 per Tamberlin J. Whatever may be the limits of an obligation upon a decision-maker to make inquiries when required to make relevant findings of fact, the obligation is even more confined when the administrative task being pursued is that of attempting to achieve a conciliated result. Only such inquiries need be undertaken by the delegate as are considered either appropriate or necessary to discharge the function of conciliation. The delegate is " not an independent arbiter charged with deciding an issue joined between adversaries " and was not bound to make his own inquiries for the purpose of forming a view about how a particular claim was to be resolved. Contrast: Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 at [26] , [2005] HCA 72 ; 225 CLR 88 at 99 per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/40.html</AustLII>
<text>38 A failure to take into account a relevant consideration only vitiates a decision if that consideration was one which the administrator was " bound " to take into account: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24.

39 None of the considerations identified by the Applicant are relevant considerations which the President was " bound " to take into account when making a decision pursuant to s 46PH(4). And some of the " Particulars " alleging considerations which, it is said, should have been taken into account do not fully set forth the facts relevant to the consideration relied upon.

40 One specific matter may be instanced. One "Particular" , again repeated in respect to the other Grounds of Review , asserts that the First Respondent failed to consider correspondence in which it is alleged the delegate " told the applicant he would be harmed if he continued the complaint ". Such a statement in correspondence emanating from the Commonwealth or its officers or delegates, without more, would be disturbing. The context, however, explains the true nature of what was being conveyed to the Applicant.

61 There is no objective basis upon which any such view could be reached in the present case. To the extent, for example, that it is alleged that it was unreasonable to take into account some considerations, a fundamental difficulty confronting the Applicant is that the considerations taken into account have been held to be relevant to the exercise of the discretionary power conferred by s 46PH(4). A further difficulty is that the weight to be given to any consideration is a matter for the First Respondent and not for the Court: Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24. Mason J there at 41 2, in an oft cited passage, observed:
 It follows that, in the absence of any statutory indication of the weight to be given to various considerations, it is generally for the decision-maker and not the court to determine the appropriate weight to be given to the matters which are required to be taken into account in exercising the statutory power.... I say "generally" because both principle and authority indicate that in some circumstances a court may set aside an administrative decision which has failed to give adequate weight to a relevant factor of great importance, or has given excessive weight to a relevant factor of no great importance. The preferred ground on which this is done, however, is not the failure to take into account relevant considerations or the taking into account of irrelevant considerations, but that the decision is "manifestly unreasonable". This ground of review was considered by Lord Greene MR in Wednesbury Corporation [[1948] 1 KB at 230, 233 4], in which his Lordship said that it would only be made out if it were shown that the decision was so unreasonable that no reasonable person could have come to it. This ground is now expressed in ss 5(2)(g) and 6(2)(g) of the AD(JR) Act in these terms. ... However, in its application, there has been considerable diversity in the readiness with which courts have found the test to be satisfied. ... But guidance may be found in the close analogy between judicial review of administrative action and appellate review of a judicial discretion. In the context of the latter, it has been held that an appellate court may review a discretionary judgment that has failed to give proper weight to a particular matter, but it will be slow to do so because a mere preference for a different result will not suffice. ... So too in the context of administrative law, a court should proceed with caution when reviewing an administrative decision on the ground that it does not give proper weight to relevant factors, lest it exceed its supervisory role by reviewing the decision on its merits. 
Nothing of that kind has been exposed in the present proceedings.

62 A further way in which the Applicant wishes to advance the Ground of unreasonableness, and also a way in which he seeks to contend that there has been a failure to take into account matters said to be relevant, is his repeated requests made of the Commission and the delegate as to the " need to gather more information ". The Applicant urged both the President of the Commission, and later the delegate, to make inquiries. The delegate took the position that it was not his task to conduct detailed inquiries with a view to resolving potentially competing factual accounts, but rather to seek to conciliate the complaint if at all possible. At the outset, in a letter written to the Applicant on 24 November 2006, the delegate wrote in part as follows: 
 As I have indicated in previous correspondence my function is not as such to make a final or binding determination of the factual issues in the complaint; I am not required to make an operative decision of these matters. I am to inquire into the complaint and to attempt to conciliate it. This may or may not be what you would wish ideally to be the position; you may wish that the legislation provided something different from this. But I do ask you to understand that that is what the legislation provides and that it is all that I can do. Please assist me by focussing on this and by bearing in mind during the conciliation that this is what is involved. It will help you to understand what I am doing and what I have done.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship v Haneef [2007] FCAFC 203 , 163 FCR 414</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/203.html</AustLII>
<text>54 An " improper purpose ", it has been said, " will not lightly be inferred and, by application of a presumption of regularity, will only be inferred if the evidence cannot be reconciled with the proper exercise of the power ": Industrial Equity Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [1990] HCA 46 ; (1990) 170 CLR 649 at 672 per Gaudron J. A person challenging an exercise of power upon the basis of improper purpose has the onus of establishing that contention. Where the purpose of a decision must be ascertained by inference from other facts, there is a presumption of regularity: Haneef v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1273 at [278] , 161 FCR 40 at 88 per Spender J. An appeal has been dismissed: Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship v Haneef [2007] FCAFC 203 , 163 FCR 414.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>O'Keefe Nominees Pty Ltd v BP Australia Ltd (No 2) [1995] FCA 1079 ; (1995) 55 FCR 591</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1995/1079.html</AustLII>
<text>87 Although it is by no means clear, it is considered that s 18(2) does not preclude an order for costs being made in favour of the Attorney-General. Such a conclusion is at least consistent with the following observations of Spender J in O'Keefe Nominees Pty Ltd v BP Australia Ltd (No 2) [1995] FCA 1079 ; (1995) 55 FCR 591 at 595. His Honour there addressed s 78A of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) as follows:
 Section 78A(2) provides that where an Attorney-General of the Commonwealth of Australia intervenes in proceedings in a court under that section, the Court may make such order as to costs against the Commonwealth or the State as the case may be as the Court thinks fit. In my opinion, where there is intervention by an Attorney-General under that section, the Court does not have power to order costs in favour of the intervening Attorney-General. Subsection (3) provides that where an Attorney-General has intervened in a court, then "for the purposes of the institution and prosecution of an appeal ... the Attorney-General shall be taken to be a party to the proceedings". The effect of this subsection is that, where an Attorney-General has intervened under s 78A for the purposes of an appeal, costs orders may be made against him or her or in his or her favour. But subs (4) provides that where the Attorney-General has instituted an appeal in which the Attorney-General has intervened, the Court hearing the appeal may make such order as to costs ... "as the court thinks fit".

88 The significance of according to the Attorney-General the status of " a party to the proceedings ", as explained by his Honour, is a reason for concluding that costs can be awarded both for and against the Attorney-General.

89 The orders of the Court are:
 
1. The Further Amended Application as filed on 7 March 2008 be dismissed. 
 
2. The Applicant to pay 80% of the costs of the Fourth Respondent.


 I certify that the preceding eighty-nine (89) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Flick. 

 Associate:

Dated: 5 June 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: The Applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Fourth Respondent: G McCarthy 
 
 Solicitor for the Fourth Respondent: M Dubey (Blake Dawson) 

 Date of Hearing: 24 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 5 June 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/827.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re JRL; Ex parte CJL [1986] HCA 39 ; (1986) 161 CLR 342</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/39.html</AustLII>
<text>31 If attention is more specifically confined to the "Particulars" in fact provided in the Further Amended Application , there is no basis for concluding that the decision of the First Respondent was vitiated by reason of " apprehended bias ". A reasonable apprehension of bias must be " firmly established ": Re JRL; Ex parte CJL [1986] HCA 39 ; (1986) 161 CLR 342 at 352. It is not sufficient if a reasonable bystander " has a vague sense of unease or disquiet ": Jones v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission [2002] FCA 1054 at [100] per Weinberg J, [2002] FCA 1054 ; 76 ALD 424. In the present proceedings there is not even a basis upon which any such " vague sense of unease " could be supported.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SBBS v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 361 , 194 ALR 749</tocase>
<text>67 Such a Ground " is a serious matter involving personal fault on the part of the decision maker ": SBBS v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 361 at [43] , 194 ALR 749 at 756. It is a Ground which should not have been advanced in the present proceedings. It is certainly considered that the Ground would not have been relied upon had the Applicant been legally represented.

68 Reliance upon this Ground was rightly abandoned by the Applicant during the course of the hearing on 28 March 2008.

69 At the outset of the hearing on 28 March 2008 of the Further Amended Application , Mr Dunstan sought leave to file yet a further variant of that Further Amended Application .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Visa International Service Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2003] FCA 977 , 131 FCR 300</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/977.html</AustLII>
<text>63 No error may be discerned in the delegate adopting that approach. There is, in any event, only limited scope for contending that a decision is unreasonable by reason of a failure to pursue inquiries: cf Luu v Renevier (1989) 91 ALR 39 ; Visa International Service Association v Reserve Bank of Australia [2003] FCA 977 at [627] [628], [2003] FCA 977 ; 131 FCR 300 at 430 1 per Tamberlin J. Whatever may be the limits of an obligation upon a decision-maker to make inquiries when required to make relevant findings of fact, the obligation is even more confined when the administrative task being pursued is that of attempting to achieve a conciliated result. Only such inquiries need be undertaken by the delegate as are considered either appropriate or necessary to discharge the function of conciliation. The delegate is " not an independent arbiter charged with deciding an issue joined between adversaries " and was not bound to make his own inquiries for the purpose of forming a view about how a particular claim was to be resolved. Contrast: Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 at [26] , [2005] HCA 72 ; 225 CLR 88 at 99 per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>