<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Inform Design and Construction Pty Ltd v Boutique Homes Melbourne Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 965 (25 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/965.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (No 2) (1996) 72 FCR 151</tocase>
<text>5 The principles that govern the award of costs in this Court are well settled. Section 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) confers upon the Court a wide discretion which must, however, be exercised judicially: Re Wilcox; Ex parte Venture Industries Pty Ltd (No 2) (1996) 72 FCR 151 at 152 per Black CJ. Detailed provisions in relation to costs are to be found in Order 62 of the Federal Court Rules. These are predicated upon the assumption that costs orders will normally be on a party and party basis. However, it is clear that the Court has a discretion under s 43 in appropriate cases to award costs on some other basis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225</tocase>
<text>6 There is a useful discussion by Sheppard J of the principles under which indemnity costs can be ordered in Colgate-Palmolive Co v Cussons Pty Ltd (1993) 46 FCR 225. There should be present some special or unusual feature in the case to justify a departure from the usual order that costs be paid on a party and party basis. Sheppard J set out some examples of such features. They included the bringing of proceedings in wilful disregard of known facts or clearly established law, the making of allegations that ought never to have been made, and an imprudent refusal of an order to compromise. Nonetheless, it must be remembered that each case has to be considered in the light of its own particular facts and care must be taken not to circumscribe the broad discretion as to costs by reference to closed categories.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Davids Holdings Pty Ltd v Coles Myer Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-383</tocase>
<text>7 Indemnity costs have been awarded on the basis of actions and/or defences maintained without a proper foundation. See, for example, Davids Holdings Pty Ltd v Coles Myer Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-383 and Ogawa v Spender [2006] FCAFC 68 ; (2006) 151 FCR 228.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ogawa v Spender [2006] FCAFC 68 ; (2006) 151 FCR 228</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/68.html</AustLII>
<text>7 Indemnity costs have been awarded on the basis of actions and/or defences maintained without a proper foundation. See, for example, Davids Holdings Pty Ltd v Coles Myer Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-383 and Ogawa v Spender [2006] FCAFC 68 ; (2006) 151 FCR 228.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Barrett Property Group Pty Ltd v Metricon Homes Pty Ltd (2007) 74 IPR 52</tocase>
<text>13 According to the respondent, even that slim hope must have dissipated once the respondent's evidence was filed on 15 May 2007. This set out clearly on oath the evidence of the three key individuals associated with the design of the Villa View, namely, Mr Di Natale, Mr de Weerd, and Mr Lazarovski. They each swore that the Villa View was based on changes made to earlier plans designed by the respondent over an extended period. They denied having seen, or having been aware of, any of the applicant's plans, or having inspected any of its homes: cf Barrett Property Group Pty Ltd v Metricon Homes Pty Ltd (2007) 74 IPR 52.

14 The respondent submitted that by that point it should have been obvious to the applicant and its advisers that its case could only succeed on the basis of subconscious copying and that this depended upon establishing sufficient points of similarity between the parties' plans to enable that inference to be drawn. However, such a case would be difficult to mount in the face of a credible and convincing explanation, supported by a clear documentary trail, of how the Villa View had independently evolved from the respondent's own earlier plans.

15 Finally, the respondent relied upon what it described as a Calderbank letter dated 17 August 2007. The purpose of such a letter is, of course, to encourage the recipient to consider carefully the consequences of proceeding further with the litigation. The party seeking a special costs order must show that the rejection of the offer that the letter contained was so unreasonable that the usual order should not be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dresna Pty Ltd v Linknarf Management Services Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 2) [2006] FCA 755</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/755.html</AustLII>
<text>21 The applicant referred to Dresna Pty Ltd v Linknarf Management Services Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 2) [2006] FCA 755 , where I said at [18] that the Court should not readily be persuaded that a case had no chance of success. The case in question had failed and, with hindsight, it might well have been anticipated that this was precisely what would occur. Nonetheless, there were some imponderables.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Black v Lipovac (by his next friend Lipovac) [1998] FCA 699 ; (1998) 217 ALR 386</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/699.html</AustLII>
<text>22 With regard to the Calderbank letter, the applicant submitted that the making of such an offer, and its rejection, did not of itself justify a special order for costs. To justify such an order, the respondent bore the onus of establishing that the rejection of the offer was "imprudent" or "plainly unreasonable": Black v Lipovac (by his next friend Lipovac) [1998] FCA 699 ; (1998) 217 ALR 386. It was also necessary to consider whether, in all the circumstances, the offer by the respondent represented any real element of compromise or whether it was an "offer to capitulate" made essentially to trigger a possible claim at a later time for indemnity costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Alpine Hardwoods (Aust) Pty Ltd v Hardys Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 224 ; (2002) 190 ALR 121</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/224.html</AustLII>
<text>23 The applicant referred to Alpine Hardwoods (Aust) Pty Ltd v Hardys Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 224 ; (2002) 190 ALR 121 , where I observed that rejection of a reasonable offer was not the same as an unreasonable refusal to compromise. It was the latter that the respondent was required to establish.

24 The applicant also submitted that the offer made to it by the respondent, namely to withdraw and pay the respondent $35,000, might be viewed as not constituting a genuine Calderbank offer. That is particularly so in the light of doubts expressed in some of the authorities as to whether a "walk-away" offer can properly be characterised as an offer of compromise. The applicant noted that, despite an assertion in the supposed Calderbank letter that the sum of $35,000 was significantly less than outgoings already incurred, there was no evidence to support that statement. It submitted that it had not acted unreasonably in refusing to accept what it justifiably regarded as an ungenerous offer.

25 The present application is finely balanced. The respondent has acted reasonably and responsibly in pointing out to the applicant, from the outset, the weaknesses in the applicant's case. It has openly flagged its defence and repeatedly warned the applicant that it would seek indemnity costs if that defence ultimately succeeded. It also made an attempt to resolve this case without the need for a trial by its offer of 17 August 2007.

26 On the other hand, it would have been irresponsible of those advising the applicant to counsel surrender merely on the basis of assertions contained in correspondence from the respondent's solicitors. The matter becomes more problematic once discovery has been completed and evidence has been filed.

27 After giving this matter anxious consideration, I am not persuaded that the case brought by the applicant was so weak that it was unreasonable to pursue it. Although the documentary trail leading back from the Villa View through to the Villa Grand and ultimately the Mawsons Lake home proved to be powerful evidence in support of the respondent's denial that copying had taken place, that trail was littered with obstacles that had to be carefully navigated. The trail was not self-evident. It had to be explained and evaluated. Mr Wines only departed from his original opinion after being cross-examined at considerable length and being taken through the earlier plans in great detail.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>