<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Centrestage Management Pty Ltd v Riedle [2008] FCA 938 (20 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/938.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>De Garis v Neville Jeffress Pidler Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 292</tocase>
<text>40 The cases to which the Magistrate referred in the last sentence are De Garis v Neville Jeffress Pidler Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 292 at 302-303, Beck v Montana Constructions Pty Ltd [1964-5] NSWLR 229 at 235 and Pacific Software Technology Ltd v Perry Group Ltd [2004] 1 NZLR 164. Her Honour put the New Zealand case aside because it turned on legislation providing that a person who commissions the making of a computer program is the first owner of the copyright in the program ( Copyright Act 1994 (NZ) s 21).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Beck v Montana Constructions Pty Ltd [1964-5] NSWLR 229</tocase>
<text>40 The cases to which the Magistrate referred in the last sentence are De Garis v Neville Jeffress Pidler Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 292 at 302-303, Beck v Montana Constructions Pty Ltd [1964-5] NSWLR 229 at 235 and Pacific Software Technology Ltd v Perry Group Ltd [2004] 1 NZLR 164. Her Honour put the New Zealand case aside because it turned on legislation providing that a person who commissions the making of a computer program is the first owner of the copyright in the program ( Copyright Act 1994 (NZ) s 21).

63 The appellant relied heavily on the decision of Jacobs J in Beck v Montana Construction Pty Ltd [1964-5] NSWLR 229. That case concerned copyright architectural plans. The question was whether the owner of land who had paid for the plans to be used in the construction of houses on the land had an implied licence to use the plans. It was held that he did. Jacobs J said at 235:
 the engagement for reward of a person to produce material of a nature which is capable of being the subject of copyright implies a permission, or consent, or licence in the person giving the engagement to use the material in the manner and for the purpose in which and for which it was contemplated between the parties that it would be used at the time of the engagement. 
That of itself would not assist the appellant. It is common ground that the appellant is entitled to use the computer program without infringing copyright.

64 The appellant also relied on the observations of Kirby and Crennan JJ in Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design &amp; Developments Pty Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 229 CLR 577 at [59] and [69] to [73]. However, those passages go no further than to recognise, as in Beck , the existence of an implied right of a property owner or a successor in title to use architectural plans. It is true that at [60] their Honours referred to a line of patent cases where an implied licence to use and repair a patented item has been upheld as an implied licence that runs with the patented item itself. But they pointed out that the licence arises because of the rights conferred by letters patent to "make, use, exercise and vend" which can be reflected in the terms of a patent specification. Nothing in that case assists the appellant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pacific Software Technology Ltd v Perry Group Ltd [2004] 1 NZLR 164</tocase>
<text>40 The cases to which the Magistrate referred in the last sentence are De Garis v Neville Jeffress Pidler Pty Ltd (1990) 18 IPR 292 at 302-303, Beck v Montana Constructions Pty Ltd [1964-5] NSWLR 229 at 235 and Pacific Software Technology Ltd v Perry Group Ltd [2004] 1 NZLR 164. Her Honour put the New Zealand case aside because it turned on legislation providing that a person who commissions the making of a computer program is the first owner of the copyright in the program ( Copyright Act 1994 (NZ) s 21).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc [1986] HCA 19 ; (1986) 161 CLR 171</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/19.html</AustLII>
<text>41 An understanding of some basic concepts involved in the construction of a computer program assists in understanding the appellant's implied term argument. The following description of the general nature of a computer program is taken from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc [1986] HCA 19 ; (1986) 161 CLR 171 at 178-179. A computer program is a set of instructions designed to cause a computer to perform a particular function or to produce a particular result. A program is usually developed in a number of stages. First, the sequence of operations the computer will be required to perform is commonly written out in ordinary language. Next a source program is prepared, usually in a source code which is human-readable. The source code cannot be used directly in the computer, and must first be converted into an object code, which is machine-readable. The program is executed by the computer's central processing unit. See Data Access Corporation v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [4] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Data Access Corporation v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/49.html</AustLII>
<text>41 An understanding of some basic concepts involved in the construction of a computer program assists in understanding the appellant's implied term argument. The following description of the general nature of a computer program is taken from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc [1986] HCA 19 ; (1986) 161 CLR 171 at 178-179. A computer program is a set of instructions designed to cause a computer to perform a particular function or to produce a particular result. A program is usually developed in a number of stages. First, the sequence of operations the computer will be required to perform is commonly written out in ordinary language. Next a source program is prepared, usually in a source code which is human-readable. The source code cannot be used directly in the computer, and must first be converted into an object code, which is machine-readable. The program is executed by the computer's central processing unit. See Data Access Corporation v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [4] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Codelfa Constructions Pty Ltd v State Rail Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/24.html</AustLII>
<text>45 In Codelfa Constructions Pty Ltd v State Rail Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 at 345-346 Mason J adverted to the difference between these two categories of implied terms:
 Of course, I am speaking of an implied term necessary to give business efficacy to a particular contract, not of the implied term which is a legal incident of a particular class of contract, of which Liverpool City Council v. Irwin [1976] UKHL 1 ; [1977] AC 239 is an example. The difference between the two categories of implied term was mentioned by Viscount Simonds in Lister v. Romford Ice and Cold Storage Co Ltd [1956] UKHL 6 ; [1957] AC 555 at 576, where he referred to the search for the second category of implied term as being based 'upon more general considerations', a comment endorsed by Lord Wilberforce in Irwin at 255.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Liverpool City Council v Irwin [1976] UKHL 1 ; [1977] AC 239</tocase>
<text>45 In Codelfa Constructions Pty Ltd v State Rail Authority (NSW) [1982] HCA 24 ; (1982) 149 CLR 337 at 345-346 Mason J adverted to the difference between these two categories of implied terms:
 Of course, I am speaking of an implied term necessary to give business efficacy to a particular contract, not of the implied term which is a legal incident of a particular class of contract, of which Liverpool City Council v. Irwin [1976] UKHL 1 ; [1977] AC 239 is an example. The difference between the two categories of implied term was mentioned by Viscount Simonds in Lister v. Romford Ice and Cold Storage Co Ltd [1956] UKHL 6 ; [1957] AC 555 at 576, where he referred to the search for the second category of implied term as being based 'upon more general considerations', a comment endorsed by Lord Wilberforce in Irwin at 255.

46 Liverpool City Council v Irwin [1976] UKHL 1 ; [1977] AC 239 ( Liverpool ) concerned multi-story council owned dwellings. The landlord retained control over common parts of the building. There had been a problem with vandalisation of the common parts. The question was whether the landlord was obliged to keep the common parts in repair. There was no express obligation to that effect in the leases. The House of Lords implied an obligation to take reasonable care to keep the common parts in reasonable repair and useability. After identifying instances of implication, including where there is an established usage in the relevant trade or activity and where without a term the contract will not work, Lord Wilberforce said at 254:
 The present case, in my opinion, represents a fourth category, or I would rather say a fourth shade on a continuous spectrum. The court here is simply concerned to establish what the contract is, the parties not having themselves fully stated the terms. In this sense the court is searching for what must be implied. 
After considering various possible implications, his Lordship went on at 254:
 In order to be able to choose between these, it is necessary to define what test is to be applied, and I do not find this difficult. In my opinion such obligation should be read into the contract as the nature of the contract itself implicitly requires, no more, no less: a test, in other words, of necessity. 
He then explained, by reference to the relationship between the parties (landlord and tenant) and the nature of the buildings (multi-occupation high rise dependent on stairs, lifts and chutes for access and liveability), that it was necessary that the landlord have some obligation to keep the common areas in repair. His Lordship concluded that since the test of the existence of the term was "necessity", the standard of repair required should not exceed what was necessary having regard to the circumstances.

47 The "necessity" test was adopted by the Privy Council in Tai Hing Cotton Mill Ltd v Liu Chong Hing Bank Ltd [1986] AC 80 at 104-105. The Board referred to Lord Salmon's explication of "necessity" in Liverpool --that the term sought to be implied must be one without which the whole transaction would become "inefficacious, futile and absurd".

50 Their Honours then quoted with approval the passage from Lord Wilberforce's speech in Liverpool set out at [46], and observations to the same effect by the House of Lords in Scally v Southern Health and Social Services Board [1992] 1 AC 294 at 307.

52 The appellant's contention that a contract for the supply of a computer program carries with it an implied licence to use the program and call for the source code is a claim for Chitty's "standardised" implied term that is not dependent on the intentions of the parties, actual or presumed. In order to determine whether the "necessity" test in Liverpool and the later cases is satisfied in relation to contracts for the supply of computer programs, it is necessary to consider the provisions of Division 4A of Part III of the Act.

53 This Division was inserted by the Copyright Amendment (Computer Programs) Act 1999 . It is headed Acts not constituting infringements of copyright in computer programs . Section 47AB provides that in Division 4A
 computer program includes any literary work that is: (i) incorporated in, or associated with, a computer program; and (ii) essential to the effective operation of a function of that computer program. 
That section builds on the definition of "computer program" in s 10, which is in Part II Interpretation :
 a set of statements or instructions to be used directly or indirectly in a computer in order to bring about a certain result.

54 Section 47D, which is headed Reproducing computer programs to make interoperable products , provides:
 
 
 (1) Subject to this Division, the copyright in a literary work that is a computer program is not infringed by the making of a reproduction or adaptation of the work if: 
 
 
 
 (a) the reproduction or adaptation is made by, or on behalf of, the owner or licensee of the copy of the program (the original program) used for making the reproduction or adaptation; and
 (b) the reproduction or adaptation is made for the purpose of obtaining information necessary to enable the owner or licensee, or a person acting on behalf of the owner or licensee, to make independently another program (the new program), or an article, to connect to and be used together with, or otherwise to interoperate with, the original program or any other program; and
 (c) the reproduction or adaptation is made only to the extent reasonably necessary to obtain the information referred to in paragraph (b); and
 (d) to the extent that the new program reproduces or adapts the original program, it does so only to the extent necessary to enable the new program to connect to and be used together with, or otherwise to interoperate with, the original program or the other program; and
 (e) the information referred to in paragraph (b) is not readily available to the owner or licensee from another source when the reproduction or adaptation is made. 
 
 
 
 (2) Subsection (1) does not apply to the making of a reproduction or adaptation of a computer program from an infringing copy of the computer program.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tai Hing Cotton Mill Ltd v Liu Chong Hing Bank Ltd [1986] AC 80</tocase>
<text>47 The "necessity" test was adopted by the Privy Council in Tai Hing Cotton Mill Ltd v Liu Chong Hing Bank Ltd [1986] AC 80 at 104-105. The Board referred to Lord Salmon's explication of "necessity" in Liverpool --that the term sought to be implied must be one without which the whole transaction would become "inefficacious, futile and absurd".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd [1995] HCA 24 ; (1995) 185 CLR 410</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/24.html</AustLII>
<text>48 The implication of terms "independent of intention" was considered in some detail in the judgment of McHugh and Gummow JJ in Byrne v Australian Airlines Ltd [1995] HCA 24 ; (1995) 185 CLR 410 ( Byrne ). At 447-448 their Honours said:
 What, then, is involved in the proposition that a contractual term is implied as a matter of law rather than as the assumed intention of the parties? There is at least one basic distinction. It is that ... terms implied by the application of what one might call the business efficacy test are terms unique to the particular contract in question, depending upon the form of the contract, the express terms and the surrounding circumstances. By contrast, terms implied by law are, in general, implied in all contracts of a particular class or which answer a given description.

49 Later at 450 their Honours said:
 Many of the terms now said to be implied by law in various categories of case reflect the concern of the courts that, unless such a term be implied, the enjoyment of the rights conferred by the contract would or could be rendered nugatory, worthless, or, perhaps, be seriously undermined. Hence, the reference in the decisions to "necessity". This notion of "necessity" has been crucial in the modern cases in which the courts have implied for the first time a new term as a matter of law.

66 In Byrne at 422 Brennan CJ, Dawson and Toohey JJ approved the following passage from the reasons of Deane J in Hawkins v Clayton [1988] HCA 15 ; (1988) 164 CLR 539 at 573:
 The most that can be said consistently with the need for some degree of flexibility is that, in a case where it is apparent that the parties have not attempted to spell out the full terms of their contract, a court should imply a term by reference to the imputed intention of the parties if, but only if, it can be seen that the implication of the particular term is necessary for the reasonable or effective operation of a contract of that nature in the circumstances of the case.

67 No term such as that sought by the appellant can be supported on the business efficacy basis. The existence of ss 47D and 47E show that the implication of the term is not necessary for the reasonable or effective operation of the particular contract in the circumstances of the case.

68 As part of its implied term case the appellant submitted that regardless of whether the respondent was its employee or an independent contractor, the purchase of a computer program includes, ipso facto, the source code. This was said to be so because of what counsel described as the "definition of " a computer program in s 21(5) of the Act:
 For the purposes of this Act, a computer program is taken to have been reproduced if: (a) an object code version of the program is derived from the program in source code by any process including compilation; or (b) a source code version of the program is derived from the program in object code by any process, including decompilation; and any such version is taken to be a reproduction of the program.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Scally v Southern Health and Social Services Board [1992] 1 AC 294</tocase>
<text>50 Their Honours then quoted with approval the passage from Lord Wilberforce's speech in Liverpool set out at [46], and observations to the same effect by the House of Lords in Scally v Southern Health and Social Services Board [1992] 1 AC 294 at 307.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design &amp; Developments Pty Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 229 CLR 577</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/55.html</AustLII>
<text>64 The appellant also relied on the observations of Kirby and Crennan JJ in Concrete Pty Ltd v Parramatta Design &amp; Developments Pty Ltd [2006] HCA 55 ; (2006) 229 CLR 577 at [59] and [69] to [73]. However, those passages go no further than to recognise, as in Beck , the existence of an implied right of a property owner or a successor in title to use architectural plans. It is true that at [60] their Honours referred to a line of patent cases where an implied licence to use and repair a patented item has been upheld as an implied licence that runs with the patented item itself. But they pointed out that the licence arises because of the rights conferred by letters patent to "make, use, exercise and vend" which can be reflected in the terms of a patent specification. Nothing in that case assists the appellant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Avel v Multicoin Amusements Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 58 ; (1991) 171 CLR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/58.html</AustLII>
<text>79 The appellant complained that the Magistrate imposed on it the burden of establishing that it had a licence to use the source code, whereas the burden lay on the respondent to show that the appellant did not have such a licence. It relied on Avel v Multicoin Amusements Pty Ltd [1990] HCA 58 ; (1991) 171 CLR 88 at 94-95. However all that was there decided was that the onus of proving the absence of the licence of the owner of copyright in relation to an issue of infringement under s 37 or s 38 of the Act lies on the party asserting infringement. That is because the absence of such licence constitutes an element of the wrong of infringement under those sections. The present case is not for infringement of copyright, and the onus submission fails.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>TSB Retail Systems Pty Ltd v 3Fold Resources Pty Ltd (No 3) (2007) 72 IPR 492</tocase>
<text>80 The same onus submission was made in relation to defects the appellant submitted existed in the program. The respondent disputed their existence. The appellant contended that the burden was on the respondent to prove there were no defects. Reliance was placed on TSB Retail Systems Pty Ltd v 3Fold Resources Pty Ltd (No 3) (2007) 72 IPR 492 at [125]. That was an infringement case. One of the defences was that the respondent was authorised to reproduce the drawings there in question. Finkelstein J said that the copyright owner had the onus of proving the absence of authorisation "for that is an element of the cause of action for copyright infringement".

81 The burden of proving the existence of defects remained with the appellant. The Magistrate was not satisfied that there were defects. Her Honour considered this issue in detail at [61] to [66] of her reasons. No error has been shown in her treatment of it.

82 The appeal must be dismissed with costs.

 I certify that the preceding eighty-two (82) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Sundberg. 


 Associate:

Dated: 20 June 2008

 Counsel for the Appellant: R Dean 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: R &amp; G Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: M Rivette 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Middletons 

 Date of Hearing: 2 June 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 20 June 2008 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/938.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Stevens v Brodribb Sawmilling Co Pty Ltd [1986] HCA 1 ; (1986) 160 CLR 16</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/1.html</AustLII>
<text>11 The parties were basically in agreement as to the law to be applied in answering this question. In Stevens v Brodribb Sawmilling Co Pty Ltd [1986] HCA 1 ; (1986) 160 CLR 16 at 24 Mason J said:
 A prominent factor in determining the nature of the relationship between a person who engages another to perform work and the person so engaged is the degree of control which the former can exercise over the latter .... But the existence of control, whilst significant, is not the sole criterion by which to gauge whether a relationship is one of employment. The approach of this Court has been to regard it merely as one of a number of indicia which must be considered in the determination of that question .... Other relevant matters include, but are not limited to, the mode of remuneration, the provision and maintenance of equipment, the obligation to work, the hours of work and provision for holidays, the deduction of income tax and the delegation of work by the putative employee.

13 The cases have identified many indicia, in addition to those to which Mason J referred, that are relevant to the inquiry. See, for example, Vabu Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 33 ATR 537 at 538 and D &amp; D Tolhurst Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (1997) 38 ATR 1001 at 1013-1014.

14 The Magistrate first instructed herself in accordance with the relevant authorities, including those referred to above. She then noted various indicia relevant to the characterisation process. They included that the respondent was a sole operator, had an ABN, sent invoices which included GST, used his own motor vehicle and secretarial facilities without expenses or allowances from the appellant, was at liberty to take other work, worked at home without supervision, and attended meetings with the appellant's clients without the appellant being present. Her Honour also recorded that the appellant did not advise the Tax Office that the respondent was its employee and did not deduct PAYE. Nor was the respondent provided with sick leave, annual leave or superannuation. The Magistrate referred to other indicia, pointing one way or the other. See [16] to [54].

15 The appellant summarised its complaints about the Magistrate's characterisation of the respondent's work status in three propositions:
 
(a) her Honour was incorrect in deciding that the indicia she relied upon were the correct set of indicia and were exhaustive of the determination of that issue;
 
(b) her Honour ignored or gave little or no regard to concrete written expressions by the respondent of his intentions as to the nature and terms of "the employment";
 
(c) her Honour gave no weight or no sufficient weight to
 
(i) the nature of the relationship between the parties, including industry practice, and
 
(ii) "implications that should arise as a consequence of the need to give business efficacy to the agreement".

16 In a comprehensive and detailed set of reasons on this issue, covering sixteen pages, the Magistrate dealt with many matters other than those to which she ultimately accorded particular weight, including those the subject of particular complaint in pars (b) and (c) at [15]. Having done so, her Honour announced her conclusion as follows:
 Taking into account all of the matters mentioned above and considering the matter as a whole, it is clear to me that the respondent worked for the applicant as an independent contractor. The respondent had his own ABN. He charged the applicant GST. The applicant claimed an input tax credit for the GST. The applicant did not [deduct] pay as you go income-tax instalment deductions from the amounts paid to the respondent. The respondent charged the applicant a fixed price for the work. The respondent was given no holiday pay, sick pay, superannuation or workers compensation insurance. The respondent was free to take other work and did including other work from the Salvation Army. The respondent, in my view, was clearly in business on his own account. Notwithstanding that Mr Roberts exercised some control over the overall direction of the project, and the respondent was doing a major job for the applicant, the respondent was not an employee.

17 The Magistrate did not treat the matters recorded in the second to seventh sentences of that passage as a "correct set of indicia". They were the matters that appealed to her as determinative after weighing and balancing a much larger range of indicia, including those relied on by the appellant. On a fair reading of the Magistrate's reasons, it cannot be said that the list of specific matters recorded in the passage quoted at [16] was propounded as "exhaustive of the determination of that question".

18 For the same reason I do not accept Counsel's oral variation of the "correct set of indicia" submission. This was that the Magistrate ticked off the matters on her check list and thus reached the wrong result because the list was incomplete.

19 For the foregoing reasons there is in my view no substance in complaint (a) at [15].

20 The "concrete written expressions" of the respondent's intentions as to the "nature and terms of his employment" in complaint (b) at [15] were twofold. The first was that in his "Proposal to Develop a Call Centre Application" sent to Mr Roberts on 20 May 2004, he described himself as "Centre Stage Management Development Manager (Tony Riedle)". As to the significance of this title, the Magistrate said:
 The applicant says that this means that the respondent acknowledged that he was not an independent contractor but that he occupied a position as a designated employee of the applicant. In my view, that reads too much into the title the respondent gave himself. The proposal was to be provided to the Salvation Army. As between the applicant and the Salvation Army, the respondent was on the applicant's team. That was sufficient to explain the respondent's description of his position. The description does not seem to me to indicate that the respondent was holding himself out as an employee. In any event, it would only be evidence of his view at the time. As previously stated, I do not consider the views of the parties, or even their solicitors, to be of significant weight in the context of this case.

41 An understanding of some basic concepts involved in the construction of a computer program assists in understanding the appellant's implied term argument. The following description of the general nature of a computer program is taken from the judgment of Gibbs CJ in Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc [1986] HCA 19 ; (1986) 161 CLR 171 at 178-179. A computer program is a set of instructions designed to cause a computer to perform a particular function or to produce a particular result. A program is usually developed in a number of stages. First, the sequence of operations the computer will be required to perform is commonly written out in ordinary language. Next a source program is prepared, usually in a source code which is human-readable. The source code cannot be used directly in the computer, and must first be converted into an object code, which is machine-readable. The program is executed by the computer's central processing unit. See Data Access Corporation v Powerflex Services Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 49 ; (1999) 202 CLR 1 at [4] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Roy Morgan Research Centre Pty v Commissioner of State Revenue (Victoria) 37 ATR 528</tocase>
<text>12 In Roy Morgan Research Centre Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (Victoria) (1997) 37 ATR 528 at 533 the Victorian Court of Appeal said that the determination of the employee/independent contractor question involves identifying factors or indicia that are capable of pointing in one direction or another, none of which is conclusive, and weighing or balancing them in order to reach a conclusion.

23 Another indicator that the respondent saw himself as an employee is said to lie in the words used on the front of the proposal to the Salvation Army: "The information in this proposal is [proprietary] and is for the sole use of Centre Stage Management in conjunction with the Salvation Army Family Stores". This was said to demonstrate "his view of the terms of the agreement and it was not that he owned the copyright". The Magistrate said this did not greatly assist in determining the employee/independent contractor issue. She said that at most, it might indicate what one of the parties might have thought the relationship was, and that in this case that was not a matter of significant weight.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>