<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Sebastian v State of Western Australia [2008] FCA 926 (19 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/926.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v The Shell Company of Australia Limited (1997) 72 FCR 386</tocase>
<text>26 I am not persuaded that this is necessarily the case. Common Law Superior Courts of record do not become functus officio merely upon the making and entry of the judgment or order that determines the rights of the parties: they retain power in the same suit to make supplemental orders not limited to orders in aid of the enforcement and working out of the order determining the rights of the parties. So observed Drummond J in Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v The Shell Company of Australia Limited (1997) 72 FCR 386 at 395. His Honour also observed that this Court's ancillary powers flow from authority under ss 22 and 23 of the FCA Act to resolve the whole of the controversy between the parties.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Birri-Gubba (Cape Upstart) People v State of Queensland [2008] FCA 659 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/659.html</AustLII>
<text>55 The issues involved are, at one level, complex. The applicants in the first motion have not been represented by solicitors or counsel. I would not, in the circumstances, be prepared to characterise the conduct of the applicants in the first motion as being unreasonable. This is so, even though I have concluded that the first motion has no reasonable prospect of success. The position may well have been different if the applicants in the first motion had been represented by experienced lawyers: cf Birri-Gubba (Cape Upstart) People v State of Queensland [2008] FCA 659. [37] These observations should not be seen in any way as a reflection on Ms Hanigan. Ms Hanigan is a law student who I have no doubt has been doing her best to represent the interests of the applicants in the first motion. They are not in receipt of public funding.

56 Furthermore, the articulation by Ms Hanigan of the two issues, which I have dealt with, together with her concession, quite properly made, that the resolution of these adverse to those whom she represents would justify the summary dismissal of the first motion greatly reduced both the time of the hearing and the issues for judgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasian Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1352.html</AustLII>
<text>21 Section 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ("FCA Act ") lowers the bar for obtaining summary judgment, including summary dismissal: White Industries Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 511 ; (2007) 160 FCR 298. It is nonetheless not relief which is granted lightly and the Court should be cautious in dismissing proceedings pursuant to s 31A: Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720. The utility of bringing such a motion in the present circumstances is questionable when, inevitably, there was, in effect, full argument on the first motion as the means of considering the motion for dismissal. I will refer to the Walman Yawuru respondents, in respect to the dismissal motion, simply as the respondents.

30 It is for the applicant to establish the grounds to warrant an order for dismissal under s 31A: Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; 236 ALR 720. Nonetheless the respondents submit that two issues arise on the first motion which, if resolved against them, would justify an order for dismissal. I take this concession to mean that if the applicant satisfies me that the respondents have no reasonable prospects of successfully demonstrating that the two issues are serious issues to be tried then the first motion ought to be summarily dismissed. Both issues reflect the core submission of the respondents which is to the effect that the applicant has no authority to negotiate future acts, on behalf of the Yawuru Community which includes the Walman Yawuru clan, with the State. In this way the matters for judgment have been significantly confined.

31 The first issue is as to whether the applicant is the "native title party" for the purpose of negotiating with the State in respect to future acts. It involves consideration of s 30(2) of the Act . Properly understood this issue does not involve any question of the construction of that statutory provision but rather, whether, on the facts, the provision presently has application.

32 The requirement to negotiate in respect to future acts is provided for in Subdivision P of Div 3 of Part 2 of the Act . Notification must be given by a Government party, before the act is done, relevantly here, to the registered native title claimant, which is by definition also the native title party (ss 29(2)(b) and 30 (1)(a); definition of "registered native title claimant" in s 253).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Caboolture Park Shopping Centre Pty Ltd (in Liquidation) v White Industries (Qld) Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 471 ; (1993) 45 FCR 224</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/471.html</AustLII>
<text>27 This Court has power to make supplemental orders and the exercise of this jurisdiction, while no doubt requiring caution, is not limited to the making of orders in aid of the enforcement and working out of original orders, although to do so may be appropriate: Caboolture Park Shopping Centre Pty Ltd (in Liquidation) v White Industries (Qld) Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 471 ; (1993) 45 FCR 224 at 234-236. These principles were reaffirmed recently by a Full Court in Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd v Energizer Australia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 47.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>James on behalf of the Martu People v State of Western Australia [2002] FCA 1208</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1208.html</AustLII>
<text>40 This drafting addressed a perceived hiatus in the Act whereby, once a native title determination had been made and taken effect over an area of land, the Registrar of the Federal Court would notify the Native Title Registrar pursuant to s 189A(b) of the Act and the Native Title Register would then be amended to remove the entry pursuant to s 190(4)(d) of the Act if the application was finalised. Early determinations became effective immediately with respect to areas where native title had been extinguished, as well as areas where native title existed, but allowed a period of time for nomination of a prescribed body corporate. An example of this is to be found in the orders made in James on behalf of the Martu People v State of Western Australia [2002] FCA 1208. In such a case, there was an hiatus period between removal of the entry from the Register of Native Title Claims and thereby removal of the details of the registered native title claimant and the entry onto the National Native Title Register of the PBC: s 193(2)(e) of the Act . In James , a period of 3 months was allowed for nomination of a PBC. Arguably, in this period there was no native title party (s 253 of the Act ) to notify or to negotiate with for the purposes of Part 2 Division 3 of the Act .

41 Since the orders of 28 April 2006 were made in these proceedings, s 190 of the Act has been amended, by s 100 of the Native Title Amendment (Technical Amendments) Act 2007 (No 125 of 2007), in the following terms:
 100. After paragraph 190(4)(d) Insert: 
 
 (da) if an approved determination of native title is made to the effect that native title exists in relation to an area: 
 
 (i) but no determination has yet been made under section 56; or (ii) a determination has been made under section 56 that the native title rights and interests are to be held by the common law holders, but no determination has yet been made under subsection 57(2) of which prescribed body corporate is to perform the functions mentioned in subsection 57(3); 
 
 amend the entry on the Register that relates to the claim so that it reflects that fact;...

42 The Explanatory Memorandum to the Native Title Amendment (Technical Amendments) Bill 2007 ("the Explanatory Memorandum") at 1.319 and 1.320 relevantly states:
 Item 100 would insert paragraph 190(4)(da). Proposed paragraph 190(4)(da) would make clear that when a determination of native title has been made but no RNTBC has yet been determined, the Register of Native Title Claims should be amended to reflect that situation. The NNTT currently proceeds on the basis that the claim is not finalised until the RNTBC has been determined or registered, which ensures that the native title holders may still be notified of any proposed future acts pending registration. However, this approach gives rise to confusion where the determination establishes that native title has been extinguished over parts of the claim area, in so far as the National Native Title Register will not reflect this (and could suggest that the claimants continue to have procedural rights over those parts).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd v Energizer Australia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 47</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/47.html</AustLII>
<text>27 This Court has power to make supplemental orders and the exercise of this jurisdiction, while no doubt requiring caution, is not limited to the making of orders in aid of the enforcement and working out of original orders, although to do so may be appropriate: Caboolture Park Shopping Centre Pty Ltd (in Liquidation) v White Industries (Qld) Pty Ltd [1993] FCA 471 ; (1993) 45 FCR 224 at 234-236. These principles were reaffirmed recently by a Full Court in Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd v Energizer Australia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 47.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 3) [2002] FCA 876 ; (2002) 120 FCR 512</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/876.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The applicants in the first motion were originally applicants but became respondents to the proceedings on behalf of a subset of the Yawuru Community, known as the Walman Yawuru ("the Walman Yawuru respondents" ) . Their independent application for native title was dismissed: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 7) [2006] FCA 459. They were joined as respondents on their application, by order of Merkel J: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 3) [2002] FCA 876 ; (2002) 120 FCR 512.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 5) [2005] FCA 1025</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1025.html</AustLII>
<text>6 The Walman Yawuru respondents were found to have a special attachment to part of the claim area known as the Mangalagun area. However, it was not such as to constitute or give rise to a native title right or interest as defined in ss 223(1) and 253 of the Act . It followed that no rights or interests claimed by the Walman Yawuru respondents were possessed by them as members of the Walman Yawuru clan: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 5) [2005] FCA 1025 [233] and [375].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 6) [2006] FCA 82</tocase>
<text>7 In later reasons, Merkel J held that any native title rights and interest in the claim area were held by the Yawuru people on a communal basis and not by members of the Walman Yawuru on a group or clan basis and that they did not have native title rights and interests in that capacity in the claim area: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 6) [2006] FCA 82. [9]

8 Nonetheless, the Walman Yawuru respondents later contended that, as a result of this recognition of special attachment to specific areas in Rubibi (No 5) they were entitled, under s 225(c) of the Act to have that attachment recognised in the determination as an "other interest" in relation to the determination area. However, Merkel J held that the only "rights" or "interests" the Walman Yawuru clan members might have in relation to the Yawuru claim area were those held in any capacity they might have as members of the Yawuru Community and not "other interests" that were required to be set out in the determination pursuant to s 225(c) of the Act : Rubibi (No 7), [13]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 7) [2006] FCA 459</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/459.html</AustLII>
<text>4 The applicants in the first motion were originally applicants but became respondents to the proceedings on behalf of a subset of the Yawuru Community, known as the Walman Yawuru ("the Walman Yawuru respondents" ) . Their independent application for native title was dismissed: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 7) [2006] FCA 459. They were joined as respondents on their application, by order of Merkel J: Rubibi Community v The State of Western Australia (No 3) [2002] FCA 876 ; (2002) 120 FCR 512.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The State of Western Australia v Sebastian [2008] FCAFC 65 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/65.html</AustLII>
<text>9 The Walman Yawuru respondents were accordingly unsuccessful in the substantive proceedings. These findings were undisturbed on appeal: The State of Western Australia v Sebastian [2008] FCAFC 65.

10 The proceedings were the subject of final orders made by Merkel J in April 2006 in Rubibi (No 7) . Those orders were amended by orders of French J made on 23 November 2006, 30 April 2007 and 9 May 2007 pursuant to a limited liberty to apply. The final orders included: 
 
(a) a determination of native title in which it was determined relevantly that the native title is held by the Yawuru Community;
 
(b) orders dealing with the determination of a prescribed body corporate ("PBC") under s 56(1) or s 57(2) of the Act to hold the native title rights and interests on trust for the common law holders of the native title or to act as agent on their behalf; 
 
(c) liberty to apply to a Judge of the Court in respect of limited matters, namely matters arising out of the determination of a PBC and the inclusion in the Determination of maps showing the location of the determination area and of the areas comprising it; and 
 
(d) a declaration that, in respect of areas where native title has been determined to exist, the Rubibi proceedings are not "finalised" within the meaning of s 190(4)(e) of the Act until a PBC has been determined. 
 
 
 
 

The orders and declarations made by Merkel J on 28 April 2006 as well as the orders made by French J on 30 April 2007 are annexed to these reasons for ease of explanation.

11 Importantly, for reasons I will explain later, the determination as to the existence of native title does not take effect until the making of a determination in respect to a PBC under s 56(1) or s 57(2) of the Act .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>White Industries Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 511 ; (2007) 160 FCR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/511.html</AustLII>
<text>21 Section 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ("FCA Act ") lowers the bar for obtaining summary judgment, including summary dismissal: White Industries Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 511 ; (2007) 160 FCR 298. It is nonetheless not relief which is granted lightly and the Court should be cautious in dismissing proceedings pursuant to s 31A: Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720. The utility of bringing such a motion in the present circumstances is questionable when, inevitably, there was, in effect, full argument on the first motion as the means of considering the motion for dismissal. I will refer to the Walman Yawuru respondents, in respect to the dismissal motion, simply as the respondents.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>