<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLNW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 910 (17 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/910.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Applicants A233 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2004] FCAFC 296</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/296.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Smith FM noted that it was not necessary for the Tribunal to discuss the chance of harm occurring which it found was less than probable, provided the Tribunal made findings of fact which permitted a conclusion that the fear of persecution was not well-founded: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam and Others [1999] FCA 794 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220 at 239-241; Applicants A233 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2004] FCAFC 296 at [11] - [14] . His Honour noted that such a factual finding had been made by the Tribunal, and accordingly found that the Tribunal had not failed to appreciate or apply the 'real chance' test.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Chan Yee Kin v The Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1989) 169 CLR 379</tocase>
<text>19 Under this ground, three separate issues are raised. Firstly, the appellant submits that the Tribunal erred by failing to consider whether there was a real chance that the appellant would suffer persecution if he returned to Lebanon. The appellant submits that the Tribunal's finding that '... those targeted were easily identifiable members of SLA, mostly from Southern Lebanon...' did not take account of former SLA members who do not satisfy such profile. It is submitted that the Tribunal failed to apply the correct test because it did not take account of a person who did not have the characteristics relied upon by the Tribunal to reach its conclusion that there was no chance of persecution, and that its finding left open the possibility that the appellant could be the subject of persecution. The appellant submits that the Tribunal accordingly failed to apply the test in Chan Yee Kin v The Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1989) 169 CLR 379 where Mason CJ said at 389:
 
 If an applicant establishes that there is a real chance of persecution, then his fear, assuming that he has such a fear, is well-founded, notwithstanding that there is less than a 50 per cent chance of persecution occurring.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang and Others [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>20 Smith FM was not persuaded that the Tribunal failed to apply the 'real chance' test. His Honour, in rejecting the appellant's submissions, observed that the appellant had concentrated attention on particular parts of the Tribunal's reasoning in isolation from its general expression. His Honour noted that such approach had been discouraged in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang and Others [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 291. The Court is unable to find any error in his Honour's reasoning.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam and Others [1999] FCA 794 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/794.html</AustLII>
<text>13 Smith FM noted that it was not necessary for the Tribunal to discuss the chance of harm occurring which it found was less than probable, provided the Tribunal made findings of fact which permitted a conclusion that the fear of persecution was not well-founded: see Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Rajalingam and Others [1999] FCA 794 ; (1999) 93 FCR 220 at 239-241; Applicants A233 of 2003 v Refugee Review Tribunal [2004] FCAFC 296 at [11] - [14] . His Honour noted that such a factual finding had been made by the Tribunal, and accordingly found that the Tribunal had not failed to appreciate or apply the 'real chance' test.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 228 CLR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>36 The appellant relies upon SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 228 CLR 152 in which the High Court of Australia held that the Tribunal erred because it did not challenge or express any reaction to answers provided by the appellant and later rejected claims which had been accepted by the delegate.

37 
 
In SZBEL the High Court of Australia said at [35]:
 
 The issues that arise in relation to the decision are to be identified by the Tribunal. But if the Tribunal takes no step to identify some issue other than those that the delegate considered dispositive, and does not tell the applicant what that other issue is, the applicant is entitled to assume that the issues the delegate considered dispositive are "the issues arising in relation to the decision under review".

38 Smith FM said at [40]:
 
 The present case has no direct parallel with SZBEL, since the Tribunal's finding which is complained of did not concern an issue of credibility which appeared uncontentious in the delegate's decision. In the present case, the applicant first presented his full claims to the Tribunal, and in particular his claim to fear reprisal from individuals in whose arrest he had been involved more than 20 years previously.

39 Contrary to such finding, and the Minister's submission that SZBEL only relates to issues of credibility, the Court finds that SZBEL does apply. The decision in SZBEL makes it plain that if the Tribunal is to determine the application before it adversely to the applicant for a specific reason, it is obliged to put that circumstance to the applicant and to invite the applicant to respond. The Court in SZBEL said at [47]:
 
 But where...there are specific aspects of an applicant's account, that the Tribunal considers may be important to the decision and may be open to doubt, the Tribunal must at least ask the applicant to expand upon those aspects of the account and ask the applicant to explain why the account should be accepted. [emphasis in original]

40 The Tribunal letter addressed the appellant's claims relating to his fear of persecution including his claim that he feared persecution from individuals whom he had arrested, and invited the appellant to comment on such claims generally. It was necessary for the Tribunal to put directly to the appellant that one of its concerns was his inability to identify the persons who might harm him if the Tribunal was going to make a factual finding adverse to the appellant on that issue. Since the Tribunal had not specifically asked for the identity of the relevant persons at the hearing and had not requested details of such in the Tribunal letter, the appellant was not placed on notice that unless he provided such detail, the Tribunal might make an adverse finding against him.

41 The Court is satisfied that the 'issues to which those reasoning processes were directed' (see SZBEL at [21]) were not adequately notified to the appellant. The Tribunal's finding that the appellant could not 'name or identify those persons' was a finding in respect of an issue upon which the appellant had not been afforded an opportunity to respond.

42 The Court is satisfied that a breach of s 425 of the Migration Act has occurred. It follows that the appellant's appeal is upheld. The first respondent is to pay the costs of the appellant. 
 I certify that the preceding forty-two (42) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Cowdroy. 


 Associate:

Dated: 17 June 2008

 Counsel for the Appellant: Mr Prince with Mr Bradley 
 
 Solicitor for the Appellant: Henry Davis York 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr Cleary 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Date of Hearing: 21 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 June 2008 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/910.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZGHS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1572</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1572.html</AustLII>
<text>21 Secondly, the appellant submits that the Tribunal considered the risk of persecution in the past and present but did not consider that the appellant could suffer harm in the future. The appellant relies upon the decision of this Court in SZGHS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1572 at [28] - [30] which held that the Court must have an 'adequately forward-looking analysis' (see SZGHS per Allsop J at [30]) when considering the prospects of persecution.

22 The Tribunal's reasons show that in reaching its conclusion it considered external information together with information supplied subsequent to the hearing in a letter from the appellant's adviser. Such letter included an extract from an Amnesty International report which referred to the possibility of reprisal attacks by Hezbollah against former Israeli collaborators. The Tribunal found:
 
 The adviser argued that Hezbollah was subjecting former SLA members to persecution and the threat of harm has increased significantly since the outbreak of hostilities with Israel in 2006. The adviser referred the Tribunal to several reports dealing with reprisals against SLA members who were suspected of collaborating with Israel before and after the 2006 conflict. The adviser argued that the applicant will be at risk of imprisonment and denied protection by the State because he was with the SLA.

23 
 
The Federal Magistrate excerpted the above passage and concluded that the Tribunal had considered whether, in the future, the appellant would be subjected to the same risk.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZHBX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1169</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1169.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Smith FM said at [40]-[41]:
 
 In my opinion, it should have been apparent to him [the appellant] and his advisers when doing so, that the Tribunal might draw inferences from the absence of any identification of particular persons who were feared, or of incidents or circumstances which suggested that there were particular persons who had an interest in pursuing him after 20 years (compare Bennett J in SZJUB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1486 at [21] and SZHBX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1169 at [14] ). 
 In my opinion, the obligations on the Tribunal under s.425 to warn an applicant as to the issues in the review did not, in the present case, require it to alert the applicant to the possibility that it might draw an inference from his evidence that he could not name or identify the persons whom he claimed to fear.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZJUB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1486</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1486.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Smith FM said at [40]-[41]:
 
 In my opinion, it should have been apparent to him [the appellant] and his advisers when doing so, that the Tribunal might draw inferences from the absence of any identification of particular persons who were feared, or of incidents or circumstances which suggested that there were particular persons who had an interest in pursuing him after 20 years (compare Bennett J in SZJUB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1486 at [21] and SZHBX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1169 at [14] ). 
 In my opinion, the obligations on the Tribunal under s.425 to warn an applicant as to the issues in the review did not, in the present case, require it to alert the applicant to the possibility that it might draw an inference from his evidence that he could not name or identify the persons whom he claimed to fear.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>