<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Orica Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 906 (17 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/906.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hepples v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 3 ; (1992) 173 CLR 492</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/3.html</AustLII>
<text>11 Mr Steward for Orica drew attention to obstacles he maintained the Commissioner will need to overcome in order to establish some of the alternative formulations of his case. However, I do not regard any of the new bases upon which the Commissioner desires to proceed as bound to fail. Because I will in due course have to hear full argument on the various points, I do not propose to say any more about the Commissioner's prospects of success on the various alternatives. The argument on the merits of the proposed new paragraphs occupied only 40 minutes or thereabouts. It is more appropriate that the merits be ruled on after more sustained submissions at trial. In this connection Mason CJ's observations in Hepples v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1992] HCA 3 ; (1992) 173 CLR 492 at 497 are pertinent:
 The provisions of s 160M(5)(6) and (7) ... and provisions to which they are related are extraordinarily complex. They must be obscure, if not bewildering, both to the taxpayer who seeks to determine his or her liability to capital gains tax by reference to them and to the lawyer who is called upon to interpret them.

12 Other parts of the Statement were attacked on the basis of form or lack of particularity. These complaints are best dealt with, not by disallowing the amendments or giving leave subject to the Commissioner accommodating the complaints, but by Orica requesting clarifications or particulars.

13 Many of the amendments and additions to the "Facts" paragraphs of the Statement are useful clarifications and particularisations which will assist the parties and the Court more readily to understand the way the Commissioner's case is put.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Queensland v JL Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/1.html</AustLII>
<text>14 I have taken into account the discretionary considerations Orica has relied on, in particular the Commissioner's failure to provide an explanation for the delay in seeking to amend, and Orica's ongoing liability to general interest charge. On the other hand, I bear in mind what was said in the joint judgment in Queensland v JL Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146 , and the desirability of permitting a litigant to raise the issues he wishes to pursue even though, by doing so at a later stage, it causes inconvenience and expense to his opponent. I have also taken into account the complex nature of the provisions of Part IIIA that are involved in the case. See [11]. Unlike some of the cases relied on by Orica, the amendments are not sought shortly before trial. The Commissioner has always contended that Orica's rights under the Distribution Agreement are an asset for the purposes of Part IIIA , that Orica disposed of that asset in circumstances where there was a capital gain, and that the disposition of that asset was a taxable event. The proposed changes do not alter that stand. Rather they amplify the ways in which the Commissioner will contend that the events that happened, most of which are not controversial, gave rise to a taxable event. In this connection I note that the "Facts" paragraphs of the Statement ([1] to [29]) are not significantly altered. Apart from the added particularisations to which I have referred, and cosmetic changes to make certain paragraphs accord more closely with the underlying documents, only pars 17 and 20A are new. Those two paragraphs are, however, of no particular significance, and neither of them will disclose to Orica anything of which it was not already well aware.

15 I will give the Commissioner leave to file the Statement. However, he may wish to consider whether, in view of the new paragraphs dealing with the separate asset ([38A] to [38E]), par 33A should retain its present form.

16 The Commissioner must pay Orica's costs of the motion notice of which was filed on 21 April 2008.

 I certify that the preceding sixteen (16) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Sundberg. 


 Associate:

Dated: 17 June 2008

 Counsel for the Applicant: S Steward 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: M Wheelahan SC and F Alpins 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 

 Date of Hearing: 30 May 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 June 2008 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/906.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>