<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Medic-Care Company Ltd v Hamilton Pharmaceutical Pty Limited (ACN 008 204 635) (No 3) [2008] FCA 976 (24 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/976.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2008] FCA 678</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/678.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The two most recent decisions in this Court, Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Limited [2008] FCA 88 and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2008] FCA 678 , indicate that any legal professional privilege in the statement is lost when the document is filed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Limited [2008] FCA 88 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/88.html</AustLII>
<text>13 The two most recent decisions in this Court, Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Amcor Limited [2008] FCA 88 and Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2008] FCA 678 , indicate that any legal professional privilege in the statement is lost when the document is filed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Complete Technology Pty Limited v Toshiba (Australia) Pty Limited [1994] FCA 1314 ; (1994) 53 FCR 125 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1314.html</AustLII>
<text>14 There are, as I have said, authorities contrary to those two decisions and I was taken to them by Mr Robertson, counsel for the applicant. In Nilsen Industrial Electronics Pty Ltd v National Semiconductor Corporation (1994) 48 FCR 337 , Olney J held that statements filed in legal proceedings continue to attract legal professional privilege unless and until they are put into evidence. In Complete Technology Pty Limited v Toshiba (Australia) Pty Limited [1994] FCA 1314 ; (1994) 53 FCR 125 , Hill J, whilst disagreeing with the reasons given by Olney J, reached the same conclusion that legal professional privilege reposed in the document until it was read. He, however, relied upon the implied undertaking as to discovery for that decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Esso Australia Resources Limited v Plowman [1995] HCA 19 ; (1995) 183 CLR 10</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/19.html</AustLII>
<text>19 In Esso Australia Resources Limited v Plowman [1995] HCA 19 ; (1995) 183 CLR 10 at 33, Mason CJ said after referring to the implied undertaking as to discovery:
 It would be inequitable if a party were compelled by court process to produce private documents for the purposes of the litigation yet be exposed to publication of them for other purposes. No doubt the implied obligation must yield to inconsistent statutory provisions and to the requirements of curial process in other litigation, eg discovery and inspection, but that circumstance is not a reason for denying the existence of the implied obligation.

22 Whilst those documents are subject to the implied undertaking referred to in O 24 r 14A of the Hong Kong Rules, in my opinion, consistent with the decisions in Esso Australia Resources Limited v Plowman [1995] HCA 19 ; 183 CLR 10 and Patrick v Capital Finance Pty Ltd (No 4) [2003] FCA 436 , the applicant should make production of those documents in this jurisdiction. No doubt the applicant will, at or before making production, apply to the High Court of Hong Kong for a release from the implied undertaking in relation to those documents. I should say that the defendants in the Hong Kong proceedings have indicated they have no objection to the documents being produced.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harman v Home Department State Secretary [1983] 1 AC 280 </tocase>
<text>18 That rule states the rule in Harman v Home Department State Secretary [1983] 1 AC 280. Mr Robertson said that his client was unable to produce the document, which it has discovered, by reason of that rule. It seems to me that there are two answers to that proposition. The first is that whilst, of course, the implied undertaking in relation to discovery binds a party, it does not prevent a party making discovery under obligations of other rules of court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mulley v Manifold (1959) 163 CLR 341 </tocase>
<text>8 There are two answers given by the applicant in response to this aspect of the application. First, it is contended the respondent has failed to identify any documents which it says the applicant has failed to discover. Secondly, the applicant contends it has not been shown that any of that correspondence would be relevant in relation to any of the issues raised on the pleadings in this proceeding. I want to make it clear that whilst many of the rules relating to discovery have changed over the recent past it is still a requirement of discovery that the document which is sought to be discovered is relevant to an issue raised on the pleadings in the sense described by the High Court in Mulley v Manifold (1959) 163 CLR 341. Attempts have been made today to show that there might be evidence which would indicate that some correspondence could be relevant to this proceeding. That, in my opinion, is not an appropriate way of addressing the question of discovery and, in particular, in addressing a question of discovery so late in the proceeding and so shortly before trial.

9 It seems to me, if the respondent wishes to identify documents which it says ought to have been discovered, it must be able to do so precisely by reference to the pleadings and by reference to the document which it says ought to be discovered. In other words, it ought to be able to discharge the obligation which lies upon a party seeking further and better discovery. In my opinion, the respondent has failed to do so in respect of this category of documents and for that reason alone I would decline to make the order sought. However, I am also not persuaded, at this stage, that any of the documents sought are relevant in the sense to which I have referred.

10 The second category of documents has three groups of documents within it. First, it contains a witness statement given by a director of the applicant; and secondly, it lists a witness statement given by a defendant in the Hong Kong proceedings. Both of those documents were filed in the proceedings in Hong Kong. The third group of documents, within this larger category, are documents which were discovered by the defendants in the Hong Kong proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>Nilsen Industrial Electronics Pty Ltd v National Semiconductor Corporation (1994) 48 FCR 337</tocase>
<text>14 There are, as I have said, authorities contrary to those two decisions and I was taken to them by Mr Robertson, counsel for the applicant. In Nilsen Industrial Electronics Pty Ltd v National Semiconductor Corporation (1994) 48 FCR 337 , Olney J held that statements filed in legal proceedings continue to attract legal professional privilege unless and until they are put into evidence. In Complete Technology Pty Limited v Toshiba (Australia) Pty Limited [1994] FCA 1314 ; (1994) 53 FCR 125 , Hill J, whilst disagreeing with the reasons given by Olney J, reached the same conclusion that legal professional privilege reposed in the document until it was read. He, however, relied upon the implied undertaking as to discovery for that decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Patrick v Capital Finance Pty Ltd (No 4) [2003] FCA 436</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/436.html</AustLII>
<text>20 Chief Justice Mason's dicta was applied by Tamberlin J in Patrick v Capital Finance Pty Ltd (No 4) [2003] FCA 436 at [15] to [21]. The point which the Chief Justice made and which was applied in Patrick v Capital Finance Pty Ltd (No 4) [2003] FCA 436 is that, notwithstanding the implied undertaking, if rules of court of a jurisdiction apply to a party who has a document in that party's possession by reason of a process in another jurisdiction, that party is still obliged to comply with the processes in the second jurisdiction and make discovery of the document if it be an application for discovery and production if production follows upon discovery. For that reason, in my opinion, the document should be produced.

21 Secondly, there has been no suggestion made by the applicant that the applicant could not obtain a release from the implied undertaking in the High Court of Hong Kong. Indeed, the applicant has sought and obtained a release in relation to other documents. I infer from the fact that such a release has been obtained, that the applicant could obtain a release in relation to the implied undertaking in respect of the witness statement of Cheng Chun Keung. The same applies to the documents discovered by the defendants in the Hong Kong proceedings which are presently in the possession, custody or control of the applicant. The applicant has discovered those documents and the respondent seeks production of them.

22 Whilst those documents are subject to the implied undertaking referred to in O 24 r 14A of the Hong Kong Rules, in my opinion, consistent with the decisions in Esso Australia Resources Limited v Plowman [1995] HCA 19 ; 183 CLR 10 and Patrick v Capital Finance Pty Ltd (No 4) [2003] FCA 436 , the applicant should make production of those documents in this jurisdiction. No doubt the applicant will, at or before making production, apply to the High Court of Hong Kong for a release from the implied undertaking in relation to those documents. I should say that the defendants in the Hong Kong proceedings have indicated they have no objection to the documents being produced.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>