<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Alcon Inc v Bausch &amp; Lomb (Australia) Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1299 (12 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1299.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Air Express International (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian European Insurance (Brokers) Pty Ltd (1999) 49 IPR 435</tocase>
<text>In Air Express International (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian European Insurance (Brokers) Pty Ltd (1999) 49 IPR 435 , in dismissing opposition to an application for registration of the letters "AEI" and a logo comprised of those letters in a stylised format, the Deputy Registrar of Trade Marks said (at 439 440): 
 
 The question of trade marks consisting of three letters has long been an issue for the registrar. Under the old law, the Trade Marks Act 1955 (Cth), where it was a question of whether a trade mark was distinctive, three letter marks were, in the main, treated as not prima facie qualified for registration. This view was in line with Lord Parker's dictum that "initials are even less adapted for trade mark purposes than names": Re W &amp; G du Cros Ltd's Application (1913) 30 RPC 660 at 672. Under the old legislation, it was the registrar's practice, prima facie, to accept three letter marks only if the letters formed a pronounceable word. The test under the new law, however, is not whether the trade mark is distinctive, but whether it is capable of distinguishing. The registrar, to this end, has adopted a new practice based on an assessment of the likelihood of others' needs to use letters, particularly as initials. It is useful for me to quote from the Trade Marks Office Draft Manual of Practice and Procedure at 22.9. 
 
 
 
 
 9. Letters 
 Trade marks consisting of one or two letters are prima facie unfit for registration because of a common need for their use in the general market place. The likelihood of other traders needing to use simple unembellished combinations of one or two letters in the form of initials or abbreviations is quite high. One or two letter trade marks, unless represented in a very unusual manner, possess little inherent adaptation to distinguish and can only be registered with significant evidence of use in terms of s 41(5) and (6). There is likely to be less need for use of combinations of three or more letters and such trade marks are prima facie capable of distinguishing. For information on how the courts have treated letter trade marks, see Registrar of Trade Marks v W &amp; G Du Cros Ltd (W &amp; G case ) 29 RPC 74 and RPC 653.
 9.1 One and two letter trade marks 
 One and two letter trade marks without significant get up are not prima facie registrable.
 ...
 9.2 Three or more letter trade marks 
 Trade marks consisting of three or more letters are prima facie capable of distinguishing unless they lack inherent adaptation to distinguish because they are well known acronyms or abbreviations used on or in relation to the goods and/or services concerned. The issue of pronunciation is not relevant ... 
 
 
 
 
 The submission from Mr Condon is that the application trade marks are merely part of the applicant's trade name and he cites Re Application by American Tobacco Co [1996] ATMO 29 ; (1996) 35 IPR 98 as support. That case, however, finds that the words "The American Tobacco Company" are generic and are therefore not capable of distinguishing one American tobacco company from another. The AEI trade marks in suite do not suffer from a generic application of that kind. The American Tobacco Co case is therefore not to the point. The evidence of the opposition certainly establishes that there is indeed one other service provider with the same initials. However, I think that a single example is not enough to find that the registrar's practice in relation to three letter marks is not a good one. AEI has not been shown to have any meaning that renders it not capable of distinguishing and I do not agree with Mr Condon that the fact it coincides with the initials of the company name of its owner indicates that it lacks that capacity. In short, I do not think it is likely that many other insurance suppliers and brokers are likely to want to use the initials AEI. I therefore find that, in terms of s 41, there is no ground for rejection.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Anheuser-Busch Inc v Budejovick&yacute; Budvar [2002] FCA 390 ; (2002) 56 IPR 182</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/390.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant referred me to the decision of Allsop J (as he then was) in Anheuser-Busch Inc v Budejovick&yacute; Budvar [2002] FCA 390 ; (2002) 56 IPR 182 at [184] [192] and submitted that the relevant principles were adequately summarised in those paragraphs of his Honour's judgment. At [184] [186] (p 227), his Honour said: The notion of trade mark use is now given content by ss 7 and 17 of the TM Act: see [129] above. The task is to examine the way the words are used in their context, including the totality of the packaging, to assess their nature and purpose in order to see whether they are used to distinguish the goods from goods of others: Shell Co above, at 422 5; Mark Foy's Ltd , above at CLR 198 200; IPR 473 5; Johnson &amp; Johnson Aust Pty Ltd v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 335, 342 5, 347 9; 101 ALR 700 at 710, 717 20, 723 5; 21 IPR 1 at 11 12; 19; 24 5; Pepsico Australia , above at 162 3, 167 9 and 178 82; Musidor BV v Tansing (t/as Apple Music House) [1994] FCA 1242 ; (1994) 52 FCR 363 at 376 7; [1994] FCA 1242 ; 123 ALR 593 at 605; [1994] FCA 1242 ; 29 IPR 203 at 215 6; Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd ; [2000] FCA 876 ; (2000) 100 FCR 90 at 100 1; [2000] FCA 876 ; 177 ALR 167 at 175 6; [2000] FCA 876 ; 48 IPR 257 at 265 6 and Aldi Stores , above at [22] [30] and [54] [58]. The assessment is made from the perspective of what a person looking at the label would see and take from it, as to the purpose and nature of its use: Shell Co , above at 425; Wrigley's (A'sia) Ltd v Life Savers (A'asia) Ltd (1936) 37 SR (NSW) 9 at 16; Aldi Stores , above, at [22] [24] and [76].

I adopt and apply the following statement made by Allsop J in Anheuser-Busch Inc [2002] FCA 390 ; 56 IPR 182 at [191] : 
 
 It is not to the point, with respect, to say that because another part of the label (the white section with "Budejovicky Budvar") is the obvious and important "brand", that another part of the label cannot act to distinguish the goods. The "branding function", if that expression is merely used as a synonym for the contents of ss 7 and 17 of the TM Act, can be carried out in different places on packaging, with different degrees of strength and subtlety. Of course, the existence on a label of a clear dominant "brand" is of relevance to the assessment of what would be taken to be the effect of the balance of the label.

Having regard to the factors set out in [155] above, I think that the letters "BSS" on the allegedly infringing label are used in a branding role. It does not matter that the respondent may have made it clear on the packaging that the commercial origin of the goods was the respondent, ie a business other than that conducted by the applicant. The letters "BSS" may have been used in this way as an opening shot in a campaign by the respondent designed to demonstrate or generate generic use of the letters "BSS" but, at the time they were used on the relevant label, they were used to distinguish the respondent's goods from those of others, ie to brand them.

Subject to the s 122(1)(b)(i) defence relied upon by it, the respondent, therefore, infringed the applicant's BSS trade mark in the manner alleged by the applicant. The Section 122(1)(b)(i) Defence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Burger King Corporation v Registrar of Trade Marks [1973] HCA 15 ; (1973) 128 CLR 417</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1973/15.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant submitted that all of the journal articles originally published overseas, the overseas dictionaries and the excerpts from the two textbooks originally published overseas should all be rejected as not being relevant to distinctiveness as at 6 December 2006 because none of those publications could conceivably be relevant to the Court's determination of that question. The applicant also submitted that, given that a trade mark is a purely territorial concept which is legally operative and effective only within the territory within which it is used and for which it is registered or for which it is to be registered, it was of no moment that, in various publications originally published overseas, there was demonstrated a use of the letters "BSS" which could arguably support the respondent's contention that the letters had become descriptive of "balanced salt solution". In support of its objection, the applicant relied upon the following passage in the judgment of Gibbs J (as he then was) in Burger King Corporation v Registrar of Trade Marks [1973] HCA 15 ; (1973) 128 CLR 417 at 422 423: 
 
 On the other hand, the evidence that the word has been extensively used in the United States of America and has there become widely known as indicating the goods of the applicant only, is in my opinion in a different situation. On this point counsel for the Registrar referred me to certain authorities whose effect is summed up in the following passage from the judgment of Tomlin J. (as he then was) in Impex Electrical Ltd. v. Weinbaum [(1927) 44 R.P.C. 405 , at p. 410], which has been accepted, by this Court as well as in the United Kingdom, as a correct statement of the law (see Re Notox Ltd.'s Application [(1930) 48 R.P.C. 168 , at p. 178]; Re Gaines Animal Foods Ltd's Application [(1951) 68 R.P.C. 178 , at p. 179]; de Cordova v. Vick Chemical Co. [(1951) 68 R.P.C. 103 , at p. 107]; and The Seven Up Co. v. O.T. Ltd. [(1947) [1947] HCA 59 ; 75 C.L.R. 203 , at pp. 215, 216]): 
 
 
 
 
 "For the purpose of seeing whether the mark is distinctive, it is to the market of this country alone that one has to have regard. For that purpose foreign markets are wholly irrelevant, unless it be shown by evidence that in fact goods have been sold in this country with a foreign mark on them, and that the mark so used has thereby become identified with the manufacturer of the goods." 
 
 
 
 
 Those cases are authority for the proposition that in deciding whether a mark is distinctive, user within the jurisdiction only is to be taken into account. However, in the present case the question is a different one, namely, whether evidence of user overseas is admissible on the issue whether a trade mark is capable of becoming distinctive. 
 

 Decision on Admissibility

I think that these submissions made on behalf of the applicant in support of its objection to all of the overseas material sought to be tendered by the respondent are correct. In my view, it is a long bow for the Court to draw to find that use in the relevant trade in Australia can be established by the availability here of journals, dictionaries and textbooks published overseas which, to some extent, may have been read or looked at by persons participating in that trade. The evidence as to who read this material and when is vague and general. Further, the dictionaries and textbooks can only prove use in the places to which they relate. There was no evidence to suggest that these latter sources related to Australia. For these reasons, I will not admit these overseas materials into evidence for the purpose of establishing that the letters "BSS" did not, as at 6 December 2006, distinguish the applicant's BSS balanced salt solution from sterile ophthalmic irrigating solutions supplied by others within s 234(2) of the Act.

Distinctiveness in fact as at 22 March 1988 may be relevant to the respondent's case for cancellation of the applicant's BSS trade mark pursuant to ss 88(1)(a), 88(2)(a), 57 and 41 of the Act. For the same reasons as those advanced for not admitting into evidence the material to which objection was taken for the purpose of establishing lack of distinctiveness as at 6 December 2006, I will not admit that material for the purpose of establishing lack of distinctiveness in fact as at 22 March 1988.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chancellor, Masters and Scholars of the University of Oxford (t/as Oxford University Press) v Registrar of Trade Marks [1990] FCA 175 ; (1990) 24 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1990/175.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 24 contemplates that the registered trade mark will be generally accepted as the sign that describes, or is the name of, the relevant article or substance. There must be general acceptance within the relevant trade that the mark is the generic name of the article or substance. Use sometimes by some people will not be enough. Nor will the requirements of the section be satisfied if the mark is only one of two or more generic names for the article or substance.

In the present case, the generic name for the particular article or substance is "balanced salt solution". Balanced salt solution is a particular type of sterile ophthalmic irrigating solution with a particular mix of constituents. Whilst "bss" may well be an acronym for "balanced salt solution", it did not become generally accepted within the relevant period as the generic signification of "balanced salt solution" or of the particular type of sterile irrigating solution comprising the constituents of standard balanced salt solution. The most that can be said, on the evidence, is that the letters "BSS" were sometimes used in the relevant period in scientific journal articles as a convenient editorial abbreviation for "balanced salt solution". Such a use does not demonstrate "general acceptance" in the relevant trade that the mark is the generic name. This is especially so in circumstances where the respondent has chosen to base its case on this point almost entirely on the publications which it tendered, most of which were authored and published overseas. The respondent called no doctor, no nurse, no pharmacist, no purchasing officer&#8212;indeed, it called no third party participant in the relevant trade.

The applicant, on the other hand, called trade evidence. That evidence established:

The respondent has failed to discharge its onus of proving that the letters "BSS" became generic or descriptive in the period after 22 March 1988 and as at 6 December 2006. The respondent's case based upon s 87 and s 24 of the Act also fails.

For the above reasons, I do not need to consider s 89 of the Act. However, I will do so against the possibility that I am wrong in the conclusions which I have reached in respect of Ground 2.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Clark Equipment Company v Registrar of Trade Marks [1964] HCA 55 ; (1964) 111 CLR 511</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/55.html</AustLII>
<text>It was common ground between the parties that the relevant principle governing inherent adaptability was that stated by Kitto J in Clark Equipment Company v Registrar of Trade Marks [1964] HCA 55 ; (1964) 111 CLR 511 at 514 where, after discussing the well-known observations of Lord Parker of Waddington in Registrar of Trade Marks v W &amp; G Du Cros Ltd [1913] AC 624 at 634 635, his Honour said: 
 
 ... the question whether a mark is adapted to distinguish [must] be tested by reference to the likelihood that other persons, trading in goods of the relevant kind and being actuated only by proper motives&#8212;in the exercise, that is to say, of the common right of the public to make honest use of words forming part of the common heritage, for the sake of the signification which they ordinarily possess&#8212;will think of the word and want to use it in connexion with similar goods in any manner which would infringe a registered trade mark granted in respect of it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Colorado Group Ltd v Strandbags Group Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 184 ; (2007) 164 FCR 506</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/184.html</AustLII>
<text>These remarks of Kitto J were made in respect of the 1955 Act. However, the Full Court of this Court has taken the same approach to the question of inherent adaptability for the purposes of s 41(3) of the Act (see Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494 at [47] [49] (pp 510 511) (per French J), at [80] [100] (pp 518 522) (per Lindgren J) and at [145] [148] (pp 532 533) (per Stone J); and Colorado Group Ltd v Strandbags Group Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 184 ; (2007) 164 FCR 506 at [36] (pp 517 518) (per Gyles J) and at [125] (p 539) (per Allsop J)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Crooks Michell Peacock Stewart Pty Ltd v Kaiser (t/as Commercial Art &amp; Industrial Design) (1994) 29 IPR 225</tocase>
<text>Similar views were expressed by a delegate of the Registrar in HCA Colours Australia Pty Ltd v Holland Colours NV (2003) 59 IPR 507 at 516 517 and in Crooks Michell Peacock Stewart Pty Ltd v Kaiser (t/as Commercial Art &amp; Industrial Design) (1994) 29 IPR 225 at 232.

Sign is defined in s 6 of the Act as follows: 
 
 sign includes the following or any combination of the following, namely, any letter, word, name, signature, numeral, device, brand, heading, label, ticket, aspect of packaging, shape, colour, sound or scent.

In the same section, the expression use of a trade mark is defined in the following way: 
 
 use of a trade mark has a meaning affected by subsections 7(1), (2) and (3).
 use of a trade mark in relation to goods has the meaning given by subsection 7(4).

Section 7 of the Act is in the following terms: 
 
 7 Use of trade mark 
 (1) If the Registrar or a prescribed court, having regard to the circumstances of a particular case, thinks fit, the Registrar or the court may decide that a person has used a trade mark if it is established that the person has used the trade mark with additions or alterations that do not substantially affect the identity of the trade mark. 
 
 
 
 
 Note: For prescribed court see section 190. 
 
 
 
 
 (2) To avoid any doubt, it is stated that, if a trade mark consists of the following, or any combination of the following, namely, any letter, word, name or numeral, any aural representation of the trade mark is, for the purposes of this Act, a use of the trade mark.
 (3) An authorised use of a trade mark by a person (see section 8) is taken, for the purposes of this Act, to be a use of the trade mark by the owner of the trade mark.
 (4) In this Act: 
 
 
 
 
 use of a trade mark in relation to goods means use of the trade mark upon, or in physical or other relation to, the goods (including second hand goods). 
 
 
 
 
 (5) In this Act: 
 
 
 
 
 use of a trade mark in relation to services means use of the trade mark in physical or other relation to the services.

In s 17 of the Act, a trade mark is defined as follows: 
 
 17 What is a trade mark? 
 A trade mark is a sign used, or intended to be used, to distinguish goods or services dealt with or provided in the course of trade by a person from goods or services so dealt with or provided by any other person.
 Note: For sign see section 6.

For a time, the respondent included the letters "BSS" on the label affixed to its 19 ml bottle of AQSIA&#8482; brand balanced salt solution. That use was upon, or in physical or other relation to, those goods. The letters which appeared on that label are substantially identical to the applicant's BSS trade mark. Those letters were used by the respondent with respect to goods in respect of which the trade mark is registered. Therefore, the sole remaining question for present consideration is whether that particular use was one which is properly characterised as use as a trade mark upon those goods. That means: Was it used, or intended to be used, as a sign to distinguish the respondent's AQSIA&#8482; brand balanced salt solution from other sterile ophthalmic irrigating solutions supplied in Australia?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HCA Colours Australia Pty Ltd v Holland Colours NV (2003) 59 IPR 507</tocase>
<text>Similar views were expressed by a delegate of the Registrar in HCA Colours Australia Pty Ltd v Holland Colours NV (2003) 59 IPR 507 at 516 517 and in Crooks Michell Peacock Stewart Pty Ltd v Kaiser (t/as Commercial Art &amp; Industrial Design) (1994) 29 IPR 225 at 232.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Ltd v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd (1991) 30 FCR 326</tocase>
<text>The applicant referred me to the decision of Allsop J (as he then was) in Anheuser-Busch Inc v Budejovick&yacute; Budvar [2002] FCA 390 ; (2002) 56 IPR 182 at [184] [192] and submitted that the relevant principles were adequately summarised in those paragraphs of his Honour's judgment. At [184] [186] (p 227), his Honour said: The notion of trade mark use is now given content by ss 7 and 17 of the TM Act: see [129] above. The task is to examine the way the words are used in their context, including the totality of the packaging, to assess their nature and purpose in order to see whether they are used to distinguish the goods from goods of others: Shell Co above, at 422 5; Mark Foy's Ltd , above at CLR 198 200; IPR 473 5; Johnson &amp; Johnson Aust Pty Ltd v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 335, 342 5, 347 9; 101 ALR 700 at 710, 717 20, 723 5; 21 IPR 1 at 11 12; 19; 24 5; Pepsico Australia , above at 162 3, 167 9 and 178 82; Musidor BV v Tansing (t/as Apple Music House) [1994] FCA 1242 ; (1994) 52 FCR 363 at 376 7; [1994] FCA 1242 ; 123 ALR 593 at 605; [1994] FCA 1242 ; 29 IPR 203 at 215 6; Koninklijke Philips Electronics NV v Remington Products Australia Pty Ltd ; [2000] FCA 876 ; (2000) 100 FCR 90 at 100 1; [2000] FCA 876 ; 177 ALR 167 at 175 6; [2000] FCA 876 ; 48 IPR 257 at 265 6 and Aldi Stores , above at [22] [30] and [54] [58]. The assessment is made from the perspective of what a person looking at the label would see and take from it, as to the purpose and nature of its use: Shell Co , above at 425; Wrigley's (A'sia) Ltd v Life Savers (A'asia) Ltd (1936) 37 SR (NSW) 9 at 16; Aldi Stores , above, at [22] [24] and [76].

In order to establish "good faith", when used in s 122, the respondent must show that it acted honestly and without any ulterior motive (see Johnson &amp; Johnson Australia Pty Ltd v Sterling Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd (1991) 30 FCR 326 at 353 354 (per Gummow J)).

In June 2005, within two years of the respondent's introduction into the Australian market of its AQSIA&#8482; brand balanced salt solution, the respondent used the letters "BSS" in promotional material for two of its other products. The applicant immediately complained about this. Then, in June 2006, the respondent began to supply its 19 ml plastic bottles of AQSIA&#8482; brand balanced salt solution with the infringing label. It took that course knowing of the existence of the applicant's BSS trade mark, knowing that that mark was registered and knowing that the applicant would not tolerate any attempt by its competitors to use the letters "BSS" generically in order to dilute its registered trade mark.

Further, the respondent did not call any evidence at all as to the circumstances in which the decision to use the letters "BSS" on the infringing label was made. Mr Stamp, the respondent's Managing Director, gave evidence at the trial but said nothing about that matter. Ms Stubbs gave no evidence in chief about that matter and answered questions in cross-examination touching upon that matter as follows: 
 
 Q: This particular product, do you know who approved the specific label that appears on this product?
 A: No, I don't.
 Q: Were you involved at all in the design and approval of this label?
 A: No, I wasn't.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/273.html</AustLII>
<text>These remarks of Kitto J were made in respect of the 1955 Act. However, the Full Court of this Court has taken the same approach to the question of inherent adaptability for the purposes of s 41(3) of the Act (see Kenman Kandy Australia Pty Ltd v Registrar of Trade Marks [2002] FCAFC 273 ; (2002) 122 FCR 494 at [47] [49] (pp 510 511) (per French J), at [80] [100] (pp 518 522) (per Lindgren J) and at [145] [148] (pp 532 533) (per Stone J); and Colorado Group Ltd v Strandbags Group Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 184 ; (2007) 164 FCR 506 at [36] (pp 517 518) (per Gyles J) and at [125] (p 539) (per Allsop J)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Registrar of Trade Marks v W &amp; G Du Cros Ltd [1913] AC 624</tocase>
<text>It was common ground between the parties that the relevant principle governing inherent adaptability was that stated by Kitto J in Clark Equipment Company v Registrar of Trade Marks [1964] HCA 55 ; (1964) 111 CLR 511 at 514 where, after discussing the well-known observations of Lord Parker of Waddington in Registrar of Trade Marks v W &amp; G Du Cros Ltd [1913] AC 624 at 634 635, his Honour said: 
 
 ... the question whether a mark is adapted to distinguish [must] be tested by reference to the likelihood that other persons, trading in goods of the relevant kind and being actuated only by proper motives&#8212;in the exercise, that is to say, of the common right of the public to make honest use of words forming part of the common heritage, for the sake of the signification which they ordinarily possess&#8212;will think of the word and want to use it in connexion with similar goods in any manner which would infringe a registered trade mark granted in respect of it.

In Air Express International (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian European Insurance (Brokers) Pty Ltd (1999) 49 IPR 435 , in dismissing opposition to an application for registration of the letters "AEI" and a logo comprised of those letters in a stylised format, the Deputy Registrar of Trade Marks said (at 439 440): 
 
 The question of trade marks consisting of three letters has long been an issue for the registrar. Under the old law, the Trade Marks Act 1955 (Cth), where it was a question of whether a trade mark was distinctive, three letter marks were, in the main, treated as not prima facie qualified for registration. This view was in line with Lord Parker's dictum that "initials are even less adapted for trade mark purposes than names": Re W &amp; G du Cros Ltd's Application (1913) 30 RPC 660 at 672. Under the old legislation, it was the registrar's practice, prima facie, to accept three letter marks only if the letters formed a pronounceable word. The test under the new law, however, is not whether the trade mark is distinctive, but whether it is capable of distinguishing. The registrar, to this end, has adopted a new practice based on an assessment of the likelihood of others' needs to use letters, particularly as initials. It is useful for me to quote from the Trade Marks Office Draft Manual of Practice and Procedure at 22.9. 
 
 
 
 
 9. Letters 
 Trade marks consisting of one or two letters are prima facie unfit for registration because of a common need for their use in the general market place. The likelihood of other traders needing to use simple unembellished combinations of one or two letters in the form of initials or abbreviations is quite high. One or two letter trade marks, unless represented in a very unusual manner, possess little inherent adaptation to distinguish and can only be registered with significant evidence of use in terms of s 41(5) and (6). There is likely to be less need for use of combinations of three or more letters and such trade marks are prima facie capable of distinguishing. For information on how the courts have treated letter trade marks, see Registrar of Trade Marks v W &amp; G Du Cros Ltd (W &amp; G case ) 29 RPC 74 and RPC 653.
 9.1 One and two letter trade marks 
 One and two letter trade marks without significant get up are not prima facie registrable.
 ...
 9.2 Three or more letter trade marks 
 Trade marks consisting of three or more letters are prima facie capable of distinguishing unless they lack inherent adaptation to distinguish because they are well known acronyms or abbreviations used on or in relation to the goods and/or services concerned. The issue of pronunciation is not relevant ... 
 
 
 
 
 The submission from Mr Condon is that the application trade marks are merely part of the applicant's trade name and he cites Re Application by American Tobacco Co [1996] ATMO 29 ; (1996) 35 IPR 98 as support. That case, however, finds that the words "The American Tobacco Company" are generic and are therefore not capable of distinguishing one American tobacco company from another. The AEI trade marks in suite do not suffer from a generic application of that kind. The American Tobacco Co case is therefore not to the point. The evidence of the opposition certainly establishes that there is indeed one other service provider with the same initials. However, I think that a single example is not enough to find that the registrar's practice in relation to three letter marks is not a good one. AEI has not been shown to have any meaning that renders it not capable of distinguishing and I do not agree with Mr Condon that the fact it coincides with the initials of the company name of its owner indicates that it lacks that capacity. In short, I do not think it is likely that many other insurance suppliers and brokers are likely to want to use the initials AEI. I therefore find that, in terms of s 41, there is no ground for rejection.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>TGI Friday's Australia Pty Ltd v TGI Friday's Inc [2000] FCA 720 ; (2000) 100 FCR 358</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/720.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 234 has been described as a "gateway" opening the way for a challenge to the continued registration of a trade mark. In TGI Friday's Australia Pty Ltd v TGI Friday's Inc [2000] FCA 720 ; (2000) 100 FCR 358 at [32] [36] (p 364), the Full Court discussed s 234. At [35] [36], the Court said: Section 234(2) does not of itself authorise rectification of the Register by cancellation of a trade mark or otherwise. Rather, the subsection acts as an impediment to any proceeding alleging invalidity. Any application by Friday's Australia and Big Country for rectification of the Register must be made under s 88 of the 1995 Act. Even if, as Friday's Australia and Big Country contend, s 234(2)(d) or (e) applies in this case, the consequence is only that the conclusive presumption of validity does not arise. Satisfaction of one of the conditions in s 234(2) does not, of itself, constitute a ground under s 88(2) of the 1995 Act for rectification of the Register. Therefore, in addition to agitating the question of renewal, Friday's Australia and Big Country seek to establish grounds within s 88(2) that satisfy s 234.

The respondent contended that it discharged its onus of proving that the applicant's BSS trade mark did not, as at 6 December 2006, distinguish the applicant's BSS balanced salt solution from the goods or services of other persons. I shall consider this contention when I come to evaluate the grounds for cancellation of that trade mark relied upon by the respondent.

Assuming for the moment that the respondent was able to pass through the s 234 gateway, it then relied upon two grounds in support of its claim that the applicant's BSS trade mark should be removed from the Register. Ground 1 (Trade Mark Not Distinctive as at Application Date)</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>