<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>G &amp; M Nicholas Pty Limited and Others v Minster for Finance and Deregulation [2009] FCA 121 (20 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/121.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Annetts and Another v McCann and Others [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/57.html</AustLII>
<text>In Annetts and Another v McCann and Others [1990] HCA 57 ; (1990) 170 CLR 596 Mason CJ, Deane and McHugh JJ at 598 observed: 
 It can now be taken as settled that, when a statute confers power upon a public official to destroy, defeat or prejudice a person's rights, interests or legitimate expectations, the rules of natural justice regulate the exercise of that power unless they are excluded by plain words of necessary intendment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/72.html</AustLII>
<text>Whilst observing that not every adverse piece of information needs to be put, his Honour said at 629: 
 
 Nevertheless in the ordinary case where no problem of confidentiality arises an opportunity should be given to deal with adverse information that is credible, relevant and significant to the decision to be made. 
 

See also Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88 at [17] . In Teoh at 311 McHugh J (in dissent) said of the rules of procedural fairness:
 
 In the absence of a clear contrary legislative intention, those rules require a decision-maker 'to bring to a person's attention the critical issue or factor on which the administrative decision on which is likely to turn so that he may have an opportunity of dealing with it'. Footnotes omitted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Applicant Y v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship and Another (2008) 100 ALD 544</tocase>
<text>The applicants contend that the passing reference to the two integers made by the Finance Minister in his concluding observations is not adequate. Reliance is placed upon Applicant Y v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship and Another (2008) 100 ALD 544 in which the Court found (at [32]) that the Migration Review Tribunal 'did not engage any assessment of' the weight or relevance of expert medical opinions. The applicants submit that the same conclusion should be drawn in the present circumstance because the Finance Minister indicated the matters of real concern and made no mention of the two integers.

The Finance Minister acknowledges that the two integers are not expressly referred to in that portion of the Reasons which itemise the three categories which he identified as ' circumstances to which I must have regard '.

The Court is satisfied that the Finance Minister included the two integers in his Reasons and took them into consideration. Accordingly, Applicant Y has no application to the facts in these proceedings.

For these reasons the Court rejects the applicants' submissions that the entirety of the Minister for Health's conduct was not taken into account by the Finance Minister when he made his decision.

In view of such finding, it is unnecessary to consider the Finance Minister's second ground of defence, namely whether he was under an obligation to consider such matter. Ground 3 Parliamentary Privilege</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General for the State of New South Wales v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 33 provides no indication of the manner in which the Finance Minister is to exercise his discretion. In Attorney-General for the State of New South Wales v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 Brennan J at 33 observed: 
 
 If the power is conferred by statute but the statute prescribes no procedure for the making of appointments nor any criteria governing the exercise of the power, the power must be at large...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/26.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicants submit that it is mandatory that the Finance Minister respond to their claims. The applicants rely upon Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389 in which the High Court found that a denial of natural justice occurred when the Refugee Review Tribunal failed to respond to a substantial and clearly articulated argument. The applicants also rely upon HTUN v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1802 ; (2001) 194 ALR 244 in which the Court found at [42] that the Refugee Review Tribunal 'failed to address and deal with how the claim was put to it, at least in part' and accordingly failed to complete the exercise of its jurisdiction.

In view of the above no issue arises relating to the kind of matters which were required to be put as considered in HTUN at [42], and the facts in the present proceedings are distinguishable from those in Dranichnikov since the Court is satisfied that the appellant's submissions were not overlooked.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>HTUN v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1802 ; (2001) 194 ALR 244</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1802.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicants submit that it is mandatory that the Finance Minister respond to their claims. The applicants rely upon Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 197 ALR 389 in which the High Court found that a denial of natural justice occurred when the Refugee Review Tribunal failed to respond to a substantial and clearly articulated argument. The applicants also rely upon HTUN v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1802 ; (2001) 194 ALR 244 in which the Court found at [42] that the Refugee Review Tribunal 'failed to address and deal with how the claim was put to it, at least in part' and accordingly failed to complete the exercise of its jurisdiction.

In view of the above no issue arises relating to the kind of matters which were required to be put as considered in HTUN at [42], and the facts in the present proceedings are distinguishable from those in Dranichnikov since the Court is satisfied that the appellant's submissions were not overlooked.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jarrat v Commissioner of Police for New South Wales and Another [2005] HCA 50 ; (2005) 224 CLR 44</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/50.html</AustLII>
<text>Such principle was confirmed by the High Court in Jarratt v Commissioner of Police for New South Wales and Another [2005] HCA 50 ; (2005) 224 CLR 44 at [24] per Gleeson CJ; at [51] per McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ and at [138] per Callinan J. At [26] Gleeson CJ said: 
 Where Parliament confers a statutory power to destroy, defeat or prejudice a person's rights, interests or legitimate expectations, Parliament is taken to intend that the power be exercised fairly and in accordance with natural justice unless it makes the contrary intention plain. This principle of interpretation is an acknowledgment by the courts of Parliament's assumed respect for justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kioa and Others v West and Another [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/81.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicants contend that whether the QTB itself was before the Finance Minister or merely a summary of the QTB as set out in the Issues paper is irrelevant. In either event the applicants were given no opportunity to address material which was adverse to their application. The applicants submit that procedural fairness required that the Finance Minister should have provided the applicants with the opportunity of responding to the material in the QTB prior to making his decision since the information in the QTB was 'credible, relevant and significant' : see Kioa and Others v West and Another [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 629.

The Finance Minister acknowledges that neither the QTB nor the description of its comments contained in the Issues paper were provided to the applicants before his decision was made. The Finance Minister states that the QTB was not before him when he made his decision but concedes that he did have a description of its contents in the Issues paper. However, the Finance Minister submits that the QTB was not adverse to the applicants' interests.

Additionally the Finance Minister relies upon the broad discretion contained in s 33 and submits that the rules of procedural fairness must be determined in accordance with the circumstances of the particular case: see Kioa at 587 per Mason J. The Finance Minister submits that s 33 conferred a broad discretion as a result of which no occasion arose to engage the rules of procedural fairness. Findings Ground 1
 Do the rules of natural justice apply?

The threshold questions raised under this ground are whether the rules of natural justice have any application, and, if they do, whether there has been a breach of such rules. Medtest's submission thus requires the Court to consider the scope of s 33 and to determine whether any duty was imposed which required the Finance Minister to provide information to the applicants as claimed.

The manner in which the power to make an ex gratia payment under s 33 is to be exercised will determine whether there is a duty to act fairly. Accordingly the legislative provisions investing power in the Finance Minister to make an act of grace payment are critical. In Kioa Mason J observed at 584-5: 
 
 Where the decision in question is one for which provision is made by statute, the application and content of the doctrine of natural justice or the duty to act fairly depends to a large extent on the construction of the statute. In Mobil Oil Australia Pty. Ltd. v. Federal Commissioner of Taxation , Kitto J. pointed out that the obligation to give a fair opportunity to parties in controversy to correct or contradict statements prejudicial to their view depends on "the particular statutory framework". What is appropriate in terms of natural justice depends on the circumstance of the case and they will include, inter alia, the nature of the inquiry, the subject-matter, and the rules under which the decision-maker is acting: Reg. v. Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commission; Ex parte Angliss Group ; National Companies and Securities Commission v. News Corporation Ltd . Footnotes omitted.

In Kioa Brennan J at 626 said: 
 
 Once the threshold question is resolved and it is established that the exercise of a power is conditioned on the observance of the principles of natural justice, the content of the principles to be observed is determined in the light of the particular circumstances. 
 

At 628 his Honour said:
 
 
 A person whose interests are likely to be affected by an exercise of power must be given an opportunity to deal with relevant matters adverse to his interests which the repository of the power proposes to take into account in deciding upon its exercise.

A basic consideration of the rules of natural justice demands that a party who is to be affected by a decision be afforded an opportunity to comment upon information which is 'credible, relevant and significant' to that decision. In Kioa at 628, Brennan J said: 
 
 A person whose interests are likely to be affected by an exercise of power must be given an opportunity to deal with relevant matters adverse to his interests which the repository of the power proposes to take into account in deciding upon its exercise: Kanda v. Government of Malaya ; Ridge v. Baldwin , per Lord Morris; De Verteuil v. Knaggs . Footnotes omitted.

The solicitors for the Finance Minister provided information which was incomplete because of the absence of the Issues paper containing the QTB summary. The information contained in the QTB summary referred to the Minister for Health's state of knowledge. Such knowledge was directly relevant to the applicants and because of the reference to controversy surrounding another pathology provider was potentially prejudicial to the applicants. In this sense, the information was personal to them; see Mason J in Kioa at 587. To similar effect, McHugh J in Teoh at 311-312 in his dissenting judgment said ' The question becomes, what does fairness require in all the circumstances of the case? '

The information contained in the QTB summary was before the Finance Minister when he reached his decision and his decision was based upon the Issues paper containing the QTB summary. Such information related to a critical issue for the applicants in their claim for an act of grace payment since the conduct of the Minister for Health both inside and outside of Parliament was the subject of major complaint and criticism by the applicants. No opportunity was provided to the applicants to comment upon the QTB summary and they were not provided with an opportunity to be heard on an issue which was credible, relevant and significant to the Finance Minister's decision as per Kioa at 587.

The Finance Minister's submission, taken at its highest, seems to suggest that because of the broad discretion under s 33, natural justice did not require him to furnish the applicants with any of the material that he would rely upon. However he did provide the applicants with the material before him in accordance with their request. Inferentially, such material was the only material which the Finance Minister would rely upon to make his decision yet the QTB summary was omitted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Israelian [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf; Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Israelian [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at [73] McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ observed the necessity to consider, at the outset, 'the statutory scheme as a whole' . At [74] the majority said: 
 
 What is important, however, is that the grounds of judicial review that fasten upon the use made of relevant and irrelevant considerations are concerned essentially with whether the decision-maker has properly applied the law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Another; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/22.html</AustLII>
<text>In Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Another: Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57 at [99] Gaudron J said: 
 The basic principle with respect to procedural fairness is that a person should have an opportunity to put his or her case and to meet the case that is put against him or her.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>The Finance Minister submits that procedural fairness does not require that every piece of information that might potentially be used adversely to another person's interest must be provided. Rather, the obligation to provide procedural fairness is limited. Reliance is placed upon the observations of McHugh J in Minister of State for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Ah Hin Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273 at 311-312 wherein his Honour observed (in his dissenting judgment): 
 
 In the absence of a clear contrary legislative intention, those rules require a decision-maker "to bring to a person's attention the critical issue or factor on which the administrative decision is likely to turn so that he may have an opportunity of dealing with it". Footnotes omitted. 
 

His Honour's decision has been recently approved by McHugh and Gummow JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at [81] - [83] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister of State for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Ah Hin Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/20.html</AustLII>
<text>The Finance Minister submits that procedural fairness does not require that every piece of information that might potentially be used adversely to another person's interest must be provided. Rather, the obligation to provide procedural fairness is limited. Reliance is placed upon the observations of McHugh J in Minister of State for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Ah Hin Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273 at 311-312 wherein his Honour observed (in his dissenting judgment): 
 
 In the absence of a clear contrary legislative intention, those rules require a decision-maker "to bring to a person's attention the critical issue or factor on which the administrative decision is likely to turn so that he may have an opportunity of dealing with it". Footnotes omitted. 
 

His Honour's decision has been recently approved by McHugh and Gummow JJ in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at [81] - [83] .

Whilst observing that not every adverse piece of information needs to be put, his Honour said at 629: 
 
 Nevertheless in the ordinary case where no problem of confidentiality arises an opportunity should be given to deal with adverse information that is credible, relevant and significant to the decision to be made. 
 

See also Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88 at [17] . In Teoh at 311 McHugh J (in dissent) said of the rules of procedural fairness:
 
 In the absence of a clear contrary legislative intention, those rules require a decision-maker 'to bring to a person's attention the critical issue or factor on which the administrative decision on which is likely to turn so that he may have an opportunity of dealing with it'. Footnotes omitted.

The solicitors for the Finance Minister provided information which was incomplete because of the absence of the Issues paper containing the QTB summary. The information contained in the QTB summary referred to the Minister for Health's state of knowledge. Such knowledge was directly relevant to the applicants and because of the reference to controversy surrounding another pathology provider was potentially prejudicial to the applicants. In this sense, the information was personal to them; see Mason J in Kioa at 587. To similar effect, McHugh J in Teoh at 311-312 in his dissenting judgment said ' The question becomes, what does fairness require in all the circumstances of the case? '

The Court does not accept that the mere fact that the discretion granted under s 33 is broad and describes no procedure for its exercise has the consequence that natural justice absolved the Finance Minister from the requirement to furnish the applicants with the material upon which he would rely. Even if it did, it is not sufficient for the Finance Minister to give the applicants the impression they were in possession of all the material upon which he would rely when this was contrary to the fact. By purporting to comply with the applicants' request that they be furnished with all information, the Finance Minister is not entitled to claim that the operation of s 33 had the consequence that he did not have to furnish them with any material at all. In these circumstances fairness required that the QTB be provided: see McHugh J in Teoh at 311-312 as extracted in paragraph [62] of this judgment.

Natural justice required that such document be put before the applicants to allow them an opportunity to respond to it before any decision was made under s 33. This is especially so in view of the repeated requests by the applicants that they be furnished with the exact material that would be relied upon to enable them to comment upon it. The failure to provide the summary to the applicants has resulted in a breach of the rules of natural justice. Ground 2 Failure to consider the totality of the applicants' claims

The applicants submit that the Finance Minister failed to have regard or proper regard, to important integers of the applicants' claim, namely that the Health Minister wrote to the NSW Health Minister and that the Health Minister directed the HIC to write to all New South Wales medical practitioners to inform them of NATA's concerns ('the two integers').</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pfizer Pty Ltd v Birkett [2001] FCA 828 ; (2001) 112 FCR 305</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/828.html</AustLII>
<text>In Pfizer Pty Ltd v Birkett [2001] FCA 828 ; (2001) 112 FCR 305 at [60] the Full Court confirmed the necessity to consider 'the relevant content of the requirement' that the decision maker proceed in a manner so as to provide natural justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Salemi v Mackellar [No. 2] [1977] HCA 26 ; (1977) 137 CLR 396</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1907/60.html</AustLII>
<text>However, the width of such power does not have the consequence that the rules of procedural fairness have no application to the Finance Minister when exercising his discretion under s 33. As was observed by Gibbs J in Salemi v Mackellar [No. 2] [1977] HCA 26 ; (1977) 137 CLR 396 at 419: 
 There is nothing technical about the principles of natural justice. It is sometimes said, or suggested, that those principles apply only to proceedings which are judicial or quasi-judicial, or where there is a duty to act judicially. To state the rule in that way seems to me to be unduly restrictive and misleading. It is at least clear that when the power which is being exercised is a statutory one, it is not necessary to be able to find in the words of the statute itself a duty to hear the party affected or otherwise to act judicially.

His Honour continued (at 419): 
 It may be enough if an interest or privilege is affected, or, as Lord Denning M.R. has said, if a man has a "legitimate expectation", of which it would not be fair to deprive him without a hearing, or reasons given: Breen v. Amalgamated Engineering Union ; and see Schmidt v. Secretary of State for Home Affairs . Footnotes omitted</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Toomer v Slipper [2001] FCA 981</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/981.html</AustLII>
<text>The power of the Finance Minister to approve an act of grace payment is unconfined and thus depends solely upon his opinion that it is 'appropriate' to do so. Such was found by Weinberg J when considering the application of s 33 in Toomer v Slipper [2001] FCA 981 at [31] : 
 There are any number of circumstances which may give rise to a claim for payment of this type. It is impossible to anticipate the situations in which such payments may be warranted. The discretion vested in the Minister is obviously broad.

In Toomer a claim was made for an act of grace payment under s 33 arising out of the applicant's termination of employment. After considering the complaint that the respondent Finance Minister had failed to accord procedural fairness to the applicant, the Court observed that a full opportunity had been provided to the applicant to be heard. The Court accordingly dismissed the applicant's claim alleging breach of procedural fairness. Weinberg J apparently proceeded on the assumption that the rules of natural justice applied to decisions of the Finance Minister made pursuant to s 33.

This Court respectfully adopts his Honour's approach. The decision of the Finance Minister made upon an application under s 33 affects the rights of an applicants, since it determines whether an act of grace payment may be made in respect of a claim which may otherwise be compensable or not compensable at law. Provided the power is exercised lawfully, his decision cannot be impugned: see Toomer at [47]. Extent of the application of the rules of natural justice

Having established the threshold question whether the rules of natural justice do attach to an exercise of s 33, the next question for determination is the extent of the application of the rules of natural justice.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>