<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gyrro Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation [2009] FCA 1477 (11 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1477.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>George Ward Steel v Kizkot (1989) 15 ACLR 464</tocase>
<text>In support of its submission that the winding up order should be set aside, the Defendant relied upon the following statement by Hodgson J in George Ward Steel v Kizkot (1989) 15 ACLR 464 at 465: 
 
 In my view, if an order winding up a company is made in the absence of the defendant company, and an application is brought promptly by the company, with notice being given to the liquidator, to the plaintiff and to any creditor who appeared at the hearing; and if the evidence shows an explanation for the non-appearance at the hearing and indicates solvency of the company; and if there is consent to setting aside, or at least non-opposition; and if the liquidator indicates that nothing in his investigations to date shows a reason for the company to be stopped from trading, then the court will normally set aside the order. 
 

His Honour was concerned with an application under Part 40 r 9(3) of the now superseded Supreme Court Rules 1970 (NSW) which was equivalent to O 35, r 7(2)(a).

The application to set aside the winding up order was determined by his Honour within about two weeks of the winding up order being made. His Honour's reasons do not reveal the reason behind the Defendant's non-appearance.

Hodgson J's decision was considered by Nicholson J in Registrar of Aboriginal Corporation v Murnkurni Women's Aboriginal Corporation (1995) 58 FCR 125 at 127-128. His Honour's reasons do not shed much light on the reason behind the respondent's failure to appear in that case, though it is apparent that the applicant had obtained an order for substituted service which was, as was accepted by the respondent in that case, properly effected. His Honour went on to say: 
 
 It may not be that the dicta of Hodgson J in Kizkot and the principles relied upon for Murnkurni are necessarily in conflict. All that Hodgson J required was evidence which "indicates" solvency. He did not say that solvency was to be established as a fact. Certainly he must have accepted there should be evidence which indicates solvency in the sense of showing it to be arguable that the company was solvent. In my opinion the effect of the authorities is to require this Court to consider whether there is an arguable defence which in turn requires the Court to consider whether solvency is arguable. 
 ... 
 

 
 
 For the reasons given I consider that both the solvency and other aspects are arguable and that, accordingly, the application to set aside the order pursuant to FCR O 35, r 7(2)(a) should be granted.

Hodgson J's decision in Kizkot was followed by Gyles J on several occasions: Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Fairchild Development (in liq) [2006] FCA 714 and Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Vallod Pty Ltd; in the matter of Vallod Pty Limited [2007] FCA 535. In the latter case Gyles J said (at [4]) that "Hodgson J's points are not, of course, a statutory formula but they are a useful checklist of things to at least take into account." Gyles J set aside the winding up order in that case within a week of it being made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Registrar of Aboriginal Corporation v Murnkurni Women's Aboriginal Corporation (1995) 58 FCR 125</tocase>
<text>Hodgson J's decision was considered by Nicholson J in Registrar of Aboriginal Corporation v Murnkurni Women's Aboriginal Corporation (1995) 58 FCR 125 at 127-128. His Honour's reasons do not shed much light on the reason behind the respondent's failure to appear in that case, though it is apparent that the applicant had obtained an order for substituted service which was, as was accepted by the respondent in that case, properly effected. His Honour went on to say: 
 
 It may not be that the dicta of Hodgson J in Kizkot and the principles relied upon for Murnkurni are necessarily in conflict. All that Hodgson J required was evidence which "indicates" solvency. He did not say that solvency was to be established as a fact. Certainly he must have accepted there should be evidence which indicates solvency in the sense of showing it to be arguable that the company was solvent. In my opinion the effect of the authorities is to require this Court to consider whether there is an arguable defence which in turn requires the Court to consider whether solvency is arguable. 
 ... 
 

 
 
 For the reasons given I consider that both the solvency and other aspects are arguable and that, accordingly, the application to set aside the order pursuant to FCR O 35, r 7(2)(a) should be granted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Fairchild Development (in liq) [2006] FCA 714</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/714.html</AustLII>
<text>Hodgson J's decision in Kizkot was followed by Gyles J on several occasions: Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Fairchild Development (in liq) [2006] FCA 714 and Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Vallod Pty Ltd; in the matter of Vallod Pty Limited [2007] FCA 535. In the latter case Gyles J said (at [4]) that "Hodgson J's points are not, of course, a statutory formula but they are a useful checklist of things to at least take into account." Gyles J set aside the winding up order in that case within a week of it being made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Vallod Pty Ltd; in the matter of Vallod Pty Limited [2007] FCA 535</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/535.html</AustLII>
<text>Hodgson J's decision in Kizkot was followed by Gyles J on several occasions: Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Fairchild Development (in liq) [2006] FCA 714 and Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Vallod Pty Ltd; in the matter of Vallod Pty Limited [2007] FCA 535. In the latter case Gyles J said (at [4]) that "Hodgson J's points are not, of course, a statutory formula but they are a useful checklist of things to at least take into account." Gyles J set aside the winding up order in that case within a week of it being made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Black on White Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 363 ; (2008) 138 FCR 314</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/363.html</AustLII>
<text>There are other decisions which might be understood to impose a higher burden on a party seeking to set aside an order pursuant to O 35, r 7(2). In Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Black on White Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 363 ; (2008) 138 FCR 314 Spender J said at [14]-[15]: 
 
 [14] In my opinion, the discretion to set aside an order pursuant to 0 35, r 7(2) of the Federal Court Rules is one that ought to be exercised only in exceptional circumstances, and that generally speaking, the jurisdiction is not to be exercised unless it can be shown that, without fault on the applicant's part, he or she had not been heard on the relevant question. 
 

 
 
 [15] In Wentworth v Rogers (No 9) (1987) 8 NSWLR 388 , Kirby P, in delivering the judgment of the court, accepted there may be unusual circumstances apart from fraud where a court would set aside or vary a perfected order, but that such power, if it existed, could only be used in the most exceptional of cases. The Full Court of the Federal Court in Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543 said at 552 that the jurisdiction was "truly exceptional" and added: 
 

 
 
 
 
 Moreover, generally speaking, the jurisdiction is not to be exercised unless it can be shown that, without fault on the applicant's part, he or she has not been heard on the relevant question.

Whether the discretion to set aside an order pursuant to O 35, r 7(2) ought to be exercised in exceptional circumstances only or whether it may be exercised in circumstances that cannot be so described is a question that does not need to be decided in the present case. Either way, I would not be disposed to accede to the Defendant's application to set aside the winding up order.

In the present case there is no satisfactory explanation given for the Defendant's non-appearance. The Defendant simply says that its directors left the country to live abroad and, while away, neglected to attend to the company's affairs for a period of almost five years. I think this is a factor that tells against the exercise of any discretion in favour of the Defendant.

I note also that there was a significant delay between the making of the winding up order and the filing of the application. The delay was in the vicinity of five months. Mr and Mrs Pagent returned to Australia in late 2005 and I infer that their neglect of the Defendant's affairs continued for several years after their return.

Even if the Defendant appeared at the hearing of the winding up application, it is doubtful whether it would have been able to demonstrate any arguable basis to resist the making of a winding up order. The Defendant's insolvency was presumed by its non-compliance with the creditor's statutory demand for payment and it would have been necessary for the Defendant to rebut the presumption of insolvency if it wished to resist the making of the order.

The Defendant's only significant assets consist of various artworks which were at the time of the winding up hearing in the possession of a third party pursuant to some arrangement which is not dealt with in the evidence in any way. The evidence does not address whether a sale of artwork constituted a practical means of obtaining cash with which to pay the Plaintiff in a timely manner. In addition, there is no evidence before me that there was, at that time, any obligation, capacity or willingness on the part of Mr and Mrs Pagent or any other person to make additional contributions to the Fund or to provide financial accommodation or assistance of some other kind which might enable the Defendant to pay the Plaintiff.

The evidence includes a recent valuation of the artwork undertaken for insurance purposes which values the artwork at about $1.2 million. But there is no evidence which indicates how easy or difficult it would be to turn any of it into cash. The payments made to the Plaintiff by or on behalf of the Defendant did not follow the sale of any of the artwork but were made possible by what were said to be non-deductible contributions recently made to the Fund by Mr Pagent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re United Medical Protection Limited (2003) ACSR 705</tocase>
<text>The relevant principles governing the making of an order pursuant to s 482(1) are well settled and were summarised by Austin J in Re United Medical Protection Limited (2003) ACSR 705 at [30]. His Honour said: 
 
 As to termination of a winding up, I was taken to Re Data Homes Pty Ltd (in liq) [1972] 2 NSWLR 22 at 26-7; Re Mascot Homes Furnishers Pty Ltd [1970] VR 593 at 598 and Mercy &amp; Sons Pty Ltd v Wanari Pty Ltd [2000] NSWSC 756 ; (2000) 35 ACSR 70 at [47] - [51] . Those cases show that in considering an application to terminate a court-ordered winding up under s 482 , the court has regard to the effect of the proposal on various categories of interests: the interests of creditors (including future creditors who might be prejudiced if the company is released from winding up in an encumbered state); the interests of the liquidator, particularly with respect costs; the interests of contributories; and the public interest (including the public interest in upholding commercial morality), the court taking the initial approach that insolvent companies should be wound up.

I have taken the matters referred to by his Honour into account in considering whether to make an order terminating the winding-up of the Defendant.

Subject to having its debt and the costs of the winding up proceedings paid, the Plaintiff consents to an order terminating the winding up of the Defendant. The Plaintiff has acknowledged that the debt has been paid.

Likewise, subject to his costs of the winding up being paid, the Liquidator consents to such an order. There is also evidence before me that the Australian Securities Investment Commission has been notified of the application to terminate the winding up and that it does not wish to be heard in relation to that application.

As to the public interest, I am satisfied that there are no public interest considerations that weigh against making an order terminating the winding up. I do not intend to imply that there are no ongoing issues to do with the management and records of the Defendant that still need to be attended to by the directors. I think there are. However, in my opinion these should be left to the directors of the Defendant and its newly appointed auditor.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>