<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZMTM v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 181 (27 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/181.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>SZMTM v Minister for Immigration and Anor [2008] FMCA 1642</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/1642.html</AustLII>
<text>There is before me an Application for Leave to Appeal from a judgment of a Federal Magistrate delivered on 8 December 2008 ( SZMTM v Minister for Immigration and Anor [2008] FMCA 1642) in which the Federal Magistrate dismissed with costs an application for judicial review of a decision made by the second respondent, the Refugee Review Tribunal ( the Tribunal ) handed down on 19 August 2008. The Tribunal's decision affirmed a decision of a delegate of the first respondent ( the Minister ) dated 14 April 2008 not to grant a protection visa to the applicant.

On 4 November 2008 Driver FM ordered that the applicant's application for judicial review be listed for a preliminary hearing under r 44.12 of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules 2001 ( the FMC Rules ). That hearing took place on 8 December 2008. On that day the learned Federal Magistrate dismissed the application pursuant to r 44.12(1)(a) of the FMC Rules. The effect of that order was that the decision of the Tribunal was affirmed.

Rule 44.12 of the FMC Rules is in the following terms: 
 44.12 Show cause hearing 
 (1) At a hearing of an application for an order to show cause, the Court may: 

(a) if it is not satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed&#8212;dismiss the application; or
 
(b) if it is satisfied that the application has raised an arguable case for the relief claimed&#8212;adjourn the proceeding and order a respondent to show cause at a final hearing why an order for the relief claimed should not be made on such of the grounds mentioned in the application as are specified by the Court; or
 
(c) without making an order under paragraph (b), make final orders in relation to the claims for relief and grounds mentioned in the application.
 
 (2) To avoid doubt, a dismissal under paragraph (1) (a) is interlocutory.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Decor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/655.html</AustLII>
<text>The discretion which the Court has in respect of such an application for leave to appeal is a wide one. However, it must not be exercised idiosyncratically and ordinarily would be informed by the principles articulated and explained by a Full Court of this Court in Decor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 33 FCR 397. In that case the Court held that, in determining whether leave to appeal should be granted from certain interlocutory decisions made by a judge in a patent case: 
(1) The decision in question must be demonstrated to be attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered on appeal; and
 
(2) The Court must be satisfied that substantial injustice would be visited upon the applicant if leave is not granted.

This is the test which I propose to apply to the application before me in the present case.

The applicant is a citizen of the People's Republic of China ( the PRC ). She arrived in Australia on 10 February 2008 on a subclass 456 business visa. On 7 March 2008, the applicant lodged an application for a Protection (Class XA) Visa with the Department of Immigration and Citizenship. A delegate of the Minister refused the application for a protection visa on 14 April 2008 and notified the applicant of that decision by letter dated, incorrectly, 14 December 2007. The reasons which accompanied that letter were dated 14 April 2008. On 9 May 2008, the applicant applied to the Tribunal for a review of that decision.

The protection claims which the applicant made originally were set out in a typed statutory declaration expressed in English. This statutory declaration accompanied her application for a protection visa. In that declaration, the applicant claimed that she had escaped from her husband, who was violent towards her, with the help of her friend, Ms Zhang, but that they were both later arrested for anti-revolutionary activities.

In the proceedings before the Tribunal the applicant claimed to fear persecution in the PRC on the basis of her political opinions. She also claimed to have been a victim of domestic violence whose problems had been publicised in newspaper articles by a journalist from the Fujian Daily . She claimed that she had been accused of being a counter-revolutionary on account of these articles, and that she had been subsequently detained for one month during which time she had been tortured and interrogated.

The applicant appeared at a hearing before the Tribunal on 9 July 2008. At that hearing, she had the assistance of an interpreter qualified to interpret as between Mandarin and English.

On 10 July 2008, the Tribunal sent a letter dated that day to Ms Priscilla Yu who was then acting as the migration agent for the applicant. In that letter the Tribunal invited the applicant to comment on and/or respond to information which was then of concern to it and which it considered to be relevant to its consideration of the applicant's application. That letter was issued pursuant to s 424A of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) ( the Act ).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>