<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLJF v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 158 (17 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/158.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 81 ALJR 1190</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/26.html</AustLII>
<text>I do not apprehend any error on the part of the Federal Magistrates Court in failing to find that such procedural fairness as is required by s 424A was not given to the appellant. In SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 81 ALJR 1190 at para 17, the High Court remarked of s 424(1)(a): 
 The use of the future conditional tense (would be) rather than the indicative, strongly suggests that the operation of section 424(1)(a) is to be determined in advance and independently of the tribunal's particular reasoning on the facts of the case.

What I have already observed in relation to s 424A is sufficient in the context of the present case to dispose of ground 2 of the notice of appeal. There was, in the circumstances, no obligation which arose under that section on the part of the Tribunal to give particulars in respect of the coincidence of lodgement of visa applications. There was no particularisation in the notice of appeal or oral submissions of what might otherwise constitute the adverse information. It is to be remembered, having regard to what was observed in SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 81 ALJR 1190 at para 18, that the Tribunal's subjective appraisals, thought processes, or determinations, do not constitute "information" for the purposes of s 424A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 269</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/269.html</AustLII>
<text>The Tribunal is required to give accurate particulars of adverse information to the applicant. Its failure to do so is jurisdictional error. see SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 269

The Appellant's application for a protection visa had been grounded upon his claim to fear persecution in India on account of his Christianity. More particularly, the claim was propounded upon his alleging to have preached to Dalits in Trivandrum, and encouraged their conversion thereby violating anti-conversion laws. He alleged that he had been arrested and held for three weeks and had been mistreated. He also alleged that he had been again arrested in January 2006 after what he described as the "Muslim dominated" CPI(M) had achieved power in Kerala. He claimed that the administration of his church had been told not to admit Muslims into the precinct and that he had been followed around Trivandrum. After the events so related the Appellant had visited Singapore. On his return he stated that he had been arrested and accused of converting Hindus. He further stated that he had been released on payment of one lakh, of Indian Rupees, and that he had been ordered to cease his religious activities.

His claim, further, was that he, his brother and his brother-in-law had subsequently resumed their Christian charitable activities in areas outside Trivandrum, but they had been arrested again in November 2006 and accused of procuring conversions. He further claimed that he, his brother and his brother-in-law had been threatened with deportation to Pakistan and ordered to cease all of their religious activities. It was on the strength of these claims that upon arrival in Australia the Appellant advanced his application for a protection visa.

Quite how the case SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 269 referred to in ground 2 was relevant was not developed in the Appellant's written or oral submissions. I have considered that case, which I note was decided on 7 March 2008. Its relevance to ground 2 is not immediately apparent.

All in all, this is just one of those cases where the Tribunal reached views concerning the claim made for a visa, based upon an assessment of the Appellant's credibility. Having considered the Tribunal's reasons, there is nothing remarkable in the Federal Magistrates Court's conclusion that the Tribunal was entitled to reach the views that it did. Findings of credit, providing they are not indicative of illogicality, are matters, "par excellence", for the Tribunal.

It follows that the appeal must be dismissed.
 I certify that the preceding twenty-three (23) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 25 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr P Cleary 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Clayton Utz Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 17 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 February 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/158.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SZKLK v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1125.html</AustLII>
<text>There was also advanced, in the course of oral submissions for the Appellant, the argument that the Federal Magistrates Court and it seems also the Tribunal, were in some way biased. There is not a scintilla of evidence which would support an apprehended bias challenge to the decision of the Federal Magistrates Court. In particular, the fact that that court gave its reasons for judgment upon the day on which the judicial review application was heard, does not support such a finding. As for the Tribunal proceeding, there was not developed before me any argument that the hearing before the Tribunal, in terms of the procedures adopted by the Tribunal, and having regard to its reasons, was such as would give rise to an apprehension of bias of the kind that I found present in SZKLK v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1125.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLPJ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1721</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1721.html</AustLII>
<text>This acknowledged, it is permissible, in my opinion, to draw an inference that, even prospectively, the adverse contingency, which generated on the part of the first Tribunal, the letter of 3 July 2007, did not form part of the second Tribunal's thinking. That inference, to me, seems to be open from para 102 of the Tribunal's reasons. I note that in SZLPJ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1721 , Perram J adopted a similar approach: see especially para 16 of his Honour's reasons for judgment.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>