<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Zegarac v Pitcher Partners [2009] FCA 1061 (17 September 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1061.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543</tocase>
<text>It has been well established that an applicant for leave to appeal has no election available to decide who shall hear the application, either a single judge or a Full Court. That is a matter for the judge before whom the motion comes for determination to decide. In Wati v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (1997) 78 FCR 543 the Full Court said at 554: 
 
 "... it is open to the applicant to ask the Court or judge before whom the matter is listed to consider referring it to a Full Court or a single judge (as the case may be). It is then for the judge or the Full Court before whom the matter is listed to consider whether the matter is more appropriately dealt with in the manner suggested by the applicant. ..."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kristoffersen v Department of Employment, Workplace Relations and Small Business [2002] FCAFC 269</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/269.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kristoffersen v Department of Employment, Workplace Relations and Small Business [2002] FCAFC 269 Drummond J (with whom Cooper and Dowsett JJ agreed) quoted this passage and went on to say: 
 
 " That, in my opinion, is a clear statement that there is in truth no election available to a litigant to determine which is the forum in which an application of the present kind will be held. As their Honours say, the litigant can request that the matter be heard either by a single judge or by a Full Court. But it is for the Court to determine, having regard to considerations such as the importance of the issue raised and the efficient deployment of judicial resources and other matters, which forum will in fact be constituted to deal with the application." 
 

 
See also Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs v WAKX [2005] FCA 227 at [25] - [33] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs v WAKX [2005] FCA 227</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/227.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kristoffersen v Department of Employment, Workplace Relations and Small Business [2002] FCAFC 269 Drummond J (with whom Cooper and Dowsett JJ agreed) quoted this passage and went on to say: 
 
 " That, in my opinion, is a clear statement that there is in truth no election available to a litigant to determine which is the forum in which an application of the present kind will be held. As their Honours say, the litigant can request that the matter be heard either by a single judge or by a Full Court. But it is for the Court to determine, having regard to considerations such as the importance of the issue raised and the efficient deployment of judicial resources and other matters, which forum will in fact be constituted to deal with the application." 
 

 
See also Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs v WAKX [2005] FCA 227 at [25] - [33] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd v Philip Morris Incorporated [1981] HCA 39 ; (1981) 148 CLR 170</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/39.html</AustLII>
<text>I am mindful of the observation of the majority of the High Court in Adam P Brown Male Fashions Pty Ltd v Philip Morris Incorporated [1981] HCA 39 ; (1981) 148 CLR 170 at 177 that: 
 
 "... appellate courts exercise particular caution in reviewing decisions pertaining to practice and procedure." 
 

 
It is clear from the judgment of the High Court that in order for leave to appeal to be granted in respect of a matter of practice and procedure it must be established that not only is there an error of principle in the reasoning of the primary judge but also that the decision appealed from must work a substantial injustice to one of the parties if it is not reviewed.

In the present case no error of principle is disclosed in the order made by the primary judge. Further, his decision does not work an injustice, whether substantial or otherwise, to the applicant. The primary judge has made no decision in relation to the disposition of the respondent's motion. The applicant will have every opportunity to respond to the matters raised by the respondent at the hearing of the motion. All that has happened is that preliminary steps have been taken by the primary judge to enable the parties to file and exchange contentions of fact and law which will facilitate the disposition of the hearing of the respondent's notice of motion.

It was for these reasons that I dismissed the application for leave to appeal. 
 I certify that the preceding eighteen (18) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Goldberg. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 18 September 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: The applicant appeared in person 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: S Bond 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Schetzer Brott &amp; Appel 
 Date of Hearing: 17 September 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 September 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1061.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>