<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>EMAS Offshore Pte Ltd v The Ship "APC Aussie 1" (No 2) [2009] FCA 1583 (23 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1583.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v DB Management Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 7 ; (2000) 199 CLR 321</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/7.html</AustLII>
<text>If the person seeking the release of the ship were not, prima facie, liable to pay all of the costs of and in connection with her custody and release, there could be a serious inhibition on the exercise by plaintiffs of their rights to arrest. And, this construction would extend the limited form of liability of a person who caused an arrest created by the Parliament in s 34 in cases where the power to arrest had been misused. I reject APC's argument that a defendant who seeks the release of its ship, would simply be required to provide security for the costs and expenses which the plaintiff had already paid to the Marshal in connection with its arrest. A literal meaning of the Rules does not support that construction : Australian Securities and Investments Commission v DB Management Pty Ltd [2000] HCA 7 ; (2000) 199 CLR 321 at 338 [34] - [35] .

I am of opinion that at the present time the costs and expenses of the actual arrest should be paid out of the amount that EMAS has paid to the Marshal and the balance of its payment of $100,000 returned to it. And, all other costs and expenses of the Marshal, including in connection with keeping the barge in custody and its release, should be paid out of the $92,100 paid by APC to secure the release. So much of the balance of those funds, equal to what was paid out of EMAS' $100,000, should be added to the amount paid into court by APC as security to abide the ultimate disposition of the proceedings. EMAS may later be able to establish its entitlement to this sum under r 75C or in the substantive proceedings.

This allocation of responsibility reflects the prima facie distribution of the burden of the undertakings in rr 41 and 53 which EMAS and APC respectively assumed when each of them became bound to honour them. And it ensures that the security available to EMAS will not be diminished by the costs of the arrest in the event that it is successful in the end result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Patrick Stevedores No 2 Pty Limited v Ship MV "Turakina" (No 2) (1998) 84 FCR 506</tocase>
<text>In Patrick Stevedores No 2 Pty Limited v Ship MV "Turakina" (No 2) (1998) 84 FCR 506 at 509E-F, Tamberlin J said that it was neither necessary nor appropriate to approach the undertakings, as then provided for in the Rules, on the basis that they were mutually exclusive. He also said that the undertakings did not have to be read down so as not to cover costs or expenses that may be encompassed by other undertakings that might be given by other persons. He observed that the Marshal could not claim double reimbursement in respect of the same costs or expenses. His Honour suggested that the parties should negotiate and resolve, as between themselves, the working out of the entitlements and obligations of each party who had provided an undertaking. However, this was prior to the introduction of r 75C.

The undertaking that form 19 requires extends to the whole of the period of the arrest and the release, because the applicant for release must apply under r 52(1) in accordance with form 19 for the release of the ship. Once the person seeking the release of the ship from arrest provides a payment to the Marshal, or a sufficient level of confidence in the undertaking given, the ship will be released. Ordinarily, the person seeking the release of the ship will be the relevant person or someone acting for the relevant person. If the arrest has been short, the costs and expenses are not likely to be large. But, if the arrest has been for a long period of time (until the relevant person has been impelled to appear or to provide the security necessary to recover the ship from arrest) prima facie, there could be a hardship on a plaintiff if APC's construction of the operation of the Rules were correct.

As Tamberlin J pointed out the Marshal cannot obtain double reimbursement. In the present case, the Marshal obtained security from EMAS, in the form of cash paid pursuant to his demands. But, the Marshal did not pay any costs and expenses prior to receiving the form 19 and payment from APC. Giving effect to APC's argument would produce the consequence that EMAS would now have to pay all of the Marshal's costs and expenses while APC would simply provide security for those payments to be available in the event that it were held liable for them at the conclusion of the proceedings. Such a construction does not lie easily with the requirements of r 52(1), r 53 and form 19. Nor, does it sit easily with the ordinary and natural meaning of s 34(1)(a)(ii) that limits the right of, among others, a relevant person in APC's position to recover damages from a plaintiff in EMAS' position for wrongful arrest.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>