<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Atkinson [2009] FCA 1565 (22 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1565.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chief Executive, Department of Internal Affairs v Atkinson &amp; Ors CIV-2008-409-002391</tocase>
<text>As to s 24(2)(c) , the circumstances in which the contravention took place are outlined in the agreed statement of facts. As to s 24(2)(d) , Mr Atkinson has not previously been found by the Court in proceedings under the Spam Act to have engaged in any conduct similar to a contravention of s 16(1). Section 24(2)(e) addresses the question of whether Mr Atkinson has previously been found by a Court in a foreign country to have engaged in any similar conduct. As to that matter, the parties make this joint submission at para 53: 
 
 In December 2008, Mr Atkinson was found by the High Court of New Zealand to have engaged in similar conduct arising from the same underlying facts [ Chief Executive, Department of Internal Affairs v Atkinson &amp; Ors CIV-2008-409-002391, per French J, 19 December 2008]. Mr Atkinson cooperated with New Zealand authorities to resolve those proceedings, and paid a pecuniary penalty in the amount of NZ$100,000 in respect of contravening emails sent to recipients in New Zealand.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Trade Commission v Atkinson &amp; Ors , United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois, Eastern Division, Case No. 08CV5666</tocase>
<text>Mr Atkinson was the subject of proceedings in the United States: Federal Trade Commission v Atkinson &amp; Ors , United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois, Eastern Division, Case No. 08CV5666. At para 6 of supplementary joint written submissions provided to the Court on the day of the hearing, the parties said this about the United States proceedings: 
 
 United States judgment 
 

 Paragraph 54 of the October submissions refers to proceedings on foot against Mr Atkinson in the United States, arising from the same conduct as is the subject of these proceedings. Default judgment has now been handed down in the United States proceedings, in the matter of Federal Trade Commission v Atkinson &amp; Ors , United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois, Eastern Division, Case No. 08CV5666. An amount of US$15,151,029 was imposed jointly and severally upon Mr Atkinson and Inet Venture Pty Ltd, as equitable monetary relief for violations of the Federal Trade Commission Act ( FTC Act ) and the Controlling the Assault of Non-Solicited Pornography and Marketing Act of 2003 ( CAN-SPAM Act ). 
 As set out at paragraphs 37 and 53- 55 of the October submissions, s.24(2) of the Spam Act provides that a relevant consideration for the Court is: 
 
 
 if the Court considers that it is appropriate to do so - whether the person has previously been found by a court in a foreign country to have engaged in any similar conduct. 
 

 The parties submit that the findings of the United States court are relevant and should be taken into account by the Court, but do not amount to prior findings of contraventions that pre-date the conduct the subject of these proceedings, as they arise from the same conduct, and accordingly are not an aggravating factor. As the penalties sought in the present proceedings are in respect only of such emails as are connected with Australia, the parties submit a penalty in the amount proposed remains appropriate.

On 4 November 2009, default judgment in the United States case was entered against five of the six defendants in the proceeding, including Mr Atkinson. The proceeding, commenced by the Federal Trade Commission ("FTC"), alleged a range of contraventions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (the "FTC Act"), concerning contended deceptive practices in connection with the sale of certain purported herbal products and a pharmaceutical medication, some of which involved representations as to sexual enhancement. There seems to be some correlation between the products in issue and those the subject of these proceedings. In addition, the proceedings involved contended contraventions of the United States Controlling the Assault of Non-Solicited Pornography and Marketing Act 2003 (the "CAN-SPAM Act"). Various provisions of the CAN-SPAM Act were relied upon by the FTC in the proceedings. The essential contention was that Mr Atkinson and others had initiated the transmission of unsolicited computer email messages in contravention of the Act in respect of the sale and promotion of the above products. The Court found, on the face of the FTC material, that there had been contraventions of the CAN-SPAM Act, and that: 
 
 (A) the total amount of consumer injury caused by Defendants Lance Thomas Atkinson and [Inet Ventures Pty Ltd, a corporate defendant of which Mr Atkinson was found to be the sole officer] for the sale of their Hoodia Products [herbal products] Male Enhancement Products, prescription drugs, and other products through illegal commercial email messages is $15,151,029.

In those proceedings a range of findings were made in relation to the pleaded conduct and judgment was entered in favour of the FTC against Lance Thomas Atkinson and Inet Ventures Pty Ltd, jointly and severally, in the amount of $15,151,029 for violations of the FTC Act and the CAN-SPAM Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Clarity1 Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1399; (2006) 155 FCR 377</tocase>
<text>There have now been three judgments of the Court in respect of contraventions of s 16 (among other provisions) of the Spam Act . They are, Australian Communications and Media Authority v Clarity1 Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1399; (2006) 155 FCR 377 per Nicholson J; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong (No 4) [2009] FCA 1225 ; (2009) 261 ALR 326 per Logan J; and a further ex tempore judgment by Logan J on 16 December 2009 concerning further respondents in the Mobilegate litigation ( Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd (No 6) [2009] FCA 1533).

The decision of Nicholson J in Clarity1 , involved conduct on the part of the corporation of sending 270,305,474 commercial electronic messages between 10 April 2004 and 13 April 2006. In the majority of these contraventions, Clarity1 had used harvested addresses in contravention of s 22(1) of the Spam Act . Mr Mansfield, the second respondent, was found to have aided, abetted, counselled and procured the contraventions and to have been knowingly concerned in or a party to them. The Court found Mr Mansfield to have been "closely involved" in the contraventions. The proceedings were contested. Nicholson J made findings of fact in a primary judgment and addressed the question of the pecuniary penalty in the judgment cited above.

Nicholson J took these matters into account: it was difficult to quantify the loss or damage caused by the conduct and thus the presence of loss or damage was treated as a possible aggravating circumstance; the contraventions involved a "huge volume" of electronic messages described by witnesses as "annoying, time consuming and frustrating" resulting in responses through filtering and blocking software; since the contravening conduct was the first conduct to be prosecuted under the Spam Act and the respondents genuinely believed that their conduct did not involve a contravention, these circumstances amounted to "an important factor in their favour"; the respondents had not been found by the Court to have engaged in previous contraventions; although the conduct of the respondents was deliberate, the deliberateness was an expression of their belief that their understanding of the new law was correct; and, the issue of capacity to pay a pecuniary penalty, although a relevant factor, was of less relevance when balanced against the necessity of imposing a penalty meeting the objective of general deterrence. His Honour applied the totality principle.

On the question of cooperation, the applicant acknowledged that the respondents had not attempted to hinder or prevent it from conducting its investigation of the respondent's conduct. The applicant contended that cooperation flowed from the fact that at no time did the respondents entertain the possibility that their conduct might contravene the Spam Act . The respondents vigorously opposed the position asserted by the applicant that they had not shown any cooperation in relevant respects. Nevertheless, one point of distinction between Clarity1 and the present proceeding is that the respondents in Clarity1 contested the proceedings because they believed their conduct did not involve a contravention of the Act. Thus, they simply sought to ventilate their view of the quality of their conduct in the face of new legislative provisions.

In these proceedings, Mr Atkinson, in the face of enforcement proceedings, exhibited genuine cooperation with the Authority.

In approaching the assessment of the pecuniary penalty, Nicholson J considered that there is a need for "commercial realism in fixing penalties". He also said this: One difficulty which emerges in the application of the pecuniary penalty provisions in the new Act is that the maximum penalties are so high as to give rise to "an unrealistically large penalty". The unrealistic character derives principally from the quantum of penalty viewed in relation to the capacity of either respondent to pay and the need for general as well as specific deterrence. It is not just the total quantum of a pecuniary penalty which can provide the element of general deterrence. That quality derives from a consideration of the penalty in relation to the conduct giving rise to it and the financial capacity of the offenders. Where the financial capacity is not great, a [lesser] pecuniary penalty in value will derive its quality of general deterrence from its magnitude in relation to that capacity. 
 [As to a penalty of $9.9m sought against Clarity1 ] A penalty in the amount of $9.9 million is clearly one beyond the capacity of Clarity1 to pay and so likely to lead to its liquidation. It is quite disproportionate to the commercial realities of Clarity1 . Even as proposed it is in the particular circumstances "an unrealistically large penalty". ... It is overly weighted in favour of general deterrence. Importantly, it does not appear to be constructed on any allowance of the new character of the legislation and the entitlement of the respondents to test their view of the effect of the legislation.

Similar views were expressed in relation to the pecuniary penalty sought against the individual, Mr Mansfield. In the end result a pecuniary penalty of $1m was imposed upon Mr Mansfield. The pecuniary penalties imposed in the matter amounted to approximately 5% of the maximum penalties possible.

Secondly , I consider that the decisions of the Court in Clarity1 and Mobilegate engage factors which significantly differentiate those cases from the present case. Clarity1 was a fully contested proceeding involving a different class and scale of conduct. There was no cooperation in relation to the proceeding because the respondents took the view that their conduct did not involve a contravention of the relevant provisions especially in circumstances where the legislation had not been tested and no judicial determination was before the respondents which may have aided their analysis of the various integers contained in the sections. The respondents in Clarity1 cooperated in the conduct of the case but not in the sense of accepting the contention that its conduct contravened the Spam Act , so as to avoid the applicant incurring the costs of the proceeding.

The decision in Mobilegate involved truly reprehensible predatory conduct of a kind which warranted a penalty directed emphatically towards specific deterrence and transparent general deterrence. The class of conduct the subject of Mobilegate is not evident in these proceedings.

Thirdly , however, as to the class of conduct on the part of Mr Atkinson, there is simply no doubt that Australian citizens find large-scale distribution of unsolicited commercial electronic messages promoting the sale of products, in the circumstances of this case, very irritating and annoying. It causes all users of computers to constantly update spam filters and other protective devices to try to deflect the unwanted rain of electrons and digits disseminated by those who wish to do what Mr Atkinson has done. The Parliament has made its intention plain that the unsolicited distribution of electronic emails (spam) is to be discouraged.

Notwithstanding these considerations, the Court ought to take into account and attach significant weight to Mr Atkinson's cooperation with the Authority in isolating the extent of the conduct and in seeking to resolve the present claims on the basis of admissions and a joint submission.

Fourthly , Mr Atkinson is represented by independent lawyers and he has formed his view as to the various matters the subject of the submission with the assistance of that advice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Limited A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong (No 4) [2009] FCA 1225 ; (2009) 261 ALR 326</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/1225.html</AustLII>
<text>There have now been three judgments of the Court in respect of contraventions of s 16 (among other provisions) of the Spam Act . They are, Australian Communications and Media Authority v Clarity1 Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1399; (2006) 155 FCR 377 per Nicholson J; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong (No 4) [2009] FCA 1225 ; (2009) 261 ALR 326 per Logan J; and a further ex tempore judgment by Logan J on 16 December 2009 concerning further respondents in the Mobilegate litigation ( Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd (No 6) [2009] FCA 1533).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Limited A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong (No 6) [2009] FCA 1533</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/1533.html</AustLII>
<text>There have now been three judgments of the Court in respect of contraventions of s 16 (among other provisions) of the Spam Act . They are, Australian Communications and Media Authority v Clarity1 Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1399; (2006) 155 FCR 377 per Nicholson J; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong (No 4) [2009] FCA 1225 ; (2009) 261 ALR 326 per Logan J; and a further ex tempore judgment by Logan J on 16 December 2009 concerning further respondents in the Mobilegate litigation ( Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd (No 6) [2009] FCA 1533).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Stihl ChainSaws (Aust) Pty Ltd (1978) ATPR 40-091</tocase>
<text>In Mobilegate , Logan J was addressing conduct involving the sending of unsolicited short-message-service messages to the mobile telephones of users who had been deceived into providing their mobile telephone numbers to representatives of either Mobilegate , the first respondent, or Winning Bid , the second respondent, under the belief that they were corresponding with individuals seeking to meet them and form relationships via dating web-sites. Logan J described the respondents as "predators on the emotionally vulnerable for reward" which was "a particularly vile form of behaviour". His Honour said the conduct was "duplicitous and exploitative" and "cruel and callous". His Honour concluded that this class of conduct warranted a "very substantial penalty". Among a number of considerations his Honour noted that the conduct was deliberate and covert and that penalties must be sufficiently significant to "deter the unscrupulous from taking a calculated business risk" but should not be so high as to be "oppressive" in the sense contemplated in Trade Practices Commission v Stihl ChainSaws (Aust) Pty Ltd [1978] FCA 104; (1978) ATPR 40-091. In addition, the evidence demonstrated that there was approximately $4m of financial loss on the part of individual mobile telephone users who were charged communications fees. His Honour found that the conduct was "of such an intimate exploitive nature that the exploiter by the very conduct gives itself, himself or herself, a degree of insulation at a practical level from suits for financial recovery" and the conduct involved a "consistent pattern of studied deception". It was deliberate contravening conduct with no mitigating circumstances.

In addition, there was no evident cooperation in the administration of justice.

The entity, Mobilegate , was ordered to pay $5m which represented 6.87% of a possible maximum of approximately $72,820,000. The entity Winning Bid was ordered to pay $3,500,000 representing 8.51% of a possible maximum of $41,140,000. So far as the individuals were concerned, Logan J took into account that their involvement was extensive, knowing and persistent. However, in examining the implications which might be drawn from statutory maximum pecuniary penalties in the context of individuals found to be parties to contravening corporate conduct, Logan J considered assessment of the maximum penalty as a "theoretical exercise". Significant pecuniary penalties were ordered against the individuals having regard to the quality of their engagement in the conduct of the corporation. There is little point isolating the amount of each penalty in respect of each individual in the circumstances of the findings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Markarian v The Queen (2005) 228 CLR 357</tocase>
<text>Clearly, it is important to take into account the scale of penalties the Parliament has selected as the appropriate range leading to a maximum penalty in respect of contraventions of particular legislation. Often, careful attention will need to be given to the Parliament's selection of maximum penalties as an expression of the Parliamentary intention that particular conduct, must be transparently deterred. This is entirely consistent with Markarian v The Queen (2005) 228 CLR 357. In addition, the Regulation Impact Statement at p 4 of the EM sets out the following statement of the problem sought to be addressed by the Spam Act at p 4. 
 
 B.1 Problem or issue identification 
 

 
 
 Unsolicited electronic messages or "spam" are reaching plague proportions and growing exponentially. It is causing immense frustration and reduced productivity for users, businesses and government agencies. If left unchecked it will reach proportions which will threaten the viability of the internet as a reliable communications medium. A recent comprehensive review of the problem by the National Office for the Information Economy recommended a multi-layered approach to addressing the problem, including the implementation of specific anti-spam legislation.

The EM describes the problem so identified as an international problem affecting the efficient operation of internet telecommunications networks and imposing costs on end-users. At p 5, the EM notes, "There are clear signs of a deleterious impact on the performance of the global e-mail network with some commentators predicting that the continuing proliferation of spam could mean the end of e-mail as an effective form of communication".

At p 67, the EM contains this observation in relation to penalties: 
 
 A daily ceiling for penalties has been set that may be charged for all contraventions against a particular provision that have occurred in one day. This has been included to ensure that a meaningful penalty may be charged for a single contravention without causing an unrealistically large penalty payable for multiple contraventions. For example, there are reported cases of dedicated spammers sending millions of unsolicited commercial electronic messages each day. Without a ceiling amount for daily contraventions, such a spammer could potentially be liable for a million contraventions. The ratio between the penalty payable for a person for single contravention and the ceiling amount is 20 times. 
 

 Conclusions</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72</tocase>
<text>Eighthly , although the pecuniary penalty is a matter for the Court to determine ( Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72), and the question of whether the Court ought to make declarations as to particular matters or injunctions framed in a particular way or at all necessarily involves discretionary considerations and questions of utility, the Court will attach significant weight to a negotiated settlement quickly reached between parties acting with the benefit of legal advice, provided the document identifies the conduct precisely; the responsibility of each respondent in that conduct is recognised (whether at the centre or at the margin); and the proposed penalty is within the range the Court would impose and is thus not manifestly inadequate: Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) (2009) 178 FCR 199. The approach to the assessment of a pecuniary penalty under the Spam Act ought, in principle, to reflect some of the considerations applied by the Court in assessing a pecuniary penalty under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). In particular, the Court will have regard to the elements of specific and general deterrence and assess whether a proposed penalty might be so high as to be oppressive in all the circumstances: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301; TPC v Stihl Chainsaws (Aust) Pty Limited ; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v ACCC at 293.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375</tocase>
<text>Eighthly , although the pecuniary penalty is a matter for the Court to determine ( Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72), and the question of whether the Court ought to make declarations as to particular matters or injunctions framed in a particular way or at all necessarily involves discretionary considerations and questions of utility, the Court will attach significant weight to a negotiated settlement quickly reached between parties acting with the benefit of legal advice, provided the document identifies the conduct precisely; the responsibility of each respondent in that conduct is recognised (whether at the centre or at the margin); and the proposed penalty is within the range the Court would impose and is thus not manifestly inadequate: Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) (2009) 178 FCR 199. The approach to the assessment of a pecuniary penalty under the Spam Act ought, in principle, to reflect some of the considerations applied by the Court in assessing a pecuniary penalty under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). In particular, the Court will have regard to the elements of specific and general deterrence and assess whether a proposed penalty might be so high as to be oppressive in all the circumstances: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301; TPC v Stihl Chainsaws (Aust) Pty Limited ; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v ACCC at 293.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285</tocase>
<text>Eighthly , although the pecuniary penalty is a matter for the Court to determine ( Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72), and the question of whether the Court ought to make declarations as to particular matters or injunctions framed in a particular way or at all necessarily involves discretionary considerations and questions of utility, the Court will attach significant weight to a negotiated settlement quickly reached between parties acting with the benefit of legal advice, provided the document identifies the conduct precisely; the responsibility of each respondent in that conduct is recognised (whether at the centre or at the margin); and the proposed penalty is within the range the Court would impose and is thus not manifestly inadequate: Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) (2009) 178 FCR 199. The approach to the assessment of a pecuniary penalty under the Spam Act ought, in principle, to reflect some of the considerations applied by the Court in assessing a pecuniary penalty under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). In particular, the Court will have regard to the elements of specific and general deterrence and assess whether a proposed penalty might be so high as to be oppressive in all the circumstances: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301; TPC v Stihl Chainsaws (Aust) Pty Limited ; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v ACCC at 293.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 754</tocase>
<text>Eighthly , although the pecuniary penalty is a matter for the Court to determine ( Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72), and the question of whether the Court ought to make declarations as to particular matters or injunctions framed in a particular way or at all necessarily involves discretionary considerations and questions of utility, the Court will attach significant weight to a negotiated settlement quickly reached between parties acting with the benefit of legal advice, provided the document identifies the conduct precisely; the responsibility of each respondent in that conduct is recognised (whether at the centre or at the margin); and the proposed penalty is within the range the Court would impose and is thus not manifestly inadequate: Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) (2009) 178 FCR 199. The approach to the assessment of a pecuniary penalty under the Spam Act ought, in principle, to reflect some of the considerations applied by the Court in assessing a pecuniary penalty under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). In particular, the Court will have regard to the elements of specific and general deterrence and assess whether a proposed penalty might be so high as to be oppressive in all the circumstances: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301; TPC v Stihl Chainsaws (Aust) Pty Limited ; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v ACCC at 293.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301</tocase>
<text>Eighthly , although the pecuniary penalty is a matter for the Court to determine ( Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72), and the question of whether the Court ought to make declarations as to particular matters or injunctions framed in a particular way or at all necessarily involves discretionary considerations and questions of utility, the Court will attach significant weight to a negotiated settlement quickly reached between parties acting with the benefit of legal advice, provided the document identifies the conduct precisely; the responsibility of each respondent in that conduct is recognised (whether at the centre or at the margin); and the proposed penalty is within the range the Court would impose and is thus not manifestly inadequate: Trade Practices Commission v TNT Australia Pty Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-375; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Radio 2UE Sydney Pty Ltd (No 2) (2009) 178 FCR 199. The approach to the assessment of a pecuniary penalty under the Spam Act ought, in principle, to reflect some of the considerations applied by the Court in assessing a pecuniary penalty under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). In particular, the Court will have regard to the elements of specific and general deterrence and assess whether a proposed penalty might be so high as to be oppressive in all the circumstances: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) (2005) 215 ALR 301; TPC v Stihl Chainsaws (Aust) Pty Limited ; NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v ACCC at 293.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>