<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lelleton v White [2009] FCA 1165 (12 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1165.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Trihakis v Official Receiver (Vic) [1999] FCA 1426</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1426.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Lelleton nonetheless contends that he satisfied the requirements of s 54(1)(a) of the Act by posting the Statement of Affairs to the Registrar in Bankruptcy. He relied on the decision of Kenny J in Trihakis v Official Receiver (Vic) [1999] FCA 1426. Her Honour there held that a Statement of Affairs could be filed by posting a completed original statement to the Registrar. In that case a declaration of the kind presently sought was granted in circumstances in which her Honour was satisfied that a Statement of Affairs had been posted but, for some undisclosed reason, could not be found on the Registrar's file.

I am satisfied, on the balance of probabilities, that Mr Lelleton posted his Statement of Affairs to the Registrar as he claims, on or about 19 April 1995. I am so satisfied for a number of reasons. Mr Lelleton has sworn that he posted the document. He retained a copy of it. The copied form appears in a format that was in use in 1995 but is not presently in use. It is dated April 1995. It is inherently unlikely that Mr Lelleton would have attempted to reconstruct such a form so long after the event. It is also inherently unlikely that, having gone to the trouble of completing a long form in a timely way, he would not have attempted to comply with the obligation which Mr White had brought to his attention by posting it from Sydney to the Registrar.

At all relevant times s 149(4) of the Act provided: 
 
 "(4) If the bankrupt becomes a bankrupt after the commencement of s 27 of the Bankruptcy Amendment Act 1991 , the bankrupt is discharged at the end of the period of 3 years from the date on which the bankrupt filed his or her statement of affairs." 
 

It is to be noted that the three year period runs from the date on which the Statement of Affairs was filed. It does not run from the date on which the Trustee is provided with a copy of the Statement. Mr Lelleton's failure to provide a copy of the Statement to Mr White in 1995 can, therefore, have no bearing on the determination of the date of his discharge from bankruptcy.

The relevant date is the date of filing. In Trihakis , Kenny J fixed the date of filing as a day that was three days after the Statement of Affairs was signed in order to allow for any delay in posting and delivery. Given that the Statement in the present proceeding was despatched from Sydney on 19 April 1995, I consider that an allowance of two business days should be made such that the date of filing should be fixed, not as 19 April 1995 (the date of signing) but 21 April 1995. Discharge, by operation of s 149(4) of the Act would, therefore, have occurred on 21 April 1998.

I note that Mr White's letter to Mr Lelleton is dated 7 April 1995. If an equivalent allowance of two days is made for it to have been received by Mr Lelleton, his Statement of Affairs was filed, as required by s 54(1)(a) of the Act, within 14 days from the date on which he was notified of his bankruptcy.

Declarations, consistent with these findings, will be made.
 I certify that the preceding nineteen (19) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 12 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr L Watts 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mr R Silverstein 
 Date of Hearing: 12 October 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 12 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1165.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sofia and Anor v Pattison and Anor [1997] VG 7619 (Unreported, Finkelstein J, 20 October 1997)</tocase>
<text>In Sofia and Anor v Pattison and Anor , [1997] VG 7619 (Unreported, Finkelstein J, 20 October 1997), his Honour said: 
 
 "Whether the word "file" in s 54(1) is intended to be a reference to the act of the bankrupt or the act of the Registrar is unclear. But, having regard to the context in which the word is used it should be regarded as a reference to the act of the bankrupt. In the first place, the obligation that is imposed by s 54(1) is an obligation that is imposed on the bankrupt. In the second place the obligation is to file a document at a particular place namely at a Registry. This suggests that the statement will be filed when it is left with an officer at the Registry rather than when it has been placed on a file that is maintained at the Registry. Thus the section will be complied with whether or not the statement is subsequently placed on a file by the officer who received it." 
 

This decision provides some assistance to Mr Lelleton. It is authority for the proposition that it cannot be concluded that a statement has not been filed for the purposes of s 54(1) simply because the document does not appear on a file maintained by the Registrar. Mr Lelleton did not, however, hand deliver his Statement to the Registry. He posted it and is unable to explain why it does not appear on file. There are a number of possibilities, the most obvious ones being that it went astray in the mail or, having been delivered to the Registry it was, for some unknown reason, not placed on file.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>