<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZJLN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 144 (16 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/144.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/21.html</AustLII>
<text>There is no merit in a challenge which would seek to overturn the Federal Magistrate's decision on the basis that the Tribunal's reasons were unreasonable and that the Federal Magistrates Court should have so found. It is important to recall, and the Appellant's submissions both written and oral as is frequently the case do not, and did not, evidence this, that it is no part of the role of the judiciary, either in the Federal Magistrates Court or on this Court, to engage in the making of value judgments or fact finding in relation to whether or not one is satisfied in terms of the Act that there is a claim for a protection visa. To do so is to violate the role consigned to the judiciary and to ignore the counsel provided by Brennan J, as his Honour was, in Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin [1990] HCA 21 ; (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 30, about a threat to the legitimacy of judicial review by descending into matters that are consigned by the legislature to the value judgment of either the Minister, his delegates or the Tribunal.

For these reasons then the appeal must be dismissed. 
 I certify that the preceding twenty-two (22) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 25 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellants: The male Appellant appeared in person on his own behalf and on behalf of his wife, the female Appellant. 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr P Cleary 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Sparke Helmore 
 Date of Hearing: 16 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 16 February 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/144.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration; Ex parte Duraraijasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/1.html</AustLII>
<text>One sees in those written submissions what, in substance, is a challenge to the credibility findings made by the Tribunal. Such findings are uniquely, "par excellence", as McHugh J stated in Re Minister for Immigration; Ex parte Duraraijasingham [2000] HCA 1 ; (2000) 168 ALR 407 at para 67, matters for the Tribunal. When one reads the Tribunal's reasons those findings are logical and reasonable; reasonable in the sense that they are made upon a basis that is readily discernible from the findings of fact the Tribunal chose to make on the material that it had before it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 81 ALJR 1190</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/26.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 422B of the Migration Act provides that the provisions found within Div 4 of Pt 7 are an exhaustive statement of the natural justice hearing rule. Those provisions include s 424A. In this instance it is at least arguable, having regard to the High Court's decision in SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 81 ALJR 1190 , that the Tribunal went beyond the obligation imposed on it by s 424A of the Act. I make that observation because it is possible to regard the letter which the Tribunal sent as disclosing the thought processes of the Tribunal. Be this as it may, it is certainly not a basis for a jurisdictional error case that the Tribunal exceeded the obligation imposed on it by s 424A.

This otherwise is a case where there is no basis for concluding that the Federal Magistrates Court was in error insofar as any jurisdictional error in relation to s 424A is concerned. The first ground of appeal has about it a generality such that when one departs from an apprehension that lying behind it might be a s 424A based challenge, one is in the area of speculation.

Having regard to the way in which the argument developed this morning it seems to me that the procedural fairness challenge may well be on the basis of a failure to take into account the translated document, exhibit 1. The Federal Magistrate dealt in what, in my opinion, is an unexceptional way with a challenge of that kind as the learned Federal Magistrate apprehended it. The short point is that the Appellants were given an opportunity to submit a translated document. It is just that, for whatever reason, that opportunity was not availed of. As it happens, the essence of the document, as the learned Federal Magistrate notes, is no different to a finding made in the male Appellant's favour; namely, membership of Shiv Sena in 2001.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZGHS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1572</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1572.html</AustLII>
<text>The second of the grounds of appeal, insofar as it goes beyond procedural fairness, is not only a ground which does not appear to have been a basis of challenge before the Federal Magistrates Court, but also, in any event, a ground which would not warrant leave to advance it in this appeal. The Tribunal, in the passage from which I have quoted, looked to and made an express finding in respect of the foreseeable future in the event of a return to India. In this regard, the Tribunal referred to findings it had already made. It suffices to note that those findings were based on a preference of independent country information as to an absence of a particular threat of prosecution. There is, in the Tribunal's reasons in this case, no error of the kind described by Allsop J (as his Honour then was) in SZGHS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1572 at paras 28, 29 and 30.

What I have stated is sufficient to dispose of the appeal in respect of the grounds stated in the notice of appeal. Neither has any merit.

On behalf of the Minister the course was taken, very properly, to engage with submissions advanced in the Appellant's written submissions, which did not find their way into the notice of appeal.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>