<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Emu Brewery Developments Pty Ltd, In the matter of Emu Brewery Developments Pty Ltd (in liquidation) [2009] FCA 1212 (27 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1212.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Dean-Willcocks v Soluble Solution Hydroponics Pty Ltd (1997) 42 NSWLR 209 at 212</tocase>
<text>The plaintiffs submit that the orders sought in this case correspond with those made in a number of cases, including QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687 and Re HIH Insurance [2004] NSWSC 5. In those cases, the order regarding the liquidator's justification for entering into the settlement was made under s 479(3) of the Act. The plaintiffs submit that s 479 and s 511 perform similar functions citing Dean-Willcocks v Soluble Solution Hydroponics Pty Ltd (1997) 42 NSWLR 209 at 212. However, as Young J pointed out this is not "completely true".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Elderslie Finance Corporation Ltd v Newpage (No 6) [2007] FCA 1030 ; (2007) 160 FCR 423</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1030.html</AustLII>
<text>The Court may approve a compromise if one of a number of ways of presenting a claim involves a "debt" claim: Elderslie Finance Corporation Ltd v Newpage (No 6) [2007] FCA 1030 ; (2007) 160 FCR 423 at [40] - [41] .

In the present case, one way in which EBD has framed its claim is that payments made by it to EBM upon false invoices were made pursuant to sham transactions, and of no legal effect and that consequently, there is no basis upon which EBM may retain the money paid by EBD. This is a claim for restitution of an amount wrongly paid which is capable of constituting a "debt". Discretion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687</tocase>
<text>The plaintiffs submit that the orders sought in this case correspond with those made in a number of cases, including QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687 and Re HIH Insurance [2004] NSWSC 5. In those cases, the order regarding the liquidator's justification for entering into the settlement was made under s 479(3) of the Act. The plaintiffs submit that s 479 and s 511 perform similar functions citing Dean-Willcocks v Soluble Solution Hydroponics Pty Ltd (1997) 42 NSWLR 209 at 212. However, as Young J pointed out this is not "completely true".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re HIH Insurance [2004] NSWSC 5</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2004/5.html</AustLII>
<text>The plaintiffs submit that the orders sought in this case correspond with those made in a number of cases, including QBE Workers Compensation (NSW) Ltd v GJ Formwork Pty Ltd (2006) 56 ACSR 687 and Re HIH Insurance [2004] NSWSC 5. In those cases, the order regarding the liquidator's justification for entering into the settlement was made under s 479(3) of the Act. The plaintiffs submit that s 479 and s 511 perform similar functions citing Dean-Willcocks v Soluble Solution Hydroponics Pty Ltd (1997) 42 NSWLR 209 at 212. However, as Young J pointed out this is not "completely true".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re One.Tel Networks Holdings Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 1065 ; (2001) 40 ACSR 83</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/1065.html</AustLII>
<text>The Settlement Deed made the direction sought in the present application a condition of the Settlement Deed taking effect is a matter which militates in favour of the Court exercising its discretion to make the orders sought: Re One.Tel Networks Holdings Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 1065 ; (2001) 40 ACSR 83 at [42] . The fact that the major creditors of EBD have had the opportunity to consider the proposed settlement, and do not oppose it, is also important. So too is the fact that EBD's liquidators have a limited opportunity to choose between the prospect of pursuing a novel application and the certainty of a settlement.

For all these reasons the compromise constituted by the Settlement Deed should be approved pursuant to s 477(2A) of the Act. There should also be a direction that the liquidators of EBD are justified in entering into the Settlement Deed. The order and direction are intended to meet the conditions precedent under clause 2 of the Settlement Deed. 
 I certify that the preceding twenty (20) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gilmour. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 27 October 2009
 
 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr J A Thomson 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the Defendant: Ms W Gillan 
 
 Solicitor for the Defendant: DLA Phillips Fox 
 Date of Hearing: 15 October 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 October 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1212.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>