<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Bedroff Pty Ltd ACN 079 158 955 (No 2) (includes Supplementary Reasons dated 26 November 2009) [2009] FCA 1399 (26 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1399.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Bedroff Pty Ltd ACN 079 158 955 [2009] FCA 1266</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/1266.html</AustLII>
<text>On 30 October 2009, for reasons which I then gave ex tempore, I adjourned the hearing of the Deputy Commissioner of Taxation's (Deputy Commissioner) application for the winding up of Bedroff Pty Ltd ACN 079 158 955 (the company) to 24 November 2009: see Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Bedroff Pty Ltd ACN 079 158 955 [2009] FCA 1266. These reasons for judgement should be read in conjunction with those earlier reasons.

On 24 November 2009, the Deputy Commissioner renewed his application for the winding up of the company. That application was opposed, nominally, by the company. The effect of the appointment of administrators on 29 October 2009 was to place the company under their control and, while it is under administration and save with the administrators' written approval, to suspend the powers of its officers to exercise their powers or functions. The company has but one officer, its director Mr Mark Tonge. To the extent that the company is itself inhibited from opposing the Deputy Commissioner's application, I am prepared to treat the application as one opposed by Mr Mark Tonge. It is he who has proposed the deed of company arrangement in question. As will be seen, he is to be the beneficiary of particular releases for which that proposed deed provides.

The submission made in opposition to the Deputy Commissioner's application was that I should be satisfied, on the material by then to hand, that it was in the interests of the company's creditors for the company to continue under administration rather than be wound up. If so satisfied I am obliged by s 440A(2) of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (Corporations Act) to adjourn further the hearing of the application for an order for the winding up of the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Public Trustee of Queensland v Octaviar Ltd (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (Receivers and Managers Appointed) (2009) 69 ACSR 621</tocase>
<text>The position which obtained on 30 October 2009 was that, though the information then to hand concerning the benefits which might flow to creditors under a Deed of Company Arrangement was then general, enough was revealed to admit of satisfaction that it was at least in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration for a short time so as to enable the terms of the deed to be precisely formulated, the position in relation to the company's affairs to be investigated at least in a preliminary way by the administrators and for a binding commitment to be made on behalf of a related creditor whom it was said would subordinate his interests to those of other unsecured creditors for the purposes of any distribution under the proposed deed of company arrangement. In effect and as matters then stood, I was persuaded that observations made by Philip McMurdo J in Public Trustee of Queensland v Octaviar Ltd (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (Receivers and Managers) (2009) 69 ACSR 621 told in favour of such satisfaction. It was not at that early stage a patent absence of a basis for satisfaction that it was in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration; cf Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v WPS Motorsport Pty Ltd (2009) 71 ACSR 640.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v WPS Motorsport Pty Ltd (2009) 71 ACSR 640</tocase>
<text>The position which obtained on 30 October 2009 was that, though the information then to hand concerning the benefits which might flow to creditors under a Deed of Company Arrangement was then general, enough was revealed to admit of satisfaction that it was at least in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration for a short time so as to enable the terms of the deed to be precisely formulated, the position in relation to the company's affairs to be investigated at least in a preliminary way by the administrators and for a binding commitment to be made on behalf of a related creditor whom it was said would subordinate his interests to those of other unsecured creditors for the purposes of any distribution under the proposed deed of company arrangement. In effect and as matters then stood, I was persuaded that observations made by Philip McMurdo J in Public Trustee of Queensland v Octaviar Ltd (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (Receivers and Managers) (2009) 69 ACSR 621 told in favour of such satisfaction. It was not at that early stage a patent absence of a basis for satisfaction that it was in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration; cf Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v WPS Motorsport Pty Ltd (2009) 71 ACSR 640.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Chief Commissioner of Stamp Duties (New South Wales) v Buckle [1998] HCA 4 ; (1998) 192 CLR 226</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/4.html</AustLII>
<text>The deed of removal and appointment does not make any express provision for the indemnification by FUFM from the trust fund of the Barr Trust of liabilities incurred by the company in the ordinary course of its prior administration of that. If it were thought at that time that the company's removal from the office of trustee and that absence of provision might in some way have insulated the trust fund from the claims of the company's creditors or its liquidator if it were wound up, that view was mistaken. That absence of express provision does not affect the position which prevails in equity. The company is entitled to be reimbursed from the trust fund of the Barr Trust in respect of expenses incurred by it in the administration of that trust up to and including the time of its removal as trustee. As was explained in Chief Commissioner of Stamp Duties (New South Wales) v Buckle [1998] HCA 4 ; (1998) 192 CLR 226 at 247, [50] (Buckle's case).by reference to a statement earlier made in Vacuum Oil Co Pty Ltd v Wiltshire [1945] HCA 37 ; (1945) 72 CLR 319 at 335, "the trustee's right to exoneration or recoupment 'takes priority over the rights in or in reference to the assets of beneficiaries or others who stand in that situation'." I did not understand the submission made in opposition to the Deputy Commissioner's application to gainsay that position.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Vacuum Oil Co Pty Ltd v Wiltshire [1945] HCA 37 ; (1945) 72 CLR 319</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/37.html</AustLII>
<text>The deed of removal and appointment does not make any express provision for the indemnification by FUFM from the trust fund of the Barr Trust of liabilities incurred by the company in the ordinary course of its prior administration of that. If it were thought at that time that the company's removal from the office of trustee and that absence of provision might in some way have insulated the trust fund from the claims of the company's creditors or its liquidator if it were wound up, that view was mistaken. That absence of express provision does not affect the position which prevails in equity. The company is entitled to be reimbursed from the trust fund of the Barr Trust in respect of expenses incurred by it in the administration of that trust up to and including the time of its removal as trustee. As was explained in Chief Commissioner of Stamp Duties (New South Wales) v Buckle [1998] HCA 4 ; (1998) 192 CLR 226 at 247, [50] (Buckle's case).by reference to a statement earlier made in Vacuum Oil Co Pty Ltd v Wiltshire [1945] HCA 37 ; (1945) 72 CLR 319 at 335, "the trustee's right to exoneration or recoupment 'takes priority over the rights in or in reference to the assets of beneficiaries or others who stand in that situation'." I did not understand the submission made in opposition to the Deputy Commissioner's application to gainsay that position.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>CPT Custodian Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (Victoria) [2005] HCA 53 ; (2005) 224 CLR 98</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/53.html</AustLII>
<text>It would seem that Mr Hayes is either unaware of the change in July in the occupancy of the office of trustee or unaware of its impact. It is unnecessary to decide which. Mr James Tonge's claim for "unpaid beneficiary entitlements" is a claim to be paid from the trust fund of the Barr Trust. It is the responsibility of the trustee for the time being of the Barr Trust to meet that claim insofar as the trust fund is in surplus and subject to any priority claim on that fund. The trustee of the Barr Trust is no longer the company but rather FUFM. Further, even assuming that there remains any surplus after the claims of secured creditors are met, unless and until the company's entitlement to reimbursement, referred to above, is satisfied, it is impossible even to state what the trust fund of the Barr Trust comprises: see also in addition to Buckle's case, CPT Custodian Pty Ltd v Commissioner of State Revenue (Victoria) [2005] HCA 53 ; (2005) 224 CLR 98 at 121, [51] . Again, the absence of any discrimination in the administrators' draft report as between the claims of those such as the Deputy Commissioner who were and remain creditors of the company and those such as Mr James Tonge who, as beneficiaries, have a claim against the trust fund (such as it may be) of the Barr Trust is a significant omission.

That employee entitlements are being foregone in the proposed deed of company arrangement is an offer the value of which is moot. As explicitly identified, they amount to no more than $7,000. Further, even this amount and the further statement in para 12.12 of the draft report that the administrators had "received a claim from Mr Mark Tonge in the amount of $300,000 for unpaid wages" is at odds with the statement in para 12.11 of the draft report where the administrators note that, "the company did not have any employees and therefore no employee entitlements are outstanding". Further, under the terms of s 556(1A) of the Corporations Act , the amount of outstanding entitlements to Mr Mark Tonge in respect of the period when he was a director of the company which would enjoy any priority in the event of a winding up is subject to a cap of $2,000.

It was for those who would wish to engender the satisfaction that it was in the interests of creditors for the administration to continue so as thereby to occasion an adjournment to resolve or explain such seeming inconsistencies. It has been known since 30 October 2009 that it would be necessary to engender such satisfaction on 24 November 2009.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Storm Financial Limited (Receivers and Managers Appointed) (Administrators Appointed) (2009) 71 ACSR 81 </tocase>
<text>In Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Storm Financial Limited (Receivers and Managers Appointed) (Administrators Appointed) (2009) 71 ACSR 81 at [20]-[27], I canvassed authorities touching upon the question of the judicial satisfaction to which s 440A(2) of the Corporations Act refers. I shall not repeat afresh what is there stated. The subsection requires that there be some persuasive case that it is in the interests of creditors for a company to continue under administration. On analysis, for reasons given above, the material now to hand reveals no such case. Rather, it reveals a situation where creditors may come to vote at the meeting on the false premise that there is a substantial benefit being conferred in relation to the deed by Mr James Tonge's offer of subordination and more generally on the basis of an absence of consideration of the ramifications of the company's having acted as the trustee of the Barr Trust.

I note that the administrators observe in the draft report that: "it is inappropriate for the administration to end and the control of the company returned to its director. The company has ceased trading and has significantly more liabilities than assets". So far as the objects of Pt 5.3A of the Corporations Act are relevant, that observation eliminates as a factor telling in favour of its being in the interests of creditors for the administration to continue that this course will "maximise the chances of the company, or as much as possible of its business, continuing in existence" (s 435A(a)).

These matters are in themselves enough to dissuade me from satisfaction that it is in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration. There is another consideration that underscores that view.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>City of Swan v Lehman Brothers Australia Limited (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (2009) 260 ALR 199</tocase>
<text>The Deputy Commissioner also pointed to the absence of any particular evidence as to the nature and extent of voidable payments which a liquidator might recover for the benefit of creditors. He also drew attention to the releases found in cl 11.5 of the proposed deed of company arrangement and submitted that, having regard to City of Swan v Lehman Brothers Australia Limited (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (2009) 260 ALR 199 (City of Swan v Lehman Brothers Australia Limited), such a term "may be contrary to the rights of creditors and render the term void".

As against this, attention was directed to the recommendation, albeit voiced only in a draft report, of the administrators that it is in the interests of the company's creditors to accept the proposal for a deed of company arrangement. Yet the presence, in the draft report, of what I have described as significant omissions in terms of an analysis of the ramifications of the company's having acted as the trustee of the Barr Trust detracts from giving weight to that recommendation. Indeed, without such an analysis, the draft report is apt to mislead as to the benefits of the proposed deed. The want of any appearance by or on behalf of the administrators meant that I did not have the benefit of submissions from them as to such ramifications or those omissions. In fairness to the administrators, it must be said that the report is but a draft. I do not in truth have any evidence as to the recommendation that the administrators are finally disposed to make or their reasons for such a recommendation.

There is no presumption, arising from the presence of Pt 5.3A in the Corporations Act , in favour of allowing the administration to continue so as to allow a vote to be taken at the meeting proposed to be held on 2 December 2009. Rather, what is offered by that Part of the Corporations Act is an alternative to liquidation but an alternative which is regulated by the provisions of that Part. Of course the object of Pt 5.3A of the Corporations Act as expressed in s 435A must be borne in mind, but the question for immediate resolution remains that posed by another of the Part's provisions, s 440A(2).

In City of Swan v Lehman Brothers Australia , supra, it was the opinion of each of the judges comprising the Full Court that Pt 5.3A of the Corporations Act could not be employed by creditors so as to prevent the exercise by some of their number of such legal rights as they had against persons other than the company the subject of the deed of company arrangement: (see at [4], [92] and [151]). Clause 11.5 seeks to achieve this so far as Mr Mark Tonge is concerned. That clause seems to me to be an essential feature of the proposed deed. Though City of Swan v Lehman Brothers Australia Limited is presently the subject of as yet unheard applications for special leave to appeal to the High Court, I am for the moment bound to follow the views expressed in the Full Court. For this additional reason, I am not satisfied that it is in the interests of creditors for the company to continue under administration.

It does not axiomatically follow that the winding up application must proceed. However, there was nothing put forward that might enliven a residual discretion to adjourn the hearing of the winding up application. To the contrary, it is in the public interest that an insolvent corporation be wound up.

I note that Mr Gregory Michael Maloney, an official liquidator, has consented to be the liquidator of the company in the event that a winding up order is made. There was no submission made to me that I should instead appoint the present administrators. There are doubtless some advantages to be gained from the work which they have already undertaken but I do not assume that they will deprive Mr Maloney of that benefit. There may equally be some advantages in a fresh mind being brought to bear on the subject of recoveries for the benefit of creditors. I see no reason not to appoint Mr Maloney as requested by the Deputy Commissioner.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>