<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Karting Association (NSW) Incorporated [2009] FCA 1255 (6 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1255.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Jurlique International Pty Ltd (2007) ATPR 42 ,146</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) [2005] FCA 265 ; (2005) 215 ALR 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/265.html</AustLII>
<text>The parties also recognise that a principal object of a penalty under s 76 is deterrence ( NW Frozen Foods ). As elaborated, the concept of deterrence is to deter repetition by the contravener and by others who might be tempted to contravene the Act ( TPC v CSR at 52,125 per French J), or to deter others who might be tempted to think that contravention would be of benefit and detection would lead merely to a compliance program for the future ( NW Frozen Foods at 294 295 per Burchett and Kiefel JJ). The need to achieve general deterrence as well as specific deterrence means that a party's capacity to pay must be weighed against the need to impose a sum which members of the public will recognise as significant and proportionate to the seriousness of the contravention ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) [2005] FCA 265 ; (2005) 215 ALR 301 at [39] per Goldberg J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Real Estate Institute of Western Australia Inc [1999] FCA 18 ; (1999) 161 ALR 79</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/18.html</AustLII>
<text>I note also that, as French J said in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Real Estate Institute of Western Australia Inc [1999] FCA 18 ; (1999) 161 ALR 79 at [18] , it is not sufficient, in making a consent order, that it is within the power of the Court to make the order nor that the parties have privately agreed as to the proposed order. The Court is not merely giving effect to the wishes of the parties. It is exercising a public function and must have regard to the public interest in doing so.

As to the specific matters relevant in the present case, the parties have made submissions on: the nature and extent of the contravening conduct; the amount of loss or damage caused; the circumstances in which the conduct took place; similar conduct in the past whether the contravener has previously been found by the Court to have engaged in similar conduct; the size of the contravening company; the degree of power the contravening company has, as evidenced by its market share and ease of entry into the market; the deliberateness of the contravention and the period over which it extended; whether the contravention arose out of conduct of senior management or at a lower level; whether the company has a corporate culture conducive to compliance with the Code, as evidenced by compliance programs and corrective measures in response to an acknowledged contravention; whether the company has shown a disposition to co-operate with the authorities responsible for the enforcement of the Code in relation to the contravention; the financial position of the respondents; the deterrent effect of the proposed penalty; and totality and parity. Application of the principles
 The nature and extent of the contravening conduct

The Understanding was reached at the AGM of the AKA, a sporting association whose members are kart racing associations based in NSW and the ACT. Mr Erdmann and Mr Whiting participated in a discussion amongst the representatives of the AKA clubs in attendance at the AGM, that discussion leading to the motion being proposed. The members voted and passed the Resolution which gave rise to the understanding.

The understanding was given effect to on three occasions when Prokart received quotes from the AKA regarding the hire of kart circuits on which to hold its race series.

The conduct ceased once the AKA became aware of the ACCC investigation and the possible contravention of the Code, which was less than three months after the Resolution was passed. The Resolution was subsequently revoked. The amount of loss or damage caused</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v White Top Taxis Ltd [2009] FCA 88 ; (2009) 253 ALR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/88.html</AustLII>
<text>Although the present proceedings concern contraventions of the Code only, the Court has jurisdiction under s 39B(1A)(a) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) which confers original jurisdiction on the Federal Court in proceedings where the Commonwealth seeks an injunction or declaration (similarly to Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v White Top Taxis Ltd [2009] FCA 88 ; (2009) 253 ALR 449). The principles for assessing penalty under the Code are the same as under the TPA ( White Top Taxis at [20] per Finkelstein J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) 19 FCR 10 </tocase>
<text>The AKA, Wagga Kart Club, Newcastle Kart Club and Manning Valley Kart Club admit that they made an arrangement or arrived at an understanding in contravention of s 45(2)(a)(i) and (ii) of the Code ( Hughes v Western Australian Cricket Association (Inc) (1986) 19 FCR 10). The AKA, Dubbo Kart Club, Newcastle Kart Club and Manning Valley Kart Club admit that they gave effect to an arrangement or understanding which contained a provision which: 
(a) was an exclusionary provision; and
 
(b) had the purpose and was likely to have the effect of substantially lessening competition;
in contravention of s 45(2)(b)(i) and 45 (2)(b)(ii) of the Code, by the conduct outlined above.

Each of Mr Erdmann and Mr Whiting admits that they were knowingly concerned in, or a party to, the making of or the arriving at the Understanding which was in contravention of s 45(2)(a)(i) and 45 (2)(a)(ii) of the Code.

I am satisfied that in each case those contraventions have been made out. PENALTY 
 Legal principles and relevant factors</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ICI Australia Operations Pty Limited v Trade Practices Commission [1992] FCA 474 ; (1992) 38 FCR 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/474.html</AustLII>
<text>Each of the respondents has consented to the imposition of injunctions. The injunctions are available pursuant to s 80 of the Code and are in the nature of public interest injunctions ( ICI Australia Operations Pty Limited v Trade Practices Commission [1992] FCA 474 ; (1992) 38 FCR 248 at 255 to 256 per Lockhart J; Truth About Motorways Pty Limited v Macquarie Infrastructure Investment Management Limited (2000) 200 CLR 591 at 602 per Gleeson CJ and McHugh J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>J McPhee &amp; Son (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2000] FCA 365 ; (2000) 172 ALR 532</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/365.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 76 of the Code sets out certain matters as relevant matters to which the Court should have regard in determining an appropriate pecuniary penalty. The parties in the joint submissions referred to further relevant factors addressed by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,152-52,153 and expanded upon in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 and J McPhee &amp; Son (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2000] FCA 365 ; (2000) 172 ALR 532. It is uncontroversial as between the parties that the total penalty for related offences ought not to exceed what is proper for the entire contravening conduct involved ( Mornington Inn v Jordan [2008] FCAFC 70 ; (2008) 168 FCR 383 at [42] - [45] , [91] per Stone and Buchanan JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Markarian v The Queen [2005] HCA 25 ; (2005) 228 CLR 357</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/25.html</AustLII>
<text>Bearing in mind the process as set out by the High Court in Markarian v The Queen [2005] HCA 25 ; (2005) 228 CLR 357 for the assessment of criminal sanctions where penalties are not fixed by statute, the ACCC and the AKA jointly submit that a total pecuniary penalty of $10,000 imposed on the AKA is appropriate and within the range of penalties that a Court would order in these circumstances. The parties point out that in considering the proposed agreed penalty, the Court should take into account the fact that a negotiated resolution may be expected to include measures designed to promote, for the future, vigorous competition in the particular market. The imposition of penalty is a matter for the Court ( NW Frozen Foods at 290) and the assessment of the appropriate penalty involves exercising a discretion taking into account all relevant factors ( Markarian at [27]). However, the parties submit that the Court should not depart from an agreed figure merely because it might otherwise have been disposed to select some other figure except in a clear case ( NW Frozen Foods at 291, approved and explained in Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 ; (2004) ATPR 41-993).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 ; (2004) ATPR 41-993</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/72.html</AustLII>
<text>Bearing in mind the process as set out by the High Court in Markarian v The Queen [2005] HCA 25 ; (2005) 228 CLR 357 for the assessment of criminal sanctions where penalties are not fixed by statute, the ACCC and the AKA jointly submit that a total pecuniary penalty of $10,000 imposed on the AKA is appropriate and within the range of penalties that a Court would order in these circumstances. The parties point out that in considering the proposed agreed penalty, the Court should take into account the fact that a negotiated resolution may be expected to include measures designed to promote, for the future, vigorous competition in the particular market. The imposition of penalty is a matter for the Court ( NW Frozen Foods at 290) and the assessment of the appropriate penalty involves exercising a discretion taking into account all relevant factors ( Markarian at [27]). However, the parties submit that the Court should not depart from an agreed figure merely because it might otherwise have been disposed to select some other figure except in a clear case ( NW Frozen Foods at 291, approved and explained in Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 ; (2004) ATPR 41-993).

The imposition of a financial penalty is a matter for the Court, whether or not the parties propose an agreed figure ( Mobil Oil ). I am aware that the AKA can pay the proposed penalty of $10,000 without going out of business or seriously impeding its activities. I am also aware of the strictures as enunciated in the cases of not substituting an amount by way of penalties simply because another sum comes to mind. I am mindful of the fact that the AKA has agreed to pay a contribution to the ACCC's costs of the proceedings in an amount to be agreed. I am conscious of the fact that this is a voluntary organisation conducting kart racing in the interests of an interested section of the public. I have taken into account the various factors elucidated in Mobil Oil regarding the public interest in the settlement of litigation. Further, I take into account the following:

I am satisfied that the agreed amount of $10,000 is within the permissible range in the present circumstances.

I am satisfied that it is appropriate to make the orders as proposed by consent. I will make the orders in Annexure A to these reasons, which, apart from one proposed declaration as to which there was no supporting evidence in the statement of agreed facts, accord with the orders proposed by the parties.
 I certify that the preceding one hundred (100) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 6 November 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr D Godwin 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr J Stephenson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Simpson &amp; Partners Solicitors Pty Limited 
 Date of Hearing: 24 September 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 November 2009 
 Annexure A 
 
THE COURT DECLARES THAT:
 Each of the first respondent ("the AKA"), second respondent ("Wagga Kart Club"), the third respondent ("Newcastle Kart Club") and the fourth respondent ("Manning Valley Kart Club"), by making a contract or arrangement or arriving at an understanding containing provisions that: 
 (a) each of the AKA clubs with bitumen kart circuits ("Kart Circuits") would not offer to supply, and would not supply Kart Circuit hire services at a price less than $4,000 plus GST per day for country clubs and $6,000 per GST per day for metropolitan clubs ("Minimum Hire Fee"); and
 
 (b) any negotiations for the supply of Kart Circuit hire services would be conducted by the AKA;
 
 made a contract or arrangement or arrived at an understanding ("Kart Circuit Hire Understanding") that:
 
 (c) had the purpose or the effect, or were likely to have the effect, of fixing, controlling or maintaining, or providing for the fixing, controlling or maintaining of, the price for Kart Circuit hire services supplied by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits in competition with each other to customers or prospective customers in New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory within the meaning of section 45A of the Competition Code of New South Wales ("the Code"); and
 
 (d) by reason of the matters alleged in subparagraph (c) above, is deemed to have the purpose or effect, or to be likely to have the effect, of substantially lessening competition in the market in New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory for the supply of Kart Circuit hiring services within the meaning of section 4E of the Code ("Kart Circuit Market"), for the purposes of section 45(2)(a)(ii) of the Code; and
 
 thereby engaged in a contravention of section 45(2)(a)(ii) of the Code.
 Each of the AKA, Wagga Kart Club, Newcastle Kart Club and Manning Valley Kart Club, by making or arriving at the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding in circumstances where two or more parties to the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding supplied Kart Circuit hire services in competition with each other, made a contract or arrangement or arrived at an understanding which contained a provision, the purpose or a substantial purpose of which was to prevent, restrict or limit one of more of the following: 
(a) the supply by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits of Kart Circuit hire services to any kart series operator who is not an AKA member on condition that the customer pay at least the Minimum Hire Fee; and
 
(b) the acquisition by any kart series operator who is not an AKA member of Kart Circuit hire services from AKA clubs with Kart Circuits on condition that the customer shall pay at least the Minimum Hire Fee;
 
 being an exclusionary provision within the meaning of section 4D of the Code, and thereby engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(a)(i) of the Code.
 The fifth respondent ("Dubbo Kart Club"), by its conduct in corresponding with the AKA regarding the hire of the Lincoln County Raceway by Prokart for the Minimum Hire Fee or a higher fee, gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby: 
 (a) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
(b) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 The AKA, by its conduct in liaising with Prokart and Dubbo Kart Club regarding the hire of the Lincoln County Raceway for the Minimum Hire Fee or a higher fee, gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby:: 
 (a) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
(b) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 
5. Manning Valley Kart Club, by its conduct in:
 
(a) advising Prokart that any negotiations for the supply of Kart Circuit hire services would be conducted by the AKA; and
 
(b) liaising with the AKA regarding the hire of the Manning Valley Kart Circuit by Prokart for the Minimum Hire Fee;
 
 gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby:
 
 (c) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
(d) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 The AKA, by its conduct in liaising with Prokart and Manning Valley Kart Club regarding the hire of the Manning Valley Kart Circuit for the Minimum Hire Fee, gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby: 
 (a) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
 (b) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 Newcastle Kart Club, by its conduct in liaising with the AKA regarding the hire of the Newcastle Kart Circuit by Prokart for the Minimum Hire Fee, gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby: 
 (a) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
 (b) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 The AKA, by its conduct in liaising with Prokart and Newcastle Kart Club regarding the hire of the Newcastle Kart Circuit, gave effect to the provisions of the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding as characterised in declarations 1 and 2 above and thereby: 
 (a) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(ii) of the Code; and
 
(b) engaged in conduct in contravention of section 45(2)(b)(i) of the Code.
 The sixth respondent ("Mr Erdmann") by his involvement in the making of or arriving at the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding with the knowledge of the essential elements of the contraventions of section 45(2)(a)(ii) and section 45(2)(a)(i) of the Code referred to in declarations 1 and 2 above, was a person directly or indirectly knowingly concerned in, or party to, those contraventions, which constitutes conduct of the kind referred to in section 75B(1)(c) and/or section 80(1)(e) of the Code. The seventh respondent ("Mr Whiting") by his involvement in the making of or arriving at the Kart Circuit Hire Understanding with the knowledge of the essential elements of the contraventions of section 45(2)(a)(ii) and section 45(2)(a)(i) of the Code referred to in declarations 1 and 2 above, was a person directly or indirectly knowingly concerned in, or party to, those contraventions, which constitutes conduct of the kind referred to in section 75B(1)(c) and/or section 80(1)(e) of the Code. 
AND, the Court orders that:
 The AKA pay to the Commonwealth a total pecuniary penalty of $10,000 within three months of the date of this order. That the AKA be permanently restrained whether by itself, its servants or agents from: 
 (a) making, or arriving at;
 
 (b) giving effect to; or
 
 (c) attempting to make or arrive at, or give effect to;
 
 any contract, arrangement or understanding with any two or more AKA members in Australia which contains a provision that:
 
 (d) has the purpose or the effect, or is likely to have the effect, of fixing, controlling or maintaining, or providing for the fixing, controlling or maintaining of, the price for Kart Circuit hire services supplied by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits to customers or prospective customers in New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory; or
 
 (e) has the purpose of preventing or restricting one or more of the following:
 
 (i) the supply by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits of Kart Circuit hire services to any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member on condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee; or
 
 (ii) the acquisition by any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member of Kart Circuit hire services from AKA clubs with Kart Circuits by the imposition of a condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee.
 An injunction permanently restraining each of Wagga Kart Club, Newcastle Kart Club, Manning Valley Kart Club, Dubbo Kart Club whether by themselves, their servants or agents from: 
 (a) making, or arriving at;
 
 (b) giving effect to; or
 
 (c) attempting to make or arrive at, or give effect to;
 
 any contract, arrangement or understanding with any other AKA member in Australia which contains a provision that:
 
 (d) has purpose or the effect, or is likely to have the effect, of fixing, controlling or maintaining, or providing for the fixing, controlling or maintaining of, the price for Kart Circuit hire services supplied by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits to customers or prospective customers in New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory; or
 
 (e) has the purpose of preventing or restricting one or more of the following:
 
(i) the supply by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits of Kart Circuit hire services to any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member by the imposition of a condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee; or
 
(ii) the acquisition by any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member of Kart Circuit hire services from AKA clubs with Kart Circuits by the imposition of a condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee.
 An injunction permanently restraining each of Mr Erdmann and Mr Whiting whether by themselves, their servants or agents from: 
 (a) attempting to induce the making, or arriving at, or the giving effect to; or
 
 (b) being knowingly concerned in, or party to, the making or arriving at, or giving effect to;
 
 any contract, arrangement or understanding with any two or more AKA members in Australia which contains a provision that:
 
(c) has purpose or the effect, or is likely to have the effect, of fixing, controlling or maintaining, or providing for the fixing, controlling or maintaining of, the price for Kart Circuit hire services supplied by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits to customers or prospective customers in New South Wales and the Australian Capital Territory; or
 
(d) has the purpose of preventing or restricting one or more of the following:
 
(i) the supply by AKA clubs with Kart Circuits of Kart Circuit hire services to any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member by the imposition of a condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee; or
 
(ii) the acquisition by any kart race series operator who is not an AKA member of Kart Circuit hire services from AKA clubs with Kart Circuits by the imposition of a condition that the customer pay at least a minimum hire fee.
 
15. The AKA shall:
 
 (a) within three months of the date of this order, establish an education training and trade practices compliance program ("Compliance Program") for officers and employees of its business, which is designed to instil an awareness of the prohibitions contained in Part IV of the Code (including section 45 and section 45A) in relation to the contravening conduct in this proceeding or any similar or related conduct;
 
 b) within one month of the date of this order, appoint a legal adviser to advise the AKA as to the content of the Compliance Program;
 
 (c) implement and administer the Compliance Program for a period of three years from the date it is established;
 
 (d) within three months of the date of this order, prepare a written report to the applicant ("the ACCC") on the content of the Compliance Program; and
 
 (e) provide a further report to the ACCC on the implementation and administration of the Compliance Program at the conclusion of each period of 12 months during which the Compliance Program is being implemented and administered.
 The AKA shall within three months of the date of this order, cause to be sent to each member of the AKA a letter substantially in the form of Attachment 1. The AKA to pay a contribution to the ACCC's costs of the proceedings in an amount as agreed between the parties. ATTACHMENT 1
 Letter to AKA members
 [To be placed on the AKA letterhead]
 
[Date]
 
 
Dear Sir/Madam
 
 
Anti-competitive arrangement by the AKA
 
 
Following civil proceedings instituted by the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission ("ACCC"), the Federal Court of Australia has found that the Australian Karting Association (NSW) Incorporated ("the AKA") and three AKA members made an anti-competitive arrangement at the annual general meeting of the AKA which was held on 19 July 2008.
 
The Court has declared that the AKA engaged in anti-competitive conduct (contravening the Competition Code of New South Wales ("the Competition Code")) by making an arrangement:
 to fix the minimum price for the hire of kart circuits by AKA clubs (which is said to substantially lessen competition); and to prevent, restrict or limit the hire of kart circuits by AKA clubs to non-AKA members by imposing a condition that the non-AKA members pay at least the minimum price (which is an exclusionary provision); 
and later giving effect to the above arrangement.
 
The Competition Code has the same provisions as the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), but applies to individuals and non-trading associations such as AKA clubs.
 
One of the Court's orders is that the AKA must write to each member to notify them of the outcome of these proceedings and to inform them of the illegality of making and giving effect to arrangements which substantially lessen competition or contain an exclusionary provision.
 
The AKA has been ordered to pay a penalty of $10,000 and to pay a contribution to the ACCC's costs. The Court has also granted injunctions restraining the AKA from making arrangements of this kind in the future and has ordered that the AKA establish a trade practices compliance program.
 
 
If as an AKA member you:
 agree with other AKA members to a minimum or set price for the hire of kart circuits; agree with other AKA members to prevent, restrict or limit the hire of kart circuits by AKA clubs to a particular class of persons on particular conditions; or give effect to an agreement set out above, 
you may be in breach of the Competition Code and may be liable to pay fines of up to $10,000,000 for a company or $500,000 for an individual, as well as damages for any loss that is caused.
 
You can obtain further information about the ACCC's proceedings against the AKA and the Trade Practices Act 1974 / Competition Code from the ACCC website at www.accc.gov.au .
 
Yours sincerely
 
 
President
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1255.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mornington Inn v Jordan [2008] FCAFC 70 ; (2008) 168 FCR 383</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/70.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 76 of the Code sets out certain matters as relevant matters to which the Court should have regard in determining an appropriate pecuniary penalty. The parties in the joint submissions referred to further relevant factors addressed by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,152-52,153 and expanded upon in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 and J McPhee &amp; Son (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2000] FCA 365 ; (2000) 172 ALR 532. It is uncontroversial as between the parties that the total penalty for related offences ought not to exceed what is proper for the entire contravening conduct involved ( Mornington Inn v Jordan [2008] FCAFC 70 ; (2008) 168 FCR 383 at [42] - [45] , [91] per Stone and Buchanan JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1996/1134.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 76 of the Code sets out certain matters as relevant matters to which the Court should have regard in determining an appropriate pecuniary penalty. The parties in the joint submissions referred to further relevant factors addressed by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,152-52,153 and expanded upon in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 and J McPhee &amp; Son (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2000] FCA 365 ; (2000) 172 ALR 532. It is uncontroversial as between the parties that the total penalty for related offences ought not to exceed what is proper for the entire contravening conduct involved ( Mornington Inn v Jordan [2008] FCAFC 70 ; (2008) 168 FCR 383 at [42] - [45] , [91] per Stone and Buchanan JJ).

The parties also recognise that a principal object of a penalty under s 76 is deterrence ( NW Frozen Foods ). As elaborated, the concept of deterrence is to deter repetition by the contravener and by others who might be tempted to contravene the Act ( TPC v CSR at 52,125 per French J), or to deter others who might be tempted to think that contravention would be of benefit and detection would lead merely to a compliance program for the future ( NW Frozen Foods at 294 295 per Burchett and Kiefel JJ). The need to achieve general deterrence as well as specific deterrence means that a party's capacity to pay must be weighed against the need to impose a sum which members of the public will recognise as significant and proportionate to the seriousness of the contravention ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum Pty Ltd (No 3) [2005] FCA 265 ; (2005) 215 ALR 301 at [39] per Goldberg J).

Bearing in mind the process as set out by the High Court in Markarian v The Queen [2005] HCA 25 ; (2005) 228 CLR 357 for the assessment of criminal sanctions where penalties are not fixed by statute, the ACCC and the AKA jointly submit that a total pecuniary penalty of $10,000 imposed on the AKA is appropriate and within the range of penalties that a Court would order in these circumstances. The parties point out that in considering the proposed agreed penalty, the Court should take into account the fact that a negotiated resolution may be expected to include measures designed to promote, for the future, vigorous competition in the particular market. The imposition of penalty is a matter for the Court ( NW Frozen Foods at 290) and the assessment of the appropriate penalty involves exercising a discretion taking into account all relevant factors ( Markarian at [27]). However, the parties submit that the Court should not depart from an agreed figure merely because it might otherwise have been disposed to select some other figure except in a clear case ( NW Frozen Foods at 291, approved and explained in Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 ; (2004) ATPR 41-993).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rural Press Limited v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/75.html</AustLII>
<text>The declarations sought in the proposed orders are sought pursuant to s 21 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The parties submit that the proposed declarations, in a convenient and abbreviated form, sufficiently identify the contravening conduct ( Rural Press Limited v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] HCA 75 ; (2003) 216 CLR 53 at [89] [90]) and thereby provide context for the pecuniary penalties. Accordingly, the parties submit the declarations operate with the pecuniary penalties to achieve the objective of general deterrence.

I am satisfied that it is appropriate to make the declarations in the form sought. Injunctions</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076</tocase>
<text>Section 76 of the Code sets out certain matters as relevant matters to which the Court should have regard in determining an appropriate pecuniary penalty. The parties in the joint submissions referred to further relevant factors addressed by French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,152-52,153 and expanded upon in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 and J McPhee &amp; Son (Australia) Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2000] FCA 365 ; (2000) 172 ALR 532. It is uncontroversial as between the parties that the total penalty for related offences ought not to exceed what is proper for the entire contravening conduct involved ( Mornington Inn v Jordan [2008] FCAFC 70 ; (2008) 168 FCR 383 at [42] - [45] , [91] per Stone and Buchanan JJ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Truth About Motorways Pty Limited v Macquarie Infrastructure Investment Management Limited (2000) 200 CLR 591</tocase>
<text>Each of the respondents has consented to the imposition of injunctions. The injunctions are available pursuant to s 80 of the Code and are in the nature of public interest injunctions ( ICI Australia Operations Pty Limited v Trade Practices Commission [1992] FCA 474 ; (1992) 38 FCR 248 at 255 to 256 per Lockhart J; Truth About Motorways Pty Limited v Macquarie Infrastructure Investment Management Limited (2000) 200 CLR 591 at 602 per Gleeson CJ and McHugh J).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>