<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Young v ICM Agriculture Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1065 (16 September 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1065.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Dataline.net.au Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1361</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1361.html</AustLII>
<text>Her Honour also referred to the fact that the director was to be a witness for the company and that there were difficulties in his position as a witness and in presenting evidence and making submissions (her Honour referred to Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Dataline.net.au Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1361 at [3] ). That difficulty does not exist in the present case because counsel will lead the evidence to be given by Mr Young. There is, however, some residual difficulty in the preparation and filing of affidavits to which I referred earlier.

The case is also distinguishable on the same or a similar basis.

In summary, I do not find any reason in the authorities to which I was referred and have discussed above to dissuade me from the view that leave should be granted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Checked-Out Pty Ltd v Eagle Eye Inspections Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1002</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1002.html</AustLII>
<text>Order 4 r 14(2) of the Federal Court Rules provides: 
 
 Except as provided by or under any Act, a corporation may not, without the leave of the Court, commence or carry on any proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor. 
 

 
Counsel for the parties referred me to the following authorities in relation to the approach to be taken on an application for leave under the rule: Tobacco Control Coalition Inc v Philip Morris (Australia) Ltd [2000] FCA 131 ( Tobacco Control ); Checked-Out Pty Ltd v Eagle Eye Inspections Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1002 ( Checked-Out ); Silkearl Pty Ltd v Ainsworth Game Technology Ltd [2006] FCA 949 ( Silkearl ) and Cytel Pty Ltd v Peoplebank Recruitment Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 985 ( Cytel ). I will return to these authorities below.

In Checked-Out , Emmett J granted leave to the applicant to carry on the proceeding without a solicitor for the purpose of resisting certain motions for summary dismissal, and to be represented on the hearing of those motions by a named individual who was not a solicitor. However, his Honour declined to grant general leave for the company to carry on the proceeding without a solicitor, noting the complexity of the legal and factual issues involved as one reason militating against the grant of leave.

The case is distinguishable on the same or a similar basis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Cytel Pty Ltd v Peoplebank Recruitment Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 985</tocase>
<text>Order 4 r 14(2) of the Federal Court Rules provides: 
 
 Except as provided by or under any Act, a corporation may not, without the leave of the Court, commence or carry on any proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor. 
 

 
Counsel for the parties referred me to the following authorities in relation to the approach to be taken on an application for leave under the rule: Tobacco Control Coalition Inc v Philip Morris (Australia) Ltd [2000] FCA 131 ( Tobacco Control ); Checked-Out Pty Ltd v Eagle Eye Inspections Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1002 ( Checked-Out ); Silkearl Pty Ltd v Ainsworth Game Technology Ltd [2006] FCA 949 ( Silkearl ) and Cytel Pty Ltd v Peoplebank Recruitment Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 985 ( Cytel ). I will return to these authorities below.

Finally, in Cytel Bennett J refused an application for leave under O 4 r 14(2). The applicant company sought leave to be represented by its sole director. Her Honour said that it was clear from the matters put by the director in submissions and the material that he had sent to her Honour's chambers, that he had no understanding of court procedure or of evidence. Her Honour was firmly of the view that if the director were to represent the applicant, the time taken to deal with evidence and submissions would be greatly extended.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Silkearl Pty Ltd v Ainsworth Game Technology Ltd [2006] FCA 949</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/949.html</AustLII>
<text>Order 4 r 14(2) of the Federal Court Rules provides: 
 
 Except as provided by or under any Act, a corporation may not, without the leave of the Court, commence or carry on any proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor. 
 

 
Counsel for the parties referred me to the following authorities in relation to the approach to be taken on an application for leave under the rule: Tobacco Control Coalition Inc v Philip Morris (Australia) Ltd [2000] FCA 131 ( Tobacco Control ); Checked-Out Pty Ltd v Eagle Eye Inspections Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1002 ( Checked-Out ); Silkearl Pty Ltd v Ainsworth Game Technology Ltd [2006] FCA 949 ( Silkearl ) and Cytel Pty Ltd v Peoplebank Recruitment Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 985 ( Cytel ). I will return to these authorities below.

In Silkearl , Allsop J (when a judge of this Court) refused an application for leave under O 4 r 14(2). The individual who wished to represent the applicant company was, with his wife, a director of the company. The case involved complex factual and legal issues. His Honour referred to the emotive language used by the individual concerned and the making of sweeping allegations of impropriety by him in correspondence with the respondent and its solicitors. I note in passing that this characteristic, which one often encounters in self-represented litigants, has been noticeably absent, so far as I am aware, in the dealings that Mr Young has had with ICM and its solicitors. In his case, the problem has not been one of lack of courtesy, but has been one of lack of knowledge of rules and procedures.

The case is distinguishable on the same or a similar basis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Tobacco Control Coalition Inc v Philip Morris (Australia) Ltd [2000] FCA 131</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/131.html</AustLII>
<text>Order 4 r 14(2) of the Federal Court Rules provides: 
 
 Except as provided by or under any Act, a corporation may not, without the leave of the Court, commence or carry on any proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor. 
 

 
Counsel for the parties referred me to the following authorities in relation to the approach to be taken on an application for leave under the rule: Tobacco Control Coalition Inc v Philip Morris (Australia) Ltd [2000] FCA 131 ( Tobacco Control ); Checked-Out Pty Ltd v Eagle Eye Inspections Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1002 ( Checked-Out ); Silkearl Pty Ltd v Ainsworth Game Technology Ltd [2006] FCA 949 ( Silkearl ) and Cytel Pty Ltd v Peoplebank Recruitment Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 985 ( Cytel ). I will return to these authorities below.

In Tobacco Control , Wilcox J granted Tobacco Control Coalition Inc leave under O 4 r 14(2) to carry on the proceeding without a solicitor but limited to preparation for, and attendance at, the hearing of certain motions which were fixed for hearing 12 days after the making of the order. The order was limited in point of time to the conclusion of the hearing of those motions.

His Honour observed (at [7]) that if the matter went to a hearing on the merits it would involve extensive evidence and complex questions of law, and that it would be "most inappropriate for such an action to be litigated without the services of a solicitor".

The present case will involve complex questions of law. Most of the evidence will be documentary, although apparently there will be some evidence as to one or two contested conversations.

Tobacco Control is, nonetheless, distinguishable by reason of the factors listed in [27] above. In particular, there was in that case only one applicant the company. In the present case the proceeding will continue in so far as it is brought by Mr Young.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>