<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Baljas v Repatriation Commission [2009] FCA 171 (2 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/171.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Hendy [2002] FCAFC 424</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/424.html</AustLII>
<text>The learned member who constituted the Tribunal identified as the only issue before him the question whether the applicant satisfied the requirements of s 24 of the VE Act. After reviewing the vague and contradictory evidence of the applicant's work history, reciting the history of his claims and applications, and summarising the legislative scheme, the Tribunal expressed a finding about the remunerative work that the applicant was undertaking after his military service. In doing so, the Tribunal reminded itself of the proposition found in Repatriation Commission v Hendy [2002] FCAFC 424 (2002) 76 ALD 47 at [36] , where the Court said: 
 The tribunal's task was to assess what the veteran probably would have done, if he had none of his service disabilities during the assessment period. The requirement to consider "remunerative work that the veteran was undertaking" does not mean a particular job with a particular employer but the substantive remunerative work that the veteran had undertaken in the past.

The Tribunal found that, after leaving the army, the applicant worked for some 24 years doing plumbing and welding work associated with the installation of commercial air-conditioners. He was then employed by Haden Engineering installing air-conditioning units and ducting in commercial and industrial premises. The applicant has a plumbing certificate from RMIT. The Tribunal found that the relevant remunerative work which the applicant was undertaking was that of an air-conditioning plumber or installer. That task involved significant manual work, including the lifting of heavy items and work in confined spaces and awkward positions.

The Tribunal then addressed the cause of the applicant's incapacity for work, particularly the application of the "alone" test, found in s 24(1)(b) and (c) of the VE Act. At [28] of its reasons for decision, the Tribunal said: 
 It should therefore be apparent that if any factors other than Mr Baljas' accepted medical conditions prevent him from continuing to undertake the remunerative work that he was undertaking, he will not be eligible for a pension at the special rate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327</tocase>
<text>Counsel for the applicant contended that the Tribunal took the wrong approach to determining what was the remunerative work that the applicant was prevented from continuing to undertake. It was said that the correct approach was to determine, as a matter of hypothetical fact, an assessment of what the applicant "probably would have done if he had none of his service disabilities": Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327 at 337 per Beaumont J, with whom Northrop and Spender JJ concurred. Further, the phrase "remunerative work which the respondent was undertaking" in s 24(1)(c) must be "read as a reference to the type of work which the member previously undertook and not to any particular job": Banovich v Repatriation Commission (1986) 69 ALR 395 at 402. The argument was that the Tribunal had restricted itself to a consideration of the actual job that the applicant had been employed to perform by Haden Engineering, and had not considered either the nature of his work in general, or other work that he might have performed but for his war-caused incapacity.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Banovich v Repatriation Commission (1986) 69 ALR 395</tocase>
<text>Counsel for the applicant contended that the Tribunal took the wrong approach to determining what was the remunerative work that the applicant was prevented from continuing to undertake. It was said that the correct approach was to determine, as a matter of hypothetical fact, an assessment of what the applicant "probably would have done if he had none of his service disabilities": Repatriation Commission v Smith (1987) 15 FCR 327 at 337 per Beaumont J, with whom Northrop and Spender JJ concurred. Further, the phrase "remunerative work which the respondent was undertaking" in s 24(1)(c) must be "read as a reference to the type of work which the member previously undertook and not to any particular job": Banovich v Repatriation Commission (1986) 69 ALR 395 at 402. The argument was that the Tribunal had restricted itself to a consideration of the actual job that the applicant had been employed to perform by Haden Engineering, and had not considered either the nature of his work in general, or other work that he might have performed but for his war-caused incapacity.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Sheehy v Repatriation Commission (1996) 66 FCR 569</tocase>
<text>Counsel for the applicant argued that the Tribunal was bound to apply s 24(2)(b) of the VE Act as a provision ameliorating the effect of s 24(1)(c). Relying on Sheehy v Repatriation Commission (1996) 66 FCR 569 at 573-574, counsel contended that the applicant's remunerative activity had ceased on his suffering of the injury to his shoulders. After that, he became a person "who has not been engaged in remunerative work". The Tribunal should have seen his return to work on light duties as not engaging in remunerative work, because the attempt was unsuccessful, but should have seen that attempt as evidence that the applicant "has been genuinely seeking to engage in remunerative work".

The attempt to rely on Sheehy , and to argue that the period of light duties undertaken by the applicant after he had suffered the injury to his shoulders was not itself engaging in remunerative work, appears to be a device adopted by counsel for the applicant to overcome the fact that there was no evidence at all that the applicant had been genuinely seeking to engage in remunerative work, or would have been so seeking but for his war-caused incapacity. In Sheehy , the Full Court held that a veteran could not be said to "undertake" remunerative work, or to have been "undertaking" such work unless he or she had managed to perform such work, to undertake it successfully or effectively. In that case, it had become apparent within a week of the return to work that the veteran concerned was unable to cope with his duties. In the present case, the return to work persisted for three months, according to the applicant's evidence. His evidence was that he started off doing all light duties and "then all of a sudden we're back to normal." He indicated that he was carrying heavy items and doing work of a kind he had done usually. At least for that period, it was clear that the applicant's own evidence was that he was undertaking that work. There was no occasion for the Tribunal to make a finding that the three-month period of return to work should have been disregarded in the determination of what remunerative work the applicant had been undertaking.

The result of this analysis is that there was no evidence that the applicant had been seeking to engage in remunerative work, or would have been so seeking but for his war-caused incapacity. He declined an approach by his former employer to be retrained for an office job. There were suggestions in cross-examination that he was reluctant to engage in employment, because there were no jobs within a reasonable distance of his home, and because he had responsibility for caring for young children at his home. On the evidence, no occasion arose for the Tribunal to consider the application of s 24(2)(b). Any finding that the applicant had been seeking to engage in remunerative work, or would have done so but for his war-caused incapacity, would have been perverse. Leniency to the applicant

Counsel for the applicant also put the well-worn argument that the Tribunal had failed to take account of the beneficial nature of s 24 of the VE Act, and had disregarded the requirements of s 119 of the VE Act. This was said to have been demonstrated by the Tribunal in a number of ways. One was simply noting conflicting evidence, without attempting to resolve the conflicts and particularly without asking the applicant or his counsel to clarify the situation. Another was the Tribunal finding that the applicant had stopped work due to bilateral arm pain, and allegedly ignoring his evidence that he was not able to cope with work because of the medication he was taking for other conditions. Yet another was the Tribunal improperly restricting the nature of remunerative work that it considered, but considering only the particular job that the applicant had been performing prior to his injury. Another was failing to identify the type of work that the applicant was capable of doing and trained to perform, which allegedly led the Tribunal to fail properly to identify the effect of the accepted war-caused disabilities on the applicant's ability to continue with or resume remunerative employment. Finally, it was suggested that the Tribunal failed to determine whether the accepted disabilities were the substantial cause of the applicant's inability to obtain work.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Giesen v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 846 (2005) 87 ALD 347</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/846.html</AustLII>
<text>In Giesen v Repatriation Commission [2005] FCA 846 (2005) 87 ALD 347 at [19] - [26] , I set out the reasoning that led me to the view that s 24(2)(b) is not construed properly as an ameliorating provision in a case such as the present. Section 24(1)(c) of the VE Act deals with a person who has been "prevented from continuing to undertake remunerative work that the veteran was undertaking", ie with someone who has worked. The purpose of s 24(2)(b) is to enable a person who cannot fit into this category, because of never having worked since his or her relevant war service, to claim pension at the special rate if he or she can satisfy the requirements of s 24(2)(b). For the reasons I gave in Giesen , I remain of the view that s 24(2)(b) has no application to the present case. In Giesen at [27], however, I indicated that I was prepared to consider the application of s 24(2)(b), on the basis that both parties took the view that it was applicable. In the present case, both parties also expressed the view that s 24(2)(b) is an ameliorating provision, applicable even where a veteran has ceased to engage in remunerative work.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>