<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Comcare v John Holland Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 1515 (17 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1515.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Australian Ophthalmic Supplies Pty Ltd v McAlary -Smith [2008] FCAFC 8 ; [2008] 165 FCR 560</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/8.html</AustLII>
<text>The overriding principle in assessing penalty is that the amount of the penalty should reflect the Court's view of the seriousness of the offending conduct in all the relevant circumstances: Madgwick J in Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207 at [120] . While penalties imposed pursuant to s 16(1) in other cases may provide some guidance, the Court in each case is required to focus on the circumstances before it and not be improperly distracted by the circumstances in other cases which are inevitably different from the circumstances before the Court. As Gray J said in Australian Ophthalmic Supplies Pty Ltd v McAlary -Smith [2008] FCAFC 8 ; [2008] 165 FCR 560 at [12] - [13] : 
 
 [12] Much of the argument put by counsel for the appellant involved a detailed comparison between the facts of this case and the facts of two other cases in which lower penalties had been imposed in respect of award breaches. The two cases, both judgments of the same Federal Magistrate, are Mason v Harrington Corporation Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 7 and Flattery v The Italian Eatery T/as Zeffirelli's Pizza Restaurant [2007] FMCA 9. This was a fundamentally wrong approach. Penalties are not a matter of precedent . The choice of penalty must be dictated by the individual circumstances of a case, not by a line by line comparison with another case. See the passage from the judgment of Burchett and Kiefel JJ in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 295, set out in the reasons for judgment of Buchanan J at [87]. 
 

 
 
 [13] Penalty decisions in other cases can be of value in demonstrating that there is a range of penalties generally considered appropriate to a particular type of case. The individual circumstances of the case at hand must then be examined, in order to determine at what point in the appropriate range the penalty should be set. This does not involve a comparison with the facts of other cases. 
 

 
 
 (emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/662.html</AustLII>
<text>The overriding principle in assessing penalty is that the amount of the penalty should reflect the Court's view of the seriousness of the offending conduct in all the relevant circumstances: Madgwick J in Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207 at [120] . While penalties imposed pursuant to s 16(1) in other cases may provide some guidance, the Court in each case is required to focus on the circumstances before it and not be improperly distracted by the circumstances in other cases which are inevitably different from the circumstances before the Court. As Gray J said in Australian Ophthalmic Supplies Pty Ltd v McAlary -Smith [2008] FCAFC 8 ; [2008] 165 FCR 560 at [12] - [13] : 
 
 [12] Much of the argument put by counsel for the appellant involved a detailed comparison between the facts of this case and the facts of two other cases in which lower penalties had been imposed in respect of award breaches. The two cases, both judgments of the same Federal Magistrate, are Mason v Harrington Corporation Pty Ltd [2007] FMCA 7 and Flattery v The Italian Eatery T/as Zeffirelli's Pizza Restaurant [2007] FMCA 9. This was a fundamentally wrong approach. Penalties are not a matter of precedent . The choice of penalty must be dictated by the individual circumstances of a case, not by a line by line comparison with another case. See the passage from the judgment of Burchett and Kiefel JJ in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 295, set out in the reasons for judgment of Buchanan J at [87]. 
 

 
 
 [13] Penalty decisions in other cases can be of value in demonstrating that there is a range of penalties generally considered appropriate to a particular type of case. The individual circumstances of the case at hand must then be examined, in order to determine at what point in the appropriate range the penalty should be set. This does not involve a comparison with the facts of other cases. 
 

 
 
 (emphasis added)

Some assistance in considering the appropriate level of penalty in circumstances involving breach of occupational health and safety standards can be found in comments of Madgwick J in Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207. In that decision his Honour took the view that the following considerations provided useful, analogical, general guidance in considering penalties under the Act: 
 
 (i) the penalty must be such as to compel attention to occupational health and safety generally, to ensure that workers whilst at work will not be exposed to risks to their health and safety;
 (ii) it is a significant aggravating factor that the risk of injury was foreseeable even if the precise cause or circumstances of exposure to the risk were not foreseeable;
 (iii) the offence may be further aggravated if the risk of injury is not only foreseeable but actually foreseen and an adequate response to that risk is not taken by the employer;
 (iv) the gravity of the consequences of an accident does not of itself dictate the seriousness of the offence or the amount of penalty. However the occurrence of death or serious injury may manifest the degree of the seriousness of the relevant detriment to safety;
 (v) a systemic failure by an employer to appropriately address a known or foreseeable risk is likely to be viewed more seriously than a risk to which an employee was exposed because of a combination of inadvertence on the part of an employee and a momentary lapse of supervision;
 (vi) general deterrence and specific deterrence are particularly relevant factors in light of the objects and terms of the Act;
 (vii) employers are required to take all practicable precautions to ensure safety in the workplace. This implies constant vigilance. Employers must adopt an approach to safety which is proactive and not merely reactive. In view of the scope of those obligations, in most cases it will be necessary to have regard to the need to encourage a sufficient level of diligence by the employer in the future. This is particularly so where the employer conducts a large enterprise which involves inherent risks to safety;
 (viii) regard should be had to the levels of maximum penalty set by the legislature as indicative of the seriousness of the breach under consideration; 
 (ix) the neglect of simple, well-known precautions to deal with an evident and great risk of injury, take a matter towards the worst case category;
 (x) the objective seriousness of the offence, without more may call for the imposition of a very substantial penalty to vindicate the social and industrial policies of the legislation and its regime of penalties. (at [120]) 
 

 Submissions of the parties as to quantum of pecuniary penalty

Comcare submits that an appropriate range for a penalty in this matter is $180,000-$210,000. It is for Comcare to demonstrate to the Court why the penalty sought is justified.

The respondent has not proposed a dollar value or range of penalty to the Court. However the respondent submitted that, after taking into account the objective considerations which reflect upon the nature and qualify of the offence, and subjective factors favourable to the respondent, a discount of up to 25% be allowed on account of the early admission by the respondent. Pecuniary penalty seriousness of the offending conduct in all the relevant circumstances

The respondent has made extensive submissions in relation to mitigation. As the respondent submits, and I also note, Madgwick J in Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207 listed no considerations favourable to a respondent in respect of assessment of penalty. However in determining a pecuniary penalty for breach of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,153 considered issues subjectively relevant to the conduct of the respondent, including:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>related</class>
<tocase>Comcare v John Holland Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1196</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/1196.html</AustLII>
<text>For the reasons provided in a previous judgment in respect of this matter Comcare v John Holland Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1196 I allowed members of Mr McCallum's family to file impact evidence statements with the Court, which I have read. While, as I indicated in my interlocutory judgment, their statements were accepted on the basis that they would not be taken into account for the purposes of determining the appropriate penalty in this case, the Court extends its sympathy to the family of Mr McCallum, and acknowledges the extreme pain and anguish caused them by the loss of Mr McCallum.
 I certify that the preceding fifty-three (53) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Collier. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 16 December 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr A Herbert 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: DibbsBarker Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr J Fernon SC with Ms W Thompson 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Business Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 27 October 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 17 December 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1515.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Comcare v John Holland Rail Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 771</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/771.html</AustLII>
<text>In the absence of mitigating circumstances, I consider that the appropriate penalty in this case would be $200,000. This is reflective of the fact that the objective seriousness of the respondent's conduct is at the higher end of the scale but does not exhibit characteristics of the worst kind of conduct. However I agree with, and adopt, observations of Barker J in Comcare v John Holland Rail Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 771 at [143] where his Honour observed: 
 
 Where, for example, a respondent in a proceeding such as these early on acknowledges fault and willingness to accept a declaration of contravention, then the respondent will ordinarily be entitled to additional consideration in the assessment of the penalty. In some contexts this process is termed giving credit or "discount" on penalty. There is no statutory entitlements to such credit or a discount but it serves public policy in that it encourages a respondent to act responsibly, and may achieve a reduction in the public resources that would otherwise be required to prosecute the proceedings against the respondent. (at [143])

I consider that the penalty should be reduced by 10% in light of the early plea by the respondent, its contrition as demonstrated by its early admission of liability and the assistance provided to both the family of Mr McCallum, other employees, and Comcare in its investigations, and the extensive changes to the work system introduced since the incident which indicate a genuine attempt by the respondent to prevent the recurrence of a similar tragedy. Accordingly, in my view the appropriate penalty is $180,000. Family Impact Evidence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076</tocase>
<text>The respondent has made extensive submissions in relation to mitigation. As the respondent submits, and I also note, Madgwick J in Comcare v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 662 ; [2007] 163 FCR 207 listed no considerations favourable to a respondent in respect of assessment of penalty. However in determining a pecuniary penalty for breach of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), French J in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Ltd (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,153 considered issues subjectively relevant to the conduct of the respondent, including:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>WorkCover Authority of New South Wales (Inspector Mayo-Ramsay) v Maitland City Council (1998) 83 IR 362</tocase>
<text>In this case the respondent admits that the result of its conduct was the death of Mr McCallum. While there is no question here that Mr McCallum's death was actually foreseen by the respondent, in my view implementing a work method incorporating an appropriate radio protocol would not have been unreasonable, and to so find now is not, in my view, "substituting reasonable hindsight for reasonable foresight" ( WorkCover Authority of New South Wales (Inspector Mayo-Ramsay) v Maitland City Council (1998) 83 IR 362 at 381). The size of the plant involved, the vulnerability of workers in front of it, and the very real risk of serious injury or death in the absence of a fail-safe means of immediate emergency communication does suggest a systemic failure by the respondent rather than "a risk to which an employee was exposed because of a combination of inadvertence on the part of an employee and a momentary lapse of supervision" as contended by the respondent. Indeed, it is not conclusive that there was either inadvertence on the part of Mr McCallum or a momentary lapse in his supervision by Mr Grech and the incident still occurred.

It is clear that, despite the efforts taken by the respondent to implement a safe working environment, the operation involving the transportation unit was flawed in its original conception. The dangers were obvious from the start, relatively simple to avoid, but unrecognised and unaddressed in a manner which raises the objective gravity of the offence in these proceedings towards the higher end of the scale.

The respondent submits that the improvements made to its work systems and the immediate action it took following the incident indicate that specific deterrence is not a factor of significance in this matter. I disagree. While the initiatives of the respondent are to be applauded, a relevant consideration in respect of the quantum of a penalty is that it be a deterrence to the specific employer in question as well as the community at large (including other employers). The respondent in this case has admitted that the result of its conduct was the death of an employee. It is necessary that the penalty reflect that fact. Further, while the work systems in place at the time of the incident support a finding that the respondent had adopted an approach to safety which was proactive rather than reactive, it is clear from both the obviousness of the risk to which Mr McCallum was fatally exposed and the simple but effective measures put in place since the incident including the adoption of a radio protocol that there were serious deficiencies in the quality of the proactive work undertaken.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>