<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited (No. 2) [2009] FCA 1391 (26 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1391.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd (No. 3) [2007] FCA 393</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/393.html</AustLII>
<text>In Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd (No. 3) [2007] FCA 393 , Jacobson J found that he was not satisfied that the contribution of a group which he described as a ' lobby group ', namely the Australian Financial Markets Association ('AFMA'), would contribute to the proceedings in a way which was ' useful or different from the contributions of the parties ' (see [12]). His Honour observed that the parties were well represented by substantial teams of legal counsel. He also observed at [13] that the applicant in those proceedings, ASIC, would not ' be influenced by tactical or forensic considerations which would be necessary to be off-set by submissions made by AFMA '.

The submissions sought to be relied upon by the IIA regurgitate in substance the submissions provided by iiNet which deal, in significant detail, with the subject matters concerning the safe harbour provisions; s 112E of the Copyright Act ; and the concept of copyright authorisation considered in the context of the AFACT notices. The submissions of iiNet have also dealt with the practical and cost consequences of an ISP being required to comply with the demands of the AFACT notices. Further, the provisions of the Telecommunications Act 1997 (Cth) and their interaction with the Copyright Act have also been the subject of extensive submissions from iiNet. Indeed, the industry, detail and comprehensiveness of iiNet's closing submissions, stretching for more than 260 pages, eclipse the brief submissions of the IIA even on the specific matters with which the IIA wishes to address the Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Breen v Williams (1994) 35 NSWLR 522</tocase>
<text>The IIA has referred the Court to several authorities in support of its submissions. IceTV Pty Limited &amp; Anor v Nine Network Australia Pty Limited [2008] HCATrans 356 was one, wherein the High Court of Australia granted leave to interveners on the ground that the Court ' may be assisted ' by them (per French CJ). Reliance is also placed upon the decision of Kirby P in Breen v Williams (1994) 35 NSWLR 522 at 533 in which the President said: 
 
 The courts should not turn a blind eye or a deaf ear to the assistance that they might receive from amicus curiae on matters of principle in test cases.

Had there been a subject matter contained in the submissions of the IIA which had not been the subject of submissions from iiNet, the Court would have adopted the approach taken by Kirby P in Breen . However, the Court is satisfied that the matters sought to be advanced before this Court by the IIA do not add any material to that which has already been provided to the Court. That is, there is no subject matter of the proposed submissions which has been omitted by iiNet, nor which could be usefully supplemented by the matters contained in those proposed submissions.

The Court has been fully assisted by both iiNet and by the applicants in respect of the issues which are the subject of the IIA's proposed submissions. The mere fact that the IIA is not iiNet and thus claims to bring a 'broader perspective' does not render its submissions ' different and useful '. Much of the IIA's submissions in favour of its intervention appear to relate to its involvement in the process of the creation of legislation that is at issue before this Court. However, that involvement is only relevant to the extent that it means that the IIA can provide actual insight as to the interpretation of legislation which iiNet cannot. It does not grant the IIA some kind of preferred status as interpreter of the legislature's will. As the applicants have rightly submitted, it does not matter who says something, it matters what is said and, as has already been stated, the IIA has not proffered anything materially different to iiNet.

If the IIA intended by its application for intervention to bring to the Court's attention the importance of its decision in these proceedings, it can take such fact as noted. The Court is, and always has been, well aware of the ramifications of the outcome of its decision for ISPs, rights holders, and the development of the internet more broadly.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>IceTV Pty Limited &amp; Anor v Nine Network Australia Pty Limited [2008] HCA Trans 356</tocase>
<text>The IIA has referred the Court to several authorities in support of its submissions. IceTV Pty Limited &amp; Anor v Nine Network Australia Pty Limited [2008] HCATrans 356 was one, wherein the High Court of Australia granted leave to interveners on the ground that the Court ' may be assisted ' by them (per French CJ). Reliance is also placed upon the decision of Kirby P in Breen v Williams (1994) 35 NSWLR 522 at 533 in which the President said: 
 
 The courts should not turn a blind eye or a deaf ear to the assistance that they might receive from amicus curiae on matters of principle in test cases.

The Court acknowledges that the fact that the IIA could not be considered impartial is irrelevant. Equally, it is irrelevant that the IIA happens to have a perspective which is aligned with one of the parties and not the other. As much is clear from the High Court allowing Telstra and the Australian Digital Alliance to act as amicus in IceTV . Therefore, the only relevant consideration is whether the IIA's submissions are ' useful and different ' from that which the Court already has before it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sharman Networks Limited and Others v Universal Music Australia Pty Limited and Others [2006] FCAFC 178 ; (2006) 155 FCR 291</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/178.html</AustLII>
<text>The IIA has also submitted that it was acknowledged in the Revised Explanatory Memorandum to the Copyright Amendment (Digital Agenda) Bill 1999 (Cth) as being an important contributor to the formulation of that Bill which became the Copyright Amendment (Digital Agenda) Act 2000 (Cth). Such Act inserted into the Copyright Act , among other things, s 112E which is an important provision under consideration in these proceedings. In short, the IIA submits that it is ' in a position to advance useful submissions in the public interest on the proper construction of certain provisions of the Copyright Act ' (see Sharman Networks Ltd and Others v Universal Music Australia Pty Limited and Others [2006] FCAFC 178 ; (2006) 155 FCR 291 at [14] .)

It appears from the submissions dated 11 November 2009 that the IIA's final submissions are primarily directed towards four aspects of the proceedings before the Court: the interpretation of s 112E of the Copyright Act ; what effect (if any) the AFACT notices should have on an internet service provider's ('ISP') liability for copyright infringement; whether such notices should lead to the termination and/or suspension of customer accounts; and the correct interpretation of the safe harbour provisions.

The IIA emphasises that it does not seek to interfere in the conduct of the proceedings and that because of the limited intervention it seeks it would not disrupt the conduct of the proceedings. It states that should the leave to intervene be granted, it would not seek to make any further oral and written submissions than those already before the Court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>