<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Austin, Nichols &amp; Co Inc v Lodestar Anstalt [2009] FCA 1228 (23 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1228.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bell Wholesale Co. Ltd v Gates Export Corporation [1984] FCA 34 ; (1984) 2 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/34.html</AustLII>
<text>Order 28 r 3 provides that when considering an application by a respondent for an order for security under s 56 , the Court may take into account the matters listed in that rule, including the fact "that an applicant is ordinarily resident outside Australia". Clearly, this does not limit the matters that the Court may take into account when exercising its jurisdiction under s 56: see to this effect Bell Wholesale Co. Ltd v Gates Export Corporation [1984] FCA 34 ; (1984) 2 FCR 1 at 2-3.

Lodestar does not rely on s 1335 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth). Section 1335(1) provides that where a corporation is plaintiff in any action or other legal proceeding, the court having jurisdiction in the matter may, "if it appears by credible testimony that there is reason to believe that the corporation will be unable to pay the costs of the defendant if successful in his, her or its defence", require sufficient security to be given for those costs and stay all proceedings until the security is given. There is no express condition of this kind in s 56 of the FCA Act. While the prospect of an applicant's inability to satisfy an adverse costs order is obviously a relevant consideration, it is not a condition of the availability of the power conferred by s 56. Indeed, the present case is one in which I am satisfied that the applicants would be able to satisfy an adverse costs order, yet will order them to provide security.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Energy Drilling Inc. v Petroz N.L. [1989] ATPR 40-954</tocase>
<text>In Energy Drilling Inc. v Petroz N.L. [1989] ATPR 40-954 ( Energy Drilling) , Gummow J said (at p 50,422): 
 
 The purpose of ordering security for costs against an applicant ordinarily resident outside the jurisdiction is to ensure that a successful respondent will have a fund available within the jurisdiction of this Court against which it can enforce the judgment for costs, so that the respondent does not bear the risk as to the certainty of enforcement in the foreign country and as to the time and complexity of the action there which might be necessary to effect enforcement : Kent Heating Ltd. V. Cook-on-Gas Products Pty. Ltd. &amp; Anor (1984) 59 A.L.R. 277 at p. 279. On the other hand, the mere circumstance that an applicant is resident outside the jurisdiction does not necessarily invite an exercise of discretion in favour of ordering security, the question being how justice will best be served in the particular case: Barton v. Minister for Foreign Affairs [1984] FCA 89 ; (1984) 2 F.C.R. 463 ; CBS Records Australia Ltd. &amp; Ors v. Telmak Teleproducts (Aust.) Pty. Ltd. (1987) ATPR p40-783 at pp. 48,554-48,555, (1987) 72 A.L.R. 270 at pp. 284-285. [My emphasis]

The applicants submit that I should find that they would be likely to satisfy any adverse costs order and that this consideration, made on the basis of evidence of what they submit are assets available within the jurisdiction and other factors, should lead me to refuse Lodestar's application. The applicants refer to: the very significant resources of both applicants, but particularly Rare Breed, outside the jurisdiction; the presence of significant intangible assets within the jurisdiction; evidence of a concrete long-term commitment to doing business in Australia on the part of the applicants; a record of the applicants satisfying costs orders against them in overseas litigation between the same parties whenever such orders have been made; and the availability of reciprocal enforcement mechanisms in the applicants' "home" jurisdictions in the United States of America.

Lodestar, on the other hand, submits that the "assets within the jurisdiction" on which the applicants rely are so problematical that they do not displace a presumption that is made in favour of an award of security in the case of foreign resident applicants, and that I should not, in effect, "trust" the applicants merely on account of their capacity to pay and other considerations on which they rely and to which I will refer below. In effect, Lodestar submits that the Court should approach the matter from the viewpoint of a respondent seeking to enforce a costs order and inquire whether that respondent would be subject to an unacceptable disadvantage by reason of the foreign residence of the applicants.

I do not think that the availability of registration in the USA overcomes the procedural disadvantage that Lodestar would suffer in enforcing its costs order. Enforcing a costs order in the United States would take time and money and involve complexity that would not attend enforcement in Australia. See Energy Drilling at p 50,422 per Gummow J noted at [21] above. (vi) Notice of contention

By a notice of contention, Lodestar seeks: a finding that Austin Nichols lacked standing under s 92(1) of the TM Act as it stood at the time when the removal applications were lodged; a finding that there were circumstances that were an obstacle to the use of the trade mark in the relevant period; and an exercise of the residual discretion not to order removal in a manner different from the way in which that discretion was exercised.

If Lodestar's first contention prevails, Lodestar will succeed even in relation to the issue on which it failed before the Delegate (see [10] above). The applicants argue that Lodestar's second and third contentions would similarly be expected to go to the whole of the goods covered, but I need not discuss this submission.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jesse James v Nolmont Pty Ltd (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (ACN 010 874 834) [2007] FCA 1604</tocase>
<text>In relation to the distribution agreement, Lodestar relies on Jesse James v Nolmont Pty Ltd (subject to a Deed of Company Arrangement) (ACN 010 874 834) [2007] FCA 1604. In that case the applicants were all resident outside Australia and the "asset within the jurisdiction" on which they relied was a stream of royalties or a potential stream of royalties payable under a trade mark licence by a licensee or licensees in Australia in respect of the trade marks. Ryan J considered that the respondent should not have to rely on "assets as speculative as an unquantified stream of royalties flowing on some completely unidentified terms to Vanilla Gorilla [one of the applicants] or either of the other applicants".

The case is not on all fours with the present one but his Honour's decision points in the direction of not regarding the present distribution agreement as an adequate "asset within the jurisdiction" for present purposes.

While it may be that the distribution agreement would provide a satisfactory source of money against which an adverse costs order against Rare Breed could be enforced, this is doubtful for the reasons mentioned above. (iii) Commitment to Australia

There is evidence that the Australian market is second in size only to that of the USA. Those two countries account for about 85% of the sales of the WILD TURKEY business the subject of the Campari Group's acquisition from the Pernod Ricard Group. There is also evidence that the Campari Group intends to expand its presence in important international markets such as Australia. The Information Memorandum contains the following (at p 8): 
 
 Wild Turkey is a global brand, with a total sales volume of more than 800,000 nine-litre cases sold in over 60 markets. The US is the largest market, and generates approximately 50% of sales, while Australia and Japan are the second and third most important markets respectively. In Australia, the bulk of the business is represented by sales of the ready-to-drink products Wild Turkey &amp; Cola and Wild Turkey &amp; Dry, which have an alcoholic content of 6% vol. sold in single serve bottles and cans. 
 .......................................................................................................
 The Issuer intends to meet the following objectives through the acquisition: ... 
 

 
 - to expand its presence on important international markets, such as Australia, where the acquisition lays the foundations for the creation of a distribution platform, and Japan.

Annual sales in Australia are of approximately 120,000 cases of straight bourbon annually and approximately 1.2 million cases of "ready-to-drink" products. I also refer to confidential volume figures at [35] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (ACN 004 069 649) [2008] FCA 1542 ; (2008) 79 IPR 286</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1542.html</AustLII>
<text>In NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (ACN 004 069 649) [2008] FCA 1542 ; (2008) 79 IPR 286 ( NV Sumatra ), Greenwood J made an order that the applicant, NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company (NVS) provide security for certain costs that might be awarded against it in favour of the respondent, British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (BAT), notwithstanding the fact that NVS was the registered proprietor of 29 trade marks in Australia and the applicant in a number of pending applications to register trade marks.

His Honour accepted that by being the registered proprietor of the trade marks, NVS had assets within the jurisdiction, but said that the question was whether they represented assets "of sufficient liquidity so as to constitute a realistic fund against which a successful respondent might enforce an order for costs" (at [20]). Greenwood J continued: 
 
 A party seeking to enforce a costs order might consider whether a receiver might be appointed to stand in possession of the registered trade marks and the rights conferred by registration so as to realise those marks and convert the assets into a fund of money. However, such a process, if available, is one which bears a risk of certainty and complexity even within the jurisdiction. Although no doubt the registered trade marks have a value which can be calculated by reference to the discounted cash flows referable to the exclusive rights conferred by registration to sell goods bearing the marks, determining that value and effecting a sale might not be easy. 
 

 
His Honour did not regard the registered trade marks as assets within the jurisdiction against which an order for costs might easily be enforced.

The applicants seek to distinguish NV Sumatra . They submit that in that case there was no evidence that the marks were in use in Australia, whereas in the present case there is ample evidence to that effect. Moreover, they submit that two problems associated with the trade marks in NV Sumatra do not exist in the present case. One problem was the difficulty of valuing the marks, and the other the difficulty of selling them. The applicants say that the present trade marks were valued as recently as April 2009 as part of an arm's length sale, that they are in use, and that at least two major companies (the respective applicants or their parent groups) have been willing buyers in the recent past. The applicants further submit that there is no reason to suppose that a receiver would have any difficulty in selling the trade marks at a price many times the amount of the respondent's costs.

With respect, the applicants' submissions fail to grapple with the critical question whether the bare trade marks would be readily convertible into cash by sale to satisfy an adverse order for costs.

The evidence to which the applicants refer is not evidence of a sale of the trade marks as items of property distinct from a sale of the underlying business.

The applicants seek to distinguish NV Sumatra on the basis that it was common ground in that case that there was no mechanism for the enforcement of Australian costs orders in Indonesia. In that case, the only mechanism for enforcement was the realisation of the Australian registered trade marks, whereas in the present case there is that mechanism, garnishment of the monies falling due from the distributor to Rare Breed, and registration of the order for costs in the USA.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>P S Chellaram &amp; Co Ltd v China Ocean Shipping Co [1991] HCA 36 ; (1991) 102 ALR 321</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/36.html</AustLII>
<text>Lodestar relies on P S Chellaram &amp; Co Ltd v China Ocean Shipping Co [1991] HCA 36 ; (1991) 102 ALR 321 ( Chellaram ). In that case, the respondents to an appeal pending in the High Court sought an order that the appellant provide security for the costs of the appeal. The application was made pursuant to the provisions of O 70 r 7 of the High Court Rules , s 1335 of the Corporations Law and the inherent jurisdiction of the High Court. McHugh J summarised the ground of the application as being that the appellant was a company incorporated in Hong Kong, had no assets in Australia, and had a deficiency of shareholders' funds of more than $HK22 million. His Honour stated (at 323): 
 
 To make or refuse to make an order for security for costs involves the exercise of a discretionary judgment. That means that the court exercising the discretion must weigh all the circumstances of the case. The weight to be given to any circumstance depends not only upon its own intrinsic persuasiveness but upon the impact of the other circumstances which have to be weighed. A circumstance which may have very great weight when only two or three circumstances have to be weighed may be of minor significance when many circumstances have to be weighed. However, for over 200 years, the fact that a party, bringing proceedings, is resident out of the jurisdiction and has no assets within the jurisdiction has been seen as a circumstance of great weight in determining whether an order for security for costs should be made. Indeed, for many years the practice has been to order such a party to provide security for costs unless that party can point to other circumstances which overcome the weight of the circumstance that that person is resident out of and has no assets within the jurisdiction. 
 

 
In the following paragraph, his Honour remarked that not only was the appellant resident out of, and without assets within, Australia, but also it was "hopelessly insolvent".

An individual who was a major shareholder in the appellant's business proffered an undertaking to meet any costs ordered to be paid by the appellant up to the amount of the security being sought by the respondent, but there was no evidence concerning his financial position, the financial position of the other major shareholder of the appellant, or evidence of how the appellant's own costs were being funded.

The present applicants correctly point out that the circumstances of the present case differ from those in Chellaram in relation to the insolvency of the party against whom the order for security was sought.

This point of difference does not, however, automatically deny the proposition that great weight should be given to the fact that a party against whom the order for security is sought is a foreign resident without assets within the jurisdiction. Indeed, the present applicants accept that an order for security will be made in those circumstances unless other factors overcome the weight to be accorded to them.

The application raises the question what is meant by "assets within the jurisdiction" for present purposes. (i) Overall solvency of the applicants

I am not persuaded by the considerations referred to by the applicants to think that the "great weight" to which McHugh J referred in Chellaram should not be attached to the circumstance that both applicants are foreign corporations who have no readily realisable assets in Australia against which an order for costs could be enforced without difficulty or delay.

Ultimately, the applicants' submission is that in view of the size and wealth of Rare Breed and the Campari Group, the considerable revenue that Rare Breed derives from the Australian market, and its apparent commitment to expand its operations in that market, it is simply unthinkable that it would not satisfy an adverse costs order. According to this approach, the presence or absence of assets in Australia is irrelevant.

In my respectful opinion, this is the wrong approach. Lodestar is entitled to have its present application for security determined on the basis that it will have to enforce the costs order hypothetically made in its favour. It is not appropriate to determine the application on the assumption that the applicants will respond to an order that they pay costs with immediate compliance. At that time they may hold a certain view of the course that the proceeding has taken and determine not to satisfy the costs order unless forced to do so.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>