<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLKP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 145 (16 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/145.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>In adopting this course, it seems to me that the Tribunal was alive to the procedure, counselled by the High Court in SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 231 ALR 592 at especially 602, para 43. There, in respect of a Tribunal proceeding, the court noted that the Tribunal had not identified particular aspects of the visa Applicant's account as important issues in the course of the hearing; that it had not challenged what the visa applicant had said; and that it did not say anything to him that would have revealed to him particular issues that were live issues in the context of the consideration of that particular visa application. Rather, based on what the delegate had decided, the Tribunal had left the visa Applicant in that case in a position where he would, and should, have understood that there was a quite different central and critical issue for determination, in the context of that case, as to whether the Tribunal was satisfied that a claim for a protection visa had been made out.

No such criticism can be voiced of the way in which the Tribunal dealt with the case in this instance, nor in any failure on the part of the Federal Magistrates Court to quash the decision of the Tribunal on such a basis. Instead, what is revealed is a considered value judgment by the Tribunal, having well and truly put the male Appellant on notice in respect of critical, factual issues for determination.

It is worthy of note, also, that the Tribunal asked the male Appellant, in the course of the hearing, whether he had any other information to provide in relation to the visa application, and that he responded that he did not. It was then that the Tribunal gave the male Appellant notice that the Tribunal might, on the information before it, be in a position to give an oral decision. The response, apparently made by the male Appellant, was that he wanted to change his life, and that he came "here"; ie, to Australia.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>