<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Strazdins, in the matter of DNPW Pty Ltd (subject to DOCA) ACN 107 484 711 v Birch Carroll &amp; Coyle Limited (No 3) [2009] FCA 1410 (1 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1410.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Fekala Pty Ltd v Cenbond Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 340</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2001/340.html</AustLII>
<text>Next the respondent argued that, consistent with the decision of the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Fekala Pty Ltd v Cenbond Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 340 , an order for costs ought to be made in the respondent's favour.

In that case, the Court was concerned with two interlocutory applications relating to an order under s 441D(2) of the Corporations Act . Section 441D operates to protect a company's property during an administration. Section 441D allows an administrator to apply to the Court for an order that a chargee or receiver or other person not perform specified functions or exercise specified powers during the course of the administration: s 441D of the Corporations Act . The section allows the Court to restrain a secured creditor from realising on the creditor's security.

In Fekala Pty Ltd v Cenbond Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 340 , the Court was asked to make an order under s 441D where the administrators had had considerable time to put forward some firm proposal in relation to a payment due to the secured creditor and even at the time of the hearing could only put forward a speculative proposal. The administrators were not in a position to give any undertaking as to damages. The trial judge, Young J, made the order under s 441D only because he thought there was some chance that the secured creditors would benefit by the order being made. He made it a condition of the order, without saying why, that the administrators pay the costs of the application.

It seems to me that that case is no authority for any general proposition that when a court makes an order under s 444F , the court should award the chargee or the owner or lessor of property its costs. Justice Young did not say that. He merely made it a condition of the order that the costs be paid. In my opinion, that case is not authority for the proposition advanced by the respondent.

Next the respondent contended that, if the applicants had applied to the Court for relief under the Law of Property Act 2000 (NT), the Court could have made an order for costs in favour of the respondent.

The applicants did initially include in their application a claim for relief under that Act but that was abandoned very early in the hearing. The matter did not proceed under that Act. It seems to me irrelevant what powers the Law of Property Act 2000 (NT) gives to the Court in relation to costs for applications under that Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hayes v Gunbola Pty Ltd (1986) 4 BPR 9247 </tocase>
<text>Next it was put that there is a presumption that where a party seeks an order for relief from forfeiture that the party seeking relief ought to pay the lessor's costs. In support of that contention the respondent relied on Hayes v Gunbola Pty Ltd (1986) 4 BPR 9247.

That was a case for relief from forfeiture under s 128 of the Conveyancing Act 1919 (NSW) in which the trial judge (Young J) was of the opinion that, in the exercise of the Court's discretion relief should be granted. His Honour addressed the question of costs and said "it is abundantly clear that as the price of getting relief against forfeiture the plaintiff must pay the lessor's reasonable costs": Hayes v Gunbola Pty Ltd 4 BPR 9247 at 9255. His Honour referred to Howard v Fanshawe [1895] 2 Ch D 581 at 592 where he said the ordinary order was that the plaintiff must bear the costs of the action except where those costs have been increased by the defendant resisting the claim and those costs must be borne by the defendant. He also referred to Langley v Foster (1909) 10 SR (NSW) 54 at 62 where Simpson CJ in Eq said: 
 
 ... prima facie one of the terms imposed should be the payment of all costs, for the plaintiff's own breach of his agreement has given rise to the litigation ... this is not a hard and fast rule, for, if it were, a lessor might always oppose relief being granted knowing he would always get his costs from the lessee. If the court thinks the lessor ought not have opposed in toto the grant of relief from forfeiture, the court may make the lessor pay the costs so far as they have been increased by the lessor resisting the claim to relief on any terms ... But the court may make, and has in one case at any rate made, the lessee pay all the costs, notwithstanding the lessor contested his claim to relief at all: Quilter v Mapleson [1882] 9 QB 672. It is a question for the court's discretion in each case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Howard v Fanshawe [1895] 2 Ch D 581 </tocase>
<text>That was a case for relief from forfeiture under s 128 of the Conveyancing Act 1919 (NSW) in which the trial judge (Young J) was of the opinion that, in the exercise of the Court's discretion relief should be granted. His Honour addressed the question of costs and said "it is abundantly clear that as the price of getting relief against forfeiture the plaintiff must pay the lessor's reasonable costs": Hayes v Gunbola Pty Ltd 4 BPR 9247 at 9255. His Honour referred to Howard v Fanshawe [1895] 2 Ch D 581 at 592 where he said the ordinary order was that the plaintiff must bear the costs of the action except where those costs have been increased by the defendant resisting the claim and those costs must be borne by the defendant. He also referred to Langley v Foster (1909) 10 SR (NSW) 54 at 62 where Simpson CJ in Eq said: 
 
 ... prima facie one of the terms imposed should be the payment of all costs, for the plaintiff's own breach of his agreement has given rise to the litigation ... this is not a hard and fast rule, for, if it were, a lessor might always oppose relief being granted knowing he would always get his costs from the lessee. If the court thinks the lessor ought not have opposed in toto the grant of relief from forfeiture, the court may make the lessor pay the costs so far as they have been increased by the lessor resisting the claim to relief on any terms ... But the court may make, and has in one case at any rate made, the lessee pay all the costs, notwithstanding the lessor contested his claim to relief at all: Quilter v Mapleson [1882] 9 QB 672. It is a question for the court's discretion in each case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Langley v Foster (1909) 10 SR (NSW) 54</tocase>
<text>That was a case for relief from forfeiture under s 128 of the Conveyancing Act 1919 (NSW) in which the trial judge (Young J) was of the opinion that, in the exercise of the Court's discretion relief should be granted. His Honour addressed the question of costs and said "it is abundantly clear that as the price of getting relief against forfeiture the plaintiff must pay the lessor's reasonable costs": Hayes v Gunbola Pty Ltd 4 BPR 9247 at 9255. His Honour referred to Howard v Fanshawe [1895] 2 Ch D 581 at 592 where he said the ordinary order was that the plaintiff must bear the costs of the action except where those costs have been increased by the defendant resisting the claim and those costs must be borne by the defendant. He also referred to Langley v Foster (1909) 10 SR (NSW) 54 at 62 where Simpson CJ in Eq said: 
 
 ... prima facie one of the terms imposed should be the payment of all costs, for the plaintiff's own breach of his agreement has given rise to the litigation ... this is not a hard and fast rule, for, if it were, a lessor might always oppose relief being granted knowing he would always get his costs from the lessee. If the court thinks the lessor ought not have opposed in toto the grant of relief from forfeiture, the court may make the lessor pay the costs so far as they have been increased by the lessor resisting the claim to relief on any terms ... But the court may make, and has in one case at any rate made, the lessee pay all the costs, notwithstanding the lessor contested his claim to relief at all: Quilter v Mapleson [1882] 9 QB 672. It is a question for the court's discretion in each case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Latoudis v Casey [1990] HCA 59 ; (1990) 170 CLR 534 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1990/59.html</AustLII>
<text>The purpose of an order for costs is to compensate the party in whose favour the costs order is made for the costs of the proceeding. The orders for costs are not an indemnity but are designed to compensate the party in whose favour the order for costs is made in part for the costs of the proceeding. The purpose of an order for costs is not to punish the party against whom the order for costs is made: Latoudis v Casey [1990] HCA 59 ; (1990) 170 CLR 534 at 543, 563 and 567; Oshlack v Richmond River Council [1998] HCA 11 ; (1998) 193 CLR 72 at 96.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Oshlack v Richmond River Council [1998] HCA 11 ; (1998) 193 CLR 72</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/11.html</AustLII>
<text>The purpose of an order for costs is to compensate the party in whose favour the costs order is made for the costs of the proceeding. The orders for costs are not an indemnity but are designed to compensate the party in whose favour the order for costs is made in part for the costs of the proceeding. The purpose of an order for costs is not to punish the party against whom the order for costs is made: Latoudis v Casey [1990] HCA 59 ; (1990) 170 CLR 534 at 543, 563 and 567; Oshlack v Richmond River Council [1998] HCA 11 ; (1998) 193 CLR 72 at 96.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>