<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pioneer Computers Australia Pty Limited v Pioneer KK (includes corrigendum dated 18 September 2009) [2009] FCA 135 (23 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/135.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Blount Inc v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/440.html</AustLII>
<text>The issues raised in the appeal, to be considered afresh by this Court ( Blount Inc v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 59) cover the same issues as faced by the Registrar. They are, broadly: Is Pioneer Computers a "person aggrieved", as required by s 92(1) of the Act as it stood at the time when the non-use applications were filed? What use has Pioneer KK established of the Pioneer KK marks on the removal goods and the removal services? What properly comes within the description of the expression "computer peripheral devices"? Would there be confusion if the registrations for the Pioneer KK marks were amended by way of removal of the removal goods and the removal services, or conversely, if the registrations for the Pioneer KK marks were maintained in their present form? If the Pioneer KK marks are liable to be removed under s 92(4)(a) or s 92(4)(b) of the Act in respect of the removal goods and the removal services, should the discretion available under s 101(3) of the Act be exercised?

Before turning to a consideration of the Pioneer KK marks, it is useful to identify the parties. Pioneer Computers

Pioneer Computers was incorporated on 23 December 1996 and has traded under that name since that date. Pioneer Computers is the manufacturer and vendor of computer products and services and has conducted business under its corporate name, Pioneer Computers Australia Pty Limited, since December 1996. It has used the trade mark PIONEER in Australia in relation to desktop computers, notebook computers, servers and other computer related goods and in relation to installation, repair and support services for computers. It uses the mark PIONEER on its website, on invoices, on stationery and on publicly distributed promotional material. Most of the computers that Pioneer Computers sells are built-to-order and, since late 1998, those built-to-order computers have been able to be ordered online via Pioneer Computers' website, www.pioneercomputers.com.au .

An appeal from a decision of the Registrar of Trade Marks is in the Court's original jurisdiction. None of the powers of the Court under s 197 of the Act affect the s 92 application, which goes to the jurisdiction of the Court to hear and determine an application for removal of a trade mark. The hearing is a "hearing de novo" where the judge reviewing the decision of the Registrar begins afresh and exercises any discretion exercised by the Registrar. The parties may adduce evidence as provided for in s 197 of the Act which evidence may include evidence not before the Registrar (see discussion in Totev v Sfar [2008] FCAFC 35 ; (2008) 167 FCR 193 by Emmett J at [12] and [13]; Blount at 59).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331</tocase>
<text>The expression "person aggrieved" has been discussed in Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104 by Sackville J (with whom Sheppard and Tamberlin JJ agreed) and by Jacobson J in Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478 . As was said by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158 at 193 (approved by Sackville J in Kraft Foods at 112-113, by Sackville J in Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331 at 363 (with whom Lehane J agreed) and by Perram J in Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14 at [23] (with whom Emmett and Besanko JJ agreed)), the expression "person aggrieved": 
 
 ... embrace [s] any person having a real interest in having the Register rectified, or the trade mark removed in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed, and thus would include any person who would be, or in respect of whom there is a reasonable possibility of his being, appreciably disadvantaged in a legal or practical sense by the Register remaining unrectified, or by the trade mark remaining unremoved in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed.

In Campomar , the Full Court was dealing with cosmetic and perfume products sold by reference to the word "Nike". Justice Sackville, with whom Lehane J agreed, concluded that it was sufficient for Nike International to be a person aggrieved that, by reason of an established reputation in one field, the sporting field, the public would be likely to think that the appellants' cosmetic and perfume products had Nike International's approval or sponsorship. This was not reversed on appeal.

The question whether computers and associated products on the one hand and the goods sold by Pioneer KK under the Pioneer KK marks on the other are the same class of goods or a similar class of goods is answered differently by the parties when considering whether Pioneer Computers is a person aggrieved and whether the public considers that the goods are sufficiently similar to give rise to possible confusion.

In considering the issue of "person aggrieved", Pioneer KK submits that Pioneer Computers is only a person aggrieved for the category of computers (and services in relation to these). Pioneer KK submits that Pioneer Computers is not a person aggrieved in respect of any of the other removal goods and removal services, including computer peripherals, which Pioneer Computers does not supply under its PIONEER mark. That is, Pioneer KK submits that care should be taken to subdivide the goods and services within the registered classes to consider which category is actually sold.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Conde Nast Publications Pty Ltd v Taylor (1998) 41 IPR 505</tocase>
<text>Pioneer Computers submits that the date at which the Court should consider the facts relevant to the exercise of discretion under s 101(3) is the date at which the non-use is to be determined, namely, the expiry of the relevant period or, alternatively, the date at which the removal applicant must establish that it is a person aggrieved, namely the date of the non-use application. There is no material difference between those dates. Pioneer Computers accepts, however, that events after the relevant date may cast light on earlier circumstances ( Conde Nast Publications Pty Ltd v Taylor (1998) 41 IPR 505 at 509). While Pioneer Computers submits that the time to consider any confusion is the expiration of the relevant period, it concedes that this is, in a sense, ' artificial ', particularly given the length of time between the relevant period and the hearing of these proceedings.

Pioneer KK says that the relevant date for a passing off case is the beginning of the conduct complained of. The discretion to maintain a trade mark registration must, Pioneer KK submits, take into account whether anyone would be deceived if the Pioneer KK marks remain on the Register in their current state or are removed from the Register insofar as the removal goods and the removal services are concerned. The date of that assessment is, Pioneer KK contends, the date of hearing, although confusion leading up to that date would also be relevant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 008 596 370) [2008] FCA 934 ; (2008) 77 IPR 69</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/934.html</AustLII>
<text>Pioneer Australia is a wholly owned subsidiary of Pioneer KK. The use of the marks indicates a connection in the course of trade with the registered proprietor of the marks, Pioneer KK. It cannot be said that the use of the marks by Pioneer Australia is somehow deceptive by indicating a different origin of the goods (see also E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 008 596 370) [2008] FCA 934 ; (2008) 77 IPR 69 at [102] ).

The products sold by Pioneer Australia were created and supplied by or on behalf of Pioneer KK. That is, the quality control of manufacture was exercised by the Japanese company. The exercise by Pioneer KK of quality control over goods and services dealt with or provided in the course of trade by its subsidiary, Pioneer Australia, is sufficient for me to conclude that use of the Pioneer KK marks by Pioneer Australia was under the control of Pioneer KK and authorised by it.

While the non-use applications filed by Pioneer Computers were defective insofar as the ground in s 92(4)(a) is concerned, I will briefly consider the issue of intention to use the Pioneer KK marks. I note that intention to use refers to intention as at the date of filing of the application for registration. Intention to use the Pioneer KK marks with respect to computers</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005 ; (2008) 78 IPR 334</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1005.html</AustLII>
<text>Pioneer Computers relies upon the requirement under the Act and Regulations (s 27(3) of the Act and Regulations 4.4(2) and 4.4 (6)) which require a trade mark applicant to specify the goods and/or services in respect of which it is sought to register the trade mark and proscribes the use of expressions such as "all goods" or "all services"; the goods or services must be indicated by name. Pioneer Computers submits that it follows from s 100(1) of the Act, which requires that a trade mark owner establish use in relation to the particular goods and/or services for which removal is sought, that there is a clear policy not to allow use for one good or service to stand as use for another good or service even though they fall within a class or broad description ( Moove (No 2) at 272).

Pioneer KK nominated the goods for which it sought and obtained registration. In the second Pioneer KK registration, the goods were specified by the general term "computer peripheral devices" followed by list of specific devices which differ from each other, for example, printers and keyboards. The specification thus encompasses the specific goods nominated and any goods that can be described as "computer peripheral devices" that are not otherwise specified.

Pioneer Computers submits that Pioneer KK cannot, by establishing use on optical disc drives and jukeboxes, rely upon that use of the mark for the other goods encompassed by the general term "computer peripheral devices". Rather, it says that the term is residual and covers goods not otherwise specified in the trade mark registration. Pioneer Computers submits that DVD drives and DVD writers fall in a distinct niche market segment that is laser and optical drives which have been specifically provided for in the second Pioneer KK trade mark registration. It submits that Pioneer KK is not entitled to a monopoly for the additional term "computer peripheral devices" for which, it says, no use has been established.

The exercise of the discretionary power to remove a mark under s 101(2) of the Act is as at the date upon which the Court makes the order for removal ( E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005 ; (2008) 78 IPR 334 at [4] per Flick J). This is a hearing de novo and the parties have adduced evidence in this hearing directed to the exercise of discretion. As it happens, the date for consideration of the evidence is not determinative of the outcome. The evidence relied upon by Pioneer KK is of confusion during the relevant period, of convergence of computer and audio-visual technologies and of brand extension by other companies operating in the computer and audio-visual fields that was evident in that period and predicted at that time to continue. The evidence with respect to post-relevant period convergence and potential for confusion has simply validated that prediction. The facts relevant to the exercise of the discretion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/100.html</AustLII>
<text>The expression "person aggrieved" has been discussed in Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104 by Sackville J (with whom Sheppard and Tamberlin JJ agreed) and by Jacobson J in Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478 . As was said by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158 at 193 (approved by Sackville J in Kraft Foods at 112-113, by Sackville J in Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331 at 363 (with whom Lehane J agreed) and by Perram J in Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14 at [23] (with whom Emmett and Besanko JJ agreed)), the expression "person aggrieved": 
 
 ... embrace [s] any person having a real interest in having the Register rectified, or the trade mark removed in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed, and thus would include any person who would be, or in respect of whom there is a reasonable possibility of his being, appreciably disadvantaged in a legal or practical sense by the Register remaining unrectified, or by the trade mark remaining unremoved in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed.

The exercise of the discretionary power to remove a mark under s 101(2) of the Act is as at the date upon which the Court makes the order for removal ( E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005 ; (2008) 78 IPR 334 at [4] per Flick J). This is a hearing de novo and the parties have adduced evidence in this hearing directed to the exercise of discretion. As it happens, the date for consideration of the evidence is not determinative of the outcome. The evidence relied upon by Pioneer KK is of confusion during the relevant period, of convergence of computer and audio-visual technologies and of brand extension by other companies operating in the computer and audio-visual fields that was evident in that period and predicted at that time to continue. The evidence with respect to post-relevant period convergence and potential for confusion has simply validated that prediction. The facts relevant to the exercise of the discretion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2009/14.html</AustLII>
<text>The expression "person aggrieved" has been discussed in Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104 by Sackville J (with whom Sheppard and Tamberlin JJ agreed) and by Jacobson J in Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478 . As was said by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158 at 193 (approved by Sackville J in Kraft Foods at 112-113, by Sackville J in Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331 at 363 (with whom Lehane J agreed) and by Perram J in Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14 at [23] (with whom Emmett and Besanko JJ agreed)), the expression "person aggrieved": 
 
 ... embrace [s] any person having a real interest in having the Register rectified, or the trade mark removed in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed, and thus would include any person who would be, or in respect of whom there is a reasonable possibility of his being, appreciably disadvantaged in a legal or practical sense by the Register remaining unrectified, or by the trade mark remaining unremoved in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hermes Trade Mark [1982] RPC 425</tocase>
<text>In E &amp; J Gallo at [202]-[203], Flick J stated that the following factors set out by Falconer J in Hermes Trade Mark [1982] RPC 425 were of assistance in considering the exercise of the discretion: there had been no abandonment of the trade mark; the registered proprietors of the mark still had a residual reputation in the mark; there had been sales by the registered proprietors of goods for which removal was sought since the relevant period ended; the applicants for removal had entered the market without having taken steps to ascertain from the Register whether anyone had a right to exclude their use of the mark; the registered proprietors were not aware of the applicant's sales under the mark. 
Pioneer KK says the first four factors are applicable in this case.

Pioneer Computers says that the present case is not one for the proper exercise of discretion to allow the Pioneer KK marks to remain on the Register and that no sufficient reason appears or has been established for doing so in respect of the removal goods and the removal services. The relevance of s 101(4) of the Act to the exercise of the discretion in s 101(3)

By amendment in 2006, s 101(4) was added to provide that without limiting the matters that the Registrar may take into account in deciding under s 101(3) not to remove a trade mark from the Register, the Registrar may take into account whether the trade mark has been used by the registered proprietor in respect of (a) similar goods or closely related services; or (b) similar services or closely related goods. The parties disagree as to whether or not the matters now raised in s 101(4) are able to be taken into account for the purposes of the unamended section; that is, whether it was necessary to insert s 101(4) to add discretionary factors not previously available, or to clarify that they were always available to be taken into account.

There is no limitation within s 101(3) on the discretion, nor any indication of the factors to be taken into account. In the Explanatory Memorandum to the Trade Marks Amendment Bill 2006 (Cth) by which s 101(4) was introduced, it is stated that '[c] urrently, it is not clear that the Registrar is able to take use on closely related goods or services into account, when deciding whether to exercise his or her discretion not to remove a trade mark from the Register ' and that the amendment was for the purposes of clarifying the Registrar's discretion. Interestingly, the example that is given in the Bill is a registration for computer software goods where the business has specialised in the provision of a custom development of software systems service with the view that they are seen as closely related services and goods.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Kowa Company Ltd v NV Organon [2005] FCA 1282 ; (2005) 223 ALR 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1282.html</AustLII>
<text>The Registrar accepted that while use of the Pioneer KK marks had been demonstrated on computer peripherals, no use had been shown on the remaining removal goods and the removal services within the relevant period and Pioneer KK could not establish circumstances that were an obstacle to the full use of the registrations. On the basis that it is not necessary for exceptional circumstances to exist before the Registrar may apply the power found in s 101(3) in favour of an opponent ( Kowa Company Ltd v NV Organon [2005] FCA 1282 ; (2005) 223 ALR 27 at [98] per Lander J), the Registrar concluded that, despite non-use being established for a range of the removal goods and for the removal services, it was not viable to limit the registrations by removing the removal goods and the removal services from the Register. The basis for this was that the difference between computer goods on the one hand and audio, audio-visual and home entertainment products on the other does not enable the drawing of "fine lines" between those goods for which use was demonstrated and those the subject of non-use.

The Registrar considered the evidence as to the likelihood of deception or confusion among consumers. She concluded that Pioneer KK had a significant reputation in the Pioneer KK marks and in the word "Pioneer". The Registrar took into account the time before the relevant period, when Pioneer KK produced and sold entire computer systems under the brand "Pioneer" and under the first Pioneer KK mark, although such sales were limited, as well as evidence as to its future plans for research and development of products that combine home entertainment and computing in one package.

The Registrar concluded at [37] that it was not appropriate to make a distinction between the computers and associated products of Pioneer Computers and the audio, visual and electronic products of Pioneer KK. She concluded that there was a ' high likelihood of deception or confusion in the marketplace '. While recognising that Pioneer Computers had seemingly used PIONEER honestly for over 10 years, had goodwill in the computer marketplace and intended to continue to use the trade mark PIONEER in connection with goods and services unless prevented from doing so, the Registrar concluded that the public interest was best served by declining to amend the registrations. Rather, she concluded that the public interest was best served by retaining the registrations in total and preserving the established trade marks.

In Kowa Company at [98], Lander J rejected the submission that a party seeking the exercise of the discretion needs to show "exceptional circumstances". In E &amp; J Gallo at [198], Flick J agreed with Lander J that there is no requirement to establish exceptional circumstances. With respect, I also agree with Lander J that there is no warrant to read a requirement for exceptional circumstances into s 101(3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104</tocase>
<text>The expression "person aggrieved" has been discussed in Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104 by Sackville J (with whom Sheppard and Tamberlin JJ agreed) and by Jacobson J in Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478 . As was said by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158 at 193 (approved by Sackville J in Kraft Foods at 112-113, by Sackville J in Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331 at 363 (with whom Lehane J agreed) and by Perram J in Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14 at [23] (with whom Emmett and Besanko JJ agreed)), the expression "person aggrieved": 
 
 ... embrace [s] any person having a real interest in having the Register rectified, or the trade mark removed in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed, and thus would include any person who would be, or in respect of whom there is a reasonable possibility of his being, appreciably disadvantaged in a legal or practical sense by the Register remaining unrectified, or by the trade mark remaining unremoved in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed.

Without refining the breadth of the expression, Sackville J gave some examples of a person aggrieved in Kraft Foods at 113:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lever Brothers, Port Sunlight Ltd v Sunniwite Products Ltd (1949) 66 RPC 84</tocase>
<text>At 114, his Honour referred to Lever Brothers, Port Sunlight Ltd v Sunniwite Products Ltd (1949) 66 RPC 84 where, in respect of a mark registered for soap, detergents and cosmetics, a manufacturer of a soapless detergent was not a person aggrieved in respect of the registration for cosmetics.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Magnavox (Aust) Pty Ltd's Trade Mark (1964) 34 AOJP 2075</tocase>
<text>It is not unreasonable, particularly in an area of technology the subject of rapid change, for an applicant for a trade mark to include within the class of goods for which the trade mark is registered, products which may not be able to be strictly described. The statement of goods should not be construed so narrowly that it fails to include goods clearly within the designated class that have not yet been developed. As was said in Magnavox (Aust) Pty Ltd's Trade Mark (1964) 34 AOJP 2075 at 2078, ' the rights arising from the registration of a trade mark should not be confined to the stage of technological development of goods specified when the mark was registered '.

The general term "computer peripheral devices" as used is an appropriate term to describe the range of goods marketed by Pioneer KK in the areas of computer and optical technology, given the rate of change and advances in those technologies. Further, as the technology has changed and as it is used, some devices may be internally connected or externally connected to a computer. One example is the DVD drive in a larger or smaller notebook computer. It seems artificial to restrict the description of a category of goods on the basis of a distinction drawn by the definition where the distinction is not drawn in use of the term in the marketplace, where it depends upon the way in which the goods are used, sometimes idiosyncratically, and where the use of a particular device as an internal component or an externally connected device may change as the technology changes. In any event, for the reasons that follow in considering discretionary matters, the distinction is not determinative of the decision regarding whether or not to remove the removal goods from the registrations for the Pioneer KK marks. The specific inclusion of certain computer peripheral devices in the Pioneer KK trade mark registrations

Pioneer Computers says that optical devices (including DVD-ROM drives and DVD writers) constitute a separate category of information technology products that comprise a niche market and that they should not be considered as satisfying the range of products encompassed by the general term "computer peripheral devices". As noted above, Pioneer Computers further argues that in the present case, the separate inclusion of various goods (including optical disc drives) in the second Pioneer KK trade mark registration means that these products are not encompassed by the term "computer peripheral devices" as used in the registration.

In this case, the inclusion of computer peripheral devices in the description of the goods for which the second Pioneer KK mark was registered seems to have been as a "catch-all" and an expression to encompass goods yet to be developed and so yet to be specifically described.

The Explanatory Memorandum does not really assist. Section 101(4) makes it clear that it has been inserted without any attempt to limit or qualify the discretion provided for in s 101(3). The Explanatory Memorandum itself speaks of "clarification". This can either recognise that s 101(4) expands the discretion or that it simply makes it clear which factors could already be taken into account under s 101(3). In my view, use of a trade mark on closely related goods or services could already be taken into account in exercising the discretion under s 101(3) in the unamended section. As I read s 101(3) , the discretion to be exercised is not limited. For the purposes of s 101(3) , account may be taken of use of the trade mark on closely related goods or services, even in cases commencing prior to the introduction of s 101(4). This has particular relevance in the case of goods that are at the forefront of technological change. Justice Dixon (as he then was) said in The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Rohm and Haas Company [1948] HCA 27 ; (1949) 78 CLR 601 at 627 that the basis of a claim to proprietorship in a trade mark so far unused is found in the combined effect of authorship of the mark, the intention to use it on or in connection with the goods and the application for registration. In Magnavox , the Assistant Registrar considered a mark which had not been used across the scope of the goods claimed. In coming to a conclusion as to use across a class of goods, I agree with the Assistant Registrar (at 2078) that ' the rights arising from the registration of a trade mark should not be confined to the stage of technological development of goods specified when the mark was registered '. The relevant date for the exercise of the discretion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McHattan v Australian Specialised Vehicle Systems Pty Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 537</tocase>
<text>Pioneer Computers submits that the term "computer peripheral devices" should be removed from the registrations. It relies on the Moove case ( Murray Goulburn Co-operative Co Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation [1990] FCA 32 ; (1990) 24 FCR 370 (' Moove (No 1) ') and Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation (1990) 17 IPR 269 (' Moove (No 2) ') where a trade mark registered for dairy products was limited to cheese and flavoured milk. It submits that the removal goods and the removal services and those in the balance of the registration are clearly and separately identifiable without fine distinctions drawn as, for example, between vehicles dependent on particular use or size as in McHattan v Australian Specialised Vehicle Systems Pty Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 537.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Murray Goulburn Co-operative Co Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation [1990] FCA 32 ; (1990) 24 FCR 370</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1990/32.html</AustLII>
<text>Pioneer Computers submits that the term "computer peripheral devices" should be removed from the registrations. It relies on the Moove case ( Murray Goulburn Co-operative Co Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation [1990] FCA 32 ; (1990) 24 FCR 370 (' Moove (No 1) ') and Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation (1990) 17 IPR 269 (' Moove (No 2) ') where a trade mark registered for dairy products was limited to cheese and flavoured milk. It submits that the removal goods and the removal services and those in the balance of the registration are clearly and separately identifiable without fine distinctions drawn as, for example, between vehicles dependent on particular use or size as in McHattan v Australian Specialised Vehicle Systems Pty Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 537.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation (1990) 17 IPR 269</tocase>
<text>Pioneer Computers submits that the term "computer peripheral devices" should be removed from the registrations. It relies on the Moove case ( Murray Goulburn Co-operative Co Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation [1990] FCA 32 ; (1990) 24 FCR 370 (' Moove (No 1) ') and Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company Ltd v New South Wales Dairy Corporation (1990) 17 IPR 269 (' Moove (No 2) ') where a trade mark registered for dairy products was limited to cheese and flavoured milk. It submits that the removal goods and the removal services and those in the balance of the registration are clearly and separately identifiable without fine distinctions drawn as, for example, between vehicles dependent on particular use or size as in McHattan v Australian Specialised Vehicle Systems Pty Ltd (1996) 34 IPR 537.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>New South Wales Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company (1989) 14 IPR 75</tocase>
<text>Further, in the demand, Pioneer KK sought generally to prevent Pioneer Computers from any use of the mark PIONEER and demanded a complete cessation of the use by Pioneer Computers of any mark which is substantially identical with or deceptively similar to "the Pioneer Trade Mark". The allegation of infringement of Pioneer KK's registered marks was general and not restricted to the removal goods and the removal services. A general allegation was sufficient in New South Wales Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company (1989) 14 IPR 75 for Gummow J (at 77) and in Unilever Australia Ltd v Karounos (2001) 113 FCR 322 for Hill J (at [35]) to find that the recipient of the allegation was a person aggrieved in respect of all of the goods/classes for which the relevant trade marks were registered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pioneer Kabushiki Kaisha v Registrar of Trade Marks [1977] HCA 56 ; (1977) 137 CLR 670</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/56.html</AustLII>
<text>Pioneer Computers submits that Pioneer KK has failed to establish that use by Pioneer Australia of the Pioneer KK marks for the services which the Australian company did provide in the relevant period was use by the Australian company as the authorised user of the marks and that the benefit of any such use accrued to the Japanese parent. Accepting that Pioneer Australia is a wholly-owned subsidiary of Pioneer KK and a distributor of Pioneer KK's products, Pioneer Computers submits that this does not establish that Pioneer KK exercised any relevant control within the meaning of s 8 of the Act over Pioneer Australia's use of the Pioneer KK marks in the relevant period. There is no evidence of a license ( Pioneer Kabushiki Kaisha v Registrar of Trade Marks [1977] HCA 56 ; (1977) 137 CLR 670 at 673). Accordingly, Pioneer Computers submits, Pioneer KK has not established that Pioneer Australia was an authorised user within the meaning of s 8 of the Act of the Pioneer KK marks in respect of the removal services in the relevant period.

Pioneer KK relies upon the fact that the products sold under the trade marks were manufactured by or on behalf of Pioneer KK and that the documents, including manuals and test protocols, were created by the Japanese company and supplied to the Australian subsidiary for supply to customers in Australia.

Use under the control of the owner of the trade marks is authorised use (ss 8(1) and 8(2) of the Act). As pointed out by Aickin J in Pioneer Kabushiki Kaisha at 683, a slight connection such as selection and quality control, or control by Pioneer KK of Pioneer Australia in the sense in which a parent company controls a subsidiary, may be sufficient.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158</tocase>
<text>The expression "person aggrieved" has been discussed in Kraft Foods Inc v Gaines Pet Foods Corporation (1996) 65 FCR 104 by Sackville J (with whom Sheppard and Tamberlin JJ agreed) and by Jacobson J in Health World Ltd (ABN 73 010 636 165) v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd (ACN 060 792 163) [2008] FCA 100 ; (2008) 75 IPR 478 . As was said by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel Ltd v Charles of the Ritz Ltd (1988) 15 NSWLR 158 at 193 (approved by Sackville J in Kraft Foods at 112-113, by Sackville J in Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd (1998) 85 FCR 331 at 363 (with whom Lehane J agreed) and by Perram J in Health World Limited v Shin-Sun Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 14 at [23] (with whom Emmett and Besanko JJ agreed)), the expression "person aggrieved": 
 
 ... embrace [s] any person having a real interest in having the Register rectified, or the trade mark removed in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed, and thus would include any person who would be, or in respect of whom there is a reasonable possibility of his being, appreciably disadvantaged in a legal or practical sense by the Register remaining unrectified, or by the trade mark remaining unremoved in respect of any goods, as the case may be, in the manner claimed.

Pioneer Computers relies upon the policy of the Act to facilitate the removal of an unused trade mark and the public interest in the integrity of the Register which, it submits, will generally demand the removal of an unused trade mark ( Shanahan at [15.145]). However, as Shanahan also points out at [15.145], the underlying policy of the Act is to give the Court sufficient flexibility to give effect to public interest considerations. This includes the flexibility not to order removal even though the trade mark is unused in the sense required by s 92. The authors suggest that removal may not be appropriate where, for example, the trade mark is nonetheless well-known either from earlier use or from advertising or publicity coming from abroad. A further consideration, as noted by McLelland J in Ritz Hotel and by the Registrar in this case, is where removal could be ' potentially conducive to public confusion ' ( Ritz Hotel at 224).

Pioneer Computers submits the following in support of its contention that the Court should not exercise its discretion in favour of Pioneer KK: Pioneer KK has had a sufficient length of time to use the Pioneer KK marks, since 1985 and 1998 respectively, and there is no evidence of any present intention on the part of Pioneer KK to expand its products within the removal goods or the removal services. It is not in the public interest, nor is it reasonable, that a trade mark owner should be permitted to "hoard" trade marks for goods and services that it has not used and has no present plans to use. Pioneer KK's business is specifically in the field of audio and audio-visual products, particularly for entertainment, as evidenced by the slogan. It is not in the business of manufacturing IT equipment, apart from the one period between 1985 and 1987 when Pioneer KK manufactured the Palcom computer. It does not manufacture computer products. It exited that market. The legitimate interests of Pioneer KK as the trade mark owner are protected by s 120(2) and s 120(3) of the Act with respect to the tests for infringement of the registered marks. They are also protected by the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). To maintain trade mark registrations for unused goods and services would be to substitute the rights properly given under ss 120(2) and 120(3) with that provided in s 120(1). Pioneer Computers has used the name "PIONEER" as part of its corporate name and as its trade mark in relation to computers, particularly personal computers, notebook computers and servers, for 10 years. The retention of the removal goods and removal services on the Register would empower Pioneer KK to take action against Pioneer Computers in circumstances where it does not have a legitimate interest to protect because there is no use in relation to the removal goods or the removal services. It is misleading to the public to maintain a registration in respect of goods and services that are not used by Pioneer KK under the Pioneer KK marks. The parties have co-existed for 10 years without any apparent confusion in the marketplace. There has been little demonstrated confusion to date and any future confusion is readily able to be remedied as it has been in the past. Pioneer Australia has known of Pioneer Computers and its business from about 1996, giving rise to an inference that Pioneer KK does not consider Pioneer Computers' business as relevantly within or impacting upon Pioneer KK's business. How should the discretion be exercised?

Approximately 50% of Pioneer Computers' annual turnover is from sales to governments and their departments through its Government, Education and Corporate Division. It has been an Australian Government Endorsed Supplier since 1999. It has substantial contracts with State governments and all computer equipment that has been supplied to those governments has, since 1999, been supplied under or by reference to the trade mark PIONEER. The support and servicing of personal computers, notebooks and servers, and the provision of on-site training and service has, since 1998, been provided through Pioneer Computers' Service Division, predominantly for PIONEER branded built-to-order computers under warranty.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schutz-Werke GmbH &amp; Co KG v Forecast &amp; Trading Pty Ltd (1998) 44 IPR 209</tocase>
<text>Regulation 9.1 provides for the declaration to state that an inquiry has been made and to set out the findings of the inquiry. It does not provide for proof even at a prima facie level of the case to be made. The onus for showing intention and/or use once an application for removal is made shifts to the trade mark owner, who is required to rebut the allegation (s 100 of the Act). There is no requirement that the statutory declaration prove the alleged non-use or satisfy any evidentiary onus. The application and supporting statutory declaration need only ' mirror the statutory provisions ' ( Shanahan at [15.25] citing Schutz-Werke GmbH &amp; Co KG v Forecast &amp; Trading Pty Ltd (1998) 44 IPR 209). Neither the Act nor the Regulations require that within those documents, an applicant for removal must establish sufficient interest in the non-use application or prove its case.

Pioneer KK did not raise any issue concerning the validity of the applications or compliance with Regulation 9.1 before the Registrar. Pioneer Computers submits that as a matter of discretion Pioneer KK should not be permitted to rely upon any such defect in this application to the Court which is an appeal from the Registrar's decision. Pioneer KK points out that it is not a question of discretion but of mandatory compliance: s 92(2)(a) provides that an application must be in accordance with the Regulations and this application represents both the initiating process before the Registrar and before the Court.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Settef SpA v Riv-Oland Marble Co (Vic) Pty Ltd (1987) 10 IPR 402</tocase>
<text>Pioneer KK emphasises that it only needs to show some use of the removal goods during the relevant period to maintain its registration. The fact that use of the mark may have been discontinued in relation to some goods after that time cannot, it submits, be relevant to the present application. Further, Pioneer KK points out that it does not need to prove significant sales of goods or provision of services during the relevant period. One sale of each type of good would be sufficient, providing that sale or use of the mark is bona fide and not de minimis ( Settef SpA v Riv-Oland Marble Co (Vic) Pty Ltd (1987) 10 IPR 402 at 437). The characterisation of the goods sold by Pioneer KK

Pioneer Australia is and has been a market leader in optical drives in Australia. Purchasers of its products included consumers, businesses and government organisations. Pioneer Australia has provided end-user support for its optical drive products.

It is common ground that Pioneer KK is a manufacturer of audio and audio-visual equipment including radios, televisions, amplifiers and sound recording and reproducing equipment including car stereo head units, speakers, amplifiers and sub-woofers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Rohm and Haas Company [1948] HCA 27 ; (1949) 78 CLR 601</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1948/27.html</AustLII>
<text>The Explanatory Memorandum does not really assist. Section 101(4) makes it clear that it has been inserted without any attempt to limit or qualify the discretion provided for in s 101(3). The Explanatory Memorandum itself speaks of "clarification". This can either recognise that s 101(4) expands the discretion or that it simply makes it clear which factors could already be taken into account under s 101(3). In my view, use of a trade mark on closely related goods or services could already be taken into account in exercising the discretion under s 101(3) in the unamended section. As I read s 101(3) , the discretion to be exercised is not limited. For the purposes of s 101(3) , account may be taken of use of the trade mark on closely related goods or services, even in cases commencing prior to the introduction of s 101(4). This has particular relevance in the case of goods that are at the forefront of technological change. Justice Dixon (as he then was) said in The Shell Company of Australia Limited v Rohm and Haas Company [1948] HCA 27 ; (1949) 78 CLR 601 at 627 that the basis of a claim to proprietorship in a trade mark so far unused is found in the combined effect of authorship of the mark, the intention to use it on or in connection with the goods and the application for registration. In Magnavox , the Assistant Registrar considered a mark which had not been used across the scope of the goods claimed. In coming to a conclusion as to use across a class of goods, I agree with the Assistant Registrar (at 2078) that ' the rights arising from the registration of a trade mark should not be confined to the stage of technological development of goods specified when the mark was registered '. The relevant date for the exercise of the discretion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Totev v Sfar [2008] FCAFC 35 ; (2008) 167 FCR 193</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/35.html</AustLII>
<text>An appeal from a decision of the Registrar of Trade Marks is in the Court's original jurisdiction. None of the powers of the Court under s 197 of the Act affect the s 92 application, which goes to the jurisdiction of the Court to hear and determine an application for removal of a trade mark. The hearing is a "hearing de novo" where the judge reviewing the decision of the Registrar begins afresh and exercises any discretion exercised by the Registrar. The parties may adduce evidence as provided for in s 197 of the Act which evidence may include evidence not before the Registrar (see discussion in Totev v Sfar [2008] FCAFC 35 ; (2008) 167 FCR 193 by Emmett J at [12] and [13]; Blount at 59).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Unilever Australia Ltd v Karounos (2001) 113 FCR 322</tocase>
<text>Further, in the demand, Pioneer KK sought generally to prevent Pioneer Computers from any use of the mark PIONEER and demanded a complete cessation of the use by Pioneer Computers of any mark which is substantially identical with or deceptively similar to "the Pioneer Trade Mark". The allegation of infringement of Pioneer KK's registered marks was general and not restricted to the removal goods and the removal services. A general allegation was sufficient in New South Wales Dairy Corporation v Murray Goulburn Co-operative Company (1989) 14 IPR 75 for Gummow J (at 77) and in Unilever Australia Ltd v Karounos (2001) 113 FCR 322 for Hill J (at [35]) to find that the recipient of the allegation was a person aggrieved in respect of all of the goods/classes for which the relevant trade marks were registered.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>