<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Parkin v O'Sullivan [2009] FCA 1096 (30 September 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1096.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Alister v The Queen (1984) 154 CLR 404</tocase>
<text>In Commonwealth v Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; (1993) 176 CLR 604 , a public interest immunity case about documents recording cabinet deliberations, the Court said at 620: 
 
 There was, therefore, no call for Jenkinson J to order that the documents be produced for inspection. But we would add that, even if there had been, the procedure of ordering production of documents for inspection by the legal representatives of one of the parties, even upon a restricted basis, before the claim for immunity had been decided by the court, was open to serious question. Whatever the safeguards, it represents an encroachment upon the confidentiality claimed for the documents. And in this case, public interest in their immunity from disclosure was of the highest order. If inspection of documents is necessary to determine the question of immunity (and in this case it was not) then it ought to be carried out by the court before ordering production for inspection by a party. No doubt this may in some cases cast a heavy burden on the court, but it is unavoidable if confidentiality is to be maintained until a claim for immunity is determined. 
 

 
See also Alister v The Queen (1984) 154 CLR 404 at 469 and Gypsy Jokers Inc v Commissioner of Police (WA) [2008] HCA 4 ; (2008) 234 CLR 532 at [180] and [185] per Crennan J.

Northern Land Council and Alister concerned inspection by the court of the documents over which privilege was claimed. In Gypsy Jokers Crennan J spoke more broadly of "information in documents", "certain material relied on for determination of a proceeding" and "confidential material before a court", which was not revealed to a party seeking it. In The Queen v Bebic (unreported, 27 May 1982) the Court of Criminal Appeal of New South Wales dealt specifically with the disclosure of the contents of an affidavit tendered in support of a public interest immunity claim. There Samuels JA, Nagle CJ at CL and Cantor J said at 4: 
 
 Mr Mason tendered an affidavit in support of his claim for privilege. He submitted, however, that the affidavit should not be placed on the file, that is to say that it should be read only by the Court and not disclosed to the party calling, on the footing that the contents of the affidavit would or might themselves compromise the claims for privilege. 
 

 
 
 We had and still have some doubts about the propriety of restricting the affidavit in the way proposed. However, it may well be that that course is, in certain cases, of which this is one, no more than a logical extension of the established practice of the Courts inspecting the allegedly privileged documents itself. 
 

 
Later at 5, after saying that the Court had read both documents in question and the affidavit in support of the claim for privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 It seems to us that granted that it is now commonplace for judges to make a private inspection of documents in order to resolve a claim for privilege ..., it follows that in a proper case the judge may similarly keep to himself the affidavit by which the claim is supported. 
 

 
The Court then ordered that the affidavit remain sealed up with the papers on the ground that to disclose its contents might prejudice the claim for privilege.

I have referred in connection with the respondent's affidavit to the great importance that is attached to the respondent's opinion as to the damage to national security incident upon disclosure. Obviously that is also the case in relation to the disclosure of the documents over which privilege is claimed. I have summarised the respondent's reasons for his opinion about the possible effects of disclosure of the documents in question. This is all derived from the open parts of his affidavit. The Final Appreciations and related briefing notes set out the reasoning process that underlies the making of security assessments, which are the key mechanism by which ASIO advises government that particular individuals pose a threat to national security. If documents falling within this class were required to be produced, ASIO would be giving information about its knowledge, assessments and methodology to the very people to whom it is most important that national security information is not disclosed: cf Alister 154 CLR at 454-455 per Brennan J. As the respondent has deposed, the relevant class is "one of the classes of documents held by ASIO that require the greatest level of protection" first, because of the inherent sensitivity of the information that is routinely contained in such documents, and second, because of the detrimental consequences in terms of the quality of decision-making that would be likely to follow if ASIO officers were forced to omit particular kinds of information from Final Appreciations and related briefing notes due to the risk that those documents will become available to persons the subject of security assessments.

The applicants contended that the respondent was not able to make a class claim. It was said that he seeks to describe as a class claim documents which he considers constitutes a Final Appreciation and documents related thereto. That description, they say, does not constitute an identifiable class. The table in the affidavit (set out at [9]) refers to an internal email, an internal minute and a briefing note. It does not refer to any Final Appreciation. By way of contrast, the applicants assert that Cabinet documents constitute a clear class claim. Here they say the so-called class claim involves the respondent asserting for himself that particular documents constitute Final Appreciations.

I do not think that is a fair description of the respondent's claim. The presently relevant parts of his affidavit are as follows: 
(a) shortly after identifying the documents in the table at [9] he describes them on a class basis as "paradigm examples of documents that ASIO should not be required to disclose save in exceptional circumstances";
 
(b) the results of complex security assessments are usually contained in a Final Appreciation document, though it may not be headed in that way;
 
(c) the Final Appreciation ordinarily takes the form of an ASIO minute;
 
(d) when the investigative branch assesses an individual to be a threat to Australia's national security, the respondent is advised, usually by a DGBN;
 
(e) often both a DGBN and a Final Appreciation are provided to the respondent for decision;
 
(f) it is the document on which a security assessment is based, being the Final Appreciation (however that document is headed) and any associated DGBN that cannot be disclosed;
 
(g) the class claim advanced concerns the class of documents shortly described as "Final Appreciation documents and related briefing notes";
 
(h) documents in this class invariably contain specific detail as to why persons are assessed as a risk to national security, and specific details of intelligence sources and methods;
 
(i) the respondent has examined the ASIO documents, namely those in the table (the class claim) and the contents claim documents; and
 
(j) the disclosure of the documents in (i) would prejudice Australia's national security for the reasons stated in the affidavit.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Carr v Finance Corporation of Australia Ltd (No 1) [1981] HCA 20 ; (1981) 147 CLR 246</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/20.html</AustLII>
<text>Five weeks after I had reserved my decision the applicants' counsel submitted a memorandum drawing my attention to a recent decision of the House of Lords in Secretary of State for the Home Department v AF (No 3) [2009] 3 WLR 74. No leave was sought to file additional material, no prior notice was given to the respondent, and the respondent submits that I should not receive the memorandum. On many occasions the High Court has said that the hearing is the time and place to present arguments, and has explained why unauthorised post-hearing submissions will generally not be received. See for example Carr v Finance Corporation of Australia Ltd (No 1) [1981] HCA 20 ; (1981) 147 CLR 246 at 258, Eastman v Director of Public Prosecutions (ACT) [2003] HCA 28 ; (2003) 214 CLR 318 at [27] - [31] and Re Chief Commissioner of Police (Vic) (2005) 214 ALR 522 at [22].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Church of Scientology v Woodward [1982] HCA 78 ; (1980) 154 CLR 25</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/78.html</AustLII>
<text>The next question is whether the respondent's public interest immunity claims should be upheld. In Church of Scientology v Woodward [1982] HCA 78 ; (1980) 154 CLR 25 at 76 Brennan J said: 
 
 Discovery would not be given against the Director-General [of Security] save in a most exceptional case. The secrecy of the work of an intelligence organization which is to counter espionage, sabotage, etc. is essential to national security, and the public interest in national security will seldom yield to the public interest in the administration of civil justice ... 
 

 
 
 ... the veil of secrecy is not absolutely impenetrable ... But the veil is not penetrated merely by a plaintiff's deposition that he is not a security risk. That, after all, may be the very matter which is under investigation. 
 

 
See also Leghaei v Director-General of Security [2007] FCAFC at [52] and R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC at [31]-[32].

In seeking to establish an exceptional case the applicants' point out that they may be unable to make out their cases if the claim to immunity is upheld. The authorities establish that this consequence of the outcome of the process of balancing public interest immunity against the public interest, upon which the applicants rely, of having conventional access to evidentiary material, is not exceptional. Thus in the Scientology case at 76-77 Brennan J referred to the obstacles in a plaintiff's path in judicial review proceedings against the Director-General arising out of the restrictions imposed upon discovery in aid of proving what is and is not relevant to security. In the same case at 61 Mason J noted that a successful claim for privilege may exclude from consideration the very material on which a plaintiff hopes to base his argument. These observations of Mason J were quoted with approval by Gummow, Hayne, Heydon and Keifel JJ in Gypsy Jokers Inc 234 CLR at [24]. In that case at [5] Gleeson CJ said that the consequence of success of a claim for public interest immunity against disclosure of information is that the information is not available as evidence to be taken into account in deciding the outcome of judicial review proceedings. The Court would not be able to have regard to some, or perhaps any, of the information on which a public official's belief was based.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth v Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; (1993) 176 CLR 604</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/24.html</AustLII>
<text>In Commonwealth v Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; (1993) 176 CLR 604 , a public interest immunity case about documents recording cabinet deliberations, the Court said at 620: 
 
 There was, therefore, no call for Jenkinson J to order that the documents be produced for inspection. But we would add that, even if there had been, the procedure of ordering production of documents for inspection by the legal representatives of one of the parties, even upon a restricted basis, before the claim for immunity had been decided by the court, was open to serious question. Whatever the safeguards, it represents an encroachment upon the confidentiality claimed for the documents. And in this case, public interest in their immunity from disclosure was of the highest order. If inspection of documents is necessary to determine the question of immunity (and in this case it was not) then it ought to be carried out by the court before ordering production for inspection by a party. No doubt this may in some cases cast a heavy burden on the court, but it is unavoidable if confidentiality is to be maintained until a claim for immunity is determined. 
 

 
See also Alister v The Queen (1984) 154 CLR 404 at 469 and Gypsy Jokers Inc v Commissioner of Police (WA) [2008] HCA 4 ; (2008) 234 CLR 532 at [180] and [185] per Crennan J.

Northern Land Council and Alister concerned inspection by the court of the documents over which privilege was claimed. In Gypsy Jokers Crennan J spoke more broadly of "information in documents", "certain material relied on for determination of a proceeding" and "confidential material before a court", which was not revealed to a party seeking it. In The Queen v Bebic (unreported, 27 May 1982) the Court of Criminal Appeal of New South Wales dealt specifically with the disclosure of the contents of an affidavit tendered in support of a public interest immunity claim. There Samuels JA, Nagle CJ at CL and Cantor J said at 4: 
 
 Mr Mason tendered an affidavit in support of his claim for privilege. He submitted, however, that the affidavit should not be placed on the file, that is to say that it should be read only by the Court and not disclosed to the party calling, on the footing that the contents of the affidavit would or might themselves compromise the claims for privilege. 
 

 
 
 We had and still have some doubts about the propriety of restricting the affidavit in the way proposed. However, it may well be that that course is, in certain cases, of which this is one, no more than a logical extension of the established practice of the Courts inspecting the allegedly privileged documents itself. 
 

 
Later at 5, after saying that the Court had read both documents in question and the affidavit in support of the claim for privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 It seems to us that granted that it is now commonplace for judges to make a private inspection of documents in order to resolve a claim for privilege ..., it follows that in a proper case the judge may similarly keep to himself the affidavit by which the claim is supported. 
 

 
The Court then ordered that the affidavit remain sealed up with the papers on the ground that to disclose its contents might prejudice the claim for privilege.

I was uncertain about the status of the "ASIO internal email dated 7 September 2005 (re: Parkin)", and called for the documents in order to determine whether it fell within the class claimed. I did this in reliance on what had been said in Northern Land Council 176 CLR at 617: 
 
 In many so-called "class" cases a court may find it necessary to consider a document, inspecting it if necessary, in order to determine whether it does in truth fall into a class which attracts immunity.

Having inspected the documents, my inference as to the Internal Minutes and Briefing Notes was confirmed. Each Internal Minute fits the description given by the respondent of a Final Appreciation. Each Briefing Note accords with his description of a DGBN. The "ASIO internal email dated 7 September 2005 (re: Parkin)" is a covering note transmitting the Internal Minute to the respondent. It contains a brief summary of the Internal Minute. It fits the respondent's description recorded at [21] that "Final Appreciation documents, and summaries thereof , are documents the disclosure of which is very likely to damage Australia's national security" (emphasis added).

On the basis of the material in the respondent's affidavit, aided by my inspection of the documents, it is clear to me that the matters relied on by the applicants do not outweigh the public interest identified by the respondent.

The contrast asserted by the applicants between Cabinet documents ('a clear class claim') and the respondent's description here (see [34]) is not helpful. That is because of the range of documents, with different levels of Cabinet connection, that may fall within the description but not necessarily qualify for immunity. At the top of the chain will be the Cabinet minutes considered in Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; 176 CLR 604. Lower down will be documents and communications between a Minster and the head of department relating to cabinet proceedings and material prepared for cabinet. Further down the chain are documents relating to the formation of government policy at a high level. Then will come other documents concerned with policy making including minutes by junior officials and correspondence with outside bodies. See S ankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1 at 39. In Conway v Rimmer [1968] UKHL 2 ; [1968] AC 910 at 952 Lord Reid said of this last-mentioned category "I do not think that it is possible to limit such documents by any definition".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Conway v Rimmer [1968] UKHL 2 ; [1968] AC 910</tocase>
<text>The contrast asserted by the applicants between Cabinet documents ('a clear class claim') and the respondent's description here (see [34]) is not helpful. That is because of the range of documents, with different levels of Cabinet connection, that may fall within the description but not necessarily qualify for immunity. At the top of the chain will be the Cabinet minutes considered in Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; 176 CLR 604. Lower down will be documents and communications between a Minster and the head of department relating to cabinet proceedings and material prepared for cabinet. Further down the chain are documents relating to the formation of government policy at a high level. Then will come other documents concerned with policy making including minutes by junior officials and correspondence with outside bodies. See S ankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1 at 39. In Conway v Rimmer [1968] UKHL 2 ; [1968] AC 910 at 952 Lord Reid said of this last-mentioned category "I do not think that it is possible to limit such documents by any definition".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dodds v The Queen [2009] NSWCCA 78</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCCA/2009/78.html</AustLII>
<text>In more recent cases it appears to have become a matter of course for "confidential" affidavits supporting public interest immunity claims to be restricted to the judge. See, for example, R v Smith (1996) 86 A Crim R 308 at 310, Dodds v The Queen [2009] NSWCCA 78 at [55] and R v Meissner (1994) 76 A Crim R 81 at 85.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Eastman v Director of Public Prosecutions (ACT) [2003] HCA 28 ; (2003) 214 CLR 318</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/28.html</AustLII>
<text>Five weeks after I had reserved my decision the applicants' counsel submitted a memorandum drawing my attention to a recent decision of the House of Lords in Secretary of State for the Home Department v AF (No 3) [2009] 3 WLR 74. No leave was sought to file additional material, no prior notice was given to the respondent, and the respondent submits that I should not receive the memorandum. On many occasions the High Court has said that the hearing is the time and place to present arguments, and has explained why unauthorised post-hearing submissions will generally not be received. See for example Carr v Finance Corporation of Australia Ltd (No 1) [1981] HCA 20 ; (1981) 147 CLR 246 at 258, Eastman v Director of Public Prosecutions (ACT) [2003] HCA 28 ; (2003) 214 CLR 318 at [27] - [31] and Re Chief Commissioner of Police (Vic) (2005) 214 ALR 522 at [22].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gypsy Jokers Inc v Commissioner of Police (WA) [2008] HCA 4 ; (2008) 234 CLR 532</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/4.html</AustLII>
<text>In Commonwealth v Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; (1993) 176 CLR 604 , a public interest immunity case about documents recording cabinet deliberations, the Court said at 620: 
 
 There was, therefore, no call for Jenkinson J to order that the documents be produced for inspection. But we would add that, even if there had been, the procedure of ordering production of documents for inspection by the legal representatives of one of the parties, even upon a restricted basis, before the claim for immunity had been decided by the court, was open to serious question. Whatever the safeguards, it represents an encroachment upon the confidentiality claimed for the documents. And in this case, public interest in their immunity from disclosure was of the highest order. If inspection of documents is necessary to determine the question of immunity (and in this case it was not) then it ought to be carried out by the court before ordering production for inspection by a party. No doubt this may in some cases cast a heavy burden on the court, but it is unavoidable if confidentiality is to be maintained until a claim for immunity is determined. 
 

 
See also Alister v The Queen (1984) 154 CLR 404 at 469 and Gypsy Jokers Inc v Commissioner of Police (WA) [2008] HCA 4 ; (2008) 234 CLR 532 at [180] and [185] per Crennan J.

Northern Land Council and Alister concerned inspection by the court of the documents over which privilege was claimed. In Gypsy Jokers Crennan J spoke more broadly of "information in documents", "certain material relied on for determination of a proceeding" and "confidential material before a court", which was not revealed to a party seeking it. In The Queen v Bebic (unreported, 27 May 1982) the Court of Criminal Appeal of New South Wales dealt specifically with the disclosure of the contents of an affidavit tendered in support of a public interest immunity claim. There Samuels JA, Nagle CJ at CL and Cantor J said at 4: 
 
 Mr Mason tendered an affidavit in support of his claim for privilege. He submitted, however, that the affidavit should not be placed on the file, that is to say that it should be read only by the Court and not disclosed to the party calling, on the footing that the contents of the affidavit would or might themselves compromise the claims for privilege. 
 

 
 
 We had and still have some doubts about the propriety of restricting the affidavit in the way proposed. However, it may well be that that course is, in certain cases, of which this is one, no more than a logical extension of the established practice of the Courts inspecting the allegedly privileged documents itself. 
 

 
Later at 5, after saying that the Court had read both documents in question and the affidavit in support of the claim for privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 It seems to us that granted that it is now commonplace for judges to make a private inspection of documents in order to resolve a claim for privilege ..., it follows that in a proper case the judge may similarly keep to himself the affidavit by which the claim is supported. 
 

 
The Court then ordered that the affidavit remain sealed up with the papers on the ground that to disclose its contents might prejudice the claim for privilege.

In seeking to establish an exceptional case the applicants' point out that they may be unable to make out their cases if the claim to immunity is upheld. The authorities establish that this consequence of the outcome of the process of balancing public interest immunity against the public interest, upon which the applicants rely, of having conventional access to evidentiary material, is not exceptional. Thus in the Scientology case at 76-77 Brennan J referred to the obstacles in a plaintiff's path in judicial review proceedings against the Director-General arising out of the restrictions imposed upon discovery in aid of proving what is and is not relevant to security. In the same case at 61 Mason J noted that a successful claim for privilege may exclude from consideration the very material on which a plaintiff hopes to base his argument. These observations of Mason J were quoted with approval by Gummow, Hayne, Heydon and Keifel JJ in Gypsy Jokers Inc 234 CLR at [24]. In that case at [5] Gleeson CJ said that the consequence of success of a claim for public interest immunity against disclosure of information is that the information is not available as evidence to be taken into account in deciding the outcome of judicial review proceedings. The Court would not be able to have regard to some, or perhaps any, of the information on which a public official's belief was based.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Haj-Ismail v Minister for Immigration Multicultural and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1982) 45 ALR 379</tocase>
<text>The same approach was taken by Lockhart J in Haj-Ismail v Minister for Immigration Multicultural and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1982) 45 ALR 379 at 389 in relation to a statement of reasons signed by the Acting Attorney-General disclosing the grounds for his objection to the production of documents for national security reasons. His Honour said, following Bebic : 
 
 Initially I had some doubt about the propriety of restricting the disclosure of the very grounds themselves in the way proposed by the Acting Attorney-General; but it is really only another facet of the established practice whereby the courts may themselves inspect documents where objection is taken to their production. 
 

 
See also R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC 1061.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Leghaei v Director-General of Security [2007] FCAFC 56</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/56.html</AustLII>
<text>Having carefully studied the redacted parts of the respondent's affidavit I have concluded that they should not be made available to the applicants' legal advisers, even on the giving of appropriate undertakings. There are many cases that establish that courts should attach very considerable weight to the view of what national security requires as is expressed by the responsible officer. See for example Leghaei v Director-General of Security [2007] FCAFC 56 at [56] - [58] , [62]. Although usually expressed in connection with the inspection of protected documents themselves, those observations apply also to an affidavit, such as that sworn in this case, which supplies the reasons for the claim to privilege. In the open part of his affidavit the respondent says that the disclosure of the redacted portions of his affidavit would be likely to prejudice national security. In the balance of the affidavit, in particular the redacted parts, he explains the basis for his opinion. Having read those parts, I am satisfied that the opinion is soundly based. Accordingly, the respondent may rely on his affidavit in support of his public interest claim without providing to the applicants' legal representatives the redacted parts thereof.

The next question is whether the respondent's public interest immunity claims should be upheld. In Church of Scientology v Woodward [1982] HCA 78 ; (1980) 154 CLR 25 at 76 Brennan J said: 
 
 Discovery would not be given against the Director-General [of Security] save in a most exceptional case. The secrecy of the work of an intelligence organization which is to counter espionage, sabotage, etc. is essential to national security, and the public interest in national security will seldom yield to the public interest in the administration of civil justice ... 
 

 
 
 ... the veil of secrecy is not absolutely impenetrable ... But the veil is not penetrated merely by a plaintiff's deposition that he is not a security risk. That, after all, may be the very matter which is under investigation. 
 

 
See also Leghaei v Director-General of Security [2007] FCAFC at [52] and R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC at [31]-[32].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC 1061</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2006/1061.html</AustLII>
<text>The same approach was taken by Lockhart J in Haj-Ismail v Minister for Immigration Multicultural and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1982) 45 ALR 379 at 389 in relation to a statement of reasons signed by the Acting Attorney-General disclosing the grounds for his objection to the production of documents for national security reasons. His Honour said, following Bebic : 
 
 Initially I had some doubt about the propriety of restricting the disclosure of the very grounds themselves in the way proposed by the Acting Attorney-General; but it is really only another facet of the established practice whereby the courts may themselves inspect documents where objection is taken to their production. 
 

 
See also R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC 1061.

The next question is whether the respondent's public interest immunity claims should be upheld. In Church of Scientology v Woodward [1982] HCA 78 ; (1980) 154 CLR 25 at 76 Brennan J said: 
 
 Discovery would not be given against the Director-General [of Security] save in a most exceptional case. The secrecy of the work of an intelligence organization which is to counter espionage, sabotage, etc. is essential to national security, and the public interest in national security will seldom yield to the public interest in the administration of civil justice ... 
 

 
 
 ... the veil of secrecy is not absolutely impenetrable ... But the veil is not penetrated merely by a plaintiff's deposition that he is not a security risk. That, after all, may be the very matter which is under investigation. 
 

 
See also Leghaei v Director-General of Security [2007] FCAFC at [52] and R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC at [31]-[32].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Meissner (1994) 76 A Crim R 81</tocase>
<text>In more recent cases it appears to have become a matter of course for "confidential" affidavits supporting public interest immunity claims to be restricted to the judge. See, for example, R v Smith (1996) 86 A Crim R 308 at 310, Dodds v The Queen [2009] NSWCCA 78 at [55] and R v Meissner (1994) 76 A Crim R 81 at 85.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Smith (1996) 86 A Crim R 308</tocase>
<text>In more recent cases it appears to have become a matter of course for "confidential" affidavits supporting public interest immunity claims to be restricted to the judge. See, for example, R v Smith (1996) 86 A Crim R 308 at 310, Dodds v The Queen [2009] NSWCCA 78 at [55] and R v Meissner (1994) 76 A Crim R 81 at 85.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Chief Commissioner of Police (Vic) (2005) 214 ALR 522</tocase>
<text>Five weeks after I had reserved my decision the applicants' counsel submitted a memorandum drawing my attention to a recent decision of the House of Lords in Secretary of State for the Home Department v AF (No 3) [2009] 3 WLR 74. No leave was sought to file additional material, no prior notice was given to the respondent, and the respondent submits that I should not receive the memorandum. On many occasions the High Court has said that the hearing is the time and place to present arguments, and has explained why unauthorised post-hearing submissions will generally not be received. See for example Carr v Finance Corporation of Australia Ltd (No 1) [1981] HCA 20 ; (1981) 147 CLR 246 at 258, Eastman v Director of Public Prosecutions (ACT) [2003] HCA 28 ; (2003) 214 CLR 318 at [27] - [31] and Re Chief Commissioner of Police (Vic) (2005) 214 ALR 522 at [22].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/43.html</AustLII>
<text>The contrast asserted by the applicants between Cabinet documents ('a clear class claim') and the respondent's description here (see [34]) is not helpful. That is because of the range of documents, with different levels of Cabinet connection, that may fall within the description but not necessarily qualify for immunity. At the top of the chain will be the Cabinet minutes considered in Northern Land Council [1993] HCA 24 ; 176 CLR 604. Lower down will be documents and communications between a Minster and the head of department relating to cabinet proceedings and material prepared for cabinet. Further down the chain are documents relating to the formation of government policy at a high level. Then will come other documents concerned with policy making including minutes by junior officials and correspondence with outside bodies. See S ankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1 at 39. In Conway v Rimmer [1968] UKHL 2 ; [1968] AC 910 at 952 Lord Reid said of this last-mentioned category "I do not think that it is possible to limit such documents by any definition".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Secretary of State for the Home Department v AF [2009] UKHL 29</tocase>
<text>Five weeks after I had reserved my decision the applicants' counsel submitted a memorandum drawing my attention to a recent decision of the House of Lords in Secretary of State for the Home Department v AF (No 3) [2009] 3 WLR 74. No leave was sought to file additional material, no prior notice was given to the respondent, and the respondent submits that I should not receive the memorandum. On many occasions the High Court has said that the hearing is the time and place to present arguments, and has explained why unauthorised post-hearing submissions will generally not be received. See for example Carr v Finance Corporation of Australia Ltd (No 1) [1981] HCA 20 ; (1981) 147 CLR 246 at 258, Eastman v Director of Public Prosecutions (ACT) [2003] HCA 28 ; (2003) 214 CLR 318 at [27] - [31] and Re Chief Commissioner of Police (Vic) (2005) 214 ALR 522 at [22].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>The Queen v Bebic (unreported, 27 May 1982) the Court of Criminal Appeal of New South Wales</tocase>
<text>Northern Land Council and Alister concerned inspection by the court of the documents over which privilege was claimed. In Gypsy Jokers Crennan J spoke more broadly of "information in documents", "certain material relied on for determination of a proceeding" and "confidential material before a court", which was not revealed to a party seeking it. In The Queen v Bebic (unreported, 27 May 1982) the Court of Criminal Appeal of New South Wales dealt specifically with the disclosure of the contents of an affidavit tendered in support of a public interest immunity claim. There Samuels JA, Nagle CJ at CL and Cantor J said at 4: 
 
 Mr Mason tendered an affidavit in support of his claim for privilege. He submitted, however, that the affidavit should not be placed on the file, that is to say that it should be read only by the Court and not disclosed to the party calling, on the footing that the contents of the affidavit would or might themselves compromise the claims for privilege. 
 

 
 
 We had and still have some doubts about the propriety of restricting the affidavit in the way proposed. However, it may well be that that course is, in certain cases, of which this is one, no more than a logical extension of the established practice of the Courts inspecting the allegedly privileged documents itself. 
 

 
Later at 5, after saying that the Court had read both documents in question and the affidavit in support of the claim for privilege, their Honours said:
 
 
 It seems to us that granted that it is now commonplace for judges to make a private inspection of documents in order to resolve a claim for privilege ..., it follows that in a proper case the judge may similarly keep to himself the affidavit by which the claim is supported. 
 

 
The Court then ordered that the affidavit remain sealed up with the papers on the ground that to disclose its contents might prejudice the claim for privilege.

The same approach was taken by Lockhart J in Haj-Ismail v Minister for Immigration Multicultural and Ethnic Affairs (No 2) (1982) 45 ALR 379 at 389 in relation to a statement of reasons signed by the Acting Attorney-General disclosing the grounds for his objection to the production of documents for national security reasons. His Honour said, following Bebic : 
 
 Initially I had some doubt about the propriety of restricting the disclosure of the very grounds themselves in the way proposed by the Acting Attorney-General; but it is really only another facet of the established practice whereby the courts may themselves inspect documents where objection is taken to their production. 
 

 
See also R v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC 1061.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Traljesic v Attorney-General (Cth) [2006] FCA 125 ; (2006) 150 FCR 199</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/125.html</AustLII>
<text>In some of the cases considered above, reference is made to disclosure of confidential information to legal advisers subject to appropriate undertakings. Such undertakings were offered in the present case. There are many cases in which access has been denied to legal advisers who have offered undertakings on the ground that the risk to national security flowing from inadvertent disclosure is simply too high. There is an elaborate discussion of this risk in Regina v Khazaal [2006] NSWSC at [31]-[39]. See also Traljesic v Attorney-General (Cth) [2006] FCA 125 ; (2006) 150 FCR 199 at [22] - [23] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>