<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268 (9 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1268.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/27.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 31A empowers the Court to award summary judgment in relation to a proceeding if satisfied that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of prosecuting it. The basis of the respondent Secretary's resort to s 31A is the contention that the applicant has not identified any question of law such as would enliven the Court's jurisdiction under s 44 of the AAT Act. Given that an appeal lies "on a question of law" only and not on a question of fact or of mixed law and fact: see Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 at [11] - [17] the issues before me are whether such a question has been raised by Mr Kronen and whether his argument thereon is sufficiently strong to warrant the matter going to trial: Vranic v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 672.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vranic v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 672 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/672.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 31A empowers the Court to award summary judgment in relation to a proceeding if satisfied that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of prosecuting it. The basis of the respondent Secretary's resort to s 31A is the contention that the applicant has not identified any question of law such as would enliven the Court's jurisdiction under s 44 of the AAT Act. Given that an appeal lies "on a question of law" only and not on a question of fact or of mixed law and fact: see Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 at [11] - [17] the issues before me are whether such a question has been raised by Mr Kronen and whether his argument thereon is sufficiently strong to warrant the matter going to trial: Vranic v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 672.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Waterford v The Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/25.html</AustLII>
<text>These in turn were enlarged upon in Mr Kronen's written submissions. These revealed that much of his complaint was with matters of fact involving merits-review. He is now aware that a wrong fact finding is not sufficient to establish an error of law: Waterford v The Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77. Nonetheless, the submissions also exposed that he was taking issue with the manner in which the Tribunal purported to apply the statute to the circumstances. In this one can discern that in several respects he was contending that the Tribunal fell into an error of law which caused it to identify a wrong issue, to ask itself a wrong question, and to ignore relevant material, so exceeding its authority or powers: Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163 at 179. The essence of his complaints are both that the Tribunal failed to apply the correct sections of the Act (eg s 615), and misconstrued or misapplied the terms of the Act (eg "to be negotiated" or "reasonable excuse"). To this extent, as I will indicate, I am satisfied that Mr Kronen's application to this Court has in some degree enlivened its jurisdiction under the AAT Act. Nonetheless, I am satisfied that the proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success and for the reason that in ascribing error to the Tribunal he misapprehends the scheme of the Act and of the decision-making processes it mandates.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/58.html</AustLII>
<text>These in turn were enlarged upon in Mr Kronen's written submissions. These revealed that much of his complaint was with matters of fact involving merits-review. He is now aware that a wrong fact finding is not sufficient to establish an error of law: Waterford v The Commonwealth [1987] HCA 25 ; (1987) 163 CLR 54 at 77. Nonetheless, the submissions also exposed that he was taking issue with the manner in which the Tribunal purported to apply the statute to the circumstances. In this one can discern that in several respects he was contending that the Tribunal fell into an error of law which caused it to identify a wrong issue, to ask itself a wrong question, and to ignore relevant material, so exceeding its authority or powers: Craig v South Australia [1995] HCA 58 ; (1995) 184 CLR 163 at 179. The essence of his complaints are both that the Tribunal failed to apply the correct sections of the Act (eg s 615), and misconstrued or misapplied the terms of the Act (eg "to be negotiated" or "reasonable excuse"). To this extent, as I will indicate, I am satisfied that Mr Kronen's application to this Court has in some degree enlivened its jurisdiction under the AAT Act. Nonetheless, I am satisfied that the proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success and for the reason that in ascribing error to the Tribunal he misapprehends the scheme of the Act and of the decision-making processes it mandates.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280</tocase>
<text>Central to this trio is Mr Kronen's conception of what is signified by the words "to be negotiated" in s 605(3). What is clear is that the level of permissible compromise and of required mutual agreement that this formula might otherwise suggest when used in other contexts, is radically curtailed in this statutory setting. Whether one can say that the ordinary meaning of "negotiate" is what is intended here (albeit what can be negotiated is limited by the Act and its purposes), hence the meaning is a question of fact: Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287 (proposition 2); or that its meaning and hence proper construction is contrived by its legislative settings, hence are questions of law: Pozzolanic , 287 (propositions 1 and 4), what is clear is that Mr Kronen misapprehends the latitude the Act gives him. Elblematic of this was his presenting Maxima with negotiation procedures which included referral to an independent panel if any terms could not be agreed.

If Mr Kronen is to qualify for a newstart allowance, he was required, in the circumstances, enter into an activity agreement: s 593(1)(e); he was required to undertake one or more activities that the Secretary regarded as suitable for the person: s 606(1); the terms of the agreement were to be approved by the Secretary. In this scheme, the "right to negotiate" could be illusory in quite some degree for some purposes and especially when the Secretary (or a delegate) takes decisions or actions in effectuation of the purposes of the Act itself. This is not to say that there was no room for discussion, accommodation and compromise. Rather, it is to recognise that the actual terms of the negotiation itself were something in relation to which the Secretary, acting reasonably and in good faith, could ultimately dictate, approve or disapprove, if there was to be an agreement.

The Tribunal clearly understood this was the case: see Reasons [106]-[108]. It committed no error of law in construing and hence giving legal effect to the "negotiation expectation" of s 605(3) as it did. Further, the Tribunal satisfied itself on the evidence before it that the requirements Maxima sought to impose were reasonable and that those upon which Mr Kronen insisted were unreasonable in the circumstances. These fact findings were open to it and were unimpeachable in this proceeding.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>