<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wright Rubber Products Pty Ltd v Bayer AG (No 2) [2009] FCA 1317 (13 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1317.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Auskay International Manufacturing &amp; Trade Pty Ltd v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1458 ; (2008) 251 ALR 166</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1458.html</AustLII>
<text>In a case such as the present where an applicant alleges the existence of a global market or a market extending beyond the bounds of Australia (but which includes Australia), it is necessary that that market be identified in any pleading. It is a material fact or particular: see Auskay International Manufacturing &amp; Trade Pty Ltd v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1458 ; (2008) 251 ALR 166 at 173. The pleadings must identify the relevant goods or services, the geographic boundaries of the market and those involved in close competition within the market whom it is said have engaged in anti-competitive conduct. A single market will thus be identified, which will include a "market in Australia".

The applicant has pleaded that there is a global market for the supply of rubber chemicals and an Australian market for those products. The particulars refer to the global market and how elements of that market extend to Australia. For example, the particulars sub-joined to paragraph 12 include the information that the "total demand for rubber chemicals in Australia in the Cartel Period was approximately AUD$120 million". That demand was met exclusively by imports, the majority of which were produced elsewhere by the Respondents and one other company. Reliance was also placed, in the particulars subjoined to paragraph 13, to a passage in the Rubber Chemicals World Data Book 2004 which refers to "a single global market". Reference was made to findings by the European Commission, in December 2005, that cartel arrangements involving the respondents and others led, after 1995, to agreed increases of prices on a global and "multi regional" basis.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v April Marketing Services Australia Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2024</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/2024.html</AustLII>
<text>Counsel for the applicant conceded that this part of the applicant's case is pleaded "at a level of generality" but contended that "the best available particulars have been provided and the core allegations are clear". Reliance was placed on the decision of Bennett J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v April Marketing Services Australia Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2024 which was said to be "an analogous ACCC cartel claim." I am not persuaded that the pleadings with which her Honour was concerned in April Marketing were analogous (except perhaps in a very broad sense) with those in the present case. Nonetheless Bennett J's reasons, especially at [48] and [49], do emphasise the need for applicants to be accorded some leeway in pleading cartel cases. She was prepared to allow the applicant to plead conclusions and defer the provision of particulars until after discovery.

Although the relevant pleadings in April Marketing were not set out in her Honour's reasons, there is nothing to suggest that they did no more than paraphrase or adapt relevant statutory provisions.

Due allowance must be made for the fact that the cartel agreements were (it may be assumed) negotiated in secrecy by the representatives of the corporate entities involved. The applicant was, of course, not privy to these discussions and the arrangements to which they gave rise. Despite this, the applicant has been able to draw on a large amount of information which has emerged from foreign proceedings in which regulatory authorities have brought participants in the cartel to account for their conduct. It has been able to prepare the detailed material in Schedule 3 to its amended statement of claim. The particulars of 110 meetings between employees of the relevant companies are itemised in that Schedule. This material includes the relevant dates, participants, locations and the subject matter of each meeting. The existence and inclusion of this material begs the question - if such detailed information is already available to the applicant, why were the pleadings not more specific?

Paragraphs 14 to 17 are central to the pleading. Some modest attempts have been made to improve the drafting since my earlier reasons were published. Nonetheless, the principal deficiencies, earlier identified, remain such that these four paragraphs are embarrassing. They should be struck out. Identification of the Markets</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1976 ; (2008) 253 ALR 89</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1976.html</AustLII>
<text>The law on what constitutes a "market in Australia" is far from settled. One thing that is clear is that a market which is wholly outside Australia is not comprehended by the statutory definition: see Singapore Airlines Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2009) 260 ALR 244 at 254; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1976 ; (2008) 253 ALR 89 at 112. The existence of a global market which extends into the geographic boundaries of Australia does not, on the other hand, preclude a finding that there exists a "market in Australia".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bruce v Odhams Press Ltd [1936] 1 KB 697</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Charlie Carter Pty Ltd v The Shop, Distributive and Allied Employees' Association (WA) (1987) 13 FCR 413</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/70.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dey v Victorian Railways Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/1.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Emirates v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2009] FCA 312 ; (2009) 255 ALR 35</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/312.html</AustLII>
<text>Riverstone does no more than support a general principle that there may, for TPA purposes, exist a market in Australia even though it forms part of a wider international market. Hill J's decision was so understood by Middleton J in Emirates v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2009] FCA 312 ; (2009) 255 ALR 35. His Honour considered the meaning of a "market in Australia" in the context of s 45 of the TPA. Significantly, his Honour held (at 53) that: 
 
 "... the definition of "market in Australia" in s 4E excludes a market that is wholly outside Australia, a conclusion with which I respectfully agree...In my opinion, Hill J in Riverstone Computer Services Pty Ltd v IBM Global Financing Australia Ltd [2002] FCA 1608 ( Riverstone ) was correct in concluding that the fact that a market was global did not signify that there could not be a market in Australia for the same products (or services)".

Emirates and the other authorities to which I have referred make it clear that, simply because a market is global, this does not mean that there could not be a market in Australia for the same products. The applicant's pleading is not, in my view, deficient by reason only that it speaks of the respondents being in competition with each other in the Australian market and throughout the world. There may be a market in Australia which forms part of a wider global market. That will, however, be the case only if the same firms are in close competition with each other to attract customers for their goods in both the global market and the Australian market which forms part of the global market. Unfortunately, the applicant does not plead sufficient material facts for the respondents to know clearly whether the applicant is alleging the existence of a global market (of which a market in Australia forms part) or whether it is alleging the existence of a market in Australia and a global market in which, for example, different or additional firms compete for business. The problem is compounded by the variable and imprecise phraseology to which attention has been drawn in paragraph 28 above.

Although the applicant's most recent attempt to identify a market in Australia has remedied some of the defects in its original statement of claim, further refinement will be necessary before the necessary degree of precision is achieved. Foreign respondents giving effect to the arrangements in Australia

In paragraphs 18 to 25 of the original statement of claim the applicant alleged, in the most general terms, that the foreign respondents gave effect to the cartel arrangements in Australia. There was a notable absence of material facts to establish this part of the applicant's case. In addition, the separate causes of action which needed to be established for the purposes of s 45 (2)(b)(i) and (ii), were rolled up.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HECEC Australia Pty Ltd v Hydro-Electric Corp [1999] FCA 822</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/822.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Johnson Tiles Pty Ltd v Esso Australia Ltd [1999] FCA 569</tocase>
<text>Counsel have drawn attention to further authorities in the course of argument. Most are relevant to particular issues and I will refer to them later in these reasons. There were, however, two passages (among others) of more general application on which counsel for the applicant placed emphasis: In Johnson Tiles Pty Ltd v Esso Australia Ltd [1999] FCA 569, at [12], Merkel J cautioned that pleadings are only a 'means to an end': 
 
 
 "the relief to be granted on a pleadings motion is a matter of discretion (see Brambles Holdings Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1979] FCA 80 ; (1979) 28 ALR 191 at 193). Even if I had acceded to the arguments of Esso to a greater extent than I have in my view the Court's individual docket system of case management and its ability to ensure that the proceeding is conducted in a manner which does not unfairly prejudice any of the parties is such that I would not strike out the pleading. Rather, if complaint is made about any particular aspect being embarrassing or prejudicial the Court has ample power to deal with that aspect so as to avoid prejudice or embarrassment in the course of its management of the case. I am satisfied that the causes of action relied upon have been pleaded in a manner that ensures that Esso understands those causes of action and the substance of the allegations made against Esso . Thus, the pleading is fulfilling its basic function at this stage. In all the circumstances I would decline to exercise my discretion to strike out the statement of claim or any part thereof". 
 

 In State of Queensland , Drummond J held (at [34]) that the nature of the case itself must determine the standard to which the pleadings are held: 
 
 "[w]here a claim is based on a clandestine compact between a number of respondents, the applicant can be expected to be unable to give precise particulars of material facts sufficient to support its allegation of the making of that compact. In such cases, the entitlement of the respondents to be apprised before trial of the nature of the applicant's case must be "accommodated to the nature of that case itself"...".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kernel Holdings Pty Ltd v Rothmans of Pall Mall (Australia) Pty Ltd [1991] FCA 557</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/557.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Ltd [1999] FCA 1101 ; (1999) 165 ALR 409</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/1101.html</AustLII>
<text>In my earlier reasons I referred to the principles which govern the exercise of the Court's power to summarily dismiss a claim on the ground that it discloses no reasonable cause of action and the principles which inform the assessment of the adequacy of pleadings. These principles were summarised by Weinberg J in McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Ltd [1999] FCA 1101 ; (1999) 165 ALR 409 at 415-421. I restate that part of my earlier reasons here for the sake of convenience and because those principles have present application:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mitanis v Pioneer Concrete (Vic) Pty Ltd [1997] ATPR 41-591</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Riverstone Computer Services Pty Ltd v IBM Global Financing Australia Ltd [2002] FCA 1608</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1608.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant submits that its definition of "the Australian market" is sufficient and not productive of confusion, notwithstanding the later references to a global market for the supply of the same rubber chemicals. It relies on the decision of Hill J in Riverstone Computer Services Pty Ltd v IBM Global Financing Australia Ltd [2002] FCA 1608 at [21] to support the proposition that a "global market is a market in Australia if the goods or services are supplied [here]."

In Riverstone , Hill J was dealing with an application for pre-action discovery. All he was called on to determine, on an interlocutory basis, was whether there existed reasonable cause to believe that the applicant had or may have had a right to relief against the respondent. His Honour found that the evidence supported the existence of a global market for new and second hand computers and rejected a submission that, simply because no reference was made in the affidavits relied on by the applicant to an Australian market for these products, no such market existed. His Honour said ([at 21]) that: 
 
 "A global market which includes Australia (and the inference is that any global market did) is arguably a market in Australia if sales are made here (and the evidence shows they are) even if that market might also exist in the United States, Japan, China or any other country which was a member of the European union" (emphasis added).

Hill J is not, therefore, to be understood as defining a "market in Australia" simply by reference to the fact goods or services which are supplied elsewhere in the world are also supplied in Australia.

Riverstone does no more than support a general principle that there may, for TPA purposes, exist a market in Australia even though it forms part of a wider international market. Hill J's decision was so understood by Middleton J in Emirates v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2009] FCA 312 ; (2009) 255 ALR 35. His Honour considered the meaning of a "market in Australia" in the context of s 45 of the TPA. Significantly, his Honour held (at 53) that: 
 
 "... the definition of "market in Australia" in s 4E excludes a market that is wholly outside Australia, a conclusion with which I respectfully agree...In my opinion, Hill J in Riverstone Computer Services Pty Ltd v IBM Global Financing Australia Ltd [2002] FCA 1608 ( Riverstone ) was correct in concluding that the fact that a market was global did not signify that there could not be a market in Australia for the same products (or services)".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Singapore Airlines Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2009) 260 ALR 244</tocase>
<text>The law on what constitutes a "market in Australia" is far from settled. One thing that is clear is that a market which is wholly outside Australia is not comprehended by the statutory definition: see Singapore Airlines Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (2009) 260 ALR 244 at 254; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1976 ; (2008) 253 ALR 89 at 112. The existence of a global market which extends into the geographic boundaries of Australia does not, on the other hand, preclude a finding that there exists a "market in Australia".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>State of Queensland v Pioneer Concrete (Qld) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 499</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/499.html</AustLII>
<text>Counsel have drawn attention to further authorities in the course of argument. Most are relevant to particular issues and I will refer to them later in these reasons. There were, however, two passages (among others) of more general application on which counsel for the applicant placed emphasis: In Johnson Tiles Pty Ltd v Esso Australia Ltd [1999] FCA 569, at [12], Merkel J cautioned that pleadings are only a 'means to an end': 
 
 
 "the relief to be granted on a pleadings motion is a matter of discretion (see Brambles Holdings Ltd v Trade Practices Commission [1979] FCA 80 ; (1979) 28 ALR 191 at 193). Even if I had acceded to the arguments of Esso to a greater extent than I have in my view the Court's individual docket system of case management and its ability to ensure that the proceeding is conducted in a manner which does not unfairly prejudice any of the parties is such that I would not strike out the pleading. Rather, if complaint is made about any particular aspect being embarrassing or prejudicial the Court has ample power to deal with that aspect so as to avoid prejudice or embarrassment in the course of its management of the case. I am satisfied that the causes of action relied upon have been pleaded in a manner that ensures that Esso understands those causes of action and the substance of the allegations made against Esso . Thus, the pleading is fulfilling its basic function at this stage. In all the circumstances I would decline to exercise my discretion to strike out the statement of claim or any part thereof". 
 

 In State of Queensland , Drummond J held (at [34]) that the nature of the case itself must determine the standard to which the pleadings are held: 
 
 "[w]here a claim is based on a clandestine compact between a number of respondents, the applicant can be expected to be unable to give precise particulars of material facts sufficient to support its allegation of the making of that compact. In such cases, the entitlement of the respondents to be apprised before trial of the nature of the applicant's case must be "accommodated to the nature of that case itself"...".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v David Jones (Australia) Pty Ltd [1985] FCA 228 ; (1985) 7 FCR 109</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1985/228.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1979/51.html</AustLII>
<text>It is thus clear that his Honour's decision does not support the absolute proposition for which the applicant contends. Furthermore, it is to be borne in mind that his Honour was dealing with a "market", whether in Australia or in a wider geographic area of which Australia formed part, in the sense identified in the authorities. It is not necessary, for present purposes, to refer in detail to all of those authorities. Although the concept defies absolute precision in definition it "is a metaphor to describe a range of competitive activities by reference to function, product and geography": see Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 193 ; (2003) 131 FCR 529 at 545. The concept was succinctly stated by Fisher J in Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609 at 647 where he quoted with approval a passage from a decision of the Trade Practices Tribunal: 
 
 "The Trade Practices Tribunal considered the concept of market in some detail in Re Queensland Co-operative Milling Association Ltd (1975-6) 8 ALR 481 at 517, where the members said: "A market is the area of close competition between firms or, putting it a little differently, the field of rivalry between them ... Within the bounds of a market there is substitution substitution between one product and another, and between one source of supply and another, in response to changing prices. So a market is the field of actual and potential transactions between buyers and sellers amongst whom there can be strong substitution, at least in the long run, if given a sufficient price incentive"...".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 193 ; (2003) 131 FCR 529</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/193.html</AustLII>
<text>It is thus clear that his Honour's decision does not support the absolute proposition for which the applicant contends. Furthermore, it is to be borne in mind that his Honour was dealing with a "market", whether in Australia or in a wider geographic area of which Australia formed part, in the sense identified in the authorities. It is not necessary, for present purposes, to refer in detail to all of those authorities. Although the concept defies absolute precision in definition it "is a metaphor to describe a range of competitive activities by reference to function, product and geography": see Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 193 ; (2003) 131 FCR 529 at 545. The concept was succinctly stated by Fisher J in Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) (1979) 26 ALR 609 at 647 where he quoted with approval a passage from a decision of the Trade Practices Tribunal: 
 
 "The Trade Practices Tribunal considered the concept of market in some detail in Re Queensland Co-operative Milling Association Ltd (1975-6) 8 ALR 481 at 517, where the members said: "A market is the area of close competition between firms or, putting it a little differently, the field of rivalry between them ... Within the bounds of a market there is substitution substitution between one product and another, and between one source of supply and another, in response to changing prices. So a market is the field of actual and potential transactions between buyers and sellers amongst whom there can be strong substitution, at least in the long run, if given a sufficient price incentive"...".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Webster v Lampard [1993] HCA 57 ; (1993) 177 CLR 598</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/57.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wright Rubber Products Pty Ltd v Bayer AG [2008] FCA 1510</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1510.html</AustLII>
<text>The respondents successfully moved the Court for orders striking out the original statement of claim: see Wright Rubber Products Pty Ltd v Bayer AG [2008] FCA 1510 ("my earlier reasons"). The shortcomings of this original pleading fell into two broad categories: first, that the applicant had failed to identify with sufficient precision the group members whom it wished to represent, and secondly, that the applicant had failed to plead sufficient material facts to establish a cause of action. More particularly, I identified the following deficiencies in the original statement of claim: Group definition
 Potential group members would have had difficulty ascertaining whether they were members of the group because of the difficulty in determining whether they had bought "Rubber Products"; The definition of "Rubber Products" was inadequate, which in turn affected the entire statement of claim; and The applicant had not pleaded sufficient material facts to establish that it was a member of the group it sought to represent. The Cartel Arrangements
 The discrete causes of action arising under sub-paragraphs (i) and (ii) of s 45(2)(a) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) ("the TPA") had not been pleaded separately. Identification of the Markets
 The pleading confused references to the global and Australian markets, referring to the global market at times and the Australian market at other times without explaining why; The pleading did not clearly establish the existence of an Australian, as distinct from a global, market; and There were inconsistencies as to whether the market was for "Rubber Chemicals" or "Rubber Products". Giving effect to the arrangements in Australia

I granted leave to the applicant to replead its statement of claim. It has done so. The respondents (other than the fourth respondent) complain that the amended statement of claim is also fatally flawed and should be struck out. They have moved the Court for an order under O 11 rule 16 of the Federal Court Rules .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>