<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>ICM Agriculture Pty Ltd v Young [2009] FCA 109 (19 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/109.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Bhagat v Global Custodians Ltd [2002] FCAFC 51 </tocase>
<text>But it was not enough for Mr Young to formulate a claim in sweeping conclusory terms and to say on oath that he believed in his claim or was confident that he would be able to sustain it on a hearing: see, for example, Ebert v The Union Trustee Co of Australia Ltd [1960] HCA 50 ; (1960) 104 CLR 346 at 350-351; Bhagat v Global Custodians Ltd [2002] FCAFC 51 at [53].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth v Ling (1993) 44 FCR 397</tocase>
<text>The present case concerns an assignment of a bare cause of action for unliquidated damages for breach of contract, not of a property right to which a cause of action is ancillary. The parties accepted that in these circumstances the assignment could be sustained only if Mr Young had a genuine commercial interest in taking the assignment and enforcing it for his own benefit: see Trendtex Trading Corporation v Credit Suisse [1982] AC 679 at 703, which has been followed in many cases in Australia including, but not limited to, Re Timothy's Pty Ltd and the Companies Act [1981] 2 NSWLR 706; Commonwealth v Ling (1993) 44 FCR 397 ; National Mutual Property Services (Australia) Pty Ltd v Citibank Savings Ltd (1995) 132 ALR 514 ; and see G Tolhurst, The Assignment of Contractual Rights (Hart Publishing, 2006) at [6.59]ff .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Ebert v The Union Trustee Co of Australia Ltd [1960] HCA 50 ; (1960) 104 CLR 346</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1960/50.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Magistrate quoted as follows from my judgment in Glew v Harrowell of Hunt and Hunt Lawyers [2003] FCA 373 ( Glew ) at [8]-[9]: In order to avoid committing the act of bankruptcy identified in par 40(1)(g) of the Act, Glew and Tresider [the recipients of the bankruptcy notice] must satisfy the Court that they have a counter-claim, set-off or cross demand against Hunts of the kind described in that paragraph. What they must do in order to "satisfy the Court" for the purposes of par 40(1)(g) of the Act that they have the asserted counter-claim, set-off or cross demand has been variously described. The descriptions do not necessarily purport to be comprehensive definitions. To state that a debtor in receipt of a bankruptcy notice must show X does not necessarily imply that he or she need not also show Y, or that he or she will not be defeated if the creditor shows Z.
 There are authorities suggesting that Glew and Tresider must satisfy me of the following interrelated and sometimes overlapping matters: that they have a "prima facie case", even if they do not adduce evidence which would be admissible on a final hearing making out that case ( Ebert v The Union Trustee Co of Australia Ltd [1960] HCA 50 ; (1960) 104 CLR 346 (" Ebert ") at 350; Re Brink; Ex parte Commercial Banking Company of Sydney Ltd (1980) 44 FLR 135 (" Brink ") at 141; Gomez v State Bank of NSW Ltd [2002] FCAFC 101 at [17], [18]); that they have "a fair chance of success" or are "fairly entitled to litigate" the claim: Brink at 141; Re Gould; Gould v Day [1999] FCA 1650 at [27] , [28]; Re Capsanis; Capsanis v The Owners Strata Plan 11727 [2000] FCA 1262 at [11] ); and that they are advancing a "genuine" or "bona fide" claim ( Re Capsanis; Capsanis v The Owners Strata Plan 11727 [2000] FCA 1262 at [11] ). 
 It may be that the first and second formulations are intended to cover the same ground. In Brink Lockhart J treated (at 141) the reference to a " prima facie case " in Ebert as a reference to "a fair chance of success".

But it was not enough for Mr Young to formulate a claim in sweeping conclusory terms and to say on oath that he believed in his claim or was confident that he would be able to sustain it on a hearing: see, for example, Ebert v The Union Trustee Co of Australia Ltd [1960] HCA 50 ; (1960) 104 CLR 346 at 350-351; Bhagat v Global Custodians Ltd [2002] FCAFC 51 at [53].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Glew v Harrowell of Hunt and Hunt Lawyers [2003] FCA 373</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/373.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Magistrate quoted as follows from my judgment in Glew v Harrowell of Hunt and Hunt Lawyers [2003] FCA 373 ( Glew ) at [8]-[9]: In order to avoid committing the act of bankruptcy identified in par 40(1)(g) of the Act, Glew and Tresider [the recipients of the bankruptcy notice] must satisfy the Court that they have a counter-claim, set-off or cross demand against Hunts of the kind described in that paragraph. What they must do in order to "satisfy the Court" for the purposes of par 40(1)(g) of the Act that they have the asserted counter-claim, set-off or cross demand has been variously described. The descriptions do not necessarily purport to be comprehensive definitions. To state that a debtor in receipt of a bankruptcy notice must show X does not necessarily imply that he or she need not also show Y, or that he or she will not be defeated if the creditor shows Z.
 There are authorities suggesting that Glew and Tresider must satisfy me of the following interrelated and sometimes overlapping matters: that they have a "prima facie case", even if they do not adduce evidence which would be admissible on a final hearing making out that case ( Ebert v The Union Trustee Co of Australia Ltd [1960] HCA 50 ; (1960) 104 CLR 346 (" Ebert ") at 350; Re Brink; Ex parte Commercial Banking Company of Sydney Ltd (1980) 44 FLR 135 (" Brink ") at 141; Gomez v State Bank of NSW Ltd [2002] FCAFC 101 at [17], [18]); that they have "a fair chance of success" or are "fairly entitled to litigate" the claim: Brink at 141; Re Gould; Gould v Day [1999] FCA 1650 at [27] , [28]; Re Capsanis; Capsanis v The Owners Strata Plan 11727 [2000] FCA 1262 at [11] ); and that they are advancing a "genuine" or "bona fide" claim ( Re Capsanis; Capsanis v The Owners Strata Plan 11727 [2000] FCA 1262 at [11] ). 
 It may be that the first and second formulations are intended to cover the same ground. In Brink Lockhart J treated (at 141) the reference to a " prima facie case " in Ebert as a reference to "a fair chance of success".

The critical paragraph of the Federal Magistrates Reasons for Judgment is [58] which stated: As per Glew the essential element that I am required to be satisfied of is that there is a prima facie case. Before that can be established it will be necessary for a final determination as to the validity of the Deed of Assignment as the total claim depends on that effective transfer to Mr Young to enable him to mount his cross-claim. If the deed of assignment is found to be defective, Mr Young has not provided a second or alternative basis for a counter claim or set off. If the secondary claim did exist independent of the Deed then the failure to raise that claim in the District Court may be estopped by the principles in the Port of Melbourne Authority v Anshun Pty Ltd [1981] HCA 45 ; (1981) 147 CLR 589. If the Deed is found to be valid and effective then the "Contract Confirmations" annexed to the second affidavit of Mr Young indicates that ICM Agriculture and entities other than AAC or its nominees have breached the licence agreement. As there has been no challenge as to the admissibility of those documents I am satisfied that a claim would exist and that Mr Young has a prima facie case for damages.

The Federal Magistrate's reference to "Contract Confirmations" is a reference to seven documents so named by which ICM sold Kabuli Chickpeas to Agrinational Pty Ltd over the period 18 to 21 August 2003. The "prima facie" claim for damages referred to is no doubt a claim for damages by AAC for breach by ICM of clauses 2, 3, 8 and 9 of the Grower's Licence, referred to at [15] - [17] above.

In sum, the Federal Magistrate noted, without attempting to resolve, the issue of the validity of the assignment, and considered that ICM's sale of the chickpeas raised a prima facie case of breach of the Grower's Licence by ICM.

If an attempt had been made to read the affidavit as evidence of any facts under the heading "Claim for relief", there would have been an objection and the affidavit would have been rejected. First, the affidavit was nothing more than a statement of Mr Young's "belief"; his state of belief was not evidence of any of the primary facts, and was not able to satisfy the test discussed in Glew (set out at [67] above and [79] below). Second, and more importantly, if Mr Young had sworn that the allegations of fact in the statement of claim were true, his affidavit would still have been inadmissible because of the nature of the material in the statement of claim. It was an amalgam of conclusions, rather than a statement of facts.

Indeed, before the Federal Magistrate Mr Young did attempt to read an affidavit sworn by him on 21 December 2007 which contained in paragraphs 18 and 19 the very material that appeared under the heading "Relief claimed" in the statement of claim. When objection was taken to the two paragraphs, they were not read. Counsel then appearing for Mr Young (not the Counsel who appeared for him on the present appeal) said that the non-reading of them was of little consequence at that stage because he proposed to tender the statement of claim which would show the monetary value of the counter-claim. Counsel appears to have thought that it sufficed to show how the counter-claim was calculated.

In Glew , immediately following [8] and [9] quoted by the Federal Magistrate and set out at [67] above, I said: In Brink Lockhart J said (at 141) that the Court is not required to "undertake a preliminary trial of the counter-claim, set-off or cross demand". But, clearly, the application of the criteria above requires the Court to make some kind of preliminary assessment, though obviously not to determine the counter-claim, set-off or cross demand finally. And in Guss v Johnstone [2000] HCA 26 ; (2000) 171 ALR 598 , Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Kirby and Callinan JJ stated (at 606):
 
"40 The state of satisfaction referred to in s 40(1)(g) , and s 41(7) , involves weighing up considerations as to the legal and factual merit of the claim relied upon by the debtor, and the justice of allowing the bankruptcy proceedings to go ahead or requiring them to await the determination of the claim."
 
 Plainly, in order to "satisfy" the Court for the purposes of par 40(1)(g), the debtor is not required to prove, as on a final hearing, the asserted entitlement to recover from the creditor. Accordingly, evidence tendered on an application to set aside is to be tested for admissibility, not as if the proceeding were one in which the debtor's claim was being finally determined, but by reference to the question whether the Court should be satisfied that the debtor has a claim deserving to be finally determined.
 Perhaps little more can usefully be said than that a debtor must satisfy the Court that there is sufficient substance to the counter-claim, set-off or cross demand asserted to make it one which the debtor should, in justice, be permitted to have heard and determined in the usual way, rather than be forced to comply with the bankruptcy notice by payment or to commit an act of bankruptcy.
 
Mr Young's supposed affidavit verifying the material quoted at [57] above could not even begin properly to satisfy the Federal Magistrates Court that Mr Young had a counter-claim against ICM in an amount equal to or exceeding the amount of ICM's judgment against him.

Mr Young submits that the point raised by the first ground of appeal was not raised before the Federal Magistrate until closing submissions, by which time it was too late for it to be raised. The notice stating grounds of opposition to the application to set aside the Bankruptcy Notice stated as a ground that Mr Young did not have a prima facie counter-claim, set-off or counter demand [sic] "within the meaning of s 40(1)(g) of the [Bankruptcy Act]". In order to be within s 40(1)(g) , a counter-claim, set-off or cross demand must be for an amount that is equal to or exceeds the amount of the judgment debt. Accordingly, there is no substance in Mr Young's argument that the point was raised too late below.

ICM's first ground of appeal succeeds, subject to resolution of Mr Young's application to lead evidence on the appeal (see [130] below). Ground 2(a): Did the alleged counter-claim have insufficient legal or factual merit?</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Exch 341(156 ER 145)</tocase>
<text>First, even if all of the facts and conclusions referred to in Mr Young's District Court statement of claim were proved, he would have failed because his claim as formulated does not fit within either the first or second limb of Hadley v Baxendale (1854) 9 Exch 341 (156 ER 145); see Castle Constructions Pty Ltd v Fekala Pty Ltd (2006) 65 NSWLR 648 at [34], [39]. The leading of evidence of value on the appeal would not have overcome this problem. A complete reformulation of the alleged counter-claim would have been necessary.

Second, in so far as AAC's losses are said to relate to "Royalties Due and Payable" in accordance with the Sublicence, those losses could not properly be said to have been caused by a breach of the Grower's Licence by ICM. They were caused by the insolvency of Namoi. It will be recalled that a voluntary administrator was appointed to Namoi on 11 July 2003, only four days after Mr Young wrote his letter of 7 July 2003 on the letterhead of Namoi. The creditors of Namoi passed a special resolution for the winding up of the company on 8 August 2003.

For the two reasons last given, Mr Young could not have properly satisfied the Federal Magistrate that ICM was liable to AAC. I acknowledge that the second reason relates to only $54,855 of the total counter-claim of $257,355. The balance of $202,500 still exceeds (just) the amount of the Bankruptcy Notice of $198,278.06. Ground 2(b): the validity of the assignment</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Monk v The Australian &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Limited (1994) 34 NSWLR 148 </tocase>
<text>Challenging the validity of the assignment, ICM relied on two propositions before the Federal Magistrate: 
(a) The cause of action was unable to be assigned by AAC to Mr Young because it was a bare cause of action and Mr Young had no genuine commercial interest to support he assignment (ICM cited Salfinger v Niugini Mining (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1532 at [108] - [124] ; Monk v The Australian &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Limited (1994) 34 NSWLR 148 at 152 ( Monk )); 
 
(b) The assignment was procured in breach of fiduciary duties owed by Mr Young to the shareholders of AAC, and on this basis the proper exercise of the Court's discretion would be to refuse to set aside the Bankruptcy Notice (ICM cited Re Daley; ex parte National Australia Bank Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 390 at 395 ( Daley )).

The circumstances of the present case are analogous to those in Monk in which the assignee's interest was that of obtaining a set-off against a judgment debt. In that case, Cohen J said (at 153): 
 The plaintiff's only apparent interest is in the possibility of his becoming a creditor of the Bank. That is, his interest is in using the debt which might arise from the cause of action for his personal benefit. That no doubt is the interest of any assignee. The using of the debt as a set-off against the judgment debt is merely an example of obtaining some personal benefit. In that regard the plaintiff is in no stronger position than he would be if he had obtained an assignment of a cause of action for negligence by a customer of the Bank who claimed to have suffered injuries arising from unsafe premises. In the authorities where the Trendtex test has been applied, the commercial interest has gone beyond a mere personal interest in profiting from the outcome of the proceedings and has required an interest by the assignee in the assignor or its business affairs or activities which the assignment may in some way protect. 

 
These observations are applicable, mutatis mutandis , to the present case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>National Mutual Property Services (Australia) Pty Ltd v Citibank Savings Ltd (1995) 132 ALR 514</tocase>
<text>The present case concerns an assignment of a bare cause of action for unliquidated damages for breach of contract, not of a property right to which a cause of action is ancillary. The parties accepted that in these circumstances the assignment could be sustained only if Mr Young had a genuine commercial interest in taking the assignment and enforcing it for his own benefit: see Trendtex Trading Corporation v Credit Suisse [1982] AC 679 at 703, which has been followed in many cases in Australia including, but not limited to, Re Timothy's Pty Ltd and the Companies Act [1981] 2 NSWLR 706; Commonwealth v Ling (1993) 44 FCR 397 ; National Mutual Property Services (Australia) Pty Ltd v Citibank Savings Ltd (1995) 132 ALR 514 ; and see G Tolhurst, The Assignment of Contractual Rights (Hart Publishing, 2006) at [6.59]ff .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Re Daley; ex parte National Australia Bank Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 390</tocase>
<text>Challenging the validity of the assignment, ICM relied on two propositions before the Federal Magistrate: 
(a) The cause of action was unable to be assigned by AAC to Mr Young because it was a bare cause of action and Mr Young had no genuine commercial interest to support he assignment (ICM cited Salfinger v Niugini Mining (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1532 at [108] - [124] ; Monk v The Australian &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Limited (1994) 34 NSWLR 148 at 152 ( Monk )); 
 
(b) The assignment was procured in breach of fiduciary duties owed by Mr Young to the shareholders of AAC, and on this basis the proper exercise of the Court's discretion would be to refuse to set aside the Bankruptcy Notice (ICM cited Re Daley; ex parte National Australia Bank Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 390 at 395 ( Daley )).

His Honour cited Heerey's decision in Daley. In Daley , the debtor, Mr Daley was a director and the sole beneficial shareholder of certain companies, and had guaranteed their liability to a bank. The bank had a judgment against Mr Daley on credit card liabilities and served a bankruptcy notice on him. One of the companies sued the bank for $45,811.28 which represented the total of the amounts of cheques drawn on the company's account which the bank had, allegedly wrongfully, honoured. That company, for a consideration of $1.00, assigned "the Debt" to Mr Daley.

Daley is distinguishable because, first, Mr Young was not a guarantor of AAC; second, what was assigned in Daley was a debt rather than a bare cause of action for unliquidated damages for breach of contract as in the present case; and, third, Mr Daley was the sole shareholder in the assignor.

At the date of the assignment, Mr Young held no shares in AAC. As noted at [51]-[54] above, it is agreed that the appeal is to be determined on the basis that at the time of the assignment Young's Rural Services Pty Ltd held one of six shares issued in AAC and Mr Young was the sole director and shareholder of Young's Rural Services Pty Ltd.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Timothy's Pty Ltd and the Companies Act [1981] 2 NSWLR 706</tocase>
<text>The present case concerns an assignment of a bare cause of action for unliquidated damages for breach of contract, not of a property right to which a cause of action is ancillary. The parties accepted that in these circumstances the assignment could be sustained only if Mr Young had a genuine commercial interest in taking the assignment and enforcing it for his own benefit: see Trendtex Trading Corporation v Credit Suisse [1982] AC 679 at 703, which has been followed in many cases in Australia including, but not limited to, Re Timothy's Pty Ltd and the Companies Act [1981] 2 NSWLR 706; Commonwealth v Ling (1993) 44 FCR 397 ; National Mutual Property Services (Australia) Pty Ltd v Citibank Savings Ltd (1995) 132 ALR 514 ; and see G Tolhurst, The Assignment of Contractual Rights (Hart Publishing, 2006) at [6.59]ff .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Salfinger v Niugini Mining (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1532</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1532.html</AustLII>
<text>Challenging the validity of the assignment, ICM relied on two propositions before the Federal Magistrate: 
(a) The cause of action was unable to be assigned by AAC to Mr Young because it was a bare cause of action and Mr Young had no genuine commercial interest to support he assignment (ICM cited Salfinger v Niugini Mining (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1532 at [108] - [124] ; Monk v The Australian &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Limited (1994) 34 NSWLR 148 at 152 ( Monk )); 
 
(b) The assignment was procured in breach of fiduciary duties owed by Mr Young to the shareholders of AAC, and on this basis the proper exercise of the Court's discretion would be to refuse to set aside the Bankruptcy Notice (ICM cited Re Daley; ex parte National Australia Bank Ltd (1992) 37 FCR 390 at 395 ( Daley )).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trendtex Trading Corporation v Credit Suisse [1982] AC 679</tocase>
<text>I referred to cl 10 at [18] above. Clause 10 was as follows: 
 The Licensor or their agent shall sell the seed or product delivered to it by the grower (or otherwise subject to this agreement) via the payment schedule as per attachment. 

 
Clause 10 appears to be a promise by AAC to ICM that AAC or Namoi will sell seed and product delivered to "it" by ICM "via the payment schedule as per attached". It is common ground that at least the form of the Commercial Crop Contract was attached. There is a sort of payment schedule in cl 4 of the Commercial Crop Contract. That clause listed "Guaranteed Minimum Prices" promised to ICM as the grower.

It appears that either AAC was, through its agent Namoi, a party to the Commercial Crop Contract as a principal whose existence and identity were not disclosed on the face of that document, or at least the agent Namoi entered into the Commercial Crop Contract in its own right but AAC approved of its doing so as the necessary and contemplated means of implementing the Grower's Licence. Even on the latter basis, it is arguable that AAC was bound by Mr Young's conduct on behalf of Namoi in the discussion on 29 May 2003.

The date fixed for completion of the Commercial Crop Contract, 30 June 2003, was not intended to be of the essence of that contract. I mean that ICM was not entitled immediately following 30 June to terminate the contractual relationship for Namoi's failure to pay on that date. This is demonstrated by the second and last sentences of cl 3(c). The whole of cl 3(c) is as follows: 
 Subject to normal seasonal conditions, delivery and payment under this contract is to be completed prior to 30 June 2003. If due to extraneous circumstances by either party that this contract is not completed by this date then mediation with regards to settlement terms must occur. A suggestion is that if the Grower is deemed to be at fault they would not charge the Licensor carry (storage) from this date and the credit limit in place would be renegotiated. If the Licensor is deemed to be at fault then a negotiated percentage of the balance of the products to be paid at this date.

The present case concerns an assignment of a bare cause of action for unliquidated damages for breach of contract, not of a property right to which a cause of action is ancillary. The parties accepted that in these circumstances the assignment could be sustained only if Mr Young had a genuine commercial interest in taking the assignment and enforcing it for his own benefit: see Trendtex Trading Corporation v Credit Suisse [1982] AC 679 at 703, which has been followed in many cases in Australia including, but not limited to, Re Timothy's Pty Ltd and the Companies Act [1981] 2 NSWLR 706; Commonwealth v Ling (1993) 44 FCR 397 ; National Mutual Property Services (Australia) Pty Ltd v Citibank Savings Ltd (1995) 132 ALR 514 ; and see G Tolhurst, The Assignment of Contractual Rights (Hart Publishing, 2006) at [6.59]ff .

The circumstances of the present case are analogous to those in Monk in which the assignee's interest was that of obtaining a set-off against a judgment debt. In that case, Cohen J said (at 153): 
 The plaintiff's only apparent interest is in the possibility of his becoming a creditor of the Bank. That is, his interest is in using the debt which might arise from the cause of action for his personal benefit. That no doubt is the interest of any assignee. The using of the debt as a set-off against the judgment debt is merely an example of obtaining some personal benefit. In that regard the plaintiff is in no stronger position than he would be if he had obtained an assignment of a cause of action for negligence by a customer of the Bank who claimed to have suffered injuries arising from unsafe premises. In the authorities where the Trendtex test has been applied, the commercial interest has gone beyond a mere personal interest in profiting from the outcome of the proceedings and has required an interest by the assignee in the assignor or its business affairs or activities which the assignment may in some way protect. 

 
These observations are applicable, mutatis mutandis , to the present case.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>