<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Fortescue Metals Group Ltd [No 5] [2009] FCA 1586 (23 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1586.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Adler v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 131 ; (2003) 179 FLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2003/131.html</AustLII>
<text>The rule in Jones v Dunkel was discussed however in Adler v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 131 ; (2003) 179 FLR 1 , Williams v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 131 ; (2003) 46 ACSR 504 , a judgment handed down before the High Court's Rich ruling, where the New South Wales Court of Appeal ruled that the trial judge, Santow J ((2002) [2002] NSWSC 171 ; 41 ACSR 72) , made no error in so far as his findings against Mr Adler, his company and Mr Williams were aided by Jones v Dunkel inferences against both those individuals and the company. In that proceeding ASIC had sought, inter alia , disqualification orders as well as pecuniary penalties. Giles JA, with whom Mason P and Beazley JA agreed, considered the High Court criminal cases discussed above and noted at [658] that proceedings for civil penalties do not share the same fundamental features of a criminal trial. His Honour stated that civil penalty proceedings are expressly to be maintained by civil law processes, not by a criminal trial with its fundamental features, [659]. He concluded that it was open for Jones v Dunkel inferences to be drawn against Mr Adler, his company, and Mr Williams in the proceedings, [661].

The rulings in Adler were therefore made on the footing that the privilege against exposure to penalty was attracted through ASIC's seeking of pecuniary penalties, but this did not prevent the trial judge from applying the rule in Jones v Dunkel, the rule and privilege both falling within the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters that the court was bound to apply pursuant to s 1317L of the act when hearing proceedings for a declaration of contravention or a pecuniary penalty order.

The High Court refused an application for special leave to appeal from the Court of Appeal's decision in Adler : [2004] HCATrans 182 , 28 May 2004. The transcript reveals that the special leave point argued was the issue of procedural fairness in dealing with the imposition of pecuniary penalties and disqualification under the civil penalties regime of the Act; there was no discussion of the rule in Jones v Dunkel .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Anaconda Nickel Ltd v Tarmoola Australia Pty Ltd [2000] WASCA 27 ; (2000) 22 WAR 101</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WASCA/2000/27.html</AustLII>
<text>Forrest had known Huston for a number of years prior to this. Huston acted as solicitor for Anaconda Nickel Ltd in proceedings in the Supreme Court of Western Australia culminating in an appeal to the Full Court: Anaconda Nickel Ltd v Tarmoola Australia Pty Ltd [2000] WASCA 27 ; (2000) 22 WAR 101. These proceedings concerned the enforceability of a short letter said to be a "heads of agreement". In certain respects it bears a remarkable similarity to the framework agreements. The majority (Ipp J; Pidgeon J agreeing) held that the heads of agreement was a valid and binding agreement.

Huston helped prepare the draft as well as the final 8 November Letter concerning the three framework agreements provided by FMG to the ASX that day. He attended a meeting with Mr Tony Walsh, Assistant Manager Issuers of the ASX, on 8 November 2004 relevantly to discuss this draft for the purpose of providing further information to the ASX as to the terms of the framework agreements. I have concluded that, for this purpose, Huston would have considered the terms of the related 5 November Letter and the three framework agreements referred to in that letter. He did not advise the FMG Board or Forrest that these agreements were not legally binding or that the 5 November Letter was to that extent incorrect or not reasonably based. Given his role in FMG, had he formed that view, I find that he should have and would have informed the board. That he did not, entitled the board and Forrest to continue to regard the disclosures concerning the legal effect of the framework agreements as correct, or at least that they were reasonably based.

That this was so is fortified by evidence of actual advice given by Huston to the FMG board that the framework agreements were legally binding as disclosed.

The FMG board minutes of its 22 January 2005 meeting, attended by Huston, record his advice to the board that the CMCC Framework Agreement was binding. So too did an email sent by him on 30 March 2005 to Forrest, Christopher Catlow, David Liu, Rowley, Alan Watling and other FMG executives concerning the AFR Article in which he repeated this advice, relying in particular upon the Anaconda decision. The 30 March 2005 email was not disclosed in ASIC's pleading. While the minutes of the 22 January board meeting were set out as a particular of two allegations concerning FMG's and Forrest's knowledge of the Chinese Contractors' attitude towards the framework agreements and of the legal effect of the agreements, ASIC did not particularise the material passage in the minutes where Huston's legal advice to the board was set out, nor did it refer to this passage in its opening or closing submissions. This is so, despite the fact that, in relation to ASIC's s 674 case, it asserted, amongst other things, that FMG ought to have been aware of the legal effect of the framework agreements asserted by ASIC by first obtaining competent legal advice. Huston was a very experienced and competent commercial solicitor.

I was not referred to these documents during the trial until the closing address by Forrest's senior counsel, Mr Myers QC. Their content, combined with other evidence, demonstrates that there was no basis for ASIC to assert dishonesty on the part of FMG, its board and in particular, Forrest. I make the same criticism of the description applied to FMG and by implication its board and particularly Forrest in the way ASIC's case was opened. It was asserted that FMG engaged in a concerted and designed course of conduct in which it made false, misleading and exaggerated statements to the ASX of which Forrest was the architect. In my view the evidence does not support such serious allegations. The principal basis, it seems, depends on ASIC's submission that the framework agreements are self-evidently not binding build and transfer agreements. I rejected that argument. I consider that there was a reasonable basis for FMG, through its board, including Forrest, to have held the view that the framework agreements were binding as claimed. It was supported by Huston's professional oversight to ensure the legal enforceability of FMG's agreements as well as his later positive advice to the effect that they were such. It was a view consistent with Forrest's knowledge of the Anaconda case. It finds arguable support in other authority.

Significantly too, CREC approved the terms of the 23 August Media Release before FMG made the notifications to the ASX on 23 August 2004. The release described the CREC Framework Agreement as a "binding agreement to build and finance the railway component of Fortescue Metals Group Ltd's $1.85 billion Pilbara iron ore project". In the release Mr Qin Jiaming (Qin), the President of CREC, is quoted as saying that the contract presented an excellent opportunity for CREC to develop internationally and that CREC was fully confident about its capacity to build the rail project. It was described by him as a 'marriage' immediately following the high level ceremony when the parties signed the Joint Statement which rendered the agreement binding.

I find that the terms of the 5 November Media Release provided to CHEC and CMCC was likewise approved, at least not disavowed, by them before disclosure to the ASX by FMG.

For at least these reasons, it is important that allegations of dishonesty should be made only where there is a reasonable evidentiary basis for them. It is my opinion that on the totality of the evidence available to ASIC there was no such basis in this case. Notwithstanding that ASIC's assertions as to the meaning and legal effect of the framework agreements differs from that disclosed by FMG to the knowledge of Forrest, this difference, which, in effect, is a difference of opinion does not of itself provide a basis for alleging dishonesty against FMG, its board and in particular Forrest. FMG's opinion was underpinned by the oversight and advice of its in-house counsel Huston. Forrest had his knowledge and experience in Anaconda to draw upon . Documents demonstrating these significant matters were available to ASIC. In light of these it is difficult to discern why ASIC ran a case alleging that FMG's board could not have made the disclosures it did if it had obtained competent legal advice. The board of FMG had no reason to doubt the correctness of Huston's view as to the meaning and legal effect of the framework agreements. He was employed by FMG primarily to ensure that all of FMG's agreements were legally enforceable. The reasonableness of FMG's opinion was strongly contended for by senior counsel for both FMG and Forrest at trial. It was an opinion which I consider was reasonably open. In my view, these allegations of dishonesty should not have been made.

I have no hesitation in concluding that FMG and its board, including Forrest, honestly and reasonably held the opinion that the framework agreements were legally enforceable in the sense asserted in FMG's disclosures. They did not hold the opinions propounded by ASIC. Those opinions do not self evidently and obviously arise upon a consideration of the terms of the framework agreements. PART 3: EVIDENTIARY MATTERS 
 Standard of proof

ASIC submits in written closing submission that the authorities such as Anaconda, Pagnan SpA, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games Ltd (1988) 18 NSWLR 540 and Uranium Equities v Fewster [2008] WASCA 33 ; (2008) 36 WAR 97 relied on by FMG state that whether or not the parties intended to contract, they must agree on such terms, normally described as essential terms, such that the contract could be enforced or made complete by implying terms or applying considerations of reasonableness. I will consider these authorities further. In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the Court of Appeal found that a binding contract had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement "constituted an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form". At [28], Ipp J referred to the following statement by Sugerman J, approved by Menzies J in Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 at 607: 
It is a first principle of the law of contracts that there can be no binding and enforceable obligation unless the terms of the bargain, or at least its essential and critical terms, have been agreed upon. So, there is no concluded contract where an essential or critical term is expressly left to be settled by future agreement of the parties. Again, there is no binding contract where the language used is so obscure and incapable of any precise or definite meaning that the court is unable to attribute to the parties any particular contractual intentions.

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the parties to the putative agreement had been negotiating over a proposed mining joint venture, but no heads of agreement had been executed. The Court found that the trial judge was right in concluding that the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed. The Court went on to state on the question of uncertainty at [257] that it is "trite" that, even when the requisite intention is present, a contract can fail for uncertainty. The Court said it is also trite that only the omission of an essential term will have the effect that a contract is so incomplete or uncertain as to render it invalid, citing Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [29] . The Court referred to the statement of Lloyd LJ from Pagnan SpA [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep at 619 and found that when regard was had to all the circumstances the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed . The Court concluded that although some of the matters left over by the parties for future negotiation were important, none were essential to the efficacy of the alleged agreement in the sense that the agreement could not be enforced without it.

ASIC also points to the absence of the following from the framework agreements: no provision for choice of contractors or the selection of materials; no definition of "practical completion"; and no specifications for any design elements of the infrastructure. The documents referred to in the Recitals to each agreement would have, no doubt, assisted in clarifying the matters absent from the agreements. In light of those documents, following the approach of Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [61] , it may have been possible to conclude that, despite the long list of matters said to render the framework agreements uncertain and incomplete, there was a binding contract, workable by implying terms or on the proper construction of the agreement. The court will apply orthodox principles of implying terms by reference to the implied duty to co-operate and use considerations of reasonableness, to give effect to that intention: Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR 540; Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd v Hebron Park Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60. The asserted uncertainty or incompleteness may therefore be overcome once the requisite intention to contract is found to be present.

In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the issue was whether a binding contract for Anaconda, a company interested in lateritic nickel, to explore and mine for base metals on the tenements of Tarmoola, a company interested mainly in gold, had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement ' constitutes an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form' . Tarmoola argued that there was no intention to contract, no agreement on essential terms, and that the agreement was incomplete and uncertain. By majority, the WA Full Court rejected these arguments and held that the heads of agreement was a binding contract. Ipp J (with whom Pidgeon J agreed) found that contractual intention was present. His Honour endorsed the existence of the fourth Masters v Cameron category in stating: 
It is well recognised that parties may enter into a valid contract containing a limited number of terms comprising those terms essential to the bargain that they wish to conclude, in the expectation that at a later date a further contract will be arrived at containing additional terms that would facilitate and clarify the initial contract. That is to say, a binding contract may be arrived at even though it leaves unresolved many matters which might arise in future. [25]

Since Anaconda was decided by the Court of Appeal on 17 February 2000 it has been cited, considered or applied without disapproval in a number of contract law cases involving questions of incompleteness or uncertainty, for example: Duskwood Pty Ltd v Bellara Willows Pty Ltd [2001] per Steytler J at [95]; Liristis Holdings Pty Ltd v Wallville Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 428 per Barrett J at [38]; African Minerals Limited v Pan Palladium Limited [2003] NSWSC 268 per Einstein J at [26]; Thompson v White &amp; Ors [2006] NSWCA 350 per Tobias JA with whom Ipp and McColl JJA agreed at [100]; Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248 per Giles JA with whom McColl JA and Young CJ in EQ agreed at [27]-[28]; Donald Fin Enterprises Pty Ltd v APIR Systems Ltd (2008) 67 ACSR 219 per Edmonds J at [131]-[132]; Strzelecki Holdings Pty Ltd v Cable Sands Pty Ltd [No 3] [2009] WASC 352 per Murray J at [90].

The approach taken in G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631, Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 and Tasman Capital [2008] NSWCA 248 was followed very recently by the Queensland Court of Appeal in Moffat Property Development Group [2009] QCA 60 , mentioned above, which underlined the importance of the parties' manifest intention to contract. The issue was whether a contract for the sale of rural residential land had been made by an exchange of letters. The Queensland Court of Appeal held that the parties intended to be legally bound through their exchange of correspondence and that there was a contract even though matters such as the timing of completion and arrangements at settlement, the precise timing of the payment of the deposit, the place of settlement, responsibility for insurance, GST issues and the terms of a put and call option were not spelt out in the correspondence. Keane JA delivered the court's judgment. His Honour: 
(a) accepted McHugh JA's point in G R Securities that "the decisive issue is always the intention of the parties": [23]-[25];
 
(b) said "the terms of the correspondence exchanged between the parties contemplated the execution of a further contract as the means whereby the bargain which they had concluded would be implemented. It is necessarily implicit in such an agreement that the parties will co-operate to do what must be done to make the further agreement": [30];
 
(c) adopted McHugh JA's approach in G R Securities and explained that the implied obligation of each party to co-operate with the other to ensure each side obtains the benefit of its bargain serves to supply the deficiencies: [34];
 
(d) cited Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR at 548 in stating: "I am of the view that there can be no doubt as to the orthodoxy of referring to 'implied terms or ... considerations of reasonableness' in order to determine whether the parties' 'consensus is sufficiently comprehensive to be legally binding : [51].

Forrest had known Huston for a number of years prior to this. Huston acted as solicitor for Anaconda Nickel Ltd in proceedings against Tarmoola Australia Pty Ltd in the Supreme Court of Western Australia: [2000] WASCA 27 ; (2000) 22 WAR 101. These concerned the enforceability of a short letter said to be a "heads of agreement". In certain respects it bears a remarkable similarity to the framework agreements. The then Full Court, in 2000, by majority (Ipp J; Pidgeon J agreeing) held that the heads of agreement was a valid and binding agreement.

The judgment in that case was the foundation of the view held and the advice given by Huston. It was a case which was already well-known to Forrest. He had been Anaconda's CEO at the time of the litigation and its signatory to the heads of agreement which was the subject matter in the case.

FMG and Forrest in particular, at least from the beginning of Oct 2004, if not before, were focused on ensuring that FMG's agreements were legally enforceable. This included the framework agreements. It is apparent that one of Huston's principal roles at FMG was to oversee and ensure the legal enforceability or, as Forrest sometimes described it, the "bankability" of FMG's agreements. On 3 October 2004 Forrest distributed a lengthy email to, amongst others, FMG executives and Huston in which he welcomed Huston to the team. Paragraph 3 with the heading "Legally binding contracts" included the following : 
Some agreements have been written in an ad hoc way with the best means available to the executive responsible. Unfortunately, on a full Bankers legal due diligence some of these may not pass the enforceability test. 
 
 
Gentlemen, please ensure with Peter complete legal enforceability on the agreements that we are all relying to construct FMG.

The text of the email, almost entirely, concerns the three framework agreements. In context, therefore, I take this request by Forrest to be referring to, or at least to include, those agreements. Forrest concluded by saying "... I am happy with the release, subject to P. Huston's sign off on the enforceability, to go." This appears to be a reference to a press release concerning an iron ore contract with a Chinese company called Hebei. It again evidences Forrest's quite specific concern that FMG's agreements were legally enforceable.

On 20 October 2004, after the execution of the CHEC and CMCC Framework Agreements but before the formal Joint Statement signing ceremony in Beijing on 5 November 2004 when those agreements became binding, Forrest sent an email to various FMG personnel, including Huston, where he referred approvingly to David Liu and his co-ordination of the arrangements with the three Chinese Contractors. He also thanked Huston for his contribution. He said: 
Peter, (Huston) thanks for the rappid (sic) fire support tonight. Hope we got your instructions right these contract (sic) better be bankable because people are signing them. David pls get the two we worked on today down to Peter for his all clear. 
 
 
I take the word "bankable" in this context to mean such as to satisfy potential FMG financiers, in the course of their due diligence process, as to the "legal enforceability" of these contracts.

It is clear from the combination of the 22 January minutes and Huston's 30 March email that, in his opinion, the CMCC Framework Agreement was a binding build and transfer agreement. The case to which he referred was Anaconda Nickel Ltd v Tarmoola Australia Pty Ltd [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 which I have referred to previously. That case concerned the enforceability of a letter containing 5 clauses and described as a "heads of agreement" signed by Forrest who then was Chief Executive of Anaconda. The letter concluded, in terms not dissimilar to clause 7 in each of the framework agreements: 
The above forms a heads of agreement which constitutes an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form.

The respondent, Tarmoola, signed the letter confirming its agreement to the tems and conditions set out in it. The parties then entered into negotiations for the "fuller agreement" but those negotiations were unsuccessful. No "fuller agreement' was concluded.

Anaconda , amongst other relief, sought a declaration that the heads of agreement was a valid and binding contract. The respondent argued that it was not so bound on a number of bases, including lack of intention to create a binding legal relationship because so many important matters had been omitted, lack of certainty and completeness of the contract.

The appeal was successful and the declaration was granted. Tarmoola's application to the High Court for special leave to appeal (P15/2000) was discontinued.

Huston , I infer, during the period he was overseeing FMG's agreements, had a detailed knowledge of this case and the reasons for judgment. He was Anaconda's instructing solicitor in that case. As ASIC pleads, Huston was an experienced and practising commercial solicitor. He had, as I have said, been directly involved in preparing the 8 November Letter which concerned all three framework agreements. One of Huston's principal responsibilities was to ensure that FMG's agreements were legally enforceable. He had not suggested to the FMG Board, including Forrest, that the framework agreements were not legally enforceable. His opinion expressed in the 22 January 2005 board minutes and the 30 March 2005 email that the CMCC Framework Agreement was binding necessarily must have applied to the other two framework agreements.

FMG's and Forrest's opinion as to the meaning and legal effect of the framework agreements was shaped and informed by Huston's involvement. They had the benefit of his dedicated professional oversight and later his advice as to the legal enforceability of the framework agreements. Forrest as CEO, was directly involved in the Anaconda case and would have been well aware of the judgments both at first instance and on appeal as well as the discontinuance of Tarmoola's application for special leave to appeal to the High Court. Forrest then had the benefit of legal advice in relation to the legal enforceability of a similar agreement. Huston alluded to this in his 30 March 2005 email when he stated, referring to the Anaconda decision: 
Thus if journalist(s) want to know why Andrew (Forrest) considers the (C)MCC agreement to be binding he is amongst other things relying on his own direct experience from this (S)upreme Court Case.

All relevant FMG staff had been told by Forrest in early October to ensure, through Huston, that FMG agreements were legally enforceable. The evidence also demonstrates that, contrary to ASIC's assertion, Huston did give legal advice to FMG as to the legal enforceability of the framework agreements. In particular, the 22 January minutes show that the FMG board turned its mind to the question of whether the CMCC Framework Agreement was binding following the statement by Mr Ma at the 17 January meeting, that it sought legal advice on that question from Huston and that he answered the question in the affirmative.

If, as I think likely, although I make no finding, he was asked to advise on the issue of the legal enforceability of the CREC Framework Agreement prior to the 23 August notification, it is reasonable to infer that his opinion and reasons for it were, or would have been, the same as he later twice provided to FMG's board.

I consider that Forrest exercised his powers and discharged his duties with the degree of care and diligence that a reasonable person would exercise if they were a director or officer of FMG in FMG's circumstances; and if they occupied the offices of Forrest within FMG and had the same responsibilities within FMG as Forrest. Forrest, as I have explained earlier in detail, as a consequence of his own appreciation of the decision in Anaconda; his reliance on the legal oversight and advice of Huston; and his appreciation that the Chinese Contractors held the same view that the framework agreements were legally binding, had reasonable grounds for approving or permitting to be made the disclosures, complained of by ASIC, by FMG between August 2004 and March 2005. I am well satisfied that Forrest acted reasonably to ensure that FMG both complied with s 674 of the Act and did not contravene s 1041H of the Act. He did not breach s 180(1) of the Act as alleged by ASIC or at all.

Given the conclusions to which I have come concerning ASIC's case under s 1041H I do not consider it necessary to deal with Forrest's further defence based in s 180(2) concerning the Business judgment rule.

For all these reasons ASIC's Application against each of the defendants should be dismissed. ASIC should pay the costs of each of the defendants. There will be orders accordingly. 
 I certify that the preceding nine hundred and six (906) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gilmour. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 23 December 2009
 
 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr N J Young QC with Mr J A Thomson, Mr D J Crennan and Mr A J Musikanth 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 
 Counsel for the First Defendant: Mr J Karkar QC with Mr B Dharmanada and Mr R J Price 
 
 Solicitor for the First Defendant: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the Second Defendant: Mr A Myers QC with Mr M Thangaraj 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Defendant: Jackson McDonald 
 Date of Hearing: 6-30 April 2009 1-7 May 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 23 December 2009 
 SCHEDULES 'A' 
 
 
 Dramatis Personae 
 
 
 ABB Australia Pty Ltd 
 
 
 Australian Securities and Investments Commission ("ASIC") Plaintiff
 
 
 Australian Securities Exchange Limited ("ASX")
Walsh, Tony, Assistant Manager Issuers
 
 
 Australian, The (Newspaper) 
Armitage, Catherine
Bromby, Robin
 
 
 Barclay Mowlem Construction Ltd ("Barclay Mowlem")
Killinger, Bill, Director and General Manager (Rail)
 
 
 BGC Contracting Pty Ltd ("BGC") 
 
 
 China Harbour Engineering Company (Group) ("CHEC")
Chen Yongkuan, Vice President
Liu Huai Yuan, President
 
 
 China International Trust &amp; Investment Corporation ("CITIC")
Wang Jun, Chairman 
 
 
 China Metallurgical Construction (Group) Corporation ("CMCC")
Ma Yanli, President/ Chairman
Shen Heting, President
Sun Longjun, Second Business Department Manager
Wang Yongguang, Vice President
Yang Changheng, Chairman, 
Zou Wei Min, General Manager
 
 
 China Railway Engineering Corporation ("CREC")
Bai Zhongren, Vice President
Liang, assistant to Mr Zhang
Qin Jiaming, President/ Chairman
Zhang, Kean, Project Manager
 
 
 Chinese Ambassador 
Madam Fu Ying
 
 
 Citigroup 
Fraser, Chris, Vice President Investment Bank 
 
 
 Downer EDI Rail 
Broad, Danny, employee 
 
 
 Expert Witnesses 
 
 
Houston, Gregory, consulting economist employed by NERA Economic Consulting
Keene, Reginald, senior client adviser at Bell Potter Securities
Sisson, Andrew, Managing Director of Balanced Equity Management Pty Limited
Watson, Iain (Dr) Deputy Dean of the UWA Business School
 
 
 External Consultants to FMG 
Bai
Lou-Lin (Lawrence) Xin 
Yin
 
 
 Field Public Relations ("Field PR")
Field, John, Managing Director
Skinner, Kevin, Senior Consultant
 
 
 Fortescue Metals Group Limited ("FMG") First Defendant
Campbell, Rod, Company Secretary
Catlow, Christopher, Chief Financial Officer
Dewar, Todd, Project Engineer
Fisher, Wei, Executive Assistant
Forrest, John Andrew Henry, Second Defendant, Chief Executive Officer and Chairman of 
 Directors of First Defendant.
 
Heyting, Ed, Project Manager of Infrastructure
Huston, Peter, in-house legal counsel 
Kirchlechner, Philip, Head of Marketing
Li, Catherine, Engineer
Liu, David, Head of China Business
Morrin, Juliet, Executive Assistant of Second Defendant
O'Reilly, Louise
Rowley, Graeme, Executive Director Operations
Rui Dana Du, Senior Business Analyst 
Scrimshaw, Russell, Director
Tapp, Julian, Head of Government Relations
Watling, Alan, Chief Operating Officer and Head of Port &amp; Rail
Williams, Jim, Head of Mining Operations
 
 
 Government of Australia 
Farmer, Pat, Assistant Minister for Education
Haase, Barry, Federal Member for Kalgoorlie
Hewett, Kym, Senior Trade Commissioner at the Australian Embassy 
Thomas, Dr Alan, Australian Ambassador to China
Vaile, Mr, Minister for Trade
 
 
 Government of Western Australia 
Brown, Clive, Minister for State Development
 
 
 Leighton Contracting 
 
 
 Leighton Holdings Group 
 
 
 Ministry of Commerce ("MOC")
Chen Jian, Assistant Minister
 
 
 National Development Reform Commission ("NDRC").
He Lianzhong , Deputy Director General, Foreign Capital Utilization Department 
Liu Xuhong , Deputy Director General, Foreign Capital Utilization Department
 
 
 Other Chinese companies 
Chiao United (Fuzhou) Steel Co. Ltd 
China Shougang International Trade &amp; Engineering Corporation
Hebei Wenfeng Iron &amp; Steel Co Ltd 
Ping Xiang Iron &amp; Steel Co. Ltd
Jiangsu Fengli Group Co Ltd 
 
 
 Patersons Securities Ltd ("Patersons")
 
 
 Quantm Ltd 
 
 
 Shanghai Baosteel Group 
 
 
 Sinosteel Corporation ("Sinosteel")
 
 
 State-Owned Assets Supervision and Administrative Commission ("SASAC")
Wang Xiaoqi, Director General of the Bureau of Planning and Development 
 
 
 ThyssenKrupp Engineering (Australia) Pty Ltd ("ThyssenKrupp") 
 
 
 Wong K C, FMG's second largest shareholder in 2004/05 
 
 
 Worley Pty Ltd ("Worley")
 
 SCHEDULE 'B' 
 CREC FRAMEWORK AGREEMENT 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 'C' 
 CHEC FRAMEWORK AGREEMENT 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 'D' 
 CMCC FRAMEWORK AGREEMENT 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 'E' 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1586.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth of Australia [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/71.html</AustLII>
<text>In Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth of Australia [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54 at 72.7, Mason J said: 
No doubt it is correct to say that, where in the recitals to a deed or an agreement it is acknowledged that the parties have agreed to do, or will do, certain acts, a promise to do those acts will be read into the agreement in the absence of an express promise to that effect. Then, there being no indication of a contrary intention, it may safely be inferred that the absence of a contractual provision was due to oversight or inadvertence.

It can be seen from the recitals that FMG accepted CREC's offer to "execute the Works", namely the "Build and Transfer" of the railway.

Applying Mason J's proposition in Ansett Transport Industries [1977] HCA 71 ; 139 CLR 54 , CREC's promise to build and transfer the railway may, arguably, be read into the operational part of the agreement, there being no indication of a contrary intention.

Accordingly, in my view, it is arguable and reasonably so that the Recitals of the agreement record the parameters of the intended agreement, that is, the offer and acceptance of the obligation to build and transfer the railway. Clause 1.1 arguably does not derogate from this obligation. This clause lists the matters which would be the subject of further development and agreement including definitive engineering design to Australian standards. Arguably this is a reference to the definitive feasibility study process which the parties knew had to be completed in order for details of their agreement to be worked out and in particular would define the scope of the Works, the scheduling of the Works and the cost of the Works.

Clause 7 provides that: 
This document represents an agreement in itself and it is recognised a fuller and more detailed agreement not different in intent from this agreement will be developed later.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Aspdin v Austin (1844) 5 QB 671</tocase>
<text>Authority supports an argument that the agreement recorded in the recitals for CREC to build or "execute" the railway should be given effect and should be treated as an agreement between FMG and CREC even where the operative provisions of the framework agreement do not contain such a provision and there is nothing inconsistent with such a construction in the operative provisions: Buckland v Buckland [1900] 2 Ch 534 at 540.3; MacKenzie v Childers (1889) 43 Ch D 265 at 274.7, 275.4-276.1; Ex parte Dawes; in re Moon (1886) 17 QBD 275 , 286.8, 288.2, 289.7; Aspdin v Austin (1844) 5 QB 671 at 683. This is even more so where, as here, the framework agreements were not drawn by lawyers. They were drafted by Heyting, an engineer, who also holds a Masters of Business Administration and who had some training in contract management. In those circumstances, arguably, a distinction between recitals and operational clauses should not be rigorously applied in an attempt to determine the parties' intention, determined objectively. Expressly, the recitals proceed on the basis that there is an agreement for the relevant Chinese contractor to build the infrastructure which is sought to be recorded in the framework agreements. The recitals do not say or imply that what follows is merely an informal arrangement, or a mere agreement to negotiate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Commission v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1973] HCA 36 ; (1973) 129 CLR 99</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1973/36.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG makes the following submission which I accept as a correct statement of the law. The proper construction of an agreement should be determined by what reasonable people in the position of the parties would have understood by the relevant clauses by considering not only their text, but also the surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the transaction: e.g. Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at [40] ; International Air Transport Association v Ansett Australia Holdings Ltd [2008] HCA 3 ; (2008) 234 CLR 151 at [8] and [53]. The whole of the document should be considered and its provisions given harmonious effect: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1973] HCA 36 ; (1973) 129 CLR 99 at 109 (Gibbs J, in dissent, but not on the applicable principle).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games (1988) 18 NSWLR 540</tocase>
<text>ASIC submits in written closing submission that the authorities such as Anaconda, Pagnan SpA, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games Ltd (1988) 18 NSWLR 540 and Uranium Equities v Fewster [2008] WASCA 33 ; (2008) 36 WAR 97 relied on by FMG state that whether or not the parties intended to contract, they must agree on such terms, normally described as essential terms, such that the contract could be enforced or made complete by implying terms or applying considerations of reasonableness. I will consider these authorities further. In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the Court of Appeal found that a binding contract had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement "constituted an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form". At [28], Ipp J referred to the following statement by Sugerman J, approved by Menzies J in Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 at 607: 
It is a first principle of the law of contracts that there can be no binding and enforceable obligation unless the terms of the bargain, or at least its essential and critical terms, have been agreed upon. So, there is no concluded contract where an essential or critical term is expressly left to be settled by future agreement of the parties. Again, there is no binding contract where the language used is so obscure and incapable of any precise or definite meaning that the court is unable to attribute to the parties any particular contractual intentions.

In Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR 540 Gleeson CJ, with whom Hope and Mahoney JJA agreed, confirmed at 584E-F the importance in a Masters v Cameron type of dispute of assessing the parties' intention to make a concluded bargain, and stated that the question of intention is distinct from, although it may be closely related to, the question whether the parties have reached agreement upon such terms as are, in the circumstances, legally necessary to constitute a contract. His Honour stated: 
Nevertheless, in the ordinary case, as a matter of fact and commonsense,
other things being equal, the more numerous and significant the areas in
respect of which the parties have failed to reach agreement, the slower a
court will be to conclude that they had the requisite contractual intention.

ASIC also points to the absence of the following from the framework agreements: no provision for choice of contractors or the selection of materials; no definition of "practical completion"; and no specifications for any design elements of the infrastructure. The documents referred to in the Recitals to each agreement would have, no doubt, assisted in clarifying the matters absent from the agreements. In light of those documents, following the approach of Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [61] , it may have been possible to conclude that, despite the long list of matters said to render the framework agreements uncertain and incomplete, there was a binding contract, workable by implying terms or on the proper construction of the agreement. The court will apply orthodox principles of implying terms by reference to the implied duty to co-operate and use considerations of reasonableness, to give effect to that intention: Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR 540; Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd v Hebron Park Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60. The asserted uncertainty or incompleteness may therefore be overcome once the requisite intention to contract is found to be present.

The approach taken in G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631, Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 and Tasman Capital [2008] NSWCA 248 was followed very recently by the Queensland Court of Appeal in Moffat Property Development Group [2009] QCA 60 , mentioned above, which underlined the importance of the parties' manifest intention to contract. The issue was whether a contract for the sale of rural residential land had been made by an exchange of letters. The Queensland Court of Appeal held that the parties intended to be legally bound through their exchange of correspondence and that there was a contract even though matters such as the timing of completion and arrangements at settlement, the precise timing of the payment of the deposit, the place of settlement, responsibility for insurance, GST issues and the terms of a put and call option were not spelt out in the correspondence. Keane JA delivered the court's judgment. His Honour: 
(a) accepted McHugh JA's point in G R Securities that "the decisive issue is always the intention of the parties": [23]-[25];
 
(b) said "the terms of the correspondence exchanged between the parties contemplated the execution of a further contract as the means whereby the bargain which they had concluded would be implemented. It is necessarily implicit in such an agreement that the parties will co-operate to do what must be done to make the further agreement": [30];
 
(c) adopted McHugh JA's approach in G R Securities and explained that the implied obligation of each party to co-operate with the other to ensure each side obtains the benefit of its bargain serves to supply the deficiencies: [34];
 
(d) cited Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR at 548 in stating: "I am of the view that there can be no doubt as to the orthodoxy of referring to 'implied terms or ... considerations of reasonableness' in order to determine whether the parties' 'consensus is sufficiently comprehensive to be legally binding : [51].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1678.html</AustLII>
<text>In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Leahy Petroleum [2004] FCA 1678 ; (2004) 141 FCR 183 , Merkel J, who was dealing with admissions in the context of proceedings against a company under the TPA, stated at [118]: 
 "(c) Admissions in the s 155 examinations 
 
 
 [118] Although s 84(2) of the (Trade Practices) Act does not extend to admissions (see TNT Management at 19 and Trade Practices Commission v Nicholas Enterprises Pty Ltd (1979) 26 ALR 609 at 633 (" Nicholas Enterprises ")), there are a number of circumstances in which the admissions of a servant or agent in relation to past events may be admissible against the principal. A servant or agent may have authority to make admissions about past events by virtue of the servant's or agent's general or specifically delegated authority to answer inquires of a particular nature: see TNT Management at 18. The inquiries may include dealing with investigating authorities in any matter concerning the business: see Nicholas Enterprises at 632.

Senior counsel for ASIC submits that s 87 of the Evidence Act may be applied to admissions in a s 19 transcript in the same way as it was applied in ACCC v Leahy [2004] FCA 1678 ; 141 FCR 183 to admissions made in examinations under s 155 of the TPA. I accept that submission.

Senior counsel for FMG did not take issue with the authenticity of the signatures of Rowley and Watling on the transcripts. He also indicated that FMG had no objection to my reading those transcripts and deriving from them whatever assistance I could. However, he said the representations in the transcripts could not be viewed as admissions because they were not adverse to FMG's case.

In Part 1 of the Dictionary of the Evidence Act , "admission" is defined as follows. 
 admission means a previous representation that is:
 
 
 (a) made by a person who is or becomes a party to a proceeding (including a defendant in a criminal proceeding); and 
 
 
 (b) adverse to the person's interest in the outcome of the proceeding.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Mayo International Pty Ltd (1998) ATPR 41-653</tocase>
<text>Merkel J noted at [120] that s 87(1)(b) of the Evidence Act has been applied in the context of cases brought pursuant to the TPA such as Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Mayo International Pty Ltd (1998) ATPR 41-653.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2001) 115 FCR 442</tocase>
<text>Further authority for the availability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel in civil penalty proceedings is found in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2001) 115 FCR 442 , where Hill J stated at [33]: 
Where the proceedings are criminal (and the present proceedings are not; they are proceedings, inter alia, for the recovery of a civil penalty) it might be thought that the failure of the accused to go into evidence should not lead to the drawing of Jones v Dunkel inferences. After all it is clear that a witness can not be compelled to give evidence which is likely to incriminate the witness or expose the witness to a penalty. However, even in criminal cases it has been held that the failure of the accused, who is in a position to deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced by the prosecution, to give evidence will permit the jury to draw inferences adverse to the accused more readily: see Azzopardi v R [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 179 ALR 349 , affirming Weissensteiner v R [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217. A fortiori, therefore, the failure of a respondent to proceedings for recovery of a pecuniary penalty to give evidence on a matter relevant to an issue in the proceeding and deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced against the respondent will permit the Court more readily to draw the inferences to which the decision in Jones v Dunkel refers.

In Council of the New South Wales Bar Association v Power [2008] NSWCA 135 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 451 at [21] , a proceeding seeking removal of a legal practitioner from the Roll, Hodgson JA, with whom Beazley and McColl JJA agreed, referred to the High Court's conclusion in Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 that it was open to a trial judge in a criminal case to make a comment relating to the absence of evidence of additional facts peculiarly within the knowledge of the accused. Hodgson JA went on to say at [22] concerning the case before him that: 
If this had been a criminal trial, then in my opinion what the High Court said in Azzopardi would have meant that a jury could have been told that inferences from proved facts could more safely be drawn because the opponent elected not to give any explanation in terms of additional facts peculiarly within his knowledge or any evidence of such facts. In my opinion, if such Jones v Dunkel reasoning is available to a jury in a criminal trial, it must a fortiori be available to a court in civil proceedings such as the present. That would be so, even if these civil proceedings are regarded as proceedings for a civil penalty. I note that a similar view was expressed by Hill J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1800 ; (2001) 201 ALR 502 at [33] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Cycclone Magnetic Engines Inc [2009] QSC 58</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QSC/2009/58.html</AustLII>
<text>In Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Cycclone Magnetic Engines Inc [2009] QSC 58 , Martin J was asked to consider whether publications including television news film made on Cycclone's website was in relation to a financial product (at [124]). Evidence was adduced that the defendant had referred prospective shareholders to its website (at [125]). Martin J stated at [146] and [147]: 
[146] The web site was, no doubt, intended to fulfil a number of functions. One would have been to publicise CME in a general way. Another was to allow interested persons to contact CME - the web site contained a feedback page. Another was, as the home page made clear, "to obtain... direct investment and to complete the development program". 
 
 
[147] The conduct of CME in placing the film on the web site and then describing it as showing the engine working is relevantly indistinguishable from writing an ASX release to the same effect, especially in the context of the introductory words on the home page about "obtaining direct investment", that is, shares in CME. That conduct, therefore, comes within s 1041H.

Forrest submits that these observations suggest that publicising FMG in a general way is not conduct in relation to a financial product. I do not agree. Martin J's comments at [147] demonstrate that he viewed the conduct in placing the film on the web site and then describing it as showing the engine working is relevantly indistinguishable from writing an ASX release to the same effect. His Honour's use of the word 'especially' in that paragraph indicates that that conclusion was reinforced by, and not dependent upon, the introductory words on the home page about obtaining direct investment.

FMG sent the 23 August Letter, 2004 Annual Financial Report, 2004 Annual Report, September Quarterly Report, 5 November Letter, 8 November Letter, November Presentation, December Quarterly Report, February Presentation and Bag of Rusty Nails Presentation to the ASX. The letters were re-published to the market in the ordinary course by the ASX. It does not dispute that those publications were in relation to a financial product.

Further FMG published the 23 August Media Release, 5 November Media Release and February Presentation on its website. The 23 August Letter and the 5 November Letter referred readers to FMGs website. It does not dispute that those publications were in relation to a financial product.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Fortescue Metals Group Ltd [No 2] (2009) 176 FCR 529</tocase>
<text>ASIC tendered signed transcripts of examinations conducted pursuant to s 19 of the ASIC Act of Rowley and Watling. The transcripts were sought to be tendered under ss 81 and 87 of the Evidence Act as evidence of admissions made on behalf of FMG. On 29 April 2009, during the trial, I ruled that, upon proof of the authenticity of the examinees' signatures and my satisfaction that the transcripts contain relevant admissions, the transcripts were admissible: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Fortescue Metals Group Ltd [No 2] (2009) 176 FCR 529 at [44].



Rowley's alleged admissions in his s 19 examination and proffered by ASIC as admissions by FMG pursuant to s 87 are: 
At all material times Rowley was a director of FMG. The knowledge he acquired in his capacity as such was therefore FMG's knowledge. [p 5 lines 15-36]
 
 
Rowley, and therefore FMG, knew, from at least 14 October 2004, that the Chinese Government had decided that the equity issue was to be resolved before there was to be further progress. [p 58 lines 8-9 39-45; p 59 lines 1-4 ] ]
 
 
Rowley, and therefore FMG, knew, from around 14 October 2004, that:
 NDRC had directed the Chinese Steel Mills not to deal directly with FMG any further, but rather to deal through (C)MCC; the process of trying to get off take agreements signed with specific steel mills had started to slow down; this had been orchestrated by the NDRC; and there was not going to be progress until there was an agreement about equity. 
 
[p 59 lines 6-17]
 
 
Rowley knew or believed that negotiations in relation to the equity participation were probably first raised when FMG started negotiations post CREC and started to involve (C)MCC and the wider China. At around that time NDRC became very much a party. [p 66 lines 27-34]
 
 
As at 22 January 2005, Rowley, and therefore FMG, knew or believed that CREC, CHEC and (C)MCC were not acting on their obligations because: 
 the issue of equity had not been resolved; and as far as China was concerned, until that issue was resolved, the agreements as they stood would not be actioned. [p 67 lines 5-7; p 69 lines 8-17]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; (2009) 256 ALR 199</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2009/287.html</AustLII>
<text>In conclusion, the standard of proof that I must apply is the balance of probabilities as prescribed by s 1332, and I accept that in deciding whether ASIC's allegations are made out on the balance of probabilities I am required to take into account the causes of action and the gravity of the matters alleged and their consequences: s 140(2) Evidence Act ; Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; 60 CLR 336. If inferences are to be drawn, ASIC has to establish that the circumstances appearing from the evidence give rise to a reasonable and definite inference and not merely to conflicting inferences of equal degrees of probability: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; (2009) 256 ALR 199 at [186] ; Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; 162 FCR 466 at [38] .

The authorities state that two inferences are involved in the rule in Jones v Dunkel . First, a court might infer that the evidence of the absent witness would not have assisted the party that failed to call that witness; secondly, a court might draw, with greater confidence, any inference unfavourable to the party that failed to call that witness, if that witness appears to be in a position to cast light on whether the inference should be drawn: Manly Council v Byrne and Anor [2004] NSWCA 123 at [51] ; ASIC v Macdonald [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 per Gzell J at [1137].

ASIC cites the recent decision in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199. It submits that the information about the Deed of Covenant and Indemnity which formed the basis of ASIC's claim against James Hardie Industries Limited made under the predecessor section to s 674 was information about the significance and effect of that Deed: at [484], as to which the defendants were too emphatic in understating the effect of this information in market releases. Yet what occurred there was the complete failure by the company to disclose the existence of certain covenants, an indemnity and the obligation to make certain payments. It was not a case, such as the present, involving, in effect, differing opinions as to the meaning and effect of agreements as a whole. I do not find it, in that respect, to be of any assistance.

I will then, against this background, consider whether the only reasonable opinion as to the meaning and legal effect of each framework agreement is as expressed in the Informations or whether the opinion of FMG that each was an enforceable agreement to build, transfer and finance the relevant Project infrastructure was reasonably held.

It is accepted that, in substance, each framework agreement is mutatis mutandis to the same effect. I will consider then the CREC Framework Agreement. However my conclusions will apply to all three framework agreements.

ASIC submits that had such advice been obtained, the misleading statements could not have been made by a responsible company or board of directors and that the failure by FMG to obtain legal advice is a relevant consideration. ASIC did not lead expert opinion evidence as to what such an opinion was likely to have been had it been sought. ASIC referred to ASIC v Macdonald [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199. There, Gzell J found at [1275] that ASIC had made out its case that the company, James Hardie Industries Limited, negligently failed to disclose information concerning the restructuring of the company in contravention of Listing Rule 3.1 and s 1001A(2) of the Corporations Law as carried over into the Act for reasons including that it did not obtain any legal advice as to whether it should disclose the information. The information did not consist of an opinion as to the meaning and legal effect of an agreement.

ASIC pleads at ASC [102] that by 26 January 2005, FMG and Forrest were aware firstly that CREC, CHEC and CMCC did not regard the framework agreements as requiring them to construct and finance the infrastructure necessary for the Project; and secondly that the agreements did not have the effect of obliging those companies to construct and finance the infrastructure. Among the particulars relied on by ASIC to establish FMG's and Forrest's knowledge are the minutes of a meeting of FMG's directors including Forrest on 22 January 2005, and Huston's attendance at the meetings on 16 and 17 January 2005 involving FMG and the representatives of CREC, CHEC and CMCC, together with Huston's status as a qualified, experienced and practicing commercial solicitor. I have discussed in some detail the meetings of 16 and 17 January in Part 9. At those meetings, FMG and the Chinese Contractors discussed their relationship and sought to reach agreement on the size of the equity interest that FMG would grant to a Chinese entity. I have found that the Chinese suggestion at the 17 January meeting that the previous agreements were merely MOUs was a negotiating tactic employed to advance their case for a majority equity interest in the Project. ASIC did not specify in its pleading what aspect of the 22 January minutes it was relying on to establish either or both of these assertions. In fact, ASIC made no reference to this document in oral or written submissions. Further, ASIC did not plead nor explain in submissions just how it was that Huston's attendance at the 16 and 17 January meetings and his status as a qualified, experienced and practicing commercial solicitor advanced ASIC's assertions.

The CHEC Framework Agreement was executed on 1 October 2004. The CMCC Framework Agreement was executed on 20 October 2004.

In ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 at the time of both alleged continuous disclosure contraventions there was a negative perception in the market place in relation to the shares of the holding company due to its asbestos liability. Gzell J noted at [507] that the reasonable person would think on receipt of the information concerning the covenants and indemnities that the company's asbestos claim liability had been controlled and that the blight upon its share price had been removed. In relation to the second set of information, his Honour noted that the severing of the company's connection to its asbestos liability was positive information and likely to reduce negative sentiment in the market regarding the company's shares: [1121].

ASIC refers to the recent decision of Gzell J in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 where Mr Macdonald, the chief executive officer and a director of James Hardie Industries Limited was held to have contravened s 180(1) by: making false or misleading statements at a press conference; and 
 approving, or failing to advise not to release, or failing to remove matters that were false or misleading from, an ASX announcement which contained over-emphatic statements and which were false or misleading.

Mr Macdonald and number of other directors were also held to have contravened s 180(1) by approving a draft ASX announcement which contained false or misleading or deceptive statements about the funding of a medical research and compensation fund that the company was establishing. His Honour stated that the directors ought to have been and they should have realised that they were prevented from approving the unequivocal and unqualified statements as to certainty of sufficient funding in the draft announcement.

In the present case, ASIC pleads (ASC [166(b)(1)]) that the information in each of FMG's disclosures was published to "persons who commonly invest in securities in the ASX's financial market". Further, ASIC pleads that FMG's conduct in publishing the information, making the statements and representations, or creating the impressions associated with the disclosures was conduct "designed to encourage reasonable investors in the ASX's financial market to invest, or to continue investments, in the First Defendant". This formulation I regard as no different, in substance, to the language of s 677 of the Act, namely the question of the influence or likely influence of information upon common investors. I do not think it is intended by ASIC to describe an actual causal consequence but merely an encouraging or influencing factor.

ASIC, borrowing from the language of Gzell J, submits that FMG's and Forrest's disclosures to the market between 23 August 2004 and 24 March 2005 were likewise emphatic, unequivocal and unqualified.

Thus while ASIC is not required to prove that FMG intended to engage in misleading or deceptive conduct to establish contraventions of s 1041H, evidence of intent will allow the Court to readily infer that the intention has been effective. ASIC submits that the evidence supports a finding that FMG and Forrest in particular intended to mislead and deceive investors and potential investors in FMG shares. The Representees

The various persons to whom ASIC claims FMG made the disclosures were: reasonable investors in the ASX's financial market; media publishers; the audience of the media publishers; persons obtaining access to media releases, FMG's letters to the ASX and other company reports on FMG's website; media representatives who attended a telephone press conference conducted by Mr Forrest on 23 August 2004; the audience of the Business Sunday television program broadcast on or about 17 October 2004; and attendees at conferences between August 2004 and March 2005 where Forrest gave presentations on behalf of FMG. Relevance of media commentary

ASIC's claim that the disclosures were false and misleading is pleaded against a factual background summarised by ASIC at ASC [18], subparas (a) to (v). That background is derived from 265 documents listed in Schedule 10 to the ASC. The documents included in the Schedule are from the following sources: Letters, media releases, conference and meeting presentations, progress reports and statutory reports provided to the ASX by FMG; and
 Media reports published by newswire services such as Australian Associated Press Financial News Wire; and by national and capital city newspapers including the Australian Financial Review, The Australian, The Sydney Morning Herald, The Age, and The West Australian.

ASIC submits that the elements found in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 that led Gzell J to find that Macdonald had breached his duties as a director are present in this case in that Forrest: 
(a) was Chairman and Chief Executive Officer; 
 
 
(b) had control and responsibility for the making of ASX announcements; 
 
 
(c) was intimately involved in the preparation and approval of the various announcements and the later company presentations; 
 
 
(d) knew full well that the statements were false, misleading and deceptive and that unqualified and emphatic statements could not be made concerning the execution of binding, build and transfer contracts by the three Chinese contractors; 
 
 
(e) knew that the ASX announcements and the company presentations had been crafted to induce a positive effect on the price or value of FMG shares by positively influencing investors; 
 
 
(f) knew that this conduct exposed FMG to serious risks to its reputation and placed it in likely contravention of important provisions of the Act; 
 
 
(g) knew that the false announcements withheld from the market the true information concerning the terms, legal effect and significance of the actual framework agreements, which steps placed FMG at risk of likely contravention of s 674.

It is not in issue that Forrest was, at all material times prior to about 17 May 2005, the chairman of directors and chief executive officer of the first defendant; and that he has, since on or about 17 May 2005, been FMG's chief executive officer.

In his closing written submissions, Forrest points out that ASIC did not tender any direct evidence regarding his, or any other FMG directors' duties or call expert evidence regarding the role of a director or a chief executive officer in a company like FMG at the material times. Forrest also points out that ASIC had sought to tender parts of his s 19 ASIC Act examination transcript but withdrew the tender after he sought to include parts of the explanatory and contextual portions of his examination transcript.

ASIC emphasized the recent judgment in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 , where Gzell J held that the Chief Executive Officer, Macdonald, and a number of other directors, had breached their duties under s 180. Gzell J held that Macdonald failed to advise the board of the company that the draft ASX announcement was expressed in too emphatic terms concerning the sufficiency of funds held by the foundation to meet all legitimate asbestos claims and that as a result the ASX announcement was misleading and deceptive. He also found that Macdonald failed to properly advise the board as to the fact that the cash flow model supporting the statements concerning funding had not verified the key assumptions contained in the model. I have already considered this case, which turns on its own facts. It is of no particular assistance in the resolution of this issue concerning Forrest.

Forrest does not dispute that he knew of FMG's duties regarding Listing Rule 3.1 but says FMG did not breach s 674(2) of the Act.

Alternatively, Forrest says, if FMG breached s 674(2) of the Act (which is denied), for the reasons regarding Forrest's honest and reasonable beliefs, a reasonable person in Forrest's position and FMG's circumstances would have acted the same way that Forrest did.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Maxwell (No 2) [2006] NSWSC 1052 ; (2006) 59 ACSR 373</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2006/1052.html</AustLII>
<text>The meaning and effect of s 180(1) was recently analysed by Brereton J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Maxwell (No 2) [2006] NSWSC 1052 ; (2006) 59 ACSR 373 at [99] - [102] and in turn adopted by Gzell J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Macdonald at [236], and by Hamilton J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sydney Investment House Equities Pty Ltd [2008] NSWSC 1224 ; (2008) 69 ACSR 1 at [27] .

Significantly, for this case, a director or other officer may breach his duties by allowing the company to contravene a provision of the Act if that contravention is likely to result in jeopardy to the interests of the company. Brereton J in ASIC v Maxwell (No 2) [2006] NSWSC 1052 ; 59 ACSR 373 said: if a contravention of s 180(1) is to be established, it must be founded on jeopardy to the interests of the corporation, and not to protection of the interests of potential investors: [105]
 relevant jeopardy to the interests of the company may be found in the actual or potential exposure of the company to civil penalties or other liability under the act, and it may no doubt be a breach of the relevant duty for a director to embark on or authorise a course which attracts the risk of that exposure, at least if the risk is clear and the countervailing potential benefits insignificant: [104]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Narain [2008] FCAFC 120 ; (2008) 169 FCR 211</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/120.html</AustLII>
<text>The effect of the amendments was to expand the scope of s 1041H beyond dealing in securities to any misleading and deceptive conduct in relation to a financial product or financial services. The Full Federal Court has recognised that the scope of the operation of s 1041H is very wide: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Narain [2008] FCAFC 120 ; (2008) 169 FCR 211. Special leave to appeal to the High Court was refused: Narain v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2008] HCATrans 408 per Crennan and Kiefel JJ. Section 1041H: general principles

He submits that the words "in relation to" signify the need for there to be some relationship or correlation between FMG's conduct and its shares: ASIC v Narain [2008] FCAFC 120 ; 169 FCR 211 per Jacobson and Gordon JJ at [69] and [74]. There the respondent was the managing director of Citrofresh International Ltd (CTF). The respondent was involved in the writing of an "ASX Release" which claimed that CTF's products could reduce the spread of four major viruses including HIV/AIDS. The respondent instructed CTF's secretary to send the statement to the Australian Stock Exchange who published it. The statement affected the price of CTF shares.

It was held at first instance that the ASX Release did not contain representations "in relation to" CTF's shares pursuant to s 1041H of the Act because the statement did not refer to shares on the face of it, or deal with the shares directly. This construction was rejected by the Full Court which held that the phase "in relation to" in s 1041H of the Act only requires an indirect or less than substantial connection between the misleading conduct or statement and the financial product and that it is not necessary for a statement to expressly refer to the shares or to deal with the shares on its face.

In deciding that the respondent engaged in conduct in relation to a financial product, CTF's shares, by publishing the statement on the ASX, Finkelstein J held that there was a sufficient connection between the statement and CTF's shares by reason of (1) the content of the statements, which concerned the business of CTF; and (2) the place of their publication, namely on the the exchange where the shares were traded. Jacobson and Gordon JJ said the concept of misleading and deceptive conduct is one which embraces all of the circumstances in which the conduct takes place, and that the relevant conduct was not merely the text of the announcement. Their Honours said the statement was an announcement made to the ASX about a "landmark" test result for the company's products and was disclosure to the market.

Forrest submits that the Court's ratio in Narain was that CTF's representations contained in announcements made to the ASX were "in relation to a financial product" because the representations were published where shares were traded. I do not think this was what their Honour's intended although the announcement in that case was made to the ASX. For Finkelstein J, the publication on the ASX was just one of two factors giving rise to the connection between the statement and the relevant financial product.

The RIU Explorers Conference brochure discloses that it was attended by representatives of a considerable number of mining companies. It appears to have been a professional conference. The RIU Presentation was not sent to the ASX. I am however not persuaded, for lack of evidence as to the attendees, that the RIU Presentation at the RIU Explorers Conference meets the statutory description as construed in ASIC v Narain [2008] FCAFC 120 ; 169 FCR 211 .

There is no precise evidence as to who attended the AJM Iron Ore and Steel Forecast where the Bag of Rusty Nails Presentation was given. I have described this as the "first disclosure". However, Kirchlechner had attended this conference for a number of years and he said that typically, amongst others, there were brokers who attended. I take him to be referring to stock brokers. A copy of the PowerPoint slides used in the presentation was sent to the ASX. I have described this as the "second disclosure". These contain information amongst other things as to the source of FMG's funding for the Project including $630m from "China Rail"; $571m from "China Harbour"and $306m from "China Metallurgical". These are references to CREC, CHEC and CMCC. The amounts are said to be "under agreement". I accept that this conveys the impression of binding agreements between FMG and each of those companies. This information lies in the context of public knowledge of the fact of the execution of these three agreements as binding agreements. They therefore constitute, in effect, a re-publication of that information to the market and therefore is conduct in relation to a financial product. I am satisfied that the first and second disclosures constituted conduct by FMG in relation to a financial product. General principles in relation to s 52 are applicable</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229</tocase>
<text>These are civil penalty proceedings, not criminal proceedings, and it would be contrary to the legislative intention underlying the civil penalty provisions to apply a de facto criminal standard of proof in such proceedings: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229 at [408].

Finally, in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229, Austin J concluded at [458] that, having considered the reasoning in Dyers and Adler , the principle in Jones v Dunkel is applicable against either party to civil penalty proceedings.

Unique amongst other corporate officers, the chief executive officer stands at the apex of the operational and managerial structures of the company, and his or her authority is qualified only by any residual power left in the board: Randall v Aristocrat Leisure Ltd [2004] NSWSC 411. A chairperson of a listed public company may have special responsibilities beyond those of other non-executive directors. These responsibilities include such things as the public announcement of information: ASIC v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229 at 463.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Rich (No 3) [2003] NSWSC 328 ; (2003) 21 ACLC 920</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2003/328.html</AustLII>
<text>Turning to the civil penalty authorities, in Rich , the High Court reversed a decision of the New South Wales Court of Appeal ( Rich v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 342 ; (2003) 203 ALR 671) that the defendants in civil penalty proceedings brought by ASIC were not permitted to resist an order for discovery made by the trial judge by claiming the privilege against self-exposure to penalty. The orders sought by ASIC included disqualification orders but not pecuniary penalties. The trial judge, Austin J, did not classify the proceedings as proceedings for the imposition of a penalty: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich (No 3) [2003] NSWSC 328 ; (2003) 21 ACLC 920 , at [53]. the Court of Appeal (Spigelman CJ, with whom Ipp JA agreed; McColl JA dissenting) upheld Austin J's ruling, identifying a disqualification order as having an exclusively protective purpose and stating that it should not be characterized as a penalty for the purposes of the penalty privilege. However, the High Court (Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ, Kirby J dissenting) decided that the disqualification order was a penalty and accordingly the proper course was to refuse any order for discovery: per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ at [37]-[40]. The ruling was made in the joint judgment in consideration of s 1317L of the Act which requires the application of the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters when hearing proceedings for a declaration of contravention or a pecuniary penalty order. Their honours concluded at [19] that that the statute itself requires the application of the body of law which has developed in relation to the privileges against penalties and forfeitures when deciding whether an order for discovery should be made.

The Rich cases therefore turned on the issue of whether a disqualification order was a penalty. It was not in dispute that the privilege against exposure to penalty protected a defendant in civil proceedings not only from being obliged to give discovery, but also from being subject to any direction that affidavits or witness statements be provided to the plaintiff prior to the hearing or at any time prior to the conclusion of the plaintiff's case: see e.g. Austin J at first instance: [2003] NSWSC 328 ; (2003) 21 ACLC 920 , at [19]-[30]. In their judgments, neither the High Court nor the Court of Appeal considered the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel ; Austin J mentioned it briefly in passing at [58].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission v Southcorp Ltd [2003] FCA 1369 ; (2003) 130 FCR 406</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/1369.html</AustLII>
<text>The legislative history of the continuous disclosure provisions was reviewed by Lindgren J in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v Southcorp Ltd [2003] FCA 1369 ; (2003) 130 FCR 406 at [7] - [16] . I gratefully adopt his Honour's review in part: 
[7] A review of the legislative history of the continuous disclosure provisions shows the importance that the legislature and the regulator have attached to them, and the publicity which has been given to them.
 
 
[8] In June 1991 the then Commonwealth Attorney-General, Michael Duffy, requested the Companies and Securities Advisory Committee (the Committee) to examine the need for a legislatively-based continuous disclosure regime.
 
 
[9] The Committee reported in September 1991. It noted that while the Corporations Law (the Law) required disclosure of information in particular sets of circumstances, it did not contain a comprehensive scheme for the full and accurate disclosure of market sensitive information on a timely basis. The Committee noted that Australian Stock Exchange (ASX) Listing Rules required a listed company or trust to notify its home exchange "immediately" of any information that was necessary to avoid the establishment of a false market in its securities, or that was likely to affect materially the price of its securities. The Committee recommended the introduction of a statute-based enhanced disclosure regime which would:
 
 overcome the inability of general market forces to guarantee adequate and timely disclosure by disclosing entities;
 encourage greater securities research by investors and advisors, thereby ensuring that securities prices more closely, and quickly, reflect underlying economic values;
 ensure that equity and loan resources in the Australian market are more effectively channelled into appropriate investments, and that funds are withheld or withdrawn from poorly performing disclosing entities. This will promote capital market efficiency;
 assist debt holders in monitoring the performance of disclosing entities and thereby determine whether, or when, to exercise any right to withdraw or reinvest their loan funds, or convert debt to equity;
 act as a further, or substitute warning device for holders of charges over corporate assets, that breaches in covenants may have taken place, or the risk of default has increased;
 assist potential equity or debt holders of disclosing entities to better evaluate their investment alternatives;
 lessen the possible distorting effects of rumour on securities prices;
 minimise the opportunities for insider trading or similar market abuses;
 improve managerial performance and accountability by giving the market more timely indicators of corporate performance;
 encourage the growth of information systems within disclosing entities. This assists directors in their decision making and compliance with their fiduciary duties; and
 reduce the time and costs involved when preparing takeover and prospectus documents.
 
[10] Following a process of consultation, the Government decided to introduce continuous disclosure provisions into the Law. On the Second Reading Speech on the Corporate Law Reform Act (No 2) 1992 (Cth), which contained continuous disclosure provisions proposed to commence on 31 December 1993, Senator Bolkus, Minister for Administrative Services, stated:
 
 
 
 ... an effective disclosure system will often be a significant inhibition on questionable corporate conduct. Knowledge that such conduct will be quickly exposed to the glare of publicity, as well as criticism by shareholders and the financial press, makes it less likely to occur in the first place. 
 
 

 
 
 
 In essence, a well-informed market leads to greater investor confidence and, in turn, to a greater willingness to invest in Australian business. ( Australia, Debates, Senate , (1992), p 3581) 
 
 

 
[11] The continuous disclosure provisions were eventually introduced as ss 1001A, 1001B, 1001C and 1001D of the Law by the Corporate Law Reform Act 1994 (Cth) s 4 , Sch 1, Item 92, and commenced on 4 September 1994. Subsection 1001A(2) provided that a listed disclosing entity must not contravene the continuous disclosure provisions of the listing rules of a securities exchange applicable to the entity, by 'intentionally, recklessly, or negligently' failing to notify the securities exchange of information that was not generally available, and which, if it were generally available, a reasonable person would expect to have a material effect on the price or value of the securities of the entity.

In November 1996, the Companies and Securities Advisory Committee (CASAC) conducted a review of the continuous disclosure regime introduced in 1994, and released a report entitled "Report on Continuous Disclosure". In that review, a survey had been conducted of listed disclosing entities. The CASAC report concluded that the regime was operating effectively for those entities. The report stated at para 1.7: 
Respondents to this survey considered that continuous disclosure had helped to keep the market, and investors in listed disclosing entities, more informed. Continuous disclosure also reinforced the obligations on directors and management to disclose material information to the market. Respondents considered that investors gained a better and more timely understanding of the issues facing the company and how these might affect the value of their shares. Continuous disclosure also encouraged listed entities to formalise their lines of internal communication to ensure that the directors and senior management were fully informed of all events affecting the price or value of the entity's securities. Overall, the respondents considered that continuous disclosure encouraged greater investor confidence in the price discovery mechanism of the securities market.

The majority of the 70 listed disclosing entities who responded to the CASAC survey, indicated, in relation to question 22 dealing with external advice, that they had sought professional advice, mainly from law firms, on the application of continuous disclosure requirements. That advice included whether disclosure was required in the circumstances, the operation of the provisions which created exceptions to mandatory disclosure, and whether certain information would have a material effect on the price or value of securities. The present case includes consideration of whether legal advice was given to FMG concerning FMG's continuous disclosure obligations; the effect of any such legal advice and the reasonableness of the defendants' reliance on any such advice.

On the commencement of the Financial Services Reform Act 2001 (Cth) on 11 March 2002, s 1001A, which contained the original continuous disclosure obligations, was replaced by s 674 in a new Chapter 6CA of the Act. The Revised Explanatory Memorandum for the Financial Services Reform Bill 2001 explained that the placement of the continuous disclosure provisions near Chapter 6D reflected the fact that these provisions deal with ongoing disclosure obligations in relation to securities as defined for the purposes of Chapters 6D and 7. The Revised Explanatory Memorandum also explained: 
Proposed section 674...generally replicates section 1001A of the Corporations Act , subject to changes in terminology. In order to comply with the Criminal Code , the fault elements currently contained in subsections 1001A(2) and (3) have been omitted and the default fault elements under the Code will apply in future to offences against this provision. Proposed section 678 applies the Criminal Code to all offences in Chapter 6CA at commencement.

The Revised Explanatory Memorandum also explained that contravention of the continuous disclosure provisions would give rise to a liability for financial services civil penalty provisions, in line with the approach taken to a number of other prohibitions related to market misconduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Sydney Investment House Equities Pty Ltd [2008] NSWSC 1224 ; (2008) 69 ACSR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2008/1224.html</AustLII>
<text>The meaning and effect of s 180(1) was recently analysed by Brereton J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Maxwell (No 2) [2006] NSWSC 1052 ; (2006) 59 ACSR 373 at [99] - [102] and in turn adopted by Gzell J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Macdonald at [236], and by Hamilton J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sydney Investment House Equities Pty Ltd [2008] NSWSC 1224 ; (2008) 69 ACSR 1 at [27] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>AWA Ltd v Daniels t/as Deloitte Haskins &amp; Sells (1992) 7 ACSR 759</tocase>
<text>I accept ASIC's submission that a chief executive officer or managing director may reasonably be expected to have more information available to him or her and to be more diligent than other board members. The title, Managing Director, is synonymous with Chief Executive Officer. This matter of principle may be discerned from a number of authorities. A managing director has a particular responsibility to make sure the other directors understand the potential harm in a proposed transaction: Permanent Building Society v Wheeler (1994) 11 WAR 187, at 241. A chief executive officer will be employed under a contract containing an express or implied term that he or she exercise the care and skill expected of a person in that position: AWA Ltd v Daniels t/as Deloitte Haskins &amp; Sells (1992) 7 ACSR 759 at 1014. At p 867 the Court explained that a chairman is: 
...responsible to a greater extent than any other director for the performance of the board as a whole and each member of it. The chairman has the primary responsibility of selecting matters and documents to be brought to the board's attention, in formulating the policy of the Board and in promoting the position of the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Azzopardi v The Queen [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 205 CLR 50</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/25.html</AustLII>
<text>In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , Azzopardi v The Queen [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 205 CLR 50 and Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 , the High Court considered the applicability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel to criminal proceedings. It decided that the rule is of very limited application to defendants in criminal cases, its reasoning based on the accusatorial nature of criminal proceedings. As an illustration of the Court's approach, in Dyers , Gaudron and Hayne JJ stated at [9]: 
As was pointed out in RPS... , it will seldom, if ever, be reasonable to conclude that an accused in a criminal trial would be expected to give evidence. Not only is the accused not bound to give evidence, it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. The mode of reasoning which is spoken of in ... Jones v Dunkel (26) ordinarily, therefore, cannot be applied to a defendant in a criminal trial. That mode of reasoning depends upon a premise that the person concerned not only could shed light on the subject but also would ordinarily be expected to do so. The conclusion that an accused could shed light on the subject-matter of the charge is a conclusion that would ordinarily be reached very easily. But given the accusatorial nature of a criminal trial, it cannot be said that, in such a proceeding, the accused would ordinarily be expected to give evidence. So to hold would be to deny that it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. That is why the majority of the Court concluded, in RPS and in Azzopardi , that it is ordinarily inappropriate to tell the jury that some inference can be drawn from the fact that the accused has not given evidence.

In Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 , in their joint majority judgment Gaudron, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ referred to Weissensteiner v The Queen [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217 where the High Court held it was appropriate for the trial judge to direct the jury as to the manner in which they might take into account the failure of the accused to give evidence, and their Honours stated at [61] that what was important in Weissensteiner and what warranted the remarks to the jury in that case was that, if there were facts which explained or contradicted the evidence against the accused, they were facts which were within the knowledge only of the accused, and thus could not be the subject of evidence from any other person or source. At [68], their Honours emphasised that cases in which a judge may comment on the failure of an accused to offer an explanation will be both rare and exceptional and will occur only if the evidence is capable of explanation by disclosure of additional facts known only to the accused. Their Honours said a comment will never be warranted merely because the accused has failed to contradict some aspect of the prosecution case.

Further authority for the availability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel in civil penalty proceedings is found in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2001) 115 FCR 442 , where Hill J stated at [33]: 
Where the proceedings are criminal (and the present proceedings are not; they are proceedings, inter alia, for the recovery of a civil penalty) it might be thought that the failure of the accused to go into evidence should not lead to the drawing of Jones v Dunkel inferences. After all it is clear that a witness can not be compelled to give evidence which is likely to incriminate the witness or expose the witness to a penalty. However, even in criminal cases it has been held that the failure of the accused, who is in a position to deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced by the prosecution, to give evidence will permit the jury to draw inferences adverse to the accused more readily: see Azzopardi v R [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 179 ALR 349 , affirming Weissensteiner v R [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217. A fortiori, therefore, the failure of a respondent to proceedings for recovery of a pecuniary penalty to give evidence on a matter relevant to an issue in the proceeding and deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced against the respondent will permit the Court more readily to draw the inferences to which the decision in Jones v Dunkel refers.

In Council of the New South Wales Bar Association v Power [2008] NSWCA 135 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 451 at [21] , a proceeding seeking removal of a legal practitioner from the Roll, Hodgson JA, with whom Beazley and McColl JJA agreed, referred to the High Court's conclusion in Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 that it was open to a trial judge in a criminal case to make a comment relating to the absence of evidence of additional facts peculiarly within the knowledge of the accused. Hodgson JA went on to say at [22] concerning the case before him that: 
If this had been a criminal trial, then in my opinion what the High Court said in Azzopardi would have meant that a jury could have been told that inferences from proved facts could more safely be drawn because the opponent elected not to give any explanation in terms of additional facts peculiarly within his knowledge or any evidence of such facts. In my opinion, if such Jones v Dunkel reasoning is available to a jury in a criminal trial, it must a fortiori be available to a court in civil proceedings such as the present. That would be so, even if these civil proceedings are regarded as proceedings for a civil penalty. I note that a similar view was expressed by Hill J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1800 ; (2001) 201 ALR 502 at [33] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553</tocase>
<text>A reasonable reader of the disclosures made by FMG and Forrest on FMG's behalf would have expected FMG to have a genuine and reasonable basis for making those statements: Global Sportsman v Mirror Newspapers [1984] FCA 180 ; 2 FCR 82 at 88; James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347 at 372 per Toohey J; Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865 at 49,375-49,376 per French J (affirmed in Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189) ; Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553 at 559 per Burchett J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 622</tocase>
<text>This fourth category was recognised by McLelland J in Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 622 and on appeal in G R Securities Pty Ltd v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 631 where McHugh JA delivered the Court of Appeal's judgment and observed that the magnitude, subject matter or complexities of a transaction may indicate that an agreement was a limited one not intended to have legal effect (634D) but that what was critical was the parties' intention objectively ascertained, and that this intention should prevail (634E-F). In Uranium Equities Ltd [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal) stated at [129] that the fourth Masters v Cameron category was a variation of the first category.

The use of such expressions supports a finding of an intention to contract. In Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd 40 NSWLR 622 , McLelland J, in finding that by an exchange of letters the parties to an alleged agreement mutually communicated their respective assents to be legally bound by terms capable of having contractual effect, afforded the expression "legally binding" primacy despite the expression "agreement in principle" also found in the relevant agreement (628). His Honour thought that the case fell into the fourth category as recognised in Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 (629F) . The appeal from McLelland J's judgment G R Securities v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital 40 NSWLR 631 was dismissed. McHugh JA accepted in line with Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 , that it was possible for the parties to be bound immediately and agree to substitute for the first contract a further contract containing additional terms (634G). Further, McHugh JA applied the general rule applicable to every contract explained by Mason J in Secured Income Real Estate (Australia) Ltd v St Martins Investments Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 51 ; (1979) 144 CLR 596 at 607 that each party was obliged to do all that was necessary on his part to enable the other party to have the benefit of the contract.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1938/34.html</AustLII>
<text>Forrest submits that one important aspect of this matter is the application of the principles found in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 to himself. He points to the seriousness of the allegations made by ASIC and the severity of the penalties it seeks in the form of large financial penalties and his disqualification from managing a corporation. He submits that these are more severe than many criminal punishments and would cause enormous harm to him and FMG. He says that, in these circumstances, the level of satisfaction that the Court requires to reach before accepting any of ASIC's contentions is as close to the criminal standard as could be in any civil proceeding.

FMG also cited Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; 60 CLR 336 , saying that, because these are civil penalty proceedings, the Court should not lightly make findings of contraventions, even applying the balance of probabilities standard, given the seriousness of the causes of action and the gravity of the matters alleged and their consequences.

FMG and Forrest are relying on the principle emerging from Dixon J's judgment in Briginshaw 60 CLR at 361-362 that in considering whether an allegation is made out to its "reasonable satisfaction", a tribunal should take into account the seriousness of the allegation and the gravity of the consequences that would follow if the allegation were to be accepted.

In Qantas Airways Limited v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69 ; (2008) 167 FCR 537 , French and Jacobson JJ stated at [110] that the "so-called Briginshaw test" does not create any third standard of proof between the civil and the criminal. Their Honours said the standard of proof remains the same, that is proof on the balance of probabilities, and that the degree of satisfaction that is required in determining that that standard has been discharged may vary according to the seriousness of the allegations of misconduct that are made.

Section 140(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (the Evidence Act ) prescribes the standard of proof in a civil proceeding as the balance of probabilities, and s 140(2) provides that the Court may take into account, in deciding whether it is so satisfied, the nature of the cause of action or defence, the nature of the subject matter of the proceeding and the gravity of the matters alleged. In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; (2007) 162 FCR 466 the Full Court noted at [31] that Dixon J's classic discussion in Briginshaw appositely expresses the considerations which s 140(2) of the Evidence Act now requires a court to take into account.

Section 1332 of the Act differs from s 140 of the Evidence Act in that it does not contain the 'Briginshaw' considerations found in s 140(2) of the Evidence Act . However this does not require s 140(2) of the Evidence Act to be read down. In any event given that s 1317L requires the Court to apply the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters when hearing proceedings for a declaration of contravention or a pecuniary penalty order, the considerations expressed in Dixon J's Briginshaw discussion are nevertheless relevant.

In conclusion, the standard of proof that I must apply is the balance of probabilities as prescribed by s 1332, and I accept that in deciding whether ASIC's allegations are made out on the balance of probabilities I am required to take into account the causes of action and the gravity of the matters alleged and their consequences: s 140(2) Evidence Act ; Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; 60 CLR 336. If inferences are to be drawn, ASIC has to establish that the circumstances appearing from the evidence give rise to a reasonable and definite inference and not merely to conflicting inferences of equal degrees of probability: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; (2009) 256 ALR 199 at [186] ; Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; 162 FCR 466 at [38] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Buckland v Buckland [1900] 2 Ch 534</tocase>
<text>Authority supports an argument that the agreement recorded in the recitals for CREC to build or "execute" the railway should be given effect and should be treated as an agreement between FMG and CREC even where the operative provisions of the framework agreement do not contain such a provision and there is nothing inconsistent with such a construction in the operative provisions: Buckland v Buckland [1900] 2 Ch 534 at 540.3; MacKenzie v Childers (1889) 43 Ch D 265 at 274.7, 275.4-276.1; Ex parte Dawes; in re Moon (1886) 17 QBD 275 , 286.8, 288.2, 289.7; Aspdin v Austin (1844) 5 QB 671 at 683. This is even more so where, as here, the framework agreements were not drawn by lawyers. They were drafted by Heyting, an engineer, who also holds a Masters of Business Administration and who had some training in contract management. In those circumstances, arguably, a distinction between recitals and operational clauses should not be rigorously applied in an attempt to determine the parties' intention, determined objectively. Expressly, the recitals proceed on the basis that there is an agreement for the relevant Chinese contractor to build the infrastructure which is sought to be recorded in the framework agreements. The recitals do not say or imply that what follows is merely an informal arrangement, or a mere agreement to negotiate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd [1980] 2 NSWLR 851</tocase>
<text>However, where there is a finding of intention to deceive, the court may more readily infer that the intention has been or in all probability will be effective: Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd [1980] 2 NSWLR 851 at 861; S &amp; I Publishing Pty Ltd v Australian Surf Life Saver Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 316 ; (1998) 88 FCR 354 at 362; Campomar Sociedad [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at [33] and National Exchange [2004] FCAFC 90 ; 22 ACLC 609 at [63] per Jacobson and Bennett JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/12.html</AustLII>
<text>In Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45 , the High Court set out a number of principles in relation to s 52 of the TPA.

In National Exchange v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2004] FCAFC 90 ; (2004) 22 ACLC 609 , Dowsett J, with whom Jacobson and Bennett JJ agreed with generally, compiled at [18] a helpful summary of the propositions relevant to the application of s 52 emerging from the High Court's judgment in Campomar Sociedad. Dowsett J's summary, to which I have added references to the paragraphs of the High Court's judgment applicable to each proposition, is as follows. His Honour accepted that these observations are of general application in proceedings alleging contravention of s 1041H(1) of the Act, [19]. Conduct will only be misleading or deceptive, or likely to mislead or deceive if there is a nexus between such conduct and any actual or anticipated misconception or deception. [98] 
 In identifying such nexus regard must be had to the circumstances of the particular case, including the remedies sought. Section 52 of the TP Act does not confer any entitlement to a remedy for breach or anticipated breach. One must look elsewhere in the TP Act for such entitlement and construe the act as a whole. [99] 
 In some cases, a representation may be made to identified individuals; in other cases the representation may be to the public at large or to a section thereof. In the former case the process of deciding whether or not the representation is misleading or deceptive or likely to be so may be 'direct and uncomplicated'. In the latter case 'the issue with respect to the sufficiency of the nexus between the conduct or the apprehended conduct and the misleading or deception or likely misleading or deception of prospective purchasers is to be approached at a level of abstraction not present where the case is one involving an express untrue representation allegedly made only to identified individuals'. (I infer that the word "representation" in [100] of Nike should be "misrepresentation", relying upon the relevant passage in Taco Bell to which the High Court was referring.) [100]
 When the representation is made to the public or to a section thereof, one must consider its effect upon an ordinary or reasonable member of the class in question. Although such class may include a wide range of persons, the ordinary or reasonable member will objectively be identified as having certain characteristics. In particular he or she can be expected to take reasonable care for his or her own interests and otherwise to behave reasonably. [101]-[102]
 It is necessary to inquire as to how a particular or anticipated misconception has arisen or may arise. In so doing, the Court will consider 'the effect of the relevant conduct on reasonable members of the class'. [103]
 Conduct will only be misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive if the representee 'labours under some erroneous assumption' or may be expected so to labour. Such an assumption or anticipated assumption may be obvious, predictable or fanciful. [104]
 In assessing the reactions or likely reactions of the ordinary or reasonable member of the class, the Court may decline to treat as reasonable, assumptions which are extreme or fanciful. The initial question which must be determined is whether the misconception or deception, alleged or anticipated, is properly attributable to an ordinary or reasonable member of the class. [105] 
 The 'question whether particular conduct causes confusion or wonderment cannot be substituted for the question whether the conduct answers the statutory description contained in s 52.' [106]

However, where there is a finding of intention to deceive, the court may more readily infer that the intention has been or in all probability will be effective: Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd [1980] 2 NSWLR 851 at 861; S &amp; I Publishing Pty Ltd v Australian Surf Life Saver Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 316 ; (1998) 88 FCR 354 at 362; Campomar Sociedad [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at [33] and National Exchange [2004] FCAFC 90 ; 22 ACLC 609 at [63] per Jacobson and Bennett JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Coal Cliff Collieries Pty Ltd v Sijehama Pty Ltd (1991) 24 NSWLR 1</tocase>
<text>ASIC relies upon the following authorities in support of its submission that the framework agreements are bare agreements to negotiate the scope and terms, in each case, of a further agreement to build transfer and finance the relevant Project infrastructure and that such agreements are not enforceable: Coal Cliff Collieries Pty Ltd v Sijehama Pty Ltd (1991) 24 NSWLR 1 ; Jobern Pty Ltd v Breakfree Resorts (Victoria) Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1066 ; Walford v Miles [1992] 2 AC 128.

Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1 concerned the enforceability of an agreement to negotiate a complex coal mining joint venture. The parties had agreed on a heads of agreement document for the proposed joint venture which included the statement: "...The parties will forthwith proceed in good faith to consult together upon the formulation of a more comprehensive and detailed Joint Venture Agreement...". The Court of Appeal (Kirby P, Handley JA and Waddell A-JA) held that the statement was not binding as a contractual promise. Kirby P, with whom Waddell A-JA agreed, held at p 27 that the promise, having regard to the context in which it was made, should be classified as too illusory or too vague and uncertain to be enforceable. Handley JA held at pp 42-43 that a promise to negotiate in good faith is illusory and therefore cannot be binding because there are no identifiable criteria by which the content of the obligation to negotiate in good faith can be determined.

Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 involved a contractual dispute where the parties had executed a document entitled 'Heads of Agreement' (HofA), clause 3.3 of which stated: "Each party will conduct all such negotiations in good faith to ensure that the terms set out in these Heads of Agreement are given full effect". It was not in dispute in Jobern that the parties were bound by the HoFA, which Gordon J stated to be a final agreement within the first category described in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 at [106] . However Gordon J considered that cl 3.3 was uncertain because it suffered from the same problems referred to by Kirby J in Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1 at [130].

In my view Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1, Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 and Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 do not assist ASIC. I do not take Coal Cliff Collieries as authority for the proposition that a bare agreement to negotiate in good faith is not enforceable, as submitted by ASIC. In my view, that case is authority for the proposition that a promise to negotiate in good faith may, in particular circumstances, be enforceable, depending on the precise terms as construed from the contract. In Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 , it was not in dispute that the heads of agreement document was binding only the negotiation clause was held to be uncertain. In Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 , the agreement that was found to be uncertain was a 'lock-in' agreement committing the parties to negotiate with each other, which is to be distinguished from the types of obligations found in the framework agreements under consideration in the present case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; (2007) 162 FCR 466</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/132.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 140(1) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) (the Evidence Act ) prescribes the standard of proof in a civil proceeding as the balance of probabilities, and s 140(2) provides that the Court may take into account, in deciding whether it is so satisfied, the nature of the cause of action or defence, the nature of the subject matter of the proceeding and the gravity of the matters alleged. In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; (2007) 162 FCR 466 the Full Court noted at [31] that Dixon J's classic discussion in Briginshaw appositely expresses the considerations which s 140(2) of the Evidence Act now requires a court to take into account.

In conclusion, the standard of proof that I must apply is the balance of probabilities as prescribed by s 1332, and I accept that in deciding whether ASIC's allegations are made out on the balance of probabilities I am required to take into account the causes of action and the gravity of the matters alleged and their consequences: s 140(2) Evidence Act ; Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; 60 CLR 336. If inferences are to be drawn, ASIC has to establish that the circumstances appearing from the evidence give rise to a reasonable and definite inference and not merely to conflicting inferences of equal degrees of probability: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Macdonald (No 11) [2009] NSWSC 287 ; (2009) 256 ALR 199 at [186] ; Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; 162 FCR 466 at [38] .

In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; (2007) 162 FCR 466 , the Court discussed the Adler and Rich cases and concluded at [76] that there is no reason in civil proceedings for pecuniary penalties to deny the applicability of the principles in Jones v Dunkel provided that in doing so the court proceeds in accordance with the principles in relation to s 140 of the Evidence Act , which prescribes he civil standard as the applicable standard of proof. I have discussed the standard of proof earlier.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Council of the New South Wales Bar Association v Power [2008] NSWCA 135 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 451</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/135.html</AustLII>
<text>In Council of the New South Wales Bar Association v Power [2008] NSWCA 135 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 451 at [21] , a proceeding seeking removal of a legal practitioner from the Roll, Hodgson JA, with whom Beazley and McColl JJA agreed, referred to the High Court's conclusion in Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 that it was open to a trial judge in a criminal case to make a comment relating to the absence of evidence of additional facts peculiarly within the knowledge of the accused. Hodgson JA went on to say at [22] concerning the case before him that: 
If this had been a criminal trial, then in my opinion what the High Court said in Azzopardi would have meant that a jury could have been told that inferences from proved facts could more safely be drawn because the opponent elected not to give any explanation in terms of additional facts peculiarly within his knowledge or any evidence of such facts. In my opinion, if such Jones v Dunkel reasoning is available to a jury in a criminal trial, it must a fortiori be available to a court in civil proceedings such as the present. That would be so, even if these civil proceedings are regarded as proceedings for a civil penalty. I note that a similar view was expressed by Hill J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1800 ; (2001) 201 ALR 502 at [33] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Dyers v The Queen [2002] HCA 45 ; (2002) 210 CLR 285</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/45.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG made no submissions on whether Jones v Dunkel had any application. Citing Dyers v The Queen [2002] HCA 45 ; (2002) 210 CLR 285 , Forrest submitted in written closing submissions that a Jones v Dunkel inference may not be drawn against an accused in a criminal case because the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel is incompatible with the presumption of innocence and the rights of the accused; further, this reasoning applies with equal force to the accused calling other persons to give evidence. Forrest then submitted that the point of principle that, when an accused exercises the right not to give evidence the jury is directed that no adverse inference should be drawn, applies to a civil proceeding as against an individual defendant. He referred to the statement of Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, and Heydon JJ in Rich v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2004] HCA 42 ; (2004) 220 CLR 129 at [24] that the privilege against exposure to penalty serves the purpose of ensuring that those who allege criminality or other (illegal) conduct should prove it, and said there is no expectation that a defendant will give evidence on matters for which the plaintiff bears the onus of proof. He said there is no authority that supports the proposition that a Jones v Dunkel inference is available against an individual defendant in a civil penalty proceeding, though, he said, the position may be different for a company. Finally, Forrest submitted that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and a Jones v Dunkel inference is not be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents, citing Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [71] .

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , Azzopardi v The Queen [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 205 CLR 50 and Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 , the High Court considered the applicability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel to criminal proceedings. It decided that the rule is of very limited application to defendants in criminal cases, its reasoning based on the accusatorial nature of criminal proceedings. As an illustration of the Court's approach, in Dyers , Gaudron and Hayne JJ stated at [9]: 
As was pointed out in RPS... , it will seldom, if ever, be reasonable to conclude that an accused in a criminal trial would be expected to give evidence. Not only is the accused not bound to give evidence, it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. The mode of reasoning which is spoken of in ... Jones v Dunkel (26) ordinarily, therefore, cannot be applied to a defendant in a criminal trial. That mode of reasoning depends upon a premise that the person concerned not only could shed light on the subject but also would ordinarily be expected to do so. The conclusion that an accused could shed light on the subject-matter of the charge is a conclusion that would ordinarily be reached very easily. But given the accusatorial nature of a criminal trial, it cannot be said that, in such a proceeding, the accused would ordinarily be expected to give evidence. So to hold would be to deny that it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. That is why the majority of the Court concluded, in RPS and in Azzopardi , that it is ordinarily inappropriate to tell the jury that some inference can be drawn from the fact that the accused has not given evidence.

Further, in my view, nothing that has been said by the High Court in Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 and the other authorities discussed above supports the proposition that the general rule proscribing the making of inferences from a defendant's failure to give evidence in criminal proceedings should be extended to civil penalty proceedings in the form of a prohibition against applying the rule in Jones v Dunkel , notwithstanding that pursuant to Rich s 1317L also obliges the court to apply the body of law which has developed in relation to the privileges against penalties and forfeitures when deciding whether an order for discovery should be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ex parte Dawes; in re Moon (1886) 17 QBD 275</tocase>
<text>Authority supports an argument that the agreement recorded in the recitals for CREC to build or "execute" the railway should be given effect and should be treated as an agreement between FMG and CREC even where the operative provisions of the framework agreement do not contain such a provision and there is nothing inconsistent with such a construction in the operative provisions: Buckland v Buckland [1900] 2 Ch 534 at 540.3; MacKenzie v Childers (1889) 43 Ch D 265 at 274.7, 275.4-276.1; Ex parte Dawes; in re Moon (1886) 17 QBD 275 , 286.8, 288.2, 289.7; Aspdin v Austin (1844) 5 QB 671 at 683. This is even more so where, as here, the framework agreements were not drawn by lawyers. They were drafted by Heyting, an engineer, who also holds a Masters of Business Administration and who had some training in contract management. In those circumstances, arguably, a distinction between recitals and operational clauses should not be rigorously applied in an attempt to determine the parties' intention, determined objectively. Expressly, the recitals proceed on the basis that there is an agreement for the relevant Chinese contractor to build the infrastructure which is sought to be recorded in the framework agreements. The recitals do not say or imply that what follows is merely an informal arrangement, or a mere agreement to negotiate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fame Decorator Agencies Pty Limited v Jeffries Industries Ltd [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 16 ACLC 1 ,235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/30.html</AustLII>
<text>In Fame Decorator Agencies Pty Limited v Jeffries Industries Ltd [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 16 ACLC 1 ,235 at 1,240-1,241, a case also dealing with s 995, Gleeson CJ with whom Powell JA agreed stated that the parliament regarded is as desirable that, although s 52 of the TPA may have applied to some cases of dealing in securities, there should be a similar provision having as its focus conduct in relation to securities. His Honour added that much of the case law which has developed around s 52 will apply also to s 995.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//tas/supreme_ct/2000/159.html</AustLII>
<text>I will now turn to the cases cited by ASIC in support of its submission that the framework agreements were unenforceable because they were uncertain due to a lack of essential terms such as price: Hall v Busst 104 CLR 207; Toyota Motor Corporation Australia Ltd v Ken Morgan Motors Pty Ltd (1994) 2 VR 106 at 168-177 per Tadgell J; Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 at [34] ; and Southern Cross Financial Group (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Rodrigues (2005) 66 IPR 166 at [36], [44].

Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 concerned a partnership agreement which included a clause containing an elaborate mechanism for the determination of the purchase price of the assets and goodwill of a deceased partner, with the price to be fixed by a valuer. Underwood J held at [34] that the rule imposed on the valuers for the ascertainment of the value of the goodwill was completely meaningless by virtue of the omission of a dollar figure from a particular subparagraph of the clause. Underwood J stated that the rule that had to be applied for the ascertainment of the value of the goodwill was incomplete in just the same way as if a contract specified that "the purchase price of the goods sold is $____". Accordingly, the uncertainty created by this omission rendered the whole contract void for uncertainty. Underwood J went on in that paragraph to state: "It is not for the Court to supply the omission upon some notions of general fairness" and cited Hall v Busst as authority for that proposition. In the present matter, my view is that the pricing mechanism in the framework agreements is arguably certain for reasons I will explain below.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fletcher Challenge Energy Ltd v Electricity Corporation of New Zealand Ltd [2002] 2 NZLR 433</tocase>
<text>I have concluded, for reasons which I explain later in this Part that, in the case of each of the framework agreements, there was an intention to contract. This, as a starting point considerably strengthens the case for the defendants because in such circumstances a Court will always strive to give effect to that intention: Hillas &amp; Co Ltd v Arcos Ltd [1932] UKHL 2 ; [1932] All ER Rep 494 ; York Air Conditioning and Refrigeration (A/sia) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth [1949] HCA 23 ; (1949) 80 CLR 11 ; G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631; Fletcher Challenge Energy [2002] NZLR 433 .

In the same vein in Fletcher Challenge Energy Ltd v Electricity Corporation of New Zealand Ltd [2002] 2 NZLR 433 at 445, Blanchard J observed: 
The court has an entirely neutral approach when determining whether the parties intended to enter into a contract. Having decided that they had that intention, however, the Court's attitude will change. It will then do its best to give effect to their intention and, if at all possible, to uphold the contract despite any omissions or ambiguities. 
 
 
At 448, Blanchard J referred to the statement of the English Court of Appeal in Pagnan SpA v Feed Products [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep 601: 
 
Merely because an important term is deferred to be settled on a future occasion that does not mean that there is no intention to be bound.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Foley v Classique Coaches Limited [1934] 2 KB 1</tocase>
<text>In Foley v Classique Coaches Limited [1934] 2 KB 1 , the sale of land under a written contract was subject to the buyer entering into a supplemental agreement to purchase petrol and/or oil from the seller, the terms of which had been agreed between them. The supplemental agreement stated that petrol would be purchased "at a price to be agreed by the parties in writing and from time to time", and provided for arbitration in the event of any dispute or difference arising on the subject matter or construction of the agreement. Scrutton LJ agreed at p 10 that there was an effective and enforceable contract, although as to the future no definite price had been agreed with regard to the petrol. Greer LJ held at p 12 that it was appropriate to imply a term in the contract that the price of the petrol supplied shall be reasonable and in no way inconsistent with the agreement. Maugham LJ held that the contract was enforceable, inter alia, because implied in the obligation to sell and purchase the petrol at an agreed price was words to the effect that, in the absence of agreement, the arbitration clause provided a means for the determination of a reasonable price for the petrol.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Global Sportsman Pty Ltd v Mirror Newspapers Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 180 ; (1984) 2 FCR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/180.html</AustLII>
<text>In Global Sportsman Pty Ltd v Mirror Newspapers Pty Ltd [1984] FCA 180 ; (1984) 2 FCR 82 , the Court (Bowen CJ, Lockhart and Fitzgerald JJ) stated at 88: 
An expression of opinion which is identifiable as such conveys no more than that the opinion expressed is held and perhaps that there is a basis for the opinion. At least if those conditions are met, an expression of opinion, however erroneous, misrepresents nothing.

A reasonable reader of the disclosures made by FMG and Forrest on FMG's behalf would have expected FMG to have a genuine and reasonable basis for making those statements: Global Sportsman v Mirror Newspapers [1984] FCA 180 ; 2 FCR 82 at 88; James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347 at 372 per Toohey J; Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865 at 49,375-49,376 per French J (affirmed in Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189) ; Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553 at 559 per Burchett J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Glorie v WA Chip and Pulp Co Pty Ltd [1981] FCA 224 ; (1981) 55 FLR 310</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1981/224.html</AustLII>
<text>In Glorie v WA Chip and Pulp Co Pty Ltd [1981] FCA 224 ; (1981) 55 FLR 310 at 328, Morling J stated: 
I do not think that a statement is necessarily misleading or deceptive if it cannot be demonstrated to be correct beyond any doubt. Nor is it necessarily misleading or deceptive merely if it is not accompanied by words indicating that a contrary view is held by others. If it were otherwise, public discussion and the free expression of opinions would be greatly inhibited. This would especially be the case where the statement is one of opinion or of mixed fact and opinion. When such a statement is made, the person to whom it is addressed will, in most cases, understand that there may be room for another opinion on the same matter. Where that is the case, I find it difficult to characterize the statement as being misleading or deceptive. The position would be different, of course, when a statement of opinion is made by a person who does not, in fact, hold that opinion.

It might be thought that the disclosures, to the effect that FMG had executed binding build and transfer agreements with each of the Chinese Contractors, ought be characterised as statements of fact rather than opinion. Certainly, they were assertive in nature and were not expressly said to be expressions of opinion. However, I consider that they constitute mixed fact and law. As an objective matter, an assertion as to the meaning and legal effect of an agreement is necessarily the product of an opinion formulated to that effect. However the disclosures are characterised, a question as to the reasonableness of the underlying opinion and, in this case, whether or not it was honestly held, arises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1973/38.html</AustLII>
<text>Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629 involved an agreement for the sale of land which contained a provision that, if required, a further agreement would be executed containing the agreed terms and such other terms as the seller's solicitors may 'reasonably require'. Despite this provision, it was held that there was a binding contract. Walsh J, with whom Mason J agreed, stated at 642: ' It is clearly established that a binding agreement may be made which leaves some important matter, e.g. the price, to be settled by the decision of a third party'. Gibbs J concurred but cast the principles slightly more narrowly in some respects (646-8). He stated at 648 that the fact that the further agreement contemplated in the case before him would contain additional covenants and conditions if the vendor's solicitors reasonably required them did not mean that the parties had not reached complete agreement. This case was decided after Hall v Busst (1960) 104 CLR 207, an authority relied on by ASIC .

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , a recent judgment of the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal), the Court stated at [127]: 
There is some overlap between the requirements of intention to create legal relations and certainty. If a contract is legally uncertain, this might indicate that the parties did not intend to create legal relations. A contract can be uncertain in various ways, one of these being incompleteness, in the sense that essential terms are lacking: Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 , 603 (Kitto J); Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629 , 646 - 647 (Gibbs J). The overlap between intention and uncertainty is at its greatest in cases in which agreement on some matters is deliberately postponed. If what is postponed is essential to the agreement (itself a question that largely depends upon the intention of the parties) , the agreement, to the extent that it has been reached, will be void. Also, the fact that essential terms have been left over for later agreement will militate against a finding that the parties intended to create contractual relations. (Emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c38">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>G R Securities Pty Ltd v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 631</tocase>
<text>This fourth category was recognised by McLelland J in Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 622 and on appeal in G R Securities Pty Ltd v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 631 where McHugh JA delivered the Court of Appeal's judgment and observed that the magnitude, subject matter or complexities of a transaction may indicate that an agreement was a limited one not intended to have legal effect (634D) but that what was critical was the parties' intention objectively ascertained, and that this intention should prevail (634E-F). In Uranium Equities Ltd [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal) stated at [129] that the fourth Masters v Cameron category was a variation of the first category.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c39">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hall v Busst (1960) 104 CLR 207</tocase>
<text>Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629 involved an agreement for the sale of land which contained a provision that, if required, a further agreement would be executed containing the agreed terms and such other terms as the seller's solicitors may 'reasonably require'. Despite this provision, it was held that there was a binding contract. Walsh J, with whom Mason J agreed, stated at 642: ' It is clearly established that a binding agreement may be made which leaves some important matter, e.g. the price, to be settled by the decision of a third party'. Gibbs J concurred but cast the principles slightly more narrowly in some respects (646-8). He stated at 648 that the fact that the further agreement contemplated in the case before him would contain additional covenants and conditions if the vendor's solicitors reasonably required them did not mean that the parties had not reached complete agreement. This case was decided after Hall v Busst (1960) 104 CLR 207, an authority relied on by ASIC .

I will now turn to the cases cited by ASIC in support of its submission that the framework agreements were unenforceable because they were uncertain due to a lack of essential terms such as price: Hall v Busst 104 CLR 207; Toyota Motor Corporation Australia Ltd v Ken Morgan Motors Pty Ltd (1994) 2 VR 106 at 168-177 per Tadgell J; Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 at [34] ; and Southern Cross Financial Group (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Rodrigues (2005) 66 IPR 166 at [36], [44].

The judgment of the High Court in Hall v Busst 104 CLR 207, illustrates how judges have disagreed as to the enforceability of a contractual clause dealing with the issue of price, where the clause leaves an aspect of the price for determination at a later time. This judgment is in relative terms an old decision, but the High Court was divided 3-2 which underscores the difficulty in construing such clauses and in a case such as the present case the unfairness which would attach to fixing on one opinion over others where those others were reasonably based and honestly held. The dispute involved a contract of sale in relation to an island off the coast of Queensland. The contract included an indenture which included an option which was in effect (in the words of Dixon CJ at 212) an option for the buyer of the land to take the land back with a refund of the sale price payment for the additions and improvements at their value less deficiences and depreciation. The clause referred to "the value of all additions and improvements to the said property" and "the value of all deficiences of chattel property and a reasonable sum to cover depreciation of all buildings and other property".

The appeal to the High Court was brought on the ground that the price payable on the exercise of the option under the indenture was prescribed or expressed in terms which left it uncertain so that the option was unenforceable. Dixon CJ held at 217 that the price described in the relevant clause was unascertained and was too uncertain to be the basis of an enforceable contract. His Honour said: 
There could be no external standard of value of additions and improvements to the island: no standard yielding a figure reasonable fixed or ascertainable. Still less would it be possible to find an external standard for the reasonable sum to cover depreciation even if one knew what 'other property' is referred to.

Fullagar J also held that the clause was uncertain because the price was not fixed with certainty. However, his Honour stated (222) that it would be sufficient if the sale was expressed to be for a price or value to be fixed by a named or described person. It was not sufficient for the sale to be expressed to be "for the value of the land" or "for the fair value of the land" or "for a reasonable price". Menzies J took a similar view, stating that no means of authoritative determination was provided by the agreement, and the necessity for further agreement revealed that there was no binding contract (231).

Kitto J dissented stating that the meaning of the clause providing for additions and subtractions to the price did not seem to be uncertain, and that the value of the additions, improvements and deficiencies were capable of being ascertained when the time arrived. The provision as to "a reasonable sum to cover depreciation" appeared to his Honour to be definite in meaning and capable of being rendered certain in application, and he referred to a number of authorities. Windeyer J also dissented, saying that the parties expressed their intention in language that was sufficiently certain to create legal obligations. His Honour stated, following reference to a range of authorities (245): 
When parties agree to sell for a reasonable price or at a fair valuation they do not leave an essential term of their bargain for further agreement, so that their agreement is incomplete. It is complete. They have fixed the price by a measure that the law knows. If they disagree as to what sum of money fills that measure, a court will determine it, at common law by a jury.

Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 concerned a partnership agreement which included a clause containing an elaborate mechanism for the determination of the purchase price of the assets and goodwill of a deceased partner, with the price to be fixed by a valuer. Underwood J held at [34] that the rule imposed on the valuers for the ascertainment of the value of the goodwill was completely meaningless by virtue of the omission of a dollar figure from a particular subparagraph of the clause. Underwood J stated that the rule that had to be applied for the ascertainment of the value of the goodwill was incomplete in just the same way as if a contract specified that "the purchase price of the goods sold is $____". Accordingly, the uncertainty created by this omission rendered the whole contract void for uncertainty. Underwood J went on in that paragraph to state: "It is not for the Court to supply the omission upon some notions of general fairness" and cited Hall v Busst as authority for that proposition. In the present matter, my view is that the pricing mechanism in the framework agreements is arguably certain for reasons I will explain below.

In Southern Cross Financial Group 66 IPR 166 , Young CJ in Eq stated at [36] that in a contract for the sale of any article there are at least three basic requirements: precise identification of the parties to the contract; the property to be sold; and the price at which it is to be sold. In connection with the price requirement, his Honour referred to the analysis of Fullagar J in Hall v Busst 104 CLR at 222, and stated at [44] that this analysis made it quite clear that with "very, very, very few" exceptions, a contract to sell property at fair value is not binding and is incomplete. The exceptions included 'an industry which has a measure of what a fair value is or there is some other criteria'. I would add that Fullagar J stated at 222 that it would be sufficient if the sale was expressed to be for a price or value to be fixed by a named or described person. The CREC Framework Agreement did not simply state that the infrastructure items would be transferred at fair value or in like terms. Rather, the agreement expressly provided a pricing mechanism. Further, Southern Cross Financial Group 66 IPR 166 is distinguishable from the present matter because Young CJ found that the case was one where the parties intended there not to be a concluded contract unless and until a formal document had been executed .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c40">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harold Holdsworth &amp; Co (Wakefield) Ltd v Caddies [1955] 1 WLR 352</tocase>
<text>The breadth of managerial powers delegated to the chief executive officer by the board is ultimately contingent on the terms of appointment of the CEO: Harold Holdsworth &amp; Co (Wakefield) Ltd v Caddies [1955] 1 WLR 352 as cited in Randall v Aristocrat Leisure [2004] NSWSC 411 at [382] . There is no evidence to demonstrate that Forrest's powers and authority as Chief Executive Officer were limited in any relevant way. I find that he was intimately and directly involved in the execution of the framework agreements, the formulation of FMG's notifications to the ASX and other disclosures, as well as the ongoing discussions with the NDRC and CMCC seeking Chinese government approval. Likewise, Forrest was intimately and directly involved in discussions with the NDRC and CMCC concerning the NDRC precondition to approval that FMG must provide one or more nominated Chinese companies with minority equity participation in FMG or the Project.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c41">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Heydon v NRMA [2000] NSWCA 374 ; (2000) 51 NSWLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2000/374.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c42">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hillas &amp; Co Ltd v Arcos Ltd [1932] UKHL 2 ; [1932] All ER Rep 494</tocase>
<text>I have concluded, for reasons which I explain later in this Part that, in the case of each of the framework agreements, there was an intention to contract. This, as a starting point considerably strengthens the case for the defendants because in such circumstances a Court will always strive to give effect to that intention: Hillas &amp; Co Ltd v Arcos Ltd [1932] UKHL 2 ; [1932] All ER Rep 494 ; York Air Conditioning and Refrigeration (A/sia) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth [1949] HCA 23 ; (1949) 80 CLR 11 ; G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631; Fletcher Challenge Energy [2002] NZLR 433 .

Kirby P did not state that an agreement to negotiate would never be enforceable. His Honour approved Lord Wright's speech in Hillas &amp; Co Ltd v Arcos Ltd [1932] UKHL 2 ; [1932] All ER Rep 494 such that, provided there was consideration for the promise, in some circumstances a promise to negotiate in good faith will be enforceable, depending on its precise terms. The proper approach to be taken in each case depends on the construction of the particular contract. His Honour stated: "In many contracts it will be plain that the promise to negotiate is intended to be a binding legal obligation to which the parties should then be held".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c43">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Ltd [1978] HCA 11 ; (1978) 140 CLR 216</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/11.html</AustLII>
<text>A further relevant principle concerns the intention of the representor. Intention is not a necessary element of the contravention of s 52. The section involves no questions of intent upon the part of the corporation whose conduct is in question: Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Ltd [1978] HCA 11 ; (1978) 140 CLR 216 at 228 per Stephen J; Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Proprietary Limited v Puxu Proprietary Limited [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 at 216 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c44">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>International Air Transport Association v Ansett Australia Holdings Ltd [2008] HCA 3 ; (2008) 234 CLR 151</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/3.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG makes the following submission which I accept as a correct statement of the law. The proper construction of an agreement should be determined by what reasonable people in the position of the parties would have understood by the relevant clauses by considering not only their text, but also the surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the transaction: e.g. Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at [40] ; International Air Transport Association v Ansett Australia Holdings Ltd [2008] HCA 3 ; (2008) 234 CLR 151 at [8] and [53]. The whole of the document should be considered and its provisions given harmonious effect: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1973] HCA 36 ; (1973) 129 CLR 99 at 109 (Gibbs J, in dissent, but not on the applicable principle).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c45">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347</tocase>
<text>A reasonable reader of the disclosures made by FMG and Forrest on FMG's behalf would have expected FMG to have a genuine and reasonable basis for making those statements: Global Sportsman v Mirror Newspapers [1984] FCA 180 ; 2 FCR 82 at 88; James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347 at 372 per Toohey J; Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865 at 49,375-49,376 per French J (affirmed in Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189) ; Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553 at 559 per Burchett J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c46">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jobern Pty Ltd v Breakfree Resorts (Victoria) Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1066</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1066.html</AustLII>
<text>ASIC relies upon the following authorities in support of its submission that the framework agreements are bare agreements to negotiate the scope and terms, in each case, of a further agreement to build transfer and finance the relevant Project infrastructure and that such agreements are not enforceable: Coal Cliff Collieries Pty Ltd v Sijehama Pty Ltd (1991) 24 NSWLR 1 ; Jobern Pty Ltd v Breakfree Resorts (Victoria) Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1066 ; Walford v Miles [1992] 2 AC 128.

Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 involved a contractual dispute where the parties had executed a document entitled 'Heads of Agreement' (HofA), clause 3.3 of which stated: "Each party will conduct all such negotiations in good faith to ensure that the terms set out in these Heads of Agreement are given full effect". It was not in dispute in Jobern that the parties were bound by the HoFA, which Gordon J stated to be a final agreement within the first category described in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 at [106] . However Gordon J considered that cl 3.3 was uncertain because it suffered from the same problems referred to by Kirby J in Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1 at [130].

In my view Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1, Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 and Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 do not assist ASIC. I do not take Coal Cliff Collieries as authority for the proposition that a bare agreement to negotiate in good faith is not enforceable, as submitted by ASIC. In my view, that case is authority for the proposition that a promise to negotiate in good faith may, in particular circumstances, be enforceable, depending on the precise terms as construed from the contract. In Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 , it was not in dispute that the heads of agreement document was binding only the negotiation clause was held to be uncertain. In Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 , the agreement that was found to be uncertain was a 'lock-in' agreement committing the parties to negotiate with each other, which is to be distinguished from the types of obligations found in the framework agreements under consideration in the present case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c47">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1959/8.html</AustLII>
<text>Accordingly, I accept that ASIC's allegations against FMG and Forrest are serious. In addition, I accept that the penalties sought against both would have severe consequences. Any monetary penalties against FMG and Forrest would likely have been very substantial. Section 1317(G)(1) allows the court to impose a pecuniary penalty of up to $200,000 for each contravention of s 180(1). ASIC alleges a total of 22 contraventions of that subsection by Forrest, ASC [177]. ASIC sought orders for Forrest to compensate FMG for the full amount of any damage which FMG suffered by reason of being liable to pay a pecuniary penalty for each contravention of s 674(2). The relevant maximum penalty for each contravention by FMG is $1 million. ASIC also sought orders for Forrest to be disqualified from managing corporations. Jones v Dunkel

FMG foreshadowed that it would call evidence from its executives, such as Rowley, David Liu and Alan Watling but it did not do so. ASIC submits that, where an inference is open from facts proved, the unexplained failure of a party to call a witness or tender a document may be taken into account as a circumstance in favour of the drawing inference: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 at 308, 312 and 320-321; RPS v The Queen [2000] HCA 3 ; (2000) 199 CLR 620 at [26] . ASIC submits that it should be inferred that Rowley, Liu and Watling were available to be called, but FMG chose not to call them for strategic reasons. As a result, ASIC says, if there are inferences to be drawn from documents in evidence, which could have been explained by these executives, or by Forrest who also elected not to give evidence, the inference should be drawn against FMG that the evidence of these executives would have been of no assistance to their case, and that the documents should bear the meaning contended for by ASIC.

FMG made no submissions on whether Jones v Dunkel had any application. Citing Dyers v The Queen [2002] HCA 45 ; (2002) 210 CLR 285 , Forrest submitted in written closing submissions that a Jones v Dunkel inference may not be drawn against an accused in a criminal case because the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel is incompatible with the presumption of innocence and the rights of the accused; further, this reasoning applies with equal force to the accused calling other persons to give evidence. Forrest then submitted that the point of principle that, when an accused exercises the right not to give evidence the jury is directed that no adverse inference should be drawn, applies to a civil proceeding as against an individual defendant. He referred to the statement of Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, and Heydon JJ in Rich v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2004] HCA 42 ; (2004) 220 CLR 129 at [24] that the privilege against exposure to penalty serves the purpose of ensuring that those who allege criminality or other (illegal) conduct should prove it, and said there is no expectation that a defendant will give evidence on matters for which the plaintiff bears the onus of proof. He said there is no authority that supports the proposition that a Jones v Dunkel inference is available against an individual defendant in a civil penalty proceeding, though, he said, the position may be different for a company. Finally, Forrest submitted that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and a Jones v Dunkel inference is not be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents, citing Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [71] .

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , Azzopardi v The Queen [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 205 CLR 50 and Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 , the High Court considered the applicability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel to criminal proceedings. It decided that the rule is of very limited application to defendants in criminal cases, its reasoning based on the accusatorial nature of criminal proceedings. As an illustration of the Court's approach, in Dyers , Gaudron and Hayne JJ stated at [9]: 
As was pointed out in RPS... , it will seldom, if ever, be reasonable to conclude that an accused in a criminal trial would be expected to give evidence. Not only is the accused not bound to give evidence, it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. The mode of reasoning which is spoken of in ... Jones v Dunkel (26) ordinarily, therefore, cannot be applied to a defendant in a criminal trial. That mode of reasoning depends upon a premise that the person concerned not only could shed light on the subject but also would ordinarily be expected to do so. The conclusion that an accused could shed light on the subject-matter of the charge is a conclusion that would ordinarily be reached very easily. But given the accusatorial nature of a criminal trial, it cannot be said that, in such a proceeding, the accused would ordinarily be expected to give evidence. So to hold would be to deny that it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. That is why the majority of the Court concluded, in RPS and in Azzopardi , that it is ordinarily inappropriate to tell the jury that some inference can be drawn from the fact that the accused has not given evidence.

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , at [26]-[27] Gaudron A-CJ, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ contrasted the reasonable expectation that a party in a civil trial would give or call relevant evidence in the circumstances described in Jones v Dunkel with the conclusion that it would seldom, if ever, be reasonable to expect an accused in a criminal trial to give evidence. Weissensteiner provides an example of where the latter would be reasonable.

The Rich cases therefore turned on the issue of whether a disqualification order was a penalty. It was not in dispute that the privilege against exposure to penalty protected a defendant in civil proceedings not only from being obliged to give discovery, but also from being subject to any direction that affidavits or witness statements be provided to the plaintiff prior to the hearing or at any time prior to the conclusion of the plaintiff's case: see e.g. Austin J at first instance: [2003] NSWSC 328 ; (2003) 21 ACLC 920 , at [19]-[30]. In their judgments, neither the High Court nor the Court of Appeal considered the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel ; Austin J mentioned it briefly in passing at [58].

The rule in Jones v Dunkel was discussed however in Adler v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 131 ; (2003) 179 FLR 1 , Williams v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 131 ; (2003) 46 ACSR 504 , a judgment handed down before the High Court's Rich ruling, where the New South Wales Court of Appeal ruled that the trial judge, Santow J ((2002) [2002] NSWSC 171 ; 41 ACSR 72) , made no error in so far as his findings against Mr Adler, his company and Mr Williams were aided by Jones v Dunkel inferences against both those individuals and the company. In that proceeding ASIC had sought, inter alia , disqualification orders as well as pecuniary penalties. Giles JA, with whom Mason P and Beazley JA agreed, considered the High Court criminal cases discussed above and noted at [658] that proceedings for civil penalties do not share the same fundamental features of a criminal trial. His Honour stated that civil penalty proceedings are expressly to be maintained by civil law processes, not by a criminal trial with its fundamental features, [659]. He concluded that it was open for Jones v Dunkel inferences to be drawn against Mr Adler, his company, and Mr Williams in the proceedings, [661].

The rulings in Adler were therefore made on the footing that the privilege against exposure to penalty was attracted through ASIC's seeking of pecuniary penalties, but this did not prevent the trial judge from applying the rule in Jones v Dunkel, the rule and privilege both falling within the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters that the court was bound to apply pursuant to s 1317L of the act when hearing proceedings for a declaration of contravention or a pecuniary penalty order.

The High Court refused an application for special leave to appeal from the Court of Appeal's decision in Adler : [2004] HCATrans 182 , 28 May 2004. The transcript reveals that the special leave point argued was the issue of procedural fairness in dealing with the imposition of pecuniary penalties and disqualification under the civil penalties regime of the Act; there was no discussion of the rule in Jones v Dunkel .

Further, in my view, nothing that has been said by the High Court in Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 and the other authorities discussed above supports the proposition that the general rule proscribing the making of inferences from a defendant's failure to give evidence in criminal proceedings should be extended to civil penalty proceedings in the form of a prohibition against applying the rule in Jones v Dunkel , notwithstanding that pursuant to Rich s 1317L also obliges the court to apply the body of law which has developed in relation to the privileges against penalties and forfeitures when deciding whether an order for discovery should be made.

Further authority for the availability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel in civil penalty proceedings is found in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2001) 115 FCR 442 , where Hill J stated at [33]: 
Where the proceedings are criminal (and the present proceedings are not; they are proceedings, inter alia, for the recovery of a civil penalty) it might be thought that the failure of the accused to go into evidence should not lead to the drawing of Jones v Dunkel inferences. After all it is clear that a witness can not be compelled to give evidence which is likely to incriminate the witness or expose the witness to a penalty. However, even in criminal cases it has been held that the failure of the accused, who is in a position to deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced by the prosecution, to give evidence will permit the jury to draw inferences adverse to the accused more readily: see Azzopardi v R [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 179 ALR 349 , affirming Weissensteiner v R [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217. A fortiori, therefore, the failure of a respondent to proceedings for recovery of a pecuniary penalty to give evidence on a matter relevant to an issue in the proceeding and deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced against the respondent will permit the Court more readily to draw the inferences to which the decision in Jones v Dunkel refers.

In Council of the New South Wales Bar Association v Power [2008] NSWCA 135 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 451 at [21] , a proceeding seeking removal of a legal practitioner from the Roll, Hodgson JA, with whom Beazley and McColl JJA agreed, referred to the High Court's conclusion in Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 that it was open to a trial judge in a criminal case to make a comment relating to the absence of evidence of additional facts peculiarly within the knowledge of the accused. Hodgson JA went on to say at [22] concerning the case before him that: 
If this had been a criminal trial, then in my opinion what the High Court said in Azzopardi would have meant that a jury could have been told that inferences from proved facts could more safely be drawn because the opponent elected not to give any explanation in terms of additional facts peculiarly within his knowledge or any evidence of such facts. In my opinion, if such Jones v Dunkel reasoning is available to a jury in a criminal trial, it must a fortiori be available to a court in civil proceedings such as the present. That would be so, even if these civil proceedings are regarded as proceedings for a civil penalty. I note that a similar view was expressed by Hill J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1800 ; (2001) 201 ALR 502 at [33] .

In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 132 ; (2007) 162 FCR 466 , the Court discussed the Adler and Rich cases and concluded at [76] that there is no reason in civil proceedings for pecuniary penalties to deny the applicability of the principles in Jones v Dunkel provided that in doing so the court proceeds in accordance with the principles in relation to s 140 of the Evidence Act , which prescribes he civil standard as the applicable standard of proof. I have discussed the standard of proof earlier.

Finally, in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229, Austin J concluded at [458] that, having considered the reasoning in Dyers and Adler , the principle in Jones v Dunkel is applicable against either party to civil penalty proceedings.

ASIC seeks to draw Jones v Dunkel inferences against FMG by reason of the failure of Forrest and the other executives to give evidence. ASIC does not seek to draw the inferences against Forrest himself. Forrest has relied on the privilege against self-incrimination and the privilege against exposure to penalty, privileges which are are not available to corporations: Trade Practices Commission v Abbco Ice Works Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1279 ; (1994) 52 FCR 96. However, even if ASIC had sought to draw inferences against Forrest as well as the corporate entity, on my review of the authorities it would not have been precluded from doing so. There is no reason therefore, in these circumstances, why the inferences cannot, as a matter of law, be drawn against FMG in the present proceedings. The question which then arises is whether I should draw such an inference in the manner urged by ASIC

The authorities state that two inferences are involved in the rule in Jones v Dunkel . First, a court might infer that the evidence of the absent witness would not have assisted the party that failed to call that witness; secondly, a court might draw, with greater confidence, any inference unfavourable to the party that failed to call that witness, if that witness appears to be in a position to cast light on whether the inference should be drawn: Manly Council v Byrne and Anor [2004] NSWCA 123 at [51] ; ASIC v Macdonald [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 per Gzell J at [1137].

In Manly Council , the Court of Appeal stated that there is no compulsion on the trial judge to draw either of the Jones v Dunkel inferences. This was confirmed by the Court of Appeal in Howell v Macquarie University [2008] NSWCA 26 at [97] - [98], where Campbell JA said, with the agreement of Spigelman CJ and Bell JA (as her Honour then was): 
In other words, in a civil trial by judge alone Jones v Dunkel licences, but does not compel, the drawing of inferences when a witness is not called. Whether either or both of the inferences are actually drawn is part of the trial judge's task of weighing the evidence.

Further, the Court of Appeal in Manly Council referred to the principles concerning the application of Jones v Dunkel set out by Glass JA in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 at 201-202 which have been widely regarded as correct although Glass JA was in dissent as to the application of the principles to the facts: per Campbell JA with whom Beazley JA and Pearlman AJA agreed, at [53]. In Payne [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 , Glass JA said that whether Jones v Dunkel should be applied depends on establishing three conditions: 
(a) the missing witness would be expected to be called by one party rather than the other, 
 
 
(b) his evidence would elucidate a particular matter, 
 
 
(c) his absence is unexplained.

Before stating my conclusion on whether I ought to make any Jones v Dunkel inferences, I will deal with the final authority cited by Forrest, Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 , from which he submits the following propositions emerge: that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and that a Jones v Dunkel inference is not to be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents. In Singh , the applicant sought judicial review of a Ministerial decision to refuse to grant a spouse visa on character grounds. The Minister's reasons for decision were given in two documents: a decision record and a statement of reasons. The applicant argued that the Minister erred in making his decision by failing to have regard to the character references in support of the applicant which were annexed to a letter attached to the decision record. The Minister did not give evidence at trial, but Sackville J found that the statement of reasons provided affirmative evidence that the Minister gave consideration to the contents of the character references. The inferences that the applicant sought to draw by the Minister's failure to give evidence were contradicted by the Minister's statement of reasons.

In my view, what Sackville J said in Singh concerning the application of the Jones v Dunkel principle to the case before him is merely an application of the second condition given by Glass JA in Payne at p 201 as to whether the principle can or should be applied, namely whether the evidence of the missing witness would elucidate a particular matter. There was no occasion to draw an inference from the Minister's failure to give evidence because in his Honour's view, the question of whether he took into account the character references was adequately addressed by the statement of reasons.

As ASIC's senior counsel put it, in ASIC's closing written submissions, generally, the evidence upon which ASIC relies to establish all of the alleged contraventions is documentary, and founded upon FMG's own business records. This evidence is supplemented by certain alleged admissions by Watling and Rowley, derived from transcripts of examinations conducted by ASIC pursuant to s 19 of the ASIC Act : ASIC's closing submissions [47]-[48]. ASIC withdrew from tender alleged admissions made by Forrest during his s 19 examination. This was so despite the fact that Forrest who had not claimed privilege, as he might have done during his examination sought to have additional parts of his transcript admitted which he said would put in context and explained what ASIC contended amounted to admissions against Forrest's interest. The additional evidence, I infer, would have been favourable to Forrest. If ASIC considered that, despite this additional evidence, the transcript nonetheless disclosed relevant admissions then it would, no doubt, have persisted with its tender. However, I was denied the benefit of any of this evidence. ASIC has not identified any particular matters that the evidence of the executives, including Forrest, would elucidate. For these reasons, I decline to make any Jones v Dunkel inference against FMG from the failure of Forrest and the other executives to give evidence. Browne v Dunn

ASIC submits there is also a small amount of direct evidence from witnesses it called which mostly went unchallenged. For example, Catherine Li, a former FMG engineer, was not cross-examined about her evidence concerning a meeting on 6 November in which Forrest offered a 30% equity interest in the Project to a Chinese investor. Likewise, Wei Fisher, a former FMG executive assistant, was not cross-examined about her evidence of a letter from CMCC on about 3 February 2005, in which she recalls that CMCC claimed that the "deal" with the Chinese contractors was off.

FMG's honesty in this respect depends on that of Forrest and other members of its board. That FMG's opinion was genuine may be inferred from other facts. For reasons contained under Part 3 I draw no Jones v Dunkel inference against Forrest by reason of him not giving evidence.

It is instructive to consider the following: 
(a) legal oversight and advice; 
 
(b) the position adopted by the Chinese Contractors; 
 
(c) FMG's internal records; 
 
(d) FMG's external communications; 
 
(e) the position adopted by FMG executives;
 
(f) Advanced framework agreements; 
 
(g) comparison with other FMG documents. 
 
 Legal oversight and advice

ASIC, in respect to its case under s 674, pleads at ASC [136(3)] amongst other things, that FMG by its board, including Forrest, ought to have come into possession of the parts of the Informations concerning, on ASIC's case, the legal effect of the framework agreements by first obtaining competent legal advice as to the legal effect of the framework agreements.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c48">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jubilee Mines NL v Riley (2009) 253 ALR 673</tocase>
<text>There is an apparent distinction between Listing Rule 3.1 which requires that the information be expected to have a "material" effect on the price or value of the securities and the deeming provision in s 677 of the Act which requires only that the information would or would be likely to "influence" common investors. This was considered by the Court of Appeal of Western Australia in Jubilee Mines NL v Riley (2009) 253 ALR 673 in respect of equivalent provisions in the continuous disclosure provisions in the Corporations Law and the ASX Listing Rules.

In Jubilee Mines 253 ALR 673 the provisions of the Act relating to continuous disclosure were at that time located in Chapter 7, Part 7.11, Div 2. They were relocated to Chapter 6CA by the Financial Services Reform Act 2001 . The relevant continuous disclosure Listing Rule was Rule 3A(1) the equivalent of that Rule is now Rule 3.1. The equivalent of s 674, s 675 and s 677 that were considered are s 1001A, s 1001B and s 1001D respectively.

In Jubilee Mines 253 ALR 673 the issue was whether Jubilee, a small listed gold exploration company that wanted to transition into a gold producing company had to disclose information that it received, in 1994, of drilling results about the nickel development potential of its tenements, on receiving that information from a neighbouring tenement holder Western Mining Corporation Ltd, which had inadvertently conducted drilling on Jubilee's tenements. When such information was released in 1996, there was a resultant increase in Jubilee's share price. But, in 1994, Jubilee was focussed on gold and was short of cash, without the necessary ability to develop any nickel assets. The Court of Appeal allowed the appeal from a judgment of a master of the Supreme Court, and held that there had been no contravention of s 1001A essentially because the information was held to be not material in 1994. Martin CJ delivered the main judgment with which Le Miere AJA agreed. McLure JA delivered a separate judgment.

Martin CJ rejected the argument that the Listing Rule can only be contravened if a reasonable person would expect the information to have a material effect on the price or value of a company's securities quite independently of the question posed by s 1001D. His Honour said the better view is that s 1001D applies to the Listing Rule, with the consequence that if information has the characteristic defined in that section, it should be taken to be information falling within the scope of the Listing Rule: [34], [54]-[62]. This was for the reason that acceptance of the argument would create an inconsistency between the Listing Rule on the one hand and ss 1001A and 1001D on the other, which would not have been intended by Parliament. The inconsistency would be that the Listing Rule would require notification only when there was a reasonably expected material impact on share price or value, whilst ss 1001A and 1001D would require notification whenever the information would, or would be likely to influence common investors: [60]-[61].

In a separate judgment, McLure JA considered whether s 1001D supplants the third element of the Listing Rule, namely materiality and concluded that because s 1001D was stated to apply for the purposes of s 1001A and s 1001B but not the Listing Rule; and because s 1001A and s 1001B apply only if information is not generally available, unlike the Listing Rule, which applies regardless, s 1001D did not describe materiality for the purposes of the Listing Rule: [149]-[150]. At [165] McLure JA also referred to the "obvious terminological differences" between the tests in s 1001D and the Listing Rule. Her Honour stated that the test in s 1001D does not rely on a hypothetical reasonable person and does not require a material effect on the price of securities. However, in the circumstances of the case, her Honour held it was unnecessary to determine whether the differences are capable of producing different outcomes, because the concession of the parties that the price of shares in the relevant company were determined by the conduct and motivations of share traders would apply to both tests and the outcome would have been the same.

On 31 July 2009, the High Court refused application for special leave to appeal the Court of Appeal's decision.

In my opinion, in substance, the approach adopted by the majority is correct. It is a matter of the proper construction of Listing Rule 3.1. I would construe "information" which "would, or would be likely to influence" common investors in deciding whether to acquire or dispose of securities as information, for the purposes of Listing Rule 3.1, that a reasonable person would expect to have a material effect on the price or value of the securities. This is merely an approach to the construction of the words "material effect on the price or value of the entity's securities" in Listing Rule 3.1 which provides harmony with the provisions of ss 674 and 677 of the Act.

Paragraph 20 of Guidance Note 8 to Listing Rule 3.1, which refers to s 674 and s 677, supports this construction.

The relevant requirements of Listing Rule 3.1 and s 674(2)(c), as applicable to FMG at the time it made the notifications to the ASX in August and November 2004 were as follows: 
(a) there must have existed "information" within the meaning of Listing Rule 3.1 and s 674(2);
 
 
(b) FMG must have been aware of that information: s 674(2)(b), Listing Rule 3.1;
 
 
(c) that information must not have been generally available: s 674(2)(c)(i), cf Listing Rule 3.1A.1; and 
 
 
(d) a reasonable person would have expected that information to have had a material effect on the price or value of FMG's shares, if it had been generally available: s 674(2)(c)(ii), Listing Rule 3.1.
 
 
The meaning and operation of the last two requirements is governed by ss 676 and s 677 respectively.

I find support, in my approach to the issue of opinion, in the context of Listing Rule 3.1, from the judgment of McLure JA in Jubilee Mines 253 ALR 673. This case involved competing opinions as to the significance of geological information (the WMC information) supplied to Jubilee.

Jubilee had obtained an expert opinion from a geologist, Mr Cooke, who was also an executive of Jubilee. In light of his opinion, Jubilee's managing director decided there was no need to disclose the information to the ASX. The respondent's expert opinion given at trial was to the contrary. McLure JA observed at [160] that expert opinions held in good faith on reasonable grounds may differ. Her Honour also stated at [185]: 
However, the fact that there are competing expert opinions on the level of significance of the WMC information does not justify a conclusion that the appellant ought to have been aware that the WMC information was highly significant. No doubt if Mr Cooke's assessment was negligent (not based on reasonable grounds) there may be room for such a finding. However, I see no basis in the evidence for a finding that Mr Cooke's opinion was other than honestly held on reasonable grounds. Subsequent drilling results do not support a finding that Mr Cooke's 1994 assessment was unreasonable. 
 
 Were ASIC's opinions as to the legal effect of the framework agreements self evident having regard to their terms?

ASIC's case is that the opinions, in effect, expressed in the Informations were obvious and the only opinions reasonably open objectively. I say opinions, because even on ASIC's case there are competing opinions. First ASIC submits that the framework agreements have no legal effect and are therefore unenforceable. Second ASIC submits that if they are enforceable they are merely agreements to enter into negotiations.

It follows that ASIC's contention necessarily extends to a submission that FMG's opinion as to the meaning and legal effect of the framework agreement, in effect contained in the disclosures opinion was not reasonably open.

I accept however that evidence of the actual effect of the information actually disclosed on FMG's share price may be relevant to assist the Court in its determination of whether s 674(2) has been contravened: Rivkin Financial Services Ltd v Sofcom Ltd (2004) 51 ACSR 486 by analogy at [113]-[116]; Jubilee Mines NL v Riley (2009) 253 ALR 673 at [33], [130] and [134]. This involves an ex post inquiry . Such evidence may constitute a relevant cross-check as to the reasonableness of an ex ante judgment about a different hypothetical disclosure. Gzell J in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) 256 ALR at [1067] said: 
Where likelihood of the occurrence of an event is in issue and relevant facts are available, they are to be preferred to prophecies.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c49">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>MacKenzie v Childers (1889) 43 Ch D 265</tocase>
<text>Authority supports an argument that the agreement recorded in the recitals for CREC to build or "execute" the railway should be given effect and should be treated as an agreement between FMG and CREC even where the operative provisions of the framework agreement do not contain such a provision and there is nothing inconsistent with such a construction in the operative provisions: Buckland v Buckland [1900] 2 Ch 534 at 540.3; MacKenzie v Childers (1889) 43 Ch D 265 at 274.7, 275.4-276.1; Ex parte Dawes; in re Moon (1886) 17 QBD 275 , 286.8, 288.2, 289.7; Aspdin v Austin (1844) 5 QB 671 at 683. This is even more so where, as here, the framework agreements were not drawn by lawyers. They were drafted by Heyting, an engineer, who also holds a Masters of Business Administration and who had some training in contract management. In those circumstances, arguably, a distinction between recitals and operational clauses should not be rigorously applied in an attempt to determine the parties' intention, determined objectively. Expressly, the recitals proceed on the basis that there is an agreement for the relevant Chinese contractor to build the infrastructure which is sought to be recorded in the framework agreements. The recitals do not say or imply that what follows is merely an informal arrangement, or a mere agreement to negotiate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c50">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Manly Council v Byrne and Anor [2004] NSWCA 123</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2004/123.html</AustLII>
<text>The authorities state that two inferences are involved in the rule in Jones v Dunkel . First, a court might infer that the evidence of the absent witness would not have assisted the party that failed to call that witness; secondly, a court might draw, with greater confidence, any inference unfavourable to the party that failed to call that witness, if that witness appears to be in a position to cast light on whether the inference should be drawn: Manly Council v Byrne and Anor [2004] NSWCA 123 at [51] ; ASIC v Macdonald [2009] NSWSC 287 ; 256 ALR 199 per Gzell J at [1137].

In Manly Council , the Court of Appeal stated that there is no compulsion on the trial judge to draw either of the Jones v Dunkel inferences. This was confirmed by the Court of Appeal in Howell v Macquarie University [2008] NSWCA 26 at [97] - [98], where Campbell JA said, with the agreement of Spigelman CJ and Bell JA (as her Honour then was): 
In other words, in a civil trial by judge alone Jones v Dunkel licences, but does not compel, the drawing of inferences when a witness is not called. Whether either or both of the inferences are actually drawn is part of the trial judge's task of weighing the evidence.

Further, the Court of Appeal in Manly Council referred to the principles concerning the application of Jones v Dunkel set out by Glass JA in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 at 201-202 which have been widely regarded as correct although Glass JA was in dissent as to the application of the principles to the facts: per Campbell JA with whom Beazley JA and Pearlman AJA agreed, at [53]. In Payne [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 , Glass JA said that whether Jones v Dunkel should be applied depends on establishing three conditions: 
(a) the missing witness would be expected to be called by one party rather than the other, 
 
 
(b) his evidence would elucidate a particular matter, 
 
 
(c) his absence is unexplained.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c51">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; (1954) 91 CLR 353</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1954/72.html</AustLII>
<text>Forrest submits that the agreement falls under the first category of agreement identified in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 such that the parties have agreed all terms and intend to be bound immediately but propose 'to have the terms restated in a form which will be fuller or more precise but not different in effect'. Like FMG, Forrest submits that the agreement was a binding first agreement for the build, finance and transfer of the railway, with a further agreement to be executed at a later date.

ASIC submits, however, that the most noteworthy aspect of the agreement is the absence of agreement on critical matters, and the complete absence of detail about other matters. ASIC makes the following submissions regarding the terms of the CREC Framework Agreement in support of its contentions that the agreement was a bare agreement to negotiate the scope and terms of a further contract to build, transfer and finance the infrastructure, and that it did not impose any legally enforceable obligations: 
(a) CREC was not obliged to actually build or transfer the railway;
 
 
(b) there was no agreed price in the agreement nor any mechanism to achieve or confirm a price;
 
 
(c) there was no definition of the scope of the works to be performed;
 
 
(d) there was no provision for choice of contractors or the selection of materials;
 
 
(e) there was no definition of "practical completion";
 
 
(f) there were no specifications for any design elements of the infrastructure. 
 
 
I will deal with each of these in turn. 
 Was CREC arguably obliged to actually build or transfer the railway?

In Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR 540 Gleeson CJ, with whom Hope and Mahoney JJA agreed, confirmed at 584E-F the importance in a Masters v Cameron type of dispute of assessing the parties' intention to make a concluded bargain, and stated that the question of intention is distinct from, although it may be closely related to, the question whether the parties have reached agreement upon such terms as are, in the circumstances, legally necessary to constitute a contract. His Honour stated: 
Nevertheless, in the ordinary case, as a matter of fact and commonsense,
other things being equal, the more numerous and significant the areas in
respect of which the parties have failed to reach agreement, the slower a
court will be to conclude that they had the requisite contractual intention.

Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 involved a contractual dispute where the parties had executed a document entitled 'Heads of Agreement' (HofA), clause 3.3 of which stated: "Each party will conduct all such negotiations in good faith to ensure that the terms set out in these Heads of Agreement are given full effect". It was not in dispute in Jobern that the parties were bound by the HoFA, which Gordon J stated to be a final agreement within the first category described in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 at [106] . However Gordon J considered that cl 3.3 was uncertain because it suffered from the same problems referred to by Kirby J in Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1 at [130].

In Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 , Dixon CJ, McTiernan and Kitto JJ explained in a joint judgment that where parties who have been in negotiation reach agreement upon terms of a contractual nature and also agree that the matter of their negotiation shall be dealt with by a formal contract, the case may belong to any of three classes, the first two involving binding contracts (360): 
(1) The parties have agreed all terms and intend to be bound immediately but at the same time propose 'to have the terms restated in a form which will be fuller or more precise but not different in effect';
 
 
(2) The parties have agreed all terms but intend to make performance of one or more terms conditional on the execution of a formal document;
 
 
(3) The intention may be not to make a concluded bargain at all unless and until the parties execute a formal contract.

The judgment went on to explain that the question depends upon the intention disclosed by the language the parties have employed (362.5) and that there is no formula, such as "subject to contract" which is so intractable as always and necessarily to produce a result that there is no binding contract (363.6).

The courts have also recognised a fourth class of case additional to the three mentioned in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 , a class identified by Knox CJ, Rich J and Dixon J in Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co Ltd v Naughton [1929] HCA 34 ; (1929) 43 CLR 310 at 317 as: 
... one in which the parties were content to be bound immediately and exclusively by the terms which they had agreed upon whilst expecting to make a further contract in substitution for the first contract, containing, by consent, additional terms.

This fourth category was recognised by McLelland J in Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 622 and on appeal in G R Securities Pty Ltd v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 631 where McHugh JA delivered the Court of Appeal's judgment and observed that the magnitude, subject matter or complexities of a transaction may indicate that an agreement was a limited one not intended to have legal effect (634D) but that what was critical was the parties' intention objectively ascertained, and that this intention should prevail (634E-F). In Uranium Equities Ltd [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal) stated at [129] that the fourth Masters v Cameron category was a variation of the first category.

In Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248 , the NSW Court of Appeal emphasised that determining whether parties have come to a concluded agreement is a matter of their objectively ascertained intention in the particular case. Giles JA stated that the Masters v Cameron categories and a possible fourth category are intellectual aids, and that categorisation does not greatly contribute to the decision in the particular case, which is concerned with finding what agreement, if any, the parties came to, [26]. Similarly, in Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60 , Keane JA, with whom McMurdo P and Atkinson J agreed, said at [37] in relation to classifying the putative agreement in that case under one of the four Masters v Cameron categories: 
In my respectful opinion, however, there is little purpose to be served in seeking to resolve the issue of classification. A concern as to classification should not be allowed to obscure or distract from the real task of the court which is to ascertain and give effect to the intentions of the parties.

Keane JA referred to Sir Anthony Mason's opening address to the Journal of Contract Law 20 th Anniversary Conference ((2009) 25 Journal of Contract Law 1, 6): 
... [T]he categories (or classifications of Masters v Cameron ((1954) [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353) , be they three or four, are no more than exemplifications of the general principle that, in the case of written documents, the intention of the parties is to be resolved objectively and as a matter of construction of the relevant documents. The categories are necessarily subject to the general principle.

The question therefore, which is of paramount importance here is whether or not the parties to the framework agreements intended them, objectively, to be legally binding.

In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the issue was whether a binding contract for Anaconda, a company interested in lateritic nickel, to explore and mine for base metals on the tenements of Tarmoola, a company interested mainly in gold, had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement ' constitutes an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form' . Tarmoola argued that there was no intention to contract, no agreement on essential terms, and that the agreement was incomplete and uncertain. By majority, the WA Full Court rejected these arguments and held that the heads of agreement was a binding contract. Ipp J (with whom Pidgeon J agreed) found that contractual intention was present. His Honour endorsed the existence of the fourth Masters v Cameron category in stating: 
It is well recognised that parties may enter into a valid contract containing a limited number of terms comprising those terms essential to the bargain that they wish to conclude, in the expectation that at a later date a further contract will be arrived at containing additional terms that would facilitate and clarify the initial contract. That is to say, a binding contract may be arrived at even though it leaves unresolved many matters which might arise in future. [25]

His Honour found that the agreement was neither incomplete nor uncertain such as to render it void or such as to indicate that the parties did not intend to enter into legal relations, and that the agreement contained all the essential terms required for a legally binding agreement. The omission to deal with particular future problems such as water did not make the agreement uncertain or incomplete: these issues could be resolved by processes of construction and implication: [79]. His Honour stated that the parties' failure to enter into a more detailed agreement may have made the exploring and mining operations contemplated by the heads of agreement more expensive, difficult and complex, but he did not accept that it was unworkable in the sense of it being objectively impossible for performance of its terms to be effected: [95]. In dissent, Anderson J noted that the trial judge had found this case to be in the third Masters v Cameron category, that is, a case in which the terms of the heads of agreement were not indtended to have and therefore did not have any binding effect of their own, and he agreed with the trial judge that the parties did not intend the heads of agreement to have binding effect as their concluded bargain ([121]-[124]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c52">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd v Hebron Park Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//qld/QCA/2009/60.html</AustLII>
<text>ASIC also points to the absence of the following from the framework agreements: no provision for choice of contractors or the selection of materials; no definition of "practical completion"; and no specifications for any design elements of the infrastructure. The documents referred to in the Recitals to each agreement would have, no doubt, assisted in clarifying the matters absent from the agreements. In light of those documents, following the approach of Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [61] , it may have been possible to conclude that, despite the long list of matters said to render the framework agreements uncertain and incomplete, there was a binding contract, workable by implying terms or on the proper construction of the agreement. The court will apply orthodox principles of implying terms by reference to the implied duty to co-operate and use considerations of reasonableness, to give effect to that intention: Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR 540; Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd v Hebron Park Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60. The asserted uncertainty or incompleteness may therefore be overcome once the requisite intention to contract is found to be present.

In Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248 , the NSW Court of Appeal emphasised that determining whether parties have come to a concluded agreement is a matter of their objectively ascertained intention in the particular case. Giles JA stated that the Masters v Cameron categories and a possible fourth category are intellectual aids, and that categorisation does not greatly contribute to the decision in the particular case, which is concerned with finding what agreement, if any, the parties came to, [26]. Similarly, in Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60 , Keane JA, with whom McMurdo P and Atkinson J agreed, said at [37] in relation to classifying the putative agreement in that case under one of the four Masters v Cameron categories: 
In my respectful opinion, however, there is little purpose to be served in seeking to resolve the issue of classification. A concern as to classification should not be allowed to obscure or distract from the real task of the court which is to ascertain and give effect to the intentions of the parties.

The approach taken in G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631, Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 and Tasman Capital [2008] NSWCA 248 was followed very recently by the Queensland Court of Appeal in Moffat Property Development Group [2009] QCA 60 , mentioned above, which underlined the importance of the parties' manifest intention to contract. The issue was whether a contract for the sale of rural residential land had been made by an exchange of letters. The Queensland Court of Appeal held that the parties intended to be legally bound through their exchange of correspondence and that there was a contract even though matters such as the timing of completion and arrangements at settlement, the precise timing of the payment of the deposit, the place of settlement, responsibility for insurance, GST issues and the terms of a put and call option were not spelt out in the correspondence. Keane JA delivered the court's judgment. His Honour: 
(a) accepted McHugh JA's point in G R Securities that "the decisive issue is always the intention of the parties": [23]-[25];
 
(b) said "the terms of the correspondence exchanged between the parties contemplated the execution of a further contract as the means whereby the bargain which they had concluded would be implemented. It is necessarily implicit in such an agreement that the parties will co-operate to do what must be done to make the further agreement": [30];
 
(c) adopted McHugh JA's approach in G R Securities and explained that the implied obligation of each party to co-operate with the other to ensure each side obtains the benefit of its bargain serves to supply the deficiencies: [34];
 
(d) cited Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR at 548 in stating: "I am of the view that there can be no doubt as to the orthodoxy of referring to 'implied terms or ... considerations of reasonableness' in order to determine whether the parties' 'consensus is sufficiently comprehensive to be legally binding : [51].

Accordingly, Moffat Property Development Group [2009] QCA 60 , has most recently emphasised that the central question is the parties' manifest intention to contract, and the court will apply orthodox principles of implying terms, by reference to the implied duty to co-operate, and use considerations of reasonableness, to give effect to the parties' contractual intention. Alleged uncertainty or incompleteness is usually able to be overcome if the requisite intention to contract is found to be present. Was the opinion of FMG and Forrest honestly and reasonably held?

In my view, for the following reasons, the evidence, particularly as to the oversight and legal advice given to FMG by Huston and the adoption of FMG's opinion by the Chinese Contractors amply supports the conclusion that the opinion of FMG through Forrest that the framework agreements were legally binding agreements to build, finance and transfer the infrastructure, were reasonably and honestly held. It also disposes of ASIC's claim that if FMG had obtained competent legal advice it would not have made the disclosures it did as to the legal effect of the framework agreements.

ASIC alleges in relation to FMG's disclosures that neither it nor Forrest genuinely held the opinion that each of the framework agreements was a legally enforceable build, finance and transfer agreement. It palpably failed to establish this allegation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c53">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Narain v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2008] HCATrans 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCATrans/2008/408.html</AustLII>
<text>The effect of the amendments was to expand the scope of s 1041H beyond dealing in securities to any misleading and deceptive conduct in relation to a financial product or financial services. The Full Federal Court has recognised that the scope of the operation of s 1041H is very wide: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Narain [2008] FCAFC 120 ; (2008) 169 FCR 211. Special leave to appeal to the High Court was refused: Narain v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2008] HCATrans 408 per Crennan and Kiefel JJ. Section 1041H: general principles</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c54">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>National Exchange v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2004] FCAFC 90 ; (2004) 22 ACLC 609</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/90.html</AustLII>
<text>In National Exchange v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2004] FCAFC 90 ; (2004) 22 ACLC 609 , Dowsett J, with whom Jacobson and Bennett JJ agreed with generally, compiled at [18] a helpful summary of the propositions relevant to the application of s 52 emerging from the High Court's judgment in Campomar Sociedad. Dowsett J's summary, to which I have added references to the paragraphs of the High Court's judgment applicable to each proposition, is as follows. His Honour accepted that these observations are of general application in proceedings alleging contravention of s 1041H(1) of the Act, [19]. Conduct will only be misleading or deceptive, or likely to mislead or deceive if there is a nexus between such conduct and any actual or anticipated misconception or deception. [98] 
 In identifying such nexus regard must be had to the circumstances of the particular case, including the remedies sought. Section 52 of the TP Act does not confer any entitlement to a remedy for breach or anticipated breach. One must look elsewhere in the TP Act for such entitlement and construe the act as a whole. [99] 
 In some cases, a representation may be made to identified individuals; in other cases the representation may be to the public at large or to a section thereof. In the former case the process of deciding whether or not the representation is misleading or deceptive or likely to be so may be 'direct and uncomplicated'. In the latter case 'the issue with respect to the sufficiency of the nexus between the conduct or the apprehended conduct and the misleading or deception or likely misleading or deception of prospective purchasers is to be approached at a level of abstraction not present where the case is one involving an express untrue representation allegedly made only to identified individuals'. (I infer that the word "representation" in [100] of Nike should be "misrepresentation", relying upon the relevant passage in Taco Bell to which the High Court was referring.) [100]
 When the representation is made to the public or to a section thereof, one must consider its effect upon an ordinary or reasonable member of the class in question. Although such class may include a wide range of persons, the ordinary or reasonable member will objectively be identified as having certain characteristics. In particular he or she can be expected to take reasonable care for his or her own interests and otherwise to behave reasonably. [101]-[102]
 It is necessary to inquire as to how a particular or anticipated misconception has arisen or may arise. In so doing, the Court will consider 'the effect of the relevant conduct on reasonable members of the class'. [103]
 Conduct will only be misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive if the representee 'labours under some erroneous assumption' or may be expected so to labour. Such an assumption or anticipated assumption may be obvious, predictable or fanciful. [104]
 In assessing the reactions or likely reactions of the ordinary or reasonable member of the class, the Court may decline to treat as reasonable, assumptions which are extreme or fanciful. The initial question which must be determined is whether the misconception or deception, alleged or anticipated, is properly attributable to an ordinary or reasonable member of the class. [105] 
 The 'question whether particular conduct causes confusion or wonderment cannot be substituted for the question whether the conduct answers the statutory description contained in s 52.' [106]

However, where there is a finding of intention to deceive, the court may more readily infer that the intention has been or in all probability will be effective: Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd [1980] 2 NSWLR 851 at 861; S &amp; I Publishing Pty Ltd v Australian Surf Life Saver Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 316 ; (1998) 88 FCR 354 at 362; Campomar Sociedad [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at [33] and National Exchange [2004] FCAFC 90 ; 22 ACLC 609 at [63] per Jacobson and Bennett JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c55">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/66.html</AustLII>
<text>In Neat Holdings Pty Ltd v Karajan Holdings Pty Ltd [1992] HCA 66 ; (1992) 110 ALR 449 at 449-450 Mason CJ, Brennan, Deane and Gaudron JJ referred to Dixon J's considerations in Briginshaw and said: 
The ordinary standard of proof required of a party who bears the onus in civil litigation in this country is proof on the balance of probabilities. That remains so even where the matter to be proved involves criminal conduct or fraud . On the other hand, the strength of the evidence necessary to establish a fact or facts on the balance of probabilities may vary according to the nature of what it is sought to prove. Thus, authoritative statements have often been made to the effect that clear or cogent or strict proof is necessary 'where so serious a matter as fraud is to be found'. Statements to that effect should not, however, be understood as directed to the standard of proof. Rather, they should be understood as merely reflecting a conventional perception that members of our society do not ordinarily engage in fraudulent or criminal conduct and a judicial approach that a court should not lightly make a finding that, on the balance of probabilities, a party to civil litigation has been guilty of such conduct. (Emphasis added. Citations omitted)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c56">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/35.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG makes the following submission which I accept as a correct statement of the law. The proper construction of an agreement should be determined by what reasonable people in the position of the parties would have understood by the relevant clauses by considering not only their text, but also the surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the transaction: e.g. Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at [40] ; International Air Transport Association v Ansett Australia Holdings Ltd [2008] HCA 3 ; (2008) 234 CLR 151 at [8] and [53]. The whole of the document should be considered and its provisions given harmonious effect: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1973] HCA 36 ; (1973) 129 CLR 99 at 109 (Gibbs J, in dissent, but not on the applicable principle).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c57">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Pagnan SpA v Feed Products [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep 601</tocase>
<text>In Pagnan SpA v Feed Products Ltd [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep 601 the English Court of Appeal held that a binding contract had been made in circumstances where no price, quantity, delivery date, loading rate, rate of demurrage and despatch or date of commencement in regard to the sale of corn gluten feed pellets had been agreed in an exchange of telexes between the parties. The fact that the terms yet to be agreed were of economic significance did not prevent a contract being binding if that was what the parties intended. Further, the fact that the parties continued to negotiate after the first agreement had been entered had no effect on whether the agreements were binding because ' ...it was only to be expected that they would continue negotiating the terms that remained without delay' (at 620.8). Lloyd LJ's listing of the principles to be derived from the authorities included at 619.1 that: 
...the parties may intend to be bound forthwith even though there are further terms still to be agreed or some further formality to be fulfilled'.

Lloyd LJ also stated at 619.5: 
It is sometimes said that the parties must agree on the essential terms and that it is only matters of detail which can be left over. This may be misleading, since the word "essential" in that context is ambiguous. If by "essential" one means a term without which the contract cannot be enforced then the statement is true: the law cannot enforce an incomplete contract. If by "essential" one means a term which the parties have agreed to be essential for the formation of a binding contract, then the statement is tautologous. If by "essential" one means only a term which the Court regards as important as opposed to a term which the Court regards as less important or a matter of detail, the statement is untrue. It is for the parties to decide whether they wish to be bound and, if so, by what terms, whether important or unimportant. It is the parties who are, in the memorable phrase coined by the Judge, "the masters of their contractual fate". Of course the more important the term is the less likely it is that the parties will have left it for future decision. But there is no legal obstacle which stands in the way of parties agreeing to be bound now while deferring important matters to be agreed later. It happens everyday when parties enter into so called 'heads of agreement'. (Emphasis added).

But at [29] Ipp J also referred to the statement of Lloyd LJ in Pagnan SpA [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep 601 that I have extracted above, where his Lordship emphasised that that the meaning of 'essential' in the context of agreeing upon essential terms was ambiguous and that there was no legal obstacle standing in the way of the parties agreeing to be bound now while deferring important matters to be agreed later.

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the parties to the putative agreement had been negotiating over a proposed mining joint venture, but no heads of agreement had been executed. The Court found that the trial judge was right in concluding that the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed. The Court went on to state on the question of uncertainty at [257] that it is "trite" that, even when the requisite intention is present, a contract can fail for uncertainty. The Court said it is also trite that only the omission of an essential term will have the effect that a contract is so incomplete or uncertain as to render it invalid, citing Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [29] . The Court referred to the statement of Lloyd LJ from Pagnan SpA [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep at 619 and found that when regard was had to all the circumstances the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed . The Court concluded that although some of the matters left over by the parties for future negotiation were important, none were essential to the efficacy of the alleged agreement in the sense that the agreement could not be enforced without it.

In the same vein in Fletcher Challenge Energy Ltd v Electricity Corporation of New Zealand Ltd [2002] 2 NZLR 433 at 445, Blanchard J observed: 
The court has an entirely neutral approach when determining whether the parties intended to enter into a contract. Having decided that they had that intention, however, the Court's attitude will change. It will then do its best to give effect to their intention and, if at all possible, to uphold the contract despite any omissions or ambiguities. 
 
 
At 448, Blanchard J referred to the statement of the English Court of Appeal in Pagnan SpA v Feed Products [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep 601: 
 
Merely because an important term is deferred to be settled on a future occasion that does not mean that there is no intention to be bound.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c58">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Proprietary Limited v Puxu Proprietary Limited [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/44.html</AustLII>
<text>A further relevant principle concerns the intention of the representor. Intention is not a necessary element of the contravention of s 52. The section involves no questions of intent upon the part of the corporation whose conduct is in question: Hornsby Building Information Centre Pty Ltd v Sydney Building Information Centre Ltd [1978] HCA 11 ; (1978) 140 CLR 216 at 228 per Stephen J; Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Proprietary Limited v Puxu Proprietary Limited [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 at 216 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c59">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191</tocase>
<text>Further, the Court of Appeal in Manly Council referred to the principles concerning the application of Jones v Dunkel set out by Glass JA in Payne v Parker [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 at 201-202 which have been widely regarded as correct although Glass JA was in dissent as to the application of the principles to the facts: per Campbell JA with whom Beazley JA and Pearlman AJA agreed, at [53]. In Payne [1976] 1 NSWLR 191 , Glass JA said that whether Jones v Dunkel should be applied depends on establishing three conditions: 
(a) the missing witness would be expected to be called by one party rather than the other, 
 
 
(b) his evidence would elucidate a particular matter, 
 
 
(c) his absence is unexplained.

In my view, what Sackville J said in Singh concerning the application of the Jones v Dunkel principle to the case before him is merely an application of the second condition given by Glass JA in Payne at p 201 as to whether the principle can or should be applied, namely whether the evidence of the missing witness would elucidate a particular matter. There was no occasion to draw an inference from the Minister's failure to give evidence because in his Honour's view, the question of whether he took into account the character references was adequately addressed by the statement of reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c60">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Permanent Building Society v Wheeler (1994) 11 WAR 187</tocase>
<text>I accept ASIC's submission that a chief executive officer or managing director may reasonably be expected to have more information available to him or her and to be more diligent than other board members. The title, Managing Director, is synonymous with Chief Executive Officer. This matter of principle may be discerned from a number of authorities. A managing director has a particular responsibility to make sure the other directors understand the potential harm in a proposed transaction: Permanent Building Society v Wheeler (1994) 11 WAR 187, at 241. A chief executive officer will be employed under a contract containing an express or implied term that he or she exercise the care and skill expected of a person in that position: AWA Ltd v Daniels t/as Deloitte Haskins &amp; Sells (1992) 7 ACSR 759 at 1014. At p 867 the Court explained that a chairman is: 
...responsible to a greater extent than any other director for the performance of the board as a whole and each member of it. The chairman has the primary responsibility of selecting matters and documents to be brought to the board's attention, in formulating the policy of the Board and in promoting the position of the company.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c61">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Qantas Airways Limited v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69 ; (2008) 167 FCR 537</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/69.html</AustLII>
<text>In Qantas Airways Limited v Gama [2008] FCAFC 69 ; (2008) 167 FCR 537 , French and Jacobson JJ stated at [110] that the "so-called Briginshaw test" does not create any third standard of proof between the civil and the criminal. Their Honours said the standard of proof remains the same, that is proof on the balance of probabilities, and that the degree of satisfaction that is required in determining that that standard has been discharged may vary according to the seriousness of the allegations of misconduct that are made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c62">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Randall v Aristocrat Leisure Ltd [2004] NSWSC 411</tocase>
<text>Unique amongst other corporate officers, the chief executive officer stands at the apex of the operational and managerial structures of the company, and his or her authority is qualified only by any residual power left in the board: Randall v Aristocrat Leisure Ltd [2004] NSWSC 411. A chairperson of a listed public company may have special responsibilities beyond those of other non-executive directors. These responsibilities include such things as the public announcement of information: ASIC v Rich [2009] NSWSC 1229 at 463.

Einstein J in Randall v Aristocrat Leisure [2004] NSWSC 411 said at [383]: 
Subject always to the terms of appointment, it is evident that the law tends to assume that where the board resolves to appoint a chief executive officer, his or her powers to control the operational and managerial aspects of the company's business will be broad indeed. In the seminal case of Freeman &amp; Lockyer (a firm) v Buckhurst Park Properties (Mangal) Ltd [1964] 2 QB 480 , for example, Lord Diplock held (at 505) that where a board permits a person to "act in the management or conduct of the company's business", that delegation of executive authority alone is sufficient to vest that person with ostensible authority to bind the company to transactions usually entered into "in the course of such business" by such managers... Moreover, and equally facilitative of the exercise by a chief executive of broad powers of company management, is the replaceable rule in s 198C(1) of the Act, which provides that "[t]he directors of a company may confer on a managing director any of the powers that the directors can exercise.

The breadth of managerial powers delegated to the chief executive officer by the board is ultimately contingent on the terms of appointment of the CEO: Harold Holdsworth &amp; Co (Wakefield) Ltd v Caddies [1955] 1 WLR 352 as cited in Randall v Aristocrat Leisure [2004] NSWSC 411 at [382] . There is no evidence to demonstrate that Forrest's powers and authority as Chief Executive Officer were limited in any relevant way. I find that he was intimately and directly involved in the execution of the framework agreements, the formulation of FMG's notifications to the ASX and other disclosures, as well as the ongoing discussions with the NDRC and CMCC seeking Chinese government approval. Likewise, Forrest was intimately and directly involved in discussions with the NDRC and CMCC concerning the NDRC precondition to approval that FMG must provide one or more nominated Chinese companies with minority equity participation in FMG or the Project.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c63">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Bradberry; National Provincial Bank Ltd v Bradberry (1943) Ch 35</tocase>
<text>This, in effect, was a restatement of what was said by Dixon J in Willis v Commonwealth [1946] HCA 22 ; (1946) 73 CLR 105 at 116 who in turn had cited a passage from Uthwatt J in In re Bradberry; National Provincial Bank Ltd v Bradberry (1943) Ch 35 at pp 42-45.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c64">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rich v Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission [2003] NSWCA 342 ; (2003) 203 ALR 671</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2003/342.html</AustLII>
<text>Turning to the civil penalty authorities, in Rich , the High Court reversed a decision of the New South Wales Court of Appeal ( Rich v Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission [2003] NSWCA 342 ; (2003) 203 ALR 671) that the defendants in civil penalty proceedings brought by ASIC were not permitted to resist an order for discovery made by the trial judge by claiming the privilege against self-exposure to penalty. The orders sought by ASIC included disqualification orders but not pecuniary penalties. The trial judge, Austin J, did not classify the proceedings as proceedings for the imposition of a penalty: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich (No 3) [2003] NSWSC 328 ; (2003) 21 ACLC 920 , at [53]. the Court of Appeal (Spigelman CJ, with whom Ipp JA agreed; McColl JA dissenting) upheld Austin J's ruling, identifying a disqualification order as having an exclusively protective purpose and stating that it should not be characterized as a penalty for the purposes of the penalty privilege. However, the High Court (Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ, Kirby J dissenting) decided that the disqualification order was a penalty and accordingly the proper course was to refuse any order for discovery: per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ at [37]-[40]. The ruling was made in the joint judgment in consideration of s 1317L of the Act which requires the application of the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters when hearing proceedings for a declaration of contravention or a pecuniary penalty order. Their honours concluded at [19] that that the statute itself requires the application of the body of law which has developed in relation to the privileges against penalties and forfeitures when deciding whether an order for discovery should be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c65">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rich v Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission [2004] HCA 42 ; (2004) 220 CLR 129</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/42.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG made no submissions on whether Jones v Dunkel had any application. Citing Dyers v The Queen [2002] HCA 45 ; (2002) 210 CLR 285 , Forrest submitted in written closing submissions that a Jones v Dunkel inference may not be drawn against an accused in a criminal case because the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel is incompatible with the presumption of innocence and the rights of the accused; further, this reasoning applies with equal force to the accused calling other persons to give evidence. Forrest then submitted that the point of principle that, when an accused exercises the right not to give evidence the jury is directed that no adverse inference should be drawn, applies to a civil proceeding as against an individual defendant. He referred to the statement of Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, and Heydon JJ in Rich v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2004] HCA 42 ; (2004) 220 CLR 129 at [24] that the privilege against exposure to penalty serves the purpose of ensuring that those who allege criminality or other (illegal) conduct should prove it, and said there is no expectation that a defendant will give evidence on matters for which the plaintiff bears the onus of proof. He said there is no authority that supports the proposition that a Jones v Dunkel inference is available against an individual defendant in a civil penalty proceeding, though, he said, the position may be different for a company. Finally, Forrest submitted that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and a Jones v Dunkel inference is not be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents, citing Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [71] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c66">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rivkin Financial Services Ltd v Sofcom Ltd (2004) 51 ACSR 486</tocase>
<text>I accept however that evidence of the actual effect of the information actually disclosed on FMG's share price may be relevant to assist the Court in its determination of whether s 674(2) has been contravened: Rivkin Financial Services Ltd v Sofcom Ltd (2004) 51 ACSR 486 by analogy at [113]-[116]; Jubilee Mines NL v Riley (2009) 253 ALR 673 at [33], [130] and [134]. This involves an ex post inquiry . Such evidence may constitute a relevant cross-check as to the reasonableness of an ex ante judgment about a different hypothetical disclosure. Gzell J in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) 256 ALR at [1067] said: 
Where likelihood of the occurrence of an event is in issue and relevant facts are available, they are to be preferred to prophecies.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c67">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>RPS v The Queen [2000] HCA 3 ; (2000) 199 CLR 620</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/3.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG foreshadowed that it would call evidence from its executives, such as Rowley, David Liu and Alan Watling but it did not do so. ASIC submits that, where an inference is open from facts proved, the unexplained failure of a party to call a witness or tender a document may be taken into account as a circumstance in favour of the drawing inference: Jones v Dunkel [1959] HCA 8 ; (1959) 101 CLR 298 at 308, 312 and 320-321; RPS v The Queen [2000] HCA 3 ; (2000) 199 CLR 620 at [26] . ASIC submits that it should be inferred that Rowley, Liu and Watling were available to be called, but FMG chose not to call them for strategic reasons. As a result, ASIC says, if there are inferences to be drawn from documents in evidence, which could have been explained by these executives, or by Forrest who also elected not to give evidence, the inference should be drawn against FMG that the evidence of these executives would have been of no assistance to their case, and that the documents should bear the meaning contended for by ASIC.

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , Azzopardi v The Queen [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 205 CLR 50 and Dyers [2002] HCA 45 ; 210 CLR 285 , the High Court considered the applicability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel to criminal proceedings. It decided that the rule is of very limited application to defendants in criminal cases, its reasoning based on the accusatorial nature of criminal proceedings. As an illustration of the Court's approach, in Dyers , Gaudron and Hayne JJ stated at [9]: 
As was pointed out in RPS... , it will seldom, if ever, be reasonable to conclude that an accused in a criminal trial would be expected to give evidence. Not only is the accused not bound to give evidence, it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. The mode of reasoning which is spoken of in ... Jones v Dunkel (26) ordinarily, therefore, cannot be applied to a defendant in a criminal trial. That mode of reasoning depends upon a premise that the person concerned not only could shed light on the subject but also would ordinarily be expected to do so. The conclusion that an accused could shed light on the subject-matter of the charge is a conclusion that would ordinarily be reached very easily. But given the accusatorial nature of a criminal trial, it cannot be said that, in such a proceeding, the accused would ordinarily be expected to give evidence. So to hold would be to deny that it is for the prosecution to prove its case beyond reasonable doubt. That is why the majority of the Court concluded, in RPS and in Azzopardi , that it is ordinarily inappropriate to tell the jury that some inference can be drawn from the fact that the accused has not given evidence.

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , at [26]-[27] Gaudron A-CJ, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ contrasted the reasonable expectation that a party in a civil trial would give or call relevant evidence in the circumstances described in Jones v Dunkel with the conclusion that it would seldom, if ever, be reasonable to expect an accused in a criminal trial to give evidence. Weissensteiner provides an example of where the latter would be reasonable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c68">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>S &amp; I Publishing Pty Ltd v Australian Surf Life Saver Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 316 ; (1998) 88 FCR 354</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/316.html</AustLII>
<text>However, where there is a finding of intention to deceive, the court may more readily infer that the intention has been or in all probability will be effective: Cadbury-Schweppes Pty Ltd v Pub Squash Co Pty Ltd [1980] 2 NSWLR 851 at 861; S &amp; I Publishing Pty Ltd v Australian Surf Life Saver Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 316 ; (1998) 88 FCR 354 at 362; Campomar Sociedad [2000] HCA 12 ; 202 CLR 45 at [33] and National Exchange [2004] FCAFC 90 ; 22 ACLC 609 at [63] per Jacobson and Bennett JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c69">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Secured Income Real Estate (Australia) Ltd v St Martins Investments Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 51 ; (1979) 144 CLR 596</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1979/51.html</AustLII>
<text>The use of such expressions supports a finding of an intention to contract. In Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd 40 NSWLR 622 , McLelland J, in finding that by an exchange of letters the parties to an alleged agreement mutually communicated their respective assents to be legally bound by terms capable of having contractual effect, afforded the expression "legally binding" primacy despite the expression "agreement in principle" also found in the relevant agreement (628). His Honour thought that the case fell into the fourth category as recognised in Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 (629F) . The appeal from McLelland J's judgment G R Securities v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital 40 NSWLR 631 was dismissed. McHugh JA accepted in line with Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 , that it was possible for the parties to be bound immediately and agree to substitute for the first contract a further contract containing additional terms (634G). Further, McHugh JA applied the general rule applicable to every contract explained by Mason J in Secured Income Real Estate (Australia) Ltd v St Martins Investments Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 51 ; (1979) 144 CLR 596 at 607 that each party was obliged to do all that was necessary on his part to enable the other party to have the benefit of the contract.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c70">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co Ltd v Naughton [1929] HCA 34 ; (1929) 43 CLR 310</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1929/34.html</AustLII>
<text>The courts have also recognised a fourth class of case additional to the three mentioned in Masters v Cameron [1954] HCA 72 ; 91 CLR 353 , a class identified by Knox CJ, Rich J and Dixon J in Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co Ltd v Naughton [1929] HCA 34 ; (1929) 43 CLR 310 at 317 as: 
... one in which the parties were content to be bound immediately and exclusively by the terms which they had agreed upon whilst expecting to make a further contract in substitution for the first contract, containing, by consent, additional terms.

The use of such expressions supports a finding of an intention to contract. In Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd 40 NSWLR 622 , McLelland J, in finding that by an exchange of letters the parties to an alleged agreement mutually communicated their respective assents to be legally bound by terms capable of having contractual effect, afforded the expression "legally binding" primacy despite the expression "agreement in principle" also found in the relevant agreement (628). His Honour thought that the case fell into the fourth category as recognised in Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 (629F) . The appeal from McLelland J's judgment G R Securities v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital 40 NSWLR 631 was dismissed. McHugh JA accepted in line with Sinclair, Scott &amp; Co [1929] HCA 34 ; 43 CLR 310 , that it was possible for the parties to be bound immediately and agree to substitute for the first contract a further contract containing additional terms (634G). Further, McHugh JA applied the general rule applicable to every contract explained by Mason J in Secured Income Real Estate (Australia) Ltd v St Martins Investments Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 51 ; (1979) 144 CLR 596 at 607 that each party was obliged to do all that was necessary on his part to enable the other party to have the benefit of the contract.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c71">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/389.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG made no submissions on whether Jones v Dunkel had any application. Citing Dyers v The Queen [2002] HCA 45 ; (2002) 210 CLR 285 , Forrest submitted in written closing submissions that a Jones v Dunkel inference may not be drawn against an accused in a criminal case because the application of the rule in Jones v Dunkel is incompatible with the presumption of innocence and the rights of the accused; further, this reasoning applies with equal force to the accused calling other persons to give evidence. Forrest then submitted that the point of principle that, when an accused exercises the right not to give evidence the jury is directed that no adverse inference should be drawn, applies to a civil proceeding as against an individual defendant. He referred to the statement of Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, and Heydon JJ in Rich v Australian Securities and Investment Commission [2004] HCA 42 ; (2004) 220 CLR 129 at [24] that the privilege against exposure to penalty serves the purpose of ensuring that those who allege criminality or other (illegal) conduct should prove it, and said there is no expectation that a defendant will give evidence on matters for which the plaintiff bears the onus of proof. He said there is no authority that supports the proposition that a Jones v Dunkel inference is available against an individual defendant in a civil penalty proceeding, though, he said, the position may be different for a company. Finally, Forrest submitted that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and a Jones v Dunkel inference is not be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents, citing Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 at [71] .

Before stating my conclusion on whether I ought to make any Jones v Dunkel inferences, I will deal with the final authority cited by Forrest, Singh v Minister for Immigration [2001] FCA 389 ; (2001) 109 FCR 152 , from which he submits the following propositions emerge: that inferences are to be drawn from the documents before considering any question of Jones v Dunkel ; and that a Jones v Dunkel inference is not to be used in determining what inference ought to be drawn from the documents. In Singh , the applicant sought judicial review of a Ministerial decision to refuse to grant a spouse visa on character grounds. The Minister's reasons for decision were given in two documents: a decision record and a statement of reasons. The applicant argued that the Minister erred in making his decision by failing to have regard to the character references in support of the applicant which were annexed to a letter attached to the decision record. The Minister did not give evidence at trial, but Sackville J found that the statement of reasons provided affirmative evidence that the Minister gave consideration to the contents of the character references. The inferences that the applicant sought to draw by the Minister's failure to give evidence were contradicted by the Minister's statement of reasons.

In my view, what Sackville J said in Singh concerning the application of the Jones v Dunkel principle to the case before him is merely an application of the second condition given by Glass JA in Payne at p 201 as to whether the principle can or should be applied, namely whether the evidence of the missing witness would elucidate a particular matter. There was no occasion to draw an inference from the Minister's failure to give evidence because in his Honour's view, the question of whether he took into account the character references was adequately addressed by the statement of reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c72">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Southern Cross Financial Group (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Rodrigues (2005) 66 IPR 166</tocase>
<text>I will now turn to the cases cited by ASIC in support of its submission that the framework agreements were unenforceable because they were uncertain due to a lack of essential terms such as price: Hall v Busst 104 CLR 207; Toyota Motor Corporation Australia Ltd v Ken Morgan Motors Pty Ltd (1994) 2 VR 106 at 168-177 per Tadgell J; Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 at [34] ; and Southern Cross Financial Group (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Rodrigues (2005) 66 IPR 166 at [36], [44].

In Southern Cross Financial Group 66 IPR 166 , Young CJ in Eq stated at [36] that in a contract for the sale of any article there are at least three basic requirements: precise identification of the parties to the contract; the property to be sold; and the price at which it is to be sold. In connection with the price requirement, his Honour referred to the analysis of Fullagar J in Hall v Busst 104 CLR at 222, and stated at [44] that this analysis made it quite clear that with "very, very, very few" exceptions, a contract to sell property at fair value is not binding and is incomplete. The exceptions included 'an industry which has a measure of what a fair value is or there is some other criteria'. I would add that Fullagar J stated at 222 that it would be sufficient if the sale was expressed to be for a price or value to be fixed by a named or described person. The CREC Framework Agreement did not simply state that the infrastructure items would be transferred at fair value or in like terms. Rather, the agreement expressly provided a pricing mechanism. Further, Southern Cross Financial Group 66 IPR 166 is distinguishable from the present matter because Young CJ found that the case was one where the parties intended there not to be a concluded contract unless and until a formal document had been executed .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c73">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/248.html</AustLII>
<text>In Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248 , the NSW Court of Appeal emphasised that determining whether parties have come to a concluded agreement is a matter of their objectively ascertained intention in the particular case. Giles JA stated that the Masters v Cameron categories and a possible fourth category are intellectual aids, and that categorisation does not greatly contribute to the decision in the particular case, which is concerned with finding what agreement, if any, the parties came to, [26]. Similarly, in Moffat Property Development Group Pty Ltd [2009] QCA 60 , Keane JA, with whom McMurdo P and Atkinson J agreed, said at [37] in relation to classifying the putative agreement in that case under one of the four Masters v Cameron categories: 
In my respectful opinion, however, there is little purpose to be served in seeking to resolve the issue of classification. A concern as to classification should not be allowed to obscure or distract from the real task of the court which is to ascertain and give effect to the intentions of the parties.

Since Anaconda was decided by the Court of Appeal on 17 February 2000 it has been cited, considered or applied without disapproval in a number of contract law cases involving questions of incompleteness or uncertainty, for example: Duskwood Pty Ltd v Bellara Willows Pty Ltd [2001] per Steytler J at [95]; Liristis Holdings Pty Ltd v Wallville Pty Ltd [2001] NSWSC 428 per Barrett J at [38]; African Minerals Limited v Pan Palladium Limited [2003] NSWSC 268 per Einstein J at [26]; Thompson v White &amp; Ors [2006] NSWCA 350 per Tobias JA with whom Ipp and McColl JJA agreed at [100]; Tasman Capital Pty Ltd v Sinclair [2008] NSWCA 248 per Giles JA with whom McColl JA and Young CJ in EQ agreed at [27]-[28]; Donald Fin Enterprises Pty Ltd v APIR Systems Ltd (2008) 67 ACSR 219 per Edmonds J at [131]-[132]; Strzelecki Holdings Pty Ltd v Cable Sands Pty Ltd [No 3] [2009] WASC 352 per Murray J at [90].

The approach taken in G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631, Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 and Tasman Capital [2008] NSWCA 248 was followed very recently by the Queensland Court of Appeal in Moffat Property Development Group [2009] QCA 60 , mentioned above, which underlined the importance of the parties' manifest intention to contract. The issue was whether a contract for the sale of rural residential land had been made by an exchange of letters. The Queensland Court of Appeal held that the parties intended to be legally bound through their exchange of correspondence and that there was a contract even though matters such as the timing of completion and arrangements at settlement, the precise timing of the payment of the deposit, the place of settlement, responsibility for insurance, GST issues and the terms of a put and call option were not spelt out in the correspondence. Keane JA delivered the court's judgment. His Honour: 
(a) accepted McHugh JA's point in G R Securities that "the decisive issue is always the intention of the parties": [23]-[25];
 
(b) said "the terms of the correspondence exchanged between the parties contemplated the execution of a further contract as the means whereby the bargain which they had concluded would be implemented. It is necessarily implicit in such an agreement that the parties will co-operate to do what must be done to make the further agreement": [30];
 
(c) adopted McHugh JA's approach in G R Securities and explained that the implied obligation of each party to co-operate with the other to ensure each side obtains the benefit of its bargain serves to supply the deficiencies: [34];
 
(d) cited Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games 18 NSWLR at 548 in stating: "I am of the view that there can be no doubt as to the orthodoxy of referring to 'implied terms or ... considerations of reasonableness' in order to determine whether the parties' 'consensus is sufficiently comprehensive to be legally binding : [51].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c74">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/41.html</AustLII>
<text>ASIC submits in written closing submission that the authorities such as Anaconda, Pagnan SpA, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games Ltd (1988) 18 NSWLR 540 and Uranium Equities v Fewster [2008] WASCA 33 ; (2008) 36 WAR 97 relied on by FMG state that whether or not the parties intended to contract, they must agree on such terms, normally described as essential terms, such that the contract could be enforced or made complete by implying terms or applying considerations of reasonableness. I will consider these authorities further. In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the Court of Appeal found that a binding contract had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement "constituted an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form". At [28], Ipp J referred to the following statement by Sugerman J, approved by Menzies J in Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 at 607: 
It is a first principle of the law of contracts that there can be no binding and enforceable obligation unless the terms of the bargain, or at least its essential and critical terms, have been agreed upon. So, there is no concluded contract where an essential or critical term is expressly left to be settled by future agreement of the parties. Again, there is no binding contract where the language used is so obscure and incapable of any precise or definite meaning that the court is unable to attribute to the parties any particular contractual intentions.

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , a recent judgment of the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal), the Court stated at [127]: 
There is some overlap between the requirements of intention to create legal relations and certainty. If a contract is legally uncertain, this might indicate that the parties did not intend to create legal relations. A contract can be uncertain in various ways, one of these being incompleteness, in the sense that essential terms are lacking: Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 , 603 (Kitto J); Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629 , 646 - 647 (Gibbs J). The overlap between intention and uncertainty is at its greatest in cases in which agreement on some matters is deliberately postponed. If what is postponed is essential to the agreement (itself a question that largely depends upon the intention of the parties) , the agreement, to the extent that it has been reached, will be void. Also, the fact that essential terms have been left over for later agreement will militate against a finding that the parties intended to create contractual relations. (Emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c75">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Tillmanns Butcheries Pty Ltd v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union [1979] FCA 84 ; (1979) 42 FLR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1979/84.html</AustLII>
<text>Tillmanns Butcheries Pty Ltd v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union [1979] FCA 84 ; (1979) 42 FLR 331 was a case under s 45D of the TPA concerning secondary boycotts. It was, in that case, necessary that the impugned conduct "would have or be likely to have" the relevant effect. Consideration was given to whether, on an ex post view, the specified effect had occurred. Deane J at 347 citing Dixon J in Willis v Commonwealth [1946] HCA 22 ; 73 CLR 105 explained: 
if conduct had run its ordinary course and had not had the specified effect, it would be but rarely that a court would feel justified in disregarding the lesson of the event and finding that while the conduct did not have the specified effect it had been more likely than not that it would have had that effect.

Tillmanns [1979] FCA 84 ; 42 FLR 331 was referred to with apparent approval by Gzell J in ASIC v Macdonald (No 11) 256 ALR at [1068] although in relation to s 1041E of the Act where the test, whilst similar, is not the same. Materiality: a commercial judgment

The question is whether the Informations was information for the purposes of s 674(2) read together with s 677 which would or would be likely to influence common investors in deciding whether to acquire or dispose of FMG's securities and thereby be information which a reasonable person would expect if it were generally available, to have a material effect on the price of FMG's shares.

The threshold of relevant influence is not, in my opinion, a high one. ASIC, in this case, says that expert assistance is unnecessary for the Court. Senior counsel for ASIC submits that the question of influence for the purposes of s 677 involves primarily a commonsense test for the Court upon a consideration of the primary facts although assistance may be derived from experts who professionally buy and sell shares in large tranches and make investment decisions of the kind contemplated by s 677. I accept this submission.

ASIC submits that the fact or likelihood of relevant influence of the Informations is obvious having regard to the nature of this information which individually and together concerned a step forward about the construction of the Project infrastructure, which was integral to FMG's plans. ASIC says that if the three framework agreements were to lead, as both parties evidently intended, to binding build, finance and transfer type agreements, this would be a major advance as it would secure finance and a construction agreement for FMG's total estimated payout costs of $1.85 billion. It adds that the likely influence upon common investors of the Informations is a matter of common sense: it was information which was very significant for the Project and its prospects of being realised, as it was a step forward in arranging for the financing and construction of the rest of its Pilbara infrastructure.

ASIC seems ambivalent as to the effect of the Framework Agreements. It says, on the one hand, that they are merely agreements to negotiate and are probably not even enforceable as such. Then on the question of materiality under s 674(2)(c)(ii) ASIC contends that they represent a "major advance" if the negotiations proved successful.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c76">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>FMG makes the following submission which I accept as a correct statement of the law. The proper construction of an agreement should be determined by what reasonable people in the position of the parties would have understood by the relevant clauses by considering not only their text, but also the surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the transaction: e.g. Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at [40] ; International Air Transport Association v Ansett Australia Holdings Ltd [2008] HCA 3 ; (2008) 234 CLR 151 at [8] and [53]. The whole of the document should be considered and its provisions given harmonious effect: Australian Broadcasting Commission v Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd [1973] HCA 36 ; (1973) 129 CLR 99 at 109 (Gibbs J, in dissent, but not on the applicable principle).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c77">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Toyota Motor Corporation Australia Ltd v Ken Morgan Motors Pty Ltd (1994) 2 VR 106</tocase>
<text>I will now turn to the cases cited by ASIC in support of its submission that the framework agreements were unenforceable because they were uncertain due to a lack of essential terms such as price: Hall v Busst 104 CLR 207; Toyota Motor Corporation Australia Ltd v Ken Morgan Motors Pty Ltd (1994) 2 VR 106 at 168-177 per Tadgell J; Faulkner v Thomas [2000] TASSC 159 at [34] ; and Southern Cross Financial Group (Newcastle) Pty Ltd v Rodrigues (2005) 66 IPR 166 at [36], [44].

Toyota Motor Corporation 2 VR 106, a judgment of the Appeal Division of the Supreme Court of Victoria concerned the enforceability of a purported agreement set out in a letter for two Toyota companies to rescue a motor vehicle dealer group of companies that was in financial trouble. The purported agreement contained 12 conditions relating to the rescue offer. Brooking J referred to many examples in the purported agreement of ambiguity, uncertainty and incompleteness. Tadgell J held that the Toyota companies did not send the letter to the dealer group as an offer, and accordingly, they could not have assented to it as embodying the terms of a contract. Furthermore, as Brooking J stated at 132: 
Each case is different. A relatively short letter may be held to record a binding agreement in a matter of great consequence and considerable complexity, in which numerous formal documents will have to be prepared and executed to give effect to the transaction, as in Custom Credit Corporation Ltd v Cenepro Pty Ltd (unreported, Court of Appeal of New South Wales, 7 August 1991).

I respectfully agree with Brooking J. The brevity of the framework agreements does not of itself point to those agreements as lacking legal effect in circumstances where the agreements expressly referred to the preparation of fuller and more detailed agreements not different in intent. Toyota Motor Corporation 2 VR 106, does not assist ASIC.

Each member of the court in Toyota Motor Corporation 2 VR 106, concluded that there was no contractual intention evident: Brooking J at 136; Tadgell J at 177; JD Phillips J at 201. This, of itself, distinguishes this decision from the present case. It is correct that no price was specified in the CREC Framework Agreement, but it is explicit as to the pricing mechanism that was agreed to apply: FMG had to make a down payment of only 10% of the value of the Works in exchange for a bank guarantee from CREC, which bank guarantee was to be returned when 10% of the Works had been completed; and thereafter FMG's obligations of payment were to arise progressively after practical completion. This was an agreement on the pricing mechanism, which meant that FMG was not required to raise capital before the Works were effected, save for the first 10% of the value. It was not an agreement to agree but arguably rather an agreement as to what would be in the general conditions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c78">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Abbco Ice Works Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1279 ; (1994) 52 FCR 96</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1279.html</AustLII>
<text>ASIC seeks to draw Jones v Dunkel inferences against FMG by reason of the failure of Forrest and the other executives to give evidence. ASIC does not seek to draw the inferences against Forrest himself. Forrest has relied on the privilege against self-incrimination and the privilege against exposure to penalty, privileges which are are not available to corporations: Trade Practices Commission v Abbco Ice Works Pty Ltd [1994] FCA 1279 ; (1994) 52 FCR 96. However, even if ASIC had sought to draw inferences against Forrest as well as the corporate entity, on my review of the authorities it would not have been precluded from doing so. There is no reason therefore, in these circumstances, why the inferences cannot, as a matter of law, be drawn against FMG in the present proceedings. The question which then arises is whether I should draw such an inference in the manner urged by ASIC</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c79">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Uranium Equities Ltd v Fewster [2008] WASCA 33 ; (2008) 36 WAR 97</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WASCA/2008/33.html</AustLII>
<text>ASIC submits in written closing submission that the authorities such as Anaconda, Pagnan SpA, Australian Broadcasting Corporation v XIVth Commonwealth Games Ltd (1988) 18 NSWLR 540 and Uranium Equities v Fewster [2008] WASCA 33 ; (2008) 36 WAR 97 relied on by FMG state that whether or not the parties intended to contract, they must agree on such terms, normally described as essential terms, such that the contract could be enforced or made complete by implying terms or applying considerations of reasonableness. I will consider these authorities further. In Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 , the Court of Appeal found that a binding contract had been made when a heads of agreement containing five clauses was signed, the last paragraph of which said that the heads of agreement "constituted an agreement in itself intended to be replaced by a fuller agreement not different in substance or form". At [28], Ipp J referred to the following statement by Sugerman J, approved by Menzies J in Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 at 607: 
It is a first principle of the law of contracts that there can be no binding and enforceable obligation unless the terms of the bargain, or at least its essential and critical terms, have been agreed upon. So, there is no concluded contract where an essential or critical term is expressly left to be settled by future agreement of the parties. Again, there is no binding contract where the language used is so obscure and incapable of any precise or definite meaning that the court is unable to attribute to the parties any particular contractual intentions.

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , a recent judgment of the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal), the Court stated at [127]: 
There is some overlap between the requirements of intention to create legal relations and certainty. If a contract is legally uncertain, this might indicate that the parties did not intend to create legal relations. A contract can be uncertain in various ways, one of these being incompleteness, in the sense that essential terms are lacking: Thorby v Goldberg [1964] HCA 41 ; (1964) 112 CLR 597 , 603 (Kitto J); Godecke v Kirwan [1973] HCA 38 ; (1973) 129 CLR 629 , 646 - 647 (Gibbs J). The overlap between intention and uncertainty is at its greatest in cases in which agreement on some matters is deliberately postponed. If what is postponed is essential to the agreement (itself a question that largely depends upon the intention of the parties) , the agreement, to the extent that it has been reached, will be void. Also, the fact that essential terms have been left over for later agreement will militate against a finding that the parties intended to create contractual relations. (Emphasis added)

In Uranium Equities [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the parties to the putative agreement had been negotiating over a proposed mining joint venture, but no heads of agreement had been executed. The Court found that the trial judge was right in concluding that the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed. The Court went on to state on the question of uncertainty at [257] that it is "trite" that, even when the requisite intention is present, a contract can fail for uncertainty. The Court said it is also trite that only the omission of an essential term will have the effect that a contract is so incomplete or uncertain as to render it invalid, citing Ipp J in Anaconda [2000] WASCA 27 ; 22 WAR 101 at [29] . The Court referred to the statement of Lloyd LJ from Pagnan SpA [1987] 2 Lloyd's Rep at 619 and found that when regard was had to all the circumstances the parties did not intend to be bound by anything said or done by them until such time as the heads of agreement had been executed . The Court concluded that although some of the matters left over by the parties for future negotiation were important, none were essential to the efficacy of the alleged agreement in the sense that the agreement could not be enforced without it.

This fourth category was recognised by McLelland J in Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd v G R Securities Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 622 and on appeal in G R Securities Pty Ltd v Baulkham Hills Private Hospital Pty Ltd (1986) 40 NSWLR 631 where McHugh JA delivered the Court of Appeal's judgment and observed that the magnitude, subject matter or complexities of a transaction may indicate that an agreement was a limited one not intended to have legal effect (634D) but that what was critical was the parties' intention objectively ascertained, and that this intention should prevail (634E-F). In Uranium Equities Ltd [2008] WASCA 33 ; 36 WAR 97 , the Supreme Court of Western Australia (Court of Appeal) stated at [129] that the fourth Masters v Cameron category was a variation of the first category.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c80">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Vines v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] NSWCA 75 ; (2007) 62 ACSR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2007/75.html</AustLII>
<text>Austin J noted that in Vines v ASIC [2007] NSWCA 75 ; (2007) 62 ACSR 1 at [62] Spigelman CJ stated that the rule in Browne v Dunn is a rule of practice designed to achieve procedural fairness, and therefore, when it is claimed that the rule has been departed from and that consequences should follow, the first consideration to be considered by the court is whether there has been some procedural fairness that needs to be addressed. That requires the assessment of "matters of fact and degree".

Forrest then submits that the mere fact that a director participates in conduct that carries with it a foreseeable risk of harm to a company's interest does not necessarily mean that the director failed to exercise a reasonable degree of care and diligence in the discharge of his duty: Vrisakis v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 9 WAR 395 per Ipp J at 449-450; Vines v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] NSWCA 75 ; (2007) 62 ACSR 1 per Santow J at [598] and [599]. Conclusion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c81">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vrisakis v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 9 WAR 395</tocase>
<text>Forrest then submits that the mere fact that a director participates in conduct that carries with it a foreseeable risk of harm to a company's interest does not necessarily mean that the director failed to exercise a reasonable degree of care and diligence in the discharge of his duty: Vrisakis v Australian Securities Commission (1993) 9 WAR 395 per Ipp J at 449-450; Vines v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] NSWCA 75 ; (2007) 62 ACSR 1 per Santow J at [598] and [599]. Conclusion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c82">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Walford v Miles [1992] 2 AC 128</tocase>
<text>ASIC relies upon the following authorities in support of its submission that the framework agreements are bare agreements to negotiate the scope and terms, in each case, of a further agreement to build transfer and finance the relevant Project infrastructure and that such agreements are not enforceable: Coal Cliff Collieries Pty Ltd v Sijehama Pty Ltd (1991) 24 NSWLR 1 ; Jobern Pty Ltd v Breakfree Resorts (Victoria) Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1066 ; Walford v Miles [1992] 2 AC 128.

Walford v Miles [1992] 2 AC 128 was an appeal to the House of Lords. The parties had been negotiating over the sale of a business. Their Lordships considered the validity of a 'lock-out' agreement, an agreement committing the seller not to negotiate with anyone other than the buyer over the sale of the business. The plaintiffs, the disappointed buyers, claimed that not only were the sellers "locked-out" for some unspecified time from dealing with any third party, but were "locked-in" to dealing with the plaintiffs for an unspecified period. The court considered the "lock-in" agreement in terms of an obligation on the parties to negotiate in good faith. Lord Ackner (with whom all the other Law Lords agreed) stated that an agreement to negotiate, like an agreement to agree, is unenforceable, because it lacks the necessary certainty. Lord Ackner said at [138G]: 
A duty to negotiate in good faith is as unworkable in practice as it is inherently inconsistent with the position of a negotiating party. It is here that the uncertainty lies. In my judgment, while negotiations are in existence either party is entitled to withdraw from these negotiations, at any time and for any reason. There can be thus no obligation to continue to negotiate until there is a 'proper reason' to withdraw. Accordingly a bare agreement to negotiate has no legal content.

In my view Coal Cliff Collieries 24 NSWLR 1, Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 and Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 do not assist ASIC. I do not take Coal Cliff Collieries as authority for the proposition that a bare agreement to negotiate in good faith is not enforceable, as submitted by ASIC. In my view, that case is authority for the proposition that a promise to negotiate in good faith may, in particular circumstances, be enforceable, depending on the precise terms as construed from the contract. In Jobern [2007] FCA 1066 , it was not in dispute that the heads of agreement document was binding only the negotiation clause was held to be uncertain. In Walford [1992] 2 AC 128 , the agreement that was found to be uncertain was a 'lock-in' agreement committing the parties to negotiate with each other, which is to be distinguished from the types of obligations found in the framework agreements under consideration in the present case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c83">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Weissensteiner v The Queen [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1993/65.html</AustLII>
<text>In Azzopardi [2001] HCA 25 ; 205 CLR 50 , in their joint majority judgment Gaudron, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ referred to Weissensteiner v The Queen [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217 where the High Court held it was appropriate for the trial judge to direct the jury as to the manner in which they might take into account the failure of the accused to give evidence, and their Honours stated at [61] that what was important in Weissensteiner and what warranted the remarks to the jury in that case was that, if there were facts which explained or contradicted the evidence against the accused, they were facts which were within the knowledge only of the accused, and thus could not be the subject of evidence from any other person or source. At [68], their Honours emphasised that cases in which a judge may comment on the failure of an accused to offer an explanation will be both rare and exceptional and will occur only if the evidence is capable of explanation by disclosure of additional facts known only to the accused. Their Honours said a comment will never be warranted merely because the accused has failed to contradict some aspect of the prosecution case.

In RPS [2000] HCA 3 ; 199 CLR 620 , at [26]-[27] Gaudron A-CJ, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ contrasted the reasonable expectation that a party in a civil trial would give or call relevant evidence in the circumstances described in Jones v Dunkel with the conclusion that it would seldom, if ever, be reasonable to expect an accused in a criminal trial to give evidence. Weissensteiner provides an example of where the latter would be reasonable.

Further authority for the availability of the rule in Jones v Dunkel in civil penalty proceedings is found in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (2001) 115 FCR 442 , where Hill J stated at [33]: 
Where the proceedings are criminal (and the present proceedings are not; they are proceedings, inter alia, for the recovery of a civil penalty) it might be thought that the failure of the accused to go into evidence should not lead to the drawing of Jones v Dunkel inferences. After all it is clear that a witness can not be compelled to give evidence which is likely to incriminate the witness or expose the witness to a penalty. However, even in criminal cases it has been held that the failure of the accused, who is in a position to deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced by the prosecution, to give evidence will permit the jury to draw inferences adverse to the accused more readily: see Azzopardi v R [2001] HCA 25 ; (2001) 179 ALR 349 , affirming Weissensteiner v R [1993] HCA 65 ; (1993) 178 CLR 217. A fortiori, therefore, the failure of a respondent to proceedings for recovery of a pecuniary penalty to give evidence on a matter relevant to an issue in the proceeding and deny, explain or answer the evidence adduced against the respondent will permit the Court more readily to draw the inferences to which the decision in Jones v Dunkel refers.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c84">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wheeler Grace &amp; PierucciPty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189</tocase>
<text>A reasonable reader of the disclosures made by FMG and Forrest on FMG's behalf would have expected FMG to have a genuine and reasonable basis for making those statements: Global Sportsman v Mirror Newspapers [1984] FCA 180 ; 2 FCR 82 at 88; James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347 at 372 per Toohey J; Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865 at 49,375-49,376 per French J (affirmed in Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189) ; Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553 at 559 per Burchett J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c85">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wilkinson v Feldworth Financial Services Pty Ltd (1999) 17 ACLC 220</tocase>
<text>The authorities dealing with misleading and deceptive conduct under s 52 of the TPA are useful when characterising conduct for the purposes of s 1041H. As Rolfe J observed in Wilkinson v Feldworth Financial Services Pty Ltd (1999) 17 ACLC 220 at 228 in relation to s 995 of the Corporations Law: 
... the engaging in conduct that is misleading or deceptive or is likely to mislead or deceive has the same meaning as, and should be treated in the same way as, those words in s 52 of the Trade Practices Act from which they have obviously been taken.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c86">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Willis v Commonwealth [1946] HCA 22 ; (1946) 73 CLR 105</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1946/22.html</AustLII>
<text>This, in effect, was a restatement of what was said by Dixon J in Willis v Commonwealth [1946] HCA 22 ; (1946) 73 CLR 105 at 116 who in turn had cited a passage from Uthwatt J in In re Bradberry; National Provincial Bank Ltd v Bradberry (1943) Ch 35 at pp 42-45.

Tillmanns Butcheries Pty Ltd v Australasian Meat Industry Employees' Union [1979] FCA 84 ; (1979) 42 FLR 331 was a case under s 45D of the TPA concerning secondary boycotts. It was, in that case, necessary that the impugned conduct "would have or be likely to have" the relevant effect. Consideration was given to whether, on an ex post view, the specified effect had occurred. Deane J at 347 citing Dixon J in Willis v Commonwealth [1946] HCA 22 ; 73 CLR 105 explained: 
if conduct had run its ordinary course and had not had the specified effect, it would be but rarely that a court would feel justified in disregarding the lesson of the event and finding that while the conduct did not have the specified effect it had been more likely than not that it would have had that effect.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c87">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865</tocase>
<text>A reasonable reader of the disclosures made by FMG and Forrest on FMG's behalf would have expected FMG to have a genuine and reasonable basis for making those statements: Global Sportsman v Mirror Newspapers [1984] FCA 180 ; 2 FCR 82 at 88; James v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (1986) 64 ALR 347 at 372 per Toohey J; Wright v Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd (1988) ATPR 40-865 at 49,375-49,376 per French J (affirmed in Wheeler Grace &amp; Pierucci Pty Ltd v Wright (1989) 16 IPR 189) ; Bateman v Slayter (1987) 71 ALR 553 at 559 per Burchett J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c88">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>York Air Conditioning and Refrigeration (A/sia) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth [1949] HCA 23 ; (1949) 80 CLR 11</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1949/23.html</AustLII>
<text>I have concluded, for reasons which I explain later in this Part that, in the case of each of the framework agreements, there was an intention to contract. This, as a starting point considerably strengthens the case for the defendants because in such circumstances a Court will always strive to give effect to that intention: Hillas &amp; Co Ltd v Arcos Ltd [1932] UKHL 2 ; [1932] All ER Rep 494 ; York Air Conditioning and Refrigeration (A/sia) Pty Ltd v The Commonwealth [1949] HCA 23 ; (1949) 80 CLR 11 ; G R Securities 40 NSWLR 631; Fletcher Challenge Energy [2002] NZLR 433 .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>