<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Shen v Gwei Ting International Fashion Corporation [2009] FCA 1131 (24 September 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1131.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pioneer Computers Australia Pty Limited v Pioneer KK (2009) 176 FCR 300</tocase>
<text>The issues raised in the appeal are to be considered afresh on the basis of the evidence before this Court, notwithstanding that this differs from the evidence before the delegate ( Pioneer Computers Australia Pty Limited v Pioneer KK (2009) 176 FCR 300 at [23]). The respondent has filed a notice of appearance, but has indicated that it does not propose to take any further action in relation to the appeal. That is, the respondent submits to any order of the Court save as to costs.

Mr Shen is the sole director and shareholder of Solar International Proprietary Limited, trading as Solar Sports. He says that he is responsible for the day to day business activities of the company, and has authorised the company to use the trade mark.

In his evidence, Mr Shen annexes copies of business records of the company, including commercial invoices, bills of lading, shipment advice, and tax invoices, relating to two shipments of footwear within the relevant period. The documents annexed to the affidavit establish that the first shipment was purchased on 1 May 2006, which led to sale of footwear under the trade mark. Those goods were sold under the trade mark in the period from 1 August 2006 to 28 February 2007. It is apparent that that period, in its totality, was within the relevant period. I also note that the goods the subject of that shipment were sold to customers in New South Wales, Queensland, and the Australia Capital Territory.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Woolly Bull Enterprises Pty Limited v Reynolds [2001] FCA 261 ; (2001) 107 FCR 166</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/261.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant must establish both ' use ' and ' use in good faith of the trade mark ' during the relevant period. As Drummond J pointed out in Woolly Bull Enterprises Pty Limited v Reynolds [2001] FCA 261 ; (2001) 107 FCR 166 at [14] , an applicant for removal must show that ' at no time during [the relevant period]' has there been use. It follows, as his Honour pointed out, that an opponent is entitled to rebut the allegation by proving even a single use on just one occasion during the three year period, such use being in good faith. At [16], his Honour expressed the view that the expression ' use in good faith ', has a well understood meaning in this context: namely real, as opposed to token, use in a commercial sense.

I am satisfied that the applicant has demonstrated real commercial use of the trade mark by the company. The evidence also establishes more than one act of use during the relevant period, were it necessary to do so. I am satisfied that the use was authorised by the applicant. That is sufficient for the purposes of s 92(4)(b) and s 100(3)(a).

The evidence establishes use during the relevant period of the trade mark on footwear. The registration was for a class of goods beyond that description. The removal application should therefore not succeed insofar as it relates to footwear. The applicant has not sought to maintain the registration for the goods beyond footwear. The applicant does not oppose the removal of the trade mark insofar as it relates to those other goods.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>