<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Asmar, in the matter of an Election for offices of the Health Services Union [2009] FCA 1294 (6 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1294.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Post, Re; Re Election for Offices in Transport Workers Union of Australia, Western Australian Branch (1992) 40 IR 162</tocase>
<text>The approach taken by the Court to the preliminary issue identified by s 201(b) of the Act was explained by French J in Re Post; Re Election for Offices in Transport Workers Union of Australia, Western Australian Branch (1992) 40 IR 162 at 166-7 as follows: 
 
 "The question for the Court ... is whether it is satisfied that there is reasonable ground for the application. It will not be so satisfied if the grounds relied upon could not, even if made out, constitute "an irregularity in relation to an election for an office in the organisation". The question whether there is such an irregularity lies at the heart of this jurisdiction. Nor will it be so satisfied if the allegations of fact relied upon in the application do not at least offer good grounds for suspicion that there has been such an irregularity. The Court will not entertain an application of a speculative nature based upon the applicant's opinion that there has been an irregularity unless that opinion rests upon some substantial factual foundation. Necessary conditions to establish the requisite state of satisfaction can be multiplied. It is harder to state what is sufficient to satisfy the Court beyond the words of the section itself which require a an evaluative judgment at this preliminary stage".

Much of the affidavit evidence relied upon by the applicant contained hearsay. Insofar as it dealt with the sending of SMS messages to the mobile phones of members, it suggested that a small number of members had received messages supporting the Bolano team. It is not clear, on the evidence, how, whoever it was who sent the messages, obtained the mobile telephone numbers of the members to whom messages were sent. In the few cases in which the deponent of an affidavit received a message, the deponent said that he or she had provided Mr Bolano or some other person associated with his campaign with his or her telephone number but had not done so for the purpose of receiving campaign material. Some of these deponents were shop stewards at their workplaces and it is understandable that they would have provided Mr Bolano, an organiser, with their telephone numbers to facilitate contact on Union business. What is important, for present purposes, is that there is no evidence that enables me to infer that Mr Bolano or anyone else obtained mobile telephone numbers of members by resort to Union records.

The evidence relied on by the applicant supports the allegation that Union meetings were convened at some hospitals using notices on Union letterhead. Those meetings were attended by some Union employees who, although supposedly on leave, were said to be present on Union (as distinct from electoral) business. Those employees used the meetings to encourage members to vote for the Bolano team. Mr Bolano and other employees said to have been involved have not, as yet, denied that such conduct occurred. In fairness to them, it must be said that some of the affidavits on which the applicant relies were not served until late on 4 November 2009.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jarman, Re; Ex parte Cook (No 2) [1996] HCA 7 ; (1996) 136 ALR 233</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/7.html</AustLII>
<text>As Kirby J said in Re Jarman; Ex parte Cook (No 2) [1996] HCA 7 ; (1996) 136 ALR 233 at 241, the institution of an inquiry under s 201 is a serious matter. The onus is on an applicant to persuade the Court that there exist reasonable grounds for the application. For the reasons given I am not satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to consider that any irregularity has occurred in relation to the election.

I would, therefore, dismiss the application by the applicant for an inquiry. It follows that no interim orders can or should be made in the proceeding.
 I certify that the preceding twenty-two (22) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 6 November 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Ms A Duffy 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Holding Redlich 
 
 Counsel for Mr M Bolano and Others: Mr M McKillop 
 
 Solicitor for Mr M Bolano and Others: Earl &amp; Associates 
 
 Counsel for the Health Services Union: Mr D Langmead 
 
 Solicitor for the Health Services Union: Slater &amp; Gordon 
 
 Counsel for Mr D Byron Mr H Borenstein SC 
 
 Solicitor for Mr D Byron Macpherson + Kelley 
 
 Counsel for the Administrator (Mr J Vines): Mr S Moore 
 
 Solicitor for the Administrator (Mr J Vines): Maurice Blackburn 
 
 Counsel for the Returning Officer: Mr R McClure 
 
 Solicitor for the Returning Officer: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 6 November 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 6 November 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1294.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>