<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Habib v Commonwealth of Australia (No 2) [2009] FCA 228 (13 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/228.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>A v Hayden [1984] HCA 67 ; (1984) 156 CLR 532</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/67.html</AustLII>
<text>Another way of arriving at the same result may be to observe that equity would not impose a fiduciary duty obedience to which would fetter foreign policy. I have no doubt that a contract entered into by the Commonwealth which purported to bind it to some particular foreign policy posture would be unenforceable: Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v Commonwealth [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54 at 75 per Mason J; A v Hayden [1984] HCA 67 ; (1984) 156 CLR 532 at 543 per Gibbs CJ; City of Subiaco v Heytesbury Properties Pty Ltd (2001) 24 WAR 146 at 157-159 [43]-[50] per Ipp J with whom Malcolm CJ and Wallwork J agreed. Whilst it is true that equity can often achieve outcomes which the common law or statute appear not to countenance the doctrine of part performance is an obvious example I do not think that the Chancellor's foot treads the boards of the world stage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Alcorn v Anbro Engineering Inc 468 P2d 216 (1970)</tocase>
<text>The authors of The Law of Torts in Australia (4th ed, OUP, 2007) devote an extensive section advocating a change to this position. They note the existence in the US of a right to recover where a case involves "extreme and outrageous intentional invasions of one's mental and emotional tranquility" citing Alcorn v Anbro Engineering Inc 468 P2d 216 (1970) at 218 [4] per Burke J. They also note the remarks of Lord Hoffman in Hunter v Canary Wharf Ltd [1997] UKHL 14 ; [1997] AC 655 at 707 to this effect: 
The perceived gap in Khorasandjian v. Bush was the absence of a tort of intentional harassment causing distress without actual bodily or psychiatric illness. This limitation is thought to arise out of cases like Wilkinson v. Downton [1897] 2 Q.B. 57 and Janvier v. Sweeney [1919] 2 K.B. 316. The law of harassment has now been put on a statutory basis (see the Protection from Harassment Act 1997) and it is unnecessary to consider how the common law might have developed. But as at present advised, I see no reason why a tort of intention should be subject to the rule which excludes compensation for mere distress, inconvenience or discomfort in actions based on negligence: see Hicks v. Chief Constable of the South Yorkshire Police [1991] UKHL 9 ; [1992] 2 All E.R. 65. The policy considerations are quite different. I do not therefore say that Khorasandjian v. Bush was wrongly decided. But it must be seen as a case on intentional harassment, not nuisance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v Commonwealth [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/71.html</AustLII>
<text>Another way of arriving at the same result may be to observe that equity would not impose a fiduciary duty obedience to which would fetter foreign policy. I have no doubt that a contract entered into by the Commonwealth which purported to bind it to some particular foreign policy posture would be unenforceable: Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v Commonwealth [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54 at 75 per Mason J; A v Hayden [1984] HCA 67 ; (1984) 156 CLR 532 at 543 per Gibbs CJ; City of Subiaco v Heytesbury Properties Pty Ltd (2001) 24 WAR 146 at 157-159 [43]-[50] per Ipp J with whom Malcolm CJ and Wallwork J agreed. Whilst it is true that equity can often achieve outcomes which the common law or statute appear not to countenance the doctrine of part performance is an obvious example I do not think that the Chancellor's foot treads the boards of the world stage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General v De Keyser's Royal Hotel Ltd [1920] UKHL 1 ; [1920] AC 508</tocase>
<text>In either event, it is plain that the question of the extent of the executive power is consigned to the Chapter III courts. In that regard, at a functional level, the situation is not so very different to the treatment given by the English courts to the question of the extent of the prerogative. For, at least since the Case of Proclamations (1611) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352, the courts of that country have asserted, and the other branches of government have eventually accepted, the final role of the courts in determining the ambit of that prerogative. Just as a Commonwealth law may delimit the scope of the executive power, so too it is well established that the prerogative may be excluded by statute. Attorney-General v De Keyser's Royal Hotel Ltd [1920] UKHL 1 ; [1920] AC 508 is an example of where a statute was found to have curtailed the prerogative. In Australia, Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 is an example where a statute was found not to have that effect; the Full Court of this Court's decision in Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719 is a contrary example.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (UK) v Heinemann Publishers Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/25.html</AustLII>
<text>Finally, the Commonwealth made a broad submission that the act of State doctrine operated to prevent this Court from examining the rights and wrongs of the acts of a foreign State. Over a century ago the doctrine was held to form part of "the settled law of all civilized countries": Potter v Broken Hill Pty Company Ltd [1906] HCA 88 ; (1906) 3 CLR 479 at 495 per Griffith CJ. More recently it has been described by the High Court as a long-recognised principle of international law: Attorney-General (UK) v Heinemann Publishers Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40 and by a judge of this Court as a rule of private international law: Petrotimor Companhia de Petroleos SARL v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] FCAFC 3 ; (2003) 126 FCR 354 at 415 [159] per Beaumont J. The Commonwealth's submission that the act of State doctrine exists must be accepted: Petrotimor at 366-369 [33]-[45] per Black CJ and Hill J, 415-416 [159]-[160] per Beaumont J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1974/20.html</AustLII>
<text>In either event, it is plain that the question of the extent of the executive power is consigned to the Chapter III courts. In that regard, at a functional level, the situation is not so very different to the treatment given by the English courts to the question of the extent of the prerogative. For, at least since the Case of Proclamations (1611) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352, the courts of that country have asserted, and the other branches of government have eventually accepted, the final role of the courts in determining the ambit of that prerogative. Just as a Commonwealth law may delimit the scope of the executive power, so too it is well established that the prerogative may be excluded by statute. Attorney-General v De Keyser's Royal Hotel Ltd [1920] UKHL 1 ; [1920] AC 508 is an example of where a statute was found to have curtailed the prerogative. In Australia, Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 is an example where a statute was found not to have that effect; the Full Court of this Court's decision in Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719 is a contrary example.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1352.html</AustLII>
<text>It will be seen that the provision requires an assessment of the prospect of Mr Habib's proceeding being successful. If this prospect is less than reasonable the Court may give judgment on the proceeding to the respondent. The insertion of subsection (3) has altered the pre-existing position that only proceedings which are hopeless or bound to fail should be dismissed. Nevertheless, it is a jurisdiction to be exercised with caution: Boston Commercial Services Pty Ltd v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720 at 731 [45] per Rares J.

The Commonwealth also applies to strike out various portions of the pleading pursuant to O 11 r 16 which relates to pleadings said not to disclose a reasonable cause of action or which are otherwise embarrassing. In relation to both s 31A and O 11 r 16 it is appropriate to assume in Mr Habib's favour that he would succeed at trial in proving each and every allegation of fact contained in the pleading. The Commonwealth's argument is that, even making that assumption, the proceeding cannot succeed.

For present purposes the contents of the pleading may be summarised as containing the following sets of allegations: 
(a) allegations that Mr Habib was wrongfully arrested in Pakistan by the Pakistani and US governments in October 2001;
 
(b) allegations of his torture whilst in Pakistan at the hands of the Pakistani authorities;
 
(c) allegations of extraordinary rendition to Egypt and allegations of torture at the hands of Egyptian authorities;
 
(d) allegations of his removal from Egypt to Afghanistan and thence to Guantanamo Bay;
 
(e) allegations of mistreatment by the US government at Guantanamo Bay;
 
(f) allegations that the Commonwealth was aware that Mr Habib was to be the subject of a rendition to Egypt and that, to the Commonwealth's knowledge, this would most likely involve torture;
 
(g) allegations that the Commonwealth made no effort to secure his release from Egypt notwithstanding its awareness that he was being, or was very likely being, tortured there;
 
(h) allegations that the Commonwealth provided the Egyptian authorities with information and documents that the Commonwealth had obtained from Mr Habib's home in Australia which the Commonwealth either knew or should have known would be used in his torture;
 
(i) allegations that the Commonwealth failed to take any sufficient steps to procure his release from Guantanamo Bay;
 
(j) allegations that an officer or officers of the Commonwealth interrogated Mr Habib in Guantanamo Bay whilst he was shackled to the floor;
 
(k) allegations that following his return to Australia he was persecuted and harassed by the Commonwealth by its assisting the publisher of the Daily Telegraph in a defamation suit brought by Mr Habib against that publisher and, additionally, by denying him a passport;
 
(l) allegations of defamation by the Commonwealth constituted, generally, by statements by its officials that Mr Habib was a terrorist.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Breen v Williams (1996) 186 CLR 71</tocase>
<text>Even assuming those obstacles could be overcome, Mr Habib's case on the breach of the alleged duty is conceptually deficient for the purpose for which his advisers seek to advance it. In the written submissions it was submitted on his behalf as follows: 
As Gaudron and McHugh JJ note [at 113] in Breen v Williams the fiduciary`s obligations under Australian law are proscriptive not prescriptive, but this does not permit the choice of a course which conflicts with either the duty owed or the dependence of the Applicant on the Respondent. In the present case a choice to decline to take steps favourable to the Applicant inevitably placed the Respondent in a position of conflict given the trust the Applicant placed in the Respondent with the Applicant abandoned to obvious unlawful detention and "rendition".

But the nature of the "position of conflict" was left unexplained. Equity imposes upon fiduciaries a duty of undivided loyalty: Maguire v Makaronis [1997] HCA 23 ; (1997) 188 CLR 449 at 465 per Brennan CJ, Gaudron, McHugh and Gummow JJ. The duty is the obligation to avoid being placed in a position where that undivided loyalty might be challenged. The breach of duty arises merely from being placed in the position of conflict and does not require that the conflict be acted upon. Thus the 'no conflict' rule is infringed where a fiduciary occupies a position where his self-interest and the duty to the beneficiary conflict: Warman International Ltd v Dwyer [1995] HCA 18 ; (1994) 182 CLR 544 at 557 per Mason CJ, Brennan, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ. It is also infringed where the fiduciary takes upon herself conflicting obligations: Breen v Williams (1996) 186 CLR 71 at 135 per Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Case of Proclamations (1611) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352</tocase>
<text>In either event, it is plain that the question of the extent of the executive power is consigned to the Chapter III courts. In that regard, at a functional level, the situation is not so very different to the treatment given by the English courts to the question of the extent of the prerogative. For, at least since the Case of Proclamations (1611) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352, the courts of that country have asserted, and the other branches of government have eventually accepted, the final role of the courts in determining the ambit of that prerogative. Just as a Commonwealth law may delimit the scope of the executive power, so too it is well established that the prerogative may be excluded by statute. Attorney-General v De Keyser's Royal Hotel Ltd [1920] UKHL 1 ; [1920] AC 508 is an example of where a statute was found to have curtailed the prerogative. In Australia, Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 is an example where a statute was found not to have that effect; the Full Court of this Court's decision in Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719 is a contrary example.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>China Navigation Company Ltd v Attorney General (1931) 40 Ll L Rep 110</tocase>
<text>The Commonwealth's submission was that it could not possibly be said that it had acted for, or on behalf of, Mr Habib. This submission is too simplistic. It is accepted that there is some kind of duty owed by the State to its overseas nationals. For example, in Mutasa v Attorney General [1980] QB 114 at 118-120 Boreham J spoke of the Crown having a duty to protect a citizen from unlawful detention but of that duty being one of imperfect obligation and thus unenforceable. So too, in China Navigation Company Ltd v Attorney General (1931) 40 Ll L Rep 110 at 112 Rowlatt J spoke of an alleged duty to assist a citizen against piracy as being but a "political" duty: cf. Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 593-594 [62] - [66] per Tamberlin J. Thus, it is a little glib to say that there was no aspect of the relationship between Mr Habib and the Commonwealth which could involve it in potentially "acting" on his behalf.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chow Hung Ching v The King [1948] HCA 37 ; (1948) 77 CLR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1948/37.html</AustLII>
<text>There are a number of different aspects to that broad principle. First , it is plain that the courts will absolutely abide the executive's views on questions such as the accession of foreign territory, the recognition of a foreign sovereign or the recognition of foreign States and ambassadors: see Chow Hung Ching v The King [1948] HCA 37 ; (1948) 77 CLR 449 at 467 per Latham CJ. Secondly , generally speaking, the issues which arise between nation States are unlikely to generate matters within the meaning of ss 75 and 76 of the Constitution for the rights and obligations in that plane do not form part of domestic law: Re Ditfort at 370 per Gummow J. Thirdly, for related reasons, such questions are usually unable to bring forth a plaintiff who has standing: Re Ditfort at 369. Fourthly , complaints about the conduct of Australian international relations are likely to take a court into an area which involves the consideration of undertakings or obligations depending entirely on political sanctions. Where that occurs it is generally thought there is no matter in the requisite sense: Re Ditfort at 370. For example, a complaint by an Australian exporter that trade sanctions had been negligently imposed on a country to which it exported would immediately involve this Court in the consideration of matters which it is institutionally unsuited to resolve: Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70 at 138-139 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>City of Subiaco v Heytesbury Properties Pty Ltd (2001) 24 WAR 146</tocase>
<text>Another way of arriving at the same result may be to observe that equity would not impose a fiduciary duty obedience to which would fetter foreign policy. I have no doubt that a contract entered into by the Commonwealth which purported to bind it to some particular foreign policy posture would be unenforceable: Ansett Transport Industries (Operations) Pty Ltd v Commonwealth [1977] HCA 71 ; (1977) 139 CLR 54 at 75 per Mason J; A v Hayden [1984] HCA 67 ; (1984) 156 CLR 532 at 543 per Gibbs CJ; City of Subiaco v Heytesbury Properties Pty Ltd (2001) 24 WAR 146 at 157-159 [43]-[50] per Ipp J with whom Malcolm CJ and Wallwork J agreed. Whilst it is true that equity can often achieve outcomes which the common law or statute appear not to countenance the doctrine of part performance is an obvious example I do not think that the Chancellor's foot treads the boards of the world stage.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Farah Constructions Pty Ltd v Say-Dee Pty Ltd [2007] HCA 22 ; (2007) 230 CLR 89</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/22.html</AustLII>
<text>The ratio decidendi of Giller is that the tort in Wilkinson v Downton is not available unless there is actual physical injury and that extreme mental distress does not constitute physical injury in the requisite sense. It would be inappropriate for me to depart from Giller unless convinced it was plainly wrong: Farah Constructions Pty Ltd v Say-Dee Pty Ltd [2007] HCA 22 ; (2007) 230 CLR 89 at 151-152 [135] . Whilst I can see the force of some of the criticisms which have been made of the present position I could not possibly say that Giller was clearly wrong. Accordingly, I am bound to follow it.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/11.html</AustLII>
<text>There are a number of different aspects to that broad principle. First , it is plain that the courts will absolutely abide the executive's views on questions such as the accession of foreign territory, the recognition of a foreign sovereign or the recognition of foreign States and ambassadors: see Chow Hung Ching v The King [1948] HCA 37 ; (1948) 77 CLR 449 at 467 per Latham CJ. Secondly , generally speaking, the issues which arise between nation States are unlikely to generate matters within the meaning of ss 75 and 76 of the Constitution for the rights and obligations in that plane do not form part of domestic law: Re Ditfort at 370 per Gummow J. Thirdly, for related reasons, such questions are usually unable to bring forth a plaintiff who has standing: Re Ditfort at 369. Fourthly , complaints about the conduct of Australian international relations are likely to take a court into an area which involves the consideration of undertakings or obligations depending entirely on political sanctions. Where that occurs it is generally thought there is no matter in the requisite sense: Re Ditfort at 370. For example, a complaint by an Australian exporter that trade sanctions had been negligently imposed on a country to which it exported would immediately involve this Court in the consideration of matters which it is institutionally unsuited to resolve: Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70 at 138-139 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Giller v Procopets [2008] VSCA 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VSCA/2008/236.html</AustLII>
<text>The authors of The Law of Torts in Australia also point to a decision of McDonald J in Gimson v Victorian Workcover Authority [1995] 1 VR 209 at 226-7 where a pleading was permitted to go forward to trial in which mere mental distress was alleged. More recently, however, the Victorian Court of Appeal has considered the issue in Giller v Procopets [2008] VSCA 236. In that case the defendant showed, or threatened to show, to others video footage depicting himself and the appellant, his former de facto partner, engaged in sexual activity. One of the claims was that those actions constituted the tort in Wilkinson v Downton . The appellant did not suffer psychiatric harm as a result of the threat but she did suffer severe emotional distress. Ashley and Neave JJ held that the tort did not extend to mental distress: [164]-[166], [471]-[477]. Maxwell P reached the opposite conclusion: [26]-[37].

The ratio decidendi of Giller is that the tort in Wilkinson v Downton is not available unless there is actual physical injury and that extreme mental distress does not constitute physical injury in the requisite sense. It would be inappropriate for me to depart from Giller unless convinced it was plainly wrong: Farah Constructions Pty Ltd v Say-Dee Pty Ltd [2007] HCA 22 ; (2007) 230 CLR 89 at 151-152 [135] . Whilst I can see the force of some of the criticisms which have been made of the present position I could not possibly say that Giller was clearly wrong. Accordingly, I am bound to follow it.

I am therefore faced with two quite different harassment cases each being seriously flawed. The current pleading does not allege psychiatric damage sufficient to constitute physical harm. While the mental and psychological distress it does allege is capable of being seen as flowing from the Commonwealth's behaviour towards Mr Habib upon his return to Australia, the decision in Giller renders this claim untenable.

On the other hand, the proposed pleading suggests that the harassment is constituted by the Commonwealth's actions prior to his arrival back in Australia but that harassment is not said to be causative of any loss. Both pleadings are deficient in form.

It is plain, I think, that the harassment allegation must be struck out. The question is whether leave to replead should be granted. I deal with that issue at the end of these reasons. Breach of fiduciary duty</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Gimson v Victorian Workcover Authority [1995] 1 VR 209</tocase>
<text>The authors of The Law of Torts in Australia also point to a decision of McDonald J in Gimson v Victorian Workcover Authority [1995] 1 VR 209 at 226-7 where a pleading was permitted to go forward to trial in which mere mental distress was alleged. More recently, however, the Victorian Court of Appeal has considered the issue in Giller v Procopets [2008] VSCA 236. In that case the defendant showed, or threatened to show, to others video footage depicting himself and the appellant, his former de facto partner, engaged in sexual activity. One of the claims was that those actions constituted the tort in Wilkinson v Downton . The appellant did not suffer psychiatric harm as a result of the threat but she did suffer severe emotional distress. Ashley and Neave JJ held that the tort did not extend to mental distress: [164]-[166], [471]-[477]. Maxwell P reached the opposite conclusion: [26]-[37].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Habib v Commonwealth of Australia [2008] FCA 1494</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1494.html</AustLII>
<text>The application is made by an amended notice of motion filed 21 July 2008 and seeks the summary dismissal of the proceeding. The current form of Mr Habib's pleading is the third further amended statement of claim which I shall refer to as 'the pleading'. Leave to file the pleading was granted on 7 October 2008 but, as was made clear on the occasion of that grant of leave, this was on the basis that the Commonwealth's complaints about the pleading's predecessor would be taken as standing against the pleading: Habib v Commonwealth of Australia [2008] FCA 1494 at [12] . The Commonwealth's motion for summary dismissal was heard by me on 9 and 10 October 2008. At that time, Mr Habib propounded a further pleading styled the "Proposed Fourth Further Amended Statement of Claim". I shall refer to that document as 'the proposed pleading'. Final written submissions were received on 28 October 2008.

The Commonwealth applies pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) for judgment in relation to all but one part of Mr Habib's case on the basis that the proceedings have no reasonable prospect of success. Section 31A provides: 
 Summary judgment 
 
(1) The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if:
 
(a) the first party is prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and
 
(b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding.
 
(2) The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if:
 
(a) the first party is defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and
 
(b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding.
 
(3) For the purposes of this section, a defence or a proceeding or part of a proceeding need not be:
 
(a) hopeless; or
 
(b) bound to fail;
 
 for it to have no reasonable prospect of success.
 
(4) This section does not limit any powers that the Court has apart from this section.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hamdan v Rumsfeld 548 US 557 (2006)</tocase>
<text>A written submission was received connecting the Third and Fourth Geneva Conventions to the negligence case but, contrary to the grant of leave, not to the misfeasance in a public office case. The Commonwealth submitted, correctly I think, that no case was being put by Mr Habib based on the Geneva Conventions insofar as the tort of misfeasance in a public office was concerned. I am bound to accept that submission. There is, therefore, no occasion to consider whether Mr Habib was a prisoner of war covered by the Third Geneva Convention, or a civilian covered by the Fourth Geneva Convention, an enemy combatant (as the Commonwealth submitted at the hearing) or simply a person not covered by either Convention because there was no armed conflict in Pakistan at the time Mr Habib was detained (as the Commonwealth submitted in writing). Nor is there any need to consider the impact of Article 5 of the Third Geneva Convention which, on one view, requires the protection of that Convention to be afforded to a person whose status is unclear until such time as that status is determined by a competent tribunal: cf Hamdan v Rumsfeld 548 US 557 (2006) at 630 per Stevens J delivering the opinion of the court; Hamdan v Rumsfeld 344 FSupp2d 152 (DDC 2004) at 161-162 per Robertson J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hamdan v Rumsfeld 344 FSupp2d 152 (DDC 2004)</tocase>
<text>A written submission was received connecting the Third and Fourth Geneva Conventions to the negligence case but, contrary to the grant of leave, not to the misfeasance in a public office case. The Commonwealth submitted, correctly I think, that no case was being put by Mr Habib based on the Geneva Conventions insofar as the tort of misfeasance in a public office was concerned. I am bound to accept that submission. There is, therefore, no occasion to consider whether Mr Habib was a prisoner of war covered by the Third Geneva Convention, or a civilian covered by the Fourth Geneva Convention, an enemy combatant (as the Commonwealth submitted at the hearing) or simply a person not covered by either Convention because there was no armed conflict in Pakistan at the time Mr Habib was detained (as the Commonwealth submitted in writing). Nor is there any need to consider the impact of Article 5 of the Third Geneva Convention which, on one view, requires the protection of that Convention to be afforded to a person whose status is unclear until such time as that status is determined by a competent tribunal: cf Hamdan v Rumsfeld 548 US 557 (2006) at 630 per Stevens J delivering the opinion of the court; Hamdan v Rumsfeld 344 FSupp2d 152 (DDC 2004) at 161-162 per Robertson J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/299.html</AustLII>
<text>The Commonwealth's submission was that it could not possibly be said that it had acted for, or on behalf of, Mr Habib. This submission is too simplistic. It is accepted that there is some kind of duty owed by the State to its overseas nationals. For example, in Mutasa v Attorney General [1980] QB 114 at 118-120 Boreham J spoke of the Crown having a duty to protect a citizen from unlawful detention but of that duty being one of imperfect obligation and thus unenforceable. So too, in China Navigation Company Ltd v Attorney General (1931) 40 Ll L Rep 110 at 112 Rowlatt J spoke of an alleged duty to assist a citizen against piracy as being but a "political" duty: cf. Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 593-594 [62] - [66] per Tamberlin J. Thus, it is a little glib to say that there was no aspect of the relationship between Mr Habib and the Commonwealth which could involve it in potentially "acting" on his behalf.

I have no doubt that the first duty does not exist, in the sense that it is not a "duty at law", although it may exist as an unenforceable political duty of imperfect obligation: Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 593-594 [62] - [66] per Tamberlin J. To embark upon a substantive consideration of whether the foreign policy steps taken by the Commonwealth were reasonable would involve this Court in directly examining the merits of Australian foreign policy. For reasons already given, such a duty cannot be countenanced.

The duty propounded in the proposed pleading is in a different category. It seeks to avoid the difficulties inherent in pursuing a remedy which requires this Court to pass on the adequacy or otherwise of Australian foreign policy. Instead, it contends only that the Commonwealth owed Mr Habib a duty to consider whether to intercede with the foreign States on his behalf. It is apparent that this novel duty has its origins in this Court's decision in Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2006) 156 FCR 574. In that case Tamberlin J refused to strike out a judicial review action brought by a Guantanamo Bay detainee against the Attorney-General. He sought to review the Commonwealth's decision not to intervene on his behalf with the US to seek his release. He did so on the basis that the Commonwealth had taken into account certain irrelevant considerations. Tamberlin J refused to strike the case out.

The duty pleaded in the proposed pleading arguably does not fall foul of the difficulty outlined in Re Ditfort . To hold that the Commonwealth should have considered whether to intercede on Mr Habib's behalf does not, arguably, involve an impermissible examination of the merits or otherwise of foreign policy. However, Mr Hicks' and Mr Habib's cases are conceptually very different. Mr Hicks sought judicial review of a decision and habeas corpus. Mr Habib seeks damages in tort. Inherent in the claim in tort is much more than Mr Hicks' claim to have the Commonwealth reconsider its position. It is a claim of wrongful conduct causing damage. It must necessarily travel further than a mere claim for reconsideration which claim Hicks v Ruddock holds to be arguable and into territory which requires the Court to reach a conclusion on what the outcome of that reconsideration should have been.

Indeed, as Lord Steyn explained at 1101 [113] in Kuwait Airways , the doctrine rests, in part, on the absence of available standards by which to judge the actions of the foreign state involved. Where the potential allegation is that the US and Egypt have committed grave breaches of the Geneva Conventions a clear standard is available: cf. Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 584-585 [21] - [23] per Tamberlin J where the potential interaction between the act of State doctrine and the Third and Fourth Geneva Conventions was examined. For those reasons, I do not think it can be said that the doctrine prevents a misfeasance suit potentially going forward. Indeed, on one view of things, it may well lie in the heart of the exceptions. Conclusion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hospital Products Ltd v United States Surgical Corporation [1984] HCA 64 ; (1984) 156 CLR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/64.html</AustLII>
<text>The Commonwealth submitted that no fiduciary duty could arise. There is, of course, no complete or comprehensive statement of what constitutes a fiduciary. However, where a novel fiduciary duty is alleged it is customary to refer to the judgment of Mason J in Hospital Products Ltd v United States Surgical Corporation [1984] HCA 64 ; (1984) 156 CLR 41 at 96-97 which is in these terms: 
The accepted fiduciary relationships are sometimes referred to as relationships of trust and confidence or confidential relations (cf. Phipps v. Boardman [1966] UKHL 2 ; [1967] 2 A.C. 46 , at p. 127), viz., trustee and beneficiary, agent and principal, solicitor and client, employee and employer, director and company, and partners. The critical feature of these relationships is that the fiduciary undertakes or agrees to act for or on behalf of or in the interests of another person in the exercise of a power or discretion which will affect the interests of that other person in a legal or practical sense. The relationship between the parties is therefore one which gives the fiduciary a special opportunity to exercise the power or discretion to the detriment of that other person who is accordingly vulnerable to abuse by the fiduciary of his position. The expressions "for", "on behalf of", and "in the interests of" signify that the fiduciary acts in a "representative" character in the exercise of his responsibility, to adopt an expression used by the Court of Appeal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hunter v Canary Wharf Ltd [1997] UKHL 14 ; [1997] AC 655</tocase>
<text>The authors of The Law of Torts in Australia (4th ed, OUP, 2007) devote an extensive section advocating a change to this position. They note the existence in the US of a right to recover where a case involves "extreme and outrageous intentional invasions of one's mental and emotional tranquility" citing Alcorn v Anbro Engineering Inc 468 P2d 216 (1970) at 218 [4] per Burke J. They also note the remarks of Lord Hoffman in Hunter v Canary Wharf Ltd [1997] UKHL 14 ; [1997] AC 655 at 707 to this effect: 
The perceived gap in Khorasandjian v. Bush was the absence of a tort of intentional harassment causing distress without actual bodily or psychiatric illness. This limitation is thought to arise out of cases like Wilkinson v. Downton [1897] 2 Q.B. 57 and Janvier v. Sweeney [1919] 2 K.B. 316. The law of harassment has now been put on a statutory basis (see the Protection from Harassment Act 1997) and it is unnecessary to consider how the common law might have developed. But as at present advised, I see no reason why a tort of intention should be subject to the rule which excludes compensation for mere distress, inconvenience or discomfort in actions based on negligence: see Hicks v. Chief Constable of the South Yorkshire Police [1991] UKHL 9 ; [1992] 2 All E.R. 65. The policy considerations are quite different. I do not therefore say that Khorasandjian v. Bush was wrongly decided. But it must be seen as a case on intentional harassment, not nuisance.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Kuwait Airways Corporation v Iraqi Airways Company (Nos 4 and 5) [2002] UKHL 19 ; [2002] 2 AC 883</tocase>
<text>Each of Mr Habib's claims would require a conclusion that a foreign State had committed grave wrongs. However, I would not regard the act of State doctrine as necessarily applicable to a claim based on misfeasance in a public office. This is because it is arguable that there is an exception to the principle where the acts of the foreign State in question constitute grave breaches of international law: Kuwait Airways Corporation v Iraqi Airways Company (Nos 4 and 5) [2002] UKHL 19 ; [2002] 2 AC 883 at 1080-1081 per Lord Nicholls (with whom Lord Hoffman agreed at 1105 [125]), 1101 [113] per Lord Steyn, 1109 [140] per Lord Hope; Petrotimor at 369 per Black CJ and Hill J; cf. Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249 at 278 per Lord Cross.

Indeed, as Lord Steyn explained at 1101 [113] in Kuwait Airways , the doctrine rests, in part, on the absence of available standards by which to judge the actions of the foreign state involved. Where the potential allegation is that the US and Egypt have committed grave breaches of the Geneva Conventions a clear standard is available: cf. Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 584-585 [21] - [23] per Tamberlin J where the potential interaction between the act of State doctrine and the Third and Fourth Geneva Conventions was examined. For those reasons, I do not think it can be said that the doctrine prevents a misfeasance suit potentially going forward. Indeed, on one view of things, it may well lie in the heart of the exceptions. Conclusion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maguire v Makaronis [1997] HCA 23 ; (1997) 188 CLR 449</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/23.html</AustLII>
<text>But the nature of the "position of conflict" was left unexplained. Equity imposes upon fiduciaries a duty of undivided loyalty: Maguire v Makaronis [1997] HCA 23 ; (1997) 188 CLR 449 at 465 per Brennan CJ, Gaudron, McHugh and Gummow JJ. The duty is the obligation to avoid being placed in a position where that undivided loyalty might be challenged. The breach of duty arises merely from being placed in the position of conflict and does not require that the conflict be acted upon. Thus the 'no conflict' rule is infringed where a fiduciary occupies a position where his self-interest and the duty to the beneficiary conflict: Warman International Ltd v Dwyer [1995] HCA 18 ; (1994) 182 CLR 544 at 557 per Mason CJ, Brennan, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ. It is also infringed where the fiduciary takes upon herself conflicting obligations: Breen v Williams (1996) 186 CLR 71 at 135 per Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Mutasa v Attorney General [1980] QB 114</tocase>
<text>The Commonwealth's submission was that it could not possibly be said that it had acted for, or on behalf of, Mr Habib. This submission is too simplistic. It is accepted that there is some kind of duty owed by the State to its overseas nationals. For example, in Mutasa v Attorney General [1980] QB 114 at 118-120 Boreham J spoke of the Crown having a duty to protect a citizen from unlawful detention but of that duty being one of imperfect obligation and thus unenforceable. So too, in China Navigation Company Ltd v Attorney General (1931) 40 Ll L Rep 110 at 112 Rowlatt J spoke of an alleged duty to assist a citizen against piracy as being but a "political" duty: cf. Hicks v Ruddock [2007] FCA 299 ; (2007) 156 FCR 574 at 593-594 [62] - [66] per Tamberlin J. Thus, it is a little glib to say that there was no aspect of the relationship between Mr Habib and the Commonwealth which could involve it in potentially "acting" on his behalf.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Northern Territory of Australia v Mengel [1995] HCA 65 ; (1994) 185 CLR 307</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/65.html</AustLII>
<text>The Commonwealth submits that such a pleading does not allege the elements of the tort of misfeasance in a public office. It is difficult to fault that submission. The tort was discussed by the High Court in Northern Territory of Australia v Mengel [1995] HCA 65 ; (1994) 185 CLR 307 at 345-348 per Mason CJ, Dawson, Toohey, Gaudron and McHugh JJ. That case establishes that the tort has the following elements: 
(a) an act or omission by a public officer done:
 
(i) with intent to harm; or
 
(ii) knowingly in excess of his or her authority; and
 
(b) involving a foreseeable risk of harm; and
 
(c) causing loss or damage.

It may be that element (a)(ii) will be satisfied where an official recklessly disregards the means of ascertaining the extent of his or her power: Mengel at 347.

There is no suggestion in this case that the Commonwealth itself deliberately harmed Mr Habib. All of the actual harm appears to have been caused by the Pakistani, Egyptian and US authorities. So viewed, the matter cannot involve intent to harm in the sense identified in Mengel . The knowledge limb, and its possible extension to the position of an official who recklessly disregards the means of ascertaining the extent of his of her power, directs attention to paragraph 24 of the pleading which alleges: 
The respondent gave to Egyptian security officials information and documents including tapes of private telphone conversations, sim cards, a laptop computer, his address book, his Egyptian identity card, files taken from his home including files relating to Raqeem, Kadr, Mohammed Al Asra and Mohammed Dawood and photographs which the respondent knew or should have known would be used by those officials in the course of interrogation of the applicant, involving maltreatment and torture.

This allegation might sustain an allegation of misfeasance in a public office if it could be alleged that so acting was beyond the executive power of the Commonwealth and that the officials involved recklessly disregarded the means of ascertaining the limits of their authority. As I have previously said, because s 61 of the Constitution extends the executive power of the Commonwealth to the maintenance of the laws of the Commonwealth, it is beyond that power to facilitate a breach of those laws. Thus, if it could be said that the provision of intelligence by the Commonwealth to the Egyptian authorities for use, to the knowledge of the Commonwealth, in Mr Habib's torture was contrary to Commonwealth law then at least one element of Mengel would be satisfied.

During the course of the hearing discussion took place about the operation of the Third and Fourth Geneva Conventions (which deal respectively with the protection of prisoners of war and civilians during armed conflicts). Prior to 26 September 2002 the Geneva Conventions Act 1957 (Cth) made "grave breaches" of those Conventions a Commonwealth crime. "Grave breaches" under both Conventions included torture and inhuman treatment (Article 130 and 147 respectively). The Act had extra-territorial operation according to its tenor: s 6(2). Section 11.2(1) of the Criminal Code (Cth) had the effect of making it an offence to aid, abet, counsel or procure the commission of those crimes. On 26 September 2002 the offences created by the Geneva Conventions Act 1957 (Cth) were removed from that Act and re-enacted as Chapter 8 Division 268 of the Criminal Code (Cth). There may be an argument that these offence provisions had the consequence that neither the executive power of the Commonwealth under s 61 of the Constitution , nor any other source of statutory power such as s 8 of the Australian Federal Police Act 1979 (Cth) or s 17 of the Australian Security Intelligence Organisation Act 1979 (Cth), conferred lawful authority to aid, abet, counsel or procure the torture or inhuman treatment of Mr Habib. With that in mind, I granted leave to Mr Habib's counsel to put on further submissions about the relationship between the Geneva Conventions and the tort of misfeasance in a public office.

In the circumstance where none of the constitutive elements of the tort have been pleaded, no explanation of how such a cause of action might operate proffered and an invitation to explore the interaction between the Geneva Conventions and Mengel unaccountably declined, it seems to me that the action must be struck out.

In this context, it is also useful to consider the allegation in paragraph 21 of the proposed pleading that Commonwealth officials interviewed Mr Habib at Guantanamo Bay whilst he was shackled in chains. Whether such actions amount to aiding and abetting within s 11.2 of the Criminal Code (Cth) need not be decided. However, one question which might arise is the extent to which the construction of Division 268 is informed by matters of international law. In that regard, the advance report of the Special Rapporteur on the promotion and protection of human rights and fundamental freedoms while countering terrorism has indicated that "even the mere presence of intelligence personnel at an interview with a person who is being held in places where his rights are violated, can be reasonably understood as implicitly condoning such practices": Martin Scheinin, UN Doc A/HRC/10/3 (2009) at 19. However, the nature of any such debate does not presently fall for decision.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249</tocase>
<text>Each of Mr Habib's claims would require a conclusion that a foreign State had committed grave wrongs. However, I would not regard the act of State doctrine as necessarily applicable to a claim based on misfeasance in a public office. This is because it is arguable that there is an exception to the principle where the acts of the foreign State in question constitute grave breaches of international law: Kuwait Airways Corporation v Iraqi Airways Company (Nos 4 and 5) [2002] UKHL 19 ; [2002] 2 AC 883 at 1080-1081 per Lord Nicholls (with whom Lord Hoffman agreed at 1105 [125]), 1101 [113] per Lord Steyn, 1109 [140] per Lord Hope; Petrotimor at 369 per Black CJ and Hill J; cf. Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249 at 278 per Lord Cross.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Petrotimor Companhia de Petroleos SARL v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] FCAFC 3 ; (2003) 126 FCR 354</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2003/3.html</AustLII>
<text>Finally, the Commonwealth made a broad submission that the act of State doctrine operated to prevent this Court from examining the rights and wrongs of the acts of a foreign State. Over a century ago the doctrine was held to form part of "the settled law of all civilized countries": Potter v Broken Hill Pty Company Ltd [1906] HCA 88 ; (1906) 3 CLR 479 at 495 per Griffith CJ. More recently it has been described by the High Court as a long-recognised principle of international law: Attorney-General (UK) v Heinemann Publishers Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40 and by a judge of this Court as a rule of private international law: Petrotimor Companhia de Petroleos SARL v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] FCAFC 3 ; (2003) 126 FCR 354 at 415 [159] per Beaumont J. The Commonwealth's submission that the act of State doctrine exists must be accepted: Petrotimor at 366-369 [33]-[45] per Black CJ and Hill J, 415-416 [159]-[160] per Beaumont J.

Each of Mr Habib's claims would require a conclusion that a foreign State had committed grave wrongs. However, I would not regard the act of State doctrine as necessarily applicable to a claim based on misfeasance in a public office. This is because it is arguable that there is an exception to the principle where the acts of the foreign State in question constitute grave breaches of international law: Kuwait Airways Corporation v Iraqi Airways Company (Nos 4 and 5) [2002] UKHL 19 ; [2002] 2 AC 883 at 1080-1081 per Lord Nicholls (with whom Lord Hoffman agreed at 1105 [125]), 1101 [113] per Lord Steyn, 1109 [140] per Lord Hope; Petrotimor at 369 per Black CJ and Hill J; cf. Oppenheimer v Cattermole (Inspector of Taxes) [1976] AC 249 at 278 per Lord Cross.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c28">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Potter v Broken Hill Pty Company Ltd [1906] HCA 88 ; (1906) 3 CLR 479</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1906/88.html</AustLII>
<text>Finally, the Commonwealth made a broad submission that the act of State doctrine operated to prevent this Court from examining the rights and wrongs of the acts of a foreign State. Over a century ago the doctrine was held to form part of "the settled law of all civilized countries": Potter v Broken Hill Pty Company Ltd [1906] HCA 88 ; (1906) 3 CLR 479 at 495 per Griffith CJ. More recently it has been described by the High Court as a long-recognised principle of international law: Attorney-General (UK) v Heinemann Publishers Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 25 ; (1988) 165 CLR 30 at 40 and by a judge of this Court as a rule of private international law: Petrotimor Companhia de Petroleos SARL v Commonwealth of Australia [2003] FCAFC 3 ; (2003) 126 FCR 354 at 415 [159] per Beaumont J. The Commonwealth's submission that the act of State doctrine exists must be accepted: Petrotimor at 366-369 [33]-[45] per Black CJ and Hill J, 415-416 [159]-[160] per Beaumont J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c29">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>R v North and East Devon Health Authority; Ex parte Coughlan [2001] QB 213</tocase>
<text>Such a cause of action may be viable in the United Kingdom: see R v North and East Devon Health Authority; Ex parte Coughlan [2001] QB 213. However, it is not open for me to entertain the argument for it has been held on high authority that Australian law knows no action based on substantive legitimate expectations: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at 21 [66] - [67] per McHugh and Gummow JJ, 48 [148] per Callinan J. See also Rush v Commissioner of Police [2006] FCA 12 ; (2006) 150 FCR 165 at 186-187 [82] per Finn J. Misfeasance in a public office</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c30">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Re Ditfort; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (NSW) (1988) 19 FCR 347</tocase>
<text>That the Commonwealth has the power to conduct foreign relations is undoubted. It is conferred by s 61 of the Constitution on the Queen and is exercisable by the Governor-General as her representative. No doubt that power bears many similarities to the similar prerogative power possessed by the Queen in her capacity as the sovereign of the United Kingdom. As Gummow J pointed out in Re Ditfort; Ex parte Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (NSW) (1988) 19 FCR 347 at 369 the question in this country is not the content of the prerogative but rather the meaning and operation of s 61. This has the immediate consequence that the question of whether the executive power extends to a particular topic is a question about the operation of s 61 and hence is a matter involving the interpretation of the Constitution within the meaning of s 76(i). And, because s 61 in turn is concerned with the maintenance of the laws of the Commonwealth, it follows that the executive power is subject to those laws. In consequence, the scope and ambit of the executive power existing under s 61 may, in a particular case, require an examination of the extent to which Commonwealth legislation has intruded into, or perhaps more accurately regulated, that power. In such a case, there would not only be a question of interpretation of s 61 but also, potentially, a matter arising under a law of the Parliament within the meaning of s 76(ii) of the Constitution .

There are a number of different aspects to that broad principle. First , it is plain that the courts will absolutely abide the executive's views on questions such as the accession of foreign territory, the recognition of a foreign sovereign or the recognition of foreign States and ambassadors: see Chow Hung Ching v The King [1948] HCA 37 ; (1948) 77 CLR 449 at 467 per Latham CJ. Secondly , generally speaking, the issues which arise between nation States are unlikely to generate matters within the meaning of ss 75 and 76 of the Constitution for the rights and obligations in that plane do not form part of domestic law: Re Ditfort at 370 per Gummow J. Thirdly, for related reasons, such questions are usually unable to bring forth a plaintiff who has standing: Re Ditfort at 369. Fourthly , complaints about the conduct of Australian international relations are likely to take a court into an area which involves the consideration of undertakings or obligations depending entirely on political sanctions. Where that occurs it is generally thought there is no matter in the requisite sense: Re Ditfort at 370. For example, a complaint by an Australian exporter that trade sanctions had been negligently imposed on a country to which it exported would immediately involve this Court in the consideration of matters which it is institutionally unsuited to resolve: Gerhardy v Brown [1985] HCA 11 ; (1985) 159 CLR 70 at 138-139 per Brennan J.

The duty pleaded in the proposed pleading arguably does not fall foul of the difficulty outlined in Re Ditfort . To hold that the Commonwealth should have considered whether to intercede on Mr Habib's behalf does not, arguably, involve an impermissible examination of the merits or otherwise of foreign policy. However, Mr Hicks' and Mr Habib's cases are conceptually very different. Mr Hicks sought judicial review of a decision and habeas corpus. Mr Habib seeks damages in tort. Inherent in the claim in tort is much more than Mr Hicks' claim to have the Commonwealth reconsider its position. It is a claim of wrongful conduct causing damage. It must necessarily travel further than a mere claim for reconsideration which claim Hicks v Ruddock holds to be arguable and into territory which requires the Court to reach a conclusion on what the outcome of that reconsideration should have been.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c31">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>Such a cause of action may be viable in the United Kingdom: see R v North and East Devon Health Authority; Ex parte Coughlan [2001] QB 213. However, it is not open for me to entertain the argument for it has been held on high authority that Australian law knows no action based on substantive legitimate expectations: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at 21 [66] - [67] per McHugh and Gummow JJ, 48 [148] per Callinan J. See also Rush v Commissioner of Police [2006] FCA 12 ; (2006) 150 FCR 165 at 186-187 [82] per Finn J. Misfeasance in a public office</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c32">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Rookes v Barnard [1964] UKHL 1 ; [1964] AC 1129</tocase>
<text>The Commonwealth denies that such facts could constitute the tort of intimidation. There are three elements to this tort. First , there must be a demand made of the plaintiff by the defendant coupled with a threat to either the plaintiff or a third party: Stratford (JT) &amp; Son Ltd v Lindley [1965] AC 269 at 283 per Lord Denning MR. Secondly , the threat issued by the defendant must be to commit an unlawful or illegal act. The illegality required need not be criminal; indeed, it has been held that a threat to breach a contract is a sufficient threat for the purposes of the tort: Rookes v Barnard [1964] UKHL 1 ; [1964] AC 1129. Thirdly , it must be shown that the plaintiff complied with the demand: Stratford at 283. Messrs Balkin and Davis in the Law of Torts (3rd ed, LexisNexis Butterworths, 2004) summarise the tort this way (at 654 [21.30]): 
The essence of the tort of intimidation is that the defendant has, by a threat to commit an unlawful act, coerced another person into acting in a way in which the latter did not wish to act, the defendant having thereby intended and caused economic damage to the plaintiff.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c33">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Rush v Commissioner of Police [2006] FCA 12 ; (2006) 150 FCR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/12.html</AustLII>
<text>Such a cause of action may be viable in the United Kingdom: see R v North and East Devon Health Authority; Ex parte Coughlan [2001] QB 213. However, it is not open for me to entertain the argument for it has been held on high authority that Australian law knows no action based on substantive legitimate expectations: see Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 at 21 [66] - [67] per McHugh and Gummow JJ, 48 [148] per Callinan J. See also Rush v Commissioner of Police [2006] FCA 12 ; (2006) 150 FCR 165 at 186-187 [82] per Finn J. Misfeasance in a public office</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c34">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719</tocase>
<text>In either event, it is plain that the question of the extent of the executive power is consigned to the Chapter III courts. In that regard, at a functional level, the situation is not so very different to the treatment given by the English courts to the question of the extent of the prerogative. For, at least since the Case of Proclamations (1611) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352, the courts of that country have asserted, and the other branches of government have eventually accepted, the final role of the courts in determining the ambit of that prerogative. Just as a Commonwealth law may delimit the scope of the executive power, so too it is well established that the prerogative may be excluded by statute. Attorney-General v De Keyser's Royal Hotel Ltd [1920] UKHL 1 ; [1920] AC 508 is an example of where a statute was found to have curtailed the prerogative. In Australia, Barton v Commonwealth [1974] HCA 20 ; (1974) 131 CLR 477 is an example where a statute was found not to have that effect; the Full Court of this Court's decision in Schlieske v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1988) 84 ALR 719 is a contrary example.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c35">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Stratford (JT) &amp; Son Ltd v Lindley [1965] AC 269</tocase>
<text>The Commonwealth denies that such facts could constitute the tort of intimidation. There are three elements to this tort. First , there must be a demand made of the plaintiff by the defendant coupled with a threat to either the plaintiff or a third party: Stratford (JT) &amp; Son Ltd v Lindley [1965] AC 269 at 283 per Lord Denning MR. Secondly , the threat issued by the defendant must be to commit an unlawful or illegal act. The illegality required need not be criminal; indeed, it has been held that a threat to breach a contract is a sufficient threat for the purposes of the tort: Rookes v Barnard [1964] UKHL 1 ; [1964] AC 1129. Thirdly , it must be shown that the plaintiff complied with the demand: Stratford at 283. Messrs Balkin and Davis in the Law of Torts (3rd ed, LexisNexis Butterworths, 2004) summarise the tort this way (at 654 [21.30]): 
The essence of the tort of intimidation is that the defendant has, by a threat to commit an unlawful act, coerced another person into acting in a way in which the latter did not wish to act, the defendant having thereby intended and caused economic damage to the plaintiff.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c36">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Warman International Ltd v Dwyer [1995] HCA 18 ; (1994) 182 CLR 544</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/18.html</AustLII>
<text>But the nature of the "position of conflict" was left unexplained. Equity imposes upon fiduciaries a duty of undivided loyalty: Maguire v Makaronis [1997] HCA 23 ; (1997) 188 CLR 449 at 465 per Brennan CJ, Gaudron, McHugh and Gummow JJ. The duty is the obligation to avoid being placed in a position where that undivided loyalty might be challenged. The breach of duty arises merely from being placed in the position of conflict and does not require that the conflict be acted upon. Thus the 'no conflict' rule is infringed where a fiduciary occupies a position where his self-interest and the duty to the beneficiary conflict: Warman International Ltd v Dwyer [1995] HCA 18 ; (1994) 182 CLR 544 at 557 per Mason CJ, Brennan, Deane, Dawson and Gaudron JJ. It is also infringed where the fiduciary takes upon herself conflicting obligations: Breen v Williams (1996) 186 CLR 71 at 135 per Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c37">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Wilkinson v Downton [1987] 2 QB 57</tocase>
<text>I turn then to the harassment claim. Strictly speaking, there is no such tort. However, there is an action on the case for the intentional but indirect infliction of harm. In Wilkinson v Downton [1897] 2 QB 57 the defendant told the plaintiff that her husband had been seriously injured in an accident and that she should go and fetch him. This was completely untrue. On hearing the statement the plaintiff suffered a violent shock to her nervous system initially involving vomiting but subsequently producing permanent physical consequences. Some of these involved serious mental illness and included weeks of physical suffering. Wright J said (at 58-59): 
The real question is as to the 100 l ., the greatest part of which is given as compensation for the female plaintiff's illness and suffering. It was argued for her that she is entitled to recover this as being damage caused by fraud, and therefore within the doctrine established by Pasley v. Freeman (1789) 3 T. R. 51 and Langridge v. Levy (1837) 2 M. &amp; W. 519. I am not sure that this would not be an extension of that doctrine, the real ground of which appears to be that a person who makes a false statement intended to be acted on must make good the damage naturally resulting from its being acted on. Here there is no injuria of that kind. I think, however, that the verdict may be supported upon another ground. The defendant has, as I assume for the moment, wilfully done an act calculated to cause physical harm to the plaintiff that is to say, to infringe her legal right to personal safety, and has in fact thereby caused physical harm to her. That proposition without more appears to me to state a good cause of action, there being no justification alleged for the act. This wilful injuria is in law malicious, although no malicious purpose to cause the harm which was caused nor any motive of spite is imputed to the defendant.

It is, however, clear that in Australia a distinction is drawn between psychological harm (mere distress) and psychiatric harm (physical injury). The tort in Wilkinson v Downton is confined to cases of physical injury which may include nervous shock (such as suffered by Mrs Wilkinson) but does not include mere mental distress or anguish.

The authors of The Law of Torts in Australia also point to a decision of McDonald J in Gimson v Victorian Workcover Authority [1995] 1 VR 209 at 226-7 where a pleading was permitted to go forward to trial in which mere mental distress was alleged. More recently, however, the Victorian Court of Appeal has considered the issue in Giller v Procopets [2008] VSCA 236. In that case the defendant showed, or threatened to show, to others video footage depicting himself and the appellant, his former de facto partner, engaged in sexual activity. One of the claims was that those actions constituted the tort in Wilkinson v Downton . The appellant did not suffer psychiatric harm as a result of the threat but she did suffer severe emotional distress. Ashley and Neave JJ held that the tort did not extend to mental distress: [164]-[166], [471]-[477]. Maxwell P reached the opposite conclusion: [26]-[37].

The ratio decidendi of Giller is that the tort in Wilkinson v Downton is not available unless there is actual physical injury and that extreme mental distress does not constitute physical injury in the requisite sense. It would be inappropriate for me to depart from Giller unless convinced it was plainly wrong: Farah Constructions Pty Ltd v Say-Dee Pty Ltd [2007] HCA 22 ; (2007) 230 CLR 89 at 151-152 [135] . Whilst I can see the force of some of the criticisms which have been made of the present position I could not possibly say that Giller was clearly wrong. Accordingly, I am bound to follow it.

This is an allegation that what was suffered was mental or psychological shock which, not being a claim for psychiatric harm, takes the claim outside the principle in Wilkinson v Downton . The words "seriously wounded and injured" when first appearing are in contradistinction to the words "suffered great pain of body and mind, mental and psychological shock and distress" which follow. The natural reading is that the first phrase is concerned with physical injury; the second with mental anguish. I accept that the words "otherwise seriously wounded and injured" may also contain an allegation of physical injury. However, for two reasons I do not read those words as applying to the harassment claim.

First , it is unclear from paragraph 50 which of the very many allegations contained in paragraphs 5 to 49 of the pleading (of which only paragraphs 40 to 48 appear to be concerned with harassment) are connected to which of the losses alleged in paragraph 50. Secondly , it is apparent from the proposed pleading that the harassment claim is no longer pressed on the basis of events following Mr Habib's return to Australia. Instead, paragraph 25 of the Proposed pleading alleges: 
The actions and conduct of the respondent during the material time amounted to sustained harassment and intimidation of the applicant.

I assume the words "material time" refer to the period after Mr Habib was picked up in Pakistan until his release from Guantanamo Bay. This must be taken to be so because the allegations contained in the pleading relating to the events which occurred upon Mr Habib's return to Australia, with the exception of the defamation allegations, have been omitted from the Proposed pleading. The pleading of loss in the Proposed pleading is at paragraph 26 and is in these terms: 
The applicant suffered physical and mental damage caused by prolonged unlawful incarceration, torture and ill treatment in Pakistan, Egypt and Cuba, and unlawful incarceration in Afghanistan.

Be all of that as it may, it seems to me that there is the possibility that Mr Habib has a case for misfeasance in a public office and, perhaps, harassment in the Wilkinson v Downton sense. Particularly where there has been so far only one strike out application I do not think that I should deny leave to replead unless I am satisfied that the defects in the statement of claim are incapable of being cured. I am not satisfied of that in the case of the two causes of action I have mentioned.

I do not see any basis upon which I may dispose of the defamation allegations as I cannot say they are incapable of succeeding even if they seem out of place in a case such as this.

My conclusion, therefore, is that the pleading must be struck out but that there should be a grant of leave to replead the claims with respect to misfeasance in a public office, harassment and defamation. In relation to those matters, particularly the first, it is to be emphasised that the pleading raises issues which are of considerable technical complexity involving as they do the interaction between constitutional and administrative law and the law of tort. Although I have not acceded to the Commonwealth's argument as to the adequacy, from a technical perspective, of the pleadings it may be safely assumed that the next pleading will be held to proper standards.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>