<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Uniline Australia Ltd ACN 010 752 057 v SBriggs Pty Ltd ACN 007 415 518 [2009] FCA 222 (16 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/222.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/788.html</AustLII>
<text>The Court might be aided in answering that question by evidence given by experts. Plainly enough, evidence can be given by experts of the meaning those skilled in the art relevant to the field of the invention would give to technical terms, phrases and concepts accepted within the relevant discipline. Where the specification addresses and the claims contain, technical terms, the Court must have evidence before it of the technical meaning so as to understand the meaning a person familiar with the state of the art at the priority date would attribute to those terms. A proper understanding of how a relevantly skilled reader would understand such terms enables the Court to construe the claims in the context of the specification and attribute meaning to the claims in isolating the essential integers. In undertaking that exercise, the Court will determine what weight ought to be attributed to particular expert evidence. The construction of the patent is a matter entirely for the Court aided by evidence of the understanding of the skilled reader. The proper construction of the patent is not determined by findings preferring one expert's view of the construction of the patent, over another. The patent will be construed according to the ordinary meaning to be attributed to the language of the document informed by the Court's understanding of technical terms through evidence reflecting the understanding of a person skilled in the relevant art (as to these principles generally, see Sachtler GMBH &amp; Co. v R E Miller [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J and particularly those authorities assembled at [20], [21] and [22]).

Uniline called evidence from an expert, Dr Duncan Gilmore. Dr Gilmore holds the degrees of Bachelor of Engineering, Master of Engineering Science and a Doctor of Philosophy. Dr Gilmore is a Fellow of the Institution of Engineers Australia and the Society of Automotive Engineers Australasia and a member of other professional bodies in the engineering field. Dr Gilmore has undertaken design work in relation to "hand winders" for a participant in the blinds industry and has undertaken work for Uniline. Dr Gilmore has provided a number of affidavits with reports annexed. Dr Gilmore's evidence provides an analysis and explanation of the spring clutch assembly described in the patent in suit. Dr Gilmore describes the spring, the assembly of the components, the general utility of the assembly and the functional operation of the clutch. Dr Gilmore considers in detail claim 13 of the patent in suit and at page 12 of his report dated 11 February 2008, Dr Gilmore sets out his preferred interpretation of claim 13. Dr Gilmore also expresses views about the features of assembly of Uniline's spring clutch, its functionality and whether the Uniline spring clutch embodies each of the integers falling within claim 13 of the patent in suit.

Apart from the question of construction of the patent in suit and matters going to functionality of each assembly, Dr Gilmore gives evidence as to the features of the spring clutch assembly described in US Patent 643 and expresses an opinion as to whether the disclosures in that patent anticipate essential features of the patent in suit.

The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.

In that sense, the Court does not first construe the claims without reference to the specification and then determine whether ambiguity exists ( Sachtler ). The document is read in its entirety and clear meaning is to be given to the clear words of a claim. Although the Court seeks to construe the language of the claims taking account of the skilled reader's (e.g. a person skilled in the relevant art) practical and commonsense understanding of terms and particular language, clear language ought to be given its natural and apparent meaning and not read down as though the evidence of the skilled reader imported a qualification upon a claim inconsistent with that meaning. No doubt evidence of particular applied terms of art in any given field or discipline may make the construction of the language of a claim using those terms a difficult question of balance between the natural expression of the language of the claims and the conditioning influence of terms of art.

Adopting a purposive approach to construction of the claims does not mean that clear limitations in the scope of the monopoly contained in the language of the claims can be avoided or the reach of the monopoly extended beyond the clear limits of the language selected. A purposive approach to construction as opposed to a purely literal one will raise the question of whether persons with practical knowledge and experience of the kind of work in which the invention was intended to be used, would understand that strict compliance with the descriptive words or phrases used in a claim was intended to be an essential requirement of the invention. If so, as a matter of construction, a variant would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect on the way the invention works. That question does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material affect upon the way the invention works ( Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 ; Kirin-Amgen Inc. v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444). The construction of the language of a claim, adopted by the Court, ultimately determines infringement. The question is whether the alleged infringement is comprehended by the clear language of the claim ( Sachtler applying Catnic and PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41). Construction of the claims</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2006) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/220.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.

The question to be determined is whether US Patent 643 discloses to a skilled addressee with common general knowledge of the relevant art, each of the integers demanded by the claims defining the monopoly ( Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd (supra) at [128] to [152]) and in that sense, the test of anticipation is the reverse infringement test. Would use of a spring clutch in accordance with the disclosures in US Patent 643 infringe claim 13? The skilled addressee must be able to read and understand the document as disclosing all of the integers of the monopoly in the combination without the exercise of "inventive ingenuity and the taking of an inventive step" ( Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin Engineering Co. &amp; Anor (1989) 91 ALR 513 , per Gummow J at 531 and 532) and without deducing an integer as part of a combination claim, by taking an obvious and non-inventive step to reach the combination. The disclosure in the document must be clear in the sense that the language of the document must provide unmistakable instruction to the addressee as to how the combination claimed is used, although the language of the disclosure need not be that of the claim. An anticipation of a claim is not determined merely by a textual comparison of the disclosure and the claim. The language of the disclosure might well be different to the language of the claim but the disclosure must teach the skilled addressee the invention (the combination of integers) and its use ( Pfizer (supra) at [311] to [324]; Evans Medical Ltd Patent [1998] RPC 517 at 576; Nicaro Holdings (supra))</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/481.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254</tocase>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/178.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1787.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1</tocase>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.

The question to be determined is whether US Patent 643 discloses to a skilled addressee with common general knowledge of the relevant art, each of the integers demanded by the claims defining the monopoly ( Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd (supra) at [128] to [152]) and in that sense, the test of anticipation is the reverse infringement test. Would use of a spring clutch in accordance with the disclosures in US Patent 643 infringe claim 13? The skilled addressee must be able to read and understand the document as disclosing all of the integers of the monopoly in the combination without the exercise of "inventive ingenuity and the taking of an inventive step" ( Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin Engineering Co. &amp; Anor (1989) 91 ALR 513 , per Gummow J at 531 and 532) and without deducing an integer as part of a combination claim, by taking an obvious and non-inventive step to reach the combination. The disclosure in the document must be clear in the sense that the language of the document must provide unmistakable instruction to the addressee as to how the combination claimed is used, although the language of the disclosure need not be that of the claim. An anticipation of a claim is not determined merely by a textual comparison of the disclosure and the claim. The language of the disclosure might well be different to the language of the claim but the disclosure must teach the skilled addressee the invention (the combination of integers) and its use ( Pfizer (supra) at [311] to [324]; Evans Medical Ltd Patent [1998] RPC 517 at 576; Nicaro Holdings (supra))

The final ground of revocation involves a contention that SBriggs obtained the patent by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation ([11], s 138(3)(d) of the Patents Act ) and that the amendment to the patent ([12], [17], [18], [56] and [57]; s 138(3)(e) of the Patents Act ) was also obtained by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation. The question is whether the conduct of SBriggs said to bear the character required by the section, materially contributed to the Commissioner's decision to grant the patent or amend the claims. It is sufficient if the conduct is a material inducing factor which led to either of those outcomes ( Prestige Group (Australia) Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1990) 26 FCR 197 ; Pfizer (supra); JMVB Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 68). Sections 138(3)(d) and 138 (3)(e) do not require proof of a deliberate intention on the part of the applicant for the patent (or amendment) to deceive the Commissioner ( Pfizer ). If the representation is based upon a belief, it is relevant to consider whether the belief is false or not held reasonably ( NSI Dental Pty Ltd v University of Melbourne (2006) 69 IPR 542).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1893.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flexible Steel Lacing Company v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/890.html</AustLII>
<text>When determining the boundaries of a claim, the specification must be read as a whole. It describes the patentee's best known method. If the language of a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be rendered ambiguous, obfuscated or qualified by statements extracted from the specification as if those statements form part of the language of the claim defining the monopoly ( Flexible Steel Lacing Company v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331). Although the language of the claim defines the monopoly, the claim marks out the boundary of a particular solution to a problem not solved by the prior art and thus has a context. Reference should be made to the specification to understand that context, to explain the background to the claims and to ascertain the meaning of technical terms ( Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co. v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253). Although the clear language of a claim should not be diluted, qualified or obfuscated by reference to the specification, unclear language used in a claim might usefully be made clear by reference to words used in the specification, in the relevant context ( Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Ltd v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1). The specification will, among other things, describe aspects of the prior art, unresolved problems in the prior art, the object the invention seeks to achieve and preferred embodiments of the invention and will recite a claim or claims staking out the patentee's exclusive ground. The Court reads that document in the logical sequence of its contentions and seeks to construe the claims, according to the words chosen in the claims, taking account of those matters, recognising that an identified embodiment or a preferred embodiment does not limit the natural language of a claim yet, the patentee may by clear language choose to limit the scope of the monopoly.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company v Beiersdorf (Australia) Limited [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1980/9.html</AustLII>
<text>When determining the boundaries of a claim, the specification must be read as a whole. It describes the patentee's best known method. If the language of a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be rendered ambiguous, obfuscated or qualified by statements extracted from the specification as if those statements form part of the language of the claim defining the monopoly ( Flexible Steel Lacing Company v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331). Although the language of the claim defines the monopoly, the claim marks out the boundary of a particular solution to a problem not solved by the prior art and thus has a context. Reference should be made to the specification to understand that context, to explain the background to the claims and to ascertain the meaning of technical terms ( Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co. v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253). Although the clear language of a claim should not be diluted, qualified or obfuscated by reference to the specification, unclear language used in a claim might usefully be made clear by reference to words used in the specification, in the relevant context ( Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Ltd v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1). The specification will, among other things, describe aspects of the prior art, unresolved problems in the prior art, the object the invention seeks to achieve and preferred embodiments of the invention and will recite a claim or claims staking out the patentee's exclusive ground. The Court reads that document in the logical sequence of its contentions and seeks to construe the claims, according to the words chosen in the claims, taking account of those matters, recognising that an identified embodiment or a preferred embodiment does not limit the natural language of a claim yet, the patentee may by clear language choose to limit the scope of the monopoly.

A question arises as to the significance of claim 14 of the patent as an aid to the construction of claims 1 to 13. Claim 14 claims the spring clutch of claim 13 where the spring "is of unitary construction". Claim 14 was introduced into the patent by amendment by leave granted by IP Australia on 1 November 2006 consequent upon an application made by the patentee on 24 October 2006. Amendments to claim 13 were made at the same time (see [17] and [18] of these reasons). Mr Hunter gave evidence that claim 14 does not add anything to the scope of claims 1 to 13 as those claims comprehend a helical spring of unitary construction with reverse winding and a plurality of helical springs of alternate winding which operate in the same way as a spring clutch incorporating a spring of unitary construction with reverse winding. In that sense, it is not said by Mr Hunter or SBriggs that claim 14 aids in the construction of claims 1 to 13 on the footing that claim 14 prescribes a monopoly directed to the integers of claim 13 limited to a unitary spring and thus claim 13 must address something other than a spring clutch incorporating a unitary spring. It is not said that, by inference drawn from claim 14, claims 1 to 13 are directed to multiple adjacent separate springs of alternate winding. SBriggs says claims 1 to 13 bring within the monopoly a helically reverse wound unitary spring and a plurality of springs that cause the spring clutch of Exhibit 1 to operate in the same way as a spring clutch incorporating a reverse wound unitary spring. As Mr Hunter points out, it is then difficult to see exactly what claim 14 adds to the scope of claims 1 to 13, on that view of those claims. Mr Hunter is correct in this respect.

The language of claim 13 requires as an essential integer of the monopoly, the presence of a single reverse wound unitary spring. The introduction into the patent of claim 14 (in its current amended terms) with the result that selective engagement of the tabs of the helical spring of claims 1 to 12 , was elevated into an amended claim 13 as part of a redefined control means (see claim 13(3)(a) and (b)), does not say anything about the helical spring of claims 1 to 12. In order to construe the language of claims 1 to 13 post-amendment in a way which extends the integers of those claims to multiple separate springs of alternate winding, further amendments would have been necessary to claims 1 to 13 to adopt clear language that brought a plurality of springs within the boundaries of the monopoly. That result does not arise simply by inference from an amendment to claim 14 (and related amendments to claim 13). The express reciting in claim 14 of a spring of unitary construction adds nothing to claims which address a single unitary spring of reverse winding.

Having regard to the construction adopted in relation to claims 1 to 13, it follows that the threats of infringement proceedings made by SBriggs by the letter from its solicitors to Uniline dated 4 April 2007 and the further letter dated 16 July 2007 from those solicitors to the patent attorneys for Uniline are unjustifiable as no infringement is made out. The Amended Cross-Claim for infringement of the patent in suit fails. Issues going to validity of the patent assuming the "counter-factual" (construction) hypothesis 
General approach

Claim 13 of the patent in suit demands the presence of a single unitary reverse wound spring engaging a longitudinal slot and key device. Plainly, that invention is not anticipated by US Patent 643. If claim 13 extends to the inclusion of a plurality of multiple springs of alternate winding with tabs engaged by the control device of claim 13, is that invention disclosed by US Patent 643? Each expert has sought to answer that question by applying a different method of analysis. Mr Hunter isolated the essential features of claim 13 (and other claims upon which it depends) and compared those features with the invention disclosed by US Patent 643, that is, the novel elements claimed for the invention (Table A, para 38, Hunter affidavit, 6 March 2008). Mr Hunter could not see all the integers of claim 13 in the integers of the invention of US Patent 643 (claims 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 9, 12, 13 (as to a helical spring for the purposes of claims 3 7, 9 and 12; and as to the feature of a single longitudinal opening defined by edges selectively engaging one or more of the tabs of the spring) and 14). Thus, no anticipation arises in his view. Mr Hunter separately considered the essential features with the prior art disclosures identified in US Patent 643 (Table B, para 38, Hunter affidavit, 6 March 2008). Mr Hunter could not see all of the integers of claim 13 in the prior art (claims 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, claim 13 (because the prior art does not disclose alternate wound springs, but otherwise all essential elements of claim 13 disclosed) and 14). Mr Hunter did not accept as correct, the methodological approach adopted by Dr Gilmore to determining anticipation by looking to the prior art disclosures of US Patent 643 and the disclosures in that part of US Patent 643 which identify features of novelty in the invention (and ultimately the integers of the claims of that patent) so as to put the disclosures together to see and understand whether the combination of claim 13 of the patent in suit is disclosed in US Patent 643.

SBriggs says that, unremarkably, US Patent 643 discusses the prior art and then distinguishes the invention from it. It does so, in part, by depicting embodiments of the invention in drawings 7 to 13 and distinguishing the invention from the prior art depicted in drawings 1 to 6. The specification describes the shortcomings of prior art clutches manifested in variations in frictional drag due to differential radial loads at bearing surfaces of prior art clutches (see [127] and [128] of these reasons). SBriggs says that the specification teaches away from the prior art and combinations evident in the prior art. It says Mr Hunter, as a skilled addressee, is led away from the prior art configuration of a single longitudinal slot to the particular features of US Patent 643 in which novelty is claimed as determined by the integers of those claims. Mr Hunter cannot see the combination of a plurality of springs of alternate winding engaging a non-complex single longitudinal slot and key device, in any of those claims. Mr Hunter separately compares the prior art of Figures 1 to 6 with the discussion of the prior art and concludes that the integers of claim 13 are not disclosed in the prior art. In particular, the prior art does not disclose springs of alternate winding. Moreover, US Patent 643, it is said, does not claim a clutch that includes a second shaft with a single longitudinal opening with edges of that opening that selectively engage one or more of the tabs, as claim 13 of the patent in suit requires.

The method adopted by Mr Hunter might usefully lead the skilled addressee to an answer to the question of whether the integers of claim 13 are anticipated by US Patent 643. Mr Hunter has sought to find that answer by looking to the prior art disclosures. He has looked to the discussion of the invention, the assertions of novelty and the integers of the claims of US Patent 643 to see if he can find the integers of claim 13 revealed in those claims. If the answer to either inquiry conducted by Mr Hunter is yes, the method would usefully reveal anticipation. If the answer to either inquiry is no, the method may simply reflect an impermissibly restricted inquiry. In determining whether a document, in this case US Patent 643, discloses the integers of claim 13, it is legitimate to look to the whole of the document to isolate the presence or disclosure of elements of the combination of claim 13 in the prior art (and relevant drawings) and in the discussion of the advantages of the invention over the prior art, the integers of the claims recited in the patent and drawings embodying the invention. The disclosures in the patent taken as a whole may reveal to a skilled addressee, the combination of the claim in the patent in suit.

If, however, the combination is to be found in a combination of disclosures rather than a disclosed combination , the skilled addressee must see and reach the combination without calling in aid his own inventive skills or ingenuity in making the combination. Nor will the disclosures anticipate the combination of claim 13 (assuming the counter-factual) even though putting together the combination might be obvious to a person skilled in the relevant art (whether Dr Gilmore or Mr Hunter or any other skilled addressee). US Patent 643 does not disclose the combination of a plurality of springs of alternate winding engaging a non-complex single longitudinal slot and key configuration to facilitate smooth transition of rotational forces between the input and output shafts of a spring clutch. The patent addresses use of multiple springs (some of which may be reverse wound in one embodiment) to support the output load in a way that overcomes an asymmetrical application of supporting forces (that produces reaction forces at the bearing surface within the clutch) by configuring a clutch employing a multiplicity of springs so as to support the load with very nearly a pure couple of forces without producing reaction forces in the bearings as a direct result of the forces produced by the springs. The invention thus eliminates frictional drag and US Patent 643 is entirely directed to that objective. The discussion in US Patent 643 of firstly the disadvantages of prior art clutches and secondly, the manner of overcoming frictional drag by a pure couple of forces, does not disclose the combination of claim 13 of the patent in suit. To the extent that such a combination might be revealed to a person skilled in the art, such a person would need to apply an inventive step in doing so. Thus, applying the counter-factual, US Patent 643 does not anticipate the combination of claim 13 of the patent in suit. False suggestion</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Limited v Arico Trading International Pty Ltd [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1349.html</AustLII>
<text>When determining the boundaries of a claim, the specification must be read as a whole. It describes the patentee's best known method. If the language of a claim is clear and unambiguous, it is not to be rendered ambiguous, obfuscated or qualified by statements extracted from the specification as if those statements form part of the language of the claim defining the monopoly ( Flexible Steel Lacing Company v Beltreco Ltd [2000] FCA 890 ; (2000) 49 IPR 331). Although the language of the claim defines the monopoly, the claim marks out the boundary of a particular solution to a problem not solved by the prior art and thus has a context. Reference should be made to the specification to understand that context, to explain the background to the claims and to ascertain the meaning of technical terms ( Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co. v Beiersdorf (Aust) Ltd [1980] HCA 9 ; (1980) 144 CLR 253). Although the clear language of a claim should not be diluted, qualified or obfuscated by reference to the specification, unclear language used in a claim might usefully be made clear by reference to words used in the specification, in the relevant context ( Kimberly-Clark Australia Pty Ltd v Arico Trading International Pty Limited [2001] HCA 8 ; (2001) 207 CLR 1). The specification will, among other things, describe aspects of the prior art, unresolved problems in the prior art, the object the invention seeks to achieve and preferred embodiments of the invention and will recite a claim or claims staking out the patentee's exclusive ground. The Court reads that document in the logical sequence of its contentions and seeks to construe the claims, according to the words chosen in the claims, taking account of those matters, recognising that an identified embodiment or a preferred embodiment does not limit the natural language of a claim yet, the patentee may by clear language choose to limit the scope of the monopoly.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183</tocase>
<text>Adopting a purposive approach to construction of the claims does not mean that clear limitations in the scope of the monopoly contained in the language of the claims can be avoided or the reach of the monopoly extended beyond the clear limits of the language selected. A purposive approach to construction as opposed to a purely literal one will raise the question of whether persons with practical knowledge and experience of the kind of work in which the invention was intended to be used, would understand that strict compliance with the descriptive words or phrases used in a claim was intended to be an essential requirement of the invention. If so, as a matter of construction, a variant would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect on the way the invention works. That question does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material affect upon the way the invention works ( Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 ; Kirin-Amgen Inc. v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444). The construction of the language of a claim, adopted by the Court, ultimately determines infringement. The question is whether the alleged infringement is comprehended by the clear language of the claim ( Sachtler applying Catnic and PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41). Construction of the claims

The point of this discussion is that it may tell the Court something about construction of the claims. If the claims are confined to a single unitary reverse wound spring, might that integer be regarded as an inessential integer if there is no functional difference between a spring clutch that includes such a spring and a spring clutch that incorporates three separate springs in adjacent alignment reflecting alternate winding. Would persons with practical knowledge and experience in the subject matter addressed by the invention understand that strict compliance with a particular descriptive word or phrase appearing in a claim was intended by the patentee to be an essential requirement of the invention so that any variation would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect upon the working of the invention. Lord Diplock in Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd (supra) noted that such a question would not arise where the variation would in fact have a material affect upon the working of the invention. The Improver or protocol questions ( Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181) pose questions, the answers to which assist construction . That is to say, the questions test whether a reasonable person skilled in the art reading the language of the claims in context would think that the patentee was intending to confine the monopoly to the natural or primary meaning of the words selected or, alternatively, would such a person think that the patentee was intending to include within that meaning a variant of no material functional difference ( Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231).

Mr Hunter and SBriggs concede that claims1, 2, 8, 10 and 11 of the patent in suit have been anticipated by reason of figure 12 in US Patent 643 (Table A, para 38, Hunter affidavit, 6 March 2008). Figure 12 shows two helical springs of reverse winding. At column 7, line 8 of US Patent 643, a reference is made to a complex arrangement of interleaved springs which will afford the advantages of the invention. An example is given of three springs which could be interleaved and used with a housing engaging three keys placed in a particular way. At line 13 of column 7, another way is described to bring the tabs of a spring close together. The specification says this: 
 Yet another way to bring the spring tangs [another word which describes tabs of a spring] close together along the spring axis is to use two springs, one spring wound with a clockwise helix , and the other with a counterclockwise helix . FIG 12 depicts a possible spring configuration for such a spring. These springs could be used in place of springs 95 and 97 of the clutch of FIGS 10 and 11 to provide the benefit of our invention for loading in one direction. 
 [emphasis added]

The above reference suggests that two springs of reverse winding might be used in the depiction in the Figure 10 drawing. Figures 10 and 12 are Schedules 7 and 8 to these reasons.

Claim 1 of US Patent 643 is in these terms: 
 1. A spring clutch for lowering and raising a window shade comprising: 

 
 a shaft;
 at least first and second helically wound axially mounted springs having first and second ends for making frictional contact with the shaft;
 first engaging means corresponding to each of said at least first and second springs for selectively applying a tightening force to one of the said ends of each of said springs for inhibiting rotation thereof with respect to said shaft;
 second engaging means for selectively applying a loosening force to the other of the said ends of each of said springs for promoting rotation thereof with respect to said shaft;
 wherein each of said first engaging means is radially and symmetrically disposed about said shaft for substantially eliminating radial bearing forces.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kirin-Amgen Inc. v Hoechst v Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444</tocase>
<text>Adopting a purposive approach to construction of the claims does not mean that clear limitations in the scope of the monopoly contained in the language of the claims can be avoided or the reach of the monopoly extended beyond the clear limits of the language selected. A purposive approach to construction as opposed to a purely literal one will raise the question of whether persons with practical knowledge and experience of the kind of work in which the invention was intended to be used, would understand that strict compliance with the descriptive words or phrases used in a claim was intended to be an essential requirement of the invention. If so, as a matter of construction, a variant would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect on the way the invention works. That question does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material affect upon the way the invention works ( Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 ; Kirin-Amgen Inc. v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444). The construction of the language of a claim, adopted by the Court, ultimately determines infringement. The question is whether the alleged infringement is comprehended by the clear language of the claim ( Sachtler applying Catnic and PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41). Construction of the claims</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/344.html</AustLII>
<text>Adopting a purposive approach to construction of the claims does not mean that clear limitations in the scope of the monopoly contained in the language of the claims can be avoided or the reach of the monopoly extended beyond the clear limits of the language selected. A purposive approach to construction as opposed to a purely literal one will raise the question of whether persons with practical knowledge and experience of the kind of work in which the invention was intended to be used, would understand that strict compliance with the descriptive words or phrases used in a claim was intended to be an essential requirement of the invention. If so, as a matter of construction, a variant would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect on the way the invention works. That question does not arise where the variant would in fact have a material affect upon the way the invention works ( Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd [1982] RPC 183 ; Kirin-Amgen Inc. v Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd (2004) 64 IPR 444). The construction of the language of a claim, adopted by the Court, ultimately determines infringement. The question is whether the alleged infringement is comprehended by the clear language of the claim ( Sachtler applying Catnic and PhotoCure ASA v Queen's University at Kingston [2005] FCA 344 ; (2005) 216 ALR 41). Construction of the claims</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181</tocase>
<text>The point of this discussion is that it may tell the Court something about construction of the claims. If the claims are confined to a single unitary reverse wound spring, might that integer be regarded as an inessential integer if there is no functional difference between a spring clutch that includes such a spring and a spring clutch that incorporates three separate springs in adjacent alignment reflecting alternate winding. Would persons with practical knowledge and experience in the subject matter addressed by the invention understand that strict compliance with a particular descriptive word or phrase appearing in a claim was intended by the patentee to be an essential requirement of the invention so that any variation would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect upon the working of the invention. Lord Diplock in Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd (supra) noted that such a question would not arise where the variation would in fact have a material affect upon the working of the invention. The Improver or protocol questions ( Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181) pose questions, the answers to which assist construction . That is to say, the questions test whether a reasonable person skilled in the art reading the language of the claims in context would think that the patentee was intending to confine the monopoly to the natural or primary meaning of the words selected or, alternatively, would such a person think that the patentee was intending to include within that meaning a variant of no material functional difference ( Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231).

Although it is true that the initial affidavit of Dr Gilmore made no reference to the points of differentiation, by reference to questions of misalignment of tabs, in the functional operation of a spring clutch incorporating three separate springs as compared with the functional operation of a spring clutch of claim 13 incorporating a single unitary reverse wound spring, the evidence of Mr Hunter and Dr Gilmore in its totality, as persons skilled in the relevant art, is such that it is simply not possible to conclude that a variation from the language of the claims of the patent in suit constituted by the use of three separate adjacent springs loaded onto shaft 1 in the manner of Exhibit 1, has no material affect upon the way the invention of claim 13 works, for the purposes of question 1 of the Improver questions. If two experts emblematic of persons skilled in the relevant art (at least for the purposes of these proceedings), cannot agree that a spring clutch incorporating three separate adjacent springs positioned on shaft 1 of a spring clutch in the manner of Exhibit 1, functions in a way which would reflect no material affect upon the evident functionality of a spring clutch incorporating a single unitary spring of reverse winding, the Court cannot be satisfied that the variation has no material affect upon functionality. The question is not to be resolved by simply accepting one person skilled in the art over another but by approaching construction taking account of the total evidence of those skilled in the art. The weight of the evidence having regard to Dr Gilmore's evidence is such that it cannot be said or found that no material affect by the use of the variant is established.

That being so, Improver questions 2 and 3 do not arise. Even if I accept entirely the evidence of Mr Hunter and reject the evidence of Dr Gilmore on this aspect of the case (thus answering Improver question 1, yes) and assume or accept that the variant of adopting three adjacent separate springs of alternate winding was obvious at the date of publication of the patent in suit to a reader skilled in the relevant art (thus answering the second Improver question, yes), the answer to the third Improver question must necessarily be, no. Here, the patentee has selected language that defines a monopoly in terms of a single spring engaging a non-complex single longitudinal slot and key configuration of two shafts (coaxial with a first shaft) to achieve identified advantages of the invention. A single spring is essential to the claims. It is the integer which enables the spring clutch to discharge its clutching function. A skilled reader would understand from the language of the claims in the context of the specification that the patentee intended that strict compliance with the primary meaning of the language of the claims was an essential requirement of the invention. Moreover, Mr Hunter acknowledges that multiple springs can work in a spring clutch when they are all wound in the same direction.

Having adopted the construction of the claims reflected in these reasons, that construction determines infringement. The Uniline spring clutch does not incorporate a single unitary spring of reverse winding and thus no infringement arises. The implications of claim 14</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/980.html</AustLII>
<text>The point of this discussion is that it may tell the Court something about construction of the claims. If the claims are confined to a single unitary reverse wound spring, might that integer be regarded as an inessential integer if there is no functional difference between a spring clutch that includes such a spring and a spring clutch that incorporates three separate springs in adjacent alignment reflecting alternate winding. Would persons with practical knowledge and experience in the subject matter addressed by the invention understand that strict compliance with a particular descriptive word or phrase appearing in a claim was intended by the patentee to be an essential requirement of the invention so that any variation would fall outside the monopoly claimed even though it could have no material affect upon the working of the invention. Lord Diplock in Catnic Components Ltd v Hill &amp; Smith Ltd (supra) noted that such a question would not arise where the variation would in fact have a material affect upon the working of the invention. The Improver or protocol questions ( Improver Corporation v Remington Consumer Products Ltd [1990] FSR 181) pose questions, the answers to which assist construction . That is to say, the questions test whether a reasonable person skilled in the art reading the language of the claims in context would think that the patentee was intending to confine the monopoly to the natural or primary meaning of the words selected or, alternatively, would such a person think that the patentee was intending to include within that meaning a variant of no material functional difference ( Root Quality Pty Ltd v Root Control Technologies Pty Ltd [2000] FCA 980 ; (2000) 177 ALR 231).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385</tocase>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/139.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/178.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2009/18.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles to be applied in construing the claims have been reviewed extensively in a number of recent authorities ( Sachtler GmbH &amp; Co. KG v R E Miller Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 788 ; (2005) 221 ALR 373 ; (2005) 65 IPR 605 per Bennett J ( Sachtler ); Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd [2005] FCAFC 220 ; (2005) 224 ALR 168 ; (2006) 67 IPR 230 , per Wilcox, Branson and Bennett JJ; K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd v Insta Image Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 481 ; (2007) 71 IPR 615 per Kiefel J; Clorox Australia Pty Ltd v International Consolidated Business Pty Ltd (2006) 68 IPR 254 per Stone J; Nufarm Ltd v Jurox Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 178 ; (2008) 75 IPR 341 per Middleton J; Ranbaxy Australia Pty Ltd v Warner-Lambert Co. LLC (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1787 ; (2007) 71 IPR 46 per Young J; Pfizer Overseas Pharmaceuticals v Eli Lilly &amp; Co. (2006) 68 IPR 1 per French and Lindgren JJ and Crennan J agreeing). I have had particular regard to the decision of the Full Court in Pfizer , the statement of ten principles of construction identified by Sheppard J in D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1988) 13 IPR 385 at 400, the judgment of the Full Court in Insta Image Pty Ltd v K D Kanopy Australasia Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 139 ; (2008) 78 IPR 20 at [82] , the judgment of the Full Court in Kinabalu Investments Pty Ltd v Barron &amp; Rawson Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 178 at [44] and [45] and the judgment of the Full Court in PAC Mining Pty Ltd v Esco Corporation [2009] FCAFC 18 at [26] to [29]. As Lindgren J observed in Breville Pty Ltd v Warehouse Group (Australia) Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1893 ; (2006) 67 IPR 576 at [41] , the Court is frequently called upon to refer to the principles which govern the construction of claims and "on each new occasion it seems that the same authorities plus the last preceding one are reviewed. And so the list lengthens." I propose to simply state the propositions to be applied derived from these authorities and some others in construing claim 13 of the patent in suit and any claim upon which it rests.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lockwood Security Products Pty Limited v Doric Products Pty Limited [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/58.html</AustLII>
<text>Uniline says that if the claims of the patent, properly construed, include within the monopoly a spring clutch comprised of a plurality of springs with reverse windings and tabs, such claims are not fairly based upon disclosures in the body of the specification. Uniline says that the invention as claimed by the terms of the monopoly might well be narrower than the disclosures contained in the specification but the claims cannot travel beyond the disclosures in the body of the specification. Uniline asks, consistent with Lockwood Security Products Pty Limited v Doric Products Pty Limited [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 , whether there has been a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification of that which is claimed or, put another way, whether the claims travel beyond the disclosures in the specification ( Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co. Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236). I have construed the claims to require a single unitary reverse wound spring as an essential integer. Those claims so construed are consistent with the disclosures in the specification. If, however, an assumption is made that the proper construction of the claims brings within the scope of the monopoly a plurality of springs of alternate winding, do the claims travel beyond the specification? The specification contemplates an invention answering the problems of the prior art by providing for a bi-directional spring clutch that confers the advantages of a single spring engaging a non-complex slot and key engagement mechanism or control means. The specification plainly discloses the use of multiple springs sequentially engaged in prior art spring clutches by a complex configuration of openings and barriers as an aspect of a prior art bi-directional clutch. If the counter-factual hypothesis is adopted that the claims include use of a plurality of springs, that hypothesis would seem to follow necessarily from an acceptance of the proposition that the object of the invention, properly construed, is to avoid a plurality of springs in combination with a complex configuration of openings and barriers. Therefore, on that hypothesis of construction, a plurality of springs engaging a slot and key control means (that is, a non-complex control means) is sufficiently disclosed by the specification by reason of the description of the object of the invention and the claims are thus, upon the counter-factual, fairly based. However, neither the object nor the claims contemplate a plurality of springs as an integer of the claimed invention. If the object of the invention is construed to require the presence of the two identified advantages (within the invention and thus the monopoly), claims which, upon the counter-factual hypothesis, include a plurality of springs of alternate winding, travel beyond the disclosure. Inutility</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co. Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/23.html</AustLII>
<text>Uniline says that if the claims of the patent, properly construed, include within the monopoly a spring clutch comprised of a plurality of springs with reverse windings and tabs, such claims are not fairly based upon disclosures in the body of the specification. Uniline says that the invention as claimed by the terms of the monopoly might well be narrower than the disclosures contained in the specification but the claims cannot travel beyond the disclosures in the body of the specification. Uniline asks, consistent with Lockwood Security Products Pty Limited v Doric Products Pty Limited [2004] HCA 58 ; (2004) 217 CLR 274 , whether there has been a real and reasonably clear disclosure in the body of the specification of that which is claimed or, put another way, whether the claims travel beyond the disclosures in the specification ( Olin Corporation v Super Cartridge Co. Pty Ltd [1977] HCA 23 ; (1977) 180 CLR 236). I have construed the claims to require a single unitary reverse wound spring as an essential integer. Those claims so construed are consistent with the disclosures in the specification. If, however, an assumption is made that the proper construction of the claims brings within the scope of the monopoly a plurality of springs of alternate winding, do the claims travel beyond the specification? The specification contemplates an invention answering the problems of the prior art by providing for a bi-directional spring clutch that confers the advantages of a single spring engaging a non-complex slot and key engagement mechanism or control means. The specification plainly discloses the use of multiple springs sequentially engaged in prior art spring clutches by a complex configuration of openings and barriers as an aspect of a prior art bi-directional clutch. If the counter-factual hypothesis is adopted that the claims include use of a plurality of springs, that hypothesis would seem to follow necessarily from an acceptance of the proposition that the object of the invention, properly construed, is to avoid a plurality of springs in combination with a complex configuration of openings and barriers. Therefore, on that hypothesis of construction, a plurality of springs engaging a slot and key control means (that is, a non-complex control means) is sufficiently disclosed by the specification by reason of the description of the object of the invention and the claims are thus, upon the counter-factual, fairly based. However, neither the object nor the claims contemplate a plurality of springs as an integer of the claimed invention. If the object of the invention is construed to require the presence of the two identified advantages (within the invention and thus the monopoly), claims which, upon the counter-factual hypothesis, include a plurality of springs of alternate winding, travel beyond the disclosure. Inutility</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin Engineering Co. &amp; Anor (1989) 91 ALR 513</tocase>
<text>The question to be determined is whether US Patent 643 discloses to a skilled addressee with common general knowledge of the relevant art, each of the integers demanded by the claims defining the monopoly ( Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd (supra) at [128] to [152]) and in that sense, the test of anticipation is the reverse infringement test. Would use of a spring clutch in accordance with the disclosures in US Patent 643 infringe claim 13? The skilled addressee must be able to read and understand the document as disclosing all of the integers of the monopoly in the combination without the exercise of "inventive ingenuity and the taking of an inventive step" ( Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin Engineering Co. &amp; Anor (1989) 91 ALR 513 , per Gummow J at 531 and 532) and without deducing an integer as part of a combination claim, by taking an obvious and non-inventive step to reach the combination. The disclosure in the document must be clear in the sense that the language of the document must provide unmistakable instruction to the addressee as to how the combination claimed is used, although the language of the disclosure need not be that of the claim. An anticipation of a claim is not determined merely by a textual comparison of the disclosure and the claim. The language of the disclosure might well be different to the language of the claim but the disclosure must teach the skilled addressee the invention (the combination of integers) and its use ( Pfizer (supra) at [311] to [324]; Evans Medical Ltd Patent [1998] RPC 517 at 576; Nicaro Holdings (supra))</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Evans Medical Ltd Patent [1998] RPC 517</tocase>
<text>The question to be determined is whether US Patent 643 discloses to a skilled addressee with common general knowledge of the relevant art, each of the integers demanded by the claims defining the monopoly ( Fresenius Medical Care Australia Pty Ltd v Gambro Pty Ltd (supra) at [128] to [152]) and in that sense, the test of anticipation is the reverse infringement test. Would use of a spring clutch in accordance with the disclosures in US Patent 643 infringe claim 13? The skilled addressee must be able to read and understand the document as disclosing all of the integers of the monopoly in the combination without the exercise of "inventive ingenuity and the taking of an inventive step" ( Nicaro Holdings Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin Engineering Co. &amp; Anor (1989) 91 ALR 513 , per Gummow J at 531 and 532) and without deducing an integer as part of a combination claim, by taking an obvious and non-inventive step to reach the combination. The disclosure in the document must be clear in the sense that the language of the document must provide unmistakable instruction to the addressee as to how the combination claimed is used, although the language of the disclosure need not be that of the claim. An anticipation of a claim is not determined merely by a textual comparison of the disclosure and the claim. The language of the disclosure might well be different to the language of the claim but the disclosure must teach the skilled addressee the invention (the combination of integers) and its use ( Pfizer (supra) at [311] to [324]; Evans Medical Ltd Patent [1998] RPC 517 at 576; Nicaro Holdings (supra))</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Prestige Group (Australia) Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1990) 26 FCR 197</tocase>
<text>The final ground of revocation involves a contention that SBriggs obtained the patent by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation ([11], s 138(3)(d) of the Patents Act ) and that the amendment to the patent ([12], [17], [18], [56] and [57]; s 138(3)(e) of the Patents Act ) was also obtained by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation. The question is whether the conduct of SBriggs said to bear the character required by the section, materially contributed to the Commissioner's decision to grant the patent or amend the claims. It is sufficient if the conduct is a material inducing factor which led to either of those outcomes ( Prestige Group (Australia) Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1990) 26 FCR 197 ; Pfizer (supra); JMVB Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 68). Sections 138(3)(d) and 138 (3)(e) do not require proof of a deliberate intention on the part of the applicant for the patent (or amendment) to deceive the Commissioner ( Pfizer ). If the representation is based upon a belief, it is relevant to consider whether the belief is false or not held reasonably ( NSI Dental Pty Ltd v University of Melbourne (2006) 69 IPR 542).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>JMVB Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1474 ; (2005) 67 IPR 68)</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1474.html</AustLII>
<text>The final ground of revocation involves a contention that SBriggs obtained the patent by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation ([11], s 138(3)(d) of the Patents Act ) and that the amendment to the patent ([12], [17], [18], [56] and [57]; s 138(3)(e) of the Patents Act ) was also obtained by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation. The question is whether the conduct of SBriggs said to bear the character required by the section, materially contributed to the Commissioner's decision to grant the patent or amend the claims. It is sufficient if the conduct is a material inducing factor which led to either of those outcomes ( Prestige Group (Australia) Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1990) 26 FCR 197 ; Pfizer (supra); JMVB Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 68). Sections 138(3)(d) and 138 (3)(e) do not require proof of a deliberate intention on the part of the applicant for the patent (or amendment) to deceive the Commissioner ( Pfizer ). If the representation is based upon a belief, it is relevant to consider whether the belief is false or not held reasonably ( NSI Dental Pty Ltd v University of Melbourne (2006) 69 IPR 542).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NSI Dental Pty Ltd v University of Melbourne (2006) 69 IPR 542</tocase>
<text>The final ground of revocation involves a contention that SBriggs obtained the patent by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation ([11], s 138(3)(d) of the Patents Act ) and that the amendment to the patent ([12], [17], [18], [56] and [57]; s 138(3)(e) of the Patents Act ) was also obtained by fraud, false suggestion or misrepresentation. The question is whether the conduct of SBriggs said to bear the character required by the section, materially contributed to the Commissioner's decision to grant the patent or amend the claims. It is sufficient if the conduct is a material inducing factor which led to either of those outcomes ( Prestige Group (Australia) Pty Ltd v Dart Industries Inc. (1990) 26 FCR 197 ; Pfizer (supra); JMVB Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd (2005) 67 IPR 68). Sections 138(3)(d) and 138 (3)(e) do not require proof of a deliberate intention on the part of the applicant for the patent (or amendment) to deceive the Commissioner ( Pfizer ). If the representation is based upon a belief, it is relevant to consider whether the belief is false or not held reasonably ( NSI Dental Pty Ltd v University of Melbourne (2006) 69 IPR 542).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c27">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ICI Chemicals &amp; Polymers Ltd v Lubrizol Corporation Inc. (2000) 106 FCR 214</tocase>
<text>As to the second representation concerning the amendments, the statements in the documents dated 24 October 2006 concern the effect of the prior art. A statement made by an applicant in good faith to the Commissioner concerning the effect of the prior art is unlikely to provide a basis for concluding that such a statement of opinion is false, when that opinion is subsequently shown to be incorrect ( ICI Chemicals &amp; Polymers Ltd v Lubrizol Corporation Inc. (2000) 106 FCR 214). A statement made expressing an opinion about the relationship or otherwise between disclosures in the prior art and changes to the scope of the monopoly defining the claims, so as to address differentiation of the invention from elements of the prior art, simply reflects a debate between the Commissioner and the applicant about the scope of the claims and the effect of proposed changes to the language of the claims judged against the prior art. Statements about those matters are simply, as in this case, argumentative statements going to matters of opinion about which minds might, in good faith, differ. There is no suggestion of bad faith on the part of SBriggs. The suggestion in this case is that SBriggs proposed an amendment which had the effect of impermissibly broadening the scope of claims 1 to 13 by reference to the express limitation contained in claim 14. Claim 14 is limited in its terms to a spring of unitary construction. Claims 1 to 13 are not said to bear an inclusive construction of multiple springs of alternate winding as a matter of inference from claim 14. They are said to bear that construction for the reasons earlier identified. The amendments proposed by SBriggs either narrow the scope of two claims to better differentiate the invention from the prior art or not. Whether that statement is true or correct is simply a matter of debate between the applicant and the Commissioner. As Mr Hunter says, claim 14 adds nothing to claims 1 to 13. No false statement or misrepresentation arises out of putting a view of the effect of the changes.

Accordingly, declarations will be made that threats of patent infringement proceedings made by SBriggs on 4 April 2007 by its solicitors and a further letter by its solicitors dated 16 July 2007 are unjustifiable. SBriggs shall be restrained from further threats of patent infringement. The Amended Cross-Claim of SBriggs by which relief is sought for infringement of claim 13 of the patent in suit, is to be dismissed. The Amended Further Cross-Claim by Uniline by which revocation of the patent in suit is sought, which only arises if infringement is found, is to be dismissed. I certify that the preceding one hundred and forty-four (144) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 16 March 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr Crowe SC and Mr Cooper 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: DLA Phillips Fox 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr Musgrave 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Mallesons Stephen Jaques 
 Date of Hearing: 14, 15, 16 and 17 April 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 16 March 2009 
 
 SCHEDULE 1 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 2 
 
 SCHEDULE 3 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 4 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 5 
 
 SCHEDULE 6 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 7 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 8 
 
 
 SCHEDULE 9 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/222.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>