<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ascot Four Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 28 (23 January 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/28.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v CSR Limited (1991) ATPR 41-076</tocase>
<text>12 It is necessary to note these facts because the prosecutor has urged that the factors relevant to penalty are those outlined by French J (as he then was) in Trade Practices Commission v CSR Limited (1991) ATPR 41-076 at 52,152 ( TPC v CSR Limited ). The defendant contended that those factors should be applied with some caution, because (it was argued) TPC v CSR Limited was decided before the introduction of Pt 1B of the Crimes Act and involved a civil pecuniary penalty imposed for contraventions of ss 46 and 47 (misuse of market power and exclusive dealing) in Pt IV of the TP Act for restrictive trade practices, rather than for contravention of a consumer protection provision of the TP Act in Pt V, or for present purposes now Pt VC. Part VC Offences was introduced into the TP Act by the Treasury Legislation Amendment (Application of Criminal Code ) Act (No 1) 2001 (Cth).

13 The judgment in TPC v CSR Limited was given on 20 December 1990 but concerned conduct engaged in from 1 May 1998 and until 5 September 1990 when consent injunctive orders were made. It is clear that the penalty imposed in that case was imposed in respect of contraventions of Pt IV of the TP Act, and was determined under s 76 of the TP Act as a civil pecuniary penalty. That does not make the observations of French J in that case irrelevant, but I accept the submission on behalf of the defendant that they should not be the starting point for determining the appropriate penalty in this matter. In any event, I do not think that the factors identified by French J in TPC v CSR Limited in any significant respect are different from those now specified in s 16A(2) of the Crimes Act . Section 16A(2)(a) of the Crimes Act directs attention to the nature and circumstances of the offence. That encompasses certain of the factors identified by French J. Section 16A(2) of the Crimes Act directs attention to the injury, loss or damage resulting from the offence. That too is a matter to which French J referred. Sections 16A(2)(f) , (g) and (h) of the Crimes Act direct attention to the contrition of the offender, the cooperation with the law enforcement agency, and whether there has been a plea of guilty to the charge in respect of the offence. That, in general terms, is encompassed also within the factors mentioned by French J. Sections 16A(2)(k) and (m) of the Crimes Act direct attention to the need to ensure that the person is adequately punished and to the personal elements of the offence. I think those factors are also encompassed within the factors identified by French J where he refers to the size of the contravening company and its degree of power in the market (not a matter directly relevant to a contravention of s 75AZC(1)(g) of the TP Act). Section 16A(2)(j) of the Crimes Act directs attention to the deterrent effect of the sentence upon the offender. That too was noted by French J. In certain circumstances, the matters referred to by French J will in fact fall into subsets of the matters listed in s 16A(2) of the Crimes Act .

14 I propose first to consider the factors specifically mentioned in s 16A(2) of the Crimes Act which are relevant in the circumstances. There is another relevant matter, namely, deterrence. Deterrence has two elements, namely specific deterrence of the offender and general deterrence in the community. It is also necessary to impose a penalty of sufficient magnitude to signal to the community the significance of the offending and to ensure that those who operate in a like commercial environment would be reminded of the consequences of contravention of the like provisions. The object of the TP Act is "to enhance the welfare of Australians through the promotion of competition and fair trading and provision for consumer protection". The defendant's conduct, as it acknowledged, was both serious and inconsistent with that object. The penalty imposed must be such as to reinforce in the mind of the community the consequences of non-compliance with the relevant legislative prescription as to how that object is to be achieved.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ascot Four [2008] FCA 1295</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1295.html</AustLII>
<text>1 On 21 August 2008 I found the defendant guilty of 11 counts of making a false or misleading representation about the price of goods, contrary to s 75AZC(1)(g) of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (the TP Act): Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Ascot Four [2008] FCA 1295. The question of the appropriate penalty to be imposed for those contraventions was then deferred. That matter has now been addressed.

2 Each contravention related to the advertising of the price of jewellery items in the defendant's 2005 Christmas Sale Catalogue (the catalogue). There were some 2.6 million copies of the catalogue. Generally there was a depiction of the jewellery item, a printed description of the item, a printed price in black print which had been struck through (the strike-through price) and a different and highlighted price printed in red and in a larger print (the sale price). I found that by that conduct the defendant represented to consumers or potential purchasers of the 11 jewellery items that, during the sale period from 24 November 2005 to 24 December 2005, the consumer would be saving the difference between the sale price and the strike-through price, or that there was a group of ordinary and reasonable members amongst prospective purchasers of those items who would understand the sale catalogue in that way in respect of the jewellery items.

3 In fact, none of the 11 jewellery items had been sold at the strike-through price. All but the Count 1 item had been offered for sale at least from 1 July 2005, and the Count 1 item had been offered for sale only from 24 November 2005. In each instance, the jewellery item had been ticketed at the strike-through price, at least for the period from 1 July 2005 (apart from the Count 1 item), but the highest price at which each of those items of jewellery had been sold over that period was significantly less than the ticketed price. The explanation given by the defendant is that the defendant operates in a "discount jewellery market" and its staff are encouraged to offer competitive price discounts to customers if that is required to secure a sale. At least in respect of the 11 jewellery items, there had been (over the period covered by the evidence) no sales at the ticketed price, and as noted all sales had been at a substantial reduction from the ticketed price.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Lowe v The Queen [1984] HCA 46 ; (1984) 154 CLR 606</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1984/46.html</AustLII>
<text>15 I have also had my attention drawn to some other cases involving imposition of penalty relating to comparative price advertising where the TP Act has been contravened. I accept that I should be cautious in drawing too much from such cases. Necessarily, the contravening conduct will differ in nature, quality and effect, as will the circumstances of the individual contravention from one case to another. Although consistency in penalty is clearly important and is desirable to ensure a rational and fair system of justice (see Lowe v The Queen [1984] HCA 46 ; (1984) 154 CLR 606 at 610-1), it is necessary to consider the individual circumstances of the contraventions and of the contravener. Nevertheless, in the manner described below, I have derived some assistance by looking at cases in which the TP Act has been contravened by comparative price advertising representations and the penalty applied in those cases.

16 I referred to the nature and circumstances of the offence in the primary judgment, and briefly above. I will not repeat that, save to note that at material times, the defendant was a proprietor of a chain of retail jewellery stores operating under the name of "Zamel's". It operated 69 retail stores throughout South Australia, Victoria, Western Australia, Tasmania and the Australian Capital Territory. The 2005 Christmas Sale Catalogue was distributed across each of those regions.

17 The catalogue was issued centrally, that is, through the defendant's head office. It, and the elements of it which contravened s 75AZC(1)(g) of the TP Act, were not the consequence of some local or store-based conduct. In fact, two of the defendant's directors were responsible for authorising the price of the jewellery items offered and advertised for sale, and for the issue of the catalogue.

31 Although parity of penalty should be achieved, so that similar contraventions of the TP Act attract similar penalties, that of course depends upon the individual circumstances of each case. Consistency is desirable, as it flows from a rational and fair system of justice: Lowe v The Queen [1984] HCA 46 ; (1984) 154 CLR 606 at 610-1 per Mason J.

32 I was referred by senior counsel for the prosecutor and senior counsel for the defendant to a number of cases in which penalties were imposed for misleading and deceptive conduct in relation to comparative price advertising.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Sest v Copperart Pty Ltd (1989) ATPR 40-945</tocase>
<text>33 Sest v Copperart Pty Ltd (1989) ATPR 40-945 concerned nine offences by three related defendants contrary to s 53(e) of the TP Act. There was, in three sales campaigns, comparative price advertising in a television advertisement one advertisement during each sales campaign where the "was" price was either an artificially inflated recommended retail price or a fictitious regular price, so the claimed savings were significantly overstated. The sentencing judge found the defendants were aware of the falsity of each of the representations. The defendants pleaded guilty. Section 79(2) of the TP Act did not apply, so separate penalties were imposed. On the three counts against the principal offender, it was fined $30,000, $20,000 and $25,000 (a total of $75,000) and ordered to pay the costs of the prosecutor. The maximum fine for each offence at the time was $100,000. The principal points of difference from the present circumstances are clear from the recital of those matters, although there were of course other factual differences of degree. The sentencing judge also was satisfied that, in applying the totality principle, the overall penalty imposed was not so high as to be oppressive.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Cue Design Ltd (1996) 85 A Crim R 500</tocase>
<text>34 
 
 Trade Practices Commission v Cue Design Ltd (1996) 85 A Crim R 500 concerned 30 offences contrary to s 53(e) of the TP Act to which the defendants had pleaded guilty. A large retail chain had offered certain garments for sale by dual priced swing tags, with the higher price crossed out; the higher price had not been one at which the garment had been offered for sale. There was no widespread advertising campaign; the contravening conduct occurred only by the in-store price tags. The contraventions attracted one penalty only, by reason of s 79(2) of the TP Act and s 4K(4) of the Crimes Act . The sentencing judge regarded the sales strategy as widespread, and the contraventions as serious. The maximum penalty was $200,000. A penalty of $37,500 was imposed against each of the defendants, making a total of $75,000. As the two defendants were related, the Court treated the contraventions as being by one offender, and imposed on each defendant a penalty equal to half of the whole intended penalty. Again, these are obviously points of difference from the present circumstances, some of which are evident from the above brief description.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Allans Music Group Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1552</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1552.html</AustLII>
<text>35 Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Allans Music Group Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1552 also concerned a prosecution under s 53(e) of the TP Act. The defendant pleaded guilty to nine charges, and cooperated fully in the inquiry into the contraventions. The defendant was a retailer of musical instruments and associated products. The contravening conduct occurred through a Christmas sale catalogue, of which there were 750,000 copies distributed in areas relevant to the defendant's six stores in Melbourne (2), Sydney, Brisbane, Adelaide and Ballarat. The catalogue offered the items the subject of the nine charges for sale at a "was"/"now" price, but had not sold any of the six items at the "was" price. The defendant, since the offending conduct, had implemented a detailed trade practices compliance program. The sentencing judge imposed one penalty of $80,000 pursuant to s 79(2) of the TP Act. At the time the maximum penalty was $200,000. As appears, there are significant similarities at a general level between the circumstances of that case, and the present circumstances. By contrast with the position of the present defendant is the level of cooperation with the ACCC and the guilty plea, whereas here the cooperation was somewhat later in coming and there was no guilty plea although the defendant cooperated in the presentation of evidence and confined its defence to, in effect, legal contentions based on the uncontested facts. That defendant also acted perhaps in a little more structured a way to ensure ongoing compliance with the TP Act, but I do not consider that difference is of much moment, as the present defendant agreed to abandon the (then potentially) impugned conduct and has since ceased to trade as a jeweller, having sold its business. There are obvious factual differences: the relative number of stores, the relative number of catalogues, the relative number of sales of the items the subject of the offending conduct, the relative cost of the advertised items (as overall, and not surprisingly, the cost of the jewellery items was much less than of musical instruments) and (as the prosecutor pointed out) the relative difference between the strike-through price and the sale price and so the suggested saving as a percentage of the strike-through price.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Carrerabenz Diamond Industries Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1103</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1103.html</AustLII>
<text>36 Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Carrerabenz Diamond Industries Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1103 concerned six counts of contraventions of s 75AZC(1)(g) of the TP Act by six separate newspaper advertisements in a daily newspaper circulating in Melbourne, Sydney (2), Perth (2) and Adelaide. Those advertisements offered in all 25 items of diamond jewellery at a "usual mark . price"" and a "crazy price". The defendant did not retail its products from established stores in those cities. During the trial, that defendant pleaded guilty to those charges, acknowledging that none of those items had previously been offered for sale at the "usual mark . price". A multiplier was used to the wholesale or acquisition price to arrive at the "usual mark . price" and the sentencing judge accepted as a mitigating factor that comparable items were in fact retailed at two locations at comparable prices to the "usual mark . price". A penalty of $220,000 was imposed, under s 4K(4) of the Crimes Act , having regard to what his Honour described as a "uniqueness about this case". The maximum penalty for a contravention was the same as that presently applicable.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wong v The Queen [2001] HCA 64 ; (2001) 207 CLR 584</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/64.html</AustLII>
<text>37 In Wong v The Queen [2001] HCA 64 ; (2001) 207 CLR 584 , Gaudron, Gummow and Hayne JJ at 611-2 re-affirmed the need for a sentencing judge to balance many different and conflicting elements to reach an appropriate sentence. The balancing exercise must take account of all of the circumstances of the offence and of the offender. I have undertaken that process.

38 In the result, in my view, the appropriate penalty to be imposed on the defendant on the counts (in respect of which as I indicated earlier I would impose a conviction) is the total sum of $380,000. I also order the defendant to pay the costs of the prosecutor.

39 There will be recorded a conviction against the defendant on each count. On the 11 counts collectively the defendant is ordered to pay a penalty of $380,000. The defendant is to pay that penalty within two calendar months of the date of these orders. Leave is given to the defendant within 21 days to apply to vary that period. The defendant is also ordered to pay the prosecutor's costs of the prosecution.

 I certify that the preceding thirty-nine (39) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Mansfield. 


 Associate:

Dated: 23 January 2009

 Counsel for the Plaintiff: Mr M Griffin QC and Mr R Perrotta 
 
 Solicitor for the Plaintiff: Commonwealth Director of Public Prosecutions 
 
 Counsel for the Defendant: Mr M Livesey QC and Mr I White 
 
 Solicitor for the Defendant: Fisher Jeffries 

 Date of Hearing: 23 December 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 23 January 2009 

 

 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/28.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>