<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZMMP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (Corrigendum dated 18 March 2009) [2009] FCA 233 (17 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/233.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen (1984) 3 FCR 344</tocase>
<text>In Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen (1984) 3 FCR 344 , the Court indicated that there were five indicia which ought to be addressed in determining whether relief ought to be given: 
 (a) Applications for an extension of time are not to be granted unless it is proper to do so; the legislative time limits are not to be ignored.
 (b) There must be some acceptable explanation for the delay.
 (c) Any prejudice to the respondent in defending the proceedings, caused by the delay, is a material factor militating against the grant of an extension.
 (d) The mere absence of prejudice to the respondent is not enough to justify the grant of an extension.
 (e) The merits of the substantial application are to be taken into account in considering whether an extension is to be granted.

The explanation for the delay is somewhat perfunctory and incomplete. As I have already noticed, it remains unclear whether the applicant was put on notice that the notice of appeal needed to be filed by 28 November. Counsel's letter to the applicant's solicitor put the solicitor on notice that there was a degree of urgency about the matter but that seems not to have been appreciated by the solicitor who swore his affidavit on 9 December 2008 but did not lodge the application for this extension until 17 December 2008. There is no prejudice to the respondent but as the Court said in Hunter Valley Developments Pty Ltd v Cohen 3 FCR 344 the mere absence of prejudice is not enough to justify the grant of an extension.

It seems to me that whether or not an extension of time should be granted in this application will be determined by reference to the merits of the appeal to which I will now turn.

The applicant was born on 7 April 1974 in the Archeng District, Harbin City, Heilongjiang Province in China. He was educated between 1981 and 1993, having studied at a technical school in the last three years of his schooling. In March 1994 he was employed by Archeng Water Company and worked for that company for more than 13 years. During this period of employment he studied for Business Management at Harbin Economic Cadre Management College.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187</tocase>
<text>In Jess v Scott (1986) 12 FCR 187 , the Full Court said that special reasons need to be shown why the appeal should be permitted to proceed. The Court explained that special reasons in that context was meant to distinguish the case under consideration from the usual course according to which the time is 21 days.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541</tocase>
<text>The applicant's contention as to the construction in s 424AA has been considered and rejected by other members of the Court in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 (Cowdroy J), SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701 (Edmonds J), SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541 (Middleton J), SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 (Gilmour J) and SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83 (Jagot J). Although the reasons in those cases may not be as these reasons, I agree in the results.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/83.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant's contention as to the construction in s 424AA has been considered and rejected by other members of the Court in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 (Cowdroy J), SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701 (Edmonds J), SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541 (Middleton J), SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 (Gilmour J) and SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83 (Jagot J). Although the reasons in those cases may not be as these reasons, I agree in the results.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZLTC v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FMCA 384</tocase>
<text>The Federal Magistrate concluded that the applicant's submission was to particularise and expand on information which the Tribunal had paraphrased or summarised in what it put to the applicant. He concluded that whilst the Tribunal could have put what was said to be what should have been put, the Tribunal could not be criticised for summarising the information in the way that it did. For those reasons, the Federal Magistrate concluded that even if the Tribunal had an obligation to give information pursuant to s 424AA(b)(i) that it did not breach that obligation. However, the Federal Magistrate also concluded that the information in question was independent country information which the Tribunal had no obligation to notify to the applicant. He followed a decision of Cowdroy J in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 in which his Honour concluded that the exclusions contained in s 424A(3) applied with equal force to s 424AA. The Federal Magistrate concluded that that decision stood for the proposition that independent country information did not have to be provided to an applicant under s 424A(1) and s 424AA. The Federal Magistrate analysed for himself the two sections and came to the same conclusion as Cowdroy J and, in doing so, disagreed with a decision of Driver FM in SZLTC v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FMCA 384 to the contrary.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1330.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant's contention as to the construction in s 424AA has been considered and rejected by other members of the Court in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 (Cowdroy J), SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701 (Edmonds J), SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541 (Middleton J), SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 (Gilmour J) and SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83 (Jagot J). Although the reasons in those cases may not be as these reasons, I agree in the results.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1270.html</AustLII>
<text>The Federal Magistrate concluded that the applicant's submission was to particularise and expand on information which the Tribunal had paraphrased or summarised in what it put to the applicant. He concluded that whilst the Tribunal could have put what was said to be what should have been put, the Tribunal could not be criticised for summarising the information in the way that it did. For those reasons, the Federal Magistrate concluded that even if the Tribunal had an obligation to give information pursuant to s 424AA(b)(i) that it did not breach that obligation. However, the Federal Magistrate also concluded that the information in question was independent country information which the Tribunal had no obligation to notify to the applicant. He followed a decision of Cowdroy J in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 in which his Honour concluded that the exclusions contained in s 424A(3) applied with equal force to s 424AA. The Federal Magistrate concluded that that decision stood for the proposition that independent country information did not have to be provided to an applicant under s 424A(1) and s 424AA. The Federal Magistrate analysed for himself the two sections and came to the same conclusion as Cowdroy J and, in doing so, disagreed with a decision of Driver FM in SZLTC v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FMCA 384 to the contrary.

The applicant's contention as to the construction in s 424AA has been considered and rejected by other members of the Court in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 (Cowdroy J), SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701 (Edmonds J), SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541 (Middleton J), SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 (Gilmour J) and SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83 (Jagot J). Although the reasons in those cases may not be as these reasons, I agree in the results.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1701.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant's contention as to the construction in s 424AA has been considered and rejected by other members of the Court in SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 (Cowdroy J), SZMAE v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1701 (Edmonds J), SZITH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 105 ALD 541 (Middleton J), SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 (Gilmour J) and SZLML v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 83 (Jagot J). Although the reasons in those cases may not be as these reasons, I agree in the results.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>