<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Garrett, as Trustee for the Garrett Family Trust [2009] FCA 252 (23 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/252.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Universal Holidays Pty Ltd v Tseng [2008] FCA 1011</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1011.html</AustLII>
<text>In Universal Holidays Pty Ltd v Tseng [2008] FCA 1011 , Lander J dismissed an application by Mr Garrett to be joined in the cross-claim in the proceeding as the sole trustee of the Garrett Family Trust. The sole issue upon that application was whether in fact the Garrett Family Trust, of which Mr Garrett claimed to be a trustee, had ever existed. After a detailed consideration of the evidence Lander J concluded relevantly that there is not, and never has been, a separate entity called the Garrett Family Trust of which Mr Garrett was one of the trustees: [121]. His Honour held that the expression "the Garrett Family Trust" when used in certain "transactional documents" was a reference to the Andrew Garrett Family Trust which was then the only relevant trust in existence. The application was accordingly dismissed.

Mr Garrett sought leave to appeal against the orders of Lander J dismissing his application. That application was refused by Lander J on 8 September 2008. In dismissing the application for leave Lander J observed that Mr Garrett was in effect seeking to re-litigate before the Full Court on different terms and on different evidence than the application which has previously been before him: Garrett v Macks [2008] FCA 1419 at [26] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Garrett v Macks [2008] FCA 1419</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1419.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Garrett sought leave to appeal against the orders of Lander J dismissing his application. That application was refused by Lander J on 8 September 2008. In dismissing the application for leave Lander J observed that Mr Garrett was in effect seeking to re-litigate before the Full Court on different terms and on different evidence than the application which has previously been before him: Garrett v Macks [2008] FCA 1419 at [26] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/10.html</AustLII>
<text>Declaratory relief must be directed to the determination of legal controversies and not to answering abstract or hypothetical questions. The person seeking relief must have a 'real interest' and relief will not be granted if the question 'is purely hypothetical', if relief is 'claimed in relation to circumstances that [have] not occurred and might never happen' or if 'the Court's declaration will produce no foreseeable consequences for the parties. The person seeking relief must have a "real interest": Ainsworth v Criminal Justice Commission [1992] HCA 10 ; (1992) 175 CLR 564 at 582.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Forster v Jododex Australia Aust Pty Ltd [1972] HCA 61 ; (1972) 127 CLR 421</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1972/61.html</AustLII>
<text>The person seeking the declaration must be able to secure a proper contradictor, that is to say, someone presently existing who has a true interest to oppose the declaration sought: Forster v Jododex Australia Pty Ltd [1972] HCA 61 ; (1972) 127 CLR 421 per Gibbs J at 437; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Admiral Mechanical Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1085 at [8] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Admiral Mechanical Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1085</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1085.html</AustLII>
<text>The person seeking the declaration must be able to secure a proper contradictor, that is to say, someone presently existing who has a true interest to oppose the declaration sought: Forster v Jododex Australia Pty Ltd [1972] HCA 61 ; (1972) 127 CLR 421 per Gibbs J at 437; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Admiral Mechanical Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1085 at [8] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Institute of Private Detectives Ltd v Privacy Commissioner [2004] FCA 1440</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1440.html</AustLII>
<text>A case is not "real", for this purpose, when the issue to be determined is divorced from the facts to which it relates. A general declaration "in air", which is unrelated to specific facts, may not resolve the dispute between the parties: Martin v Taylor [2000] FCA 1002. Nor is the case "real" if by granting a declaration the Court will be acting in an advisory way and will not be quelling an existing controversy or establishing any immediate right, duty or liability between the parties: Australian Institute of Private Detectives Ltd v Privacy Commissioner [2004] FCA 1440 ; (2004) 139 FCR 394.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bass v Permanent Trustee Company Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/9.html</AustLII>
<text>In Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334 at 356 [48] the majority observed that one crucial difference between an advisory opinion and a declaratory judgment was the fact that an advisory opinion is not based on a concrete situation and does not amount to a binding decision raising a res judicata between parties. They then adopted, with apparent approval, what is found in Zamir &amp; Woolf, 'The Declaratory Judgment', (1993) 2 nd Ed where it was emphasised that where the dispute is divorced from the facts it is considered hypothetical and not suitable for judicial resolution by way of declaration or otherwise.

In my opinion such is the situation here.

The declarations sought are not directed to a resolution of the complex factual matters adverted to by Mr Garrett in his correspondence addressed to Fosters Group Ltd although in a very limited way they may relate to them. The affidavit does not clarify the interest which is said to be the subject of the declarations sought. Furthermore the application filed by Mr Garrett does not name any respondents.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Williams v Hunt [1905] 1 KB 512</tocase>
<text></text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>