<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEWL v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 209 (9 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/209.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 16</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/16.html</AustLII>
<text>In VBAM of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] FCA 504 at [44] Gray J said: 
 "The evidence of the three witnesses was information that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application." 

 
His Honour did not refer to the terms of s 426 when arriving at that conclusion. That decision was followed by Gordon J in SZIAT v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 766 at [39] . She also referred to Bennett J's decision in SZAQI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1653 at [23] - [24] . There, Bennett J again referred to the concept of an applicant calling a witness to give oral evidence on his or her behalf as being within the scope of s 424A(3)(b). Bennett J distinguished the contrary construction by Branson J in SZECG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 733 at [17] - [22] .

In SZECG [2006] FCA 733 at [21] Branson J followed the obiter reasons of Lee and Tamberlin JJ in Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 16 at [96] - [99] per Lee J, with whose reasons Tamberlin J agreed at [108]. They held that s 424A was engaged where the tribunal relied on alleged inconsistencies between evidence of the applicant's husband and that of the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Applicant NAAF of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] HCA 62 ; (2004) 221 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/62.html</AustLII>
<text>Moreover, the appellant has given no indication of any further material which he might have tendered to the tribunal in order to deal with the position. He had already put before the tribunal the material he wished to rely upon for this aspect of the matter (leaving aside any response to any invitation under s 424A referred to in considering ground 3): cf Applicant NAAF of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] HCA 62 ; (2004) 221 CLR 1 at 12 [34] per McHugh, Gummow, Callinan and Heydon JJ. I reject this ground of appeal.

This ground asserted that the tribunal assumed or took account of a consideration that the appellant could reasonably have been expected to have taken more steps to be reunited with Ms L and their child and that his failure to do so led to, or contributed to, its adverse assessment of the nature of their relationship.

This ground amounts to an attack on the reasoning processes of the tribunal in arriving at its findings of fact. The tribunal explained why it found unpersuasive the appellant's case that he would live together with Ms L. It reasoned was that if the relationship had the strength of commitment that the appellant was asking the tribunal to find, it would have expected that the appellant would have done more to reunite with Ms L and his child. There was no unstated assumption or irrelevant consideration here. The tribunal expressed, in its own language, its lack of satisfaction with the appellant's claim based on its assessment of his conduct. In other words, the tribunal looked at the objective evidence that revealed that the appellant, over 8 years, apparently had not done more to be with Ms L and their child than pursue his protection visa claim here. It was open for the tribunal to find that this was not demonstrative of the level of commitment to the relationship that the appellant asserted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/72.html</AustLII>
<text>The tribunal departed from the procedure to afford procedural fairness mandated by ss 424A and 424AA of the Act. I cannot say that no different result would have ensued had the tribunal afforded the appellant the opportunity which ss 424A(1) and 424AA required him to have, however unlikely it is that he would have been able to dissuade the tribunal from taking the particular view it did of the facts: Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141 at 145-146 per Mason, Wilson, Brennan, Deane and Dawson JJ; Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88 at 95 [14] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v QAAH of 2004 [2006] HCA 53 ; (2006) 231 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/53.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, the statutory scheme does not permit that construction. First, a witness is not "information". The fact that an applicant for review asked the tribunal to take evidence from a person cannot make everything that the person said, if the tribunal called him or her to give evidence, information that the applicant gave to the tribunal. Self-evidently, the witness gave the information. It is a truism in litigation that there is no property in a witness. Moreover, the procedures of the tribunal are inquisitorial, not adversarial: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v QAAH of 2004 [2006] HCA 53 ; (2006) 231 CLR 1 at 17 [40] per Gummow ACJ, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ, 43 [126] per Kirby J; SZAYW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 49 ; (2006) 230 CLR 486 at 491 [4] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Crennan JJ. It would be incongruous to hold that s 424A(3)(b) characterised everything that might be said by a witness nominated by an applicant for review as a person whom he or she wished the tribunal to call to give evidence as being "information ... that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application for review". The only "information" that could possibly be in that category would be the witness's name and contact details. What the witness came to say in evidence would be information that the witness, not the applicant for review, gave to the tribunal. Any other construction of the section would make no sense. The applicant for review, as s 426(3) provides expressly, has no right to require the tribunal to call anybody to give evidence, apart from himself or herself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration of Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>It is important to allow some latitude to an administrative decision-maker in the expression of his or her reasons. They are meant to inform readers what the decision-making process covered: see Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 272 per Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ. The trial judge found that the tribunal's conclusion was based on the evidence before it. I too am unable to detect any jurisdictional error in the tribunal's approach. I reject this ground.

The appellant complained that the tribunal ignored relevant evidence as to the nature of the close relationship he said he had with Ms L. This argument is nothing more than a claim for merits review, and his Honour was correct to dismiss this ground on that basis.

The appellant argued that the tribunal did not approach the question of whether he would be the subject of persecution involving serious harm to him or his family under s 91R(1)(b). That section provided that persecution had to involve serious harm to the person. The tribunal found that were he returned to Bangladesh, and unable to live in a familial relationship with Ms L and their child, his circumstances would not be substantially different to his present circumstances of separation from them - that he had endured in Australia since 2000. The appellant argued that there was a substantive difference, namely that the reason for the separation would be different: in Bangladesh it would be because of the threat of harm to the appellant or his family, whereas in Australia it was by operation of law (there being no visa at the moment allowing the co-habitation).

However, his Honour found that the tribunal had concluded, on the merits, that the nature of the relationship between the appellant and Ms L was such that they did not have a strong commitment to live together and that, for that reason, any future separation would not in the circumstances constitute serious harm. I agree.

The appellant argued that the tribunal should not have accepted DFAT Report 803. That report informed the tribunal that the Embassy in Bangladesh could not find any documentation there suggesting acts of violence against an atheist or non-believer and that while the Embassy accepted that he may be subjected to some cultural alienation, that did not amount to serious harm for the purposes of s 91R(1)(b). In addition, the tribunal found that there was no real chance that the appellant would suffer persecution due to his religion or conduct, whether religious or cultural, were he to move away from his local area in which there were, on his account, "Muslim extremists" and relocate to Dhakar or another big city.

The tribunal accepted that serious harm might include a permanent separation from a person, spouse and child. The appellant did not suggest that the tribunal made any error in that regard.

As his Honour found, this ground of challenge amounted simply to a disagreement with the tribunal's findings of fact. The argument relied on a footnote to DFAT Report 803 that referred to another report prepared by the State Department of the United States of America entitled "International Religious Freedom Report". The footnote referred to the latter report "for an overview of religious practices in Bangladesh". The appellant supplied the tribunal with a portion of the latter report in response to its s 424A letter dealing with the DFAT Report. However, it was a matter for the tribunal to assess what evidence on this topic it would accept. I see no error in what his Honour concluded.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 228 CLR 294</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/24.html</AustLII>
<text>The tribunal used Ms L's evidence of her inquiries and her failure to tell the appellant of them as a basis for its rejection of the appellant's claim. In SAAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 24 ; (2005) 228 CLR 294 , McHugh, Kirby and Hayne JJ held that the tribunal had failed to comply with s 424A(1) because it had not given an applicant for review notice in writing of evidence given by her daughter as a reason to affirm the decision under review: see SAAP 228 CLR at 308 [37] per McHugh J, 338 [144], 345 [170], 345-346 [172]-[173] per Kirby J, 348 [184] per Hayne J. In that case the daughter had been called as a witness by the tribunal of its own motion.

As the statutory scheme makes clear, it is the tribunal, and not an applicant for review, which calls witnesses. Thus, s 426 provides that if in response to a notice issued to an applicant for review under ss 425 and 425A, that applicant notifies the tribunal within seven days that he or she "... wants the tribunal to obtain oral evidence from a person or persons named in the notice" pursuant to s 426(2), the tribunal is obliged to have regard to the applicant's wishes, but it is not required to obtain that evidence orally or otherwise from the person named in the applicant's notice (see s 426(3)). As a matter of statutory construction it is not open to suggest that an applicant for review can call any witness, other than himself or herself, pursuant to the right conferred under s 425(1).

A number of single judges of the Court have expressed the view that information given by a witness nominated by an applicant for review under s 426(2) and called by the tribunal to give evidence amounted to "information ... that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application for review" so as to fall within the exception provided in s 424A(3)(b). They have held that the witnesses were in fact called by the applicant so that their evidence was information given by the applicant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/54.html</AustLII>
<text>The tribunal departed from the procedure to afford procedural fairness mandated by ss 424A and 424AA of the Act. I cannot say that no different result would have ensued had the tribunal afforded the appellant the opportunity which ss 424A(1) and 424AA required him to have, however unlikely it is that he would have been able to dissuade the tribunal from taking the particular view it did of the facts: Stead v State Government Insurance Commission [1986] HCA 54 ; (1986) 161 CLR 141 at 145-146 per Mason, Wilson, Brennan, Deane and Dawson JJ; Applicant VEAL of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] HCA 72 ; (2005) 225 CLR 88 at 95 [14] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Kirby, Hayne and Heydon JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>SZAYW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 49 ; (2006) 230 CLR 486</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/49.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, the statutory scheme does not permit that construction. First, a witness is not "information". The fact that an applicant for review asked the tribunal to take evidence from a person cannot make everything that the person said, if the tribunal called him or her to give evidence, information that the applicant gave to the tribunal. Self-evidently, the witness gave the information. It is a truism in litigation that there is no property in a witness. Moreover, the procedures of the tribunal are inquisitorial, not adversarial: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v QAAH of 2004 [2006] HCA 53 ; (2006) 231 CLR 1 at 17 [40] per Gummow ACJ, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ, 43 [126] per Kirby J; SZAYW v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 49 ; (2006) 230 CLR 486 at 491 [4] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Crennan JJ. It would be incongruous to hold that s 424A(3)(b) characterised everything that might be said by a witness nominated by an applicant for review as a person whom he or she wished the tribunal to call to give evidence as being "information ... that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application for review". The only "information" that could possibly be in that category would be the witness's name and contact details. What the witness came to say in evidence would be information that the witness, not the applicant for review, gave to the tribunal. Any other construction of the section would make no sense. The applicant for review, as s 426(3) provides expressly, has no right to require the tribunal to call anybody to give evidence, apart from himself or herself.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 228 CLR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>The Minister argued that the tribunal's questioning and statements about the appellant's apparent lack of effort was a sufficient indication to him that his lack of exploration of his being able to go to the Philippines or Ms L's and their daughter's being able to come back to Australia was an issue for the purposes of s 425(1) of the Act. In SZBEL (2006) 228 CLR 512 at 165-166 [47] Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ said that the tribunal's statements or questions during the hearing could sufficiently indicate to an applicant for review that everything he or she said in support of the application was in issue. Such an indication could be given in many ways and no particular formula of words was required. However, the questions put to the applicant for review must, taken as a whole, put him or her on notice of the tribunal's concerns.

Their Honours said that if there were specific aspects of an applicant's account that the tribunal considered may be important to the decision and open to doubt, it must at least ask the applicant for review to expand upon those aspects of the account and ask him or her to explain why the account should be accepted: SZBEL 228 CLR at 166.

In my opinion, the appellant's argument fails. His Honour was correct to hold that the tribunal had not failed to comply with s 425 of the Act and that this ground should be dismissed. The tribunal sufficiently raised its concerns about the appellant's apparent lack of effort to explore other means of being with Ms L and their daughter. It questioned the appellant directly about his exploration of the possibility of him living in the Philippines. The tribunal made the comment that he had not made much apparent effort to be with his family. And it referred to the fact that he had not seen Ms L for about nine years, was not aware of any enquires that she had made about her coming to Australia and had made no enquiries about his going to the Philippines. The tribunal told him: 
 " It seems to me that you don't really have the intention of living together , given that you have been living apart for 8 years, even though you talk to each other and send photographs to each other and you support her financially. But how can I be satisfied given that if you do have to return to Bangladesh that she will come with you ." (emphasis added)

Given the real possibility that if the appellant's claim for a protection visa were rejected, he would have to return either to Bangladesh or travel to the Philippines, his lack of any enquiries over a lengthy period to make arrangements to be with the persons he claimed he loved so much that they would live together as a family, was a matter which the tribunal had fairly raised during the course of the hearing. Moreover, I am of opinion that there was no reason to consider that the tribunal's exploration of this issue was not a legitimate approach open to the tribunal to assess the appellant's claim.

The appellant argued that Ms L's evidence to the tribunal of the steps she had taken to come to Australia and the reason she gave it for not telling him about those steps was "information" that formed part of the reason for its rejection of the appellant's claim within the meaning of s 424A(1). He argued that the tribunal took into account his apparent unfamiliarity with the steps undertaken by Ms L to seek residence in Australia in forming the view that their relationship was not of the close kind that he asserted. In that context, he contended that the tribunal committed a jurisdictional error in failing to comply with s 424A in respect of this information.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2007) 235 ALR 609</tocase>
<text>The Minister supported the trial judge's finding that the information conveyed by Ms L at the hearing was not part of the reason for the tribunal's decision because it did not undermine the appellant's claim to be a refugee. His Honour made that finding, relying on what was said by Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ in SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2007) 235 ALR 609 at 615 [17]. In addition, his Honour held that Ms L's evidence was called at the request of the appellant, and was thus to be taken to have been given by him for the purposes of his application for review within the meaning of the exception in s 424A(3)(b).

In SZBYR 235 ALR at 615 [17], Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Callinan, Heydon and Crennan JJ said that the reason or part of the reason for affirming the decision under review was that the appellant was not a person to whom Australia owed protection obligations under the Convention. In that case, a statutory declaration that did not in terms contain a rejection, denial or undermining of the appellant's claims to refugee status was held not to attract the operation of s 424A(1)(a).

Tamberlin, Finn and Besanko JJ applied that reasoning in SZICU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCAFC 1 ; (2008) 100 ALD 1 at 7-8 [26] . In that case the Court held that information in an appellant's passport was neutral, and that what undermined his claims was not conveyed by the passport, but by country information. There, the tribunal had used the country information in assessing whether the appellant was of adverse interest to the authorities because he had obtained his passport and was able to leave his country of origin with it. Their Honours, applying SZBYR 235 ALR at 616 [18], said that the relevant "information" within the meaning of s 424A(1) was not to be found in disbeliefs arising from a process of reasoning applied to the evidence.

In SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 at 259 [205] , Allsop J said: 
 "Information is that of which one is told or apprised; it is knowledge communicated concerning some particular fact, subject or event: the Complete Oxford English Dictionary (2 nd ed, 1991)." 

 
And, in SZBYR 235 ALR at 616 [18], the plurality said:
 
 "However broadly 'information' be defined, its meaning in this context is related to the existence of evidentiary material or documentation , not the existence of doubts, inconsistencies, or the absence of evidence." (emphasis added)

The next question is whether the jurisdictional error I have found entitles the appellant to relief. A grant of constitutional writ relief is discretionary and may be refused if no useful result could ensue from quashing the tribunal's decision and ordering it to perform its duty according to law: SZBYR 235 ALR at 618 [28]-[29].

I am of opinion that the tribunal should have drawn the appellant's attention to the significance it proposed to give to the failure of Ms L to discuss with him the efforts she had made to explore obtaining a visa. The tribunal was conscious of the evidence she had given, including her statement that he may have become too excited had she told him what she was undertaking and then depressed if she failed, as a result of which she decided not to tell him. However, Ms L also gave other accounts of why she did not tell him, which the tribunal had noted in its statement of the evidence. For example, it recorded that Ms L had told it that she had not told the appellant because she did not think it was necessary as she could not get it [the visa] anyway.

The question here is whether, had the tribunal written a letter under s 424A(1) or given oral particulars under s 424AA and identified the reason why what Ms L's evidence had conveyed could have caused the tribunal to decide as it did, that would have made any difference to the result.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>approved</class>
<tocase>SZECG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 733</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/733.html</AustLII>
<text>In VBAM of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] FCA 504 at [44] Gray J said: 
 "The evidence of the three witnesses was information that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application." 

 
His Honour did not refer to the terms of s 426 when arriving at that conclusion. That decision was followed by Gordon J in SZIAT v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 766 at [39] . She also referred to Bennett J's decision in SZAQI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1653 at [23] - [24] . There, Bennett J again referred to the concept of an applicant calling a witness to give oral evidence on his or her behalf as being within the scope of s 424A(3)(b). Bennett J distinguished the contrary construction by Branson J in SZECG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 733 at [17] - [22] .

In SZECG [2006] FCA 733 at [21] Branson J followed the obiter reasons of Lee and Tamberlin JJ in Applicant M164/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 16 at [96] - [99] per Lee J, with whose reasons Tamberlin J agreed at [108]. They held that s 424A was engaged where the tribunal relied on alleged inconsistencies between evidence of the applicant's husband and that of the applicant.

Branson J doubted that it could be said that the appellant "gave" the information implicit in his father's evidence. She said that the hearing before the tribunal was not an inter parties judicial hearing but formed part of an administrative enquiry. Her Honour observed that the appellant there did not call his father to give evidence but rather advised the tribunal that he wanted it to take evidence from his father". Branson J did not reach a concluded view on the question although she doubted that s 424A(3)(b) disclosed an intention that every piece of information that the tribunal gleaned from the evidence of the witness called at the request of an applicant for review was to be treated as evidence given to the tribunal by that applicant for the purpose of the application: SZECG [2006] FCA 733 at [22] - [23] .

None of these authorities construed s 426 or dealt with the fact that an applicant could not "call a witness". I am of the firm opinion that on the proper construction of the Act, information given orally by a witness, other than the applicant for review, cannot be "information" that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application for review within the meaning of the exception of s 424A(3)(b).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/2.html</AustLII>
<text>In SZEEU v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 at 259 [205] , Allsop J said: 
 "Information is that of which one is told or apprised; it is knowledge communicated concerning some particular fact, subject or event: the Complete Oxford English Dictionary (2 nd ed, 1991)." 

 
And, in SZBYR 235 ALR at 616 [18], the plurality said:
 
 "However broadly 'information' be defined, its meaning in this context is related to the existence of evidentiary material or documentation , not the existence of doubts, inconsistencies, or the absence of evidence." (emphasis added)</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>reversed</class>
<tocase>SZEWL v Minister for Immigration and anor [2008] FMCA 1495</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/1495.html</AustLII>
<text>The first tribunal decided to affirm the delegate's decision in late November 2002, but in July 2006 Allsop J upheld an appeal from the Federal Magistrates Court and set the first tribunal's decision aside: SZEWL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 968. His Honour held that the tribunal had failed to give the appellant notice in accordance with s 424A of material from the appellant's passport and supporting documentation. He had provided that material to the delegate in support of his application for a protection visa but the appellant had not given that material to the tribunal for the purposes of its review: SZEWL [2006] FCA 968 at [14] - [18] .

In November 2006 the second tribunal affirmed the delegate's decision. But in early March 2007 the Federal Magistrates Court, by consent, ordered that decision be set aside for failure of the tribunal to accord the appellant common law procedural fairness in relation to independent country information. The third tribunal again affirmed the delegate's decision in late July 2007, but its decision, too, was set aside by consent, on the basis that it ignored the evidence given to the previously constituted tribunal regarding the relationship between the appellant and Ms L.

One might have thought that after all this, the issues arising in relation to the decision of the delegate under review were clear. The fourth tribunal (it being differently constituted on each occasion, although continuing to conduct the original review) decided to affirm the delegate's decision on 5 May 2008. In November 2008 the Federal Magistrates Court dismissed an application for constitutional writ relief from that decision: SZEWL v Minister for Immigration and anor [2008] FMCA 1495.

Before the trial judge and before me, the appellant relied on eight bases for suggesting that the fourth tribunal committed a jurisdictional error. I will deal with these in detail below. The central issue in the appeal, however, was the way in which the tribunal dealt with the relationship between the appellant and Ms L. The tribunal did not accept that their relationship was a spousal or de facto relationship or a committed familial relationship of the nature claimed by the appellant.

The appellant raised many issues challenging the validity of the tribunal's decision before the trial judge, and these were repeated in the appeal. But his substantive complaints were that: 
(a) the tribunal did not inform the appellant that each of the following was an issue arising in relation to the decision under review, namely:
 his lack of familiarity with the steps taken by Ms L to seek residence in Australia; his desire to remain in Australia was stronger than his desire to live with Ms L and their child (Ground 2); 
(b) the tribunal failed to invite the appellant to comment on the information Ms L had given it in relation to the steps she had taken to seek residence in Australia and her reason for not telling the appellant of those steps (Ground 3).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>SZIAT v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 766</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/766.html</AustLII>
<text>In VBAM of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] FCA 504 at [44] Gray J said: 
 "The evidence of the three witnesses was information that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application." 

 
His Honour did not refer to the terms of s 426 when arriving at that conclusion. That decision was followed by Gordon J in SZIAT v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 766 at [39] . She also referred to Bennett J's decision in SZAQI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1653 at [23] - [24] . There, Bennett J again referred to the concept of an applicant calling a witness to give oral evidence on his or her behalf as being within the scope of s 424A(3)(b). Bennett J distinguished the contrary construction by Branson J in SZECG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 733 at [17] - [22] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZICU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCAFC 1 ; (2008) 100 ALD 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/1.html</AustLII>
<text>Tamberlin, Finn and Besanko JJ applied that reasoning in SZICU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCAFC 1 ; (2008) 100 ALD 1 at 7-8 [26] . In that case the Court held that information in an appellant's passport was neutral, and that what undermined his claims was not conveyed by the passport, but by country information. There, the tribunal had used the country information in assessing whether the appellant was of adverse interest to the authorities because he had obtained his passport and was able to leave his country of origin with it. Their Honours, applying SZBYR 235 ALR at 616 [18], said that the relevant "information" within the meaning of s 424A(1) was not to be found in disbeliefs arising from a process of reasoning applied to the evidence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>notfollowed</class>
<tocase>VBAM of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] FCA 504</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/504.html</AustLII>
<text>In VBAM of 2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] FCA 504 at [44] Gray J said: 
 "The evidence of the three witnesses was information that the applicant gave for the purpose of the application." 

 
His Honour did not refer to the terms of s 426 when arriving at that conclusion. That decision was followed by Gordon J in SZIAT v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 766 at [39] . She also referred to Bennett J's decision in SZAQI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1653 at [23] - [24] . There, Bennett J again referred to the concept of an applicant calling a witness to give oral evidence on his or her behalf as being within the scope of s 424A(3)(b). Bennett J distinguished the contrary construction by Branson J in SZECG v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 733 at [17] - [22] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>