<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of Storm Financial Limited (Receivers and Managers Appointed) (Administrators Appointed) v Storm Financial Limited (Receivers and Managers Appointed)(Administrators Appointed) (No 2) [2009] FCA 298 (1 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/298.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd (No 3) (2002) ATPR 41-873</tocase>
<text>Observation of the administration of justice is one thing; the ability freely to inspect every document on the Court's file is another. So much is evident from the structure of O 46 r 6. Rule 6(2) lists out those types of document which may be inspected as of right with r 6(3) then providing that the ability to inspect other types of document requires a grant of leave. As to the latter, while there may be a general disposition to permit a non-party to have access to such non-confidential affidavits and exhibits as are admitted into evidence: Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 9) [2005] FCA 1394 ; (2005) 148 FCR 1 , at [26], the extent of further access must in each case be considered on its merits. That is so even in relation to material read in open court or referred to by a judge: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd (No 3) (2002) ATPR 41-873 at [7]. One factor which can be relevant to the withholding of access is the approach adopted by the parties to objections to evidence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>R v Davis [1995] FCA 1321 ; (1995) 57 FCR 512</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1995/1321.html</AustLII>
<text>Such public administration of justice and the consequent ability for the public freely to observe it and for the media readily to report it is a safeguard against the abuse of the very considerable authority entailed in the exercise of the judicial power of the Commonwealth: R v Davis [1995] FCA 1321 ; (1995) 57 FCR 512 at 514.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 9) [2005] FCA 1394 ; (2005) 148 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1394.html</AustLII>
<text>Observation of the administration of justice is one thing; the ability freely to inspect every document on the Court's file is another. So much is evident from the structure of O 46 r 6. Rule 6(2) lists out those types of document which may be inspected as of right with r 6(3) then providing that the ability to inspect other types of document requires a grant of leave. As to the latter, while there may be a general disposition to permit a non-party to have access to such non-confidential affidavits and exhibits as are admitted into evidence: Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 9) [2005] FCA 1394 ; (2005) 148 FCR 1 , at [26], the extent of further access must in each case be considered on its merits. That is so even in relation to material read in open court or referred to by a judge: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd (No 3) (2002) ATPR 41-873 at [7]. One factor which can be relevant to the withholding of access is the approach adopted by the parties to objections to evidence.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>