<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tennant Ltd v Uhlen [2009] FCA 29 (16 January 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/29.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley 40 DLR (3d) 371</tocase>
<text>6 The principles upon which the applicants rely are not in dispute. They are established in two authorities of the High Court and by a Canadian authority. The High Court authorities are Pilmer v Duke Group Ltd (in liq) [2001] HCA 31 ; (2001) 207 CLR 165 at [78] and Consul Developments Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373 at 393. The Canadian authority is the decision in Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley 40 DLR (3d) 371 ( 'Canaero' ). The statements of principle in the Canaero decision were set out in the judgment of Laskin J at 382, as follows:
 In my opinion, this ethic disqualifies a director or senior officer from usurping for himself or diverting to another person or company with whom or with which he is associated a maturing business opportunity which his company is actively pursuing; he is also precluded from so acting even after his resignation where the resignation may fairly be said to have been prompted or influenced by a wish to acquire for himself the opportunity sought by the company, or where it was his position with the company rather than a fresh initiative that lead him to the opportunity which he later acquired.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Consul Developments Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1975/8.html</AustLII>
<text>6 The principles upon which the applicants rely are not in dispute. They are established in two authorities of the High Court and by a Canadian authority. The High Court authorities are Pilmer v Duke Group Ltd (in liq) [2001] HCA 31 ; (2001) 207 CLR 165 at [78] and Consul Developments Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373 at 393. The Canadian authority is the decision in Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley 40 DLR (3d) 371 ( 'Canaero' ). The statements of principle in the Canaero decision were set out in the judgment of Laskin J at 382, as follows:
 In my opinion, this ethic disqualifies a director or senior officer from usurping for himself or diverting to another person or company with whom or with which he is associated a maturing business opportunity which his company is actively pursuing; he is also precluded from so acting even after his resignation where the resignation may fairly be said to have been prompted or influenced by a wish to acquire for himself the opportunity sought by the company, or where it was his position with the company rather than a fresh initiative that lead him to the opportunity which he later acquired.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pilmer v Duke Group Ltd (in liq) [2001] HCA 31 ; (2001) 207 CLR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/31.html</AustLII>
<text>6 The principles upon which the applicants rely are not in dispute. They are established in two authorities of the High Court and by a Canadian authority. The High Court authorities are Pilmer v Duke Group Ltd (in liq) [2001] HCA 31 ; (2001) 207 CLR 165 at [78] and Consul Developments Pty Ltd v DPC Estates Pty Ltd [1975] HCA 8 ; (1975) 132 CLR 373 at 393. The Canadian authority is the decision in Canadian Aero Service Ltd v O'Malley 40 DLR (3d) 371 ( 'Canaero' ). The statements of principle in the Canaero decision were set out in the judgment of Laskin J at 382, as follows:
 In my opinion, this ethic disqualifies a director or senior officer from usurping for himself or diverting to another person or company with whom or with which he is associated a maturing business opportunity which his company is actively pursuing; he is also precluded from so acting even after his resignation where the resignation may fairly be said to have been prompted or influenced by a wish to acquire for himself the opportunity sought by the company, or where it was his position with the company rather than a fresh initiative that lead him to the opportunity which he later acquired.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ridgeway International Ltd v McCullum (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales (Equity Division), Bryson J, 9 April 1998)</tocase>
<text>7 Canaero has been referred to in Australia with approval in the decision of Bryson J in Ridgeway International Ltd v McCullum (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales (Equity Division), 9 April 1998); see also Meagher R, Heydon D &amp; Leeming M, Equity Doctrines &amp; Remedies (4 th ed, Butterworths LexisNexis, 2002) at [5-100].

8 No evidence was filed by the respondents to suggest that Mr Uhlen, or the other respondents, would suffer any hardship or inconvenience or any practical difficulties as a result of the continuation of Order 3(a). However, three matters were raised by Mr Greenwood SC who appeared for Mr Uhlen, and I will address Mr Greenwood's points.

9 First Mr Greenwood cross-examined Mr Wolfe, the Managing Director of Tennant, to suggest that the applicants would not be able to meet their undertakings as to damages. Mr Wolfe's evidence on this issue was not entirely satisfactory. It is true that he was given no advance warning, but I would have expected him to have a better knowledge of the financial position of the company than he revealed this morning. Nevertheless, I am satisfied on the basis of Mr Wolfe's evidence that the applicants are in a position to meet the undertaking.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>