<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Narnia Investments Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 395 (22 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/395.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 374</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/374.html</AustLII>
<text>The maximum penalty of 12 months' imprisonment reflects Parliament's view that "the provision of false information in response to a s 155 notice is a serious offence"; see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v GIA Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1298 at [19] per Heerey J, see also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 374 at [50] per North J. Considerations relevant to penalty

Having regard to the importance of general deterrence, as stressed by Lindgren J in Neville , and the ameliorating factors referred to at [22] above, I consider that a monetary penalty between mid-range and high range should be imposed. The charge is too serious to warrant the imposition of a conditional discharge under s 19B(1) of the Crimes Act in respect of Mr Clarke. To do so would be inconsistent with the approach adopted by this Court in Neville, GIA and Rana . The disqualification of Mr Clarke from managing another corporation under s 206B of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) is a matter which Mr Clarke should have had regard to before committing the offence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Neville [2007] FCA 1583</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1583.html</AustLII>
<text>The factors referred to in the preceding paragraph weigh in favour of a reduction in penalty from the high range to a range in excess of a mid-range penalty but below that of a high range penalty. However, as Lindgren J said in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Neville [2007] FCA 1583 at [43] : 
 an important purpose of the penalty to be imposed in the present case is that of general deterrence. It is most important that persons furnishing information or giving evidence in response to a notice issued by the ACCC under s 155 of the TP Act do so frankly and honestly. It serves the public interest that the ACCC be enabled to carry out its investigations efficiently and effectively. Section 155 of the TP Act is directed to that end. If a person who is required to give evidence under s 155(1)(c) of the TP Act gives false or misleading evidence, not only does this have the immediate effect of obstructing and delaying the particular investigation: it also has the potential to direct the ACCC away from other sources of information and to draw human and financial resources away from its other work. The general public should know that conduct of that kind will be treated seriously by the Court.

Specific deterrence is not a central consideration as I am confident that Mr Clarke will not re-offend.

Having regard to the importance of general deterrence, as stressed by Lindgren J in Neville , and the ameliorating factors referred to at [22] above, I consider that a monetary penalty between mid-range and high range should be imposed. The charge is too serious to warrant the imposition of a conditional discharge under s 19B(1) of the Crimes Act in respect of Mr Clarke. To do so would be inconsistent with the approach adopted by this Court in Neville, GIA and Rana . The disqualification of Mr Clarke from managing another corporation under s 206B of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) is a matter which Mr Clarke should have had regard to before committing the offence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Commercial and General Publications Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 1349</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1349.html</AustLII>
<text>Accordingly, a fine of $5,600 will be imposed on Narnia and fine of $1,400 will be imposed on Mr Clarke. I would have ordinarily imposed a penalty of $7,000 on Narnia but have reduced that amount by $1,400 to reflect the penalty imposed on Mr Clarke. I have done so given that Narnia was, in practical terms, Mr Clarke's alter ego. One must be careful to avoid what is, in effect, double punishment of a sole director of a company; see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Commercial and General Publications Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 1349 at [27] [29] per Heerey J.

The penalties are to be paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund on or before 20 May 2009. It is agreed that the defendants should pay the prosecutor's costs of the proceeding.
 I certify that the preceding twenty-seven (27) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Marshall. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 23 April 2009
 
 Counsel for the Prosecutor: Mr I Faulkner SC with Mr I Arendt 
 
 Solicitor for the Prosecutor: Commonwealth DPP 
 
 Counsel for the Defendants: Mr D Barclay 
 
 Solicitor for the Defendants: Page Seager 
 Date of Hearing: 22 April 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 April 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/395.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v GIA Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1298.html</AustLII>
<text>The maximum penalty of 12 months' imprisonment reflects Parliament's view that "the provision of false information in response to a s 155 notice is a serious offence"; see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v GIA Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 1298 at [19] per Heerey J, see also Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 374 at [50] per North J. Considerations relevant to penalty

In GIA , Heerey J considered that a mid-range penalty was appropriate because the relevant conduct was "more a matter of minimisation and evasion than denial or the laying of a false trail"; at [19]. In the current case, the conduct was in the nature of denial and the laying of a false trail. The nature and circumstances of each offence make it a serious transgression for Narnia and Mr Clarke respectively; see s 16A(2)(a) of the Crimes Act which requires the Court to take into account the "nature and circumstances of the offence".

On the face of the conduct, the offence by each defendant should attract a high range monetary penalty. I accept that it would not be appropriate in all the circumstances to imprison Mr Clarke, especially given that he has pleaded guilty and has no prior convictions.

The applicable considerations in amelioration of penalty in the current circumstances include the following:</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>