<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Style Limited, in the matter of; Merim Pty Ltd v Style Limited [2009] FCA 314 (2 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/314.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec Ltd [2002] SASC 344</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/2002/344.html</AustLII>
<text>A person applying for an order pursuant to s 247A bears the onus of establishing that he is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose: Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec Ltd [2002] SASC 344 at [29] . Merim must do more than demonstrate that it is dissatisfied with the management decisions: Re Augold NL [1987] 2 Qd R 297 at 308 Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115 at 117. Merim must satisfy me that it is entitled to inspect the books because the information sought relates to matters that it as a shareholder ought to be informed of by the company: see, for example, Czerwinski v Syrena Royal Pty Ltd (No 1) [2000] VSC 125 ; (2000) 34 ACSR 245 at 248.

The authorities in relation to s 247A and its predecessor were usefully summarised in a series of propositions by Debelle J in Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec (supra) at [29]: 
 "1. The requirement that the applicant is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose expresses a composite notion and the court will determine whether each has been demonstrated by applying an objective test. 

 The onus is on the applicant to demonstrate that he is acting in good faith and that the inspection is for a proper purpose. 
 The section operates where the applicant seeks to protect some specific or a personal right by the making of the order. Examples are where a shareholder contemplates proceedings under s 233 of the Corporations Act (the statutory successor of s 320 of the Companies Code)... or where a shareholder reasonably takes the view that a transaction could adversely affect his investment and he seeks to investigate the transaction for the purpose of determining what action he should take ... or where a shareholder seeks to ascertain facts for the purpose of considering a takeover offer.... 
 If the applicant's primary or dominant purpose is a proper purpose, it is not to the point that an inspection may be of benefit to the applicant for some other purpose... 
 The rights provided by s 247A should not be regarded as affecting the basic rule of company law that a shareholder should not ordinarily have recourse to the courts to challenge a managerial decision made by or with the approval of the directors. 
 Since every shareholder has a right to apply under the section for an inspection order, it is no answer to an application that, if an order is made, the applicant may acquire information not available to other shareholders and thereby be in a more advantageous position than those shareholders. 
 Applicants do not necessarily lack a proper purpose merely because (a) they are hostile to other directors; or (b) they will, after inspection, have more information than other members. 
 The procedure under s 247A is not intended to be a process as wide-ranging as the process of discovery of documents so that, as a general rule, inspection will be confined to, say, the results of decisions of directors rather than all the documents such as board papers leading to decisions... I emphasise that this is a general rule. There may be occasions where it is proper to admit inspection of board papers ... 
 Even where an applicant is acting bona fide and has shown a proper purpose, the court has a discretion whether to order inspection. 
"
 
[citations omitted]

Mr Yunghanns said that he has sought information from Style in relation to various matters, including the application of the funds acquired through the capital raising and the settlement of the debt recovery proceedings, and that, in particular, he has not received a substantive response to the request contained in his email of 4 July 2008. That proposition is not disputed by Style. In answer to a question from me, whether Mr Yunghanns had received an answer to his queries, counsel for Style replied "Not comprehensively". I am satisfied Merim has not received an answer to the questions raised in Mr Yunghanns' email of 4 July 2008, nor has Merim received answers to a number of the questions and issues raised in subsequent emails and letters sent to Style and its officers.

Style's explanation for not responding to, and answering these queries is partly, as Style's counsel put it: 
 "...he [Mr Yunghanns] has to establish some reason to suspect that the funds have been used other than properly ... and there is nothing to suggest that it [money] has been taken by the directors or used improperly."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re Augold NL [1987] 2 Qd R 297</tocase>
<text>A person applying for an order pursuant to s 247A bears the onus of establishing that he is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose: Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec Ltd [2002] SASC 344 at [29] . Merim must do more than demonstrate that it is dissatisfied with the management decisions: Re Augold NL [1987] 2 Qd R 297 at 308 Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115 at 117. Merim must satisfy me that it is entitled to inspect the books because the information sought relates to matters that it as a shareholder ought to be informed of by the company: see, for example, Czerwinski v Syrena Royal Pty Ltd (No 1) [2000] VSC 125 ; (2000) 34 ACSR 245 at 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115</tocase>
<text>A person applying for an order pursuant to s 247A bears the onus of establishing that he is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose: Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec Ltd [2002] SASC 344 at [29] . Merim must do more than demonstrate that it is dissatisfied with the management decisions: Re Augold NL [1987] 2 Qd R 297 at 308 Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115 at 117. Merim must satisfy me that it is entitled to inspect the books because the information sought relates to matters that it as a shareholder ought to be informed of by the company: see, for example, Czerwinski v Syrena Royal Pty Ltd (No 1) [2000] VSC 125 ; (2000) 34 ACSR 245 at 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Knightswood Nominees Pty Ltd v Sherwin Pastoral Company Ltd (1989) 15 ACLR 151</tocase>
<text>While there is some evidence that Mr Yunghanns may be contemplating action to gain control of, or take over, Style, I do not consider that I should reject his evidence as to his purpose in seeking the order for inspection. In the absence of cross-examination of Mr Yunghanns there is no reason why I should reject his evidence as to his purpose having regard to the sequence of communications between Mr Yunghanns and Style to which I have referred. I am satisfied that even if the inspection sought may assist Mr Yunghanns or Merim in a proposal to gain control of, or take over, Style, Merim's primary or dominant purpose is as stated by Mr Yunghanns. In any event as Brooking J observed in Knightswood Nominees Pty Ltd v Sherwin Pastoral Company Ltd (1989) 15 ACLR 151 at 158, the fact that a takeover offer for the defendant (in the position of Style) might be made by a company controlled by a person who controls the plaintiff which is seeking inspection of the books of the defendant and that information derived from inspection of the defendant's books might be used for the purposes of the takeover offer: 
 "neither prevents the arising of the power to make the order sought, nor makes it appropriate to refuse the order sought as a matter of discretion."

I am satisfied that Mr Yunghanns has not been given a satisfactory answer or information in relation to the financial issues concerning Style which he has raised. Section 247A requires me to be satisfied that Merim is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose. I am so satisfied. Mr Yunghanns has raised a number of financial issues concerning Style which Style has not answered. In my view, those issues are substantive and not fanciful.

Mr Yunghanns' queries raise specific matters that cause concern to Mr Yunghanns and, on the material placed before me, I do not consider those concerns are artificial, specious or contrived. To adopt the expression used by Brooking J in Intercapital Holdings Ltd v MEH Ltd (1988) 13 ACLR 595 at 601-602 and in Knightswood Nominees Pty Ltd v Sherwin Pastoral Company Ltd (supra) at 154, I consider there is a "case for investigation".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Intercapital Holdings Ltd v MEH Ltd (1988) 13 ACLR 595</tocase>
<text>Mr Yunghanns' queries raise specific matters that cause concern to Mr Yunghanns and, on the material placed before me, I do not consider those concerns are artificial, specious or contrived. To adopt the expression used by Brooking J in Intercapital Holdings Ltd v MEH Ltd (1988) 13 ACLR 595 at 601-602 and in Knightswood Nominees Pty Ltd v Sherwin Pastoral Company Ltd (supra) at 154, I consider there is a "case for investigation".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Czerwinski v Syrena Royal Pty Ltd (No 1) [2000] VSC 125 ; (2000) 34 ACSR 245</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VICSC/2000/125.html</AustLII>
<text>A person applying for an order pursuant to s 247A bears the onus of establishing that he is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose: Acehill Investments Pty Ltd v Incitec Ltd [2002] SASC 344 at [29] . Merim must do more than demonstrate that it is dissatisfied with the management decisions: Re Augold NL [1987] 2 Qd R 297 at 308 Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115 at 117. Merim must satisfy me that it is entitled to inspect the books because the information sought relates to matters that it as a shareholder ought to be informed of by the company: see, for example, Czerwinski v Syrena Royal Pty Ltd (No 1) [2000] VSC 125 ; (2000) 34 ACSR 245 at 248.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Unity APA Ltd v Humes Ltd (No 2) [1987] VR 474</tocase>
<text>Provided the primary or dominant purpose for which the inspection is sought by Merim is a proper purpose, any subsidiary purpose for some other benefit is not relevant. In Unity APA Ltd v Humes Ltd (No 2) [1987] VR 474 Beach J said at 480: 
 "Having heard the evidence of the witness Wayland in relation to the matter I am satisfied that although Unity APA may well be seeking an order for inspection with a view to assisting its takeover offer that is not its dominant purpose. In my view its primary or dominant purpose is to ascertain whether or not the directors of Humes have been and are in breach of their duties to the shareholders of Humes in so far as the proposed acquisition of Smorgon Steel is concerned and whether or not it should oppose the proposal. If that is its dominant purpose as I am satisfied it is, in my opinion it is not to the point that an inspection of Humes books relating to the proposal may in some way be of benefit to Unity APA so far as its take over is concerned. If its primary purpose is a valid purpose such a consideration is irrelevant. ..."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Gerah Imports Pty Ltd v Duke Group Ltd (In Liq) [1993] SASC 4359 ; (1993) 61 SASR 557</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/1993/4359.html</AustLII>
<text>In Gerah Imports Pty Ltd v Duke Group Ltd (In Liq) [1993] SASC 4359 ; (1993) 61 SASR 557 , the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia permitted a liquidator to seek information as to the nature and extent of the professional indemnity insurance cover held by professional advisors to the company in liquidation to determine the likely possibility of recovering any judgment obtained against them having regard to the cost likely to be generated by liquidation.

Merim did not seek to rely, by analogy on O15A r 6 of the Federal Court Rules which enable an order to be made for preliminary discovery. Merim accepted that the Court, under O 15A r 6, is required to determine whether an applicant has reasonable cause to believe that it may have a cause of action against another person, and whether the applicant has insufficient information to enable the decision to be made. Merim acknowledged that access to insurance policies are usually denied under this Rule (unless relevant to investigating the identity of potential parties to an action).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Grosvenor Hill (Queensland) Pty Ltd v Barber [1994] FCA 921 ; (1994) 48 FCR 301</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/921.html</AustLII>
<text>Merim submitted the position for a shareholder, who is granted inspection of the books of a company pursuant to s 247A for the purpose of considering whether proceedings should be commenced in the name of the company against its directors is analogous to that of a liquidator examining the affairs of a company to determine whether litigation on behalf of the company should be pursued. I do not consider that there is an exact analogy between the position of a shareholder and the position of a liquidator in these circumstances. The liquidator is given specific functions and powers by statute and has a status quite independent of any other interest in the company. This status was emphasised by the Full Federal Court in Grosvenor Hill (Queensland) Pty Ltd v Barber [1994] FCA 921 ; (1994) 48 FCR 301. The Full Court said at 306: 
 "A liquidator, when engaged in litigation on behalf of a company which is being wound up, or when contemplating instituting such litigation, is not in the same position as an ordinary litigant. The liquidator comes to the company as an officer of the court under a duty and responsibility to get in and maximise the assets of the company for distribution for the benefit of creditors. In the discharge of his or her duty and function, the liquidator comes to the company with limited or no knowledge of the company's assets, business and affairs. The liquidator is therefore in a position of disadvantage to make informed decisions of both a legal and a commercial nature necessary to carry out the winding up. 

 
 The legislature has recognised this position of disadvantage and addressed the problem by the enacting of s 596B of the Law and its predecessors. The effect of the legislation is to place a liquidator in a privileged position to obtain information relevant to and necessary for the proper discharge of his or her statutory function. The seeking of information to make decisions as to whether or not litigation ought to be embarked upon or continued in itself is no more than 'an exercise of his duties and the fulfilment of his responsibilities as liquidator' (per Bryson J in Lombard Nash International Pty Ltd v Berentsen (1990) 8 ACLC 1213 at 1217)."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/21.html</AustLII>
<text>Style contended that there was no analogy between the issues in this proceeding and the situation of a liquidator investigating whether to institute proceedings against directors of the company. Style emphasised the unique situation of a liquidator compared to that of an ordinary litigant, Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 166 CLR 486 , 497. According to Style, the 'real' purpose of s 247A is to enable a shareholder who has identified a case suspected as requiring investigation to the requisite degree to obtain access to documents of the company to determine whether the case has substance; it is not to enable a shareholder to inspect all the documents of the company that the shareholder may wish to see to determine whether a derivative action would result in the company ultimately recovering substantial funds from directors if a case against them is proved.

The situation facing Merim is quite different from the situation facing a liquidator in the cases where a liquidator has sought production of directors and officers insurance policies. In those cases the liquidator did not know whether any such policies were held by the relevant companies or persons against whom proceedings were being contemplated. In this case Merim knows that Style holds, or at least has held, directors and officers insurance. So much is stated on page 22 of Style's Annual Financial Report for the year ended 30 June 2007 in the Directors' Report under the heading "Indemnifying Officers or Auditor" in the following terms: 
 " Indemnifying Officers or Auditor 
 During or since the end of the financial year the company has given an indemnity or entered an agreement to indemnify, or paid or agreed to pay insurance premiums as follows: 

 
 The company has procured Directors &amp; Officers insurance to insure each of the following directors against liabilities for costs and expenses incurred by them in defending any legal proceedings arising out of their conduct while acting in the capacity of director of the company, other than conduct involving a wilful breach of duty in relation to the company. The amount of the premium is estimated to be $12,636. 

 
 Gregory Johnson 
 Sean McDaniell 
 Murray Freeman 
 Stephen Roux" 

 
It is not unreasonable to assume that Style has continued to procure that insurance during periods subsequent to 30 June 2007.

Merim therefore knows of the existence of a policy of insurance and the amount of the premium estimated by Style to be payable under it. That was the position as at 30 June 2007. What Merim does not know, however, is the extent of the cover granted under that policy and whether it is current.

I therefore consider that it is appropriate, as a matter of exercise of discretion to order that Style produce for inspection any directors and officers insurance policies currently held by Style. The cover granted under any such policies will be relevant to the decision to be made by Merim, after inspection of the other documents in respect of which I propose to make an order, whether to apply for leave under s 237 of the Act to bring a proceeding on behalf of Style in its name against any directors or officers of Style.

Counsel for Style submitted that, if I was minded to make an order under s 247A, that Mr Yunghanns, in addition to Senior Counsel and an instructing solicitor for Merim ("the Nominated Individuals"), be permitted to inspect the relevant documents they should be required to sign undertakings in relation to their inspection of the documents and adhere to a confidentiality regime proposed by Style. Senior Counsel for Merim also requested that an accountant for Merim be added to the list of persons to inspect the relevant documents.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Spedley Securities Ltd (In Liq); Ex parte Potts (1990) 8 ACLC 673</tocase>
<text>The Full Court also noted that in Re Spedley Securities Ltd (In Liq); Ex parte Potts (1990) 8 ACLC 673 , Young J recognised that the statutory power in s 596B of the Corporations Law (also s 596B of the Act) in relation to an examination of a person about "examinable affairs" of a corporation was not limited to ordering an examination to obtain evidence to prove a claim but also getting evidence to determine the prospects of success. As was pointed out in the cases to which I have earlier referred (par [67] above) the rationale underlying s 247A, insofar as the purpose is to inspect documents in order to consider possible legal proceedings against directors is to enable a shareholder who has identified an appropriate "case for investigation" to determine whether that case has any substance or prospects.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>