<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited [2009] FCA 332 (15 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/332.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>ACCC v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd (unreported, O'Loughlin J, 5 March 1997)</tocase>
<text>The application of O 11 r 16 should now be considered in the light of the principles discussed in relation to s 31A: see Commonwealth Bank of Australia (ACN 123 123 124) v ACN 000 247 601 Pty Ltd (in liq) (formerly Stanley Thompson Valuers) [2006] FCA 1416 at [11] , namely that a proceeding need not be hopeless or bound to fail before the Court can strike out a pleading or part of a pleading. In deciding whether to strike out, the Court must have regard to the adequacy of the pleading and must take the evidence at its highest. That is, the Court must assess the pleadings as if the facts alleged are true: see ACCC v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd (unreported, O'Loughlin J, 5 March 1997). The Court should err on the side of striking out rather than giving summary judgment where the underlying complaint of a pleading supports a reasonable cause of action, although the pleading itself has deficiencies: see Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691 at [1] . ISSUES NOW AGREED 
 Quantum of Pecuniary relief</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>AWB Ltd v Honourable Terrance Rhoderic Hudson Cole (No 6) [2006] FCA 1274</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1274.html</AustLII>
<text>Pursuant to s 43 of the Court Act, the Court has an unfettered general discretion in respect of the award of costs, provided that such discretion is exercised judicially: see Ruddock and Others v Vardarlis and Others (No 2) (2001) 115 FCR 229 at [9]. The general rule is that costs follow the event: see Ruddock at [11]. In AWB Ltd v Honourable Terrance Rhoderic Hudson Cole (No 6) [2006] FCA 1274 , Young J, at [16]-[17], ordered each party to pay their own costs, given that each had achieved a ' substantial measure of success '. His Honour could not find that either party could be considered the ' successful litigant '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth Bank of Australia (ACN 123 123 124) v ACN 000 247 601 Pty Ltd (in liq) (formerly Stanley Thompson Valuers) [2006] FCA 1416</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1416.html</AustLII>
<text>The application of O 11 r 16 should now be considered in the light of the principles discussed in relation to s 31A: see Commonwealth Bank of Australia (ACN 123 123 124) v ACN 000 247 601 Pty Ltd (in liq) (formerly Stanley Thompson Valuers) [2006] FCA 1416 at [11] , namely that a proceeding need not be hopeless or bound to fail before the Court can strike out a pleading or part of a pleading. In deciding whether to strike out, the Court must have regard to the adequacy of the pleading and must take the evidence at its highest. That is, the Court must assess the pleadings as if the facts alleged are true: see ACCC v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd (unreported, O'Loughlin J, 5 March 1997). The Court should err on the side of striking out rather than giving summary judgment where the underlying complaint of a pleading supports a reasonable cause of action, although the pleading itself has deficiencies: see Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691 at [1] . ISSUES NOW AGREED 
 Quantum of Pecuniary relief</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fortron Automotive Treatments Pty Ltd v Jones (No 2) [2006] FCA 1401</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1401.html</AustLII>
<text>The observations of French J in Fortron Automotive Treatments Pty Ltd v Jones (No 2) [2006] FCA 1401 at [19] - [21] are particularly useful in distinguishing between the requirements for a summary judgment under s 31A and a strike out as discussed below. His Honour observed that s 31A renders judgment, and is thus distinct from a strike out, which can be followed by the amendment of a pleading. Thus judgment should only be entered where no amendment of pleadings or particulars is possible, that is, where there is a defect in the pleadings which cannot be cured. Order 11 rule 16 of the Rules

Order 11 rule 16 of the Rules provides: 
 Where a pleading&#8722;
 (a) discloses no reasonable cause of action or defence or other case appropriate to the nature of the pleading;
 (b) has a tendency to cause, prejudice, embarrassment or delay in the proceeding; or
 (c) is otherwise an abuse of the process of the Court,
 the Court may at any stage of the proceeding order that the whole or any part of the pleading be struck out.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (N.S.W.) and Others [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/69.html</AustLII>
<text>The test which was applied generally on an application for summary judgment prior to insertion of s 31A in the Court Act was that referred to in General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (N.S.W.) and Others [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125. At 129 Barwick CJ determined the test to be applied where an application is made to strike out a claim. His Honour said: 
 At times the test has been put as high as saying that the case must be so plain and obvious that the court can say at once that the statement of claim, even if proved, cannot succeed; or "so manifest on the view of the pleadings, merely reading through them, that it is a case that does not admit of reasonable argument" ; "so to speak apparent at a glance".

Section 31A of the Court Act has been said to impose a less stringent test than that described in General Steel Industries and may be understood to enable summary dismissal of unmeritorious matters: see Jewiss v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (2006) 65 ATR 222 at [26] and Gordon J in Jefferson Ford at [124]. Gordon J at [126] said that ' whether a proceeding or part of a proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success ' requires: 
 1. identification of the cause of action pleaded;
 2. identification of the pleaded facts said to give rise to that cause of action;
 3. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in support of the claim for judgment;
 4. identification of the defence pleaded;
 5. identification of any facts pleaded which are said to give rise to the defence; and
 6. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in defence of the claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>International Writing Institute Inc v Rimala Pty Ltd and Another (1995) 57 FCR 135</tocase>
<text>In International Writing Institute Inc v Rimala Pty Ltd and Another (1995) 57 FCR 135 the Full Court said (at 139): 
 Conversion occurs when goods are dealt with in a manner inconsistent with the rights of the owner, but this must be clear... Whilst it is possible that conversion occurs at some different point...the sale of the goods will, generally speaking, provide the necessary certainty.

Crucially, in relation to s 116 of the Copyright Act , the conduct referred to in paragraphs 67A to 67E attaches to conversion of an ' infringing copy '. The term ' infringing copy ' is relevantly defined in s 10 of the Copyright Act to mean ' a copy of the film... being an article (which may be an electronic reproduction or copy of the...film) the making of which constituted an infringement of the copyright in the...film '. The word ' copy ' is defined to mean ' any article or thing in which visual images or sounds comprising the film are embodied '. Findings relating to the conversion claim

For the reasons considered hereunder, the Court concludes that the existing pleadings are deficient.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Company of Australia Ltd and Others [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/60.html</AustLII>
<text>There has been a judicial difference of opinion in two recent decisions of the Full Court concerning the interpretation of s 31A: see Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Company of Australia Ltd and Others [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 and Wills v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (2009) 253 ALR 228.

Section 31A of the Court Act has been said to impose a less stringent test than that described in General Steel Industries and may be understood to enable summary dismissal of unmeritorious matters: see Jewiss v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (2006) 65 ATR 222 at [26] and Gordon J in Jefferson Ford at [124]. Gordon J at [126] said that ' whether a proceeding or part of a proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success ' requires: 
 1. identification of the cause of action pleaded;
 2. identification of the pleaded facts said to give rise to that cause of action;
 3. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in support of the claim for judgment;
 4. identification of the defence pleaded;
 5. identification of any facts pleaded which are said to give rise to the defence; and
 6. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in defence of the claim.

Despite some difference in the judicial approach of Finkelstein J and Gordon J in Jefferson Ford , the Court is prepared to follow the observations of Gordon J as providing a practical guide to the interpretation of s 31A of the Court Act. The conflict between Gordon J and Rares J in Jefferson Ford (see [129], [73]) and which was not resolved in Wills , relating to whether judges retain a general discretion to enter summary judgment under s 31A, is irrelevant to the current judgment, and accordingly it is unnecessary for the Court to consider the conflicting judicial opinions.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jewiss v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (2006) 65 ATR 222</tocase>
<text>Section 31A of the Court Act has been said to impose a less stringent test than that described in General Steel Industries and may be understood to enable summary dismissal of unmeritorious matters: see Jewiss v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (2006) 65 ATR 222 at [26] and Gordon J in Jefferson Ford at [124]. Gordon J at [126] said that ' whether a proceeding or part of a proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success ' requires: 
 1. identification of the cause of action pleaded;
 2. identification of the pleaded facts said to give rise to that cause of action;
 3. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in support of the claim for judgment;
 4. identification of the defence pleaded;
 5. identification of any facts pleaded which are said to give rise to the defence; and
 6. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in defence of the claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/691.html</AustLII>
<text>The application of O 11 r 16 should now be considered in the light of the principles discussed in relation to s 31A: see Commonwealth Bank of Australia (ACN 123 123 124) v ACN 000 247 601 Pty Ltd (in liq) (formerly Stanley Thompson Valuers) [2006] FCA 1416 at [11] , namely that a proceeding need not be hopeless or bound to fail before the Court can strike out a pleading or part of a pleading. In deciding whether to strike out, the Court must have regard to the adequacy of the pleading and must take the evidence at its highest. That is, the Court must assess the pleadings as if the facts alleged are true: see ACCC v Alice Car &amp; Truck Rentals Pty Ltd (unreported, O'Loughlin J, 5 March 1997). The Court should err on the side of striking out rather than giving summary judgment where the underlying complaint of a pleading supports a reasonable cause of action, although the pleading itself has deficiencies: see Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691 at [1] . ISSUES NOW AGREED 
 Quantum of Pecuniary relief</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Oakley v Lyster [1931] 1 KB 148</tocase>
<text>IiNet relies upon the principles referred to in Oakley v Lyster [1931] 1 KB 148 at 153 in support of its contention that the tort of conversion involves deliberate intent. The principles concerning conversion under s 116 have been considered recently by the Full Court in Venus Adult Shops Pty Ltd and Others v Fraserside Holdings Ltd and Another [2006] FCAFC 188 ; (2006) 157 FCR 442 at [85] to [94]. At [88] the Full Court said: 
 The essence of conversion is interference with a right of possession. It is nevertheless properly described as a "varied and somewhat amorphous tort" serving two distinct functions. One function is tortious, whereby it compensates a person deprived of the use of goods. However it also acts as a "surrogate for the Roman vindicatio ; that is, in order to give a dispossessed owner the means to recover his goods in specie , or if that is not appropriate their market value" &#8722; Tettenborn, Wiley and Bennett; The Law of Damages (LexisNexis UK, 2003) p 294. The conduct which may constitute conversion is diverse. It has been said to include:
 (i) refusal to return;
 (ii) taking;
 (iii) receipt;
 (iv) disposal or deprivation of title;
 (v) destruction;
 (vi) loss as a bailee;
 (vii) keeping.
 The diversity of that list raises questions about the universal appropriateness of a "market value" approach to the assessment of damages &#8722; Tettenborn A, "Damages in Conversion: the Exception or the Anomaly" (1993) 52 CLJ 128.

Relying upon the observations in Oakley v Lyster , iiNet has also submitted that conversion is an intentional tort, and Roadshow's pleadings relating to this cause of action are thereby deficient for failing to plead this integer. Such contention raises the question whether intentional dealing with the property of Roadshow is an integral requirement of the tort of conversion. As such contention is arguable, the Court concludes that to strike out the pleading on the basis that intentional dealing is not pleaded or to arrive at an interlocutory judgment on such question is inappropriate. This issue will require detailed argument at the hearing. Paragraph 67F of the ASOC primary infringement claim

In addition to Roadshow's claim that the iiNet users have infringed copyright in the films and that iiNet has authorised such conduct, Roadshow relies upon some of the same paragraphs as the conversion claim in support of a claim that iiNet itself has infringed the copyright in the films ('primary infringement'). The fact that paragraph 67F refers only to paragraph 67B(b) for such claim, together with the Amended Particulars, suggests that Roadshow alleges the primary infringement claim only arises from the data which is stored transiently in iiNet's facilities and which was discussed at [46] of this judgment, and not the transmission of such data.

The issues the Court has raised regarding the definition of ' infringing copy ', and whether that could apply on the facts pleaded, do not arise in relation to this claim. If it is found that there was transient storage of the whole or substantial part of the films, this may give rise to there being a ' copy ' for the purposes of s 86(c) of the Copyright Act , and consequently the problems discussed above in relation to ' electronic transmission ' do not apply.

The Court finds no deficiency in the pleading of the primary infringement claim. Separate hearings

The Court now considers iiNet's claim in paragraph nine of its Notice of Motion for a separate determination of the issues relating to the 86 identified films from the other films in the catalogue of Roadshow.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ruddock and Others v Vardarlis and Others (No 2) (2001) 115 FCR 229</tocase>
<text>Pursuant to s 43 of the Court Act, the Court has an unfettered general discretion in respect of the award of costs, provided that such discretion is exercised judicially: see Ruddock and Others v Vardarlis and Others (No 2) (2001) 115 FCR 229 at [9]. The general rule is that costs follow the event: see Ruddock at [11]. In AWB Ltd v Honourable Terrance Rhoderic Hudson Cole (No 6) [2006] FCA 1274 , Young J, at [16]-[17], ordered each party to pay their own costs, given that each had achieved a ' substantial measure of success '. His Honour could not find that either party could be considered the ' successful litigant '.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Cooper [2005] FCA 1878</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1878.html</AustLII>
<text>If Roadshow establishes an infringement of copyright in the 86 films, such finding may provide a basis to extend any injunctive relief to the whole film catalogue. Such an order was made in Kazaa at 94 and Universal Music Pty Ltd v Cooper [2005] FCA 1878 , in proceedings which are not dissimilar to the current proceedings. The Court considers that it would not be appropriate for the hearing to be limited only to the 86 identified films, and accordingly rejects iiNet's motion. ROADSHOW'S MOTION 
 Paragraph 63 of the Defence Adequacy of iiNet's Defence

Roadshow, by paragraph three of its Notice of Motion, seeks to have paragraph 63(l) of the Defence struck out. Paragraph 63 of the ASOC alleges, inter alia, that iiNet took no action to cause the alleged infringements of copyright by iiNet's users to cease. Paragraph 63(l) of the Defence which responds in part to such claim states that notifications made by the AFACT to iiNet, using data collected by DtecNet of allegedly infringing iiNet users, ' were mere allegations of copyright infringement '. Roadshow submits that the statement that the notifications constitute ' mere allegations ' uses terminology which is not a term of art, nor is it found in the copyright legislation.

The Court has no difficulty in understanding such pleading as being a statement that the AFACT notifications did no more than bring to iiNet's attention an allegation of copyright infringement. Whether the notifications from DtecNet of alleged infringement are sufficient to prove infringement by iiNet's users or might be used as evidence that iiNet was aware of the infringement of its users is necessarily a matter requiring evidence and thus is a matter for determination at the hearing. So considered, there is nothing further which needs to be added to the pleading. The Court rejects Roadshow's assertion that such statement is inadequate.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Cooper and Others [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/972.html</AustLII>
<text>As the Court considers that it is appropriate that the issues of liability and the question of damages be separated, the Court will make such orders to separate liability from quantum of pecuniary relief such as occurred in Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Sharman Licence Holdings Ltd and Others [2005] FCA 1242 ; 65 IPR 289 at 295 (' Kazaa ') and Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Cooper and Others [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1 at [148] . Sufficiency of certain paragraphs of iiNet's Defence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Sharman Licence Holdings Ltd and Others [2005] FCA 1242 ; 65 IPR 289</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1242.html</AustLII>
<text>As the Court considers that it is appropriate that the issues of liability and the question of damages be separated, the Court will make such orders to separate liability from quantum of pecuniary relief such as occurred in Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Sharman Licence Holdings Ltd and Others [2005] FCA 1242 ; 65 IPR 289 at 295 (' Kazaa ') and Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Cooper and Others [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1 at [148] . Sufficiency of certain paragraphs of iiNet's Defence</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Venus Adult Shops Pty Ltd and Others v Fraserside Holdings Ltd and Another [2006] FCAFC 188 ; (2006) 157 FCR 442</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/188.html</AustLII>
<text>IiNet relies upon the principles referred to in Oakley v Lyster [1931] 1 KB 148 at 153 in support of its contention that the tort of conversion involves deliberate intent. The principles concerning conversion under s 116 have been considered recently by the Full Court in Venus Adult Shops Pty Ltd and Others v Fraserside Holdings Ltd and Another [2006] FCAFC 188 ; (2006) 157 FCR 442 at [85] to [94]. At [88] the Full Court said: 
 The essence of conversion is interference with a right of possession. It is nevertheless properly described as a "varied and somewhat amorphous tort" serving two distinct functions. One function is tortious, whereby it compensates a person deprived of the use of goods. However it also acts as a "surrogate for the Roman vindicatio ; that is, in order to give a dispossessed owner the means to recover his goods in specie , or if that is not appropriate their market value" &#8722; Tettenborn, Wiley and Bennett; The Law of Damages (LexisNexis UK, 2003) p 294. The conduct which may constitute conversion is diverse. It has been said to include:
 (i) refusal to return;
 (ii) taking;
 (iii) receipt;
 (iv) disposal or deprivation of title;
 (v) destruction;
 (vi) loss as a bailee;
 (vii) keeping.
 The diversity of that list raises questions about the universal appropriateness of a "market value" approach to the assessment of damages &#8722; Tettenborn A, "Damages in Conversion: the Exception or the Anomaly" (1993) 52 CLJ 128.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wills v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (2009) 253 ALR 22</tocase>
<text>There has been a judicial difference of opinion in two recent decisions of the Full Court concerning the interpretation of s 31A: see Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Company of Australia Ltd and Others [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 and Wills v Australian Broadcasting Corporation (2009) 253 ALR 228.

Despite some difference in the judicial approach of Finkelstein J and Gordon J in Jefferson Ford , the Court is prepared to follow the observations of Gordon J as providing a practical guide to the interpretation of s 31A of the Court Act. The conflict between Gordon J and Rares J in Jefferson Ford (see [129], [73]) and which was not resolved in Wills , relating to whether judges retain a general discretion to enter summary judgment under s 31A, is irrelevant to the current judgment, and accordingly it is unnecessary for the Court to consider the conflicting judicial opinions.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>