<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hunter on behalf of the Wiri People No 2 v State of Queensland [2009] FCA 325 (27 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/325.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Christie George on behalf of the Gurambilbarra People v State of Queensland [2008] FCA 1518</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1518.html</AustLII>
<text>The long and the short of it is, the application is one which has failed a registration test. Every opportunity has been given for the Applicants to amend the application or at least provide some hope, in a meaningful way, that an amendment is likely which would provide a basis for retention of the case in the Court's list. There is no basis for forming an opinion that this is anything other than a case which does not warrant the further expenditure of public funds in terms of judicial time and also in terms of the investment of public funds in a Respondent State considering the case and attending. There are bases then upon which the application may be dismissed and should be dismissed under s 190F(6). I canvassed the background to that particular provision in the legislation in a decision which I gave in another case: Christie George on behalf of the Gurambilbarra People v State of Queensland [2008] FCA 1518. I shall not repeat what I there stated.

There is another basis upon which this application should be dismissed and it is one which ought not be forgotten. That is there is a default of appearance. In fact, more than one, there are multiple defaults of appearance. Defaults of appearance, in themselves, provide a basis upon which an application may be dismissed.

It is understandable that in some circumstances, for reasons about which a judge may be unaware, the State may wish, for its own particular reasons, not to move under s 190F(6) but rather prefer to see a dismissal occur in an appropriate case of the court's own motion. Those same sentiments, with respect, do not apply where the practice and procedure of a court is not observed. In the ordinary course of events, one might expect a respondent, particularly a public respondent, acting responsibly to move for dismissal in a case where there is an event of default in the ordinary practice and procedure of a court, as a model litigant would move in other cases involving the wider interests of the public. Be that as it may, there is then a basis in terms of default under the practice of the court as well as under s 190F(6) , for the dismissal of this application. The order that I make is that the application be dismissed.
 I certify that the preceding six (6) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 14 April 2009
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: No appearance by the Applicant 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Crown Solicitor of Queensland 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: There was no appearance for the Second Respondent 
 Date of Hearing: 27 March 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 March 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/325.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>