<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Limited [2009] FCA 40 (2 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/40.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Spargos Mining NL (1990) 3 ACSR 1</tocase>
<text>The "contrary to the interests" provision now contained in subpar (d) of s 232 has a separate and distinct area of operation from the "oppression" provisions in subpar (e) of s 232. The manner in which a company is being administered and in which its affairs are conducted may fall within the category of conduct contrary to the interests of the company's members as a whole although it may not be described as oppressive, unfairly prejudicial to, or unfairly discriminatory against members of the company: Turnbull v National Roads &amp; Motorists' Association Limited [2004] NSWSC 577 ; (2004) 50 ACSR 44 at 52, 57; Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 95 ; (2008) 66 ACSR 359 at 400. (See also Re Spargos Mining NL (1990) 3 ACSR 1 at 42; Shelton v NRMA Limited (2005) 51 ACSR 278.) An example of such conduct may be found where a company is formed for the purpose of undertaking particular activities but the directors and management disregard those activities and direct the company into different commercial areas.

In the course of final submissions Senior Counsel for the plaintiff submitted that the Council ought to be condemned for its failure to meet the expectations of its members. However, s 232 is not a punitive provision but rather a remedial provision: Re Spargos Mining NL (supra) at 44. The remedy to be granted under ss 232 and 233 is not to punish or to condemn but rather to remedy and end such oppression as has existed or such conduct which has arisen.

Senior Counsel for the plaintiff explained the concerns of the plaintiff in response to a question I put to him when he drew my attention to the fact that in the audited financial statements for the year ended 30 June 2008 there was a significant variation in the figure shown as the surplus between the draft financial statements and the final financial statements. The Income Statement in the draft financial statements showed a net surplus for the period ended 30 June 2008 of $666,448 whereas the Income Statement in the final financial statements showed a net surplus of $1,074,464 for the same period. I asked Counsel how he put the variation on the issue of oppression. Counsel responded: 
 "Your Honour, it doesn't constitute oppression in itself, the clause starting with the financial records, but it's consistent with a company that's not paying attention to its objectives and its data, which is included to have good governance and financial controls. We say it's consistent with an organisation that simply isn't effectively pursuing its objectives and properly conducting its affairs. But in itself, it doesn't constitute oppression and as it doesn't disclose insolvency it isn't a ground we rely upon for winding up. We don't pursue winding up. But, your Honour, it's also consistent with a course of conduct with not providing documents which ought to have been provided. When they're requested they're still not provided, let alone within a reasonable time. 

 
 So, it's consistent with the other complaints we make and supportive of the proposition that confronted with the failure to properly conduct the company and pursue its objects and involve members in the way that had been contemplated and then failure to disclose financial information to establish the basis upon which it could fund the activities it was supposed to pursue or any budget for the business plans that had been produced, Mr Szental was really left ... He either walked away, saying well it doesn't matter that this company is not being conducted properly, it doesn't matter that it's not pursuing its objectives, it doesn't matter that the demand side policies aren't being developed and advocated. 

 
 It doesn't matter that there's a process by which there is a selection of representatives not based on any procedure or structure to participate in briefings and advocacy. He could do that, that would be an easy thing to do. Or he could do it really as the only effective form of proceeding that he could bring, which is this proceeding, to attempt to remedy those deficiencies, which is what he's done." 

 
Mr Szental's concerns were understandable but they do not warrant a finding of oppression.

Further, by the commencement of the final hearing the substantive matters complained of by the plaintiff had been attended to by the Council. That consequence gives rise to the question as to whether it is open to a court to grant relief under s 233(1) when the conduct complained of, although in existence at the time the proceeding was filed, is no longer continuing as at the date of the trial or thereafter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Shelton v NRMA Limited (2005) 51 ACSR 278</tocase>
<text>The "contrary to the interests" provision now contained in subpar (d) of s 232 has a separate and distinct area of operation from the "oppression" provisions in subpar (e) of s 232. The manner in which a company is being administered and in which its affairs are conducted may fall within the category of conduct contrary to the interests of the company's members as a whole although it may not be described as oppressive, unfairly prejudicial to, or unfairly discriminatory against members of the company: Turnbull v National Roads &amp; Motorists' Association Limited [2004] NSWSC 577 ; (2004) 50 ACSR 44 at 52, 57; Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 95 ; (2008) 66 ACSR 359 at 400. (See also Re Spargos Mining NL (1990) 3 ACSR 1 at 42; Shelton v NRMA Limited (2005) 51 ACSR 278.) An example of such conduct may be found where a company is formed for the purpose of undertaking particular activities but the directors and management disregard those activities and direct the company into different commercial areas.

An essential feature of the "oppression" provisions in subpar (e) of s 232 is whether or not there has been commercial unfairness. The manner in which the Court should approach the issue whether there has been commercial unfairness was conveniently identified by Tamberlin J in Shelton v NRMA Limited (supra) as follows at 284 5: 
 "It is not practicable to delineate the numerous ways in which oppressive conduct may be established. The court will generally look at the overall course of conduct and consider whether it is so unfair that reasonable directors would not consider it fair. If directors exercise a power so as to impose a disability or burden on a member that is unfair according to ordinary standards of reasonableness and fair dealing, then such conduct may be described as oppressive. The question is one of fact and degree for the Court to determine, having regard to the view the directors have formed themselves, and allowing for any special skill or knowledge possessed by the directors. The test of unfairness is objective: see Wayde v NSW Rugby League Limited [1985] HCA 68 ; (1985) 180 CLR 459 at 472 (" Wayde ") per Brennan J; Morgan v 45 Flers Avenue Pty Ltd (1987) 11 NSWLR 573. The court should not take a narrow approach to cases of oppression. It is necessary for the court to come to a conclusion that there has been conduct unfairly prejudicial to or unfairly discriminatory or oppressive to a member before it makes an order to this effect: see John J Starr (Real Estate) Pty Ltd v Andrew (Australasia) Pty Limited (1991) 6 ACSR 63 , and the authorities there collected at 65-67."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Turnbull v NRMA Limited [2004] NSWSC 577 ; (2004) 50 ACSR 44</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2004/577.html</AustLII>
<text>The "contrary to the interests" provision now contained in subpar (d) of s 232 has a separate and distinct area of operation from the "oppression" provisions in subpar (e) of s 232. The manner in which a company is being administered and in which its affairs are conducted may fall within the category of conduct contrary to the interests of the company's members as a whole although it may not be described as oppressive, unfairly prejudicial to, or unfairly discriminatory against members of the company: Turnbull v National Roads &amp; Motorists' Association Limited [2004] NSWSC 577 ; (2004) 50 ACSR 44 at 52, 57; Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 95 ; (2008) 66 ACSR 359 at 400. (See also Re Spargos Mining NL (1990) 3 ACSR 1 at 42; Shelton v NRMA Limited (2005) 51 ACSR 278.) An example of such conduct may be found where a company is formed for the purpose of undertaking particular activities but the directors and management disregard those activities and direct the company into different commercial areas.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 95 ; (2008) 66 ACSR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/95.html</AustLII>
<text>The "contrary to the interests" provision now contained in subpar (d) of s 232 has a separate and distinct area of operation from the "oppression" provisions in subpar (e) of s 232. The manner in which a company is being administered and in which its affairs are conducted may fall within the category of conduct contrary to the interests of the company's members as a whole although it may not be described as oppressive, unfairly prejudicial to, or unfairly discriminatory against members of the company: Turnbull v National Roads &amp; Motorists' Association Limited [2004] NSWSC 577 ; (2004) 50 ACSR 44 at 52, 57; Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 95 ; (2008) 66 ACSR 359 at 400. (See also Re Spargos Mining NL (1990) 3 ACSR 1 at 42; Shelton v NRMA Limited (2005) 51 ACSR 278.) An example of such conduct may be found where a company is formed for the purpose of undertaking particular activities but the directors and management disregard those activities and direct the company into different commercial areas.

The proposition that the purpose of granting a remedy under ss 232 and 233 is to bring to an end the conduct or oppression of which complaint is made was explained by Giles JA in Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd (supra) at 386 7: 
 "The predecessors to ss 232 and 233 were introduced in the United Kingdom as s 210 of the Companies Act 1948 (UK), as a means of giving an aggrieved shareholder a remedy when winding-up on the just and equitable ground would be too harsh. They enabled orders by which the oppression came to an end with the shareholder remaining a shareholder (as in Re H R Harmer Ltd [1958] 3 All ER 689; (1959) 1 WLR 62) or came to an end through the shareholder being brought out as a shareholder (as in Scottish Cooperative Wholesale Society Ltd v Meyer [1959] AC 324 ; [1958] 3 All ER 66 ( Scottish Cooperative )). That legislation was adopted in Australia, and has since been significantly amended to the form earlier set out. There are more widely available statutory remedies, but historically the point of granting a remedy is to bring an end to the oppression as Powell J said in Re Dernacourt Investments Pty Ltd (1990) 20 NSWLR 588 at 620; 2 ACSR 553 at 566 "if it be possible, to bring the 'oppression' to an end without recourse to a cure the effects of which would, in many cases, be worse than the disease"." 

 
See also per Basten JA at 397; Young CJ in Eq at 430.

Given that the purpose of granting a remedy under ss 232 and 233 is to bring to an end the conduct complained of, what is the situation if that conduct, in existence at or prior to the commencement of the proceeding, has terminated by the time of trial?

The general trend of authority is that it is open to a court to grant relief under s 233(1) of the Act notwithstanding the fact that at the time of the trial or the making of an order the conduct or oppression complained of is not continuing.

A considerable number of authorities in this context were considered by the members of the Court in Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd (supra). I consider that the appropriate approach to take is that expressed by Giles JA in Campbell v BackOffice Investments Pty Ltd (supra) at 389: 
 "In my opinion, it is not necessary that the conduct complained of be continuing at the time the court considers making an order. Rather, claimed relief founded on conduct which is no longer continuing may be refused, but will not always be refused, in the exercise of the discretion, and the discretion adequately allows for the logicality to which Hamilton J referred [in Bessounian v Australian Wholesale Mortgages Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 35 ]."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gamlestaden Fastigheter AB v Baltic Partners Ltd [2007] 4 All ER 164</tocase>
<text>Basten JA relied on the decision of the Privy Council in Gamlestaden Fastigheter AB v Baltic Partners Ltd [2007] 4 All ER 164 as authority for the proposition that "neither the occasion nor the purpose of an order under s 233 need involve continuing oppressive conduct" (at 404).

However, Young CJ in Eq took the view (at 432) that "the authorities still require one to show continuing oppression at the date of hearing unless one is complaining about an act in the past of a director or other controller of the company which has a continuing effect".

As the Council had attended to the substantive matters complained of by the plaintiff by the commencement of the final hearing, there is no conduct which needs to be the subject of an order or relief to operate prospectively. In any event, I do not consider that the relief sought by the plaintiff is an appropriate form of relief either in the circumstances of this case or for the purposes of satisfying s 233 of the Act.

The relief sought by the plaintiff is that an independent person from one of the major four accounting firms be appointed to prepare a report to the members of the Council as to the Council's compliance with its obligations under the Memorandum of Understanding and the Information Memorandum, as to the adequacy of the Council's financial records and its solvency, and as to the extent and adequacy of the policies, mechanisms and procedures of the Council concerning corporate governance, reporting to the board and financial record-keeping, budgeting, forecasting and reporting. Further, the plaintiff seeks that the independent person provide recommendations as to what changes should be made to such policies, mechanisms and procedures.

There are a number of criticisms or objections to this form of order of relief. Such relief leads nowhere. It does not resolve or remove the conduct complained of by the plaintiff or the acts upon which it relies for the purpose of complaining about the conduct of the Council's affairs. The matters upon which the independent person is required to report are not solely accounting or financial matters and extend beyond his or her probable expertise and experience. In particular, compliance with the Council's obligations under the Memorandum of Understanding and the Information Memorandum are not matters appropriate for determination by an accountant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1992/34.html</AustLII>
<text>The Council then submitted that in seeking an order that will not remove oppression the plaintiff had commenced and continued the proceeding as a means of obtaining some advantage for which the proceeding was not designed or some collateral advantage beyond what the law offered: Williams v Spautz [1992] HCA 34 ; (1992) 174 CLR 509 at 526 7. The Council contended that the plaintiff's true purpose in bringing the proceeding was to obtain findings from the court for potential distribution to members of the Council. The Council relied on the following passages in Mr Szental's cross-examination: 
 "But isn't your position in this litigation that you want the court to order an independent report to be provided to the members and then you want the members in some fashion to consider that report?---I think an independent report from the court or the court findings would carry different weight to the proposition that you've been putting, which is basically that I am a sole dissenting member of the board, and I think that it would carry an independence and a weight that possibly I could never muster. It would also - - - 

 
 Though really it is sorry?---And it would make findings that there are actual deficiencies. 

 
 So really is the object of this exercise to get court findings rather than an independent report? ---The object of this exercise is to bring to the attention of the members that the management of the industry association up till now has been far from adequate and not in their best interests. I mean I have nothing to gain out of this other than to try and improve the benefits. I led three-quarters of the members through the BCSE into this merger and I have an obligation to them and I'm trying to fulfil that obligation by trying to inform them that what they signed on for isn't what they got."

I do not accept the Council's submission. The plaintiff has brought the proceeding in order to have the manner of the conduct of the Council's affairs changed. It seeks to achieve this result by seeking certain relief a report by an independent accountant to the members of the Council in relation to particular aspects of the conduct of the Council's affairs. For reasons to which I shall refer, I do not consider that that form of relief is appropriate in the circumstances of this case or that it will achieve a result of the type contemplated by ss 232 and 233. But that conclusion does not mean the plaintiff has been motivated by an improper purpose in commencing the proceeding. Its purpose in bringing the proceeding is to end a course of conduct. Accepting Mr Szental's evidence that the plaintiff commenced the proceeding to obtain findings by the Court which it could distribute to members does not mean an abuse of process. Rather, it means that the means by which the plaintiff is seeking to achieve its purpose is misguided and inappropriate.

The discretion committed to the Court by s 233 is very wide and unconstrained. In an appropriate case, a particular type of conduct of the affairs of a company might be eliminated or terminated by directing a particular person to report on particular aspects of the conduct of a company's affairs to its members or by a Court making particular findings as to the manner in which the company's affairs have been conducted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Fexuto Pty Ltd v Bosnjak Holdings Pty Ltd [1998] NSWSC 413 ; (1998) 28 ACSR 688</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/1998/413.html</AustLII>
<text>The plaintiff may be misconceived as to whether the relief it seeks will end the conduct or oppression of which it complains. That misconception does not mean that it is seeking an improper collateral advantage in bringing the proceeding. The advantage sought by the plaintiff in the proceeding is to terminate the manner in which the Council's affairs have been conducted in a number of respects. Section 232 gives the plaintiff the opportunity to seek relief within the range of relief provided in s 233 of the Act. The appropriate relief to grant in any given case is a matter for the Court and the court must tailor that relief so as bring to an end the impugned conduct: Fexuto Pty Ltd v Bosnjak Holdings Pty Ltd [1998] NSWSC 413 ; (1998) 28 ACSR 688 , 742.

As I noted in par [21] above, I do not propose to make specific findings in relation to the numerous complaints made by the plaintiff. A number of the issues raised by the plaintiff were acknowledged by the Council with the addendum that they had been rectified and remedied by the time the proceeding commenced. I have referred to some of these issues in par [47] above.

The power to grant relief under s 233 is very wide and the specific types of orders set out in s 233(1) are inclusive rather than exclusive. However, in considering what remedies should be made available to a party seeking relief under ss 232 and 233, it is necessary to consider the appropriateness of the remedy as at the time of the trial, and not simply at the time the application to the Court for relief was filed. Notwithstanding the width of the discretion in s 233 as to the relief which may be granted, the relief to be granted should be such as to terminate or remove the oppressive conduct or the conduct which is contrary to the interests of the members of the company. As Young J put it in Fexuto Pty Ltd v Bosnjak Holdings Pty Ltd [1998] NSWSC 413 ; (1998) 28 ACSR 688 at 742: 
 "The flavour of the section also is that the court is only to give the remedy which removes the oppression. Note the remedy in fact given in Re H R Harmer Ltd [1959] 1 WLR 62 at 68. Thus it is not enough merely to find oppression and then proceed to find some remedy that might bring peace to the company generally. The court should only grant the remedy that removes the oppression found."</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>