<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZYBC v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2009] FCA 417 (4 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/417.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>affirmed</class>
<tocase>MZYBC v Minister for Immigration and Anor [2008] FMCA 1567</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/1567.html</AustLII>
<text>This appeal is from a judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court, delivered on 21 November 2008, and published as MZYBC v Minister for Immigration and Anor [2008] FMCA 1567. The learned federal magistrate dismissed with costs an application by the appellant to review a decision of the second respondent to the appeal, the Refugee Review Tribunal ("the Tribunal"). The Tribunal affirmed a decision of a delegate of the first respondent to the appeal, the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship ("the Minister"), to refuse to grant to the appellant a protection visa.

The appellant is a citizen of Sri Lanka. She arrived in Australia on 12 April 2007. On 21 May 2007, she applied for a protection visa. On 10 July 2007, the Minister's delegate made a decision refusing to grant her a protection visa. Unfortunately, by letter dated the same date, the appellant's migration agent was mistakenly advised that the appellant had been granted a protection visa. The letter was erroneous in that, although it included in the heading the name of the appellant, following the abbreviation "Ms", the references to the migration agent's client in the letter were all expressed in the male gender. The error was corrected by a subsequent letter dated 16 July 2007, which enclosed a copy of the earlier decision record, giving the delegate's reasons for refusing the application.

The appellant applied to the Tribunal for review of the decision. The Tribunal conducted a hearing on 10 October 2007, at which the appellant gave oral evidence through an interpreter in the Sinhalese language, and at which the appellant was represented by a migration agent. The Tribunal's decision was dated 1 May 2008 and handed down, or sent to the appellant, on 3 June 2008.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>