<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZMZQ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 409 (22 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/409.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 228 CLR 152</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>Thus, it cannot be said that the delay between the date of the delegate's decision and the date upon which the Tribunal heard and determined the matter affected the Tribunal's reasoning processes. It seems to me therefore that the Tribunal complied with its obligations under s 425 of the Act and that there was no denial of procedural fairness. As the High Court said in SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 ; (2006) 228 CLR 152 at [25] : 
 What is required by procedural fairness is a fair hearing, not a fair outcome. ... The relevant question is about the Tribunal's processes, not its actual decision.

The High Court's observations seem to me to be apt in the present case. Moreover, I do not see that the delay between the appellant's date of arrival in Australia and the date upon which the Tribunal dealt with the matter can be said to give rise to any ground of review. The appellant complained that he had forgotten the relevant facts which occurred in 1995, but as the High Court observed in SZBEL at [40]: 
 [I]t is for the applicant for a protection visa to establish the claims that are made out.

This is not a case in which the appellant was affected by any disparity between the issues considered to be dispositive by the delegate and the issues which arose in relation to the decision under review. Here it appears that the appellant's claim before the delegate had a different basis to the claim which he put before the tribunal in the written statement to which I have referred above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/26.html</AustLII>
<text>Finally, it cannot be said that there was any breach of s 424A of the Act because the information upon which the Tribunal relied was not "information" within the meaning of section 424A(1): see SZBYR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [18] .

It follows that the appeal must be dismissed with costs.
 I certify that the preceding nineteen (19) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Jacobsson. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 24 April 2009
 
 The Appellant was self-represented. 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: P. Reynolds 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Clayton Utz 
 Date of Hearing: 22 April 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 22 April 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/409.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>