<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Priestley v Godwin (No 4) [2009] FCA 560 (28 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/560.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Conservation Foundation Incorporated v The Commonwealth of Australia (1980) 146 CLR 493</tocase>
<text>Ms Godwin submits that, if there were a decision for the purposes of s 13 of the ADJR Act, Mr Priestley is not a person aggrieved by that decision. She submits that there is nothing in Mr Priestley's application which indicates the manner in which Mr Priestley alleges his interests were affected, adversely or otherwise, by the decisions he alleges Mr Budak made on 17 October 2007. Accordingly, she submits, Mr Priestley is not a person aggrieved within the meaning of s 3(4)(a)(i) of the ADJR Act for the purposes of ss 5 and 13 of that Act. Ms Godwin submits that Mr Priestley has no special interest as described in Australian Conservation Foundation Incorporated v The Commonwealth of Australia (1980) 146 CLR 493 at 530-531. She submits that, as the High Court pointed out, a belief that particular conduct should be taken or prevented is not sufficient to give the possessor of that belief locus standi . Mr Priestley is not, she says, a person interested, in that he is not likely to gain some advantage, other than the satisfaction of righting a wrong, upholding a principle or winning a contest. Ms Godwin submits that Mr Priestley cannot demonstrate and has not demonstrated an interest in Mr Budak's alleged decision beyond an interest being held by virtue of being a member of the public, albeit a public linked to Parliamentary Service employees ( Tooheys Ltd v Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs [1981] FCA 121 ; (1981) 36 ALR 64).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Foreman Stevedores Association v Crone (1989) 20 FCR 377</tocase>
<text>Mr Priestley does not deny that he received the letter containing the reasons of 17 October 2007. The document was delivered specifically to Mr Priestley. I am prepared to infer that it was delivered on behalf of Mr Budak ( Australian Foreman Stevedores Association v Crone (1989) 20 FCR 377 at 385). This leaves open the question whether the requirement in s 13(2) that ' the person who made the decision shall, subject to this section, as soon as practicable, and in any event within 28 days, after receiving the request, prepare the statement and furnish it to the person who made the request ' requires that the decision be furnished personally by the decision-maker. "Furnish" means "provide or supply" ( Macquarie Dictionary , Revised 3 rd Edition). Section 13(2) cannot, in my opinion, be read to preclude, for example, the sending by post. This itself involves the use of other persons to furnish the reasons. I see no substantive difference in asking another person to arrange to have the reasons of the decision-maker sent to the person who made the request. In this case, Mr Budak's reasons were enclosed in a letter signed by Ms Karen Labrum, Acting Regional Director, ACT, Australian Public Service Commission.

The basis of Mr Priestley's application is that he was given no reasons for an alleged decision made on 17 October 2007. The complaint that he received reasons but that they were not furnished to him by the decision-maker does not seem relevant to this application. In any event, I do not accept that they were not furnished as required.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/7.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Priestley says that he is entitled to reasons for decisions which he says were made on 17 October 2007. Before one looks to see whether there is a decision under an enactment, which must be expressly or impliedly required or authorised by the enactment and must confer, alter, or otherwise affect legal rights or obligations ( Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 at [89] ), a threshold question must be considered: was there a decision made on that date?

An examination of Mr Budak's reasons of 17 October 2007 for his decision of 18 September 2007 discloses that he considered the substance of the allegations against the Parliamentary Service Commissioner, Ms Briggs. Mr Budak explained in his reasons that he formed the view that Mr Priestley's allegations against Ms Briggs were not sufficiently persuasive to warrant further investigation. Specifically, Mr Budak said that the letter and attachments that were said by Mr Priestley to have been divulged by Ms Briggs to the former Merit Protection Commissioner, Mr Lamond, were in fact received by Ms Briggs after Mr Lamond's departure for a position in another Department. Accordingly, the allegation that the documents had been passed by Ms Briggs to Mr Lamond for purposes connected with Mr Lamond's then current position as Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner was unfounded, as was the allegation that the receipt of the letter and attachments by Mr Lamond had prompted his resignation. He had already left the position.

Mr Priestley's letter of 27 August 2007 also contained allegations concerning breaches of the Code of Conduct by Mr Lamond himself. Mr Priestley appears to submit that Mr Budak was obliged to make a decision pursuant to clause 2.4.3 of the Determination to refer the allegations concerning Mr Lamond to the relevant officer holder.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Priestley v Godwin (Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner) (2008) 251 CLR 612</tocase>
<text>In his submissions, Mr Priestley raises various complaints about previous orders made by a judge of the Court. No appeal or application for leave to appeal was brought against the making of those orders in this Court. However, it appears that those orders were the subject of consideration by the High Court in Priestley v Godwin (Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner) (2008) 251 CLR 612. In that case, French CJ said that Mr Priestley's allegations regarding those previous orders were ' baseless '. I will not consider them further.

Mr Priestley also provided detailed submissions on the obligation to provide a statement of reasons within the meaning of the ADJR Act. That obligation is not disputed. Ms Godwin does not deny that such a general obligation exists as provided by the ADJR Act. Rather, she says that a decision was made on 18 September 2007, that reasons were given on 17 October 2007 and that no further decisions were made.

At the time that Mr Budak wrote to Mr Priestley informing him that he did not come to a new decision in his statement of reasons of 17 October 2007 and did not accept that he was obliged to provide a further statement of reasons, he was no longer the Acting Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner. This is of relevance because s 13(3) of the ADJR Act relevantly provides: 
 Where a person to whom a request is made under subsection (1) is of the opinion that the person who made the request was not entitled to make the request, the first-mentioned person may, within 28 days after receiving the request: 

 
 (a) give to the second-mentioned person notice in writing of his or her opinion; or...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thomson Australian Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/48.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 23 of the Federal Court Act provides that the Court has power, in relation to matters in which it has jurisdiction, to make orders of such kinds, including interlocutory orders, and to issue or direct the issue of writs of such kinds, as the Court thinks appropriate. Section 23 does not invest the Court with jurisdiction. Jurisdiction is conferred by other statutes ( Thomson Australian Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150 at 161).

Relevantly for these proceedings, Parliament has invested the Court with jurisdiction in relation to statements of reasons pursuant to s 13 of the ADJR Act. Section 13(4A) of the ADJR Act provides that the Court may, on application, make an order declaring that the person who made a request for a statement of reasons was, or was not, entitled to make the request. That section is the source of the Court's jurisdiction to make orders with respect to statements of reasons and, Ms Godwin submits, limits the Court's powers in granting relief to declaring that a person does, or does not have, an entitlement to make a request for a statement of reasons. A declaration that a person was entitled to make a request for a statement of reasons then requires the person to whom the request was made to provide such a statement within 28 days (s 13(4) of the ADJR Act).

Ms Godwin points to the procedures in s 13 of the ADJR Act. Mr Priestley made a request to Mr Budak for reasons for the decisions he says were made on 17 October 2007 (s 13(1)). Mr Budak formed the opinion that Mr Priestley was not entitled to make the request because there was no decision as alleged and gave Mr Priestley notice in writing of his opinion (purportedly under s 13(3)). Following the receipt of a s 13(3) notice, the course available to Mr Priestley would have been to apply to the Court for an order declaring that he was or was not entitled to make the request (s 13(4A)).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tooheys Ltd v Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs [1981] FCA 121 ; (1981) 36 ALR 64</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1981/121.html</AustLII>
<text>On 25 September 2007 Mr Priestley wrote to Mr Budak again, requesting that Mr Budak provide a statement of reasons pursuant to s 13 of the ADJR Act for: 
 [T] he refusal to accept my report of 27 August 2007 pursuant to paragraph 1(b), and [subclauses] (2) and (3) of clause 2.4.3 of [the Determination] ; 

 
 [T] he failure to investigate the alleged breaches of the Code of Conduct by the [Parliamentary Service Commissioner] ; and 

 
 [T] he failure to refer the report concerning alleged breaches of the [Code of Conduct] by the former Merit Protection Commissioner to the relevant office holder.

By covering letter bearing the date 22 September 2007, Mr Budak provided to Mr Priestley a document entitled "Statement of Reasons under Section 13 of Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 ". In that statement Mr Budak set out his decision and findings on material questions of fact. The statement of reasons was dated 17 October 2007. It is accepted that the September date on the covering letter was incorrect.

In relation to the first two matters for which Mr Priestley requested reasons, Mr Budak stated that, while he considered the letter of 27 August 2007 ' as potentially being ' a whistleblower's report, as a report pursuant to paragraph (1)(b) of clause 2.4.3 of the Determination, he did not consider that the matter warranted further investigation. Mr Budak also set out the findings which formed the basis of his decision that the matter did not warrant further investigation.

In a further letter to Mr Budak dated 19 November 2007, Mr Priestley accepted that Mr Budak had furnished a statement as required by s 13(2) of the ADJR Act. However, he added that: ' You correctly concluded that my letter of 27 August 2007 was a whistleblower's report as it was intended by me and as I had indicated in the letter. In consequence, therefore, you were obliged to reconsider the issue and in so doing [you] came to a new decision and refused to make a decision '. He requested a statement of reasons pursuant to s 13(1) of the ADJR Act for the alleged further decisions, which he described as decisions: 
 [T] o make no further inquiry into the alleged breaches of the Parliamentary Service Code of Conduct by [the Parliamentary Service Commissioner] ; and 

 
 [T] o receive and not refer the alleged breaches of the Parliamentary Service Code of Conduct by [the former Merit Protection Commissioner] to the appropriate office holder.

Mr Priestley also requested a statement of reasons for what he asserted was a refusal to investigate an alleged separate breach of the Code of Conduct by the Parliamentary Service Commissioner, namely, that she did not refer allegations made against the former Merit Protection Commissioner to the Presiding Officers.

It is apparent from the detailed submissions and assertions in his letter of 19 November 2007 that Mr Priestley considered that there had been a variation or revocation of the original decision. He asserted that the terms of the original decision showed that there had been a ' fundamental procedural failure ' to consider his letter of 27 August 2007 in accordance with s 48(1) of the Parliamentary Service Act and clause 2.4.3 of the Determination. It followed, he said, that Mr Budak had been obliged to revisit the issue and in so doing had come to a new decision and refused or failed to make a decision.

Ms Godwin submits that, if there were a decision for the purposes of s 13 of the ADJR Act, Mr Priestley is not a person aggrieved by that decision. She submits that there is nothing in Mr Priestley's application which indicates the manner in which Mr Priestley alleges his interests were affected, adversely or otherwise, by the decisions he alleges Mr Budak made on 17 October 2007. Accordingly, she submits, Mr Priestley is not a person aggrieved within the meaning of s 3(4)(a)(i) of the ADJR Act for the purposes of ss 5 and 13 of that Act. Ms Godwin submits that Mr Priestley has no special interest as described in Australian Conservation Foundation Incorporated v The Commonwealth of Australia (1980) 146 CLR 493 at 530-531. She submits that, as the High Court pointed out, a belief that particular conduct should be taken or prevented is not sufficient to give the possessor of that belief locus standi . Mr Priestley is not, she says, a person interested, in that he is not likely to gain some advantage, other than the satisfaction of righting a wrong, upholding a principle or winning a contest. Ms Godwin submits that Mr Priestley cannot demonstrate and has not demonstrated an interest in Mr Budak's alleged decision beyond an interest being held by virtue of being a member of the public, albeit a public linked to Parliamentary Service employees ( Tooheys Ltd v Minister for Business and Consumer Affairs [1981] FCA 121 ; (1981) 36 ALR 64).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>