<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (ACN 064 829 616) (No 3) [2009] FCA 53 (5 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/53.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (2007) 242 ALR 370</tocase>
<text>On two previous occasions I have refused summarily to dismiss Mr Kowalski's application and gave him leave to file and serve an amended application and statement of claim: see Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (2007) 242 ALR 370 and Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691. On the latter occasion I indicated that I was providing him with his last opportunity to provide an intelligible and unobjectionable pleading. I have, though with little optimism, recommended to him that he obtain competent legal assistance. He has to date demonstrated little understanding both of the law he seeks to invoke in his own favour and of how to present, albeit in lay form, a clear statement of the claim he seeks to prosecute. My recommendation was not accepted. As he has done in so many proceedings in this Court and in other courts and tribunals concerning his relationship with his past employer, Mitsubishi Motors Australia Ltd (MMAL), he acted without legal representation on the motion presently before me. That motion, brought by the two respondents, again seeks the summary dismissal of the proceeding pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) or else under O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/691.html</AustLII>
<text>On two previous occasions I have refused summarily to dismiss Mr Kowalski's application and gave him leave to file and serve an amended application and statement of claim: see Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (2007) 242 ALR 370 and Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 691. On the latter occasion I indicated that I was providing him with his last opportunity to provide an intelligible and unobjectionable pleading. I have, though with little optimism, recommended to him that he obtain competent legal assistance. He has to date demonstrated little understanding both of the law he seeks to invoke in his own favour and of how to present, albeit in lay form, a clear statement of the claim he seeks to prosecute. My recommendation was not accepted. As he has done in so many proceedings in this Court and in other courts and tribunals concerning his relationship with his past employer, Mitsubishi Motors Australia Ltd (MMAL), he acted without legal representation on the motion presently before me. That motion, brought by the two respondents, again seeks the summary dismissal of the proceeding pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) or else under O 20 r 5 of the Federal Court Rules .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Paramasivam v University of New South Wales [2007] FCAFC 176</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/176.html</AustLII>
<text>This is not a matter in which it is necessary to consider in detail the varying and by no means harmonious views that have been expressed by judges as to the burden of the "no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting" formula and of the nature of, and limits to, the assessment it requires be made. As I have indicated, I have a plethora of evidence before me and the principal task it presents is the making of an assessment of it, as a matter of fact, as to whether Mr Kowalski has no reasonable prospect of proving each of the facts necessary to perfect the elements of the causes of action he advances in his pleading: cf Paramasivam v University of New South Wales [2007] FCAFC 176 at [41] ; see also Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Co of Australia Ltd [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 at [23] . Beyond that, as I will indicate, there is also a question whether his claims are legally untenable in any event.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Co of Australia Ltd [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/60.html</AustLII>
<text>This is not a matter in which it is necessary to consider in detail the varying and by no means harmonious views that have been expressed by judges as to the burden of the "no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting" formula and of the nature of, and limits to, the assessment it requires be made. As I have indicated, I have a plethora of evidence before me and the principal task it presents is the making of an assessment of it, as a matter of fact, as to whether Mr Kowalski has no reasonable prospect of proving each of the facts necessary to perfect the elements of the causes of action he advances in his pleading: cf Paramasivam v University of New South Wales [2007] FCAFC 176 at [41] ; see also Jefferson Ford Pty Ltd v Ford Motor Co of Australia Ltd [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 at [23] . Beyond that, as I will indicate, there is also a question whether his claims are legally untenable in any event.

It is well accepted that the moving party bears the onus of persuading the Court that the applicant has no reasonable prospects of success. But once that party has established a prima facie case that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of success, the applicant must respond by pointing to specific factual or evidentiary disputes that make a trial necessary: Jefferson Ford at [127].

Importantly for present purposes, as Gordon J observed in Jefferson Ford at [130] (citations omitted): 
 ... where there is a real issue of fact relevant to a pleaded cause of action, it is unlikely that that part of the proceeding has no prospect of success ... So, for example, if the pleadings, affidavits, and other materials considered in connection with the summary judgment motion, reveal a factual dispute and that factual dispute must be resolved to determine whether or not the claim succeeds, it cannot be said that the claim has "no reasonable prospect of success" ... On the other hand, if the factual contest is unnecessary to the resolution of the cause of action pleaded, then in the absence of other relevant material, there is nothing to prevent the court entering judgment on that claim. 
 Breach of Trust/Fiduciary Duty

Doing the best I can with the underlying material which is said to found the complaints made, and conscious of the opportunities I have given Mr Kowalski to propound a cause of action, albeit in lay terms, I have as I have foreshadowed, concluded that the proceedings should be summarily dismissed. While it will not often be the case that a Court will be required to or should properly conduct as detailed an examination of the materials put on by the parties as I have, this is not an ordinary proceeding with an ordinary and uneventful provenance. The evolving manner in which Mr Kowalski has perceived his grievances and has formulated them to secure the relief he has in mind, has necessitated that I conduct in essence a "preliminary trial": Jefferson Ford , at [23].

I intend to deal briefly with the factual material chronologically, focussing primarily upon those matters which have led me to my conclusion.

It is, I consider, important to acknowledge that in 1992 both the insurer and the Trustee declined Mr Kowalski's formal application for a TPD Benefit. The Trustee's decision has not been challenged in this proceeding. I mention this decision because, as the Trustee later recognised, it did not preclude the further consideration of whether Mr Kowalski may have been entitled to a TPD Benefit when his employment terminated in 1994.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>White Industries Aust Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 511 ; (2007) 160 FCR 298</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/511.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 31A is not concerned as such with the bare question whether a person's pleading discloses a reasonable cause of action. Its concern is with substance and not just form. But as Lindgren J observed in White Industries Aust Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 511 ; (2007) 160 FCR 298 at [47] , while the existence of a reasonable cause of action and the pleading of a reasonable cause of action remain distinct concepts 
 [a] failure after ample opportunity to plead a reasonable cause of action may suggest that none exists and therefore that the applicant has no reasonable prospects of success.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2007/1173.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).

For present purposes, I accept that the grounds upon which a court will review an exercise of a superannuation trustee's discretionary determination are essentially those stated by McGarvie J in Karger v Paul [1984] VR 161 , though they have been somewhat elaborated if not adapted: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd at [8] in the superannuation context. They are that (i) the discretion was not exercised in good faith; (ii) there was not a real and genuine consideration of the correct question; (iii) the discretion was not exercised for the purpose for which it was conferred; (iv) if the trustee has given reasons for its exercise of discretion, those reasons were not sound; and (v) if the material before the trustee can be identified, that the trustee's decision was one that no reasonable person could come to on that material.

There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.

Finally, though it is not a matter which it is appropriate for me to enter upon in this proceeding, I acknowledge that there remains a real question as to the appropriateness of applying to superannuation trusts as of course principles of review evolved in contexts of settlor bounty and charity contexts which are remote from the modern employment relationship: see eg Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd ; Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme at [8]; and see generally Dal Pont and Chalmers, Equity and Trusts in Australia , 727 ff (4 th ed, 2007). THE CLAIMS 
 (i) The 1994 Claim: FASC paras 14, 16, 29.1 and 30</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2004/94.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).

There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2003/945.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//vic/VICSC/2000/107.html</AustLII>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).

There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1</tocase>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995)</tocase>
<text>In Kowalski (No 2) I set out in relatively short form the principles governing the review of a decision of a superannuation trustee denying a member's entitlement to a claimed benefit. As I then indicated there is now a significant body of Australian case law dealing with that matter and many of the cases have involved claims for total and permanent disability benefits having criteria similar to those embedded in cl 1(6) of the Deed: see eg Jeffrey Guy Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 1173 ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd [2004] NSWSC 94 ; Sayseng v Kellogg Superannuation Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 945 ; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd [2000] VSC 107 ; Minehan v AGL Employees Superannuation Pty Ltd (1998) 134 ACTR 1 ; Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd (unreported, Supreme Court of New South Wales, Bryson J, 3 March 1995).

Finally, though it is not a matter which it is appropriate for me to enter upon in this proceeding, I acknowledge that there remains a real question as to the appropriateness of applying to superannuation trusts as of course principles of review evolved in contexts of settlor bounty and charity contexts which are remote from the modern employment relationship: see eg Vidovic v Email Superannuation Pty Ltd ; Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme at [8]; and see generally Dal Pont and Chalmers, Equity and Trusts in Australia , 727 ff (4 th ed, 2007). THE CLAIMS 
 (i) The 1994 Claim: FASC paras 14, 16, 29.1 and 30</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Karger v Paul [1984] VR 161</tocase>
<text>For present purposes, I accept that the grounds upon which a court will review an exercise of a superannuation trustee's discretionary determination are essentially those stated by McGarvie J in Karger v Paul [1984] VR 161 , though they have been somewhat elaborated if not adapted: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd at [8] in the superannuation context. They are that (i) the discretion was not exercised in good faith; (ii) there was not a real and genuine consideration of the correct question; (iii) the discretion was not exercised for the purpose for which it was conferred; (iv) if the trustee has given reasons for its exercise of discretion, those reasons were not sound; and (v) if the material before the trustee can be identified, that the trustee's decision was one that no reasonable person could come to on that material.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-17</tocase>
<text>There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601</tocase>
<text>There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139</tocase>
<text>There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397</tocase>
<text>There are three additional matters I should emphasise. First, I have emphasised that it is the review of the Trustee's decision that is of present concern. The present is not a case in which the Trustee was, in substance, deciding a question that was assigned by the Deed itself to an insurer: cf Chammas v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [No 1] (1993) 7 ANZ Ins Cas 61-175. Secondly, while both under the general law and under cl 3(1) of the trust deed the Trustee had no duty to give reasons for a determination adverse to Mr Kowalski, a failure to give reasons in circumstances where explanation might be called for is another matter. As Young J observed in Maciejewski v Telstra Super Pty Ltd (1998) 44 NSWLR 601 at 604, in dealing with the suggestion that because a trustee is not bound to give any reasons, therefore the matter is completely unreviewable: 
 Nothing could be further from the truth. Indeed, whilst trustees do not have to give reasons in a case where a plaintiff puts forward a prima facie case that the trustee's discretion has miscarried, the absence of reasons and the absence of any evidence before the Court as to what happened, will tend to make that prima facie case a virtual certainty. 

 
This view has been endorsed in many subsequent cases: see Baker v Local Government Superannuation Scheme Pty Ltd ; Hay v Total Risk Management Pty Ltd ; Alcoa of Australia Retirement Plan Pty Ltd v Thompson (2002) 116 FCR 139 at [37]; Flegeltaub v Telstra Super Pty Ltd ; see also Butler LM, "Reviewing Trustees' Decisions: The Right to Reasons" (1999) 7 Aust Property LJ 251. Thirdly, as the Trustee has considered Mr Kowalski's entitlement to a TPD Benefit on a number of occasions and has decided against it, an issue that presently arises is whether, if at all, it is obliged to reconsider that matter and, if so, in what circumstances. These issues have helpfully been considered by the Full Court of Western Australia in Tonkin v Western Mining Corporation Ltd (1998) 10 ANZ Ins Cases 61-397 and in a context not dissimilar from the present. In a judgment endorsed by the other members of the Court, Franklyn J made observations which though lengthy are presently relevant in several respects (at 74,270):
 
 In my view, having regard to the terms of the Deed and the relevant definition, there is no obligation on the trustee, on an application for the TPD Benefit supported by evidence inadequate to give rise to the necessary opinion, to seek out, on its own initiative, evidence for its consideration and so strain to obtain evidence relevant to the formation of the necessary opinion, thereby attempting to bring within the definition a member not otherwise within its terms. It may, however, in the exercise of its fiduciary duty and as a matter of discretion, if it considers it appropriate, seek and obtain additional medical evidence. It may also, as a matter of discretion, require medical evidence to be submitted to it for the purposes of its consideration. As trustee, it is not an adversary either for or against an applicant for the benefit. Relevantly, it has a duty only to act in accordance with the trust. If it fails to perform the same, the court will compel it to do so or do so for it. It is not bound by any rules as to how it exercises a discretion conferred on it, save such as it is obliged to comply with by the terms of the Deed, provided always that it must act honestly and in good faith, on an informed view of whether or not to exercise its discretion, and exercise the power with due consideration for the purpose for which it was conferred and for no ulterior purpose. In the case of powers conferred on it and as to whether it should do or refrain from doing something, it must exercise its judgment actively and honestly and act accordingly. The court will not control a trustee in the exercise of its purely discretionary powers unless it is acting mala fide or has misconceived the nature of its discretion and acted upon that misconception. When appointed to exercise a trust according to discretion, a trustee is not bound to state reasons for any conclusion at which it may have arrived and on which it has acted, but again the discretion must be exercised with an absence of indirect motive with honesty of intention and on a fair consideration of the issues. The duty of the court generally is to see that the discretion of the trustee has been exercised in this manner and not to deal with the accuracy of the conclusion at which it may have arrived. See Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , 5 th Ed, p 372-379. 

 
 In my opinion, it has at all times been open to the appellant to submit further medical evidence, including the reports relied on in para 17.2A to the respondent for its consideration pursuant to the Deed definition in respect of the claim for the TPD Benefit. In such case the respondent is bound to give them proper consideration. No time limit is fixed or imposed by the Deed for making application for the Benefit or for the required consideration of medical evidence. Whether any statutory limitation might apply is not relevant to our consideration as no issue in that respect has been raised. In the event of the respondent, having considered medical evidence before it, failing to form the necessary opinion there is nothing in the Deed or rules to inhibit the appellant from providing, for its further consideration, further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. There is nothing in the Deed to lead to the conclusion that, once having failed or refused to form the necessary opinion after consideration of the medical evidence then before it, the respondent is under no obligation to consider further medical evidence relevant to the formation of that opinion. Indeed, in my opinion, on the proper construction of the Deed and having regard to the fiduciary nature of the trustee's obligations, the respondent, if requested to do so, is bound to consider such evidence relevant to formation of the opinion as may from time to time be put before it. Consequently, medical evidence, whether coming into existence prior or subsequent to any particular failure or refusal to form the necessary opinion will necessarily have to be considered if made available by or on behalf of the applicant for that purpose. 

 
I should note that for present purposes the respondents have conceded that, beyond medical evidence, if other material is provided to a trustee and is of such character as would lead a reasonable trustee to consider whether or not to reconsider its former opinion, that material will have to be considered.

Turning now to the 1994 claim in the FASC, several matters seem indisputable. First, no formal application was made of the time of termination for a TPD Benefit. Mr Kowalski does not suggest otherwise. Secondly, the Trustee was unaware that it should consider Mr Kowalski's termination entitlements with such a benefit in mind. It did not inquire into whether there was medical evidence capable of supporting such an entitlement. It had no need, or obligation, to in the circumstances: cf Tonkin , at 74,269. I note that before it could pay a member a TPD Benefit under Rule C7, the Trustee was required to be of the opinion "after consideration of medical evidence satisfactory to them [sic]" that the member is incapacitated to the extent required by the Rule.

The Trustee in this matter simply paid a Rule C9 retirement benefit. If the Trustee was later presented with an application for, or medical evidence in support of, a TPD Benefit, the paying of the Rule C9 benefit would not have relieved the Trustee of its obligation to consider that application. This is not to say that the C9 decision was vitiated by some breach of duty on the Trustee's part. Rather, its correctness was examinable because an error may have been made in providing the member with his or her entitlement as a member. Under the Rules of Annex C, the member was entitled to be paid the benefits of the particular Rule which his or her circumstances required. The Trustee may have had to be satisfied that the member met the criteria of a particular rule, but it did not have an unfettered discretion to decide which benefit might be provided to a member. As I will indicate below, the Trustee subsequently considered and rejected Mr Kowalski's claim for a TPD Benefit from the cessation of his employment in 1994.

Mr Kowalski's 1994 claim proceeds on two false assumptions. The first, is that the Trustee had, in the circumstances, a duty to consider whether he had an entitlement to a TPD Benefit. I need not repeat what I have said above. The second is that the Trustee was obliged to consider Dr McFarlane's "report" (as the 29 April 1993 interview notes are misdescribed). There is no evidence at all that the Trustee was informed of, or provided with the report, at any time relevant to the determination of Mr Kowalski's 1994 retirement benefit. Mr Kowalski does not contend to the contrary.

While it is a trustee's duty to act in the interests of its beneficiaries, absent an express power of dictation, a trustee is not the pawn of a beneficiary. As Tonkin indicates, a beneficiary is entitled to seek the reconsideration of a decision affecting his or her interests unless this is precluded by the nature of the decision itself or by the terms of the trust instrument. But where the decision, as here, requires the Trustee to form a particular opinion and that opinion has previously been formed adversely to the beneficiary, the Trustee is not obliged to reconsider that opinion absent some reason for so doing. Where, as here, what is raised by the beneficiary is matter which the Trustee has previously had raised before it and dealt with, the Trustee is entitled to decline to re-entertain that same matter in the future unless, because of change of circumstances or otherwise, that decision was not one that a reasonable person could then make. Such is not the position here.

Accordingly, I am satisfied that having regard to the material underlying Mr Kowalski's 2005 claim, that claim has no reasonable prospects of success.

I am conscious that in reaching the conclusions I have, I have made no direct reference to the medical evidence or to issues of causation. As to the medical evidence, I accept that there was material before the Trustee in 2001 which both supported and contradicted Mr Kowalski's position. The Trustee in light of this had to make its own decision. While Mr Kowalski asserts the Trustee's opinion was incorrect, that is not the question with which I am concerned. Not being aware of all of the material that was before the Trustee when it took its decisions in 2001 and 2005, I am left to consider if it can properly be alleged that there was not a real and genuine consideration of the correct question by the Trustee. There is nothing before me reasonably to suggest such was the case and hence should be examined at trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Halloran v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 913</tocase>
<text>(vii) On 16 April 2003, Colonial wrote to Mr Smelt concerning Mr Kowalski and the life insurance policy relating to him. The letter stated in part: 
 We refer to the claim by Mr Kowalski who was a life insured covered under a group life insurance policy ("the policy") issued by the State Government Insurance Commission (SGIC) ("now Colonial") to Mitsubishi Motors Australia Employees' Superannuation Fund. 

 
 Mr Kowalski made a claim for Total and Permanent ("TPD") benefit on 20 February, 1992 claiming that the Life Insured had been absent from employment since 16 August, 1991 as a result of emotional stress and pathologically intense state of anxiety and that he was TPD. 

 
 After considering medical evidence available to it, SGIC denied the claim for TPD benefits on 4 August, 1992 on the basis that the evidence supported that the insured was not TPD. We note that Colonial subsequently re-examined Mr Kowalski's claim and affirmed its decision to deny the claim by letter dated 13 June, 2001. 

 
 We note you subsequently requested that Colonial review the claim on 3 July, 2001 taking into consideration further medical evidence. Colonial reviewed the claim at this time and communicated its decision to you via email correspondence on or about August, 2001. Mr Kowalski however, alleges that Colonial did not re-examine his claim as requested. We deny this allegation. 

 
 Mr Kowalski has contacted Colonial on a number of occasions regarding his claim including a recent letter dated 14 February, 2003. We note that the policy is between Colonial and the Trustee. Therefore, we are writing to Mr Kowalski informing him that any future questions he has about the policy should be directed to the Trustee and not Colonial. 

 
 We have examined our file and provide the following summary of the assessment of Mr Kowalski's claim for your information: 

 
 The insured's claim has been assessed by determining whether he was TPD as at February, 1992. We refer to the policy provisions for an explanation of the assessment of the insured's claim in this way. Under the policy the period of cover ends on the earliest to occur of: 

 
 - the end of the term of group life policy or its earliest termination, or 

 
 - the termination of employment, or 

 
 - cessation of gainful employment by the life insured as reflected in the following provisions of the Group Life Policy. 

 
 Clause 4 (Duration of Cover) of the Group Life Policy provides: 

 
 "The insurance cover evidenced by this Policy issued pursuant to the Proposal shall be effective from midnight of the Commencement Date until midnight of the same date of the month as the anniversary in which the contract guarantee period expires." 

 
 "Contract Guarantee Period" in the Group Life Policy is defined to mean the period from the commencement date to 1 st February, 1992. 

 
 Clause 5(2) of the policy provides that "Cover in respect of a Life Insured ceases at the earliest of the following events" including: 

 
 (ii) termination of service with the employer and 

 
 (v) cessation of gainful employment 

 
 Accordingly, the insured's claim must be assessed by determining whether he was TPD as at February, 1992 or any earlier date on which the insured's employment was terminated prior to this date or the insured ceased gainful employment prior to this date. 

 
 If you would like us to reassess the life insured's claim then you should provide us with documents that you consider relevant to whether the life insured was TPD as at February, 1992. 

 
 We note that we are already in possession of copies of the following documents: 

 Medical Report of Dr Scanlon dated 28 October, 1991 
 Workers Compensation Medical Certificate dated 23 February 1993 including comments by Dr Jagerman 
 Notes of JA Fountain, solicitor acting for Mitsubishi Motors Australia Ltd attending Dr McFarlane dated 29 April 1993. 
 
 Please note that we are in possession of several other documents however these are not relevant to the reassessment of the life insured's TPD claim as at February, 1992 and therefore have not been listed. 

 
 Please provide any additional documents, which you consider are appropriate if you consider that Mr Kowalski's claim should be reassessed.
 (Emphasis added.) 

 
This letter was copied to Mr Kowalski. There is nothing in the material to which I have been taken to suggest that the Trustee sought the reassessment referred to in the last quoted paragraph or that it disputed the insurer's view as to the period of cover. I should add I have emphasised the paragraph where Colonial limited its liability to February 1992. While this may have been the case insofar as concerned Colonial in respect of any TPD Benefit claim, it was not the case for the Trustee. From February 1992 until the termination date in 1994, the Trustee "self insured" in respect of any possible TPD Benefit claim by Mr Kowalski: on insuring benefits see Trust Deed cl 8; see also Halloran v Harwood Nominees Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 913.

(viii) In mid-2003 Mr Kowalski and others acting on his behalf sought to obtain a copy of Colonial's determination of August 2001. The Trustee's solicitors denied having a copy of it.

(ix) In March and April of 2004 the Trustee's solicitors wrote to Mr Kowalski and to his union indicating on instructions that no formal application for a TPD Benefit was made to the Trustee in October 1998. In the letter to Mr Kowalski, the solicitors further observed that, in consequence, no such application was considered or rejected at that time.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Trident General Insurance Co Ltd v McNiece Bros Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 44 ; (1988) 165 CLR 107</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/44.html</AustLII>
<text>I readily acknowledge that the trust device has in practice proved "a disappointing and unreliable instrument" for circumventing the privity doctrine: see Cheshire and Fifoot's Law of Contract , [7.44] (9 th Aust ed, 2008). Nonetheless, in this particular setting both where trust and contract so obviously interact: see Dal Pont and Chalmers, at 727; and where the contracting parties intent was, on the face of the Heads of Agreement, to bring the Trustee within its purview so both to benefit and to burden it, the observations of Deane J in Trident General Insurance Co Ltd v McNiece Bros Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 44 ; (1988) 165 CLR 107 at 147-148 are singularly apposite. His Honour observed that the requisite intention of the contracting parties to constitute a trust of a promise for a third party should be inferred: 
 ... if it clearly appears that it was the intention of the promise that the third party should himself be entitled to insist upon performance of the promise and receipt of the benefit and if trust is, in the circumstances, the appropriate legal mechanism for giving effect to that intention. A fortiori, equity's requirement of an intention to create a trust will be at least prima facie satisfied if the terms of the contract expressly or impliedly manifest that intention as the joint intention of both promisor and promise. 

 
 ... If the trustee of the promise declines to institute [proceedings for the enforcement of the promise or damages for its breach], the beneficiary can bring proceedings against the promisor in his own name, joining the trustee as defendant. 

 
See also Bahr v Nicolay (No 2) [1988] HCA 16 ; (1988) 164 CLR 604 at 618; Ford and Lee, Principles of the Law of Trusts , [17.11010]. It is not necessary that the contracting parties know and understand that they are creating a trust. It is sufficient that they intend to create a relationship which, in equity, conforms to that of a trust: see Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] 2 AC 164 at [71]; Ford and Lee at [2035].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bahr v Nicolay (No 2) [1988] HCA 16 ; (1988) 164 CLR 604</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/16.html</AustLII>
<text>I readily acknowledge that the trust device has in practice proved "a disappointing and unreliable instrument" for circumventing the privity doctrine: see Cheshire and Fifoot's Law of Contract , [7.44] (9 th Aust ed, 2008). Nonetheless, in this particular setting both where trust and contract so obviously interact: see Dal Pont and Chalmers, at 727; and where the contracting parties intent was, on the face of the Heads of Agreement, to bring the Trustee within its purview so both to benefit and to burden it, the observations of Deane J in Trident General Insurance Co Ltd v McNiece Bros Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 44 ; (1988) 165 CLR 107 at 147-148 are singularly apposite. His Honour observed that the requisite intention of the contracting parties to constitute a trust of a promise for a third party should be inferred: 
 ... if it clearly appears that it was the intention of the promise that the third party should himself be entitled to insist upon performance of the promise and receipt of the benefit and if trust is, in the circumstances, the appropriate legal mechanism for giving effect to that intention. A fortiori, equity's requirement of an intention to create a trust will be at least prima facie satisfied if the terms of the contract expressly or impliedly manifest that intention as the joint intention of both promisor and promise. 

 
 ... If the trustee of the promise declines to institute [proceedings for the enforcement of the promise or damages for its breach], the beneficiary can bring proceedings against the promisor in his own name, joining the trustee as defendant. 

 
See also Bahr v Nicolay (No 2) [1988] HCA 16 ; (1988) 164 CLR 604 at 618; Ford and Lee, Principles of the Law of Trusts , [17.11010]. It is not necessary that the contracting parties know and understand that they are creating a trust. It is sufficient that they intend to create a relationship which, in equity, conforms to that of a trust: see Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] 2 AC 164 at [71]; Ford and Lee at [2035].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] 2 AC 164</tocase>
<text>I readily acknowledge that the trust device has in practice proved "a disappointing and unreliable instrument" for circumventing the privity doctrine: see Cheshire and Fifoot's Law of Contract , [7.44] (9 th Aust ed, 2008). Nonetheless, in this particular setting both where trust and contract so obviously interact: see Dal Pont and Chalmers, at 727; and where the contracting parties intent was, on the face of the Heads of Agreement, to bring the Trustee within its purview so both to benefit and to burden it, the observations of Deane J in Trident General Insurance Co Ltd v McNiece Bros Pty Ltd [1988] HCA 44 ; (1988) 165 CLR 107 at 147-148 are singularly apposite. His Honour observed that the requisite intention of the contracting parties to constitute a trust of a promise for a third party should be inferred: 
 ... if it clearly appears that it was the intention of the promise that the third party should himself be entitled to insist upon performance of the promise and receipt of the benefit and if trust is, in the circumstances, the appropriate legal mechanism for giving effect to that intention. A fortiori, equity's requirement of an intention to create a trust will be at least prima facie satisfied if the terms of the contract expressly or impliedly manifest that intention as the joint intention of both promisor and promise. 

 
 ... If the trustee of the promise declines to institute [proceedings for the enforcement of the promise or damages for its breach], the beneficiary can bring proceedings against the promisor in his own name, joining the trustee as defendant. 

 
See also Bahr v Nicolay (No 2) [1988] HCA 16 ; (1988) 164 CLR 604 at 618; Ford and Lee, Principles of the Law of Trusts , [17.11010]. It is not necessary that the contracting parties know and understand that they are creating a trust. It is sufficient that they intend to create a relationship which, in equity, conforms to that of a trust: see Twinsectra Ltd v Yardley [2002] 2 AC 164 at [71]; Ford and Lee at [2035].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wilson v Darling Island Stevedoring &amp; Lighterage Co Ltd [1956] HCA 8 ; (1956) 95 CLR 43</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1956/8.html</AustLII>
<text>Importantly for present purposes, as Gordon J observed in Jefferson Ford at [130] (citations omitted): 
 ... where there is a real issue of fact relevant to a pleaded cause of action, it is unlikely that that part of the proceeding has no prospect of success ... So, for example, if the pleadings, affidavits, and other materials considered in connection with the summary judgment motion, reveal a factual dispute and that factual dispute must be resolved to determine whether or not the claim succeeds, it cannot be said that the claim has "no reasonable prospect of success" ... On the other hand, if the factual contest is unnecessary to the resolution of the cause of action pleaded, then in the absence of other relevant material, there is nothing to prevent the court entering judgment on that claim. 
 Breach of Trust/Fiduciary Duty

While it is not strictly necessary that I express a concluded view on this foreshadowed defence, and while I share the view of Fullagar J in Wilson v Darling Island Stevedoring &amp; Lighterage Co Ltd [1956] HCA 8 ; (1956) 95 CLR 43 at 67 that it is "difficult to understand the reluctance which courts have sometimes shown to infer a trust in such cases" a reluctance I acknowledge I am satisfied that having regard not only to the text of the agreement but also to the known surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the contract: cf Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; a court would readily infer a trust intention in this matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/35.html</AustLII>
<text>While it is not strictly necessary that I express a concluded view on this foreshadowed defence, and while I share the view of Fullagar J in Wilson v Darling Island Stevedoring &amp; Lighterage Co Ltd [1956] HCA 8 ; (1956) 95 CLR 43 at 67 that it is "difficult to understand the reluctance which courts have sometimes shown to infer a trust in such cases" a reluctance I acknowledge I am satisfied that having regard not only to the text of the agreement but also to the known surrounding circumstances and the purpose and object of the contract: cf Pacific Carriers Ltd v BNP Paribas [2004] HCA 35 ; (2004) 218 CLR 451 at [22] ; a court would readily infer a trust intention in this matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lidden v Composite Buyers (1996) 67 FCR 560</tocase>
<text>While ordinarily MMAL would be a necessary party to the raising of such a defence: see Lidden v Composite Buyers (1996) 67 FCR 560 ; see also Jacobs' Law of Trusts in Australia , [2303] (7 th ed, 2006); the respondents acknowledge were the matter to proceed to trial, MMAL could be joined as a party for the purpose of enforcing the trust.

I should add that, while the Trustee did not seek to insist on its rights for the purpose of the 2001 reconsideration and properly so given Mr Smelt's assurance at the time of the mediation agreement that he would raise the TPD claim with Colonial the Trustee has done nothing that could be said (i) to amount to a renunciation of its rights; or (ii) to found an estoppel against it for the future.

Given this available defence, I am satisfied it provides a further basis for concluding that Mr Kowalski's application has no reasonable prospects of success.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>