<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wingecarribee Shire Council v Lehman Bros Australia Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 532 (19 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/532.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority (NSW) [2006] HCA 27 ; (2006) 226 CLR 256</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/27.html</AustLII>
<text>The protection of the processes of the Court and the administration of justice which this involves may, in a proper case, extend to asset preservation orders against third parties to the principal litigation: Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority (NSW) [2006] HCA 27 ; (2006) 226 CLR 256 at 265 per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne and Crennan JJ (citing from the joint judgments of Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Callinan JJ in Cardile 198 CLR at 395 [25] and in CSR Ltd v Signa Insurance Australia Limited [1997] HCA 33 ; (1997) 189 CLR 345 at 391).

The effect of the administration, as Pt 5.3A contemplates, will be to bind all creditors, including the council, in the event that a deed of company arrangement is entered into and is not terminated. Because that may produce outcomes that possibly may impact on the conduct of the current proceedings in a way that is not necessarily the same as in the ordinary course of every other piece of litigation, I am of opinion that it is appropriate to require production of the insurance information sought having regard to considerations to which I have referred: Jackson [1987] HCA 23 ; 162 CLR 612 ; Batistatos [2006] HCA 27 ; 226 CLR 256 ; Lopez [1997] FCA 454.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd v Price Waterhouse (1996) 68 SASR 19</tocase>
<text>Significantly, however, his Honour held that the Court, as a matter of jurisdiction had power to grant the relief sought. Lehman Brothers argues, however, that in formulating the limits of this power the Court should be guided by the decision of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia in Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd v Price Waterhouse (1996) 68 SASR 19. In that case, there were solvent defendants. The evidence established that they would be unlikely to be able to meet more than the costs of a lengthy and highly complicated piece of litigation, in circumstances, were the plaintiff successful, which might result in an award of very substantial damages. The Full Court held that the defendants could not be required to discover documents relating to their insurance position or otherwise to produce them in accordance with particular rules of the Supreme Court of South Australia. The Full Court was unanimous in that view, although Cox J dissented on the basis that he felt constrained to follow an earlier decision to the contrary of the Full Court of the Supreme Court of South Australia. Importantly, in that case, as on the evidence now before me, the insurer had not declined liability under the professional indemnity policy. There the insurer treated itself as having had a claim made on it, but had not at that stage either admitted or denied liability. Rather, the insurer was treating the claim as one which might attract liability under the relevant policy.

Perry J accepted that an earlier decision of the Full Court, J N Taylor Holdings Limited (In liq) v Bond (1993) 59 SASR 432 , illustrated that an insurer may be properly joined as a defendant, where, first, it had denied liability and, secondly, there was a need to ensure that if the proceedings went ahead, the insurer would be bound by the findings of fact and law that may enliven liability in its insured: see Beneficial Finance 68 SASR at 28. However, his Honour concluded that because the insurer was not denying liability under the policy, any attempt to have access to the insurance documents must, in those circumstances, have amounted to nothing more than a fishing exercise designed to reveal whether the documents indicated a basis for the plaintiff seeking a declaration. He held that the necessity or desirability of a declaration that the insurance responded to the claim could not be demonstrated at that stage. In that way, he distinguished the earlier decision in J N Taylor 59 SASR 432: see Beneficial Finance 69 SASR at 36 and at 52-53, Lander J was of a similar view.

In my opinion, Beneficial Finance 68 SASR 19 is distinguishable. The current application is not an application for discovery but for production of documents. I accept that considerations relevant to the issue of discovery may also govern or assist in the formulation of discretionary judgments as to whether documents ought be produced in particular circumstances.

But the present circumstances are that the council is involved in the current litigation and an event has occurred in its course that has given rise to this application being made. That event is the administration of Lehman Brothers. No longer is Lehman Brothers the same entity as that with which the council dealt unlike in Beneficial Finance 68 SASR 19 , where the plaintiff had to take the solvent defendants as it found them. The same circumstances that enlivened Olney J's exercise of discretion to order production in Lopez [1997] FCA 454 have been introduced here by the intervening event of the administration and the consequent, inferred admission that Lehman Brothers is insolvent.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cardile v LED Builders Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 18 ; (1999) 198 CLR 380</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/18.html</AustLII>
<text>The power of the Court to require a party to proceedings in which relief is sought against it to disclose its assets has been established authoritatively in Jackson v Sterling Industries Limited [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612. In the leading judgment, Deane J ( Jackson 162 CLR at 622-623) discussed the power to make what are now known as Mareva orders ( Cardile v LED Builders Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 18 ; (1999) 198 CLR 380 at 401 [42] ) saying that (omitting citations): 
 "That general power has been held to encompass an order requiring the disclosure by a defendant of his assets ... As a general proposition, it should now be accepted in this country that "a Mareva injunction can be granted ... if the circumstances are such that there is a danger of [the defendant's] absconding, or a danger of the assets being removed out of the jurisdiction or disposed of within the jurisdiction, or otherwise dealt with so that there is a danger that the plaintiff, if he gets judgment, will not be able to get it satisfied"."

I am of opinion that the purposes of Pt 5.3A are relevant and do inform the exercise of the Court's discretion in this application to order production of documents of the kind sought. However, those purposes do not deny to the Court power properly to control and determine what orders it ought make in each particular case in the interests of the administration of justice, pursuant to its powers under s 23 of the Federal Court of Australia Act , or in its inherent or implied jurisdiction to ensure the protection of its process from any abuse: cf: Cardile 198 CLR at 396 [33]. The power of the Court to prevent abuse of its process comprehends a power to protect the integrity of its processes once set in motion. That includes the power to preserve the efficacy of the execution that would lie against a prospective judgment debtor.

The protection of the processes of the Court and the administration of justice which this involves may, in a proper case, extend to asset preservation orders against third parties to the principal litigation: Batistatos v Roads and Traffic Authority (NSW) [2006] HCA 27 ; (2006) 226 CLR 256 at 265 per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne and Crennan JJ (citing from the joint judgments of Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Callinan JJ in Cardile 198 CLR at 395 [25] and in CSR Ltd v Signa Insurance Australia Limited [1997] HCA 33 ; (1997) 189 CLR 345 at 391).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Hearne v Street [2008] HCA 36 ; (2008) 235 CLR 125</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/36.html</AustLII>
<text>Last, there is an issue as to whether the solicitor for the council should be allowed to have access to these documents. She gave evidence that she acts for over 30 other councils, which are considering bringing similar or related claims against Lehman Brothers. The implied obligation or undertaking, as to confidentiality, is an important adjunct to the administration of justice in proceedings. The implied undertaking is a formula by which the law ensures that no harsher or more oppressive burden is placed on litigants or persons who produced documents than is necessary to do justice in the proceedings, at the stage they have reached. Persons who give discovery or produce documents under compulsion can suffer a very serious invasion of the privacy and confidentiality of their affairs: Hearne v Street [2008] HCA 36 ; (2008) 235 CLR 125 , at 158-159 [107] per Hayne, Heydon and Crennan JJ.

There is a public interest in preserving the ordinary confidentiality that attaches to production of documents under compulsion by the Court. It is the circumstance that Lehman Brothers is, in fact, a party to this litigation, which attracts the jurisdiction and, ultimately, the exercise of my discretion, to order production of the documents the council has sought. I do not see, at the moment, any reason why the council should be relieved of the constraint, imposed in the implied undertaking to keep confidential and to use the documents only for the purposes of these proceedings and to assist it in determining its position for the adjourned second creditors' meeting. The council's ability to use the information in the documents to be produced extends to include, in my view, informing itself as to how it ought approach voting on any proposals for a deed of company arrangement, or liquidation, of Lehman Brothers, since those matters affect its entitlement to enforce, or may affect its entitlement to enforce, any judgment and the quantification of that judgment.

I am of opinion that there is good reason to suppose that if Ms Banton is given access to the documents that I have ordered be produced, she will be placed in an impossible position as a fiduciary with the knowledge that she will gain of their contents in advising or dealing with persons who are her other clients. I think that I should afford the parties an opportunity to discuss and formulate an appropriate order that enables a person who would be bound by the implied undertaking, or may give express undertakings, who can advise the council, but will not be able to be involved in giving advice to or communicate with the other clients of Ms Banton's. Whether that person is independent entirely of the solicitors for the council or a person who, through the use of Chinese walls, can discharge that function, I think I should leave for the parties to discuss in the first instance.

Finally, Lehman Brothers has asked that any order I make be stayed for 24 hours to enable it to consider its position as to whether it would wish to seek leave to appeal from my decision. I think that is a reasonable request. The reason I have given my judgment now is because of the urgency and the need, if any party wishes to challenge my decision, that they have some opportunity to do so and I would not wish to frustrate that.
 I certify that the preceding fifty-two (52) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 21 May 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: M Pembroke SC and T Mehigan 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Piper Alderman 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: B Coles QC and V Whittaker 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Clayton Utz 
 Dates of Hearing: 19 and 21 May 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 19 May 2009 
 
 Date of making of Orders: 21 May 2009 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/532.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Houghton v Arms [2006] HCA 59 ; (2006) 225 CLR 553</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/59.html</AustLII>
<text>Part of the relief claimed by the council in the principal proceedings is in relation to allegedly misleading statements by Lehman Brothers. In those circumstances, one Lehman Brothers' related company is proposing a deed of company arrangement that would have the effect, on the evidence before me, of seeking to destroy the creditors' right to sue directors and officers of the company for breaches of their obligations. Such a right may be capable of being enforced directly against the directors and officers in an action under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) or its analogues in State Fair Trading Acts : Houghton v Arms [2006] HCA 59 ; (2006) 225 CLR 553 at 566-567 [40] - [42] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Heydon and Crennan JJ.

The council is also in the position where its vote at the proposed meeting of creditors is, because of the administrators' current view, likely to be admitted at merely nominal value, whereas, the other parties who may benefit in that meeting, such as the related Lehman Brothers companies, have debts that will be available to vote for their full value of about $180 million, on a proposal they are seeking to put forward and commend to the other creditors. That may all have a dramatic impact on the rights and recourse of the council, were it successful in this litigation, in the event that the proceedings were permitted to continue having regard to the terms of the deed or any subsequent orders made by the Court granting the council leave to proceed to final hearing against Lehman Brothers. The grant of any such orders may, in themselves, be affected by the existence of insurance that, prima facie, does respond.

Lehman Brothers has made claims on insurers A and B with respect to these proceedings. The information available to the council, as an ordinary incident of an administration under Pt 5.3A , is less than other creditors involved in this very administration, such as the related Lehman Brothers companies. While that is a result contemplated by the Parliament as potentially possible, the questions arise whether there will be potential or actual prejudice to the council in these proceedings of rights that may be valuable in the event that the council were able to succeed in obtaining a judgment in its favour.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>discussed</class>
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Jackson v Sterling Industries Limited [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1987/23.html</AustLII>
<text>The council argued essentially that the issue for decision was properly characterised in my summary in Wingecarribee (No 1) [2009] FCA 503 at [10] where I said: 
 "In my opinion, the question whether a respondent or defendant has assets that are available to satisfy a judgment and whether there is another party who may be liable, such as an insurer the subject of a charge under s 6 of the Law Reform (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act are matters which are within the power of the Court to require to be disclosed in the proceedings themselves: see Jackson v Sterling Industries Limited [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612 at 622-623 per Deane J, where he discussed the ambit of s 23 of the Federal Court of Australia Act and the power of the court to grant relief in the nature of Mareva orders, including the disclosure of assets by a defendant or respondent."

Section 23 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) provides that: 
 "The Court has power, in relation to matters in which it has jurisdiction, to make orders of such kinds, including interlocutory orders, and to issue, or direct the issue of, writs of such kinds, as the Court thinks appropriate." 

 
The inherent or implied power of the Court as a superior court of record constituted under the Act may also give the court additional powers.

Lehman Brothers argues that essentially there are two substantive reasons why there is either no power, or the circumstances of the proceedings are such as to condition and constrain the exercise of any such power. First, it points to the general principle that the courts have been unwilling to accept that insurance arrangements entered into between parties to proceedings for indemnity in respect of any liability that might be established against those parties in the proceedings are relevant or discoverable in the ordinary course of litigation or having regard to the principles on which discovery is given.

The power of the Court to require a party to proceedings in which relief is sought against it to disclose its assets has been established authoritatively in Jackson v Sterling Industries Limited [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612. In the leading judgment, Deane J ( Jackson 162 CLR at 622-623) discussed the power to make what are now known as Mareva orders ( Cardile v LED Builders Pty Ltd [1999] HCA 18 ; (1999) 198 CLR 380 at 401 [42] ) saying that (omitting citations): 
 "That general power has been held to encompass an order requiring the disclosure by a defendant of his assets ... As a general proposition, it should now be accepted in this country that "a Mareva injunction can be granted ... if the circumstances are such that there is a danger of [the defendant's] absconding, or a danger of the assets being removed out of the jurisdiction or disposed of within the jurisdiction, or otherwise dealt with so that there is a danger that the plaintiff, if he gets judgment, will not be able to get it satisfied"."

The other members of the High Court agreed with that approach: Jackson 162 CLR at 616 per Mason CJ, at 617 and 619 per Wilson and Dawson JJ. Indeed, Wilson and Dawson JJ said that the purpose of the grant of a Mareva order is to prevent the abuse of the process of the Court by frustration of its remedies. The power could be exercised for purposes including to prevent a defendant from removing assets in order to defeat a judgment: ( Jackson 162 CLR at 617). They explained that the power ( Jackson 162 CLR at 619): 
 "... exists not to create additional rights but to enable a court to protect its process from abuse in relation to the enforcement of its orders. It is neither a species of anticipatory execution nor does it give a form of security for any judgment which may ultimately be awarded."

Likewise, Brennan J, in agreeing, explained that the remedy was incidental to the exercise by the court of its jurisdiction to enter judgment for a debt or damages and was designed to prevent the defendant from divesting himself of his assets whereby enforcement of such a judgment might be frustrated ( Jackson 162 CLR at 621).

There is no suggestion here that the administrators have the purpose of interfering with or frustrating the ordinary execution of the Court's orders. But, the effect of implementation of a deed of company arrangement, as opposed to a liquidation, can radically affect the ordinary rights of creditors. In a liquidation their rights would be converted into a right to prove in the liquidation which may be different to their rights under a deed of company arrangement. Indeed, some of the proposed terms of Lehman Brothers Asia Holdings' deed to which I have referred, such as the release of rights against third parties including directors and officers, could have a significant and adverse affect on a creditor being able to enforce its ordinary remedies. In addition, the suggested deed of company arrangement will make provision for the distribution of whatever entitlements may be available to creditors that would otherwise have had rights in respect of insurance policies, such as those written by insurers A, B or C that might respond to the various claims. Those proposals include ones affecting the creditors rights to proceed directly against insurers under s 6 of the Law Reform (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1946 (NSW) or against the directors and officers of Lehman Brothers or their insurers.

I am of opinion that the Court's power to require Lehman Brothers to produce the insurance documents is found in s 23 and the inherent or implied power of the Court to do justice in a matter before it. It is an important part of the Court's ordinary processes to permit litigants before it to have effective remedies and the means, if appropriate, of enforcing them when orders are made.

The effect of the administration, as Pt 5.3A contemplates, will be to bind all creditors, including the council, in the event that a deed of company arrangement is entered into and is not terminated. Because that may produce outcomes that possibly may impact on the conduct of the current proceedings in a way that is not necessarily the same as in the ordinary course of every other piece of litigation, I am of opinion that it is appropriate to require production of the insurance information sought having regard to considerations to which I have referred: Jackson [1987] HCA 23 ; 162 CLR 612 ; Batistatos [2006] HCA 27 ; 226 CLR 256 ; Lopez [1997] FCA 454.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Lopez v Star World Enterprises Pty Ltd [1997] FCA 454</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1997/454.html</AustLII>
<text>In Lopez v Star World Enterprises Pty Ltd [1997] FCA 454 (unreported, 18 April 1997) Olney J held that a respondent company that had been placed in administration could be ordered by the Court to make available its insurance policies to the applicant. He held that after the respondent company had been placed in administration, and was in jeopardy of going into liquidation, the question whether or not there was any insurance indemnity available in the event of liability being established was a matter appropriate to take into account for the purpose of determining whether or not leave to proceed against the company should be given under s 440D(1) of the Corporations Act . For the purposes of doing justice and to progress the matter in an orderly fashion, Olney J ordered that the respondent company produce for inspection evidence of any relevant insurance policy that it had.

Lehman Brothers does not suggest that his Honour erred in principle. But it seeks to distinguish his decision on the ground that those proceedings were brought under Pt IVA of the Federal Court of Australia Act , as representative proceedings. Lehman Brothers argues that the discretionary considerations attaching to the conduct of such proceedings and the fact that there is a large body of potential group members who may be affected, are grounds for confining the exercise of a similar discretion in favour of production of the insurance documents in a case such as the present.

But the present circumstances are that the council is involved in the current litigation and an event has occurred in its course that has given rise to this application being made. That event is the administration of Lehman Brothers. No longer is Lehman Brothers the same entity as that with which the council dealt unlike in Beneficial Finance 68 SASR 19 , where the plaintiff had to take the solvent defendants as it found them. The same circumstances that enlivened Olney J's exercise of discretion to order production in Lopez [1997] FCA 454 have been introduced here by the intervening event of the administration and the consequent, inferred admission that Lehman Brothers is insolvent.

The effect of the administration, as Pt 5.3A contemplates, will be to bind all creditors, including the council, in the event that a deed of company arrangement is entered into and is not terminated. Because that may produce outcomes that possibly may impact on the conduct of the current proceedings in a way that is not necessarily the same as in the ordinary course of every other piece of litigation, I am of opinion that it is appropriate to require production of the insurance information sought having regard to considerations to which I have referred: Jackson [1987] HCA 23 ; 162 CLR 612 ; Batistatos [2006] HCA 27 ; 226 CLR 256 ; Lopez [1997] FCA 454.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>