<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Harris Scarfe Australia Pty Ltd (Corrigendum dated 5 February 2009) [2009] FCA 54 (5 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/54.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Ryan v ETSA (No 1) (1987) 47 SASR 220</tocase>
<text>Clearly, Harris Scarfe did not (and subject to the outcome of these proceedings, does not) consider that either the television commercial or the catalogue breached ss 52 or 53(e) of the TP Act. Consequently, neither the development of the Advertising Rule Book, nor its contents can be taken as an admission. It is a sensible process to undertake, after an occurrence about which the ACCC is concerned, and to adapt to its concerns: see eg Ryan v ETSA (No 1) (1987) 47 SASR 220. Nevertheless, it is significant in my view, on the issue of the appropriateness of any orders, if a contravention or contraventions are established, that Harris Scarfe has sought to reinforce the processes which it had in place, and which it had reason to think would protect it from contravention of the TP Act, by the introduction of the Advertising Rule Book and the training associated with it. There is evidence of that training having now been undertaken.

Harris Scarfe has also offered, on an open basis, to enter into yet a further s 87B undertaking in a form proposed. That form is responsive to the nature of the contraventions currently asserted in these proceedings. Further, Harris Scarfe has adopted a cooperative approach to the ACCC's inquiries at all times and endeavoured to address those concerns without the need for litigation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/44.html</AustLII>
<text>This proceeding does not attempt to break new ground in the application of ss 52 and 53(e) of the TP Act. The applicable principles are now well established: see eg Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 ( Parkdale ); Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd [1982] FCA 136 ; (1982) 42 ALR 177 ( Taco Bell ).

Conduct is misleading or deceptive if it induces or is capable of inducing error (to adopt the expression in Harris Scarfe's written submissions). That must of course be understood as applying not in an absolute sense, but in relation to consumers or to a relevant class of consumers. Evidence of members of the public having been misled is not conclusive: Parkdale at 198-9. Of course, the converse is also not necessarily correct. That is, the absence of evidence that members of the public have been misled does not necessarily negate the fact of a contravention having occurred. It has also been held that the words "likely to mislead or deceive" do not add much to the section: Parkdale at 198. In the submissions, nothing was made of those particular words. It is sufficient if there is a real chance that the conduct will mislead or deceive: Global Sportsman Pty Ltd v Mirror Newspapers Ltd [1984] FCA 180 ; (1984) 2 FCR 82 at 87.

Importantly, whether conduct is misleading or deceptive or is likely to mislead or deceive must be determined in context. In Parkdale it was said at 199: 
 It seems clear enough that consideration must be given to the class of consumers likely to be affected by the conduct. Although it is true, as has often been said, that ordinarily a class of consumers may include the inexperienced as well as the experienced, and the gullible as well as the astute, the section must in my opinion by (sic) regarded as contemplating the effect of the conduct on reasonable members of the class. The heavy burdens which the section creates cannot have been intended to be imposed for the benefit of persons who fail to take reasonable care of their own interests. What is reasonable will or (sic) course depend on all the circumstances.

The test is an objective one for the Court upon the whole of the evidence. Not every member of the public needs to have been misled or capable of having been misled for the conduct to be misleading or deceptive. The test is applied to the public, or a relevant section of the public, to whom the representation is made or in relation to whom the conduct is engaged in, including 
 the astute and the gullible, the intelligent and the not so intelligent, the well educated as well as the poorly educated, men and women of various ages pursuing a variety of vocations. 

 
See Taco Bell at 202. That passage was referred to with approval in Parkdale at 199 but, as the passage from Parkdale quoted above shows, it is to be measured against reasonable members of the class.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd [1982] FCA 136 ; (1982) 42 ALR 177</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1982/136.html</AustLII>
<text>This proceeding does not attempt to break new ground in the application of ss 52 and 53(e) of the TP Act. The applicable principles are now well established: see eg Parkdale Custom Built Furniture Pty Ltd v Puxu Pty Ltd [1982] HCA 44 ; (1982) 149 CLR 191 ( Parkdale ); Taco Company of Australia Inc v Taco Bell Pty Ltd [1982] FCA 136 ; (1982) 42 ALR 177 ( Taco Bell ).

The test is an objective one for the Court upon the whole of the evidence. Not every member of the public needs to have been misled or capable of having been misled for the conduct to be misleading or deceptive. The test is applied to the public, or a relevant section of the public, to whom the representation is made or in relation to whom the conduct is engaged in, including 
 the astute and the gullible, the intelligent and the not so intelligent, the well educated as well as the poorly educated, men and women of various ages pursuing a variety of vocations. 

 
See Taco Bell at 202. That passage was referred to with approval in Parkdale at 199 but, as the passage from Parkdale quoted above shows, it is to be measured against reasonable members of the class.

In the submissions, no difference was identified between the application of s 52 and s 53(e) to the relevant conduct. The applicability of s 53(e) is similarly a question of fact to be assessed objectively in the context of the conduct and the surrounding circumstances: Taco Bell at 202.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Global Sportsman Pty Ltd v Mirror Newspapers Ltd [1984] FCA 180 ; (1984) 2 FCR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/180.html</AustLII>
<text>Conduct is misleading or deceptive if it induces or is capable of inducing error (to adopt the expression in Harris Scarfe's written submissions). That must of course be understood as applying not in an absolute sense, but in relation to consumers or to a relevant class of consumers. Evidence of members of the public having been misled is not conclusive: Parkdale at 198-9. Of course, the converse is also not necessarily correct. That is, the absence of evidence that members of the public have been misled does not necessarily negate the fact of a contravention having occurred. It has also been held that the words "likely to mislead or deceive" do not add much to the section: Parkdale at 198. In the submissions, nothing was made of those particular words. It is sufficient if there is a real chance that the conduct will mislead or deceive: Global Sportsman Pty Ltd v Mirror Newspapers Ltd [1984] FCA 180 ; (1984) 2 FCR 82 at 87.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Optus Communications Pty Ltd &amp; Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (1996) 64 FCR 326</tocase>
<text>Those considerations apply equally to representations by advertising as to other forms of conduct. Whether a representation has been made in advertising material must be assessed not by a particular statement taken in isolation, but by the statement in its context and, where appropriate, in the surrounding circumstances: Trade Practices Commission v Optus Communications Pty Ltd &amp; Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (1996) 64 FCR 326 ( Optus ) at 336-8; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Thorn Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 157 at [13] - [14] ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Signature Security Group Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 3 ( Signature ) at [25]-[28].

Where printed advertising is under consideration, it is appropriate to consider not simply the words or images depicted but also their relative emphasis (whether by print size, location, colour or other manner of presentation) to determine whether the asserted representation has been made in its overall context. So, where, as here, particular words or figures are accompanied by an asterisk and the asterisk apparently directs attention to a footnote, it is necessary to do more than treat the whole of the communication as one piece of text. It is necessary to look to the way the asterisk is placed, the size of the footnote relative to the text in the body of the advertisement, and the terms of the footnote: see per Davies J in Trade Practices Commission v QDSV Holdings Pty Ltd (t/as Bush Friends Australia) [1994] FCA 1562 ; (1995) 128 ALR 551 at 559. Whilst, as his Honour says, the ideal is that qualifying words should be in the same sized print as the print which catches the eye, it is not necessary for qualifying print to be in that size to avoid the large print which first catches the eye from conveying a representation without regard to the qualification. See the discussion in Optus at 339-41; Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy (2003) 205 ALR 402 at [35]-[41].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Thorn Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 157</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/157.html</AustLII>
<text>Those considerations apply equally to representations by advertising as to other forms of conduct. Whether a representation has been made in advertising material must be assessed not by a particular statement taken in isolation, but by the statement in its context and, where appropriate, in the surrounding circumstances: Trade Practices Commission v Optus Communications Pty Ltd &amp; Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (1996) 64 FCR 326 ( Optus ) at 336-8; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Thorn Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 157 at [13] - [14] ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Signature Security Group Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 3 ( Signature ) at [25]-[28].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Signature Security Group Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 3</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2003/3.html</AustLII>
<text>Those considerations apply equally to representations by advertising as to other forms of conduct. Whether a representation has been made in advertising material must be assessed not by a particular statement taken in isolation, but by the statement in its context and, where appropriate, in the surrounding circumstances: Trade Practices Commission v Optus Communications Pty Ltd &amp; Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (1996) 64 FCR 326 ( Optus ) at 336-8; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Thorn Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 157 at [13] - [14] ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Signature Security Group Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 3 ( Signature ) at [25]-[28].

I have taken into account the asterisk where it appears, and the footnote text. In that regard, I note what Stone J said in Signature [2003] FCA 3 at [26] in the following terms: 
 I agree with the respondent's submission that George Weston Foods Pty Ltd v Goodman Fielder Ltd (2001) 49 IPR 553 ('the Wonder White case') is authority for the fact that an asterisk can be sufficient to draw the attention of a consumer to a qualification of a representation. That case concerned, inter alia, the packaging of the respondent's bread which declared in large typeface 'Now Twice the Fibre*'. Moore J observed that: 

 
"the asterisk is prominent and would be taken to signify some qualification or explanation of the words used. One could expect a consumer interested in the fibre content to seek out the qualification or explanation. Not only is the explanation within 2 cm of the words used on the package (albeit in much smaller type) but it is repeated elsewhere on the packaging."

In my view, the asterisk is quite prominent and is sufficient to direct attention to the asterisk at the bottom of each page. The footnote disclaimer accompanied by the asterisk is not hard to find and is not hidden. But the context is clear, by the relative size of the headline and the footnote: the footnote is not to contradict the headline, but to explain or qualify or limit it. If it were simply to contradict the headline, one would expect the footnote to be much more prominent.

In my view, the footnote on each page was of limited effect. It said two things: that discounts were off "regular prices"; and that no further discounts apply to catalogue lines. 
As noted above, the footnote on page 1 of the sale catalogue added that the banner content excluded television, sound, digital cameras and toys (on page 1 only).

The corrective advertising sought by the ACCC is said to match the placement of the advertising in the sale catalogue giving rise to the contraventions. In my view, there is no real purpose in making such an order in the present circumstances. The injunctive order will prevent the form of advertising which gave rise to the contraventions. There is no evidence of any consumer having suffered loss as a result of the contravening conduct. There was a significant period after the sale catalogue was published before these proceedings were instituted, and a further period has since elapsed. In those circumstances, it is difficult to see how the proposed corrective advertising would serve any useful purpose: see Hospitals Contribution Fund of Australia Ltd v Switzerland Australia Health Fund Pty Ltd (1987) 78 ALR 483 ; St Lukes Health Insurance v Medical Benefits Funds of Australia [1995] FCA 1314 per Northrop J at [34]; Wizard Mortgage per Merkel J at [27]; Signature [2002] FCA 3.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Chief Executive Officer, Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 1097</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1097.html</AustLII>
<text>In the case of television advertising, necessarily the message is conveyed visually with images and in this case printed text and generally with oral text. It is relatively fleeting (although the fleeting impression is often sought to be reinforced by iteration or abridged iteration, sometimes in successive advertisements). Nevertheless, it is still necessary to determine the overall impression of what is conveyed from consideration of all parts of the television presentation to ensure the message is taken in context: Chief Executive Officer, Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 1097 ( MBF No 2 ) at [45].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v QDSV Holdings Pty Ltd (t/as Bush Friends Australia) [1994] FCA 1562 ; (1995) 128 ALR 551</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1994/1562.html</AustLII>
<text>Where printed advertising is under consideration, it is appropriate to consider not simply the words or images depicted but also their relative emphasis (whether by print size, location, colour or other manner of presentation) to determine whether the asserted representation has been made in its overall context. So, where, as here, particular words or figures are accompanied by an asterisk and the asterisk apparently directs attention to a footnote, it is necessary to do more than treat the whole of the communication as one piece of text. It is necessary to look to the way the asterisk is placed, the size of the footnote relative to the text in the body of the advertisement, and the terms of the footnote: see per Davies J in Trade Practices Commission v QDSV Holdings Pty Ltd (t/as Bush Friends Australia) [1994] FCA 1562 ; (1995) 128 ALR 551 at 559. Whilst, as his Honour says, the ideal is that qualifying words should be in the same sized print as the print which catches the eye, it is not necessary for qualifying print to be in that size to avoid the large print which first catches the eye from conveying a representation without regard to the qualification. See the discussion in Optus at 339-41; Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy (2003) 205 ALR 402 at [35]-[41].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy (2003) 205 ALR 402</tocase>
<text>Where printed advertising is under consideration, it is appropriate to consider not simply the words or images depicted but also their relative emphasis (whether by print size, location, colour or other manner of presentation) to determine whether the asserted representation has been made in its overall context. So, where, as here, particular words or figures are accompanied by an asterisk and the asterisk apparently directs attention to a footnote, it is necessary to do more than treat the whole of the communication as one piece of text. It is necessary to look to the way the asterisk is placed, the size of the footnote relative to the text in the body of the advertisement, and the terms of the footnote: see per Davies J in Trade Practices Commission v QDSV Holdings Pty Ltd (t/as Bush Friends Australia) [1994] FCA 1562 ; (1995) 128 ALR 551 at 559. Whilst, as his Honour says, the ideal is that qualifying words should be in the same sized print as the print which catches the eye, it is not necessary for qualifying print to be in that size to avoid the large print which first catches the eye from conveying a representation without regard to the qualification. See the discussion in Optus at 339-41; Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy (2003) 205 ALR 402 at [35]-[41].

In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556) [2007] FCA 2058 , Gordon J summarised the principles concerning the issue of whether corrective advertising should be made. Her Honour said at [4]: 
 Section 86C of [the TP Act] confers power on the Court to make an order for corrective advertising. Corrective advertising may have a number of purposes: 

 
 (1) to protect the public interest by dispelling an incorrect or false impression that has been created as a result of misleading or deceptive conduct ( Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [49] (Full Court) and ACCC v Wizard Mortgage Corporation Ltd (2002) ATPR 41-903 at [27]) especially where all of the misleading or deceptive conduct arose out of advertisements and other public statements and promotions;
 
 (2) to alert consumers to the fact of the misleading or deceptive conduct and inform them that they might have some remedy if they relied upon any of the misleading or deceptive conduct: Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [54] ;
 
 (3) as an "aid in the enforcement of the primary orders and the prevention of repetition of the contravening conduct": ACCC v Real Estate Institute (WA) Inc (1999) 95 FCR 114 at 133 per French J, cited with approval in Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [51] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Nationwide News Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 75</tocase>
<text>My conclusions reflect the passage quoted with evident approval by Heerey J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Nationwide News Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 75 at 85 from the decision of the United States Supreme Court delivered by Hugo Black J in Federal Trade Commission v Standard Education Society [1937] USSC 142 ; 302 US 112 (1937) at 115: 
 The fact that a false statement may be obviously false to those who are trained and experienced does not change its character, nor take away its power to deceive others less experienced. There is no duty resting upon a citizen to suspect the honesty of those with whom he transacts business. Laws are made to protect the trusting as well as the suspicious. The best element of business has long since decided that honesty should govern competitive enterprises, and that the rule of caveat emptor should not be relied upon to reward fraud and deception.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Federal Trade Commission v Standard Education Society [1937] USSC 142 ; 302 US 112 (1937)</tocase>
<text>My conclusions reflect the passage quoted with evident approval by Heerey J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Nationwide News Pty Ltd (1996) 36 IPR 75 at 85 from the decision of the United States Supreme Court delivered by Hugo Black J in Federal Trade Commission v Standard Education Society [1937] USSC 142 ; 302 US 112 (1937) at 115: 
 The fact that a false statement may be obviously false to those who are trained and experienced does not change its character, nor take away its power to deceive others less experienced. There is no duty resting upon a citizen to suspect the honesty of those with whom he transacts business. Laws are made to protect the trusting as well as the suspicious. The best element of business has long since decided that honesty should govern competitive enterprises, and that the rule of caveat emptor should not be relied upon to reward fraud and deception.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Trade Practices Commission v Cue Design Pty Ltd (1996) 85 A Crim R 500</tocase>
<text>In my view, it is appropriate to make a declaratory order in respect of the contraventions I have found to be established. It will be in the form proposed by the ACCC. The facts that the contraventions occurred notwithstanding Harris Scarfe's efforts to comply with the TP Act over quite some time, and that they occurred notwithstanding in particular the 2004 undertaking and the 2006 undertaking, indicate to my mind that it is appropriate to make the declaratory order sought, as relevant to the contraventions, rather than permit Harris Scarfe to provide yet another undertaking to the ACCC. Moreover, and perhaps more importantly, the acceptance of a s 87B undertaking is within the discretion of the ACCC. It does not appear that the Court has power to oblige the ACCC to accept such an undertaking: Trade Practices Commission v Cue Design Pty Ltd (1996) 85 A Crim R 500 ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Monza Imports Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1455. The ACCC is not prepared to do so in respect of these contraventions. Even if it could be obliged to do so, contrary to the decisions referred to, I would not impose upon the ACCC the acceptance of yet a further s 87B undertaking. Then, rather than there be no formal recording of the contraventions, I would make the relevant declaratory order sought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Monza Imports Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1455</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1455.html</AustLII>
<text>In my view, it is appropriate to make a declaratory order in respect of the contraventions I have found to be established. It will be in the form proposed by the ACCC. The facts that the contraventions occurred notwithstanding Harris Scarfe's efforts to comply with the TP Act over quite some time, and that they occurred notwithstanding in particular the 2004 undertaking and the 2006 undertaking, indicate to my mind that it is appropriate to make the declaratory order sought, as relevant to the contraventions, rather than permit Harris Scarfe to provide yet another undertaking to the ACCC. Moreover, and perhaps more importantly, the acceptance of a s 87B undertaking is within the discretion of the ACCC. It does not appear that the Court has power to oblige the ACCC to accept such an undertaking: Trade Practices Commission v Cue Design Pty Ltd (1996) 85 A Crim R 500 ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Monza Imports Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1455. The ACCC is not prepared to do so in respect of these contraventions. Even if it could be obliged to do so, contrary to the decisions referred to, I would not impose upon the ACCC the acceptance of yet a further s 87B undertaking. Then, rather than there be no formal recording of the contraventions, I would make the relevant declaratory order sought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2004] FCAFC 167</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/167.html</AustLII>
<text>That form of injunctive order is quite specific. It is not generic, in the sense that it simply prohibits conduct which the TP Act prohibits: see BMW Australia Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2004] FCAFC 167. It captures the form of advertising in the sale catalogue which has led to the contravention. Such conduct occurred notwithstanding Harris Scarfe's compliance program, and the considerable effort and expense which Harris Scarfe had in the past put into trying to avoid conduct in contravention of ss 52 and 53 of the TP Act. An injunction in those terms should therefore deter Harris Scarfe from engaging in such conduct during the period of its currency: ICI Australia Operations Pty Ltd v Trade Practices Commission (1992) 38 FCR 248 at 268.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Wizard Mortgage Corporation Ltd [2002] FCA 1317</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/1317.html</AustLII>
<text>Harris Scarfe, since the conduct giving rise to the contraventions, has introduced and developed its Advertising Rule Book. It appears to address the circumstances giving rise to the present contraventions. However, as in any substantial retail organisation with an extensive product range, there may be scope for different views about the way such a document should be construed or applied. So too is there such scope, notwithstanding a compliance program and its Compliance Manual and its Advertising Rule Book and ongoing training, for oversight or error. The fact that Harris Scarfe committed the contraventions despite the extensive external and internal structures and resources it utilised to avoid contravening the TP Act provides reason to specifically prohibit the offending advertising style. The steps taken by Harris Scarfe to avoid such contraventions in the future may provide a reason not to make any injunctive order (cf Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Wizard Mortgage Corporation Ltd [2002] FCA 1317 ( Wizard Mortgage ) per Merkel J at [22]). However, having regard to the past history including the 2004 undertaking, and the 2006 undertaking, my conclusion on balance is that it is appropriate to make the injunctive order in the terms sought.

The corrective advertising sought by the ACCC is said to match the placement of the advertising in the sale catalogue giving rise to the contraventions. In my view, there is no real purpose in making such an order in the present circumstances. The injunctive order will prevent the form of advertising which gave rise to the contraventions. There is no evidence of any consumer having suffered loss as a result of the contravening conduct. There was a significant period after the sale catalogue was published before these proceedings were instituted, and a further period has since elapsed. In those circumstances, it is difficult to see how the proposed corrective advertising would serve any useful purpose: see Hospitals Contribution Fund of Australia Ltd v Switzerland Australia Health Fund Pty Ltd (1987) 78 ALR 483 ; St Lukes Health Insurance v Medical Benefits Funds of Australia [1995] FCA 1314 per Northrop J at [34]; Wizard Mortgage per Merkel J at [27]; Signature [2002] FCA 3.

In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556) [2007] FCA 2058 , Gordon J summarised the principles concerning the issue of whether corrective advertising should be made. Her Honour said at [4]: 
 Section 86C of [the TP Act] confers power on the Court to make an order for corrective advertising. Corrective advertising may have a number of purposes: 

 
 (1) to protect the public interest by dispelling an incorrect or false impression that has been created as a result of misleading or deceptive conduct ( Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [49] (Full Court) and ACCC v Wizard Mortgage Corporation Ltd (2002) ATPR 41-903 at [27]) especially where all of the misleading or deceptive conduct arose out of advertisements and other public statements and promotions;
 
 (2) to alert consumers to the fact of the misleading or deceptive conduct and inform them that they might have some remedy if they relied upon any of the misleading or deceptive conduct: Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [54] ;
 
 (3) as an "aid in the enforcement of the primary orders and the prevention of repetition of the contravening conduct": ACCC v Real Estate Institute (WA) Inc (1999) 95 FCR 114 at 133 per French J, cited with approval in Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [51] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Midland Brick Co Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 693 ; (2004) 207 ALR 329</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/693.html</AustLII>
<text>The purpose is not to add to Harris Scarfe the possible exposure to contempt of court if it commits a further contravention such as those which have been established. It is to add the additional incentive, or deterrence, of quite specific injunctive orders to prevent the re-occurrence of the offending conduct, albeit in the context of voluntary action already taken by Harris Scarfe which makes the risk of such re-occurrence quite small. It will, however, be limited in time to a period of three years: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Midland Brick Co Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 693 ; (2004) 207 ALR 329 at [45] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hospitals Contribution Fund of Australia Ltd v Switzerland Australia Health Fund Pty Ltd (1987) 78 ALR 483</tocase>
<text>The corrective advertising sought by the ACCC is said to match the placement of the advertising in the sale catalogue giving rise to the contraventions. In my view, there is no real purpose in making such an order in the present circumstances. The injunctive order will prevent the form of advertising which gave rise to the contraventions. There is no evidence of any consumer having suffered loss as a result of the contravening conduct. There was a significant period after the sale catalogue was published before these proceedings were instituted, and a further period has since elapsed. In those circumstances, it is difficult to see how the proposed corrective advertising would serve any useful purpose: see Hospitals Contribution Fund of Australia Ltd v Switzerland Australia Health Fund Pty Ltd (1987) 78 ALR 483 ; St Lukes Health Insurance v Medical Benefits Funds of Australia [1995] FCA 1314 per Northrop J at [34]; Wizard Mortgage per Merkel J at [27]; Signature [2002] FCA 3.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>St Lukes Health Insurance v Medical Benefits Funds of Australia [1995] FCA 1314</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1995/1314.html</AustLII>
<text>The corrective advertising sought by the ACCC is said to match the placement of the advertising in the sale catalogue giving rise to the contraventions. In my view, there is no real purpose in making such an order in the present circumstances. The injunctive order will prevent the form of advertising which gave rise to the contraventions. There is no evidence of any consumer having suffered loss as a result of the contravening conduct. There was a significant period after the sale catalogue was published before these proceedings were instituted, and a further period has since elapsed. In those circumstances, it is difficult to see how the proposed corrective advertising would serve any useful purpose: see Hospitals Contribution Fund of Australia Ltd v Switzerland Australia Health Fund Pty Ltd (1987) 78 ALR 483 ; St Lukes Health Insurance v Medical Benefits Funds of Australia [1995] FCA 1314 per Northrop J at [34]; Wizard Mortgage per Merkel J at [27]; Signature [2002] FCA 3.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited [2004] FCA 1132</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1132.html</AustLII>
<text>I have not overlooked that, in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited [2004] FCA 1132 , Gyles J granted an injunctive order for five years. His Honour discussed that question at [5]. In my view, however, the period of three years, acting as a reinforcement in the manner I have described, is appropriate to enable the advertising practices of Harris Scarfe to have been cemented so as to thereafter carry little or no risk of like contravening conduct. The orders for corrective advertising and refinement of Harris Scarfe's compliance program are founded upon s 86C of the TP Act. It relevantly provides: 
 (1) The Court may, on application by the Commission, make one or more of the orders mentioned in subsection (2) in relation to a person who has engaged in contravening conduct. 

 
 (2) The orders that the Court may make in relation to the person are: 

 
 (a) ...
 (b) a probation order for a period of no longer than 3 years; and
 (c) ...
 (d) an order requiring the person to publish, at the person's expense and in the way specified in the order, an advertisement in the terms specified in, or determined in accordance with, the order.
 (3) ... 

 
 (4) In this section: 

 
 "Probation order" , in relation to a person who has engaged in contravening conduct, means an order that is made by the Court for the purpose of ensuring that the person does not engage in the contravening conduct, similar conduct or related conduct during the period of the order, and includes: 

 
 (a) an order directing the person to establish a compliance program for employees or other persons involved in the person's business, being a program designed to ensure their awareness of the responsibilities and obligations in relation to the contravening, similar conduct or related conduct; and
 (b) an order directing the person to establish an education and training program for employees or other persons involved in the person's business, being a program designed to ensure their awareness of the responsibilities and obligations in relation to the contravening conduct, similar conduct or related conduct; and
 (c) an order directing the person to revise the internal operations of the person's business which lead to the person engaging in the contravening conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556) [2007] FCA 2058</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/2058.html</AustLII>
<text>In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Telstra Corporation Limited (ACN 051 775 556) [2007] FCA 2058 , Gordon J summarised the principles concerning the issue of whether corrective advertising should be made. Her Honour said at [4]: 
 Section 86C of [the TP Act] confers power on the Court to make an order for corrective advertising. Corrective advertising may have a number of purposes: 

 
 (1) to protect the public interest by dispelling an incorrect or false impression that has been created as a result of misleading or deceptive conduct ( Medical Benefits Fund of Australia Ltd v Cassidy [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [49] (Full Court) and ACCC v Wizard Mortgage Corporation Ltd (2002) ATPR 41-903 at [27]) especially where all of the misleading or deceptive conduct arose out of advertisements and other public statements and promotions;
 
 (2) to alert consumers to the fact of the misleading or deceptive conduct and inform them that they might have some remedy if they relied upon any of the misleading or deceptive conduct: Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [54] ;
 
 (3) as an "aid in the enforcement of the primary orders and the prevention of repetition of the contravening conduct": ACCC v Real Estate Institute (WA) Inc (1999) 95 FCR 114 at 133 per French J, cited with approval in Medical Benefits Fund [2003] FCAFC 289 ; (2003) 135 FCR 1 at [51] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Prouds Jewellers Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/476.html</AustLII>
<text>Those principles were applied by Moore J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Prouds Jewellers Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 476. In the light of the injunctive order proposed to be made, and in the particular circumstances, I do not think any of those three purposes would usefully be served now by corrective advertising. The public interest is adequately protected by the injunctive order, in effect reinforcing the voluntary action taken by Harris Scarfe. The absence of any identified consumer who suffered loss as a result of the contravening conduct makes it quite unlikely now that corrective advertising would alert any particular consumer to the possibility of a remedy. And I have already indicated the injunctive order itself is to aid in preventing a repetition of the contravening conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Target Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1326</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1326.html</AustLII>
<text>Corrective advertising may, of course, raise public awareness as to the type of conduct that may contravene the TP Act, as well as the outcome of the particular case: see per Lee J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Target Australia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1326 at [21] . That case involved orders, including corrective advertising, proposed to be made by consent. In the particular circumstances, I do not consider that factor in the overall balance warrants the making of orders for corrective advertising. Consumers are unlikely to be further exposed to such contravening conduct on the part of Harris Scarfe for the reasons already given. Competitors will no doubt become aware of the outcome of this case, and take account of its reasons in their further advertising. Hence, consumers more generally are also not likely to benefit from corrective advertising specific to Harris Scarfe's contravening conduct unless, first, a competitor engaged in similar conduct and the connection between that advertising and the corrective advertising specific to Harris Scarfe was made.

I therefore decline to order corrective advertising.

The final package of orders sought by the ACCC under s 86C involve Harris Scarfe being required to revise and review its internal operations in relation to its compliance with the TP Act. Specifically, the package of orders would require: (1) Harris Scarfe to appoint a senior employee as its "Internal Review Manager"; (2) Harris Scarfe, on the recommendation of its Internal Review Manager, to retain an appropriately qualified and experienced Independent Reviewer (a person not previously involved in the design or implementation of the compliance program); (3) the Independent Reviewer to review the compliance program and the process of producing the sale catalogue to determine why the contraventions occurred, and to recommend steps to be taken, including revision of the compliance program, to ensure similar or related conduct does not occur in the future; (4) Harris Scarfe to provide a copy of the Independent Reviewer's report to the ACCC; (5) Harris Scarfe to implement the Independent Reviewer's recommendations as it "considers reasonably necessary" to ensure it does not engage in the contravening conduct or any similar or related conduct in the future; (6) Harris Scarfe to report to the ACCC of the steps it has taken pursuant to (5) or to report that it has decided not to implement any of those recommendations. 
Then, if the ACCC did not agree with Harris Scarfe's actions, the ACCC is to be given the right to apply to the Court "regarding the adequacy of any step taken by Harris Scarfe to review its internal operations". Presumably, the expectation is that the Court would then be asked to determine whether some further orders in relation to Harris Scarfe's internal systems should be directed by the Court.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>