<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wide Bay Conservation Council Inc v Burnett Water Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 540 (15 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/540.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Booth v Bosworth [2001] FCA 1453 ; (2001) 114 FCR 39</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1453.html</AustLII>
<text>On analysis, that reliance can be seen to be misconceived, for the following reasons: 
(a) Booth v Bosworth [2001] FCA 1453 ; (2001) 114 FCR 39. The foundation for the injunctive relief sought in that case under s 475 was an alleged breach of s 12 of the Act. An element of s 12 is that the action concerned either have a significant impact on world heritage values or be likely to have such an impact in respect of a declared world heritage property. In contrast, "significant impact" is - unless it has in some way in the wording of a condition in a particular case, and this is not one of no relevance at all in respect of whether there has been a contravention of a condition of the kind with which s 142 is concerned.
 
(b) Minister for the Environment and Heritage v Greentree (No 2) [2004] FCA 741 ; (2004) 138 FCR 198. In that case, the injunctive relief sought pursuant to s 475 had as its foundation an alleged breach of s 16 of the Act as read with s 17. Regard to s 16 discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element akin to that found in s 12, but in this instance focused upon the ecological character of a declared RAMSAR wetland. For reasons already given in respect of Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play here in relation to the alleged breach of the condition and hence a contravention of s 142.
 
(c) Brown v Forestry Tasmania (No 4) [2006] FCA 1729 ; (2006) 157 FCR 1. In this case, the alleged contravention grounding injunctive relief was a contravention of s 18 of the Act. Regard to that section discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element, on this occasion related to listed threatened species included in the "extinct in the wild" category. Again, for reasons given in relation to Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play in this case in relation to s 142.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Brown v Forestry Tasmania (No 4) [2006] FCA 1729 ; (2006) 157 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1729.html</AustLII>
<text>On analysis, that reliance can be seen to be misconceived, for the following reasons: 
(a) Booth v Bosworth [2001] FCA 1453 ; (2001) 114 FCR 39. The foundation for the injunctive relief sought in that case under s 475 was an alleged breach of s 12 of the Act. An element of s 12 is that the action concerned either have a significant impact on world heritage values or be likely to have such an impact in respect of a declared world heritage property. In contrast, "significant impact" is - unless it has in some way in the wording of a condition in a particular case, and this is not one of no relevance at all in respect of whether there has been a contravention of a condition of the kind with which s 142 is concerned.
 
(b) Minister for the Environment and Heritage v Greentree (No 2) [2004] FCA 741 ; (2004) 138 FCR 198. In that case, the injunctive relief sought pursuant to s 475 had as its foundation an alleged breach of s 16 of the Act as read with s 17. Regard to s 16 discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element akin to that found in s 12, but in this instance focused upon the ecological character of a declared RAMSAR wetland. For reasons already given in respect of Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play here in relation to the alleged breach of the condition and hence a contravention of s 142.
 
(c) Brown v Forestry Tasmania (No 4) [2006] FCA 1729 ; (2006) 157 FCR 1. In this case, the alleged contravention grounding injunctive relief was a contravention of s 18 of the Act. Regard to that section discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element, on this occasion related to listed threatened species included in the "extinct in the wild" category. Again, for reasons given in relation to Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play in this case in relation to s 142.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Millington v Loring (1880) 6 QBD 190</tocase>
<text>There is a question as to the content of the term "material facts" in O 11 r 2 of the rules. An English case, Millington v Loring (1880) 6 QBD 190 , is still annotated in the Butterworths Practice for a proposition that: 
 Whether or not a fact is material will depend on the circumstances of each case. Material facts are not limited to the facts constituted in the cause of action, but extend to the relief being sought, and generally, so that there is no chance of the respondent being taken by surprise. 

I can see how this proposition has pertinence in relation to the giving of particulars in relation to the damages which an applicant seeks in either a common law or statutory cause of action founded claim for damages. It is rather less easy to see how this has any application in relation to a claim for injunctive relief under s 475. Especially, that is so, having regard to the terms of s 479 which excludes from the fatality of impact on a discretion to grant injunctive relief particular considerations, that, under the general law of equity, would be followed. Whether or not the considerations that are set out in relation to these representations become material may depend upon the course taken by Burnett Water in its defence. I do not see that they have any place in the statement of claim. I strike them out.

Paragraphs 60-82 are as follows: 
 Compliance audit and internal audit 

 In early June 2007 the department administering the EPBC Act, then the Department of Environment and Water Resources ("DEWR"), informed the respondent that it proposed to conduct a random compliance inspection of the dam to assess compliance with the conditions of approval ("the compliance audit").
 Prior to the compliance audit occurring in June 2007 the upstream fishway had not been operated for a period of 8 consecutive months as particularised in paragraph 26 above.
 At the time of the compliance audit and subsequently a company trading as "SunWater" operated the dam as agent of the respondent.
 PARTICULARS OF AGENT AND AGENCY 

 
 (a) On or about 16 December 2005 the respondent became a wholly-owned subsidiary of SunWater Pty Ltd (ACN 059 666 625), trading as "SunWater".
 (b) on 16 January 2006 SunWater Pty Ltd changed its company name to ACN 059 666 625 Pty Ltd, trading as "SunWater".
 (c) On 12 May 2008 ACN 059 666 625 Pty Ltd was de-registered and its assets transferred to a newly incorporated company, SunWater Pty Ltd (ACN 131 034 985), trading as "SunWater").
 (d) The agency between the respondent (as principal) and SunWater(as agent) commenced in or about November 2005 when the dam commenced operation and continued thereafter.
 (e) The scope of the agency was at all material times for SunWater to operate the dam on the respondent's behalf, including compliance with the approval and negotiations with the department administering the EPBC Act. 

 Prior to the site visit to the dam by a four person audit team from DEWR for the purposes of performing the compliance audit, an employee of SunWater and agent of the respondent, Andrew Maughan, worked to ensure that the upstream fishway operation would be demonstrated to the auditors.
 When the DEWR audit team conducted a site inspection of the dam on 26 June 2007, SunWater staff acting as agents for the respondent operated the upstream fishway to represent to the auditors that the upstream fishway was in fact operational.
 Further, on 10 August 2007 Peter Sampson, General Manager Water Services, SunWater, and an agent of the Respondent, wrote to DEWR and requested that the audit report find, inter alia , that "The upstream fish lift is operational."
 In so doing Mr Sampson represented to DEWR that the upstream fishway was operational.
 On 8-10 October 2007 an internal auditor employed by SunWater, Danny Green, acting also as an agent for the respondent, conducted an internal audit of the environmental management system of the dam.
 Mr Green found in his report, dated 10 October 2007 ("the internal audit report") inter alia :
 
It is noted that SunWater may be breaching the conditions outlined within its Federal licence to operate and maintain Paradise Dam. The wording of the condition may work in the favour of SunWater however SunWater is exposed to negative publicity and undue political scrutiny even if a court does find that the organisation has not breached the conditions.
 
 Further, Mr Green found in the internal audit report:
 
There is a possible non-conformance with the operation of the upstream fish lift at Paradise Dam as it has only been operated 13 days in the year up to 30 June 2007.
 
 The operation of the upstream fishway at the Paradise Dam for 13 days in the year up to 30 June 2007 represented operation for 3.5% of total daily time.
 The findings of the internal audit report were not conveyed to DEWR.
 DEWR and representatives of SunWater, acting as agents for the respondent, arranged a meeting in Brisbane on 22 November 2007 to discuss a draft compliance audit report provided by DEWR to SunWater concerning the findings of the compliance audit of the dam conducted by DEWR in June 2007.
 On 14 November 2007 Mike Smith, Director of the DEWR Monitoring and Audit Section sent an email to Briony Pomplum, Environmental Services Manager, SunWater, setting out the issues that DEWR wished to address at the meeting. One of the issues raised by Mr Smith was:
 
Can SunWater provide advice as to whether the fishlift has been operating as intended i.e., with optimal operating times and if not, what are SunWater's plans to address any shortfall in operational performance?
 
 The proposed meeting on 22 November 2007 to discuss the draft DEWR compliance audit report was cancelled by DEWR and in lieu of the meeting SunWater prepared a letter to answer the questions raised by Mr Smith.
 Ms Pomplun prepared a draft response to Mr Smith's questions on 22 November 2007 that responded to his question regarding "whether the fishlift has been operating as intended ..." by stating in reply that the upstream fishway had been "plagued with mechanical failure."
 On 22 November 2007 Mr Danny Green, acting as an employee of SunWater and agent of the respondent, stated in an email in relation to the draft response prepared by Ms Pomplun, inter alia , that:
 
I suggest that the words responding to whether the fishlift has been operating as intended should be modified. The audit did not come down too hard on this aspect so I don't [sic] think we should include comments like "plagued with mechanical failure".
 
 Mr Green's email on 22 November 2007 in relation to Mr Pomplun's draft response was copied, inter alia , to Peter Boettcher, Chief Executive Officer of SunWater and Chief Operating Officer of the respondent.
 On 23 November 2007, Mr Boettcher wrote, as Chief Operating Officer of the respondent, to DEWR in lieu of the meeting planned for 22 November 2007 and responded to the question from DEWR particularised in paragraph 73 above by stating:
 
The upstream fishway operating range is EL 44.44m to EL66.66m. The fishway became operational when the dam commenced in December 2005. The fishway has not been operated as intended due to:
 
 December 2005 to March 2006 represented the commissioning phase of the fishway; Initial mechanical problems were experienced during March 2006 to June 2006; During the period June 2006 December 2006, the fishway operation was interrupted by the construction of the mini-hydro facility at the Dam; Advice was received in August 2006, from the Burnett Dam Alliance (BDA), to cease operating the fishway at the then current level of EL 49.09m, due to concerns by BDA that the fish hopper might hit a submerged rock pimple ( Evidence Doc No. 14 ). The storage continued below this level from August 2006 to October 2007. Investigations during July to September 2007 by [Burnett Water Pty Ltd (BWPL)], found that the fishway could in fact be operated to the full lower operating level of EL44.44m, without damaging the hopper. On 10 October 2007, a correction was received from BDA that the fishway could operate to the EL 44.44m ( Evidence Doc No. 15 ) and operation of the fishway recommenced with on-site supervision.
 
The current operation will be monitored to assess any further operational issues, whilst the operator is on-site. Once reliable operation is confirmed, continuous operation of the fishway will recommence.
 
 The statements by Mr Boettcher in his letter to DEWR of 23 November 2007, particularised in paragraph 78, acknowledged that:
 
 (a) condition 3 of the approval required continuous operation; and
 (b) the respondent knew it had failed to operate the upstream fishway for long periods. 

 The conduct engaged in by Mr Boettcher, set out in the preceding paragraphs, was engaged in on behalf of the respondent by Mr Boettcher as an employee of the respondent with in the scope of his actual or apparent authority.
 In the premises, that state of mind of Mr Boettcher in engaging in the conduct set out in the preceding paragraphs was the state of mind of the respondent pursuant to section 498B(2) of the EPBC Act.
 In the premises, the respondent, through its employees and agents, knew that the upstream fishway had not operated for long periods during 2006 and 2007 and the respondent knew that this contravened or may contravene condition 3 of the approval.

There are a number of criticisms that were made, legitimately, in my opinion, in relation to these paragraphs. As a general proposition the paragraphs plead evidence rather than material facts. That aside, paras 79 - 82 are particular conclusions related to Burnett Waters having acknowledged that condition 3 of the approval required continuance of operation and then Burnett Water knowingly contravening that. The submission is made that these allegations going to the subsequent conduct are irrelevant.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Minister for the Environment and Heritage v Greentree (No 2) [2004] FCA 741 ; (2004) 138 FCR 198</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/741.html</AustLII>
<text>On analysis, that reliance can be seen to be misconceived, for the following reasons: 
(a) Booth v Bosworth [2001] FCA 1453 ; (2001) 114 FCR 39. The foundation for the injunctive relief sought in that case under s 475 was an alleged breach of s 12 of the Act. An element of s 12 is that the action concerned either have a significant impact on world heritage values or be likely to have such an impact in respect of a declared world heritage property. In contrast, "significant impact" is - unless it has in some way in the wording of a condition in a particular case, and this is not one of no relevance at all in respect of whether there has been a contravention of a condition of the kind with which s 142 is concerned.
 
(b) Minister for the Environment and Heritage v Greentree (No 2) [2004] FCA 741 ; (2004) 138 FCR 198. In that case, the injunctive relief sought pursuant to s 475 had as its foundation an alleged breach of s 16 of the Act as read with s 17. Regard to s 16 discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element akin to that found in s 12, but in this instance focused upon the ecological character of a declared RAMSAR wetland. For reasons already given in respect of Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play here in relation to the alleged breach of the condition and hence a contravention of s 142.
 
(c) Brown v Forestry Tasmania (No 4) [2006] FCA 1729 ; (2006) 157 FCR 1. In this case, the alleged contravention grounding injunctive relief was a contravention of s 18 of the Act. Regard to that section discloses that it, too, has a "significant impact" element, on this occasion related to listed threatened species included in the "extinct in the wild" category. Again, for reasons given in relation to Booth [2001] FCA 1453 ; 114 FCR 39 , "significant impact" has no role to play in this case in relation to s 142.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NRMCA (Queensland) Limited v Andrew (1993) 2 Qd R 706</tocase>
<text>It is convenient also to make some comment in respect of what one might term a root authority in relation to factors that are relevant in deciding whether or not, in planning and environment cases, to grant injunctive relief as a consequence of a failure to comply with a condition of land use or with an unlawful use of land in some other way. That case is Warringah Shire Council v Sedevic (1987) 10 NSWLR 335. In that case (at page 339), Kirby P, as his Honour then was, sets out a number of guidelines for the exercise of a court's discretion in relation to the granting of injunctive relief. Whilst whether or not injunctive relief should be granted in the present case is dependent upon the terms of s 475 and also is informed by s 479, his Honour's guidelines nonetheless have a persuasive value. So, too, so far as the granting of injunctive relief is concerned as a matter of discretion, do remarks made in the Queensland Court of Appeal in NRMCA (Queensland) Limited v Andrew (1993) 2 Qd R 706 at 713. These remarks were made in the context of the width of the discretion granted to the court under Queensland's Local Government (Planning and Environment) Act 1990 (Qld). It was that stated that the discretion to grant or refuse an injunction is not constrained by any rule that it must enjoin the illegality unless special circumstances are shown. The court rejected a submission that there was a prima facie right to an injunction in the case before it, instead endorsing that the correct approach was to treat the matter as necessitating the exercise of wide discretion.

Paragraphs 53 - 59 are as follows: 
 Representations made to obtain approval 

 In seeking to obtain the approval the respondent submitted an environmental impact statement ("the EIS") to the Minister in September 2001 that, inter alia , proposed to install a fish transfer device to mitigate impacts on the passage of fish movement caused by the construction of the dam at an estimated cost of $1,492,000 within an overall project cost then estimated at $180,864,000.
 The fish transfer device was proposed by the respondent in the EIS to mitigate the impacts of the dam on a number of fish species, including lungfish.
 On 4 November 2002, Mike Montefiore, then Director of the respondent, wrote to the department then administering the EPBC Act, Environment Australia, regarding actions the respondent proposed to take focussed on the lungfish and giving commitments to implement a range of initiatives "to ensure the ongoing health fo the species."
 In his correspondence of 4 November 2002 Mr Montefiore stated that the project specific actions to protect lungfish to be undertaken by the respondent were, inter alia :
 
 incorporation of a fishway into the Burnett River Dam ... to allow downstream and upstream passage of fish, including lungfish. The fishway has been designed to accommodate the lungfish. 
 
 Based, inter alia , on the respondent's commitments to incorporate a fish transfer device into the dam, between or about 3 April 2003 and 29 July 2003 Environment Australia and the respondent negotiated and agreed to additional conditions to be attached to the approval focused on the lungfish.
 The respondent represented to Environment Australia on or about 26 June 2003 that the additional conditions were:
 
 ... specifically relevant to the lungfish that would, in the opinion of Burnett Water Pty Ltd and its expert advisers, be appropriate to protect the lungfish and mitigate damage to the lungfish from the construction and operation of the Burnett River Dam. 
 
 The additional conditions attached to the approval of the dam by the Minister on 8 August 2003 adopted to the respondent's commitments to "a suite of initiatives to address the long-term survival of the Australian lungfish." 
These paragraphs are directed to allegations in respect of representations said to have been made on behalf of Burnett Water in order to obtain the approval subject to conditions. They are not relevant to whether or not the condition has been breached. In relation to whether, as a matter of discretion, injunctive relief should go, it is possible to see how, having regard to Warringah Shire Council (1987) 10 NSWLR 335 and the NRMCA (Queensland) Limited (1993) 2 Qd R 706 , evidence of what was put to the Minister might have a relevance if what was constructed was something completely different.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Warringah Shire Council v Sedevic (1987) 10 NSWLR 335</tocase>
<text>It is convenient also to make some comment in respect of what one might term a root authority in relation to factors that are relevant in deciding whether or not, in planning and environment cases, to grant injunctive relief as a consequence of a failure to comply with a condition of land use or with an unlawful use of land in some other way. That case is Warringah Shire Council v Sedevic (1987) 10 NSWLR 335. In that case (at page 339), Kirby P, as his Honour then was, sets out a number of guidelines for the exercise of a court's discretion in relation to the granting of injunctive relief. Whilst whether or not injunctive relief should be granted in the present case is dependent upon the terms of s 475 and also is informed by s 479, his Honour's guidelines nonetheless have a persuasive value. So, too, so far as the granting of injunctive relief is concerned as a matter of discretion, do remarks made in the Queensland Court of Appeal in NRMCA (Queensland) Limited v Andrew (1993) 2 Qd R 706 at 713. These remarks were made in the context of the width of the discretion granted to the court under Queensland's Local Government (Planning and Environment) Act 1990 (Qld). It was that stated that the discretion to grant or refuse an injunction is not constrained by any rule that it must enjoin the illegality unless special circumstances are shown. The court rejected a submission that there was a prima facie right to an injunction in the case before it, instead endorsing that the correct approach was to treat the matter as necessitating the exercise of wide discretion.

Paragraphs 53 - 59 are as follows: 
 Representations made to obtain approval 

 In seeking to obtain the approval the respondent submitted an environmental impact statement ("the EIS") to the Minister in September 2001 that, inter alia , proposed to install a fish transfer device to mitigate impacts on the passage of fish movement caused by the construction of the dam at an estimated cost of $1,492,000 within an overall project cost then estimated at $180,864,000.
 The fish transfer device was proposed by the respondent in the EIS to mitigate the impacts of the dam on a number of fish species, including lungfish.
 On 4 November 2002, Mike Montefiore, then Director of the respondent, wrote to the department then administering the EPBC Act, Environment Australia, regarding actions the respondent proposed to take focussed on the lungfish and giving commitments to implement a range of initiatives "to ensure the ongoing health fo the species."
 In his correspondence of 4 November 2002 Mr Montefiore stated that the project specific actions to protect lungfish to be undertaken by the respondent were, inter alia :
 
 incorporation of a fishway into the Burnett River Dam ... to allow downstream and upstream passage of fish, including lungfish. The fishway has been designed to accommodate the lungfish. 
 
 Based, inter alia , on the respondent's commitments to incorporate a fish transfer device into the dam, between or about 3 April 2003 and 29 July 2003 Environment Australia and the respondent negotiated and agreed to additional conditions to be attached to the approval focused on the lungfish.
 The respondent represented to Environment Australia on or about 26 June 2003 that the additional conditions were:
 
 ... specifically relevant to the lungfish that would, in the opinion of Burnett Water Pty Ltd and its expert advisers, be appropriate to protect the lungfish and mitigate damage to the lungfish from the construction and operation of the Burnett River Dam. 
 
 The additional conditions attached to the approval of the dam by the Minister on 8 August 2003 adopted to the respondent's commitments to "a suite of initiatives to address the long-term survival of the Australian lungfish." 
These paragraphs are directed to allegations in respect of representations said to have been made on behalf of Burnett Water in order to obtain the approval subject to conditions. They are not relevant to whether or not the condition has been breached. In relation to whether, as a matter of discretion, injunctive relief should go, it is possible to see how, having regard to Warringah Shire Council (1987) 10 NSWLR 335 and the NRMCA (Queensland) Limited (1993) 2 Qd R 706 , evidence of what was put to the Minister might have a relevance if what was constructed was something completely different.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wide Bay Conservation Council Inc v Burnett Water Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1900</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1900.html</AustLII>
<text>The broad factual background to the proceedings is described in an earlier interlocutory judgment which I gave on 12 December 2008, Wide Bay Conservation Council Inc v Burnett Water Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1900.

The most convenient way to deal with the challenge made is, first, to make some particular comments on the general submission advanced on behalf of the Conservation Council: that the paragraphs under challenge were factors going to the exercise of a discretion to grant injunctive relief, and therefore necessarily pleaded in the statement of claim so as to avoid Burnett Water being taken by surprise. In that regard, a number of decisions of this Court in which a question of the granting of injunctive relief under s 475 of the Act were relied upon.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wide Bay Conservation Council Inc v Burnett Water Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 237</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/237.html</AustLII>
<text>This practice application is a sequel to an order which I made on 18 March 2009 striking out the then existing statement of claim for reasons which I then published: Wide Bay Conservation Council Inc v Burnett Water Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 237. Having so done, I granted leave to the Wide Bay Burnett Conservation Council Inc (Conservation Council) to file and serve an amended statement of claim. In today's application, Burnett Water Pty Ltd (Burnett Water) seeks the following orders in respect of the amended statement of claim: that paras 35 - 43, 45, 46 - 90 and 96 - 98 be struck out.

In Professor Cairns' work, Australian Civil Procedure (6 th Ed) at page 160, the following statement is made in respect of the Australian position relative to the system of pleadings which developed in England following the Judicature Act 1875 (UK) (Judicature Act) reforms: 
 The same system was later introduced into the Australian jurisdictions. The system of pleading initiated by the Judicature Act 1875 is still in force, although with some modifications. Supreme Courts in the Australian States and Territories are courts of unlimited jurisdiction. Their rules adopt the procedural concepts of the 1883 revision of the English rules of 1875. 

That particular observation made by Professor Cairns commended itself to the authors of Bullan and Leake and Jacob's Precedents of Pleadings (16 th Ed) at para 1-08 as a good background in respect of the Australian position. 
 
Professor Cairns, in the paragraph quoted, speaks of the position in relation to the Supreme Courts of the States and Territories. Whilst a purist might these days debate the proposition as to whether or not truly those courts are courts of unlimited jurisdiction, having regard to the impact of Federal statute law conferring exclusive jurisdictions on this Court, the proposition about the taking up of the Judicature Act rules which Professor Cairns makes in respect of the Supreme Courts, has, so far as the essence of the pleading rule in this court is concerned, equal resonance. By that I mean that in O 11 r 2 one finds familiar language having regard to post-Judicature Act pleading rules. That rule provides as follows:
 
 Subject to these rules: 

 
 (a) a pleading of a party shall contain and contain only a statement in summary form of the material facts on which the party relies but not the evidence by which those facts are to be proved.

Order 11, rule 16 of this Court's rules provides: 
 Where a pleading: 

 
 (a) discloses no reasonable cause of action or defence or other case appropriate to the nature of the pleading; 
 (b) has a tendency to cause prejudice, embarrassment or delay in the proceeding; or 
 (c) is otherwise an abuse of process of the court, the court may at any stage of the proceeding order that the whole or any part of the pleading be struck out. 

It is under this rule that Burnett Water seeks the striking out of the paragraphs identified.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>