<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Priestley v Hawker [2009] FCA 561 (28 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/561.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gurney v Grimmer (1932) 38 Com Cas 7</tocase>
<text>Clause 2.3.3(2) of the Determination, which uses the term ' and/or ' without further limitation, leaves open the possibility in option (d) above. A referral in terms of option (d) is not void for uncertainty ( Looke v Parbury, Henty &amp; Co Pty Ltd [1950] VLR 94) but authorises the Parliamentary Service Commissioner to decide which of the above alternatives (ie. (a), (b) or (c)) to adopt ( Gurney v Grimmer (1932) 38 Com Cas 7).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Looke v Parbury, Henty &amp; Co Pty Ltd [1950] VLR 94</tocase>
<text>Clause 2.3.3(2) of the Determination, which uses the term ' and/or ' without further limitation, leaves open the possibility in option (d) above. A referral in terms of option (d) is not void for uncertainty ( Looke v Parbury, Henty &amp; Co Pty Ltd [1950] VLR 94) but authorises the Parliamentary Service Commissioner to decide which of the above alternatives (ie. (a), (b) or (c)) to adopt ( Gurney v Grimmer (1932) 38 Com Cas 7).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Priestley v Godwin (Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner) [2008] HCA 59 ; (2008) 251 ALR 612</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/59.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Priestley made submissions concerning orders made at an earlier stage of these proceedings by a judge of the Court. No appeal or application for leave to appeal was brought against those orders in this Court. However, it appears that those orders were the subject of consideration by the High Court in Priestley v Godwin (Parliamentary Service Merit Protection Commissioner) (2008) 251 CLR 612. In that case, French CJ said that Mr Priestley's allegations regarding those previous orders were ' baseless '. I indicated to Mr Priestley that I would not deal with his submissions regarding those previous orders in these proceedings and I do not do so.

In his application, Mr Priestley also seeks orders that he be provided with a statement in writing setting out the findings on material questions of fact, referring to the evidence or other material on which those findings were based and giving reasons for the claimed decision dated 10 May 2007, as well as disclosure of the evidence or other material on which the findings on material questions of fact were based. To the extent that this represents an additional order to the order sought to provide reasons for the claimed decision, it is also predicated upon there having been a decision as Mr Priestley characterised it made on that date. The relevant facts as to whether or not the claimed decision was made and what decision was made are evident from the documentary material in evidence. There was no claimed decision. He is not entitled to these orders.

The decision for which Mr Priestley seeks reasons was not made. Mr Priestley's application has no reasonable prospect of success. It follows that the proceedings should be dismissed pursuant to s 31A of the Federal Court Act, with costs. 
 I certify that the preceding twenty-six (26) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Bennett. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 28 May 2009
 
 The Applicant appeared in person. 
 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr D O'Donovan 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 28 April 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 28 May 2009 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/561.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Priestley v Godwin (No 4) [2009] FCA 560</tocase>
<text>It follows from my conclusions above that it is unnecessary to consider whether or not Mr Priestley is a person aggrieved or whether or not s 23 of the Federal Court Act is a source of additional jurisdiction. In any event, I considered these grounds in Priestley v Godwin (No 4) [2009] FCA 560 which was heard concurrently with this application and the same conclusions apply. Section 23 of the Federal Court Act is not a source of additional jurisdiction ( Thomson Australian Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150 at 161). Mr Priestley may not have established that he is a person aggrieved but that does not fall to be determined on this application under s 31A of the Federal Court Act. I am prepared to assume for the purposes of this notice of motion that, had the claimed decision been made, Mr Priestley would have been a person aggrieved.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Thomson Australian Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1981/48.html</AustLII>
<text>It follows from my conclusions above that it is unnecessary to consider whether or not Mr Priestley is a person aggrieved or whether or not s 23 of the Federal Court Act is a source of additional jurisdiction. In any event, I considered these grounds in Priestley v Godwin (No 4) [2009] FCA 560 which was heard concurrently with this application and the same conclusions apply. Section 23 of the Federal Court Act is not a source of additional jurisdiction ( Thomson Australian Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Trade Practices Commission [1981] HCA 48 ; (1981) 148 CLR 150 at 161). Mr Priestley may not have established that he is a person aggrieved but that does not fall to be determined on this application under s 31A of the Federal Court Act. I am prepared to assume for the purposes of this notice of motion that, had the claimed decision been made, Mr Priestley would have been a person aggrieved.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>