<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Mellor v Australian Postal Corporation [2009] FCA 504 (19 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/504.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Asioty v Canberra Abattoir Proprietary Limited [1989] HCA 40 ; (1989) 167 CLR 533</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/40.html</AustLII>
<text>The fact that symptoms abate on each occasion that the worker ceases work does not preclude compensation where enhanced susceptibility to the onset of symptoms has been caused by the work. In those circumstances, the enhanced susceptibility constitutes an aggravation of the disease ( Asioty v Canberra Abattoir Proprietary Limited [1989] HCA 40 ; (1989) 167 CLR 533 at 540).

Neither the absence of change in the underlying condition nor the temporary nature of the symptoms experienced preclude the existence of an aggravation of an ailment for the purposes of the SRC Act ( Federal Broom; Asioty; Beattie ).

In Asioty, there had been an increased susceptibility to dermatitis caused by the employment of the worker in an abattoir. That constituted the aggravation or exacerbation of the disease. Here, the Tribunal did not find any increased susceptibility but rather that employment resulted in temporary pain from Mr Mellor's back without any permanent effect.

At [259] the Tribunal stated that it accepted that increased symptoms in the form of pain constituted a temporary aggravation of the constitutional kyphoscoliosis of the thoracic spine. The Tribunal then turned to consider whether that temporary aggravation constituted an aggravation to a "material degree". It is at that stage of the reasoning that the Tribunal concluded that the thoracic pain did not fulfil the requirements of an injury under the SRC Act.

In considering the lumbar spine, the Tribunal accepted that the pain constituted an aggravation of Mr Mellor's condition but found that it was a temporary aggravation that ceased when he stopped his work activities or shortly thereafter. The Tribunal found that this did not fulfil the requirement that Mr Mellor's employment contribute to his lower back conditions in a material degree.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Canute [2005] FCAFC 262 ; (2005) 148 FCR 232</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/262.html</AustLII>
<text>That is, the Tribunal concluded that the employment was the cause of the aggravation represented by the pain but that the effect of that aggravation was not material because it was temporary and not severe. Is the requirement of materiality directed to the cause of the aggravation or its effect? "Disease" means an ailment or aggravation of an ailment ' that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment '. "Injury" means, relevantly, a disease or an aggravation of an injury other than a disease. In Sahu-Khan , Finn J traced the legislative history of and judicial consideration of the requirement of materiality, including the decision of the Full Court in Comcare v Canute [2005] FCAFC 262 ; (2005) 148 FCR 232. In Canute at [67], French and Stone JJ said that the term "material" ' imposes an evaluative threshold below which a causal connection may be disregarded '. Justice Finn in Sahu-Khan adopted that analysis at [13]. It is the nature of the contribution that is necessarily material ( Sahu-Khan at [15]).

Australia Post submits that the requirement of materiality qualifies the word "ailment" in the expression ' the aggravation of any such ailment; being ... an aggravation [of any such ailment] that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment '. I do not accept this to be the case. It is also inconsistent with the discussion of materiality in Canute and Sahu-Khan , although neither of those cases directly considers the issue raised in the present case. Australia Post submits that Parliament would not have intended that the Commonwealth be liable for any aggravation of disease regardless of how insignificant that aggravation might be. However, s 4 does not give effect to such an intention.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Sahu-Khan [2007] FCA 15 ; (2007) 156 FCR 536</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/15.html</AustLII>
<text>The requirement of materiality is, by reason of the definition of "disease" in s 4, a requirement that the employee's employment contribute materially to the suffering of the ailment in question ( Comcare v Sahu-Khan [2007] FCA 15 ; (2007) 156 FCR 536 at [16] per Finn J) or to the aggravation of the ailment, that is, '[i] n a material degree; substantially, considerably ' (the Shorter Oxford English Dictionary cited by Finn J in Sahu-Khan at [15]).

Mr Mellor submits that, in his case, the correct question is not whether the underlying pathology of a disease or frank injury had been materially contributed to but whether the aggravation of symptoms, being an injury, had been materially contributed to. The worsening of symptoms of an injury can, he submits, be sufficient to ground liability without any change in the underlying pathology.

That is, the Tribunal concluded that the employment was the cause of the aggravation represented by the pain but that the effect of that aggravation was not material because it was temporary and not severe. Is the requirement of materiality directed to the cause of the aggravation or its effect? "Disease" means an ailment or aggravation of an ailment ' that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment '. "Injury" means, relevantly, a disease or an aggravation of an injury other than a disease. In Sahu-Khan , Finn J traced the legislative history of and judicial consideration of the requirement of materiality, including the decision of the Full Court in Comcare v Canute [2005] FCAFC 262 ; (2005) 148 FCR 232. In Canute at [67], French and Stone JJ said that the term "material" ' imposes an evaluative threshold below which a causal connection may be disregarded '. Justice Finn in Sahu-Khan adopted that analysis at [13]. It is the nature of the contribution that is necessarily material ( Sahu-Khan at [15]).

The Tribunal correctly summarised the principles in Sahu-Khan at [227]. It appreciated that there was a requirement of materiality for a causal connection to be found. However, at [286]-[287], in considering the lumbar spine, it said that because there was no lasting effect of the aggravation and no underlying change in the condition, the contribution by the employment to the lower back conditions was not material. With respect to the thoracic spine, the Tribunal stated at [260] that it did not accept that the temporary increase in Mr Mellor's symptoms represented an aggravation of his condition in a material degree. This was to confuse the requirement that the employment be a material cause of the aggravation with a requirement that the effect of the aggravation be material.

The confusion on this point is also evident from [225] of the Tribunal's decision, where the following statement is made: 
 Mr Mellor claims that his employment contributed to or aggravated all of these ailments, and that the contribution or aggravation was to a material degree so that these ailments constituted an injury within the meaning of the [SRC] Act, and therefore he is entitled to claim compensation pursuant to s 14 of the [SRC] Act. 
 
 (emphasis added)

The Tribunal may have been led to take this course because of the way in which the cased was argued by Mr Mellor.

Australia Post submits that the requirement of materiality qualifies the word "ailment" in the expression ' the aggravation of any such ailment; being ... an aggravation [of any such ailment] that was contributed to in a material degree by the employee's employment '. I do not accept this to be the case. It is also inconsistent with the discussion of materiality in Canute and Sahu-Khan , although neither of those cases directly considers the issue raised in the present case. Australia Post submits that Parliament would not have intended that the Commonwealth be liable for any aggravation of disease regardless of how insignificant that aggravation might be. However, s 4 does not give effect to such an intention.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth of Australia v Beattie (1981) 35 ALR 369</tocase>
<text>As was pointed out by the Full Court in Commonwealth of Australia v Beattie (1981) 35 ALR 369 , the definitions in issue in Federal Broom were different from those in Beattie (as they are from the definitions in s 4 of the SRC Act). The Full Court said at 377-378 that, notwithstanding differences, Federal Broom establishes that there may be an exacerbation or aggravation, which relevantly mean the same thing, notwithstanding that there is no change in the underlying pathology. Whether there is such an exacerbation or aggravation is a question of fact in each case.

For present purposes, the relevant part of the definition of "injury" is the reference to "disease", which, in turn, is defined as an ailment or an aggravation of an ailment to which the employee's employment contributes in a material degree. On the Tribunal's findings, Mr Mellor's employment did not affect the underlying pathology of his back conditions but, in causing pain, it rendered the back conditions temporarily symptomatic, or irritated them ( Macquarie Dictionary , definition of "aggravate"). Pain may constitute an aggravation of an ailment or injury ( Beattie ). The Tribunal's conclusions on aggravation and materiality

In the case of each of Mr Mellor's thoracic kyphoscoliosis and lumbar spine, the Tribunal concluded that the requirement of materiality was not satisfied. This was because the Tribunal did not accept that a temporary increase in symptoms represented an aggravation of the thoracic spine condition in a material degree and found that the temporary aggravation of the lumbar spine condition meant that the contribution to the lower back condition was not sufficiently significant to meet the threshold of "in a material degree".

Further, Australia Post points out that the Tribunal was referred to Tippett v Australian Postal Corporation (1998) 27 AAR 40 , which inaccurately summarised the joint judgment of Evatt and Sheppard JJ in Beattie as stating that an injury will be aggravated if the experience of the injury is increased or intensified. In fact, their Honours said that ' it is enough to say that pain brought on by work activity may constitute an aggravation ' (emphasis added). Australia Post submits that this may well have influenced the Tribunal to make findings that pain and discomfort in Mr Mellor's thoracic and lumbar regions constituted temporary aggravations, notwithstanding its reservations made apparent by the qualifications indicating that the Tribunal was not persuaded that the pain in each case actually amounted to aggravations of the underlying ailments.

Australia Post submits that I should draw the conclusion that, had the Tribunal been aware of the correct statement in Beattie , it would have concluded that no aggravation had occurred and that Mr Mellor was not suffering from work-aggravated diseases in his thoracic and lumbar spines. It follows, in Australia Post's submission, that I should come to that conclusion and not remit the matter to the Tribunal.

I see the force of the submission but I do not accept that the conclusions that the Tribunal would make in applying Beattie are so clear from its reasons. The Tribunal expressed its conclusions in terms of a requirement that the aggravation be material. The Tribunal did not correctly address the question whether or not the pain that Mr Mellor felt, being only temporary but experienced when he returned to work, constituted an aggravation of an ailment to which his employment contributed in a material degree and which, in turn, constituted a disease and thereby an injury for the purposes of the Act.

It may be that the Tribunal will conclude that the symptoms suffered by Mr Mellor do not amount to an aggravation but that is not conclusive from the reasons.

The matter should be remitted to the Tribunal to enable it to make findings in accordance with law.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Federal Broom Company Pty Limited v Semlitch [1964] HCA 34 ; (1964) 110 CLR 626</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/34.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Mellor relies for that principle on Federal Broom Company Pty Limited v Semlitch [1964] HCA 34 ; (1964) 110 CLR 626 , where the High Court held that there is a compensable exacerbation of a disease where the experience of the disease by the patient is increased or intensified by an increase or intensification of the symptoms. In that case, the plaintiff was already suffering from a disease but her employment resulted in a new manifestation of it. Justice McTiernan observed at 629 that, for the purposes of the Act then under consideration, the Workers' Compensation Act 1926-1960 (NSW), manifestations of a disease are relevant only so far as they cause incapacity and where the manifestations are causally related to employment. Justice Kitto, with whom Taylor and Owen JJ agreed, said at 632-633 that employment can be said to be a contributing factor to the aggravation of a disease where it provides an incident or state of affairs to which the worker is exposed in the performance of his (sic) duties and to which the worker would not otherwise have been exposed. There is no requirement that the underlying disease is made worse; it is sufficient if a new manifestation is suffered. Indeed, his Honour noted at 634, "exacerbation" applies to the effects of the disease rather than to the disease itself. Justice Windeyer said at 642 that it was not to the point that the plaintiff might have broken down because of her illness in any event; the precipitating event occurred at work.

As was pointed out by the Full Court in Commonwealth of Australia v Beattie (1981) 35 ALR 369 , the definitions in issue in Federal Broom were different from those in Beattie (as they are from the definitions in s 4 of the SRC Act). The Full Court said at 377-378 that, notwithstanding differences, Federal Broom establishes that there may be an exacerbation or aggravation, which relevantly mean the same thing, notwithstanding that there is no change in the underlying pathology. Whether there is such an exacerbation or aggravation is a question of fact in each case.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Tippett v Australian Postal Corporation (1998) 27 AAR 40</tocase>
<text>Further, Australia Post points out that the Tribunal was referred to Tippett v Australian Postal Corporation (1998) 27 AAR 40 , which inaccurately summarised the joint judgment of Evatt and Sheppard JJ in Beattie as stating that an injury will be aggravated if the experience of the injury is increased or intensified. In fact, their Honours said that ' it is enough to say that pain brought on by work activity may constitute an aggravation ' (emphasis added). Australia Post submits that this may well have influenced the Tribunal to make findings that pain and discomfort in Mr Mellor's thoracic and lumbar regions constituted temporary aggravations, notwithstanding its reservations made apparent by the qualifications indicating that the Tribunal was not persuaded that the pain in each case actually amounted to aggravations of the underlying ailments.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>