<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Van Efferen v CMA Corporation Limited [2009] FCA 597 (4 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/597.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Amcor Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2005] HCA 10 ; (2005) 222 CLR 241</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/10.html</AustLII>
<text>This passage was quoted with approval by two members of the High Court in Amcor Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2005] HCA 10 ; (2005) 222 CLR 241 at 271 (Kirby J), 282-3 (Callinan J). In Australasian Meat Industry Employees Union v Coles Supermarkets Australia Pty Ltd (1998) 80 IR 208 at 212 Northrop J expressly agreed with this statement of principles and held that it had even stronger application to certified agreements than it did to awards.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australasian Meat Industry Employees Union v Coles Supermarkets Australia Pty Ltd (1998) 80 IR 208</tocase>
<text>This passage was quoted with approval by two members of the High Court in Amcor Ltd v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2005] HCA 10 ; (2005) 222 CLR 241 at 271 (Kirby J), 282-3 (Callinan J). In Australasian Meat Industry Employees Union v Coles Supermarkets Australia Pty Ltd (1998) 80 IR 208 at 212 Northrop J expressly agreed with this statement of principles and held that it had even stronger application to certified agreements than it did to awards.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (1977) 180 CLR 266</tocase>
<text>In this Court single judges have adopted a more guarded approach. In McDonald (at 398-400) Buchanan J reviewed the authorities relating to the mutual trust and confidence term. He expressed disquiet about the notion that such a term could have escaped judicial notice for so long. More significantly he queried whether such a term could be implied consistently with the principles expounded by the High Court in BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (1977) 180 CLR 266 at 283. I respectfully share his Honour's reservations.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth v Amann Aviation Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 54 ; (1991) 174 CLR 64</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1991/54.html</AustLII>
<text>Although s 721(1) of the Act provides that a person who suffers loss or damage as a result of a breach of an AWA may recover that loss or damage in curial proceedings, the provision is silent as to the basis on which such loss and damage should be calculated. Mr Van Efferen submits that, because AWAs are statutory contracts, damages should be calculated as they would be in respect of any breach of contract. The applicant should be placed in the same situation, as far as money may do it, as if the contract had been performed: Commonwealth v Amann Aviation Pty Ltd [1991] HCA 54 ; (1991) 174 CLR 64 at 80 (Mason CJ and Dawson J), 98-9 (Brennan J), 116 (Deane J) and 148 (Gaudron J). In appropriate cases damages could be calculated by reference to what the applicant was entitled to expect by way of performance by the respondent and the losses incurred when the respondent failed to comply with its contractual obligations: Amann Aviation , at 91-2.

Mr Van Efferen submitted that, had CMA complied with clause 2.10, he would not have been removed from the Dolphin Project and would have continued to perform his duties as marine supervisor until the project was completed on 15 April 2008. He submitted that damages should be assessed by reference to what he would have earned during this period, less the amount which he had earned since the termination of his employment. Alternatively, Mr Van Efferen contended that the same measure of damages should be awarded if a "loss of expectation" or "loss of chance" analysis of the kind deployed in Amann Aviation was applied.

The award of compensatory damages for breach of contract protects the expectation interest of the innocent party: Amann Aviation at 80. That expectation is that the contract would be performed according to its terms. Mr Van Efferen sought to characterise the present case as one involving a "loss of chance" because he had lost the opportunity to obtain benefits which would have resulted from his continued employment with CMA. These submissions led to what I regard as an unprofitable debate about whether damages could and should be awarded in the present case on the alternative basis of a "loss of chance".

In Amann Aviation , the plaintiff obtained damages against the Commonwealth for breach of a three year contract under which the plaintiff was to provide aerial coastal surveillance. Damages were awarded on the conventional basis. Additional damages were also awarded to compensate the plaintiff for a loss of opportunity to obtain a further contract after the repudiated contract had run its term. The plaintiff succeeded. The court considered that there was "a strong prospect of renewal" (at 94): it would have had the benefit of three years experience and any competitor would effectively have been starting from scratch. It was this latter award of damages that attracted the terms "loss of a chance" or "lost opportunity".

More recently, in McDonald v Parnell Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd (2007) 168 IR 375 Buchanan J cautioned that the award of damages for "loss of a chance" could not occur, consistently with Amann Aviation , in the absence of a fixed term contract and evidence supporting the possibility that the contract might be renewed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kilburn v Enzed Precision Products Pty Ltd (1988) 4 VIR 31</tocase>
<text>Where an employer wrongfully terminates an employment contract which has a fixed term, thereby causing damage to an employee, damages are normally calculated on the basis that the employee would have enjoyed the benefits of the contract for the remainder of its term: see Kilburn v Enzed Precision Products Pty Ltd (1988) 4 VIR 31 at 33; Patterson v Middle Harbour Yacht Club (1996) 64 FCR 405 at 406; Martin v Tasmanian Development and Resources (1999) 89 IR 98 at 120-1. The employee is under an obligation to mitigate his loss by seeking to obtain alternative remunerative employment. Although the AWA had a three year term, Mr Van Efferen only sought damages until CMA's work on the Dolphin Project ceased.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 182</tocase>
<text>In dealing with the construction of awards in Kucks v CSR Limited (1996) 66 IR 182 at 184 Madgwick J observed that: 
 "It is trite that narrow or pedantic approaches to the interpretation of an award are misplaced. The search is for the meaning intended by the framer(s) of the document, bearing in mind that such framer(s) were likely of a practical bent of mind: they may well have been more concerned with expressing an intention in ways likely to have been understood in the context of the relevant industry and industrial relations environment than with legal niceties or jargon. Thus, for example, it is justifiable to read the award to give effect to its evident purposes, having regard to such context, despite mere inconsistencies or infelicities of expression which might tend to some other reading. And meanings which avoid inconvenience or injustice may reasonably be strained for. For reasons such as these, expressions which have been held in the case of other instruments to have been used to mean particular things may sensibly and properly be held to mean something else in the document at hand."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Martin v Tasmania Development and Resources (1999) 89 IR 98</tocase>
<text>Where an employer wrongfully terminates an employment contract which has a fixed term, thereby causing damage to an employee, damages are normally calculated on the basis that the employee would have enjoyed the benefits of the contract for the remainder of its term: see Kilburn v Enzed Precision Products Pty Ltd (1988) 4 VIR 31 at 33; Patterson v Middle Harbour Yacht Club (1996) 64 FCR 405 at 406; Martin v Tasmanian Development and Resources (1999) 89 IR 98 at 120-1. The employee is under an obligation to mitigate his loss by seeking to obtain alternative remunerative employment. Although the AWA had a three year term, Mr Van Efferen only sought damages until CMA's work on the Dolphin Project ceased.

Full Courts of this Court have applied the "loss of a chance" approach to the assessment of damages for breaches of employment contracts. In Tasmania Development and Resources v Martin [1999] FCA 593 ; (2000) 97 IR 66 the Full Court upheld the trial judge's decision to award damages to reflect the applicant's loss of the prospect that his contract would be renewed even though he had no legal right to renewal. The applicant was employed by a statutory authority. He was employed on a three year contract. After about 18 months his employment was terminated on the grounds of redundancy. The trial judge found that the contract had been terminated by the statutory authority in breach of a provision which required that there be consultation between employer and employee before an employee was terminated for redundancy. The trial judge held that, had the contract not been wrongly terminated, the employee would have enjoyed its benefits for the remainder of the three year term. He allowed damages for that period. He also allowed a further sum to compensate the employee for loss of the chance of obtaining a fresh contract at the end of the term of the existing contract.

In any event, in the circumstances in the present case, it is, at best for Mr Van Efferen, doubtful that the two implied terms add anything to CMA's contractual obligations having regard to the protective procedures incorporated expressly in clause 2.10 of the AWA. CMA was obliged to act in good faith in applying clause 2.10: cf Tasmania Development and Resources v Martin [1999] FCA 593 ; (2000) 97 IR 66 at 72. Had it done so no breach would have occurred.

No detailed submissions were advanced relating to the precise terms of the orders which should be made were Mr Van Efferen to be successful. In particular no attention was directed as to the taxation implications of any order which the Court might be minded to make in Mr Van Efferen's favour: see Martin v Tasmania Development and Resources (1999) 89 IR 98 at 121-122. It is also necessary to consider whether any specific provision should be made in the court's order to deal with Mr Van Efferen's entitlement to interest. I will, therefore, direct that the parties file and serve minutes of orders which will give effect to these reasons.
 I certify that the preceding eighty-eight (88) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice TRACEY. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 4 June 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr J L Bourke and Mr M Felman 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Petersens Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr T Saunders 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Sparke Helmore Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 16, 17 and 18 December 2008 
 
 Date of Judgment: 4 June 2009 
 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/597.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>McDonald v Parnell Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd (2007) 168 IR 375</tocase>
<text>CMA's argument on damages seemed to proceed on the assumption that compensatory damages were not available. It resisted the "loss of chance" claim on the basis that Mr Van Efferen did not have a contract for a specific term and that no question of the possibility of renewal of the contract arose: see McDonald v Parnell Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd (2007) 168 IR 375 at 397-8. In this context it relied on the arguments, outlined above at [52] which, it contended, supported the view that there was no causal nexus between any contravention of clause 2.10 and the damage alleged by Mr Van Efferen.

More recently, in McDonald v Parnell Laboratories (Aust) Pty Ltd (2007) 168 IR 375 Buchanan J cautioned that the award of damages for "loss of a chance" could not occur, consistently with Amann Aviation , in the absence of a fixed term contract and evidence supporting the possibility that the contract might be renewed.

In this Court single judges have adopted a more guarded approach. In McDonald (at 398-400) Buchanan J reviewed the authorities relating to the mutual trust and confidence term. He expressed disquiet about the notion that such a term could have escaped judicial notice for so long. More significantly he queried whether such a term could be implied consistently with the principles expounded by the High Court in BP Refinery (Westernport) Pty Ltd v Shire of Hastings (1977) 180 CLR 266 at 283. I respectfully share his Honour's reservations.

As a single judge I would follow the decisions of other single judges unless I considered them to be clearly wrong: see Bank of Western Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 55 FCR 233 at 255. Although Buchanan J's observations in McDonald were obiter I nonetheless consider them to be correct. Kenny J's ruling in Walker forms part of the ratio of her decision in that case. I do not consider either decision to be clearly wrong. Had it been necessary I would have followed them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Pan Foods Company Importers and Distributors Pty Ltd v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [2000] HCA 20 ; (2000) 170 ALR 579</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/20.html</AustLII>
<text>Guidance as to the construction of industrial instruments may also be obtained by reference to principles which courts apply to the construction of commercial contracts. Commercial contracts should, as Kirby J held in Pan Foods Company Importers &amp; Distributors Pty Ltd v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [2000] HCA 20 ; (2000) 170 ALR 579 at 584 "be construed practically, so as to give effect to their presumed commercial purposes and so as not to defeat the achievement of such purposes by an excessively narrow and artificially restricted construction." An interpretation which accords with business common sense will be preferred to one which does not: see Upper Hunter County District Council v Australian Chilling and Freezing Co Ltd [1968] HCA 8 ; (1968) 118 CLR 429 at 437.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Patterson v Middle Harbour Yacht Club (1996) 64 FCR 405 at 406</tocase>
<text>Where an employer wrongfully terminates an employment contract which has a fixed term, thereby causing damage to an employee, damages are normally calculated on the basis that the employee would have enjoyed the benefits of the contract for the remainder of its term: see Kilburn v Enzed Precision Products Pty Ltd (1988) 4 VIR 31 at 33; Patterson v Middle Harbour Yacht Club (1996) 64 FCR 405 at 406; Martin v Tasmanian Development and Resources (1999) 89 IR 98 at 120-1. The employee is under an obligation to mitigate his loss by seeking to obtain alternative remunerative employment. Although the AWA had a three year term, Mr Van Efferen only sought damages until CMA's work on the Dolphin Project ceased.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Russell v The Trustees of the Roman Catholic Church for the Archdiocese of Sydney [2008] NSWCA 217 ; (2008) 176 IR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/217.html</AustLII>
<text>In Russell Rothman J held that both terms should be implied in contracts of employment. In that case they did not avail the employee because, although they had been breached, the plaintiff had suffered no damage by reason of the breaches. On appeal, the New South Wales Court of Appeal went no further than holding that such terms may be implied in contracts of employment. Basten JA was (at [2008] NSWCA 217 ; (2008) 176 IR 82 [32]) inclined to treat the two implied terms as a single obligation. He considered (at [33]) that there was uncertainty as to the "scope and extent of the implied duties." Campbell JA was prepared to assume, without deciding, that an employer owed implied contractual obligations of the kind relied on by Mr Van Efferen. Giles JA (at [1]) was also prepared to assume rather than determine that such implied terms were incorporated in contracts of employment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Russell v The Trustees of the Roman Catholic Church for the Archdiocese of Sydney [2007] NSWSC 104 ; (2007) 69 NSWLR 198</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2007/104.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Tasmania Development &amp; Resources v Martin [1999] FCA 593 ; (2000) 97 IR 66</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/593.html</AustLII>
<text>Full Courts of this Court have applied the "loss of a chance" approach to the assessment of damages for breaches of employment contracts. In Tasmania Development and Resources v Martin [1999] FCA 593 ; (2000) 97 IR 66 the Full Court upheld the trial judge's decision to award damages to reflect the applicant's loss of the prospect that his contract would be renewed even though he had no legal right to renewal. The applicant was employed by a statutory authority. He was employed on a three year contract. After about 18 months his employment was terminated on the grounds of redundancy. The trial judge found that the contract had been terminated by the statutory authority in breach of a provision which required that there be consultation between employer and employee before an employee was terminated for redundancy. The trial judge held that, had the contract not been wrongly terminated, the employee would have enjoyed its benefits for the remainder of the three year term. He allowed damages for that period. He also allowed a further sum to compensate the employee for loss of the chance of obtaining a fresh contract at the end of the term of the existing contract.

In any event, in the circumstances in the present case, it is, at best for Mr Van Efferen, doubtful that the two implied terms add anything to CMA's contractual obligations having regard to the protective procedures incorporated expressly in clause 2.10 of the AWA. CMA was obliged to act in good faith in applying clause 2.10: cf Tasmania Development and Resources v Martin [1999] FCA 593 ; (2000) 97 IR 66 at 72. Had it done so no breach would have occurred.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>In determining whether a commercial document imposes contractual obligations regard is had to the intention of the parties: would a reasonable person conclude that the person making the alleged binding promise intend to be contractually bound by that promise. In Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 179 the High Court summarised the position as follows: 
 "It is not the subjective beliefs or understanding of the parties about their rights and liabilities that govern their contractual relations. What matters is what each party by words and conduct would have led a reasonable person in the position of the other party to believe ... That, normally requires consideration not only of the text, but also of the surrounding circumstances known to the parties, and the purpose and object of the transaction."

Clause 2.10 is, as it says, designed to deal with "concerns" which CMA may, from time to time have about the behaviour of its employees. Those concerns may arise from some innocent act of the employee which leads CMA mistakenly to believe that some misconduct has occurred. At the other end of the spectrum concern may be raised by blatant misconduct which occurs in the presence of a supervisor. Between these extremes fall many forms of conduct which have the potential to give rise to concern on the part of the employer. They include matters such as unapproved absences from duty, the failure to meet production targets, the performance of work in a manner which might compromise the health and safety of other employees, failure to contribute as part of a team and many more possibilities. Clause 2.10 is intended to deal with all such situations. Step 1 would, for example, be of use where CMA suspected that an employee had engaged in some misconduct but was not sure. The discussion between the manager and the employee may set the manager's mind at rest. Step 1 might also be useful where an employee is thought not to be working productively. If the issue is raised with the employee the employee may be able to offer a satisfactory explanation to CMA such as that his work is being impeded by some work-related injury. Serious misconduct such as abuse of a supervisor or actions which jeopardise the health and safety of other employees can be dealt with by immediate counselling under Step 2. The subsequent steps ensure that the employee knows that he or she is on notice that any repetition will place his or her continued employment in jeopardy. Extreme misconduct may lead to summary dismissal.

Clause 2.10 can be engaged even when CMA has not determined that disciplinary action against the employee is warranted. The prefatory words of the clause make no mention of disciplinary action and do not condition its application on a decision by CMA that disciplinary action is warranted. The adoption of the term "grievance procedure" suggests that the clause was intended to have application to a wider range of "concerns" than those which have disciplinary implications. This is made plain by a reading of the clause as a whole. Its language confirms that it has application if CMA has a concern about an employee's behaviour and wishes to ascertain whether the employee has, in fact, done anything wrong. CMA may also harbour concerns about behaviour which it is satisfied amounts to misconduct but, in respect of which, it considers it appropriate to do no more than draw the matter to the employee's attention and request or direct that the conduct not be repeated. The word "grievance" is, of course, apt also to embrace CMA's reaction to conduct by an employee which CMA considers does or may warrant disciplinary action.

The terms in which industrial instruments are drafted often require a distinction to be drawn between aspirational and promissory statements. In accordance with the objective theory of contract expounded in Toll , a provision in a document proffered by an employer, will be treated as promissory in nature if the hypothetical, reasonable, potential employee to whom the document is presented would have concluded that CMA intended to be contractually bound to follow the procedures, outlined in it if CMA developed any concerns about the behaviour of the employee.

Whether or not he or she would have so concluded will depend on a consideration of the terms of the clause, the surrounding circumstances known to the parties and the nature of the arrangement which is being entered into. In my view clause 2.10 does impose an obligation on CMA to proceed at least as far as step 1 in a case such as the present.

The clause appears in a particular type of contract which is recognised and regulated by statute. It is an agreement which is intended to govern the employment relationship of an employer and an employee. It provides a form of protection to an employee whose conduct has, for any reason, given the employer cause for concern. It is designed to ensure that the employee is informed of the nature of those concerns and has the opportunity to disabuse the employer or to have the opportunity (in most instances) of rectifying any shortcomings which have given rise to the employer's misgivings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Upper Hunter County District Council v Australian Chilling and Freezing Co Ltd [1968] HCA 8 ; (1968) 118 CLR 429</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/8.html</AustLII>
<text>Guidance as to the construction of industrial instruments may also be obtained by reference to principles which courts apply to the construction of commercial contracts. Commercial contracts should, as Kirby J held in Pan Foods Company Importers &amp; Distributors Pty Ltd v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [2000] HCA 20 ; (2000) 170 ALR 579 at 584 "be construed practically, so as to give effect to their presumed commercial purposes and so as not to defeat the achievement of such purposes by an excessively narrow and artificially restricted construction." An interpretation which accords with business common sense will be preferred to one which does not: see Upper Hunter County District Council v Australian Chilling and Freezing Co Ltd [1968] HCA 8 ; (1968) 118 CLR 429 at 437.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1678 ; (2005) 226 ALR 114</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/1678.html</AustLII>
<text>In Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1678 ; (2005) 226 ALR 114 at 156-157 Kenny J held that, in Australia, a term of good faith "does not apply to employment contracts." On appeal the Full Court did not need to express a view on her Honour's finding: see Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 101 ; (2006) 233 ALR 687 at 708 [86] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 101 ; (2006) 233 ALR 687</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/101.html</AustLII>
<text>In Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 101 ; (2006) 233 ALR 687 it was held that damages could be assessed on a "loss of a chance" basis where a contract of employment had been repudiated before the applicant had commenced to perform duties under it. The Full Court considered that, on the evidence, had Mr Walker been permitted to commence work under the contract, it was to be expected that he would not have left his employment voluntarily or for cause within a five year period. Damages were assessed on this basis with a 25% discount applied to take account of the possibility that the contract might have been terminated during the five year period.

In Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1678 ; (2005) 226 ALR 114 at 156-157 Kenny J held that, in Australia, a term of good faith "does not apply to employment contracts." On appeal the Full Court did not need to express a view on her Honour's finding: see Walker v Citigroup Global Markets Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCAFC 101 ; (2006) 233 ALR 687 at 708 [86] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Watts v Rake [1960] HCA 58 ; (1960) 108 CLR 158</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1960/58.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Van Efferen gave evidence about his attempts to obtain alternative employment between October 2006 and April 2008. He had found it impossible to obtain maritime work but had been prepared to take whatever work he could get. He was able to obtain some short term employment. His evidence was not seriously challenged. I accept it. CMA has failed to discharge the onus which fell on it to prove that Mr Van Efferen failed to mitigate his loss: see: Watts v Rake [1960] HCA 58 ; (1960) 108 CLR 158.

There is no reason, in my opinion, why Mr Van Efferen's damages should not be assessed on the normal contractual basis. He had a contract for a three year term which did not expire until mid-2009. He confines his claim to the period of the Dolphin Project.

The amount Mr Van Efferen would have earned during the life of the project would have been $313,007.47 in salary plus $14,284 in superannuation. This is a total of $327,291.47. From this figure must be deducted the amount which Mr Van Efferen earned in alternative employment during the relevant period. That figure was $22,525.94. His loss was, therefore, $304,765.53.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>