<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>AZAAA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 554 (27 May 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/554.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Erduran v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 814 ; (2002) 122 FCR 150</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/814.html</AustLII>
<text>That order was quashed, and the Tribunal was directed to determine "the matter the subject of the decision according to law", by a consent order made by the Federal Magistrates Court on 29 January 2008. The order noted that the Minister acknowledged that the Tribunal had committed jurisdictional error by failing to ask itself the right question, namely whether the applicant's conscientious objection to performing military service could be regarded as a form of political opinion, or whether "conscientious objectors" could constitute a particular social group. The Minister's acknowledgment was based upon the decision of Gray J in Erduran v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 814 ; (2002) 122 FCR 150 at [28] , affirmed in the Full Court of this Court in VCAD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 1.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>VCAD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/1.html</AustLII>
<text>That order was quashed, and the Tribunal was directed to determine "the matter the subject of the decision according to law", by a consent order made by the Federal Magistrates Court on 29 January 2008. The order noted that the Minister acknowledged that the Tribunal had committed jurisdictional error by failing to ask itself the right question, namely whether the applicant's conscientious objection to performing military service could be regarded as a form of political opinion, or whether "conscientious objectors" could constitute a particular social group. The Minister's acknowledgment was based upon the decision of Gray J in Erduran v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 814 ; (2002) 122 FCR 150 at [28] , affirmed in the Full Court of this Court in VCAD v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 1.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>SZLQK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FMCA 633</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/633.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant relies upon the decision of Lindsay FM in SZLQK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FMCA 633 ( SZLQK ), delivered on 23 May 2008. His Honour there determined that the scheme of the Act required that s 421 dealt only with the initial constitution of the Tribunal, that reconstitution of the Tribunal could not be effected by using s 421 of the Act, and that reconstitution of the Tribunal could occur only if s 422 or s 422A was available in the particular circumstances: see at [14]-[15]. His Honour thought that, otherwise, there would be no need for either of those provisions: see at [23]-[24]. He specifically indicated that cl 19 of the Principal Member's Direction issued on 9 August 2007 headed "Caseload and Constitution Policy" (which is in the same terms as cl 20 of the current direction) indicated a misapprehension on the part of the Principal Member that a remittal for reconsideration had the effect of requiring the constitution of a wholly new review: see at [33]. His Honour concluded that, in the circumstances of that case, s 422 was not available as a mechanism to reconstitute the Tribunal by the Principal Member (at [43]), and that the only means by which that could be done would be under s 422A. The Principal Member had not made the reconstitution pursuant to that section. Hence, there was error on the part of the Principal Member in appointing a different member to constitute the Tribunal. Nevertheless, his Honour concluded that the error on the part of the Principal Member was not a jurisdictional error going to the validity of the decision of the Tribunal. It was a procedural error, and so the challenge did not succeed.

In NBMB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 100 ALD 118 ( NBMB ), delivered on 26 February 2008, Flick J reached a different conclusion. As it happened, his Honour's conclusion was not part of the ultimate reason for deciding the case. In the course of a challenge to a decision of the Tribunal, the applicant sought leave to amend the application to allege that the reconstitution of the Tribunal on the remittal of the review had been improper. His Honour refused leave to so amend the application, and in any event his Honour said that he would have resolved the point adversely to that applicant. In that case, as here, the Minister said that the reconstitution of the Tribunal following the quashing of its earlier decision was made under s 421 of the Act rather than s 422A of the Act (as contemplated by Lindsay FM in SZLQK ). His Honour noted that the justice of the case, when a decision of the Tribunal has been set aside, is generally that the Tribunal be reconstituted by a different member: see also Northern NSW FM Pty Limited v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43; Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. In NBMB , at [39]-[41], Flick J decided that there was no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2) in that circumstance. As he pointed out, it is a power that can be exercised from time to time: Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), s 33(1). The discretion to exercise that power, his Honour said, is to be exercised in the light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court quashing the initial decision and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done". His Honour also adverted to the possibility that the unavailability of a member for the purposes of s 422 may not simply be where the term of appointment has expired, or the member has died or become unable to carry out his duties, or has resigned. Unavailability might also arise, his Honour speculated at [41], where an order is made quashing the decision of the Tribunal as originally constituted. Otherwise, a member may remain "available" even though "justice in general is better seen to be done" if that member did not further participate in any re-hearing.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>NBMB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 100 ALD 118</tocase>
<text>In NBMB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 100 ALD 118 ( NBMB ), delivered on 26 February 2008, Flick J reached a different conclusion. As it happened, his Honour's conclusion was not part of the ultimate reason for deciding the case. In the course of a challenge to a decision of the Tribunal, the applicant sought leave to amend the application to allege that the reconstitution of the Tribunal on the remittal of the review had been improper. His Honour refused leave to so amend the application, and in any event his Honour said that he would have resolved the point adversely to that applicant. In that case, as here, the Minister said that the reconstitution of the Tribunal following the quashing of its earlier decision was made under s 421 of the Act rather than s 422A of the Act (as contemplated by Lindsay FM in SZLQK ). His Honour noted that the justice of the case, when a decision of the Tribunal has been set aside, is generally that the Tribunal be reconstituted by a different member: see also Northern NSW FM Pty Limited v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43; Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. In NBMB , at [39]-[41], Flick J decided that there was no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2) in that circumstance. As he pointed out, it is a power that can be exercised from time to time: Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), s 33(1). The discretion to exercise that power, his Honour said, is to be exercised in the light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court quashing the initial decision and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done". His Honour also adverted to the possibility that the unavailability of a member for the purposes of s 422 may not simply be where the term of appointment has expired, or the member has died or become unable to carry out his duties, or has resigned. Unavailability might also arise, his Honour speculated at [41], where an order is made quashing the decision of the Tribunal as originally constituted. Otherwise, a member may remain "available" even though "justice in general is better seen to be done" if that member did not further participate in any re-hearing.

There are good reasons that it should be available to be so exercised it, namely that the decision of Member Muling had been quashed for jurisdictional error. As Flick J said in NBMB at [39]-[40]: 
 The decision of the Tribunal as initially constituted had been set aside by the Federal Magistrates Court. Where such an order is made, "justice is in general better seen to be done if the Court or the Tribunal is reconstituted for the purposes of the rehearing" : Northern NSW FM Pty Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43. See also Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. The "usual position [is] that remission to a differently constituted tribunal is the ordinary way to proceed": Industry Research and Development Board v IMT Ltd [2001] FCA 85 at [40] . 

 
 There is no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2). The decision of the initial tribunal having been set aside, the exercise of the power conferred by s 421(2) thereafter arose for consideration. It is a power that can be exercised from time to time: s 31 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth). The discretion to be exercised by the principal member or his delegate was a discretion to be exercised in light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done." Section 421(2) confers a power of appointment upon the principal member or his delegate: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Wang [2003] HCA 11 ; (2003) 215 CLR 518 at [40] per McHugh J. In the present proceedings, that power was exercised by a person with an appropriate delegation.

The applicant submitted that s 33(1) of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) does not support the conclusion I have reached, although Flick J in NBMB in the passage set out above also referred to it. It relevantly provides that, where an Act confers a power, then that power may be exercised from time to time as the occasion arises, unless the contrary intention appears. The argument was that, by reason of ss 422 and 422A, a contrary intention did appear. I have rejected the contention that ss 422 and 422A cover all the circumstances in which the Tribunal may be reconstituted, as I consider they confine the general power in s 421 only in respect of the circumstances to which they relate. In other circumstances, or at least in circumstances such as the present, they do not limit the availability of s 421 to permit the reconstitution of the Tribunal. They do not reveal the contrary intention asserted on behalf of the applicant. Section 33(1) of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) therefore can, as it does, make clear that the power under s 421 may where it is available to be used be exercised from time to time.

In the light of that conclusion, I do not need to consider the alternative contention of the Minister that, in any event, s 422 applies as the circumstances enable the Tribunal to be reconstituted because the initial member is not, or is no longer "available" for the purpose of the review. That was a possibility adverted to by Flick J in NBMB at [41]. There are some circumstances where, in the interests of justice, the remitted review might clearly be conducted by the initially appointed member (an obvious example is where the member applied the law as expressed in a binding decision, but that decision was subsequently reversed on an appeal). Thus, it would not appear that the quashing of a decision of the initial member necessarily leads to that member then becoming no longer "available" to conduct the review. Consequently, if that alternative contention is correct, the concept of availability would be a somewhat amorphous one, perhaps depending on the nature and gravity of the jurisdictional error in the first decision. It is not clear that such an inquiry was intended when a decision of the Tribunal has been quashed for jurisdictional error.

I note the applicant's further argument in support of the alternative contention, based on s 422(1)(b) referring to the initial member of the Tribunal no longer being available for the purpose of the review "at the place" where the review is being conducted. It was argued that such an expression, directing attention to a geographical focus as one of the elements for the exercise of the power, also indicates that s 422 is not available in circumstances such as the present to reconstitute the Tribunal. It is not necessary to address that argument, in view of my conclusion above. I note that the "place where the review is being conducted" is not defined in the Act. Section 430A refers to the place at which a decision is to be handed down. A review may be conducted by a member sitting in one location or State, and the visa applicant being in another location or State; sometimes a legal representative or another migration agent, or an interpreter, is in yet another location. Sometimes, I assume, the hearing conducted under s 425 will occur away from the location or State in which the application for review was filed. I suspect that the reference to the "place where the review is being conducted" is not a necessary limiting factor upon when a member is no longer "available" to conduct that review. As I have said, it is not necessary to decide that question.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Northern NSW FM Pty Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39</tocase>
<text>In NBMB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 100 ALD 118 ( NBMB ), delivered on 26 February 2008, Flick J reached a different conclusion. As it happened, his Honour's conclusion was not part of the ultimate reason for deciding the case. In the course of a challenge to a decision of the Tribunal, the applicant sought leave to amend the application to allege that the reconstitution of the Tribunal on the remittal of the review had been improper. His Honour refused leave to so amend the application, and in any event his Honour said that he would have resolved the point adversely to that applicant. In that case, as here, the Minister said that the reconstitution of the Tribunal following the quashing of its earlier decision was made under s 421 of the Act rather than s 422A of the Act (as contemplated by Lindsay FM in SZLQK ). His Honour noted that the justice of the case, when a decision of the Tribunal has been set aside, is generally that the Tribunal be reconstituted by a different member: see also Northern NSW FM Pty Limited v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43; Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. In NBMB , at [39]-[41], Flick J decided that there was no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2) in that circumstance. As he pointed out, it is a power that can be exercised from time to time: Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), s 33(1). The discretion to exercise that power, his Honour said, is to be exercised in the light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court quashing the initial decision and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done". His Honour also adverted to the possibility that the unavailability of a member for the purposes of s 422 may not simply be where the term of appointment has expired, or the member has died or become unable to carry out his duties, or has resigned. Unavailability might also arise, his Honour speculated at [41], where an order is made quashing the decision of the Tribunal as originally constituted. Otherwise, a member may remain "available" even though "justice in general is better seen to be done" if that member did not further participate in any re-hearing.

There are good reasons that it should be available to be so exercised it, namely that the decision of Member Muling had been quashed for jurisdictional error. As Flick J said in NBMB at [39]-[40]: 
 The decision of the Tribunal as initially constituted had been set aside by the Federal Magistrates Court. Where such an order is made, "justice is in general better seen to be done if the Court or the Tribunal is reconstituted for the purposes of the rehearing" : Northern NSW FM Pty Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43. See also Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. The "usual position [is] that remission to a differently constituted tribunal is the ordinary way to proceed": Industry Research and Development Board v IMT Ltd [2001] FCA 85 at [40] . 

 
 There is no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2). The decision of the initial tribunal having been set aside, the exercise of the power conferred by s 421(2) thereafter arose for consideration. It is a power that can be exercised from time to time: s 31 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth). The discretion to be exercised by the principal member or his delegate was a discretion to be exercised in light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done." Section 421(2) confers a power of appointment upon the principal member or his delegate: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Wang [2003] HCA 11 ; (2003) 215 CLR 518 at [40] per McHugh J. In the present proceedings, that power was exercised by a person with an appropriate delegation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426</tocase>
<text>In NBMB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2008) 100 ALD 118 ( NBMB ), delivered on 26 February 2008, Flick J reached a different conclusion. As it happened, his Honour's conclusion was not part of the ultimate reason for deciding the case. In the course of a challenge to a decision of the Tribunal, the applicant sought leave to amend the application to allege that the reconstitution of the Tribunal on the remittal of the review had been improper. His Honour refused leave to so amend the application, and in any event his Honour said that he would have resolved the point adversely to that applicant. In that case, as here, the Minister said that the reconstitution of the Tribunal following the quashing of its earlier decision was made under s 421 of the Act rather than s 422A of the Act (as contemplated by Lindsay FM in SZLQK ). His Honour noted that the justice of the case, when a decision of the Tribunal has been set aside, is generally that the Tribunal be reconstituted by a different member: see also Northern NSW FM Pty Limited v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43; Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. In NBMB , at [39]-[41], Flick J decided that there was no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2) in that circumstance. As he pointed out, it is a power that can be exercised from time to time: Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth), s 33(1). The discretion to exercise that power, his Honour said, is to be exercised in the light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court quashing the initial decision and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done". His Honour also adverted to the possibility that the unavailability of a member for the purposes of s 422 may not simply be where the term of appointment has expired, or the member has died or become unable to carry out his duties, or has resigned. Unavailability might also arise, his Honour speculated at [41], where an order is made quashing the decision of the Tribunal as originally constituted. Otherwise, a member may remain "available" even though "justice in general is better seen to be done" if that member did not further participate in any re-hearing.

There are good reasons that it should be available to be so exercised it, namely that the decision of Member Muling had been quashed for jurisdictional error. As Flick J said in NBMB at [39]-[40]: 
 The decision of the Tribunal as initially constituted had been set aside by the Federal Magistrates Court. Where such an order is made, "justice is in general better seen to be done if the Court or the Tribunal is reconstituted for the purposes of the rehearing" : Northern NSW FM Pty Ltd v Australian Broadcasting Tribunal (1990) 26 FCR 39 at 43. See also Australian Trade Commission v Underwood Exports Pty Ltd (1997) 49 ALD 426 at 427. The "usual position [is] that remission to a differently constituted tribunal is the ordinary way to proceed": Industry Research and Development Board v IMT Ltd [2001] FCA 85 at [40] . 

 
 There is no reason to impose any constraint upon the power conferred by s 421(2). The decision of the initial tribunal having been set aside, the exercise of the power conferred by s 421(2) thereafter arose for consideration. It is a power that can be exercised from time to time: s 31 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth). The discretion to be exercised by the principal member or his delegate was a discretion to be exercised in light of all the circumstances, including the order of the Federal Magistrates Court and what is recognised as "justice being seen to be done." Section 421(2) confers a power of appointment upon the principal member or his delegate: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Wang [2003] HCA 11 ; (2003) 215 CLR 518 at [40] per McHugh J. In the present proceedings, that power was exercised by a person with an appropriate delegation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>SZEPZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 107 ; (2007) 159 FCR 291</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/107.html</AustLII>
<text>Finally, on this issue, I refer to the decision of the Full Court in SZEPZ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 107 ; (2007) 159 FCR 291. I have given anxious thought to whether that decision, which is of course binding on me, dictates a different conclusion to the one I have reached. Where the Tribunal has been differently reconstituted following the quashing of its initial decision, that case decided that s 424A did not require the Tribunal as newly constituted to re-give particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or part of the reason, for affirming the decision under review. I do not think that decision dictates an opposite conclusion. Clearly, in the case of a Tribunal reconstituted under ss 422 or 422A, where the Tribunal's task is to "finish the review", that decision is apt. It may also be apt where the Tribunal has been reconstituted under s 421, where at least in one sense the process of review by its consideration of a member of the Tribunal recommences. In the latter circumstance, the activating fact to enliven s 424A must be the assessment of the information by the Tribunal as constituted. If, however, as appears to have been the case in that decision, the Tribunal as reconstituted formed the same view about certain information as the Tribunal as previously constituted, because (as the Full Court pointed out at [42]) the giving of the required notice may be given administratively, the notice given earlier would satisfy s 424A.

The second ground of review, so the applicant argues, is that the Tribunal wrongly asked whether the applicant is a conscientious objector rather than whether he would refuse to undergo further military service if he were to return to Israel. For that reason, I have put the words "conscientious objector" in quotation marks in the heading to this part of my reasons.

The critical part of its reasons are set out at [15] above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 77 ALJR 1088</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/26.html</AustLII>
<text>The Tribunal was obliged to consider any claim made by the applicant which could, if the asserted facts were established to the satisfaction of the Tribunal, resolve the application for a protection visa in his favour: Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 77 ALJR 1088 at [23] and [32] per Gummow and Callinan JJ, Hayne J agreeing, and at [65] and [74] per Kirby J. That case involved a failure to respond to a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying upon established facts, and so a failure to exercise its jurisdiction in relation to that claim. In NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [63] , the Court (Black CJ, French and Selway JJ) said: 
 It follows that if the Tribunal makes an error of fact in misunderstanding or misconstruing a claim advanced by the applicant and bases its conclusion in whole or in part upon the claim so misunderstood or misconstrued its error is tantamount to a failure to consider the claim and on that basis can constitute jurisdictional error. 

 
See also Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157 at [114] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2004/263.html</AustLII>
<text>The Tribunal was obliged to consider any claim made by the applicant which could, if the asserted facts were established to the satisfaction of the Tribunal, resolve the application for a protection visa in his favour: Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 77 ALJR 1088 at [23] and [32] per Gummow and Callinan JJ, Hayne J agreeing, and at [65] and [74] per Kirby J. That case involved a failure to respond to a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying upon established facts, and so a failure to exercise its jurisdiction in relation to that claim. In NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [63] , the Court (Black CJ, French and Selway JJ) said: 
 It follows that if the Tribunal makes an error of fact in misunderstanding or misconstruing a claim advanced by the applicant and bases its conclusion in whole or in part upon the claim so misunderstood or misconstrued its error is tantamount to a failure to consider the claim and on that basis can constitute jurisdictional error. 

 
See also Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157 at [114] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1901.html</AustLII>
<text>The Tribunal was obliged to consider any claim made by the applicant which could, if the asserted facts were established to the satisfaction of the Tribunal, resolve the application for a protection visa in his favour: Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2003] HCA 26 ; (2003) 77 ALJR 1088 at [23] and [32] per Gummow and Callinan JJ, Hayne J agreeing, and at [65] and [74] per Kirby J. That case involved a failure to respond to a substantial, clearly articulated argument relying upon established facts, and so a failure to exercise its jurisdiction in relation to that claim. In NABE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs (No 2) [2004] FCAFC 263 ; (2004) 144 FCR 1 at [63] , the Court (Black CJ, French and Selway JJ) said: 
 It follows that if the Tribunal makes an error of fact in misunderstanding or misconstruing a claim advanced by the applicant and bases its conclusion in whole or in part upon the claim so misunderstood or misconstrued its error is tantamount to a failure to consider the claim and on that basis can constitute jurisdictional error. 

 
See also Chen v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1901 ; (2000) 106 FCR 157 at [114] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v District Court of Queensland Northern District; Ex parte Thompson [1968] HCA 48 ; (1968) 118 CLR 488</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1968/48.html</AustLII>
<text>I do not need to consider the contention that the Tribunal, by focusing on the term "conscientious objector" as it is explained in the context of s 29A of the National Service Act 1951 (Cth) in R v District Court of Queensland Northern District; Ex parte Thompson [1968] HCA 48 ; (1968) 118 CLR 488 at 492, failed to ask itself the correct question under the Convention. I have reached the view that it failed to consider the applicant's claim to have been a conscientious objector according to law.

The third contention of the applicant can be shortly dealt with.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/63.html</AustLII>
<text>Section 425(1) obliges the Tribunal to invite the applicant to appear to give evidence and present arguments relating to the issues arising in relation to the decision under review. The nature and extent of that obligation, in the sense of the Tribunal putting the applicant on notice as to the matters he should address at the hearing, was discussed by the High Court in SZBEL v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] HCA 63 at [35] , [36] and [47]. In particular, at [36] the Court (Gleeson CJ, Kirby, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ) said: 
 Ordinarily then, as was the case here, the Tribunal will begin its interview of an applicant who has accepted the Tribunal's invitation to appear, knowing that it is not persuaded by the material already before it to decide the review in the applicant's favour. That lack of persuasion may be based on particular questions the Tribunal has about specific aspects of the material already before it; it may be based on nothing more particular than a general unease about the veracity of what is revealed in that material. But unless the Tribunal tells the applicant something different, the applicant would be entitled to assume that the reasons given by the delegate for refusing to grant the application will identify the issues that arise in relation to that decision.

It is appropriate, where there has been a remittal of an earlier decision of the Tribunal, to apply that observation to the reasons given by the Tribunal as earlier constituted, provided of course that the reasons for that decision being quashed do not negate the relevant earlier reasons.

The problem here, however, is not that the Tribunal did not ask the applicant to expand on those aspects of his claim based upon his asserted political beliefs which would lead him not to undertake further military service and to explain why that account should be accepted. The problem here, as I have found, is simply that the Tribunal appears not to have recognised that the applicant did expand on that aspect of his claim as it did not then consider whether to accept his evidence or to consider its consequences. In my view, the Tribunal's error was not in failing to fulfil the requirements of s 425. It is a different one.

For those reasons, I direct that the decision of the Tribunal given on 7 July 2008 be quashed, and the matter constituting the review instigated by application made on 25 May 2007 be remitted to the Tribunal again for consideration according to law. The Minister should pay to the applicant his costs of the application.
 I certify that the preceding sixty-two (62) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Mansfield. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 27 May 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: S Ower 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: McDonald Steed McGrath 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: C Bleby 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 27 April 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 27 May 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/554.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>