<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Clarion Marketing Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 666 (9 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/666.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill (2006) 227 CLR 57 ; [2006] HCA 46</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2006/46.html</AustLII>
<text>In Australian Broadcasting Corporation v O'Neill (2006) 227 CLR 57 ; [2006] HCA 46 at [65] , Gummow and Hayne JJ said that it is enough for a plaintiff to show a sufficient likelihood of success to justify, in the circumstances, the preservation of the status quo pending trial; how strong the probability need be depends on the practical consequences likely to flow from the relief.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong [2009] FCA 539</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/539.html</AustLII>
<text>I accept Mr Webb's submission that the observations of Logan J in Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A Company Incorporated in Hong Kong [2009] FCA 539 at [1] and [28] are distinguishable from the present matter.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Campomar Sociedad Limitada v Nike International Limited (2000) 202 CLR 45 ; [2000] HCA 12</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/12.html</AustLII>
<text>Although Mr Webb SC who appeared for Clarion conceded that there is a serious question to be tried, he submitted that the likelihood of success at the trial is not great. He pointed in particular to the observations of the High Court in Campomar Sociedad Limitada v Nike International Limited (2000) 202 CLR 45 ; [2000] HCA 12 at [101] to [103], and he emphasised the full wording of the scratch cards and the leisurely circumstances in which a hypothetical, reasonable consumer will be likely to be able to study the full details.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Kolback Securities Ltd v Epoch Mining NL (1987) 8 NSWLR 533</tocase>
<text>However, I am satisfied that there is a sufficient likelihood of success to justify the relief for which the ACCC ultimately contended, or relief substantially in that form. In coming to this view, I have taken into account, in particular, the balance of convenience which, in my opinion, justifies the relief when weighed in the balance with the serious question to be tried. The relief which is sought does not in a practical sense determine the substance of the matter in issue; compare Kolback Securities Ltd v Epoch Mining NL (1987) 8 NSWLR 533. It merely requires Clarion to send an SMS to a scratch card winner informing him or her that to claim a prize it is necessary to pay the subscription fees to which I have referred, as well as to give some indication of the value of the prize that has been won. The "winner" is then given the opportunity to proceed or withdraw.

The cost of complying with this order is relatively minor and it is in conformity with an industry code which is shortly to come into operation. It takes into account the public interest character of the proceedings and the serious questions to which I have referred above.

I have heard argument as to the appropriate form of the order and I have taken into account the evidence of Ms Lesley Hynes in her affidavit sworn 9 June 2009. The orders I will make are as set out in the short minutes of order handed up by Ms Higgins for the Commission, save that the form of the SMS message set out in paragraph 1.1 is to be as follows: 
 Free Msg Must subscribe 2 Mobyplanet 2 get prize $10 every 6 days. Flexibreak prize worth $80 or more (min spend reqd). Subscribe reply Yes.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>