<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Star Poultry Pty Ltd v Ryan (In his capacity as trustee of the Bankrupt Estate of Ramadan Alievski) [2009] FCA 688 (1 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/688.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Oayda v Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd (unreported, Wilcox J, 20 February 1995)</tocase>
<text>I inquired of counsel for the applicants as to the source of the power to make the order sought in para 4 of the orders by consent. The effect of that order, in conjunction with para 3, would be to cast upon the respondent personal liability for the costs of this proceeding by preventing him from reimbursing himself from the bankrupt estate. In my view, it is appropriate that the respondent assume personal liability for the costs of the application. Counsel for the applicants referred me to the judgment of Wilcox J in Oayda v Mercantile Mutual Life Insurance Co Ltd (unreported, Wilcox J, 20 February 1995) in which his Honour made an order the effect of which was to require a trustee in bankruptcy to pay costs personally, when the trustee in bankruptcy had acted wrongly in relation to a proof of debt. On considering the question, I think that s 179(1)(b) of the Bankruptcy Act provides me with sufficient authority to make an order ensuring that the respondent will bear the costs personally.

For these reasons, I make the following orders by consent, that: Pursuant to s 179 of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth), the respondent is removed as trustee in bankruptcy of the bankrupt estate of Ramadan Alievski. Pursuant to s 179 of the Bankruptcy Act 1966 (Cth), Gess Rambaldi of Level 19, 15 William Street, Melbourne, Victoria, be appointed as trustee in bankruptcy of the bankrupt estate of Ramadan Alievski in place of the respondent. The respondent pay the applicants' costs of this application in the amount of $7,000. The costs payable by the respondent under order 3 herein must not be reimbursed by the bankrupt estate of Ramadan Alievski.
 I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the reasons for judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Gray. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 24 June 2009
 
 Counsel for the applicants: Mr S Waldren 
 
 Solicitor for the applicants: Taylor Splatt &amp; Partners 
 
 The respondent did not appear but signed orders by consent 
 
 Date of hearing: 1 June 2009 
 
 Date of judgment: 1 June 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/688.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>