<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Huntley Management Limited v Australian Olives Limited (No 2) [2009] FCA 686 (24 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/686.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Australian Olives Limited v Stout [2007] FCA 1958</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1958.html</AustLII>
<text>Counsel for Huntley referred to a statement by Greenwood J in Australian Olives Limited v Stout [2007] FCA 1958 at [33] where his Honour observed: 
 In order to maintain continuity for those persons dealing with the register, a company recorded by ASIC as a responsible entity of a registered scheme remains the responsible entity until the record is altered to name the new entity, notwithstanding anything in Division 2. 

 
This passage paraphrases subs(1) of s 601FJ and adds an explanation of the purpose of the provision, namely, "to maintain continuity for those persons dealing with the register".

I do not see any inconsistency between the passage quoted and my construction of s 601FJ(1). The passage quoted applies comfortably to AOL's position. Even on the assumption that there was a valid removal of AOL and appointment of Huntley, those who had dealt with AOL on the faith of the register would be safe in continuing to do so until the register was altered to name Huntley as the new RE.

Counsel for Huntley suggests that my construction would lead to intolerable outcomes for innocent third parties, who would be in a quandary as to which company they should deal with as RE. It is true that at the present time, for example, according to the construction I have suggested, Huntley's status as registered RE might be falsified, so that a person dealing with Huntley in reliance on the register might subsequently discover that AOL was the RE. However, the person would have the benefit of the prima facie evidence constituted by the register, which would have to be displaced by evidence, and would have a claim against Huntley for breach of an implied warranty that it was the RE and therefore trustee for the scheme members (see s 601FC(2) of the Act). In any event, the construction urged by Huntley can also lead to difficulty in that the true RE would be denied that status, even if it placed convincing proof of it before the person, unless and until the dispute between the rivals for the position of RE was resolved and ASIC altered the register. Whatever course is followed, the disconformity between the true facts and those suggested by the registration could be a potential cause of hardship and loss in particular circumstances that can be hypothesised.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>H A Stephenson &amp; Son Limited (in liq) v Gillanders, Arbuthnot &amp; Co [1931] HCA 47 ; (1931) 45 CLR 476</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1931/47.html</AustLII>
<text>Second, the construction suggested is consistent with the scheme of the registers kept by ASIC. Generally speaking, an ASIC writing that is based on the ASIC national database is only prima facie evidence: see, for example, ss 1274(7) and 1274B(2) of the Act. An exception is found in s 1274(7A) which is the familiar provision to the effect that a certificate issued by ASIC stating that a company has been registered under the Act is conclusive evidence that all requirements of the Act for its registration were complied with and that the company was duly registered as a company under the Act on the date specified in the certificate. The policy underlying that longstanding provision in the companies legislation was explained Evatt J in H A Stephenson &amp; Son Limited (in liq) v Gillanders, Arbuthnot &amp; Co [1931] HCA 47 ; (1931) 45 CLR 476 at 497 500. Unlike the issuing of a certificate of registration of a company, the making or changing of entries in a register on information supplied to ASIC does not create a new entity and associated rights and obligations, but is supposed to reflect rights and obligations that have already arisen.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>ING Funds Management Limited v ANZ Nominees Limited [2009] NSWSC 243</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2009/243.html</AustLII>
<text>Third, a somewhat analogous provision is found in s 601GC(2) of the Act which requires that any modification to a registered scheme's constitution be lodged with ASIC and cannot take effect until lodged. In ING Funds Management Limited v ANZ Nominees Limited [2009] NSWSC 243 there was a question as to the effectiveness of actions taken by an RE to suspend the rights of members of two registered schemes to require redemption of their units. The RE contended that the actions taken by it were effective to modify the constitutions of the schemes to create the suspension.

Section 601GC of the Act provided: 
 (1) The constitution of a registered scheme may be modified, or repealed and replaced with a new constitution; 

(a) ...
 
(b) by the responsible entity if the responsible entity reasonably considers the change will not adversely affect members' rights.
 
 
 (2) The responsible entity must lodge with ASIC a copy of the modification of the new constitution. The modification, or repeal and/or replacement cannot take effect until the copy has been lodged. 

 
The RE lodged documents with ASIC.

Barrett J held, for reasons that do not presently matter, that a deed was required and that the execution and lodgment of the documents, which, it was common ground, did not constitute deeds, did not cause the constitutions to be modified pursuant to s 601GC(1)(b).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>