<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Futuris Corporation Limited (ACN 004 336 636) v Commissioner of Taxation [2009] FCA 600 (4 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/600.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Futuris Corporation Limited (ACN 004 336 636) v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 1096</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1096.html</AustLII>
<text>The history of this matter, and another related matter, are described in the judgment of Finn J in Futuris Corporation Limited (ACN 004 336 636) v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 1096 relevantly at [2]-[10]. I respectfully adopt his Honour's description. I do not need to refer to those background facts further. For present purposes, it is sufficient to set out the pleadings and subsequent correspondence giving rise to the present application for particulars.

On 15 December 2006, the applicant filed its Statement of Grounds. At paragraph 39 of the Statement of Grounds, the applicant set out the background to the applicant's tax return for the year of income ended 30 June 1998: On or about the 7 December 1998 Futuris, being a relevant entity within the meaning of Division 1B of Part VI of the ITAA 1936, furnished a return in respect of the year of income ended 30 June 1998 ("the 1998 Return"). Futuris specified in the 1998 Return:
 
 39.1 that it had a taxable income of: $86,088,045.00 

 
 39.2 that tax payable on that taxable income was: $30,991,696.20

On 23 March 2007, the respondent filed its "Response to the Applicant's Statement of Grounds" (the Response). At paragraph 32 of the Response, the respondent pleaded: The Commissioner admits the allegations in paragraph 39 of the Applicant's Statement and says further that:-
 
 (a) the taxable income of $86,088,045 ("the declared amount") understated the taxable income for the 1998 year by $82,950,090 ("the understated amount") and the amount of $30,991,696.20 is the gross tax on the declared amount; 

 
 (b) the understated amount was described in the 1998 return as "Division 19A Value Shift".

The applicant submitted that, in most circumstances, it is unlikely that an issue will arise as to the alternative postulate, but submitted that the present circumstances are different because they involve a factually complicated arrangement leading up to the ultimate sale of the entity called Walshville, as described by Finn J in Futuris Corporation Limited (ACN 004 336 636) v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 1096 referred to above.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Peabody [1994] HCA 43 ; (1994) 181 CLR 359</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1994/43.html</AustLII>
<text>In support of its contentions, the applicant referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Peabody [1994] HCA 43 ; (1994) 181 CLR 359 ( Peabody's Case ), in particular at 385 where the nature of a "reasonable expectation" for the purposes of s 177C was described by the High Court as follows:
 
 A reasonable expectation requires more than a possibility. It involves a prediction as to events which would have taken place if the relevant scheme had not been entered into or carried out and the prediction must be sufficiently reliable for it to be regarded as reasonable. 

 
The applicant placed emphasis on the requirement of a "prediction". The applicant also referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Hart (2004) 217 CLR 216 where Gummow and Hayne JJ, when interpreting the similar provision s 177C(1)(b), said at [66]:
 
 
 In the present matters, the respondents would obtain a tax benefit if, in the terms of s 177C(1)(b), had the scheme not been entered into or carried out, the deductions "might reasonably be expected not to have been allowable". When that is read with s 177D(b) it becomes apparent that the inquiry directed by Pt IVA requires comparison between the scheme in question and an alternative postulate. To draw a conclusion about purpose from the eight matters identified in s 177D(b) will require consideration of what other possibilities existed. 

 
The applicant submitted that in order to make such a comparison, the Commissioner would have needed to identify an alternative postulate, and that identifying what would have occurred had the scheme not been entered into, ie the alternative postulate, is a critical element in contending whether a tax benefit arose.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Hart (2004) 217 CLR 216</tocase>
<text>In support of its contentions, the applicant referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Peabody [1994] HCA 43 ; (1994) 181 CLR 359 ( Peabody's Case ), in particular at 385 where the nature of a "reasonable expectation" for the purposes of s 177C was described by the High Court as follows:
 
 A reasonable expectation requires more than a possibility. It involves a prediction as to events which would have taken place if the relevant scheme had not been entered into or carried out and the prediction must be sufficiently reliable for it to be regarded as reasonable. 

 
The applicant placed emphasis on the requirement of a "prediction". The applicant also referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Hart (2004) 217 CLR 216 where Gummow and Hayne JJ, when interpreting the similar provision s 177C(1)(b), said at [66]:
 
 
 In the present matters, the respondents would obtain a tax benefit if, in the terms of s 177C(1)(b), had the scheme not been entered into or carried out, the deductions "might reasonably be expected not to have been allowable". When that is read with s 177D(b) it becomes apparent that the inquiry directed by Pt IVA requires comparison between the scheme in question and an alternative postulate. To draw a conclusion about purpose from the eight matters identified in s 177D(b) will require consideration of what other possibilities existed. 

 
The applicant submitted that in order to make such a comparison, the Commissioner would have needed to identify an alternative postulate, and that identifying what would have occurred had the scheme not been entered into, ie the alternative postulate, is a critical element in contending whether a tax benefit arose.

The applicant also referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lenzo [2008] FCAFC 50 ; (2008) 167 FCR 255 ( Lenzo's Case ), where Sackville J noted at [120]:
 
 Since any tax benefit identified must be related to a scheme, as must any conclusion of a dominant tax avoidance purpose, the identification of the scheme and of the tax benefit is of central importance to the operation of Pt IVA: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Hart (2004) 217 CLR 216 at 223.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lenzo [2008] FCAFC 50 ; (2008) 167 FCR 255</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/50.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant also referred to Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Lenzo [2008] FCAFC 50 ; (2008) 167 FCR 255 ( Lenzo's Case ), where Sackville J noted at [120]:
 
 Since any tax benefit identified must be related to a scheme, as must any conclusion of a dominant tax avoidance purpose, the identification of the scheme and of the tax benefit is of central importance to the operation of Pt IVA: Federal Commissioner of Taxation v Hart (2004) 217 CLR 216 at 223.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bailey v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1977] HCA 11 ; (1977) 136 CLR 214</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1977/11.html</AustLII>
<text>Further reference was made to Bailey v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1977] HCA 11 ; (1977) 136 CLR 214 ( Bailey's Case ), where an application was made for particulars in the context of the predecessor of Part IVA , and the taxpayer requested particulars of the "arrangement" upon which the Commissioner's use of s 260 was based, but the Commissioner refused to supply them. It was held that the Supreme Court had power to order the Commissioner to give particulars of the "arrangement", and that such particulars should be given in the circumstances. The applicant relied on Bailey's Case , particularly at 230 where Aickin J referred with apparent approval to the decision in Tomlinson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1974) 23 FLR 314 where Jeffrey J concluded 
 that in the exercise of its discretion the court will give paramountcy to the principle that the appellant should have the fullest particulars necessary to him to enable him to appraise the case which he has to disapprove and should have access to documents necessary for the proof by him of this case. With a general proposition expressed in those general terms I would respectfully agree.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Tomlinson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1974) 23 FLR 314</tocase>
<text>Further reference was made to Bailey v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1977] HCA 11 ; (1977) 136 CLR 214 ( Bailey's Case ), where an application was made for particulars in the context of the predecessor of Part IVA , and the taxpayer requested particulars of the "arrangement" upon which the Commissioner's use of s 260 was based, but the Commissioner refused to supply them. It was held that the Supreme Court had power to order the Commissioner to give particulars of the "arrangement", and that such particulars should be given in the circumstances. The applicant relied on Bailey's Case , particularly at 230 where Aickin J referred with apparent approval to the decision in Tomlinson v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1974) 23 FLR 314 where Jeffrey J concluded 
 that in the exercise of its discretion the court will give paramountcy to the principle that the appellant should have the fullest particulars necessary to him to enable him to appraise the case which he has to disapprove and should have access to documents necessary for the proof by him of this case. With a general proposition expressed in those general terms I would respectfully agree.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Futuris Corporation Limited [2008] HCA 32</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2008/32.html</AustLII>
<text>Further, the respondent noted that the decision of the High Court in relation to the challenge to the Commissioner's Part IVA determination was handed down on 31 July 2008: Commissioner of Taxation v Futuris Corporation Limited [2008] HCA 32. On the programming orders that have been made to date in this proceeding, the evidence is filed, save for any responding evidence of the applicant. The matter is set down for hearing in a little over five weeks. The respondent submitted that the proximity to hearing should be a factor considered in the exercise of the discretion whether to order further and better particulars.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/70.html</AustLII>
<text>It is a fundamental principle that a party is entitled to be informed about the opponent's case with sufficient clarity and particularity to allow that party a fair opportunity to meet the case: Dare v Pulham [1982] HCA 70 ; (1982) 148 CLR 658 at 664. The object of requiring a party to give particulars is to limit any generality in the pleadings, so as to inform the party's opponent of the nature of the case which that party must meet, and to prevent the opponent from being taken by surprise at the trial. The provision of appropriate particulars also means that unnecessary expense to the parties is avoided either in pre-trial preparation or at the hearing.

The Court has power to order the furnishing of further and better particulars, whether pursuant to its inherent jurisdiction, or pursuant to Order 12 rule 5 of the Federal Court Rules . The question is whether in the circumstances that power should be exercised.

The issues in the proceeding will be whether the applicant obtained a "tax benefit", and if it did, whether it could be concluded that the relevant scheme was entered into or carried out for the dominant purpose of obtaining a tax benefit.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lenzo v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] HCATrans 371</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCATrans/2008/371.html</AustLII>
<text>I note that this approach was described by Sackville J in Lenzo's Case , and that an application for special leave to appeal to the High Court in that case was refused: Lenzo v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] HCATrans 371 (12 November 2008).

In my view, the applicant is not entitled to further and better particulars of the respondent's case which it seeks.

In any event, if the applicant were entitled to the sort of particulars that it seeks, the respondent has provided them. It has identified the amount of the tax benefit, and the detailed transactions by which it alleges the tax benefit was obtained. The respondent has provided all the particulars that it could sensibly be expected to provide in relation to the obtaining of a tax benefit.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>