<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Horizontal Falls Adventure Tours Pty Ltd (ACN 108 455 410) v Thomas [2009] FCA 639 (11 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/639.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 85 ALR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1989/21.html</AustLII>
<text>Order 27 r 4 of the Federal Court Rules empowers the Court to set aside a subpoena in whole or in part on the application of any party or person having a sufficient interest. Ms Chaloner is clearly such a person. Grounds upon which subpoenas are traditionally set aside include the excessive width of documents sought or whether the subpoena on its face is oppressive. Relevantly, Deane and Gaudron JJ in Hamilton v Oades [1989] HCA 21 ; (1989) 85 ALR 1 at 11 said: 
 The inherent power of a court to control and supervise proceedings includes the power to take appropriate action to prevent injustice... In this context injustice is not simply a question of the purpose for which the relevant proceedings were instituted but includes a consideration of the consequences for the person invoking the power. The terms oppressive and vexatious are often used to signify those considerations which justify the exercise of the power to control proceedings to prevent injustice, those terms respectively conveying, in an appropriate context, the meaning that the proceedings are seriously and unfairly burdensome, prejudicial or damaging and productive of serious and unjustified trouble and harassment.

In the circumstances before me I am not prepared to set aside the subpoena served on Ms Chaloner. I take this view for the following reasons:

The appropriate order is that the notice of motion be dismissed.
 I certify that the preceding nine (9) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Collier. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 22 June 2009
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Mr SC Russell of Russell and Company 
 
 Counsel for the First and Second Respondents: Mr P Telford 
 
 Solicitor for the First and Second Respondents: BCI Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 11 June 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 June 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/639.html</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>