<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hunter v State of Western Australia [2009] FCA 654 (11 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/654.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Munn (for and on behalf of the Gunggari People) v Queensland (2001) 115 FCR 109 ; [2001] FCA 1229</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1229.html</AustLII>
<text>This requirement must be construed in the context of the Act as a whole and in conformity with the purpose of the Act. The Act provides for mediation and ultimate agreement as the primary means for resolving native title applications. Thus, the main concern of the Court when considering an application under s 87 and s 87A is whether there has been a genuine agreement which was made freely and on an informed basis: Nangkiriny v State of Western Australia (2002) 117 FCR 6 ; [2002] FCA 660 at [14] . A relevant consideration on this aspect will be whether the parties have had independent and competent legal representation and, in the case of State parties, whether they have given appropriate consideration to the claims of the applicants: Munn (for and on behalf of the Gunggari People) v Queensland (2001) 115 FCR 109 ; [2001] FCA 1229 at [29] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Nangkiriny v State of Western Australia (2002) 117 FCR 6 ; [2002] FCA 660</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/660.html</AustLII>
<text>This requirement must be construed in the context of the Act as a whole and in conformity with the purpose of the Act. The Act provides for mediation and ultimate agreement as the primary means for resolving native title applications. Thus, the main concern of the Court when considering an application under s 87 and s 87A is whether there has been a genuine agreement which was made freely and on an informed basis: Nangkiriny v State of Western Australia (2002) 117 FCR 6 ; [2002] FCA 660 at [14] . A relevant consideration on this aspect will be whether the parties have had independent and competent legal representation and, in the case of State parties, whether they have given appropriate consideration to the claims of the applicants: Munn (for and on behalf of the Gunggari People) v Queensland (2001) 115 FCR 109 ; [2001] FCA 1229 at [29] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Ward v State of Western Australia [2006] FCA 1848</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1848.html</AustLII>
<text>The emphasis in the Act on mediation towards agreement is designed to minimise cost and delay. The section should therefore not be construed to require parties to an agreement to provide evidence to the Court on an application under s 87 or s 87A of the same nature as if the case had gone to trial. The purpose of the section is to encourage parties to avoid a trial: Ward v State of Western Australia [2006] FCA 1848 at [8] ( Ward ). In most circumstances the fact of agreement will be sufficient evidence upon which the Court may act under the section. It will not ordinarily be necessary for the Court to be provided with evidence of the primary facts substantiating native title: Ward [2006] FCA 1848 at [8] .

In the present case all the parties were legally represented. In relation to the consideration given by the State of Western Australia to the application, Mr Hamley, who is the Executive Director of the Office of Native Title (ONT) in the Western Australian Department of Treasury and Finance, explained the process which led to the agreement of the State of Western Australia. The process is laid down in the State's Guidelines for the Provision of Information and Support of Applications for a Determination of Native Title dated October 2004 (the Guidelines). First, the applicants were required to provide evidence of connection. In response they provided a Connection Report dated April 2006 from Dr Nicholas Smith, the Senior Anthropologist with the Pilbara Native Title Service. The report came with a DVD showing a number of the Nyangumarta People explaining their connection with country, and also with genealogies and genealogical sources. In accordance with the Guidelines this material was reviewed internally by Ms Debbie Fletcher, the Director of Research. On the basis of this internal review the ONT advised the then Deputy Premier that the State should enter into negotiations toward an agreed determination of native title. Mr Hamley explained the basis upon which this advice was given. He said: 
 ...In particular, ONT was satisfied that the connection material supports the existence of a body of traditional laws and customs under which the claimants hold rights and interests within the area covered by the application. This was on the basis that: 

 
 (a) the Nyangumarta claimants are a clearly defined group of people who acknowledge and observe a shared set of normative rules for determining group membership and are descended from Nyangumarta ancestors who were present in the claim area at the time of settlement; 

 
 (b) there is evidence of continuity of acknowledgement and observance of traditional laws and customs in relation to the claim area by the claimants and transmission of these laws and customs to younger members of the claim group; and 

 
 (c) the continued connection of the Nyangumarta people to the claim area has been underpinned by acknowledgement and observance of a normative system of law and custom.

During its assessment process, the State of Western Australia engaged an independent expert anthropologist to assess the connection material. In the meantime further material was provided by the applicants from October 2006 until December 2008.

The affidavit of Mr Mathews filed on behalf of the applicants exhibited the report of Dr Smith with certain deletions designed to protect confidentiality. This was only part of the connection material provided by the applicants to the State of Western Australia. Excluding the seven appendices the report ran to 240 pages. It is a comprehensive discussion of each of the elements together with supporting evidence which the applicants would need to prove at a trial to secure a native title determination.

The affidavit material amply demonstrates not only that the State of Western Australia gave detailed and comprehensive consideration to the applicants' case, but also that the applicants have a strong basis for the determination of native title sought.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lovett on behalf of the Gunditjmara People v State of Victoria [2007] FCA 474</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/474.html</AustLII>
<text>In Lovett on behalf of the Gunditjmara People v State of Victoria [2007] FCA 474 the issue was addressed thus: ... There is a question as to how far a State party is required to investigate in order to satisfy itself of a credible basis for an application. One reason for the often inordinate time taken to resolve some of these cases is the overly demanding nature of the investigation conducted by State parties. The scope of these investigations demanded by some States is reflected in the complex connection guidelines published by some States.
 The power conferred by the Act on the Court to approve agreements is given in order to avoid lengthy hearings before the Court. The Act does not intend to substitute a trial, in effect, conducted by State parties for a trial before the Court. Thus, something significantly less than the material necessary to justify a judicial determination is sufficient to satisfy a State party of a credible basis for an application.

As a result of my recurring concern with the undue burden placed upon applicants in cases resulting in consent determinations, I wrote to the parties prior to the hearing raising this concern in relation to the volume of material provided by the applicants in the present case. The State responded with a helpful and constructive submission which explained first, that in the recent Central Desert application filed by the Birriliburu People, the report provided by the representative body was short and targeted, and was used as a model report at the connection workshop conducted by the State at the end of 2008, and second, that the detail of the report in this case was provided by the applicants as a matter of their choice.

It is to be hoped that the State will give careful consideration in future matters under s 87 and s 87A to easing the present unnecessary burden either placed on or assumed by native title applicants.

On the material before the Court it is clearly appropriate to make the orders and the determination sought by the parties.

It is now necessary to consider the proposed determination that the Nyangumarta Warrarn Aboriginal Corporation (the Corporation) be the trustee of the native title. Section 56 of the Act relevantly provides: 
 Trust determination 
 (1) One of the determinations that the Federal Court must make is whether the native title is to be held in trust, and, if so, by whom. 

 
 Steps in making determination 
 (2) The Federal Court is to take the following steps in making the determination: 

(a) first, it must request a representative of the persons it proposes to include in the determination of native title as the native title holders (the common law holders ) to indicate whether the common law holders intend to have the native title held in trust by:
 
 
(i) nominating, in writing given to the Federal Court within a specified period, a prescribed body corporate to be trustee of the native title; and
 
 
(ii) including with the nomination the written consent of the body corporate; and
 
 
(b) secondly, if the common law holders give the nomination within the period, the Federal Court must determine that the prescribed body corporate is to hold the rights and interests from time to time comprising the native title in trust for the common law holders; and
 
 
(c) thirdly, if the common law holders do not give the nomination within the period, the Federal Court must determine that the rights and interests are to be held by the common law holders.
 
 
 Native title held in trust 
 (3) On the making of a determination under paragraph (2)(b), the prescribed body corporate holds, in accordance with the regulations, the rights and interests from time to time comprising the native title in trust for the common law holders.

One of Mr Matthews' affidavits proves that the Corporation was registered under the Corporations (Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander) Act 2006 (Cth) on 11 March 2009 and was thus a prescribed body corporate for the purposes of ss 56(2) and (3) (see reg 4(1) of the Native Title (Prescribed Bodies Corporate) Regulations 1999 (Cth) (the Regulations). Section 56(3) of the Act requires that the Corporation holds the native title rights and interests in accordance with the Regulations. I am satisfied that this is so. The rule book of the Corporation was tendered in evidence and rule 5.2.2 satisfies the requirement of reg 4(2)(a), rule 3(c)(i) satisfies the requirement of reg 4(2)(b), and rules 3(c)(i) and (ii) satisfy the requirements of reg 6(1).

The Nyangumarta People filed a written nomination of the Corporation on 22 May 2009 in accordance with s 56(2)(a)(i) of the Act. The Corporation consented to the nomination and filed a written consent dated 22 May 2009 in accordance with s 56(2)(a)(ii) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>