<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Food Channel Network Pty Ltd ACN 079 015 339 v Television Food Network, G.P. [2009] FCA 68 (11 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/68.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1542.html</AustLII>
<text>The application before this Court under s 104 is an application in the original jurisdiction of the Court. Having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court under s 197 of the Act, it is plain that it is not necessary on appeal under s 104 to determine whether the decision of the Registrar was correct when made. In that sense, the appeal proceeding is a hearing conducted "afresh" or de novo (like an appeal proceeding under s 56 of the Act: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542) on material properly placed before the Court ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]). Section 197 is in these terms: On hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar, the Federal Court may do any one or more of the following:
 
 (a) admit further evidence orally, or on affidavit or otherwise;
 (b) permit the examination and cross-examination of witnesses, including witnesses who give evidence before the Registrar;
 (c) order an issue of fact to be tried as it directs;
 (d) affirm, reverse or vary the Registrar's decision or direction;
 (e) give any judgment, or make any order, that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit;
 (f) order a party to pay costs to another party.

The second application is an application by FCN as applicant for an order that TFN provide security for FCN's costs of and incidental to the appeal proceeding. That application although conceded by FCN to be novel, is made, it is said, on the footing that although FCN is the applicant in the proceeding, TFN ought to be regarded for all practical purposes as the prime mover or aggressor having initiated the application for removal of the trade mark before the Registrar. FCN says its appeal arises out of that "proceeding" and is responsive to it in the sense that FCN is exercising a right of appeal derivative of that proceeding. Therefore, it is said, s 56(5) of the Court Act in conjunction with Order 28 of the Federal Court Rules contemplates that an order for security for costs might be made against a respondent before this Court, who is (or was) an "applicant" in a proceeding before the Registrar of Trade Marks. That result is said to follow because Order 28, r 1 provides that references to an applicant (for the purposes of that Order) "extend to any person who makes a claim for relief in any proceeding" (Order 28, r 1). Secondly, FCN's application is said to be supported by the powers conferred on the Court by s 197 of the Act to make any order that in all the circumstances the Court thinks fit (s 197(e)). FCN says s 197 should be read in conjunction with s 222 of the Act which confers power upon the Registrar of Trade Marks in these terms: 
 222. If a person who neither resides nor carries on business in Australia: 

 
 (a) ...
 (b) applies to the Registrar under Part 9 for a trade mark to be removed from the Register; 

 
 the Registrar may require the person to give security for the costs of the proceeding and may, if security is not given, dismiss the proceeding.

FCN says that the Court in hearing and determining an appeal under s 104 must be taken to have the same powers conferred upon it as those conferred under s 222 upon the Registrar or alternatively the empowering provision of s 197 confers sufficient power to enable an order to be made directing TFN to provide security for FCN's costs of and incidental to the hearing, assuming the relevant discretionary factors are made out. Principal among those for the moment are said to be that TFN ought to be characterised as the prime mover or aggressor and secondly, TFN is a partnership foreign to the jurisdiction with no assets within the jurisdiction. TFN says that FCN's application for security is misconceived because s 56 of the Court Act and Order 28 of the Federal Court Rules only contemplate orders for security for costs against an applicant or appellant or a person who "makes a claim for relief in any proceeding" (Order 28, r 1). TFN says it makes no claim for relief in this proceeding and the reference in Order 28, r 1 can only be a reference to a proceeding in the Court. Thus, there is no power to make an order against a respondent who makes no claim upon an applicant. Secondly, s 222 of the Act confers power upon the Registrar and only the Registrar, in the circumstances of the section and is not a provision which confers power on the Court. Thirdly, FCN's notice of motion is confined to an order sought under s 222 and does not, in terms, rely upon s 197. Fourthly, s 197 is directed to the powers of the Court in the hearing and determination of an appeal and does not confer power to make an order for security for costs. The power to do so in a s 104 proceeding before the Court is, it is said, determined by the Court Act and the Federal Court Rules . TFN's application for security

TFN says in reliance upon an affidavit by Mr Anthony Bennett sworn 12 December 2008 that FCN is a company that operates a website described as "The Food Channel". By FCN's website material it describes itself as a company founded in 1997 that utilises the internet and television as the medium for distributing multimedia productions to promote a range of services and products in a range of regions. TFN says that FCN is a company which has one issued share of $1.00 in paid up capital and Mr Lawrence is the only shareholder. TFN says that searches fail to reveal any significant assets held by FCN. Further, TFN says that The Food Channel website does not identify the entity conducting the business nor the business premises.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/440.html</AustLII>
<text>The application before this Court under s 104 is an application in the original jurisdiction of the Court. Having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court under s 197 of the Act, it is plain that it is not necessary on appeal under s 104 to determine whether the decision of the Registrar was correct when made. In that sense, the appeal proceeding is a hearing conducted "afresh" or de novo (like an appeal proceeding under s 56 of the Act: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542) on material properly placed before the Court ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]). Section 197 is in these terms: On hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar, the Federal Court may do any one or more of the following:
 
 (a) admit further evidence orally, or on affidavit or otherwise;
 (b) permit the examination and cross-examination of witnesses, including witnesses who give evidence before the Registrar;
 (c) order an issue of fact to be tried as it directs;
 (d) affirm, reverse or vary the Registrar's decision or direction;
 (e) give any judgment, or make any order, that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit;
 (f) order a party to pay costs to another party.

Section 197 of the Act is framed in broad terms. The terms of that enabling provision are directed to conferring broad powers of rehearing in the disposition of an appeal from the particular decision of the Registrar ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks (supra)), that is: admit further evidence; permit examination and cross-examination of witnesses; permit an issue of fact to be tried as directed; affirm, reverse or vary the primary decision; give any judgment or make any order the Court thinks fit; and make an order as to costs. That which is to be reheard on the application (appeal) of FCN is whether FCN can make out, on all the evidence, its opposition to removal of the mark having failed to make out that position before the Registrar's delegate. The decision from which the appeal lies did not involve any element of security for costs. Nevertheless, s 197(e) of the Act confers broad power to "... give any judgment, or make any order , that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit on hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar" [emphasis added]. The conferral of power upon the Court to make any order on hearing an appeal is sufficiently broad to confer a power to make any order in the course of an appeal proceeding including any interlocutory order. That power may extend in a given case to a security for costs order. In the ordinary course however, an applicant for security would find the source of the power for such an order in s 56 of the Court Act and Order 28, r 1 of the Federal Court Rules . The conferral of an express power on the Court to order security under the Trade Marks Act was probably not thought necessary having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court by the Court Act and the Federal Court Rules . In principle, the scope of s 197(e) is broad enough to confer power on the Court to make an order against any party in all the circumstances in any given case, if the relevant discretionary factors are satisfied.

In this case, it is not necessary to consider any further the scope of the power particularly as it relates to a potential order that might be made against a respondent (if at all) as no order ought to be made in the exercise of discretion for these reasons. First, no claim for relief is made by the respondent other than to affirm the decision of the respondent's delegate challenged by the applicant by way of rehearing. Secondly, although the respondent initiated the proceeding before the Registrar and sought to remove the trade mark from the Register, the present applicant seeks the rehearing and could have put on before the Registrar all of the evidence that it now proposes to put on in the appeal. If all the evidence bearing on the question is as compelling as FCN contends, the Court proceeding and the attendant costs would not have been necessary. Thirdly, the applicant bore the rebuttal burden as a matter of law under s 100 of the Act before the Registrar in relation to any allegation made by TFN under s 92(4)(b) of the Act and failed to put on all the evidence that might have discharged that burden. Fourthly, the evidence as to the amount of costs which might be the subject of an order is scant.

Accordingly, FCN's application for security is to be dismissed, with costs.
 I certify that the preceding twenty-seven (27) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Greenwood. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 11 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr Stephens 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Potts &amp; Co, Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Respondent represented by its solicitors 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Bennett &amp; Philp Lawyers 
 Date of Hearing: 5 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 11 February 2009 
 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/68.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/333.html</AustLII>
<text>The application before this Court under s 104 is an application in the original jurisdiction of the Court. Having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court under s 197 of the Act, it is plain that it is not necessary on appeal under s 104 to determine whether the decision of the Registrar was correct when made. In that sense, the appeal proceeding is a hearing conducted "afresh" or de novo (like an appeal proceeding under s 56 of the Act: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542) on material properly placed before the Court ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]). Section 197 is in these terms: On hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar, the Federal Court may do any one or more of the following:
 
 (a) admit further evidence orally, or on affidavit or otherwise;
 (b) permit the examination and cross-examination of witnesses, including witnesses who give evidence before the Registrar;
 (c) order an issue of fact to be tried as it directs;
 (d) affirm, reverse or vary the Registrar's decision or direction;
 (e) give any judgment, or make any order, that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit;
 (f) order a party to pay costs to another party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291</tocase>
<text>The application before this Court under s 104 is an application in the original jurisdiction of the Court. Having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court under s 197 of the Act, it is plain that it is not necessary on appeal under s 104 to determine whether the decision of the Registrar was correct when made. In that sense, the appeal proceeding is a hearing conducted "afresh" or de novo (like an appeal proceeding under s 56 of the Act: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542) on material properly placed before the Court ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]). Section 197 is in these terms: On hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar, the Federal Court may do any one or more of the following:
 
 (a) admit further evidence orally, or on affidavit or otherwise;
 (b) permit the examination and cross-examination of witnesses, including witnesses who give evidence before the Registrar;
 (c) order an issue of fact to be tried as it directs;
 (d) affirm, reverse or vary the Registrar's decision or direction;
 (e) give any judgment, or make any order, that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit;
 (f) order a party to pay costs to another party.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Intercraft Cabinets Pty Ltd v Sampas Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 16 ACLC 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1998/30.html</AustLII>
<text>It is true that FCN has failed to identify assets of the company out of which an order for costs might be satisfied. However, on the evidence, FCN is a going concern. FCN has previously satisfied at least one order for costs in litigation between the same parties. The undertaking offered by Mr Lawrence is not decisive of TFN's application in the sense that the offer of the undertaking is determinative of a decision in the exercise of the discretion. It is one important factor to be taken into account. In Intercraft Cabinets Pty Ltd v Sampas Pty Ltd [1998] HCA 30 ; (1998) 16 ACLC 1 at p 8, Malcolm CJ put the principle in these terms: 
 While the fact that those who stand behind the company have offered to guarantee payment of the taxed costs of the appellant is a material consideration, it is not the only consideration. There are other matters to be considered such as the merits of the action, the conduct of the parties and any other matter relevant to the exercise of the discretion, including the proposition that the mere impecuniosity of a plaintiff should not be a bar to the commencement of proceedings. 
 [emphasis added]</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Mantaray Pty Ltd v Brookfield Breeding Co. Pty Ltd (1990) 8 ACLC 304</tocase>
<text>In Mantaray Pty Ltd v Brookfield Breeding Co. Pty Ltd (1990) 8 ACLC 304 at 306 Byrne J adopted observations of Connolly J (Campbell CJ and Demack J agreeing with Connolly J) in Harpur &amp; Ors v Ariadne Australia Ltd &amp; Ors (1984) 2 ACLC 356 at 362 to the effect that the purpose of an order for security is to require a person to step out from behind the "skirts of the company" and bring his or her own assets into play. Connolly J also observed that, "If however he [or she] is already available for whatever he [or she] is worth, the object of the legislation is seen to be satisfied". In Gentry Bros. Pty Ltd v Wilson Brown &amp; Associates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1992) 10 ACLC 1394 at 1399, Cooper J observed that once the shareholders have been exposed to personal liability, the weight to be given to the statutory purpose of an order for security against the corporation is gone. Cooper J described the offer by shareholders to accept personal liability for the costs of the corporation as a factor "weighing heavily" against the making of an order for security "notwithstanding that the worth of the shareholders may ultimately prove insufficient to satisfy any judgment in whole or in part". In KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 13 ACLC 437 , Beazley J at 445 considered both Mantaray and Gentry and put the principle to be adopted in these terms: 
 ... the offer of security by way of guarantee from the directors or shareholders or other persons interested in the outcome of the litigation [is] a factor, which could be decisive in a given case, to be considered in determining whether any other form of order for security for costs should be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Harpur &amp; Ors v Ariadne Australia Ltd &amp; Ors (1984) 2 ACLC 356</tocase>
<text>In Mantaray Pty Ltd v Brookfield Breeding Co. Pty Ltd (1990) 8 ACLC 304 at 306 Byrne J adopted observations of Connolly J (Campbell CJ and Demack J agreeing with Connolly J) in Harpur &amp; Ors v Ariadne Australia Ltd &amp; Ors (1984) 2 ACLC 356 at 362 to the effect that the purpose of an order for security is to require a person to step out from behind the "skirts of the company" and bring his or her own assets into play. Connolly J also observed that, "If however he [or she] is already available for whatever he [or she] is worth, the object of the legislation is seen to be satisfied". In Gentry Bros. Pty Ltd v Wilson Brown &amp; Associates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1992) 10 ACLC 1394 at 1399, Cooper J observed that once the shareholders have been exposed to personal liability, the weight to be given to the statutory purpose of an order for security against the corporation is gone. Cooper J described the offer by shareholders to accept personal liability for the costs of the corporation as a factor "weighing heavily" against the making of an order for security "notwithstanding that the worth of the shareholders may ultimately prove insufficient to satisfy any judgment in whole or in part". In KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 13 ACLC 437 , Beazley J at 445 considered both Mantaray and Gentry and put the principle to be adopted in these terms: 
 ... the offer of security by way of guarantee from the directors or shareholders or other persons interested in the outcome of the litigation [is] a factor, which could be decisive in a given case, to be considered in determining whether any other form of order for security for costs should be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Gentry Bros. Pty Ltd v Wilson Brown &amp; Associates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1992) 10 ACLC 1394</tocase>
<text>In Mantaray Pty Ltd v Brookfield Breeding Co. Pty Ltd (1990) 8 ACLC 304 at 306 Byrne J adopted observations of Connolly J (Campbell CJ and Demack J agreeing with Connolly J) in Harpur &amp; Ors v Ariadne Australia Ltd &amp; Ors (1984) 2 ACLC 356 at 362 to the effect that the purpose of an order for security is to require a person to step out from behind the "skirts of the company" and bring his or her own assets into play. Connolly J also observed that, "If however he [or she] is already available for whatever he [or she] is worth, the object of the legislation is seen to be satisfied". In Gentry Bros. Pty Ltd v Wilson Brown &amp; Associates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1992) 10 ACLC 1394 at 1399, Cooper J observed that once the shareholders have been exposed to personal liability, the weight to be given to the statutory purpose of an order for security against the corporation is gone. Cooper J described the offer by shareholders to accept personal liability for the costs of the corporation as a factor "weighing heavily" against the making of an order for security "notwithstanding that the worth of the shareholders may ultimately prove insufficient to satisfy any judgment in whole or in part". In KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 13 ACLC 437 , Beazley J at 445 considered both Mantaray and Gentry and put the principle to be adopted in these terms: 
 ... the offer of security by way of guarantee from the directors or shareholders or other persons interested in the outcome of the litigation [is] a factor, which could be decisive in a given case, to be considered in determining whether any other form of order for security for costs should be made.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>quoted</class>
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 13 ACLC 437</tocase>
<text>In Mantaray Pty Ltd v Brookfield Breeding Co. Pty Ltd (1990) 8 ACLC 304 at 306 Byrne J adopted observations of Connolly J (Campbell CJ and Demack J agreeing with Connolly J) in Harpur &amp; Ors v Ariadne Australia Ltd &amp; Ors (1984) 2 ACLC 356 at 362 to the effect that the purpose of an order for security is to require a person to step out from behind the "skirts of the company" and bring his or her own assets into play. Connolly J also observed that, "If however he [or she] is already available for whatever he [or she] is worth, the object of the legislation is seen to be satisfied". In Gentry Bros. Pty Ltd v Wilson Brown &amp; Associates Pty Ltd &amp; Ors (1992) 10 ACLC 1394 at 1399, Cooper J observed that once the shareholders have been exposed to personal liability, the weight to be given to the statutory purpose of an order for security against the corporation is gone. Cooper J described the offer by shareholders to accept personal liability for the costs of the corporation as a factor "weighing heavily" against the making of an order for security "notwithstanding that the worth of the shareholders may ultimately prove insufficient to satisfy any judgment in whole or in part". In KP Cable Investments Pty Ltd v Meltglow Pty Ltd (1995) 13 ACLC 437 , Beazley J at 445 considered both Mantaray and Gentry and put the principle to be adopted in these terms: 
 ... the offer of security by way of guarantee from the directors or shareholders or other persons interested in the outcome of the litigation [is] a factor, which could be decisive in a given case, to be considered in determining whether any other form of order for security for costs should be made.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>