<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Millar v Bornholt [2009] FCA 637 (15 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/637.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bankstown Municipal Council v Fripp [1919] HCA 41 ; (1919) 26 CLR 385</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1919/41.html</AustLII>
<text>It is a feature of reg 87(4) of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations , noted by the Full Court in Martincevic [2007] FCAFC 164 ; (2007) 164 FCR 45 at 54, [44] , that, once the Chief of Army (or a delegate) forms the opinion described in that sub-regulation, the service of the member concerned must be terminated. One aspect of that opinion is whether the decision-maker is "satisfied" in terms of reg 87(1)(e) that the member is not suited to be an enlisted member. These features of reg 87 mean that it is one of those provisions where "some fact or event [is] condition upon the existence of which the jurisdiction of a court or tribunal shall depend": R v Federal Court of Australia; ex parte Pilkington ACI (Operations) Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 60 ; (1978) 142 CLR 113 at 125. In this instance, the "fact or event" upon which the jurisdiction of the Chief of Army to terminate the service of a member depends is a state of subjective satisfaction, an opinion. In Bankstown Municipal Council v Fripp [1919] HCA 41 ; (1919) 26 CLR 385 at 403, Isaacs and Rich JJ observed of provisions of this type that they are employed with the object of preventing litigation on matters of jurisdictional fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1947/14.html</AustLII>
<text>Like the power to terminate the service of an officer or an enlisted member, the power exercisable in respect of a referred redress of grievance complaint is in modern form statutory and found in the Defence Regulations but, to borrow language employed by Sir Own Dixon in describing the former in Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 at 268, it is no new subject. Though, for the purposes of the present case (Part XV was further amended on 1 May 2008 by the Defence Force Amendment Regulations 2008 (No 1), SLI 68 of 2008 in ways not presently material), they find contemporary expression in reg 75, 76 and 77 within Part XV of the Defence Regulations, when CPL Millar made a complaint to her commanding officer seeking redress of a grievance and then sought the subsequent referral of that complaint to the professional head of the Australian Army she was invoking rights the origins of which are ancient and deeply rooted in our constitutional heritage.

As will be seen, it is also no coincidence that the Governor-General in Council by (at the time) reg 81(1)(b) of the Defence Regulations, prescribed Brigadier to be the minimum rank to be held by an officer to whom the Chief of Army may delegate the power to determine a referred redress of grievance complaint.

Knowledge of legal history, of the relationship between the Sovereign, the Parliament and the Armed Forces, of the rank structure and chain of command within the Army and of the responsibilities in respect of subordinates assumed by those who hold the Queen's commission in the Defence Force is essential to an appreciation of the nature of the power exercisable on the referral of a complaint seeking a redress of grievance; all the more so because the language of reg 77 is compressed. That regulation assumes that its reader will either have that knowledge or at least make an effort to obtain it.

In "not suited to be an enlisted member" the present offers a paradigm example of "a matter of opinion or policy or taste". Further, as Sir Owen Dixon noted in Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 , at 268 of other regulations governing the relationship between the Commonwealth (and that term is used to include the Crown in right of the Commonwealth) and members of the Defence Force and in a passage to which I have already alluded: 
 [In] considering the meaning and effect of the Air Force Regulations their purpose cannot be neglected, namely to provide rules to govern one of the armed forces of the Crown. The relation to the Crown of members of the armed forces is no new subject; the rules of the common law define it. The regulations are not to be read in disregard of those rules and of the long tradition to which they have contributed. At common law neither commission nor enlistment in the services does or can amount to a contract with the Crown and neither officer nor man obtains any legal right against the Crown to pay, deferred pay, half pay, pension or emolument. 'All engagements between those in the military service of the Crown and the Crown are voluntary only on the part of the Crown, and give no occasion for an action in respect of any alleged contract:' per Lord Esher M.R. in Dunn v. The Queen: see Macdonald v. Steele; Gibson v. East India Co.; R. v. Secretary of State for War; Leaman v. The King: Lucas v. Lucas. (footnote references omitted).

The relationship between the Crown and a soldier is not that of employer and employee: Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1955] AC 457, at 489-490; Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1952] HCA 2 ; (1951-1952) 85 CLR 237 , at 301-302 per Kitto J. At common law, the relationship between the Crown and a soldier may be terminated without notice and for any reason, no reason or a mistaken reason: The Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 , at 257-258 per Latham CJ, McTiernan J agreeing; at 262 per Rich J, at 274 per Williams J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 105 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v. Perpetual Trustee Company [1952] HCA 2 ; (1951-1952) 85 CLR 237</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1952/2.html</AustLII>
<text>The relationship between the Crown and a soldier is not that of employer and employee: Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1955] AC 457, at 489-490; Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1952] HCA 2 ; (1951-1952) 85 CLR 237 , at 301-302 per Kitto J. At common law, the relationship between the Crown and a soldier may be terminated without notice and for any reason, no reason or a mistaken reason: The Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 , at 257-258 per Latham CJ, McTiernan J agreeing; at 262 per Rich J, at 274 per Williams J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 105 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v. Perpetual Trustee Company [1955] AC 457</tocase>
<text>The relationship between the Crown and a soldier is not that of employer and employee: Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1955] AC 457, at 489-490; Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1952] HCA 2 ; (1951-1952) 85 CLR 237 , at 301-302 per Kitto J. At common law, the relationship between the Crown and a soldier may be terminated without notice and for any reason, no reason or a mistaken reason: The Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 , at 257-258 per Latham CJ, McTiernan J agreeing; at 262 per Rich J, at 274 per Williams J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 105 per Brennan J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Marks v. The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1964/45.html</AustLII>
<text>In a passage later cited with approval by Dawson J in Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 120, Windeyer J, observed in Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 564 that, in Australia, the position of the Crown in relation to the Defence Force depended not upon the prerogative but rather upon statute such that the inquiry was whether the relevant statute law modified or abrogated the common law position. Hence the significance of Sir Owen Dixon's observation as to the manner of construing the provisions now found in reg 87 of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations . This observation of Sir Owen Dixon has subsequently been cited with approval both in the High Court ( Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 573 per Windeyer J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 98 per Wilson J, Brennan J agreeing).and in this Court ( Bowthorpe v Minister for Defence (1986) 17 IR 192, at 195 per Neaves J; Bromet v Oddie ((2002) 78 ALD 320, at 331 per Finn J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1976/24.html</AustLII>
<text>The feature just mentioned does not mean that statutory powers the exercise of which is dependent upon the engendering or achievement of a state of "satisfaction" in relation to an event or fact are unexaminable on judicial review either at common law or under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act , as was explained by Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ in a survey of pertinent authority in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 275-277. Paragraph 5(1)(f) of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act would permit the setting aside of BRIG Bornholt's decision in the event that it "involved an error of law". CPL Millar's referred redress complaint relevantly pressed a case that he should countermand the termination decision because he ought on the whole of the material not form an opinion in terms of reg 87(4) and 87(1)(e) of the Defence Personnel Regulations. In these circumstances and having regard to the nature of the regulation concerned an error of law might be found, as with judicial review under s 75(v) of the Constitution , in one or more of the ways described by Gibbs J in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118-119: 
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. [Emphasis added] 

 
In respect of the words emphasised in the passage quoted. Gummow J made the following observation in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 654, [137] :
 
 This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>R v Federal Court of Australia; ex parte Pilkington ACI (Operations) Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 60 ; (1978) 142 CLR 113</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/60.html</AustLII>
<text>It is a feature of reg 87(4) of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations , noted by the Full Court in Martincevic [2007] FCAFC 164 ; (2007) 164 FCR 45 at 54, [44] , that, once the Chief of Army (or a delegate) forms the opinion described in that sub-regulation, the service of the member concerned must be terminated. One aspect of that opinion is whether the decision-maker is "satisfied" in terms of reg 87(1)(e) that the member is not suited to be an enlisted member. These features of reg 87 mean that it is one of those provisions where "some fact or event [is] condition upon the existence of which the jurisdiction of a court or tribunal shall depend": R v Federal Court of Australia; ex parte Pilkington ACI (Operations) Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 60 ; (1978) 142 CLR 113 at 125. In this instance, the "fact or event" upon which the jurisdiction of the Chief of Army to terminate the service of a member depends is a state of subjective satisfaction, an opinion. In Bankstown Municipal Council v Fripp [1919] HCA 41 ; (1919) 26 CLR 385 at 403, Isaacs and Rich JJ observed of provisions of this type that they are employed with the object of preventing litigation on matters of jurisdictional fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Coutts v. The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/40.html</AustLII>
<text>The relationship between the Crown and a soldier is not that of employer and employee: Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1955] AC 457, at 489-490; Attorney-General (NSW) v Perpetual Trustee Company [1952] HCA 2 ; (1951-1952) 85 CLR 237 , at 301-302 per Kitto J. At common law, the relationship between the Crown and a soldier may be terminated without notice and for any reason, no reason or a mistaken reason: The Commonwealth v Welsh [1947] HCA 14 ; (1947) 74 CLR 245 , at 257-258 per Latham CJ, McTiernan J agreeing; at 262 per Rich J, at 274 per Williams J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 105 per Brennan J.

In a passage later cited with approval by Dawson J in Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 120, Windeyer J, observed in Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 564 that, in Australia, the position of the Crown in relation to the Defence Force depended not upon the prerogative but rather upon statute such that the inquiry was whether the relevant statute law modified or abrogated the common law position. Hence the significance of Sir Owen Dixon's observation as to the manner of construing the provisions now found in reg 87 of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations . This observation of Sir Owen Dixon has subsequently been cited with approval both in the High Court ( Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 573 per Windeyer J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 98 per Wilson J, Brennan J agreeing).and in this Court ( Bowthorpe v Minister for Defence (1986) 17 IR 192, at 195 per Neaves J; Bromet v Oddie ((2002) 78 ALD 320, at 331 per Finn J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/81.html</AustLII>
<text>In what has become a seminal Australian exposition on the subject of procedural fairness, Mason J, in Kioa v West [1985] HCA 81 ; (1985) 159 CLR 550 at 585, remarked of the expression that it "conveys the notion of a flexible obligation to adopt fair procedures which are appropriate and adapted to the circumstances of the particular case". It is not difficult to see how, in the context of operational service in times of a large scale deployment of the Australian Army, the content of a procedural fairness obligation in respect of a redress complaint either as initially made or on referral may in some cases be very limited indeed. In the present case, though the occasion for the initiation of termination procedures arose from incidents on operational service, the decision making process occurred in more benign circumstances in Australia. There is nothing in the circumstances which would suggest that any attenuated procedural fairness obligation attended BRIG Bornholt's consideration of the referred redress complaint. Thus, the assumption of the parties that the making of a decision by him was attended with a procedural fairness obligation which included the affording of a fair opportunity to CPL Millar to know the case made against her and to contradict it is correct. I accept therefore that he was obliged to afford CPL Millar procedural fairness in determining that referred redress complaint. The nature of that obligation though, as Mason J observed, depends on the circumstances of the particular case.

In this case, CPL Millar had already been the recipient of a Termination Notice which set out the basis upon which it was proposed to terminate her service in the Army. Only after that notice and an opportunity to respond had been given was the decision to terminate her service made by a delegate of the Chief of Army. In turn, before BRIG Bornholt became involved, CPL Millar had already sought redress from her CO and had the benefit of a reasoned decision as to why her complaint was not upheld. In light of those processes and their outcomes, it is clear that CPL Millar was well aware by then that the reason why a decision had been made to terminate her service on the basis of unsuitability and why her initial grievance was not upheld was a view, supported by the opinion of the Army psychologist CAPT Brown in her report of 15 November 2006 in particular, that, considering her behaviour on operational service in Iraq against the background of her service as a whole, there was a risk that under stress her performance would not be satisfactory. In seeking to have the Chief of Army overturn the termination decision on the review of her grievance complaint she furnished a further report from Mr Zemaitis along with character references from military associates and superiors.

Upon referral and as required by Defence Instruction (General) PERS 34-1 Redress of Grievance Tri-Service Procedures made under the Defence Act, a report in respect of the referred complaint was prepared for the Chief of Army's (or delegate's) consideration by the Complaints Resolution Agency within the Headquarters of the Australian Defence Force. It is the report of that agency which came before BRIG Bornholt and which he came to adopt. In adopting that report, its suggested outcome and the reasons as his own BRIG Bornholt adopted a report in which the case advanced by CPL Millar was thoroughly rehearsed and commented upon, as was the process that had led up to the decision to terminate her service and the initial rejection of her redress complaint. No new consideration personal to CPL Millar was introduced by the staff who compiled the report for Brig Bornholt. Neither did he do this of his own motion.

In these circumstances, a further passage from the judgement of Mason J in Kioa v West (at 559) is apposite: 
 [T]his is not to say that fairness will necessarily, or even generally, require that an applicant for a further entry permit be given an opportunity to be heard even where deportation may follow from its refusal. The grant of an entry permit is a matter of discretion. Indeed, the cancellation of a temporary entry permit is expressed to be a matter of absolute discretion (s.7(1)) . In the ordinary course of granting or refusing entry permits there is no occasion for the principles of natural justice to be called into play. The applicant is entitled to support his application by such information and material as he thinks appropriate and he cannot complain if the authorities reject his application because they do not accept, without further notice to him, what he puts forward. But if in fact the decision-maker intends to reject the application by reference to some consideration personal to the applicant on the basis of information obtained from another source which has not been dealt with by the applicant in his application there may be a case for saying that procedural fairness requires that he be given an opportunity of responding to the matter ( In re H.K. (An Infant) (1967) 2 QB 617). If the application is for a further temporary entry permit and it is made in circumstances which are relevantly similar to those in which the earlier permit was granted, the applicant may have a legitimate expectation that the further entry permit will be granted or will not be refused in the absence of an opportunity to deal with the grounds on which it is to be refused. And if the refusal is to be attended by the making of a deportation order, the case for holding that procedural fairness requires that such an opportunity be given is unquestionably stronger. 
 40. In this respect recent decisions illustrate the importance which the law attaches to the need to bring to a person's attention the critical issue or factor on which the administrative decision is likely to turn so that he may have an opportunity of dealing with it. FAI is one illustration. Cole v. Cunningham (1983) 49 ALR 123 , is another, as are Reg. v. Gaming Board for Great Britain; Ex parte Benaim and Khaida (1970) 2 QB 417, at p 431; and Daganayasi v. Minister of Immigration (1980) 2 NZLR 130 . 

 
BRIG Bornholt was obliged to investigate the referred complaint. As a senior officer he was able, as would have been the Chief of Army of Army himself, to require staff to prepare a report on the subject. In that regard, the procedure envisaged by the Defence Instruction (General) is not inconsistent with the Defence Regulations in relation to the investigation of a referred redress complaint. Whether he interfered with the termination decision was a matter for the exercise of discretion after investigation. Given the particular way in which the investigation was conducted, effectively on the papers, there was no need to give CPL Millar any further opportunity to be heard before making a decision. At the very latest, the fullness of the case she had to meet, both in terms of expert opinion and underlying reports and service history had been exposed to her in the disposal by her CO of her redress complaint. BRIG Bornholt decided not to uphold her redress complaint not on the basis of new information personal to her obtained from another source and not exposed already to her but on the basis of existing materials. In these circumstances, and contrary to the submission advanced on her behalf, he was not obliged again to revert to her and to offer her an opportunity to comment upon the reasons he proposed to adopt in declining to uphold her redress application. Rather, as is evident from the passage quoted, she, "cannot complain if the authorities reject [her] application because they do not accept, without further notice to [her], what [she] puts forward". I therefore reject the submission that BRIG Bornholt denied CPL Millar procedural fairness in making his decision.

A further submission was made that CPL Millar had not been afforded an opportunity to comment upon an assessment made of her by her Squadron Sergeant Major which was taken into account by CAPT Brown in her report. However, as the Respondents demonstrated in their written submissions, by the time that CPL Millar sought the referral of her redress complaint she had had two opportunities to comment upon this assessment, of which she had taken advantage; once in the course of showing cause why her service ought not be terminated and again in the seeking of the referral of her redress complaint. There is no substance in this aspect of her procedural fairness challenge. Neither, when it is recalled that it is the referral decision which is under review is there any substance in her assertion that she was denied an opportunity to comment upon comments made by the Army's Psychological Support Service North Queensland on the subject of her suitability. Those comments were limited to a concurrence with the views already expressed by CAPT Brown and were exposed to CPL Millar in the results of the "Quick Assessment" which was made of her initial redress complaint.

An examination of his reasons discloses that BRIG Bornholt approached his task in two particular ways. On the one hand, he examined whether the procedures adopted to date had been appropriate and whether the decisions reached were reasonably open; on the other and in any event he reached his own opinion on the whole of the evidence before him, which included the further evidence provided by CPL Millar in seeking the referral of her redress complaint, as to whether she was, in terms of reg 87(1)(e) of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations , suited to be an enlisted member.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin (1990) 170 CLR 1</tocase>
<text>The following observation of Brennan J in Attorney-General (NSW) v Quin (1990) 170 CLR 1 at 35-6 is no less pertinent in this case than in other judicial review cases: 
 The essential warrant for judicial intervention is the declaration and enforcing of the law affecting the extent and exercise of power: that is the characteristic duty of the judicature as the third branch of government ... [T]he duty extends to judicial review of administrative action alleged to go beyond the power conferred by statute or by the prerogative or alleged to be otherwise in disconformity with the law. The duty and the jurisdiction of the courts are expressed in the memorable words of Marshall CJ in Marbury v Madison : 
 "It is, emphatically, the province and duty of the judicial department to say what the law is."
 The duty and jurisdiction of the court to review administrative action do not go beyond the declaration and enforcing of the law which determines the limits and governs the exercise of the repository's power. If, in so doing, the court avoids administrative injustice or error, so be it; but the court has no jurisdiction simply to cure administrative injustice or error. The merits of administrative action, to the extent that they can be distinguished from legality, are for the repository of the relevant power and, subject to political control, for the repository alone.
 (footnote reference omitted) 

 
Like other officers of the Commonwealth, the decisions of the Chief of Army and his delegates are amenable to judicial review either by the High Court by constitutional writ under s 75(v) of the Constitution or in such other courts as the Parliament invests with federal jurisdiction judicially to review their decisions, but only for error of law.

There is nothing inherently illogical or unreasonable about the opinion as to CPL Millar's suitability to which BRIG Bornholt came. Twice before she had been considered for discharge on the basis of unsuitability but a choice had been made as between competing assessments not to discharge her. As a result of her performance on operational service two psychologists, MAJ Hadfield (provisionally) and CAPT Brown formed the opinion that CPL Millar was not suited to be a soldier. Assisted by their opinions and looking at the whole of her service history, BRIG Bornholt was entitled to form the opinion he did as to her unsuitability. In so doing, he was entitled to and self evidently did take into account the views of Mr Zemaitis. It is just that he chose not to accept the latter's views.

BRIG Bornholt was also entitled to form a view, based on a comparison of the reports of the Army psychologists and Mr Zemaitis prepared for him by staff and adopted by him that one reason for the differing views may have been that Mr Zemaitis did not have access to CPL Millar's full psychological file.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/6.html</AustLII>
<text>The feature just mentioned does not mean that statutory powers the exercise of which is dependent upon the engendering or achievement of a state of "satisfaction" in relation to an event or fact are unexaminable on judicial review either at common law or under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act , as was explained by Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ in a survey of pertinent authority in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 275-277. Paragraph 5(1)(f) of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act would permit the setting aside of BRIG Bornholt's decision in the event that it "involved an error of law". CPL Millar's referred redress complaint relevantly pressed a case that he should countermand the termination decision because he ought on the whole of the material not form an opinion in terms of reg 87(4) and 87(1)(e) of the Defence Personnel Regulations. In these circumstances and having regard to the nature of the regulation concerned an error of law might be found, as with judicial review under s 75(v) of the Constitution , in one or more of the ways described by Gibbs J in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118-119: 
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. [Emphasis added] 

 
In respect of the words emphasised in the passage quoted. Gummow J made the following observation in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 654, [137] :
 
 This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/21.html</AustLII>
<text>The feature just mentioned does not mean that statutory powers the exercise of which is dependent upon the engendering or achievement of a state of "satisfaction" in relation to an event or fact are unexaminable on judicial review either at common law or under the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act , as was explained by Brennan CJ, Toohey, McHugh and Gummow JJ in a survey of pertinent authority in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Wu Shan Liang [1996] HCA 6 ; (1996) 185 CLR 259 at 275-277. Paragraph 5(1)(f) of the Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act would permit the setting aside of BRIG Bornholt's decision in the event that it "involved an error of law". CPL Millar's referred redress complaint relevantly pressed a case that he should countermand the termination decision because he ought on the whole of the material not form an opinion in terms of reg 87(4) and 87(1)(e) of the Defence Personnel Regulations. In these circumstances and having regard to the nature of the regulation concerned an error of law might be found, as with judicial review under s 75(v) of the Constitution , in one or more of the ways described by Gibbs J in Buck v Bavone [1976] HCA 24 ; (1976) 135 CLR 110 at 118-119: 
 In all such cases the authority must act in good faith; it cannot act merely arbitrarily or capriciously. Moreover, a person affected will obtain relief from the courts if he can show that the authority has misdirected itself in law or that it has failed to consider matters that it was required to consider or has taken irrelevant matters into account. Even if none of these things can be established, the courts will interfere if the decision reached by the authority appears so unreasonable that no reasonable authority could properly have arrived at it. However, where the matter of which the authority is required to be satisfied is a matter of opinion or policy or taste it may be very difficult to show that it has erred in one of these ways, or that its decision could not reasonably have been reached. [Emphasis added] 

 
In respect of the words emphasised in the passage quoted. Gummow J made the following observation in Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Eshetu [1999] HCA 21 ; (1999) 197 CLR 611 at 654, [137] :
 
 This passage is consistent with the proposition that, where the criterion of which the authority is required to be satisfied turns upon factual matters upon which reasonable minds could reasonably differ, it will be very difficult to show that no reasonable decision-maker could have arrived at the decision in question. It may be otherwise if the evidence which establishes or denies, or, with other matters, goes to establish or to deny, that the necessary criterion has been met was all one way.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Martincevic v Commonwealth [2007] FCAFC 164 ; (2007) 164 FCR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/164.html</AustLII>
<text>For completeness, I should note that, though reference is made by the Full Court in Martincevic v Commonwealth [2007] FCAFC 164 ; (2007) 164 FCR 45 to a redress of grievance investigation, it did not prove necessary in that case for the Full Court to explore the nature of the power able to be exercised by the Chief of Army upon the referral of a redress complaint. Rather, that case highlighted that the existence and outcome of a subsisting redress investigation before the making of a discharge decision may constitute (and in the circumstances of that case was held to constitute) a relevant consideration for the purposes of the making of that discharge decision.

It does not follow from the lack of understanding of the nature of the power evident in the Commonwealth's submissions that CPL Millar must succeed in her judicial review application. To determine that it is first necessary to relate in more detail the factual background which gave rise to CPL Millar's initial redress complaint, its later referral and this judicial review application. It is also necessary to set out why BRIG Bornholt came to confirm the decision to terminate her service with the Army. BRIG Bornholt's reasons are comprehensive. It would do that officer less than justice not to set them out in full but so to do in the main body of the judgement would, in my opinion, detract from its continuity and ready comprehensibility. I therefore annex the full text of BRIG Bornholt's reasons and highlight pertinent features in the main body of the judgement.

Before CPL Millar deployed to Iraq as part of Operation CATALYST 2 she undertook pre-deployment training at Randwick Barracks in Sydney from 27 June 2006 for a period of one month. During that time, CPL Millar maintained a good rapport with most, but not all, of the members attending this pre-deployment training course.

It is a feature of reg 87(4) of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations , noted by the Full Court in Martincevic [2007] FCAFC 164 ; (2007) 164 FCR 45 at 54, [44] , that, once the Chief of Army (or a delegate) forms the opinion described in that sub-regulation, the service of the member concerned must be terminated. One aspect of that opinion is whether the decision-maker is "satisfied" in terms of reg 87(1)(e) that the member is not suited to be an enlisted member. These features of reg 87 mean that it is one of those provisions where "some fact or event [is] condition upon the existence of which the jurisdiction of a court or tribunal shall depend": R v Federal Court of Australia; ex parte Pilkington ACI (Operations) Pty Ltd [1978] HCA 60 ; (1978) 142 CLR 113 at 125. In this instance, the "fact or event" upon which the jurisdiction of the Chief of Army to terminate the service of a member depends is a state of subjective satisfaction, an opinion. In Bankstown Municipal Council v Fripp [1919] HCA 41 ; (1919) 26 CLR 385 at 403, Isaacs and Rich JJ observed of provisions of this type that they are employed with the object of preventing litigation on matters of jurisdictional fact.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bowthorpe v. Minister for Defence (1986) 17 IR 192</tocase>
<text>In a passage later cited with approval by Dawson J in Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 120, Windeyer J, observed in Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 564 that, in Australia, the position of the Crown in relation to the Defence Force depended not upon the prerogative but rather upon statute such that the inquiry was whether the relevant statute law modified or abrogated the common law position. Hence the significance of Sir Owen Dixon's observation as to the manner of construing the provisions now found in reg 87 of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations . This observation of Sir Owen Dixon has subsequently been cited with approval both in the High Court ( Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 573 per Windeyer J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 98 per Wilson J, Brennan J agreeing).and in this Court ( Bowthorpe v Minister for Defence (1986) 17 IR 192, at 195 per Neaves J; Bromet v Oddie ((2002) 78 ALD 320, at 331 per Finn J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bromet v. Oddie ((2002) 78 ALD 320</tocase>
<text>In a passage later cited with approval by Dawson J in Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 120, Windeyer J, observed in Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 564 that, in Australia, the position of the Crown in relation to the Defence Force depended not upon the prerogative but rather upon statute such that the inquiry was whether the relevant statute law modified or abrogated the common law position. Hence the significance of Sir Owen Dixon's observation as to the manner of construing the provisions now found in reg 87 of the Defence (Personnel) Regulations . This observation of Sir Owen Dixon has subsequently been cited with approval both in the High Court ( Marks v The Commonwealth [1964] HCA 45 ; (1964) 111 CLR 549 , at 573 per Windeyer J; Coutts v The Commonwealth [1985] HCA 40 ; (1984-1985) 157 CLR 91 , at 98 per Wilson J, Brennan J agreeing).and in this Court ( Bowthorpe v Minister for Defence (1986) 17 IR 192, at 195 per Neaves J; Bromet v Oddie ((2002) 78 ALD 320, at 331 per Finn J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>R v The Army Council; ex parte Ravenscroft [1917] 2 KB 504</tocase>
<text>Such is the plenary nature of the power exercisable on the merits by the Chief of Army or a delegate on a referred redress complaint that this Court might decide, as a matter of discretion rather than jurisdiction, summarily to dismiss the application of a member of the Army who has chosen to seek judicial review of a termination of service decision rather than seek redress under the Defence Regulations. That, I note, was one of the bases upon which a Queen's Bench Divisional Court refused to grant prerogative relief to an officer in such a position in R v The Army Council; ex parte Ravenscroft [1917] 2 KB 504. Insofar as there are also suggestions (at 508 per Viscount Reading CJ, at 512 per Ridley J and at 513 per Avory J) in that case that a court would not interfere with the dismissal of an officer because that was a matter of military discipline, the case is inconsistent with, for example, Welsh's Case , supra, here and not good law. The latter aspect of the case is perhaps explicable on the basis that, at the time, officers served at the pleasure of the Crown with the basis for their dismissal being the Prerogative rather than, as in Australia, statutory. That distinguishing feature does not though affect the authority of that case insofar as it recognises that the plenary nature of the right of redress may provide a basis for discretionary refusal of a prerogative writ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>R v Army Board of the Defence Council; ex parte Anderson [1992] 1 QB 169</tocase>
<text>It was common ground as between CPL Millar and the Respondents that BRIG Bornholt was obliged to afford her procedural fairness in deciding her referred redress complaint. As it happens, there is contemporary English intermediate appellate authority which would support such a conclusion in the particular context of the consideration of a referred redress of grievance complaint, in that case one arising from an allegation of racial discrimination by a member of the British Army: R v Army Board of the Defence Council; Ex parte Anderson [1992] 1 QB 169.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2006] F.C.J. No. 625; 2006 FC 505</tocase>
<text>These same sentiments are evident in judgements of the Federal Court of Canada with respect to the judicial review of decisions relating to the disposition of grievances in the Canadian Forces. In Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2006] F.C.J. No. 625; 2006 FC 505 Layden-Stevenson J observed of the grievance procedures for which s 29 of the National Defence Act (Can) and Chapter 7 of the Queen's Regulations and Orders made thereunder provide: 
 [34] The purpose of the National Defence Act (NDA) is to provide for the management, direction and administration of the Canadian Forces (CF). The purpose of the specific provisions, in relation to this matter, is the efficient resolution of grievances or disputes. The issue in this case is not polycentric. Rather, it is of a private or personal nature. Some deference is appropriate in view of the fact that the final decision lies with the Chief of the Defence Staff (CDS), or an officer delegated by him.
 [35] The expertise of the decision-maker militates in favour of deference. The CDS, the most senior officer in the CF, is charged with control and administration of the CF. The NDA mandates that all orders and instructions to the CF, to carry out the directions of the Governor in Council or the Minister, are to be issued through the CDS. It is to be expected that the CDS, or his delegate, will be conversant with all facets of the military context, unlike the court. This factor indicates a high level of deference. 

 
Her Honour's judgement was affirmed on appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal: Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2007] F.C.J. No. 546; 2007 FCA 157 and has since been cited with approval in relation to another judicial review proceeding arising out of the Canadian Forces grievance resolution provisions: Leading Seaman D.M. Morphy v Canada (Attorney General) [2008] F.C.J. No. 242; 2008 FC 190 at [63]. The observation Layden-Stevenson J made has like application for like reasons in the present case in relation to whether CPL Millar is suitable to be an enlisted member. In the circumstances of this case, the person to be "satisfied" or not on this subject was a senior military officer, not a judicial officer. Deference is called for in relation to the value judgement made by that military officer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2007] F.C.J. No. 546; 2007 FCA 157</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/157.html</AustLII>
<text>These same sentiments are evident in judgements of the Federal Court of Canada with respect to the judicial review of decisions relating to the disposition of grievances in the Canadian Forces. In Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2006] F.C.J. No. 625; 2006 FC 505 Layden-Stevenson J observed of the grievance procedures for which s 29 of the National Defence Act (Can) and Chapter 7 of the Queen's Regulations and Orders made thereunder provide: 
 [34] The purpose of the National Defence Act (NDA) is to provide for the management, direction and administration of the Canadian Forces (CF). The purpose of the specific provisions, in relation to this matter, is the efficient resolution of grievances or disputes. The issue in this case is not polycentric. Rather, it is of a private or personal nature. Some deference is appropriate in view of the fact that the final decision lies with the Chief of the Defence Staff (CDS), or an officer delegated by him.
 [35] The expertise of the decision-maker militates in favour of deference. The CDS, the most senior officer in the CF, is charged with control and administration of the CF. The NDA mandates that all orders and instructions to the CF, to carry out the directions of the Governor in Council or the Minister, are to be issued through the CDS. It is to be expected that the CDS, or his delegate, will be conversant with all facets of the military context, unlike the court. This factor indicates a high level of deference. 

 
Her Honour's judgement was affirmed on appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal: Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2007] F.C.J. No. 546; 2007 FCA 157 and has since been cited with approval in relation to another judicial review proceeding arising out of the Canadian Forces grievance resolution provisions: Leading Seaman D.M. Morphy v Canada (Attorney General) [2008] F.C.J. No. 242; 2008 FC 190 at [63]. The observation Layden-Stevenson J made has like application for like reasons in the present case in relation to whether CPL Millar is suitable to be an enlisted member. In the circumstances of this case, the person to be "satisfied" or not on this subject was a senior military officer, not a judicial officer. Deference is called for in relation to the value judgement made by that military officer.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Leading Seaman D.M. Morphy v. Canada (Attorney General) [2008] F.C.J. No. 242; 2008 FC 190</tocase>
<text>These same sentiments are evident in judgements of the Federal Court of Canada with respect to the judicial review of decisions relating to the disposition of grievances in the Canadian Forces. In Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2006] F.C.J. No. 625; 2006 FC 505 Layden-Stevenson J observed of the grievance procedures for which s 29 of the National Defence Act (Can) and Chapter 7 of the Queen's Regulations and Orders made thereunder provide: 
 [34] The purpose of the National Defence Act (NDA) is to provide for the management, direction and administration of the Canadian Forces (CF). The purpose of the specific provisions, in relation to this matter, is the efficient resolution of grievances or disputes. The issue in this case is not polycentric. Rather, it is of a private or personal nature. Some deference is appropriate in view of the fact that the final decision lies with the Chief of the Defence Staff (CDS), or an officer delegated by him.
 [35] The expertise of the decision-maker militates in favour of deference. The CDS, the most senior officer in the CF, is charged with control and administration of the CF. The NDA mandates that all orders and instructions to the CF, to carry out the directions of the Governor in Council or the Minister, are to be issued through the CDS. It is to be expected that the CDS, or his delegate, will be conversant with all facets of the military context, unlike the court. This factor indicates a high level of deference. 

 
Her Honour's judgement was affirmed on appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal: Armstrong v Canada (Attorney General) [2007] F.C.J. No. 546; 2007 FCA 157 and has since been cited with approval in relation to another judicial review proceeding arising out of the Canadian Forces grievance resolution provisions: Leading Seaman D.M. Morphy v Canada (Attorney General) [2008] F.C.J. No. 242; 2008 FC 190 at [63]. The observation Layden-Stevenson J made has like application for like reasons in the present case in relation to whether CPL Millar is suitable to be an enlisted member. In the circumstances of this case, the person to be "satisfied" or not on this subject was a senior military officer, not a judicial officer. Deference is called for in relation to the value judgement made by that military officer.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>