<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Humphries v Newport Quays Stage 2A Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 699 (29 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/699.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Fox v Olsen [1999] SASC 411</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/1999/411.html</AustLII>
<text>There is likely to be a saving of time if the proceedings are tried together, but it is difficult to quantify the extent of the saving. It would be nowhere near the substantial saving referred to in Fox v Olsen [1999] SASC 411 at [7] per Mullighan J (with whom Doyle CJ and Wicks J agreed). It seems to me that 2 weeks is a reasonable estimate for the trial of the proceeding brought by Mr Humphries. It is difficult to be precise about an estimate of trial time if all proceedings are tried at the same time, but, doing the best I can, I proceed on the basis of an estimate of 4-8 weeks. If tried separately, the proceedings involving Mr Humphries would, as I have said, take 2 weeks and the other 7 proceedings would take 1-2 weeks each. There is a real prospect that the parties in those 7 proceedings would not contest a number of findings of fact made in the first proceeding and therefore, if they did proceed, the estimate for each proceeding would be closer to 1 week than to 2 weeks.

Trial management issues are likely to loom large if all proceedings are tried together. It would be necessary to put in place detailed and possibly complex procedural orders to ensure the trial proceeded in an orderly fashion. There is considerable potential for time-consuming arguments about the cross-admissibility of evidence. Counsel would need to be alert to the evidence rulings about cross-admissibility. These problems are by no means insurmountable, but they are a reason not to order that the proceedings be tried together.

The proceeding involving Mr Humphries is further advanced, in terms of preparation for trial, than any of the other proceedings.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>