<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>JMB Beverages Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2009] FCA 668 (22 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/668.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General v Prince Ernest Augustus of Hanover [1957] AC 436</tocase>
<text>Reference was also made to the canon of statutory construction that terms used in statutes that are in pari materia should be given the same meaning unless there is a clear indication to the contrary: Attorney-General v Prince Ernest Augustus of Hanover [1957] AC 436 at 461 per Viscount Simonds; The Wik Peoples v The State of Queensland (1996) 187 CLR 1 at 171 per Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bristol-Myers Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 126</tocase>
<text>Section 9-30(1)(a) of the GST Act provides , inter alia , that a supply is GST-free if it is GST-free under Div 38. Section 38-2 provides that a supply of food is GST-free. Section 38-4(1)(c) provides that beverages for human consumption are food. There is a definition of the term 'beverage' in s 38-4(2) saying that it 'includes water'. A more helpful description of the word is to be found in Bristol-Myers Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1990) 23 FCR 126 where Lockhart J described a beverage as 'a drink of any kind' and 'any liquid which is swallowed to quench thirst or for nourishment' and said that 'a beverage is consumed either hot or cold and is normally taken to quench the person's thirst or for stimulation or as an accompaniment to solid foods either at meal times or between meals'.

It is common ground between the parties that the Edenvale products are beverages for the purposes of the GST Act. Nonetheless, an exemption is only available if the Edenvale products are beverages of a kind specified in the third column of the Table in cl 1 of Sch 2 to the GST Act.

It is again common ground that Edenvale Chardonnay, Edenvale Shiraz and Edenvale Rose need to fall within Item 12 of the Table and that Edenvale Sparkling Cuvee needs to fall within Item 11 of the Table, an excerpt from which follows: 
 Beverages that are GST-free 
 
*Beverages specified in the third column of the table are GST-free.
 
 Beverages that are GST-free Item Category Beverages 10 Fruit and vegetable juices concentrates for making non-alcoholic *beverages, if the concentrates consist of at least 90% by volume of juices of fruits 11 
 non-alcoholic carbonated *beverages, if they consist wholly of juices of fruits or vegetables 12 
 non-alcoholic non-carbonated *beverages, if they consist of at least 90% by volume of juices of fruits or vegetables 
 
By s 182-15 of the GST Act, the second column cannot be taken into account in interpreting an item unless it is for the purpose, inter alia , of determining the meaning of an item which is ambiguous or obscure or, if the ordinary meaning conveyed by its text, taking into account its context in the GST Act and the purpose or object underlying the item, leads to a result that is manifestly absurd or is unreasonable: see subs 182-10(2).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Cascade Brewery Co Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 821 ; (2006) 153 FCR 11</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/821.html</AustLII>
<text>Such a legislative purpose is also discernable both from the circumstances in which the amendments arose, and the context in which Items 11 and 12 appear in the Table. This was recognised by Gzell J in P &amp; N at [32]: 
 There is a lot to be said for the submission of the Commissioner that when the compromise was made for a qualified exemption for food to ensure the passage of legislation, as Sundberg J points out Cascade Brewery Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 821 ; (2006) 153 FCR 11 at [40] , the legislature seems to have drawn the line between exempt and non-exempt food supplies in favour of food that is fresh, natural or unprocessed. For example, the beverages that are not included in the table to cl 1 of Sch 2 of the GST Act and are therefore not GST-free, include soft drinks and cordials, flavoured milk (Item 2) and flavoured soy milk and rice milk (Item 4). The only carbonated beverages that are GST-free are those satisfying Item 11, and water (Item 14), is GST-free only if it is non-carbonated and without any other additives. 

 First Issue: Whether the Edenvale products consist wholly (Item 11) or at least 90% by volume (Item 12) of the juices of fruits?
 The phrase 'juices of fruits'

Reference was made to Cascade Brewery Company Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 821 ; 153 FCR 11 where Sundberg J said at [40]: 
 The reason for the qualified exemption of food from GST is well-known, and was common ground. It was the political compromise reached in order that the GST scheme might become law. The distinction drawn in Totalizator between an exemption directed at a particular person or body and one that encourages a particular activity is applicable here. It is true, as Cascade says, that item 13 is not directed at a particular person or body. But nor is it concerned to encourage any particular activity. It is not intended to encourage the production of beverages or ingredients of any kind. It was the result of a political deal that gave partial exemption to food. In the case of the beverage component of food, the result was that the beverage or an ingredient therefore would be exempt if it was of a kind marketed principally as food for infants or invalids. In accordance with Totalizator , there is no occasion to approach the meaning of 'infant' or 'invalids' in any manner other than by according the words their ordinary meaning.

According to the Commissioner, the applicant is not correct in submitting that the expressions 'juices of fruits' is an anachronism resulting from the history of the sales tax legislation and that the meaning intended to be conveyed by the draftsman by the use of that expression was the same as 'fruit juice'. It follows, the Commissioner argued, that 'juices of fruits' and 'fruit juice' are not synonymous and any purported trade meaning as to 'fruit juice' in the beverage industry (being the definition in the Foods Standard Code ) has no relevance to the interpretation of the expression 'juices of fruits'.

In any event, the Commissioner submitted, the definition of 'fruit juice' in the Food Standards Code could not have had significance in construing the expression 'juices of fruits' in circumstances where that expression was used in taxing legislation many years before the Food Standards Code was introduced. The expression 'juices of Australian fruits' had been a term used in the wholesale sales tax since the 1930s and 1940s.

I have come to the conclusion, not without some hesitation, that the Commissioner's approach is to be preferred because it better promotes the legislative purpose of the GST Act in relation to food , namely, that the exemption or GST-free status is a qualified one where, as Sundberg J pointed out in Cascade Brewery , the legislature seems to have drawn the line between exempt and non-exempt food supplies in favour of food that is fresh, natural or unprocessed. The fact that one can readily point to some specific exclusions to this line in the GST Act does not reduce or mitigate against its force as an overall observation or conclusion.

For these reasons, I am of the view that the Edenvale products are not non-alcoholic beverages. While their respective alcohol content by volume is low, it owes its existence to an infused process of fermentation rather than a naturally occurring one.

The application must be dismissed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>CIC Insurances Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1997) 187 CLR 384</tocase>
<text>It is the same with the GST Act. As Hill J (with whom Stone and Allsop JJ agreed) said in H P Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553 at [44] : 
 It is clear, both having regard to the modern principles of interpretation as enunciated by the High Court in cases such as CIC Insurance Limited v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1997) 187 CLR 384 and s 15AA of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) that the Court will prefer an interpretation of a statute which would give effect to the legislative purpose, as opposed to one that would not. This requires the Court to identify that purpose, both by reference to the language of the statute itself and also any extrinsic material which the Court is authorised to take into account.

He submitted that in such circumstances a construction of the legislation that promotes the purpose of the GST Act is to be preferred to one which would not promote the purpose; see s 15AA of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth); CIC Insurances Ltd v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1997) 187 CLR 384. He submitted that confining non-alcoholic beverages to those beverages which do not acquire their alcohol content through human intervention (i.e., by using yeast to cause or accelerate fermentation), and contain an amount of alcohol by volume which is considered insignificant, best promotes the legislative purpose of the GST Act in respect of food namely, that GST-free status is confined to 'basic' food.

As the alcoholic content of the applicant's Edenvale products arises through human intervention those products are not, according to the Commissioner, non-alcoholic even though the level of that content may be low after the de-alcoholisation process has taken place.

By reference to the same principle of construction, the applicant contended that a non-alcoholic beverage meant a beverage other than an alcoholic beverage; this gives meaning and operation to Items 11 and 12 and is therefore to be preferred.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Agfa-Gevaert Ltd [1996] HCA 36 ; (1996) 186 CLR 389</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1996/36.html</AustLII>
<text>His Honour observed at [24] that it was common ground that the phrase 'juices of fruits' does not have a trade meaning. At [36] he referred to what was said by a Full Court of this Court in Zeroz Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 35 ATR 349 at 357, 'if there is no trade usage then a fortiori the expression must be used in its ordinary English sense'. But P &amp; N in that case, like the applicant in this case, made a number of submissions which, at the risk of doing the applicant a disservice, went something like this: 
(1) While the phrase 'juices of fruits' does not have a trade meaning, the phrase is synonymous with 'fruit juice' and that term had a trade meaning as defined in the Food Standards Code .
 
(The Food Standards Code is a reference to the Australia New Zealand Food Standards Code as defined in the Food Standards Australia New Zealand Act 1991 (Cth). The Food Standards Code , standard 2.6.1, with respect to fruit juice and vegetable juice, defined fruit juice or vegetable juice as the liquid portion, with or without pulp, obtained from fruit or vegetables respectively and in the case of citrus fruit, other than lime, the endocarp only of the fruit and included products that had been concentrated and later reconstituted with water to a concentration consistent with that of the undiluted juice from which it had been made. At [21] and [22], his Honour observed that it was common ground that the fruit drinks supplied by P &amp; N met the Food Standards Code requirements. It was also common ground that P &amp; N fruit drinks contained non-fruit based additives, vitamins and minerals or used processing aids within the limits permitted by the Food Standards Code . The evidence was that the fruit drinks contained 98% - 99% fruit juice and 1% - 2% additives and processing aids not directly derived from fruit.)
 
(2) In substituting a trade meaning of 'fruit juice' for 'juices of fruits' that has no trade meaning, reliance was placed on Collector of Customs v Agfa-Gevaert Ltd [1996] HCA 36 ; (1996) 186 CLR 389 where the phrase 'silver dye bleach reversal process' in a tariff concession had no trade meaning but the words 'silver dye bleach process' did. The High Court held that the Tribunal's construction of the composite phrase by reference to the trade meaning of the lesser phrase and the ordinary meaning of the word 'reversal', involved no error of law. The submission, by parity of reasoning, was that in the Item 11 composite phrase 'wholly of juices of fruits', the word 'wholly' should be given its ordinary meaning and the words 'juices of fruits' (in both Items 11 and 12) should be given the trade meaning for 'fruit juice'.
 
(3) That having adopted the Foods Standards Code prior to the introduction of the GST Act, its concepts were well known to the Parliament and that it may be taken to have had regard to them in respect of a law dealing with the exemption of food.

As to the reliance on Agfa-Gevaert in substituting a trade meaning of 'fruit juice' for 'juices of fruits', his Honour said at [27]: 
 Agfa-Gevaert is quite different from the instant circumstances. The composite phrase was not one that had an obvious ordinary meaning. Nor did the lesser phrase. In those circumstances, the lesser [phrase] aided the proper interpretation of the composite one. Here, the words that comprise the composite phrase are words of common parlance, even if they are oddly arranged, and there is not the same need to call in aid a trade meaning.

As to the submission that Parliament may be taken to have adopted the Food Standards Code and its trade meaning of 'fruit juice' in respect of a law dealing with the exemption of food, his Honour said at [34] [35]: 
 [34] ... Furthermore, the extrinsic materials do not suggest that parliament adopted a trade meaning in the Foods Standards Code . If it had, one would have expected it to have departed from the unusual [phrase] "juices of fruits". The extrinsic material makes it clear, in my view, that parliament intended to bring within the scope of the amendments to the GST Act the exemptions or concessions in relation to food products under the existing sales tax legislation. Hence the adoption of the phraseology in Item 11. 

 
 [35] Parliament was invoking its past legislation rather than adopting a trade meaning of other words in an industry code that the past legislation preceded. The harking back to a phrase used in the sales tax legislation in 1935 leads to the irresistible conclusion that parliament was carrying forward some of the exemptions and concessions with respect to food in the sales tax legislation and not attributing to the phrase any trade meaning of a different term in the Foods Standards Code . There was no logical reason for parliament, in introducing a new tax, to adopt a code intended to ensure that the public was protected from poorly prepared food. The 2 objects are clearly distinct. If parliament had intended to adopt the code, one would have expected a collocation such as: "non-alcoholic carbonated beverages produced wholly in accordance with the Foods Standards Code ". 

 ANALYSIS 
 Relevant Principles of Statutory Construction</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Taxation v Bargwanna [2009] FCA 620</tocase>
<text>Recently, in Commissioner of Taxation v Bargwanna [2009] FCA 620 (12 June, 2009), in the course of considering whether a fund was applied for the purposes for which it was established within s 50-60 of the Income Tax Assessment Act 1997 (Cth), I said (at [28]): 
 It can be accepted that where Parliament has enacted legislation to encourage a particular activity, for example, legislation which gives particular concessions to the mining or petroleum industries, the legislation must be construed so as to promote Parliament's purpose and not so as to detract from that purpose: Totalizator Agency Board v Commissioner of Taxation (1996) 69 FCR 311 at 323A per Hill J, with whom Tamberlin J and Sundberg J agreed. Thus an exemption which exists for the purpose of encouraging, rewarding or protecting some class of activity is to be given a liberal rather than a narrow construction and application: see Commissioner of Taxation v Reynolds Australia Alumina Ltd (1987) 18 FCR 29 at 35 per Beaumont J and at 46 47 per Burchett J; Diethelm Manufacturing Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [1993] FCA 437 ; (1993) 44 FCR 450 at 457 per French J. But in the case of a provision which confers an exemption upon a particular kind of body or fund which meets certain requirements, Parliament's purpose is not promoted by construing the provision in a manner favourable to the body or fund referred to in it: see TAB at 323C per Hill J. Indeed, there is much to be said for the view that the privileged status of exemption from income tax on the income of a fund which aspires to that status demands strict adherence to the requirements that must be met before that status is conferred ...</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Pepsi-Cola Metropolitan Bottling Co Inc (1967) 10 FLR 101 </tocase>
<text>Item 36(3), specifically Item 36(3)(d)(ii), was the subject of further consideration by the Supreme Court of New South Wales in Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Pepsi-Cola Metropolitan Bottling Co Inc (1967) 10 FLR 101, when it was in the following terms: 
 Fruit juice products, namely:- 

 
(a) Concentrates for the making of non-alcoholic beverages, being concentrates which consist of not less than 25% by volume of juices of Australian fruits;
 
 
(b) Cordials for the making of non-alcoholic beverages, and preparations for use in the flavouring of foods, being cordials or preparations which consist of not less than 25% by volume of 
 
 
(i) juices of Australian fruits
 
(ii) a mixture of concentrates and juices of Australian fruits and water, being a mixture of a strength not less than the natural strength of the juices;
 
(iii) juices of Australian fruits and a mixture of concentrates of juices of Australian fruits and water, being a mixture of a strength not less than the natural strength of the juices;
 
 
(c) Non-alcoholic beverages consisting wholly of juices of Australian fruits or vegetables (including herbage)
 
 
(d) Non-alcoholic carbonated beverages containing not less than 5% by volume of :
 
 
(i) juices of Australian fruits
 
(ii) a mixture of concentrates of juices of Australian fruits and water, being a mixture of a strength not less than the natural strength of the juices;
 
(iii) juices of Australian fruits and a mixture of concentrates of juices of Australian fruits and water, being a mixture of a strength not less than the natural strength of the juices;' 
 
(Emphasis added).

I have referred at some length to the Pepsi-Cola case because of the reliance placed on it by counsel for the applicant for his submission, or the first alternative of it, that the Edenvale products consist of the requisite measures by volume of the juices of fruits at the point of supply notwithstanding the anterior fermentation and de-alcoholisation processes. For reasons I will come to, reliance on the Pepsi-Cola case for that submission, in my view, is flawed.

Immediately before the commencement of the GST Act, Item 11 of the Table found expression in Item 13(4) of the Second Schedule to the E &amp; C Act 1992 : 'non-alcoholic carbonated beverages, if they consist wholly of juices of fruits or vegetables', and Item 12 of the Table found expression in Item 13(3) of the Second Schedule to the E &amp; C Act, although the bar for the volume requirement of juices of fruits or vegetables was set much lower: 'non-alcoholic non-carbonated beverages, if they consist of at least 25% by volume of juices of fruits or vegetables'. In both cases they were subject to 10% sales tax rather than being, as under the GST Act, tax free.

The applicant relies on the decisions in Faulding and Pepsi-Cola in support of its position.

The decision in Pepsi-Cola does not create any tension with such a conclusion because the item in question in that case used the word 'containing', not 'consisting', a distinction apparent to Macfarlan J in the extract from his judgment (at 106) reproduced at [51] above and the reason why, in that case, his Honour concluded that in using the word 'containing', rather than 'consisting', 'Parliament [was] only concerned to ensure that an Australian fruit juice in the prescribed quantity shall have been used in the carbonated beverage' (at 109).

An additional impediment for the applicant in the case of the carbonated Edenvale product is that Item 11 of the Table requires that it must consist 'wholly' of juices of fruit and even in the applicant's case, it admitted that the product only consists of 97.3% by volume of juices of fruit. However, the applicant argues that the additional volume largely consists of rainwater added to the beverage as part of the reconstitution process and, accordingly, the rainwater should properly be regarded as part of the grape juice. Once an adjustment is made for the rainwater (and taken into account as being part of the juices of fruits, but see [96] below), the product consists of 99.1% by volume of juices of fruits. It is then suggested by the applicant that the de minimis rule should apply to the remainder.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Federal Commissioner of Taxation v F.H. Faulding &amp; Co Ltd [1950] HCA 42 ; (1950) 83 CLR 594</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1950/42.html</AustLII>
<text>In Federal Commissioner of Taxation v F H Faulding &amp; Co Limited [1950] HCA 42 ; (1950) 83 CLR 594 , the High Court of Australia had occasion to consider Item 36(3) of, what was then, the First Schedule to the E &amp; C Act, when it was in the following terms: 'Essences, concentrates and cordials, consisting wholly or principally of juices of Australian fruits, for the making of non-alcoholic beverages; non-alcoholic beverages consisting wholly of Australian fruits'. It is important to an appreciation of what was said in the Full High Court and its relevance to this case, that the framework of the issues which came up to the Full Court be understood. It was not disputed that the liquids sold were cordials nor that they were cordials for the making of non-alcoholic beverages or that they contained substantial quantities of juices of Australian fruits. They did not consist wholly of such juices. The only controversy was as to whether they consisted principally of juices of Australian fruits. In the present case, there is a real issue as to whether the beverage supplied consists of 'juices of fruits'.

At first instance, Rich J held that the words 'consisting ... principally of juices of Australian fruits' referred to the characteristic feature of the cordial to what his Honour described as the element giving it its name and nature, its essential properties.

On appeal to the Full Court, Latham CJ said (at 596 597): 
 The difficulty which this view meets is found in the words "consisting of". The reference is not to the principal characteristic of the cordial considered as a cordial, but to the content of the cordial. In the phrase "consisting wholly or principally of juice of Australian fruits" the word "wholly" necessarily requires the application of a quantitative standard. The word "principally" must, in my opinion, be similarly construed. Words might have been used which would have given the exemption to any fruit juice cordial in which the whole or larger part of the fruit juice used was juice of Australian fruits. So also an exemption might have been given to all cordials in which any flavouring of Australian fruit juice was contained. Possibly some such provision would represent the result which Parliament intended to achieve. But the court cannot speculate upon such a matter. It must construe the words actually used. The word "consisting" refers to the physical components of the cordial, and the questions to be asked in determining whether the exemption is applicable are (1) Does this cordial consist wholly of juices of Australian fruits? In the present case the answer to this question must be--No: (2) Does it consist principally of juices of Australian fruits? The answer to this question must also, in my opinion, be--No, because the words "consisting principally of" must be read as referring to quantity expressed in terms of either volume or weight of the substance of the cordial and cannot be read as referring to that constituent of the cordial, whatever its proportionate quantity, which gives to the cordial its distinctive flavour as a cordial.

Paragraph (d) was added to Item 36(3) by Act No. 71 of 1957. Significantly, it uses the word 'containing', not the words 'consisting' or 'consist of' as in paras (a), (b) and (c). After referring to what was said by Latham CJ in Faulding in the extract reproduced at [49] above, Macfarlan J said (at 106): 
 If, indeed, as the High Court in Faulding's case appears to have thought, the use of the word "consisting" means "constituents actually existing at the time of tax and physically identifiable by reference to the qualities prescribed for exemption" the word "containing" might be thought to have been intended to have a different meaning. Were it not so, then one might reasonably have expected that the word "consisting" would have been used again. This, indeed, was an argument submitted on behalf of the defendant, while learned counsel for the plaintiff distinctly accepted that his argument on this point meant that there existed an identity of meaning for the words "contain" and "consist".

After referring to various dictionary definitions of the word 'containing' to which he was taken by counsel for both parties, his Honour said (at 107 109): 
 The word "containing" qualifies the words "non-alcoholic carbonated beverage". In other words, the mixture which is afterwards described in par. (ii) must be contained in the non-alcoholic carbonated beverage and in the present case, the beverage being carbonated when it is in the bottle for sale by retail, the contents of that bottle must then contain the "mixture". It is therefore necessary to inquire what is contained in the bottle at that time. 

 
 ... 

 
 In my opinion all the circumstances lead to the conclusion that, subject to certain matters I will mention in a moment, Parliament is only concerned to insure that an Australian fruit juice in the prescribed quantity shall have been used in the carbonated beverage. In my opinion, the meaning of the word "contain" must be understood in this way.

The applicant relies on the decisions in Faulding and Pepsi-Cola in support of its position.

The decision in Faulding is entirely consistent with the Commissioner's position. In Faulding , the majority (which included Latham CJ) concluded, in the context of Item 36(3), that the word 'consisting' refers to a quantitative test in terms of the constituents actually existing at the time of supply and physically identifiable by reference to the qualities prescribed for exemption. Latham CJ said (at 597): 
 [T]he words 'consisting principally of' must be read as referring to quantity expressed in terms of either volume or weight of the substance of the cordial and cannot be read as referring to that constituent of its cordial, whatever its proportionate quantity, which gives to the cordial its distinctive flavour as a cordial.

So too must the de-alcoholised wine under consideration consist of at least 90% (or wholly, for the carbonated Edenvale product) of 'juices of fruits' and not merely be derived from those products while retaining some of their character.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>H P Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/126.html</AustLII>
<text>It is the same with the GST Act. As Hill J (with whom Stone and Allsop JJ agreed) said in H P Mercantile Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2005] FCAFC 126 ; (2005) 143 FCR 553 at [44] : 
 It is clear, both having regard to the modern principles of interpretation as enunciated by the High Court in cases such as CIC Insurance Limited v Bankstown Football Club Ltd (1997) 187 CLR 384 and s 15AA of the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth) that the Court will prefer an interpretation of a statute which would give effect to the legislative purpose, as opposed to one that would not. This requires the Court to identify that purpose, both by reference to the language of the statute itself and also any extrinsic material which the Court is authorised to take into account.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Network Ten Pty Ltd v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 14 ; (2004) 218 CLR 273</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/14.html</AustLII>
<text>In Network Ten Pty Ltd v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 14 ; (2004) 218 CLR 273 at [11] the High Court affirmed the observations made by McHugh J in Newcastle City Council v GIO General Ltd [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85 at 42 that: 
 [A] court is permitted to have regard to the words used by the legislature in their legal and historical context and, in appropriate cases, to give them a meaning that will give effect to any purpose of the legislation that can be deduced from that context.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Newcastle City Council v GIO General Ltd [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/53.html</AustLII>
<text>In Network Ten Pty Ltd v TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 14 ; (2004) 218 CLR 273 at [11] the High Court affirmed the observations made by McHugh J in Newcastle City Council v GIO General Ltd [1997] HCA 53 ; (1997) 191 CLR 85 at 42 that: 
 [A] court is permitted to have regard to the words used by the legislature in their legal and historical context and, in appropriate cases, to give them a meaning that will give effect to any purpose of the legislation that can be deduced from that context.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>P &amp; N Beverages Australia Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] NSWSC 338 ; (2007) 210 FLR 202 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2007/338.html</AustLII>
<text>Item 11, but not Item 12, of the Table came up for judicial consideration in P &amp; N Beverages Australia Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2007] NSWSC 338 ; (2007) 210 FLR 202. The plaintiff taxpayer (P &amp; N) manufactured carbonated fruit drinks by reconstituting a fruit concentrate with water and non-fruit based additives. It sought declarations that supplies of the fruit drinks were exempt from GST in reliance on Item 11 of the Table. The Supreme Court of New South Wales (Gzell J) dismissed the claim for relief and in doing so rejected a number of submissions concerning the phrase 'juices of fruits', at least three of which were repeated by the applicant in the present case.

Such a legislative purpose is also discernable both from the circumstances in which the amendments arose, and the context in which Items 11 and 12 appear in the Table. This was recognised by Gzell J in P &amp; N at [32]: 
 There is a lot to be said for the submission of the Commissioner that when the compromise was made for a qualified exemption for food to ensure the passage of legislation, as Sundberg J points out Cascade Brewery Co Pty Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 821 ; (2006) 153 FCR 11 at [40] , the legislature seems to have drawn the line between exempt and non-exempt food supplies in favour of food that is fresh, natural or unprocessed. For example, the beverages that are not included in the table to cl 1 of Sch 2 of the GST Act and are therefore not GST-free, include soft drinks and cordials, flavoured milk (Item 2) and flavoured soy milk and rice milk (Item 4). The only carbonated beverages that are GST-free are those satisfying Item 11, and water (Item 14), is GST-free only if it is non-carbonated and without any other additives. 

 First Issue: Whether the Edenvale products consist wholly (Item 11) or at least 90% by volume (Item 12) of the juices of fruits?
 The phrase 'juices of fruits'

It is common ground that the phrase 'juices of fruits' does not have a trade meaning. The applicant submitted, through the line of reasoning rejected in P &amp; N (see [55] and [58] above), that 'juices of fruits' is 'fruit juice' as defined in the Food Standards Code , which defines 'fruit juice' to include products that have been concentrated and later reconstituted with water to a concentration consistent with that of the undiluted juice from which it was made. The Commissioner did not accept that 'juices of fruits' is synonymous with 'fruit juice', the first step in the applicant's line of reasoning. Insofar as the applicant called in aid the second column of the Table, the Commissioner submitted that this was not permissible: s 182-15 of the GST Act. According to the Commissioner, there is no ambiguity, obscurity or manifestly absurd or unreasonable result flowing from the ordinary meaning of the text, taking into account its context and the purpose or object underlying it, which would mandate such recourse: see subs 182-10(2).

The Commissioner submitted that the phrase 'juices of fruits', not having a trade meaning, is to be interpreted according to its ordinary English meaning. In this regard 'juice' is relevantly defined to mean: 
The Oxford English Dictionary :
 
 
 1.a. The watery or liquid part of vegetables or fruits, which can be expressed or extracted; commonly containing the characteristic flavour and other properties. 

 
 Macquarie Dictionary :
 
 
 1. the liquid part of plant or animal substance ... 

 
 2. any extracted liquid, especially from a fruit

According to the Commissioner, the ordinary meaning of 'juices', in the context of the GST Act, suggests that 'juices of fruits' is the liquid extracted from those fruits. The extraction process entails that the juice originally formed 'part' of the fruit and, therefore, the juice is extracted from the fruit through some mechanical process such as pressing or crushing.

Similarly in the current proceedings the Food Standards Code could have no relevance for the same reason. As Gzell J said in P &amp; N at [33]: 
 ... The phrase had its origin in 'juices of Australian fruits' in 1935 well before the gazettal of the Foods Standards Code in 1987. It was unreal to say that the code preceded the GST Act when the origin of Item 11 in the table in cl 1 of Sch 2 preceded the code.

I agree with the Commissioner's submissions. In my view, they compel the conclusion that the phrase 'juices of fruits' in Items 11 and 12 of the Table is to have its ordinary English meaning of being confined to juices extracted from fruits and does not extend to 'fruit juice' in the wider embrace of that term in trade parlance, assisted or unassisted by the definition in the Food Standards Code. The phrase 'consist of'

The carbonated Edenvale product will only qualify for GST-free status under Item 11 of the Table if it ' consist[s] wholly of juices of fruits' at the supply point and the non-carbonated Edenvale products will only qualify for GST-free status under Item 12 of the Table 'if they consist of at least 90% by volume of juices of fruits' at the supply point (emphasis added).

Subject to the de minimis rule applying, which was not argued in P &amp; N , Gzell J stated that 'wholly' meant 100%: 
At [36] [37]:
 
 [I]n my view ... Item 11 must be construed according to its ordinary meaning. 

 
 ... 

 
 The concession by P &amp; N that the word 'wholly' meant 100% was a proper one. Items 10 and 12 in the table to cl 1 in Sch 2 of the GST Act are, respectively, concentrates for making non-alcoholic beverages if the concentrates consist of at least 90% by volume of juices of fruit, and non-alcoholic non-carbonated beverages if they consist of at least 90% by volume of juices of fruit or vegetables. In that context, 'wholly' must, in my view, mean 100%. 

 
And later at [41]:
 
 It follows from my finding that any trade meaning derived from the Foods Standards Code is not attracted by the legislation and my rejection of the argument that the ordinary meaning of the phrase 'wholly of juices of fruits' encompasses fruit drinks with non-fruit based additives, that P &amp; N must fail. Having accepted that to qualify for exemption, the fruit drinks of P &amp; N must consist of 100% of juices of fruits, the introduction of even 1 % of non-fruit based additives means that the exemption is not attracted. No de minimis argument was raised on behalf of P &amp; N.

The de minimis rule does not arise for consideration in the current context unless the rainwater that is added to the beverage is regarded as being part of the 'juices of fruit'. Dr Brooke-Taylor in his further report (annexed to his affidavit sworn on 2 April 2009) describes the product to which the 'reconstitution' (by way of the addition of rainwater) is made as follows (at para (3)): 
 [W]here a fruit juice product which contained ethanol was concentrated by a process of evaporation that removed the ethanol and the concentrate was later reconstituted with water to a concentration consistent with that of undiluted juice product, the resulting product would be fruit juice within the scope of the definition in Standard 2.6.1. (Emphasis added.) 

 
The reference to 'fruit juice product' in the above extract is not a reference to either the fruit juice concentrate or low sugar juice, but to the de-alcoholised base wine. The adding of rainwater to the de-alcoholised base wine would not constitute the reconstitution of juices of fruit as the de-alcoholised base wine at that point in the process (even if it was 'concentrated') does not constitute juices of fruit.

In any event, the de minimis rule has no scope to operate in circumstances where the clear intent of the legislature was that the product consist of 100% of the juices of fruit. This is made clear by the fact that in the case of Items 10 and 12 of the Table the requirement imposed by the legislature for the volume of juices of fruit was 'at least 90%' which had the effect of allowing the beverage to include non fruit based additives without the loss of the exemption.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>The Wik Peoples v The State of Queensland (1996) 187 CLR 1</tocase>
<text>Reference was also made to the canon of statutory construction that terms used in statutes that are in pari materia should be given the same meaning unless there is a clear indication to the contrary: Attorney-General v Prince Ernest Augustus of Hanover [1957] AC 436 at 461 per Viscount Simonds; The Wik Peoples v The State of Queensland (1996) 187 CLR 1 at 171 per Gummow J.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Zeroz Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 35 ATR 349</tocase>
<text>His Honour observed at [24] that it was common ground that the phrase 'juices of fruits' does not have a trade meaning. At [36] he referred to what was said by a Full Court of this Court in Zeroz Pty Ltd v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 35 ATR 349 at 357, 'if there is no trade usage then a fortiori the expression must be used in its ordinary English sense'. But P &amp; N in that case, like the applicant in this case, made a number of submissions which, at the risk of doing the applicant a disservice, went something like this: 
(1) While the phrase 'juices of fruits' does not have a trade meaning, the phrase is synonymous with 'fruit juice' and that term had a trade meaning as defined in the Food Standards Code .
 
(The Food Standards Code is a reference to the Australia New Zealand Food Standards Code as defined in the Food Standards Australia New Zealand Act 1991 (Cth). The Food Standards Code , standard 2.6.1, with respect to fruit juice and vegetable juice, defined fruit juice or vegetable juice as the liquid portion, with or without pulp, obtained from fruit or vegetables respectively and in the case of citrus fruit, other than lime, the endocarp only of the fruit and included products that had been concentrated and later reconstituted with water to a concentration consistent with that of the undiluted juice from which it had been made. At [21] and [22], his Honour observed that it was common ground that the fruit drinks supplied by P &amp; N met the Food Standards Code requirements. It was also common ground that P &amp; N fruit drinks contained non-fruit based additives, vitamins and minerals or used processing aids within the limits permitted by the Food Standards Code . The evidence was that the fruit drinks contained 98% - 99% fruit juice and 1% - 2% additives and processing aids not directly derived from fruit.)
 
(2) In substituting a trade meaning of 'fruit juice' for 'juices of fruits' that has no trade meaning, reliance was placed on Collector of Customs v Agfa-Gevaert Ltd [1996] HCA 36 ; (1996) 186 CLR 389 where the phrase 'silver dye bleach reversal process' in a tariff concession had no trade meaning but the words 'silver dye bleach process' did. The High Court held that the Tribunal's construction of the composite phrase by reference to the trade meaning of the lesser phrase and the ordinary meaning of the word 'reversal', involved no error of law. The submission, by parity of reasoning, was that in the Item 11 composite phrase 'wholly of juices of fruits', the word 'wholly' should be given its ordinary meaning and the words 'juices of fruits' (in both Items 11 and 12) should be given the trade meaning for 'fruit juice'.
 
(3) That having adopted the Foods Standards Code prior to the introduction of the GST Act, its concepts were well known to the Parliament and that it may be taken to have had regard to them in respect of a law dealing with the exemption of food.

In this regard, in Zeroz , reference had been made by the taxpayer to the Food Standards Code (as it then existed) for the purpose of ascertaining the trade meaning of a term in the sales tax legislation. A Full Court of this Court said at 354 and 359 360: 
 One might wonder at the relevance in interpreting a statutory provision first incorporated in legislation effective from 20 September 1985 (when Item 23 of the 1935 Act was introduced by Act No 145 of 1985) of a standard not published until 1987 and on the evidence still the subject of consideration and alteration until that date. [p 354] 

 
 ... 

 
 It is hard to accept that a public document still in the process of formulation and not yet published at the time the word "yoghurt" was introduced into the sales tax law should be seen as the source of a definition of the expression "yoghurt" in statute passed years earlier. [p 359 360]</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>