<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Borcherdt v Department of Families, Housing, Community Service and Indigenous Affairs [2009] FCA 62 (3 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/62.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321</tocase>
<text>One thing which s 44 does not confer upon this Court is jurisdiction to embark upon an appeal by way of a rehearing of the merits or otherwise of conclusions of fact to which the Tribunal came in its assessment of the material before it. A series of decisions of the Full Court of this Court earlier this decade have emphasised the centrality of the need for a question of law for there to be jurisdiction to entertain a proceeding under s 44 of the AAT Act. I refer in that regard to the decisions of the Full Court in Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321 and Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522.

When one turns to examine the so-called questions of law in para 2 of the notice of appeal those which appear immediately under the heading "The applicant says that", save perhaps for the first dot point, do not, it seems to me, raise a question of law. Neither, for that matter, do any of the other propositions which appear in the balance of para 2. Rather, they seem to me to have a quality which was described in Etheridge's case at para 29 in these terms: 
 The invitation which is inherent in the above question, to examine the evidence and other material before the Tribunal is sufficient to show that it is not a question of law within the meaning of s 44(1) of the AAT Act (see Birdseye at para 18). It is at best a mixed question of law and fact. Looked at more critically, it is open to be understood as an invitation to the Court to conduct a rehearing with respect to important aspects of the controversy that came before the Tribunal for determination. This is not an invitation that the Court may accept on an appeal under s 44(1) of the AAT Act.

The first dot point does not, in terms, pose a question but rather makes a statement: 
 The Tribunal erred in the application of s 17 of the Social Security Act as applying to the facts of the matter as presented and in accordance with the applicable standard of proof.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280</tocase>
<text>In what has proved to be an influential decision, a Full Court of this Court, in Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287, set out five general propositions which emerge from the cases as to what can amount to a question of law. The fifth of those propositions was this: 
 The only question whether facts fully found fall within the provisions of a statutory enactment properly construed is generally a question of law. 

Authority is then cited for that proposition. Their Honours then qualify that fifth proposition by reference to remarks that Fullagar J made in Hayes v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1956] HCA 21 ; (1956) 96 CLR 47 and, at page 288 observe:
 
 This principle is qualified when a statute uses words according to their ordinary meaning and the question is whether the facts found fall within those words. Where it is reasonably open to hold that they do then the question whether they do or not is one of fact.

In the way in which the first dot point in para 2 is cast, and having regard to what was said in Pozzolanic in relation to the fifth principle and its qualification, it seems to me that there is not a raised question of law. There was material before the Tribunal which admitted of a conclusion that the payment that came to be made to Mr Borcherdt, pursuant to the order of the court, was one which was made in respect of economic loss. The Tribunal's reasoning in that regard does not seem to me to be in any way illogical, or made unreasonably in the sense of being unsupported by any material before it.

Mr Borcherdt's contract arguments depended, in the end, on an acceptance by the Tribunal of the proposition that, irrespective of whether or not he had validly rescinded an agreement struck on 27 November, there had nonetheless been an acceptance of a repudiation by the defendant and its representatives and a payment pursuant to an offer which he had made in that letter. That is not an inference which necessarily arises as the only inference to be drawn. The Tribunal was not, in any way, obliged to accept that as a necessary conclusion of fact on the material at hand.

It is to be noted that there is an absence of correspondence between the terms of Mr Borcherdt's letter as to bases of payment and payees and the form in which the order of the court, on 29 February, came to be made. Even then if my conclusion, that there is not raised in the notice of appeal a question of law is incorrect, and that the case is to be viewed as one in which the question propounded is whether the Tribunal was entitled to conclude on the evidence before it that the payment was one within the terms of the statute, it seems to me that the Tribunal was reasonably entitled to reach that conclusion.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/27.html</AustLII>
<text>One thing which s 44 does not confer upon this Court is jurisdiction to embark upon an appeal by way of a rehearing of the merits or otherwise of conclusions of fact to which the Tribunal came in its assessment of the material before it. A series of decisions of the Full Court of this Court earlier this decade have emphasised the centrality of the need for a question of law for there to be jurisdiction to entertain a proceeding under s 44 of the AAT Act. I refer in that regard to the decisions of the Full Court in Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321 and Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Department of Social Security v A'Beckett [1990] FCA 332 ; (1990) 26 FCR 349</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1990/332.html</AustLII>
<text>A mischief to which s 1169 and s 1170 , read in conjunction with the definitions of "compensation" and "compensation affected payment" is directed, was stated by reference to an earlier, but nonetheless analogous, regime in social security legislation by von Doussa J in Secretary of the Department of Social Security v A'Beckett [1990] FCA 332 ; (1990) 26 FCR 349 at 359-360 in these terms: 
 In my opinion, the intention of the scheme for preclusion and recovery is to prevent double payments from arising from that part of a payment by way of compensation, which is fairly to be characterised as damages or compensation for an incapacity for work.

The intention of the scheme, in my opinion, remains to prevent double payments arising from payments which are to be characterised as compensation affected payments, and in that way, not to burden the revenue, ie, the Australian taxpayer, with the making of payments to an individual who has already received a compensation affected payment from another source.

The Tribunal was, in my opinion, well entitled, having regard to the facts that it found, to reach the conclusion that the payment received by Mr Borcherdt was a compensation affected payment. In particular, the Tribunal was, in my opinion, well entitled to reach the conclusion that the payment was one that fell within the terms of s 17(2)(c) , and that it was one which was made wholly or partly "in respect of" lost earnings or lost capacity to earn, resulting from personal injury. Those words, "in respect of," as they appear in s 17(2) , have a role to play. In that regard, reference might usefully be had to earlier decisions of this Court in respect of words used in an analogous way in earlier statutory regimes and, in particular, the observation made by von Doussa J in A'Beckett's case as to the policy which lies behind the statutory regime is instructive.

In the absence of very singular evidence as to the construction of a settlement payment and the heads of damage for which it is made, where one sees a payment made in the course of either compensation or personal injuries proceedings, which is made as a result of those proceedings having been brought, it would ordinarily be an unremarkable conclusion, where the proceedings have included a claim in respect of loss of earning capacity or incapacity to undertake work, to reach a conclusion that the payment was one which had been made wholly or partly "in respect" of earnings or lost capacity to earn, resulting from personal injury.

However one approaches this case, either on the basis that it is not truly an appeal on the question of law, or even if, perhaps, with respect, charitably, one approaches it on the basis that raised for consideration is whether the Tribunal was entitled on the facts that it found to reach the conclusion that it did, there is no merit in the appeal. It follows, necessarily, that it must be dismissed.
 I certify that the preceding thirty-five (35) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Logan. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 10 February 2009
 
 Counsel for the Appellant: The Appellant appeared in person 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Minter Ellison 
 Date of Hearing: 3 February 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 3 February 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/62.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hayes v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1956] HCA 21 ; (1956) 96 CLR 47</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1956/21.html</AustLII>
<text>In what has proved to be an influential decision, a Full Court of this Court, in Collector of Customs v Pozzolanic Enterprises Pty Ltd (1993) 43 FCR 280 at 287, set out five general propositions which emerge from the cases as to what can amount to a question of law. The fifth of those propositions was this: 
 The only question whether facts fully found fall within the provisions of a statutory enactment properly construed is generally a question of law. 

Authority is then cited for that proposition. Their Honours then qualify that fifth proposition by reference to remarks that Fullagar J made in Hayes v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1956] HCA 21 ; (1956) 96 CLR 47 and, at page 288 observe:
 
 This principle is qualified when a statute uses words according to their ordinary meaning and the question is whether the facts found fall within those words. Where it is reasonably open to hold that they do then the question whether they do or not is one of fact.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>