<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wik and Wik Way Native Title Claim Group v State of Queensland [2009] FCA 789 (29 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/789.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2000] FCA 1443</tocase>
<text>The Co-Existence Agreement cast obligations upon the traditional owners to commence determination applications under the Act in respect of any or all parts of the ILUA area, according to the terms and conditions of the Co-Existence Agreement. Such an application is regarded as a conforming application for the purposes of that agreement. Prior to the parties entering into the Co-Existence Agreement, a claim group on behalf of the Wik and Wik Way Peoples commenced a native title determination before the National Native Title Tribunal on 24 March 1994 and proceedings QG6001 of 1998 were commenced in this Court by which a determination of native title rights and interests was sought. Determination application QUD6001 of 1998 came to be described as the main application. Three determinations of the subsistence of native title rights and interests have been made by the Court in relation to the land and waters the subject of the claim in the main application. The first determination was made by Justice Drummond on 3 October 2000 in respect of what was described as Part A of the determination application. Part A of the application was confined to lands that had always been unallocated Crown lands or lands that had only ever been subject to forms of title granted for the benefit of Aboriginal peoples ( Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2000] FCA 1443). Part B of the application comprised the balance of the lands and waters of the claim area, which contained lands held under pastoral and mining titles. The parties to the main application negotiated, through mediation processes, a resolution of the Part B claim and on 13 October 2004, Justice Cooper made two determinations of the native title rights and interests of the Wik and Wik Way Peoples in respect of those lands and waters ( Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2004] FCA 1306).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2004] FCA 1306</tocase>
<text>The Co-Existence Agreement cast obligations upon the traditional owners to commence determination applications under the Act in respect of any or all parts of the ILUA area, according to the terms and conditions of the Co-Existence Agreement. Such an application is regarded as a conforming application for the purposes of that agreement. Prior to the parties entering into the Co-Existence Agreement, a claim group on behalf of the Wik and Wik Way Peoples commenced a native title determination before the National Native Title Tribunal on 24 March 1994 and proceedings QG6001 of 1998 were commenced in this Court by which a determination of native title rights and interests was sought. Determination application QUD6001 of 1998 came to be described as the main application. Three determinations of the subsistence of native title rights and interests have been made by the Court in relation to the land and waters the subject of the claim in the main application. The first determination was made by Justice Drummond on 3 October 2000 in respect of what was described as Part A of the determination application. Part A of the application was confined to lands that had always been unallocated Crown lands or lands that had only ever been subject to forms of title granted for the benefit of Aboriginal peoples ( Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2000] FCA 1443). Part B of the application comprised the balance of the lands and waters of the claim area, which contained lands held under pastoral and mining titles. The parties to the main application negotiated, through mediation processes, a resolution of the Part B claim and on 13 October 2004, Justice Cooper made two determinations of the native title rights and interests of the Wik and Wik Way Peoples in respect of those lands and waters ( Wik Peoples v State of Queensland [2004] FCA 1306).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Members of the Yorta Yorta Aboriginal Community v State of Victoria (2002) 214 CLR 422</tocase>
<text>Orders made under s 87 of the Act take effect not only inter-parties in the resolution of the claims made in the proceedings but represent an independent judicial determination, in the exercise of the judicial power of the Commonwealth, that may be asserted, as a matter of law, against anyone. Although the Act by s 223(1)(c) in part defines native title or native title rights and interests by reference to the rights and interests recognised by the common law of Australia, a determination of native title expresses the recognition and protection of those rights and interests in relation to land and waters defined and described in s 223 of the Act which find their origin in traditional laws and customs, not the Act ( Members of the Yorta Yorta Aboriginal Community v State of Victoria (2002) 214 CLR 422 at [75] and [76] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Hayne JJ).

A number of considerations are to be taken into account in determining whether the proposed orders appear appropriate to the Court. First, the Act recognises and encourages the resolution of applications by mediation, negotiation and ultimately agreement without the need for a hearing and the assessment of evidence and fact-finding by the Court necessary in the course of a resolving a controversy. Second, the Court will be concerned to understand and place emphasis upon whether the agreement is freely made on an informed basis by all parties and whether the parties are represented by experienced independent lawyers. In the case of a State party representing the public interest, the Court will consider whether appropriate consideration has been given to the issues raised by the proposed consent determination. Third, so far as the State is concerned, the Court recognises that a State has access to its own archival material and generally has had a long period of engagement with Aboriginal communities and is therefore likely to be familiar with the historical arrangements within those communities. Fourth, although it is not necessary for the Court to consider the body of material that would be available to it in the course of a contested hearing, the Court ought to have regard to sufficient material which is capable of demonstrating that the agreement and the proposed orders are "rooted in reality" (" Native Title A Constitutional Shift? ", University of Melbourne Law School, JD Lecture Series, Chief Justice French, 24 March 2009).

In that sense, the Court ought to be satisfied that the proposed orders are prima facie appropriate in order to satisfy the test under s 87(2) of the Act.

Section 94A of the Act requires that an order for a determination of native title must set out details of the matters mentioned in s 225 of the Act which must be read together with s 223 of the Act. These sections give meaning to the terms "determination of native title" and "native title" and "native title rights and interests". In Members of the Yorta Yorta Aboriginal Community v State of Victoria (supra) at [76], Gleeson CJ, Gummow and Hayne JJ treated the statutory elements contained in s 223 as central. The mandatory requirements for a determination of native title are these. The native title rights and interests must be communal, group or individual. They must be rights and interests in relation to land or waters. They must be possessed under the traditional laws acknowledged and the traditional customs observed by Aboriginal peoples; Aboriginal people by their law and customs must have a connection with the land or waters; and the native title rights and interests must be recognised by the common law of Australia.

I am satisfied that the anthropological material demonstrates that the Wik and Wik Way Peoples are descended from a society of Aboriginal people who were in occupation of the land and waters of the Determination Area at sovereignty and who formed a society united by their acknowledgement and observance of a normative body of traditional laws, customs and beliefs. Through their continued acknowledgement and observance of these normative laws and customs, the Wik and Wik Way Peoples have, since sovereignty, maintained a connection with the Determination Area. I am satisfied that the content of those native title rights and interests which derive from the practice of traditional laws and customs have been identified and established through the anthropological material. The agreement provides for consent orders entirely consistent with the anthropological material.

I am satisfied the proposed orders address each of the elements of s 225 of the Act. Thus, I am satisfied that the orders appear appropriate in accordance with s 87 of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>