<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2009] FCA 794 (30 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/794.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321</tocase>
<text>The meaning of "a question of law" in s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) has been considered by this Court in a number of cases. In addition, the requirements in the Rules of Court as to the contents of a notice of appeal under s 44(1) (see O 53 rr 2, 3 and Form numbered 55A) have been considered. It is not necessary for me to discuss the cases: Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321; Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 ; Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522 ; HBF Health Funds Inc v Minister for Health and Ageing [2006] FCAFC 34 ; (2006) 149 FCR 291.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Collector of Customs (NSW) v Brian Lawlor Automotive Pty Ltd [1979] FCA 21 ; (1979) 41 FLR 338</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1979/21.html</AustLII>
<text>This statement of the relevant principles is correct: Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1979] AATA 179 ; (1979) 24 ALR 577 ; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Brian Lawlor Automotive Pty Ltd [1979] FCA 21 ; (1979) 41 FLR 338. Deledio does not provide support for the applicant's submission. Ground 7</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/27.html</AustLII>
<text>The meaning of "a question of law" in s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) has been considered by this Court in a number of cases. In addition, the requirements in the Rules of Court as to the contents of a notice of appeal under s 44(1) (see O 53 rr 2, 3 and Form numbered 55A) have been considered. It is not necessary for me to discuss the cases: Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321; Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 ; Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522 ; HBF Health Funds Inc v Minister for Health and Ageing [2006] FCAFC 34 ; (2006) 149 FCR 291.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1979] AATA 179 ; (1979) 24 ALR 577</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/1979/179.html</AustLII>
<text>This statement of the relevant principles is correct: Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1979] AATA 179 ; (1979) 24 ALR 577 ; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Brian Lawlor Automotive Pty Ltd [1979] FCA 21 ; (1979) 41 FLR 338. Deledio does not provide support for the applicant's submission. Ground 7</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Ettridge v TransAdelaide [1997] SASC 6753</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//sa/SASC/1997/6753.html</AustLII>
<text>The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law "on the grounds of duplicity". There is no question of duplicity in the present proceeding and the case to which the applicant referred, Ettridge v TransAdelaide [1997] SASC 6753 , is not relevant to any issue before me. No doubt there were a number of issues before the Deputy President, but there is no reason to think that the proceeding miscarried because of the number of issues the parties were required to address. Ground 19

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in refusing to allow the applicant "to run his case in the way that he wished".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297</tocase>
<text>The respondent's response to this contention is, in my opinion, correct. The applicant claimed that his conditions were related to service through a connection with his duodenal ulcer and, in those circumstances, the Tribunal was required to determine whether his duodenal ulcer was relevantly related to his defence service: Langley v Repatriation Commission [1993] FCA 299 ; (1993) 43 FCR 194 at 201 per Lockhart and Beazley JJ; McKenna v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 323 ; (1999) 86 FCR 144 at 151 [20] per Branson, Sundberg and Kenny JJ. The previous acceptance of liability for the applicant's duodenal ulcer under the Compensation (Commonwealth Government Employees) Act 1971 (Cth) did not prevent the Tribunal from considering this matter. The cases to which the applicant referred do not support his argument ( Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297 and Power v Comcare (1998) 89 FCR 514). Ground 2

In order to explain this ground, it is necessary to set out the following passages from the Deputy President's reasons. 
 "As mentioned in paragraph 6 above, during the hearing I raised a concern as to jurisdiction, because the application for review refers to the decision of the VRB instead of the decision of the Commission. To overcome my concern I suggested that Mr Kowalski should lodge a fresh application to review the decision of the Commission. He did this, and I made an order, with the consent of the Commission, to extend the time for making the new application. I then gave directions to the effect that the existing proceedings and the new proceedings should be heard together, with the evidence in each case being treated as evidence in the other. 

 
 ...
 As there is no issue of jurisdiction in relation to the new application, and in view of the conclusion I have reached, it is not necessary for me to determine whether I had jurisdiction by virtue of the original application. However, on reflection, I think that the original application was sufficient." 

 
That reasoning is correct and nothing was said by the Full Court in Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297 which suggests that the Deputy President's approach was erroneous.
 Ground 10

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that the error that the applicant had made by referring to the Board's decision in his application for review instead of referring to the respondent's decision was an obvious error that should not have rendered his application for review ineffective, or deprived the Tribunal of its jurisdiction or power to make a determination on his application for review. The passage of which the applicant complains is as follows: 
 "In the present case Mr Kowalski clearly intended to invoke the jurisdiction of this tribunal because he was dissatisfied with the decision of the VRB. The error he made in referring to the wrong decision was an obvious error, and should not render his application for review ineffective."

That approach favours the applicant and it is not at all clear why he is attacking it. In any event, the approach does not involve error. Ground 11

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal failed to consider the applicant's many contentions and his contention based on the changed "ability to work classification" from FE on enlistment to HO on discharge to which the Tribunal referred in paragraph 29 of its reasons "because the facts found in those par's [sic] clearly meet the evidentiary burden on the applicant to adduce sufficient evidence to establish his claims, therefore, Jarvis DP erred in law in finding that the conditions for which the applicant was claiming a disability pension were not caused by his compulsory National Service in the Army".

I have set out above the Deputy President's conclusions in the penultimate paragraph in his reasons (see [29]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Giannarelli v Wraith [1988] HCA 52 ; (1988) 165 CLR 543</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/52.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant referred to various passages in the transcript of the hearing before the Tribunal (pages 194, 195, 197, 201, 202, 204, 205, 208, 209, 210, 214, 216, 217, 218, 219, 220 and 233-345). He also referred to the decision in Giannarelli v Wraith [1988] HCA 52 ; (1988) 165 CLR 543.

I have considered the transcript and I am satisfied that the Deputy President did no more than control the proceeding before him in an appropriate manner. Ground 20

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in refusing to allow the applicant to ask witnesses relevant questions and to cross-examine witnesses in the witness box. This ground seems to be formulated on the assumption that an applicant is entitled to ask whatever question he or she thinks is appropriate. That is not the case. The Deputy President has the power to disallow irrelevant, scandalous or oppressive questions. In my opinion, the Deputy President did no more than exercise appropriate control in respect of the conduct of the application for review. Ground 21</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>HBF Health Funds Inc v Minister for Health and Ageing [2006] FCAFC 34 ; (2006) 149 FCR 291</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2006/34.html</AustLII>
<text>The meaning of "a question of law" in s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) has been considered by this Court in a number of cases. In addition, the requirements in the Rules of Court as to the contents of a notice of appeal under s 44(1) (see O 53 rr 2, 3 and Form numbered 55A) have been considered. It is not necessary for me to discuss the cases: Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321; Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 ; Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522 ; HBF Health Funds Inc v Minister for Health and Ageing [2006] FCAFC 34 ; (2006) 149 FCR 291.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2008] FCA 1970</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1970.html</AustLII>
<text>Before concluding these reasons, I record the fact that the applicant asked me to disqualify myself from hearing this appeal. I declined to do so: Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2008] FCA 1970. Leave to appeal from my decision was refused: Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2009] FCA 47. 
 I certify that the preceding one hundred and twenty-eight (128) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 30 July 2009
 
 The Applicant appeared in person. 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr G Camilos 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 22 January 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 July 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/794.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2009] FCA 47</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2009/47.html</AustLII>
<text>Before concluding these reasons, I record the fact that the applicant asked me to disqualify myself from hearing this appeal. I declined to do so: Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2008] FCA 1970. Leave to appeal from my decision was refused: Kowalski v Repatriation Commission [2009] FCA 47. 
 I certify that the preceding one hundred and twenty-eight (128) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Besanko. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 30 July 2009
 
 The Applicant appeared in person. 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr G Camilos 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Hearing: 22 January 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 30 July 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/794.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Langley v Repatriation Commission [1993] FCA 299 ; (1993) 43 FCR 194</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/299.html</AustLII>
<text>The respondent's response to this contention is, in my opinion, correct. The applicant claimed that his conditions were related to service through a connection with his duodenal ulcer and, in those circumstances, the Tribunal was required to determine whether his duodenal ulcer was relevantly related to his defence service: Langley v Repatriation Commission [1993] FCA 299 ; (1993) 43 FCR 194 at 201 per Lockhart and Beazley JJ; McKenna v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 323 ; (1999) 86 FCR 144 at 151 [20] per Branson, Sundberg and Kenny JJ. The previous acceptance of liability for the applicant's duodenal ulcer under the Compensation (Commonwealth Government Employees) Act 1971 (Cth) did not prevent the Tribunal from considering this matter. The cases to which the applicant referred do not support his argument ( Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297 and Power v Comcare (1998) 89 FCR 514). Ground 2</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/398.html</AustLII>
<text>The Deputy President referred to the definition of "hypertension" in clause 2(b) and the definition of the expression "being obese" in clause 8. He also referred to the meaning of "clinical onset" as articulated in the cases ( Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750).

It is clear from the Deputy President's reasons that he was aware of the blood pressure reading in March 1973 and that he took it into account (at [67]-[68]). I also agree with the respondent's submission that the Deputy President's analysis of the authorities ( Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750) was correct and it was open to him to find that the clinical onset of the applicant's hypertension was 24 August 1984. Ground 4</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>McDonald v Director-General of Social Security [1984] FCA 57 ; (1984) 1 FCR 354</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1984/57.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion, the respondent's submission, that where the decision-maker cannot be satisfied on the evidence before it of the existence of a necessary fact for the claim to succeed, then it cannot decide the claim in the claimant's favour, is correct ( McDonald v Director-General of Social Security [1984] FCA 57 ; (1984) 1 FCR 354 at 358-359 per Woodward, Northrop and Jenkinson JJ).

Deledio and O'Brien do not support the applicant's submission. Ground 12

The contention raised in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in placing the onus of proof on the applicant. I have read the paragraphs in the Tribunal's reasons to which the applicant referred ([123], [125], [127] and [128]). I do not think that the Tribunal placed the onus of proof on the applicant. The Deputy President said: 
 "However, except to this extent, it remained necessary for Mr Kowalski to adduce evidence or documents in support of his claim. Proceedings in this tribunal are administrative proceedings, and where (as in the present matter) the relevant legislation does not impose, expressly or by implication, an onus of proof, neither party bears such an onus: Bushell (supra) at 425. Nevertheless, it remains necessary for a party asserting facts to adduce evidence which would support a finding by the tribunal that those facts exist: McDonald v Director-General of Social Security [1984] FCA 57 ; (1984) 1 FCR 354 , at 358."

There is no error in the Deputy President's reasoning and this ground of appeal must be rejected. Ground 38

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in failing to determine, as a preliminary matter, whether the applicant suffered from the claimed psychiatric conditions in accordance with s 120(4) of the Act. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. In any event, nothing was put to support the ground of appeal. Ground 39</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>McKenna v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 323 ; (1999) 86 FCR 144</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/323.html</AustLII>
<text>The respondent's response to this contention is, in my opinion, correct. The applicant claimed that his conditions were related to service through a connection with his duodenal ulcer and, in those circumstances, the Tribunal was required to determine whether his duodenal ulcer was relevantly related to his defence service: Langley v Repatriation Commission [1993] FCA 299 ; (1993) 43 FCR 194 at 201 per Lockhart and Beazley JJ; McKenna v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 323 ; (1999) 86 FCR 144 at 151 [20] per Branson, Sundberg and Kenny JJ. The previous acceptance of liability for the applicant's duodenal ulcer under the Compensation (Commonwealth Government Employees) Act 1971 (Cth) did not prevent the Tribunal from considering this matter. The cases to which the applicant referred do not support his argument ( Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297 and Power v Comcare (1998) 89 FCR 514). Ground 2</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Oliver v Repatriation Commission [2002] AATA 408</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/aat/2002/408.html</AustLII>
<text>Oliver v Repatriation Commission [2002] AATA 408 (" Oliver ") was a decision of a senior member of the Tribunal. The issue was whether the death of a veteran was due to war service and, in particular, whether the veteran satisfied factor (d) of the relevant principles concerning ischaemic heart disease. The senior member had particular evidence before him and he made certain findings of fact. The circumstances and evidence before the Deputy President in this case were different and Oliver is therefore of no assistance to the resolution of the present matter.

I do not think the Deputy President erred. To link the applicant's hypertension with service through a service-related obesity there was a need to show that the applicant was obese at the time of the clinical onset of hypertension and the applicant had plainly not shown that. As I have said, the reference to Oliver does not assist the applicant. Ground 3

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that the date of clinical onset of the applicant's hypertension was 24 August 1984 and that there was no evidence that the applicant had a pre-existing condition of hypertension that worsened. This ground does not raise a question of law.

The contention in this ground of appeal is that, in view of the Tribunal's decision in Oliver , the Tribunal erred in law in determining that there was no evidence that the applicant was suffering from dyslipidaemia as defined in the SoP prior to the clinical onset of the ischaemic heart disease and that the applicant's claim was not supported by factor 6(f). This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law.

The Deputy President's findings were open to him on the evidence before him. Oliver does not support the applicant's submission for reasons previously given. Ground 8

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that it was unnecessary for the Tribunal to consider whether the material before it raised a connection between the ischaemic heart disease and his compulsory National Service in the Army within the meaning of s 120B(3)(a) of the Act. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law.

The Deputy President was not required to consider the matter in s 120B(3)(a) in circumstances where he was satisfied that s 120B(3)(b) had not been met. Oliver and Deledio do not support the applicant's submission for reasons previously given. Ground 9

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that the decision under review as varied by the Board was affirmed. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Again, Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien do not support the applicant's submissions. Ground 13

This ground of appeal is without content. No particulars are provided as to the test said to have been applied by the Tribunal, the reasons it was the wrong test, the details of the Tribunal's application of the SoPs and the statements made from the bar table. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Reference was made to Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien but, for reasons previously given, those cases do not advance the applicant's submission. Ground 14</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Power v Comcare (1998) 89 FCR 514</tocase>
<text>The respondent's response to this contention is, in my opinion, correct. The applicant claimed that his conditions were related to service through a connection with his duodenal ulcer and, in those circumstances, the Tribunal was required to determine whether his duodenal ulcer was relevantly related to his defence service: Langley v Repatriation Commission [1993] FCA 299 ; (1993) 43 FCR 194 at 201 per Lockhart and Beazley JJ; McKenna v Repatriation Commission [1999] FCA 323 ; (1999) 86 FCR 144 at 151 [20] per Branson, Sundberg and Kenny JJ. The previous acceptance of liability for the applicant's duodenal ulcer under the Compensation (Commonwealth Government Employees) Act 1971 (Cth) did not prevent the Tribunal from considering this matter. The cases to which the applicant referred do not support his argument ( Fitzmaurice v Repatriation Commission (1989) 19 ALD 297 and Power v Comcare (1998) 89 FCR 514). Ground 2</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2002/750.html</AustLII>
<text>The Deputy President referred to the definition of "hypertension" in clause 2(b) and the definition of the expression "being obese" in clause 8. He also referred to the meaning of "clinical onset" as articulated in the cases ( Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750).

It is clear from the Deputy President's reasons that he was aware of the blood pressure reading in March 1973 and that he took it into account (at [67]-[68]). I also agree with the respondent's submission that the Deputy President's analysis of the authorities ( Lees v Repatriation Commission [2002] FCAFC 398 ; (2002) 125 FCR 331 ; Repatriation Commission v Cornelius [2002] FCA 750) was correct and it was open to him to find that the clinical onset of the applicant's hypertension was 24 August 1984. Ground 4</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1998/391.html</AustLII>
<text>Repatriation Commission v Deledio [1998] FCA 391 ; (1998) 83 FCR 82 (" Deledio ") was a decision of the Full Court of this Court. The case concerned the proper approach to the application of s 120(1) and (3) of the Act. By contrast, this case involved the application of s 120(4) and s 120B(3) of the Act. Deledio is therefore of no direct assistance to the resolution of the issues in this case.

This statement of the relevant principles is correct: Drake v Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs [1979] AATA 179 ; (1979) 24 ALR 577 ; Collector of Customs (NSW) v Brian Lawlor Automotive Pty Ltd [1979] FCA 21 ; (1979) 41 FLR 338. Deledio does not provide support for the applicant's submission. Ground 7

The Deputy President was not required to consider the matter in s 120B(3)(a) in circumstances where he was satisfied that s 120B(3)(b) had not been met. Oliver and Deledio do not support the applicant's submission for reasons previously given. Ground 9

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that the decision under review as varied by the Board was affirmed. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Again, Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien do not support the applicant's submissions. Ground 13

This ground of appeal is without content. No particulars are provided as to the test said to have been applied by the Tribunal, the reasons it was the wrong test, the details of the Tribunal's application of the SoPs and the statements made from the bar table. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Reference was made to Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien but, for reasons previously given, those cases do not advance the applicant's submission. Ground 14

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law by failing to follow and rely upon the decision of this Court in Deledio . Deledio is not relevant for reasons previously given. Ground 18

Again, this ground of appeal does not raise a question of law, and I agree with the respondent's submission that the Deputy President did not find clinical onset of anxiety disorder in 1973 and therefore there is no proper basis for this contention. Again, Deledio does not support the applicant's submission for the reasons previously given. Ground 24

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in failing to find that the clinical onset of the applicant's anxiety disorder was 20 August 1973. Again, the applicant makes reference to the fact that the applicant was prescribed Librax on 20 August 1973.

This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. I have previously dealt with the merits of the ground in relation to ground 22. Ground 25</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/192.html</AustLII>
<text>The meaning of "a question of law" in s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) has been considered by this Court in a number of cases. In addition, the requirements in the Rules of Court as to the contents of a notice of appeal under s 44(1) (see O 53 rr 2, 3 and Form numbered 55A) have been considered. It is not necessary for me to discuss the cases: Birdseye v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 76 ALD 321; Repatriation Commission v Hill [2002] FCAFC 192 ; (2002) 69 ALD 581 ; Comcare v Etheridge [2006] FCAFC 27 ; (2006) 149 FCR 522 ; HBF Health Funds Inc v Minister for Health and Ageing [2006] FCAFC 34 ; (2006) 149 FCR 291.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1985/10.html</AustLII>
<text>Repatriation Commission v O'Brien [1985] HCA 10 ; (1985) 155 CLR 422 (" O'Brien ") was a decision of the High Court and it involved the interpretation of s 47(2) of the Repatriation Act 1920 (Cth) which subsection provided for a test of whether the determining body was satisfied beyond reasonable doubt that there were insufficient grounds for granting the claim. An observation by Gibbs CJ, Wilson and Dawson JJ (at 430) on the facts of that case (upon which the applicant relied) is of no assistance to the resolution of the issues in this case. Ground 1

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal had no jurisdiction or power to make a determination with respect to the applicant's "previously accepted compensable defence-caused duodenal ulcer" where neither the respondent nor the Board had made a determination with respect to that matter.

The Deputy President's finding was as follows: 
 "In summary, the SoP does not uphold the contention that the ulcer was, on the balance of probabilities, connected with Mr Kowalski's service, and I am not satisfied that his duodenal ulcer arose out of or was attributable to his eligible defence service, or that it would not have occurred but for that service."

The contention in this ground of appeal is that the Tribunal erred in law in determining that the decision under review as varied by the Board was affirmed. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Again, Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien do not support the applicant's submissions. Ground 13

This ground of appeal is without content. No particulars are provided as to the test said to have been applied by the Tribunal, the reasons it was the wrong test, the details of the Tribunal's application of the SoPs and the statements made from the bar table. This ground of appeal does not raise a question of law. Reference was made to Oliver , Deledio and O'Brien but, for reasons previously given, those cases do not advance the applicant's submission. Ground 14</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>