<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>City of Swan v Lehman Bros Australia Ltd [2009] FCA 784 (23 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/784.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>AWB Limited v Cole [No 2] (2006) 233 ALR 453</tocase>
<text>In AWB Limited v Cole [No 2] (2006) 233 ALR 453 at 460-463 [26]-[40], Young J reviewed the authorities from which (without reciting the authorities to which his Honour referred) I have taken the following principles: 
 (1) As a general rule the starting point is that all issues of fact and law should be determined at the one time.
 
 (2) A party seeking the determination of separate questions must satisfy the Court that it is "just and convenient" for the order to be made. The order must be made on concrete facts, either established or agreed, for the purpose of quelling a controversy between the parties so as to produce a conclusive or final judicial decision on the issue, which is of a real, not hypothetical, importance to the determination of the controversy.
 
 (3) There are special problems where the separate issue involves a mixed question of fact and law, although it may still be able to be decided as a separate issue. However, care must be taken in precisely formulating the question and specifying the facts upon which it is to be decided.
 
 (4) The Court must have all relevant matters before it as a precondition of it being asked to exercise its discretion if the separate question involves the grant or refusal of declaratory relief.
 
 (5) It may still be appropriate to determine a separate question even if it will not resolve all the issues, provided that there is a strong prospect that the parties will agree upon the result when the core of the dispute has been decided or if the decision will obviate unnecessary and expensive hearings of other questions.
 
 (6) Generally speaking an issue will not be appropriate for separate determination if it is simply one of two or more alternative ways in which an applicant or plaintiff frames its case and its determination would leave other significant issues unresolved.
 
 (7) It is relevant to consider whether:</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/9.html</AustLII>
<text>Lehman Australia and the administrators argued that questions 1 and 2 were founded on the false assumption that apart from cl 7.1, the plaintiffs had an unqualified right, superior to Lehman Australia itself, to conduct, prosecute or resolve litigation with that company's insurers. It argued that the construction of cl 11.5 was not a matter of controversy and that it related only to claims against Lehman Australia being released. It argued that this construction would defeat the plaintiffs' contention that cl 11.5 was wider than its apparent terms. (As appears above, Lehman Bros disputes this construction.) Lehman Australia also argued that if the impugned provisions could not be supported by Pt 5.3A of the Act, then the deed would still be valid but those clauses would not be an operative part of the deed. Lehman Australia argued that if question 6 were answered "no", it would not follow that the deed would then become ineffective or void. Accordingly it argued that question 6 was of no utility to resolve any issue. Lehman Australia referred to the dangers of separate issues discussed in Tepko Pty Ltd v Water Board [2001] HCA 19 ; (2001) 206 CLR 1 and Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334.

In Woolcock Street 216 CLR at 524-525 [7] Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ stressed the importance of recognising that there may be difficulties in using procedures for separate issues in cases in which it is necessary to consider developing, as distinct from applying, common law principles and continued: 
 "The dangers of developing common law principle against an artificially constricted body of fact are self-evident. That is why, in some cases, even if the parties join in asking a court to determine a question separate from trial of the facts, it may be prudent for the court to decline to answer the question presented as being one which it is inappropriate to answer ( Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334 at 357-358 [51] - [53] ). Indeed, as Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd illustrates ( Bass [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334 at 359 [56] . See also Malika Holdings Pty Ltd v Stretton [2001] HCA 14 ; (2001) 204 CLR 290 at 308-309 [61] .), in some circumstances to answer a question may be contrary to the judicial process. If the question is answered, it is important to identify any limitations which the procedure adopted may impose on the breadth of any principle that is to be identified as having been established or applied."

If some or all of the separate questions can be answered they may prove decisive and, in any event, will clarify the future extent of the controversy so as to facilitate its efficient management. As Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow, Hayne and Callinan JJ pointed out in Bass 198 CLR at 356 [48], a crucial difference between an advisory opinion and a declaratory judgment "... is the fact that an advisory opinion is not based on a concrete situation and does not amount to a binding decision raising a res judicata between parties". What the plaintiffs seek will lead to a binding decision on a concrete situation, at least on the issues of construction and, if the questions as to power or any of them are answered in their favour, will be likely further to narrow the controversy considerably.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd [2008] FCAFC 38 ; (2008) 166 FCR 494</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/38.html</AustLII>
<text>Essentially, the evidence will be relevant to whether the meaning of the expression "Claims" when used in the impugned clauses extends to any claims that might be made against Lehman companies other than Lehman Australia, notwithstanding the definition of "Claims" in the deed. While, no doubt, substantial arguments will be used to illuminate the rival constructions, little evidence will be relevant to placing the Court into the position that a reasonable person in the position of the parties would have occupied so as to be able to understand the genesis of the transaction, the background, context and circumstances by reference to which the deed was resolved to be made: Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 178-180 [36] , [41] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ; Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289 at 292-293 [9] - [12] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd [2008] FCAFC 38 ; (2008) 166 FCR 494 at 510-512 [50] - [53] where I considered the authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Henderson v Pioneer Homes Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 55 ; (1979) 142 CLR 294</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1979/55.html</AustLII>
<text>For these reasons, I am satisfied that I should order a hearing under O 29 r 2 that the separate questions be heard before the rest of the proceedings. In my opinion, the questions of construction and (if possible) power should be decided by a Full Court exercising the original jurisdiction so that, the balance of the proceedings can be tried more efficiently and expeditiously. I propose to reserve the separate questions for hearing by a Full Court pursuant to s 25(6) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). The power of a single judge sitting in the Court's original jurisdiction to reserve a question for consideration by a Full Court can only be exercised in a matter where an appeal would lie to a Full Court: s 25(6). An appeal, by leave, from an order answering the separate questions, would lie to a Full Court under s 24(1) and (1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act . Therefore, under s 25(6) of the Act, a single judge has power to reserve for consideration and determination by a Full Court, those questions and the question of whether any amendment or addition to those questions is necessary and, if so ought be made, so as to enable the Full Court to determine the proper construction of cll 7, 9 and 11 of the deed and their validity: Henderson v Pioneer Homes Pty Ltd [1979] HCA 55 ; (1979) 142 CLR 294 at 298-299 per Stephen, Mason and Wilson JJ.

There is an important public interest in the prompt determination of these proceedings so that the administrators and the creditors know their positions, particularly if the deed is invalid or the impugned provisions are found to be void or are varied. In addition, the administration of Lehman companies in other jurisdictions and the positions of insurers may be affected by the final decision of this Court. Answers to these questions will provide a suitable means of moving more promptly and efficiently to the final resolution of this complex matter.

The parties should prepare an agreed bundle of documents constituting the factual matrix together with the deed and prepare a timetable for submissions. I will direct the parties to bring in short minutes to give effect to these reasons.
 I certify that the preceding forty-six (46) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Rares. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 23 July 2009
 
 Counsel for the First, Second and Third Plaintiffs: N C Hutley SC, A Coleman and D Sulan 
 
 Solicitor for the First, Second and Third Plaintiffs: Piper Alderman 
 
 Counsel for the First, Second and Third Defendants: B A Coles QC and P Kulveski 
 
 Solicitor for the First, Second and Third Defendants: Clayton Utz 
 
 Counsel for the Fourth Defendant: D Williams SC and J Castaldi 
 
 Solicitor for the Fourth Defendant: Dibbs Barker 
 
 Counsel for the Fifth Defendant: T F Bathurst QC and E Hyde 
 
 Solicitor for the Fifth Defendant: Jones Day 
 
 Counsel for the Amicus Curiae D Barnett 
 
 Solicitor for the Amicus Curiae Australian Securities and Investments Commission 
 Date of Hearing: 3, 10 and 21 July 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 23 July 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/784.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/63.html</AustLII>
<text>Lehman Bros was joined as the fifth defendant at its request on 16 July 2009. It argued that it wished to lead unspecified further evidence as to the surrounding circumstances of the making of the deed, as well as evidence that would support its rectification claim. It did not elaborate how this evidence could go beyond the evidence of the factual matrix on which the parties to the proceedings may rely on issues of construction, in order to establish the relevant common intention of the parties, being the creditors (including Lehman Asia), Lehman Australia and the administrators: cf Pukallus v Cameron [1982] HCA 63 ; (1982) 180 CLR 447 per Wilson J at 452, with whom Gibbs CJ agreed at 448, per Brennan J at 456.

Lehman Bros argued that if the questions were answered favourably to the plaintiffs then one of two results followed, either the deed was not a deed of company arrangement and fell outside the scope of Pt 5.3A or, it fell within the scope of the Part but was void. In the latter case remedial options in Pt 5.3A were available and there would be substantial arguments that the Court should exercise a discretion to give effect to the wish of the majority of creditors by value and number voting at the meetings. On the other hand, Lehman Bros accepted that if the plaintiffs were correct and the Court could not make any orders remedying the deed, it would seek termination of the deed, as well as the plaintiffs, since its rights were prejudiced. Lehman Bros argued that it had only agreed to subordinate its debt in the proposed arrangement in order to obtain the releases.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2002/5.html</AustLII>
<text>Essentially, the evidence will be relevant to whether the meaning of the expression "Claims" when used in the impugned clauses extends to any claims that might be made against Lehman companies other than Lehman Australia, notwithstanding the definition of "Claims" in the deed. While, no doubt, substantial arguments will be used to illuminate the rival constructions, little evidence will be relevant to placing the Court into the position that a reasonable person in the position of the parties would have occupied so as to be able to understand the genesis of the transaction, the background, context and circumstances by reference to which the deed was resolved to be made: Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 178-180 [36] , [41] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ; Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289 at 292-293 [9] - [12] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd [2008] FCAFC 38 ; (2008) 166 FCR 494 at 510-512 [50] - [53] where I considered the authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Tepko Pty Ltd v Water Board [2001] HCA 19 ; (2001) 206 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/19.html</AustLII>
<text>Lehman Australia and the administrators argued that questions 1 and 2 were founded on the false assumption that apart from cl 7.1, the plaintiffs had an unqualified right, superior to Lehman Australia itself, to conduct, prosecute or resolve litigation with that company's insurers. It argued that the construction of cl 11.5 was not a matter of controversy and that it related only to claims against Lehman Australia being released. It argued that this construction would defeat the plaintiffs' contention that cl 11.5 was wider than its apparent terms. (As appears above, Lehman Bros disputes this construction.) Lehman Australia also argued that if the impugned provisions could not be supported by Pt 5.3A of the Act, then the deed would still be valid but those clauses would not be an operative part of the deed. Lehman Australia argued that if question 6 were answered "no", it would not follow that the deed would then become ineffective or void. Accordingly it argued that question 6 was of no utility to resolve any issue. Lehman Australia referred to the dangers of separate issues discussed in Tepko Pty Ltd v Water Board [2001] HCA 19 ; (2001) 206 CLR 1 and Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334.

In Tepko (2001) 206 CLR at 55 [168]-[170], Kirby and Callinan JJ observed in their dissenting judgment that the attractions of trials of issues rather than of cases in their totality are often more chimerical than real. They noted that common experience demonstrated that saving in time and expense were often illusory, particularly when they overlapped within parties' preparation for other factual matters. They said that a party might feel aggrieved if their case were knocked out on the trial of a preliminary or single issue, and might suspect that the abbreviated course had been adopted to meet the court's, rather than the parties', interests. And they noted that there was a potential for further appeals, particularly if the separate issue having been decided one way initially were reversed on appeal and the matter sent back for a full trial of the whole of the issues.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/52.html</AustLII>
<text>Essentially, the evidence will be relevant to whether the meaning of the expression "Claims" when used in the impugned clauses extends to any claims that might be made against Lehman companies other than Lehman Australia, notwithstanding the definition of "Claims" in the deed. While, no doubt, substantial arguments will be used to illuminate the rival constructions, little evidence will be relevant to placing the Court into the position that a reasonable person in the position of the parties would have occupied so as to be able to understand the genesis of the transaction, the background, context and circumstances by reference to which the deed was resolved to be made: Toll (FGCT) Pty Ltd v Alphapharm Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 52 ; (2004) 219 CLR 165 at 178-180 [36] , [41] per Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Callinan and Heydon JJ; Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust v South Sydney City Council [2002] HCA 5 ; (2002) 186 ALR 289 at 292-293 [9] - [12] per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; Bowen Investments Pty Ltd v Tabcorp Holdings Ltd [2008] FCAFC 38 ; (2008) 166 FCR 494 at 510-512 [50] - [53] where I considered the authorities.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Woolcock Street Investments Pty Ltd v CDG Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 16 ; (2004) 216 CLR 515</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/16.html</AustLII>
<text>Lehman Bros argued that a number of judgments tended to suggest that, in analogous statutory contexts, courts had allowed companies involved in re-organisations or arrangements to stipulate that their creditors give releases to third parties. Lehman Bros argued that it will be necessary to consider the whole factual context in order to be able to come to a conclusion about whether, in the circumstances established at a trial, the impugned provisions could have been included in the deed. It referred to the caution expressed about separate questions by Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ in Woolcock Street Investments Pty Ltd v CDG Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 16 ; (2004) 216 CLR 515 at 524-525 [7] , noting that those remarks were made where all the parties had agreed to the use of the separate question, unlike the present case.

Lehman Bros argued that there may be relevant facts, such as the existence of joint or joint and several liability on the part of one or more of the Lehman companies with Lehman Australia, that could affect how the Court would determine the extent of the power under Pt 5.3A to authorise the making of a deed to bind creditors in respect of their rights against third parties. Lehman Bros argued that because of the need to have regard to a variety of potential factual contexts, it was impractical to order a separation of issues concerning the ambit of the power in Pt 5.3A for a deed to bind creditors, in the absence of the full context of all of the circumstances. It contended that it wished to advance evidence to show a connection between, and justifying, the exercise of the power to make the impugned clauses and the circumstances of the case. Lehman Bros argued that that would involve a factual investigation into the degree of connection between the impugned provisions and the source of power in Pt 5.3A , not suitable for investigation in a separate question. It also contended that evidence could support the inclusion of the impugned provisions in relation to potential claims for contribution or indemnity that it or other Lehman entities might have against Lehman Australia were they sued by one of the plaintiffs or another dissenting creditor.

The plaintiffs emphasised in reply that the only beneficiaries of the wider release in cl 11.5 were Lehman companies. They contended that the separate questions still had utility. They argued that the issue whether there was power under Pt 5.3A to give effect to the impugned clauses in the deed should be determined on the basis that if the Court came to the conclusion that further evidence than the deed itself and the relevant matrix of fact in which the creditors' meeting came to resolve that it be executed could affect the outcome, then those questions should not be answered. Nonetheless, the plaintiffs argued that the issue of power under Pt 5.3A was a stark one and that the questions were capable of receiving an affirmative answer. They argued that if there were no power, the onus to demonstrate that there was no prejudice would then be on any defendants who sought to uphold a validation of the deed or its amendment under the provisions in Pt 5.3A of the Act on which they had relied.

In Woolcock Street 216 CLR at 524-525 [7] Gleeson CJ, Gummow, Hayne and Heydon JJ stressed the importance of recognising that there may be difficulties in using procedures for separate issues in cases in which it is necessary to consider developing, as distinct from applying, common law principles and continued: 
 "The dangers of developing common law principle against an artificially constricted body of fact are self-evident. That is why, in some cases, even if the parties join in asking a court to determine a question separate from trial of the facts, it may be prudent for the court to decline to answer the question presented as being one which it is inappropriate to answer ( Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334 at 357-358 [51] - [53] ). Indeed, as Bass v Permanent Trustee Co Ltd illustrates ( Bass [1999] HCA 9 ; (1999) 198 CLR 334 at 359 [56] . See also Malika Holdings Pty Ltd v Stretton [2001] HCA 14 ; (2001) 204 CLR 290 at 308-309 [61] .), in some circumstances to answer a question may be contrary to the judicial process. If the question is answered, it is important to identify any limitations which the procedure adopted may impose on the breadth of any principle that is to be identified as having been established or applied."</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>