<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Singleton, in the matter of Allcommercial Finance Australia Pty Limited [2009] FCA 714 (26 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/714.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re ACN 076 673 875 Ltd (2002) 42 ACSR 2096</tocase>
<text>In Re ACN 076 673 875 Ltd (2002) 42 ACSR 2096 at [16], Austin J said that: 
 In formulating his or her attitude to a proposed agreement the liquidator must act in good faith and for a proper purpose but
 provided he or she does so the court gives the liquidator considerable latitude in exercising his or her commercial judgment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re GA Listing &amp; Maintenance Pty Ltd (1994) 15 ACSR 308</tocase>
<text>The principles which govern the exercise of the Court's power under s 477(2B) have been considered in a number of authorities. In Re GA Listing &amp; Maintenance Pty Ltd (1994) 15 ACSR 308 at 310, Young J said that: 
 The whole purpose of liquidation is, to borrow a metaphor used by Sir Laurence Street some years ago, to lead the horse back into the stable. ... Any activity which marks a substantial deviation from the activity of "leading the horse back to the stable" is, generally speaking, outside the power of the liquidator. However, human activity is so diverse that there will be situations where the liquidator cannot lead the horse back to the stable by the direct route. He may have to pause along the way because the path is blocked by some litigation or other impediment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Spedley Securities Ltd (1992) 9 ACSR 83</tocase>
<text>His Honour referred to the observations of Giles J in Re Spedley Securities Ltd (1992) 9 ACSR 83 at 85-86. Giles J there observed that the Court will not ordinarily interfere unless there can be seen to be a lack of good faith, an error or law or principle, or real and substantial grounds for doubting the prudence of the liquidator's conduct.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Warne v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (2006) 233 ALR 181</tocase>
<text>In Warne v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (2006) 233 ALR 181 at [58], Austin J said that: 
 Generally speaking, the court grants approval under s 477(2B) only where the transaction is for the proper realisation of the assets of the company or otherwise assists in the winding up of the company.

I am satisfied in the present case on the evidence before me that the liquidators have acted in good faith and for a proper purpose. They have retained the services of, and acted upon the advice of, leading solicitors to advise them in relation to the liquidation of the company.

The liquidators have satisfied themselves that:

The power of attorney which is the subject of the present application is an irrevocable power of attorney and will survive the company's deregistration. Such a power of attorney is authorised by legislation in New South Wales, Victoria, Queensland, Western Australia and the Northern Territory. The relevant legislative provisions are referred to in MFI-1 and it is unnecessary for me to repeat them.

As is observed in MFI-1, the position is less certain in Tasmania, South Australia and the Australian Capital Territory, however this difficulty is overcome because the proposed deed provides for an assignment of the financial facilities and securities to the trustee as may be required.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>