<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Martinez v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 781 (23 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/781.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1982/33.html</AustLII>
<text>The test to be applied in determining whether leave should be granted to advance new grounds of appeal is well known. That test is in short, whether it is expedient and in the interests of justice that such leave be granted. In the present circumstances the relevant facts underlying the decision on review are not controversial. In O'Brien v Komesaroff [1982] HCA 33 ; (1982) 150 CLR 310 Mason J (with whom the other members of the Court agreed) said at 319: 
 "In some cases when a question of law is raised for the first time in an ultimate court of appeal, as for example upon the construction of a document, or upon facts either admitted or proved beyond controversy, it is expedient in the interests of justice that the question should be argued and decided (Connecticut Fire Insurance Co. v. Kavanagh (14); Suttor v. Gundowda Pty Ltd. (15); Green v. Sommerville (16))." 

 
In this appeal the relevant facts are not controversial and the particular ground now sought to be raised can be argued by both sides without the need for further factual investigation.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/33.html</AustLII>
<text>In Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1 , the majority of the High Court at 7-8 following this observation of Mason J drew no distinction between its application before an intermediate court of appeal and an ultimate court of appeal. Nevertheless, the majority of the High Court recognised the limitations which should be placed on raising new arguments on appeal. In that case the majority concluded that the respondents must be bound by the conduct of their case at trial. The majority said at 11: 
 "It would not be fair to the appellants to subject them at this stage of the proceedings to what is virtually a new trial on an entirely different issue to that which has been litigated. In the pursuit of such a course, the interests of expedition, finality and justice are denied." 

 
I do not consider that the present appeal falls into the category of case identified by the majority in Coulton v Holcombe (supra).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Vishnumolakala v Minister for Immigration and Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 248</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/248.html</AustLII>
<text>In determining whether it is expedient or in the interests of justice to grant leave to raise a new ground, it is accepted that consideration needs to be given to the merits of the ground proposed to determine whether that ground has a reasonable prospect of success: MZWCL v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 635 at [35] [37]; Vishnumolakala v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCA 248 at [5] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>MZWCL v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 635</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/635.html</AustLII>
<text>In determining whether it is expedient or in the interests of justice to grant leave to raise a new ground, it is accepted that consideration needs to be given to the merits of the ground proposed to determine whether that ground has a reasonable prospect of success: MZWCL v Minister for Immigration, Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 635 at [35] [37]; Vishnumolakala v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2007] FCA 248 at [5] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; Ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/22.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Lat (2006) 151 FCR 214 the Full Court observed that s 51A was intended to overcome the effect of the decision of the High Court in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57. The Full Court concluded at [66] that what was intended by the introduction of s 51A and related provisions into the Act was that Subdiv AB "provide comprehensive procedural codes which contain detailed provisions for procedural fairness but which exclude the common law natural justice hearing rule." The issues raised by the appellant in ground 2 of the notice of appeal do not identify any particular provision of Subdiv AB of Div 3 of Part 2 of the Act in respect of which there has been a contravention or a failure to comply.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Lat (2006) 151 FCR 214</tocase>
<text>In Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v Lat (2006) 151 FCR 214 the Full Court observed that s 51A was intended to overcome the effect of the decision of the High Court in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs; ex parte Miah [2001] HCA 22 ; (2001) 206 CLR 57. The Full Court concluded at [66] that what was intended by the introduction of s 51A and related provisions into the Act was that Subdiv AB "provide comprehensive procedural codes which contain detailed provisions for procedural fairness but which exclude the common law natural justice hearing rule." The issues raised by the appellant in ground 2 of the notice of appeal do not identify any particular provision of Subdiv AB of Div 3 of Part 2 of the Act in respect of which there has been a contravention or a failure to comply.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Plaintiff s157/2002 v Commonwealth of Australia (2003) 211 CLR 476</tocase>
<text>The decision of the delegate was a privative decision in accordance with s 474 of the Act. Nevertheless, s 474, does not preclude a court from determining that a decision does not fall within the privative provisions of s 474 if it involves a failure to exercise jurisdiction or is in excess of jurisdiction: Plaintiff s157/2002 v Commonwealth of Australia (2003) 211 CLR 476 at 506. In my opinion, the delegate accordingly fell into jurisdictional error: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at [82] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1988/12.html</AustLII>
<text>The principles applicable in determining whether a new ground can be raised on appeal were reiterated by the majority of the High Court in Water Board v Moustakas [1988] HCA 12 ; (1988) 180 CLR 491 at 497: 
 "More than once it has been held by this Court that a point cannot be raised for the first time upon appeal when it could possibly have been met by calling evidence below. Where all the facts have been established beyond controversy or where the point is one of construction or of law, then a court of appeal may find it expedient and in the interests of justice to entertain the point, but otherwise the rule is strictly applied. 

 
 In deciding whether or not a point was raised at trial no narrow or technical view should be taken."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2001/30.html</AustLII>
<text>The decision of the delegate was a privative decision in accordance with s 474 of the Act. Nevertheless, s 474, does not preclude a court from determining that a decision does not fall within the privative provisions of s 474 if it involves a failure to exercise jurisdiction or is in excess of jurisdiction: Plaintiff s157/2002 v Commonwealth of Australia (2003) 211 CLR 476 at 506. In my opinion, the delegate accordingly fell into jurisdictional error: Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 206 CLR 323 at [82] .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>