<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd (ACN 004 743 408) v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (No 3) [2009] FCA 779 (23 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/779.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 123 ; (2008) 169 FCR 227</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/123.html</AustLII>
<text>On 28 April 2009 I overruled a threshold or preliminary objection to the motion by ASIC and the second and third respondents, Brookfield Multiplex Limited and Brookfield Multiplex Funds Management Limited (collectively "Multiplex") that the applicants were precluded from bringing the motion as it re-litigated a matter not open to them on an interlocutory hearing because the matter had already been determined against them by the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 123 ; (2008) 169 FCR 227. ASIC and Multiplex submitted that the motion amounted to an abuse of process. On the same day, I dismissed a notice of motion filed by Multiplex on 13 March 2009 seeking orders that the applicants' motion be dismissed or permanently stayed as an abuse of process of the Court.

ASIC sought leave to appeal against the orders. The Full Court granted leave to appeal, allowed the appeal, set aside the orders and ordered that the thirty-six specified documents and forty-one transcripts of examination of twenty-three witnesses produced to the Court pursuant to the subpoena were protected from production to, and inspection by, the applicants and Multiplex on the ground of PII: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd [2008] FCAFC 123 ; (2008) 169 FCR 227. An application by the applicants to the High Court for leave to appeal was refused.

The parties were in agreement as to the process of analysis and consideration which I should undertake in determining a challenge to an application for production and inspection of documents produced under subpoena on the ground of PII because the documents might tend to disclose the identity of an informer or informers. The first step is to determine whether the documents disclose the existence of an informer or informers to ASIC. The second step is to determine whether the documents tend to identity an informer or informers to ASIC. If they do, the second step also involves determining whether the documents can be redacted or masked in such a way that, in their masked form, it will not be possible, even by the conveying of "a shrewd idea", to identify the informer or informers. The third step is to undertake a balancing exercise and determine whether, in the circumstances of this case, the documents to the extent to which they are not redacted or masked are of sufficient importance for the applicants' conduct of the proceeding to outweigh the importance of not disclosing the identity of the informer or informers. ASIC and Multiplex submitted that the Full Court had decided this balancing exercise against the applicants and that it was not open to the applicants to raise this issue and that I was bound by the Full Court's finding.

The position and circumstances facing the Court on the hearing of the present motion are different from the circumstances facing the Court at the time I made the order on 14 November 2007 dismissing ASIC's application. The relevant different circumstances are as follows: 
(a) it has been made public, and the applicants are now aware, that the basis for ASIC's claim that the documents and transcripts are protected from production and inspection on the ground of PII is that inspection will disclose the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC. The exact number of informers is irrelevant for present purposes;
 
 
(b) the identity of Mr Stuart Cummins as an informer to ASIC in relation to the affairs of Multiplex has been disclosed. The consequence is that there is no longer any confidentiality attached to Mr Cummins' identity as an informer to ASIC or as a

 
person entitled to protection pursuant to Pt 9.4AAA of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) ("the Act");
 
 
(c) the Full Court handed down its decision on 4 July 2008.

As a result of the disclosure of the identity of Mr Cummins as an informer to ASIC, ASIC accepts, subject to it reserving its rights in respect of any appeal which it may seek to bring against my ruling on 28 April 2009 that production and inspection of the following documents cannot be objected to by it on the ground that they would or might disclose Mr Cummins' identity as an informer to ASIC. The documents numbered: 
(a) 1, 5, 8, 9, 10, 13, 15, 16, 20, 21, 23, 24, 25, 28, 29, 30, 35 and 36 on the ground that they would or might disclose Mr Cummins' identity as a protected discloser and informer to ASIC.
 
 
(b) 4, 6, 7, 11, 12, 14, 18, 19, 22, 26, 27, 31 and 32 in redacted or masked form.

ASIC still opposes the production and inspection of documents numbered 2, 3, 17, 33 and 34 on the ground that inspection of those documents would or might disclose the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC who are entitled to protection in respect of their disclosures to ASIC pursuant to Pt 9.4AAA of the Act. For the same reason ASIC continues to object to the production and inspection of all forty-one transcripts.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (No 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466</tocase>
<text>There is a considerable background to the applicants' motion and this proceeding which is set out in my earlier ruling on 28 April 2009: P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (No 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466. I do not propose to rehearse it in detail and I incorporate that ruling in these reasons.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] FCA 1659 ; (2007) 65 ACSR 239</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/1659.html</AustLII>
<text>When the return of the subpoena first came before the Court, ASIC objected to the production of the documents and transcripts for inspection on the ground of PII. At the time the basis for the objection that they tended to reveal the identity of informers to ASIC was not disclosed publicly in open hearing. I rejected ASIC's objection, in substance, on the basis that the identity of the informers, which ASIC was seeking to protect from disclosure, was already known within Multiplex and I set out my reasons in a confidential schedule to the published judgment: P Dawson Nominees Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] FCA 1659 ; (2007) 65 ACSR 239. On 14 November 2007 I ordered that ASIC's application that the documents and transcripts were protected from production for inspection on the ground of PII be dismissed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Areva NC (Australia) Pty Ltd v Summit Resources (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] WASC 67</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//wa/WASC/2009/67.html</AustLII>
<text>The practice or task of undertaking the redaction or masking exercise in respect of documents the subject of an order for discovery or inspection is well accepted. However, there have been different approaches to the manner in which such redaction or masking is to be undertaken and as to the principal basis for the practice. The various approaches are discussed and analysed by Martin CJ in Areva NC (Australia) Pty Ltd v Summit Resources (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] WASC 67.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Sankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1978/43.html</AustLII>
<text>In Sankey v Whitlam [1978] HCA 43 ; (1978) 142 CLR 1 at 66-67, Stephen J considered whether Loan Council documents in issue might be the subject of redaction or masking. The informant had sought the production of the Loan Council documents for the purpose of establishing that the claimed proposed borrowing of $4 billion was not the subject of Loan Council consent. Stephen J said at 67: 
 "At the conclusion of argument it seemed to me scarcely credible that an inspection of the papers would not reveal the practicability of extracting material in itself quite innocuous, consisting perhaps of no more than the figure of approved Commonwealth borrowings not in fact availed of, which would provide evidence of this negative character. Were production of such material, and of such material only, to be permitted, no public interest would be prejudiced and at the same time the course of justice would not be impeded unnecessarily. Authority for such a course is to be found in Conway v Rimmer . Lord Reid (35), contemplated that part only of a document might properly be withheld, according to it alone privilege from production: Lord Pearce said (36), that the court might call for and itself inspect a document and then, if 'part of a document is innocuous but part is of such a nature that its disclosure would be undesirable, it should seal up the latter part and order discovery of the rest, provided that this will not give a distorted or misleading impression'. A statement of the outcome of the inspection of the Loan Council documents which has in fact been undertaken by this Court appears at the end of the several statements of reasons for judgment in this case." 

 
In the result, the High Court undertook an inspection of the Loan Council documents and ordered disclosure of those parts that disclosed only the figure of borrowing approved by the Commonwealth.

As I have noted earlier (par [8] above) ASIC accepts that, subject to any appeal against my ruling on 28 April 2009, the following documents cannot be the subject of objection to it on the ground of PII, namely 1, 5, 8, 9, 10, 13, 15, 16, 20, 21, 23, 24, 25, 28, 29, 30, 35 and 36.

ASIC made a similar submission in relation to the documents numbered 4, 6, 7, 11, 12, 14, 18, 19, 22, 26, 27, 31 and 32 in a redacted or masked form. I have considered the redaction or masking proposed by ASIC in relation to those documents and have also had regard to the confidential affidavits filed by ASIC which bear upon the redaction and masking of these documents. I have reached the conclusion that the redaction and masking undertaken by ASIC goes beyond the redaction and masking which are necessary in order to ensure that the documents do not have a tendency to disclose the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC. I set out in confidential Appendix A to these reasons the redaction and masking of these documents which I consider should be undertaken. This appendix will only be made available to ASIC's legal advisers and the deponents of its affidavits for the purpose of determining the form of any public non-confidential order which I should make.

Adopting and adapting the observation and words of Stephen J in Sankey v Whitlam (supra), the applicants submitted that it "seemed scarcely credible" that an inspection of the forty-one transcripts would not reveal the practicability of extracting material in itself quite innocuous without revealing or tending to reveal the identity of any informer.

I have considered whether I should accept that submission and undertake the exercise of seeking to redact and mask parts of the forty-one transcripts so as to leave those parts which are, in general terms, innocuous, on the basis that they do not identify or tend to identify an informer or informers. I have reached the conclusion that I should not undertake this task for the following reasons.

The transcripts record the evidence of twenty-three witnesses. The identity, occupation, role, employment title and employer of each of them is disclosed in the transcripts. If I were to redact or mask the transcripts so as to leave the "innocuous" parts so that the names, occupations, roles, employment titles and employers of the various witnesses and the organisation or company which employs them or with which they were involved were still disclosed, the applicants' legal advisers would still be left with material by which a shrewd idea would be conveyed as to the identity of an informer or informers other than Mr Cummins.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Attorney-General (NSW) v Stuart (1994) 34 NSWLR 667</tocase>
<text>I am satisfied that the confidential material relied upon by ASIC discloses the existence and identity of an informer or informers to ASIC other than Mr Cummins. It is implicit in the Full Court's reasoning that the Court reached the same conclusion. It was accepted by all parties that the protection of the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC from disclosure is a legitimate and accepted basis upon which to object to the protection and inspection of documents on the ground of PII: see, for example, Rogers v Home Secretary [1973] AC 388; Cain v Glass (No 2) (1985) 3 NSWLR 230 ; Spargos Mining NL v Standard Chartered Australia Ltd (No 1) (1989) 1 ACSR 311 ; Attorney-General (NSW) v Stuart (1994) 34 NSWLR 667.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Cain v Glass (No 2) (1985) 3 NSWLR 230</tocase>
<text>I am satisfied that the confidential material relied upon by ASIC discloses the existence and identity of an informer or informers to ASIC other than Mr Cummins. It is implicit in the Full Court's reasoning that the Court reached the same conclusion. It was accepted by all parties that the protection of the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC from disclosure is a legitimate and accepted basis upon which to object to the protection and inspection of documents on the ground of PII: see, for example, Rogers v Home Secretary [1973] AC 388; Cain v Glass (No 2) (1985) 3 NSWLR 230 ; Spargos Mining NL v Standard Chartered Australia Ltd (No 1) (1989) 1 ACSR 311 ; Attorney-General (NSW) v Stuart (1994) 34 NSWLR 667.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Rogers v Home Secretary [1973] AC 388</tocase>
<text>I am satisfied that the confidential material relied upon by ASIC discloses the existence and identity of an informer or informers to ASIC other than Mr Cummins. It is implicit in the Full Court's reasoning that the Court reached the same conclusion. It was accepted by all parties that the protection of the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC from disclosure is a legitimate and accepted basis upon which to object to the protection and inspection of documents on the ground of PII: see, for example, Rogers v Home Secretary [1973] AC 388; Cain v Glass (No 2) (1985) 3 NSWLR 230 ; Spargos Mining NL v Standard Chartered Australia Ltd (No 1) (1989) 1 ACSR 311 ; Attorney-General (NSW) v Stuart (1994) 34 NSWLR 667.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Spargos Mining NL v Standard Chartered Australia Ltd (No 1) (1989) 1 ACSR 311</tocase>
<text>I am satisfied that the confidential material relied upon by ASIC discloses the existence and identity of an informer or informers to ASIC other than Mr Cummins. It is implicit in the Full Court's reasoning that the Court reached the same conclusion. It was accepted by all parties that the protection of the identity of an informer or informers to ASIC from disclosure is a legitimate and accepted basis upon which to object to the protection and inspection of documents on the ground of PII: see, for example, Rogers v Home Secretary [1973] AC 388; Cain v Glass (No 2) (1985) 3 NSWLR 230 ; Spargos Mining NL v Standard Chartered Australia Ltd (No 1) (1989) 1 ACSR 311 ; Attorney-General (NSW) v Stuart (1994) 34 NSWLR 667.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>