<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pull v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2009] FCA 747 (15 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/747.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2005/7.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant made the following submissions on the effect of the s 195A visa on the proceedings: 
(1) The grant of the s 195A visa on 12 May 2009, removed the controversy which underlay proceedings NSD 17/2009 and SAD 52/2009. The applicant now has a visa and resides freely in the migration zone as a 'lawful non-citizen'. There is no need for an order in the nature of mandamus.
 
(2) The basis for declaratory relief has also fallen away. A suit for declaratory relief would only result in a declaration that the applicant holds a second visa; or a determination (or declaration) that he is not in possession of a second visa. Neither outcome will alter any legal right or liability of the applicant, for he is now a lawful non-citizen.
 
(3) The relief sought in the application is now futile. In such cases, the Court exercises its discretion to refuse relief ( Aala at [59]; SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [29] ), and it is responsible practice for an applicant to desist from pursuing such relief.
 
(4) At the directions hearing on 3 June 2009, the Minister appeared to invite the applicant to clarify his TP visa status, suggesting that his s 195A visa was only temporary. The applicant also has no interest in acceding to such a request; he does not favour the possession of a TP visa over his current s 195A visa. It has been, and remains, common ground that the applicant fails the 'character test' under s 501 of the Act ( Pull v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20). Any TP visa held by the applicant would be vulnerable to a new cancellation on this ground. Even if he did have such an interest, such an interest is insufficient to constitute a matter in federal jurisdiction ( Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 at [90] ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513</tocase>
<text>On the costs issue, the applicant referred the Court to the following principles in a case of discontinuance for futility and their application in the present case: 
(1) When a party, for its own reasons, discontinues a proceeding with leave pursuant to O 22 r 2(1)(d) of the Rules, the respondent is not automatically entitled to have the applicant pay his or her costs. Rather, costs are in the discretion of the Court under s 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ( Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513 ; Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 at [13] (Stone J)). The 'conduct of the parties in the matter and the reasons for the discontinuance can bear heavily on the exercise of the discretion as to costs' ( O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 at [13] (Finn J); Sullivan at [13] (Stone J)).
 
(2) A fortiori the significance of discretionary considerations in a case where the discontinuance is merely the procedural vehicle to terminate the dispute, and any futility in the proceedings has not been brought about by an external event, or the applicant's change of heart (cf., Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464 at [58] [59]), but by the opposing party's change in position.
 
(3) Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 at 624 625 suggests a structure for the exercise of a broad discretionary power. It does not lay down a rule which substitutes for the discretion of the Court. The critical considerations were stated by McHugh J as follows:
 
 In an appropriate case, a court will make an order for costs even when there has been no hearing on the merits and the moving party no longer wishes to proceed with the action. The court cannot try a hypothetical action between the parties. To do so would burden the parties with the costs of a litigated action which by settlement or extra-curial action they had avoided. In some cases, however, the court may be able to conclude that one of the parties has acted so unreasonably that the other party should obtain the costs of the action. In administrative law matters, for example, it may appear that the defendant has acted unreasonably in exercising or refusing to exercise a power and that the plaintiff had no reasonable alternative but to commence a litigation. Thus, for example, in R v Gold Coast City Council ; Ex parte Raysun Pty Ltd [[1971] QWN 13], the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Queensland gave a prosecutor seeking mandamus the costs of the proceedings up to the date when the respondent council notified the prosecutor that it would give the prosecutor the relief that it sought. The Full Court said that the prosecutor had reasonable ground for complaint in respect of the attitude taken by the respondent in failing to consider the application by the prosecutor for approval of road and drainage plans. 

 
 Moreover, in some cases a judge may feel confident that, although both parties have acted reasonably, one party was almost certain to have succeeded if the matter had been fully tried... But such cases are likely to be rare. 

 
 If it appears that both parties have acted reasonably in commencing and defending the proceedings and the conduct of the parties continued to be reasonable until the litigation was settled or its further prosecution became futile, the proper exercise of the cost discretion will usually mean that the court will make no order as to the cost of the proceedings. This approach has been adopted in a large number of cases. 

 
(4) Without a hearing on the merits, the Court is unable to be guided by the general rule as to costs. The difficulty cannot be resolved by embarking on a hypothetical consideration of which party would have been successful had the action proceeded. But the Court may consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the respective parties until the discontinuance ( Smith v Airservices at [46] [47]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Malloch v Aberdeen Corporation [1971] 1 WLR 1578 </tocase>
<text>According to the applicant, the Minister incorrectly fuses (i) the question whether the applicant is a lawful non-citizen, being a 'non-citizen in the migration zone who holds a visa that is in effect' (s 13 of the Act (emphasis added; see definition of 'visa': s 29)), with (ii) the discrete, and now futile, question whether the applicant holds a particular visa, namely a TP visa. The applicant says that the first question is answered completely by the grant of the s 195A visa; the second question is futile. The applicant does not require a declaration regarding his possession of a second visa: 'The Court does not act in vain': Malloch v Aberdeen Corporation [1971] 1 WLR 1578 at 1595 per Lord Wilberforce; cited in Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at [58] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/6.html</AustLII>
<text>On 9 March 2009, the applicant's solicitors wrote to the Minister's solicitors in the following terms: 
 We refer to the above proceedings in respect of which we have recently accepted instructions to act for Mr Pull. We confirm that we will shortly be filing a Notice of Appearance in the proceedings. 

 
 We are instructed to put you on notice that Mr Pull intends to challenge the constitutional validity of Item 7 of Schedule 4 to the Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 1) 2008 ( the amending statute ). Mr Pull will also contend that the invalidity of Item 7 renders invalid the visa cancellation decision of 2 June 2005 ( the decision ) made by the delegate of the Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship ( the Minister ). 

 
 Mr Pull has been detained as a result of the change in his legal status flowing from the decision. It is therefore reasonable for him to bring these proceedings to have the decision quashed. If Mr Pull is forced to move forward with these proceedings, considerable time and effort will be incurred in, inter alia, the preparation of pleadings, submissions and notices pursuant to s78B of the Judiciary Act 2003 (Cth). 

 
 The validity of the decision is the subject matter of these proceedings. We therefore ask that, in the event that the Minister intends to move away from the decision whether through revocation or the consideration of a new cancellation decision or otherwise you notify us of this intention within 7 days of the date of this letter. 

 
 In order that you may better understand Mr Pull's position, we will provide you with pleadings that state the intended grounds of review in advance of the directions hearing on Wednesday 11 March 2009. 

 
 We invite the Minister to revoke the decision and release Mr Pull from detention. In the event that we do not receive such a notification and the Minister later reconsiders the decision, our client intends to rely on this letter on the question of costs under the principles stated in Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622.

On 27 March 2009, the applicant's solicitors sent an email letter to the Minister's solicitors in the following terms: 
 Basis of Mr Pull's detention 
 We note your email confirming that Mr Pull was originally detained under section 189(1) of the Migration Act 1958 (Cth), and is now detained under section 196 of the Act. Given this confirmation, we require no further documents regarding his legal status at this time. 

 
 Costs letter 
 Also, we note that we have not received any response to our letter dated Friday 9 March 2009 (Our Letter). We understand that you received Our Letter on Monday 12 March 2009. 

 
 As noted in Court on Wednesday 14 March 2009, Mr Pull still puts his case for release from detention on the basis of the constitutional invalidity of the Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 1) 2008 . We have therefore proceeded in the preparation of our case on the basis that the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship ( Minister ) intends to defend fully the validity of Mr Pull's detention. In the event that there is any dispute about costs, we will rely on this correspondence.

On 31 March 2009, the Minister's solicitors responded as follows: In response to your letter dated 9 March 2009 the respondent does not concede that Item 7 of Schedule 4 to the Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 1) 2008 is invalid.
 As, in our client's view, the original decision made on 2 June 2005 to cancel your client's visa remains operative and authorises your client's continuing detention, the question of revocation or a need to make a further decision to cancel, as suggested at paragraph 4 of your letter, does not arise.
 We look forward to receiving your client's Amended Application.

On the costs issue, the applicant referred the Court to the following principles in a case of discontinuance for futility and their application in the present case: 
(1) When a party, for its own reasons, discontinues a proceeding with leave pursuant to O 22 r 2(1)(d) of the Rules, the respondent is not automatically entitled to have the applicant pay his or her costs. Rather, costs are in the discretion of the Court under s 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ( Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513 ; Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 at [13] (Stone J)). The 'conduct of the parties in the matter and the reasons for the discontinuance can bear heavily on the exercise of the discretion as to costs' ( O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 at [13] (Finn J); Sullivan at [13] (Stone J)).
 
(2) A fortiori the significance of discretionary considerations in a case where the discontinuance is merely the procedural vehicle to terminate the dispute, and any futility in the proceedings has not been brought about by an external event, or the applicant's change of heart (cf., Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464 at [58] [59]), but by the opposing party's change in position.
 
(3) Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 at 624 625 suggests a structure for the exercise of a broad discretionary power. It does not lay down a rule which substitutes for the discretion of the Court. The critical considerations were stated by McHugh J as follows:
 
 In an appropriate case, a court will make an order for costs even when there has been no hearing on the merits and the moving party no longer wishes to proceed with the action. The court cannot try a hypothetical action between the parties. To do so would burden the parties with the costs of a litigated action which by settlement or extra-curial action they had avoided. In some cases, however, the court may be able to conclude that one of the parties has acted so unreasonably that the other party should obtain the costs of the action. In administrative law matters, for example, it may appear that the defendant has acted unreasonably in exercising or refusing to exercise a power and that the plaintiff had no reasonable alternative but to commence a litigation. Thus, for example, in R v Gold Coast City Council ; Ex parte Raysun Pty Ltd [[1971] QWN 13], the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Queensland gave a prosecutor seeking mandamus the costs of the proceedings up to the date when the respondent council notified the prosecutor that it would give the prosecutor the relief that it sought. The Full Court said that the prosecutor had reasonable ground for complaint in respect of the attitude taken by the respondent in failing to consider the application by the prosecutor for approval of road and drainage plans. 

 
 Moreover, in some cases a judge may feel confident that, although both parties have acted reasonably, one party was almost certain to have succeeded if the matter had been fully tried... But such cases are likely to be rare. 

 
 If it appears that both parties have acted reasonably in commencing and defending the proceedings and the conduct of the parties continued to be reasonable until the litigation was settled or its further prosecution became futile, the proper exercise of the cost discretion will usually mean that the court will make no order as to the cost of the proceedings. This approach has been adopted in a large number of cases. 

 
(4) Without a hearing on the merits, the Court is unable to be guided by the general rule as to costs. The difficulty cannot be resolved by embarking on a hypothetical consideration of which party would have been successful had the action proceeded. But the Court may consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the respective parties until the discontinuance ( Smith v Airservices at [46] [47]).

The Minister referred to the Court's broad discretionary power in relation to costs afforded by s 43 of the Federal Court Act; noted that the discretion should be exercised judicially and referred to the same passage in the reasons of McHugh J in Lai Qin referred to by the applicant and recited in [26(3)] above.

It lay at the heart of the Minister's submissions that the Minister's decision to grant the applicant a s 195A visa did not render the declaratory relief he sought in NSD 17/2009 'moot'. According to the Minister, the issue of whether or not the applicant is in fact the holder of a TP visa is a live issue in that there remains a real and ongoing dispute between the parties as to the entitlement of the applicant to remain in Australia beyond the life of the s 195A visa granted to him; while the urgency of the resolution of that dispute is no longer present, that fact does not render the dispute between the parties moot.

The Minister submitted that the power he ultimately exercised to grant the applicant a s 195A visa is a 'non-compellable' power and the failure of the Minister to exercise that power by any particular date, or at all, can never be unreasonable in the relevant sense.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1680.html</AustLII>
<text>On the costs issue, the applicant referred the Court to the following principles in a case of discontinuance for futility and their application in the present case: 
(1) When a party, for its own reasons, discontinues a proceeding with leave pursuant to O 22 r 2(1)(d) of the Rules, the respondent is not automatically entitled to have the applicant pay his or her costs. Rather, costs are in the discretion of the Court under s 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ( Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513 ; Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 at [13] (Stone J)). The 'conduct of the parties in the matter and the reasons for the discontinuance can bear heavily on the exercise of the discretion as to costs' ( O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 at [13] (Finn J); Sullivan at [13] (Stone J)).
 
(2) A fortiori the significance of discretionary considerations in a case where the discontinuance is merely the procedural vehicle to terminate the dispute, and any futility in the proceedings has not been brought about by an external event, or the applicant's change of heart (cf., Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464 at [58] [59]), but by the opposing party's change in position.
 
(3) Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 at 624 625 suggests a structure for the exercise of a broad discretionary power. It does not lay down a rule which substitutes for the discretion of the Court. The critical considerations were stated by McHugh J as follows:
 
 In an appropriate case, a court will make an order for costs even when there has been no hearing on the merits and the moving party no longer wishes to proceed with the action. The court cannot try a hypothetical action between the parties. To do so would burden the parties with the costs of a litigated action which by settlement or extra-curial action they had avoided. In some cases, however, the court may be able to conclude that one of the parties has acted so unreasonably that the other party should obtain the costs of the action. In administrative law matters, for example, it may appear that the defendant has acted unreasonably in exercising or refusing to exercise a power and that the plaintiff had no reasonable alternative but to commence a litigation. Thus, for example, in R v Gold Coast City Council ; Ex parte Raysun Pty Ltd [[1971] QWN 13], the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Queensland gave a prosecutor seeking mandamus the costs of the proceedings up to the date when the respondent council notified the prosecutor that it would give the prosecutor the relief that it sought. The Full Court said that the prosecutor had reasonable ground for complaint in respect of the attitude taken by the respondent in failing to consider the application by the prosecutor for approval of road and drainage plans. 

 
 Moreover, in some cases a judge may feel confident that, although both parties have acted reasonably, one party was almost certain to have succeeded if the matter had been fully tried... But such cases are likely to be rare. 

 
 If it appears that both parties have acted reasonably in commencing and defending the proceedings and the conduct of the parties continued to be reasonable until the litigation was settled or its further prosecution became futile, the proper exercise of the cost discretion will usually mean that the court will make no order as to the cost of the proceedings. This approach has been adopted in a large number of cases. 

 
(4) Without a hearing on the merits, the Court is unable to be guided by the general rule as to costs. The difficulty cannot be resolved by embarking on a hypothetical consideration of which party would have been successful had the action proceeded. But the Court may consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the respective parties until the discontinuance ( Smith v Airservices at [46] [47]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/57.html</AustLII>
<text>According to the applicant, the Minister incorrectly fuses (i) the question whether the applicant is a lawful non-citizen, being a 'non-citizen in the migration zone who holds a visa that is in effect' (s 13 of the Act (emphasis added; see definition of 'visa': s 29)), with (ii) the discrete, and now futile, question whether the applicant holds a particular visa, namely a TP visa. The applicant says that the first question is answered completely by the grant of the s 195A visa; the second question is futile. The applicant does not require a declaration regarding his possession of a second visa: 'The Court does not act in vain': Malloch v Aberdeen Corporation [1971] 1 WLR 1578 at 1595 per Lord Wilberforce; cited in Re Refugee Review Tribunal; ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at [58] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ.

The applicant made the following submissions on the effect of the s 195A visa on the proceedings: 
(1) The grant of the s 195A visa on 12 May 2009, removed the controversy which underlay proceedings NSD 17/2009 and SAD 52/2009. The applicant now has a visa and resides freely in the migration zone as a 'lawful non-citizen'. There is no need for an order in the nature of mandamus.
 
(2) The basis for declaratory relief has also fallen away. A suit for declaratory relief would only result in a declaration that the applicant holds a second visa; or a determination (or declaration) that he is not in possession of a second visa. Neither outcome will alter any legal right or liability of the applicant, for he is now a lawful non-citizen.
 
(3) The relief sought in the application is now futile. In such cases, the Court exercises its discretion to refuse relief ( Aala at [59]; SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [29] ), and it is responsible practice for an applicant to desist from pursuing such relief.
 
(4) At the directions hearing on 3 June 2009, the Minister appeared to invite the applicant to clarify his TP visa status, suggesting that his s 195A visa was only temporary. The applicant also has no interest in acceding to such a request; he does not favour the possession of a TP visa over his current s 195A visa. It has been, and remains, common ground that the applicant fails the 'character test' under s 501 of the Act ( Pull v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20). Any TP visa held by the applicant would be vulnerable to a new cancellation on this ground. Even if he did have such an interest, such an interest is insufficient to constitute a matter in federal jurisdiction ( Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 at [90] ).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sales v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCAFC 132 ; (2008) 171 FCR 56 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/132.html</AustLII>
<text>Following the decision of a Full Court of this Court in Sales v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCAFC 132 ; (2008) 171 FCR 56 , the decision to cancel the applicant's TP visa was ineffective for reason that at the time of cancellation it was not authorised by s 501(2) of the Act. As a result, the applicant was released from detention on, or shortly after, 21 July 2008.

Schedule 4 of the Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 1) 2008 (Cth), which took effect on 19 September 2008, amended the Act to authorise a cancellation of a TP visa under s 501 of the Act and to validate previous decisions to cancel TP visas that were held to be unauthorised in the Full Court's decision in Sales.

By letter dated 29 October 2008, the applicant was informed that as a consequence of the legislative amendments made under the Migration Legislation Amendment Act (No. 1), the decision to cancel his TP visa was validated, and he was liable to be detained under s 189 of the Act and removed from Australia. The applicant was arrested on or around 18 November 2008 and taken into detention.

On 8 January 2009, the applicant commenced a proceeding under s 39B of the Judiciary Act (NSD 17/2009) seeking relief in the nature of habeas corpus ordering his release from detention and various other orders, including a declaration that he is a lawful non-citizen, and injunctions, including an injunction preventing the respondent from giving effect to the purported cancellation of his visa and removing him from Australia.

The other significant component of the overall relief sought by the applicant in proceeding NSD 17/2009 was the declaratory relief that the applicant was a 'lawful non-citizen' by reason that he was the holder of a TP visa which had not been cancelled ( Sales ), even with the aid of amending legislation purporting to retrospectively validate the cancellation, because that legislation was invalid.

The Minster's submission that the declaratory relief sought by the applicant was not rendered 'moot' by the grant of the s 195A visa is, in a juridical sense, correct; but as a practical matter, the grant of that visa rendered the declaratory relief sought futile. Why would the applicant, with little or no financial resources and dependent, for the able prosecution of his case, on the O 80 relief I determined on 4 February 2009, want to continue to press for that declaratory relief when his status as a 'lawful non-citizen' was no longer in issue, at least until the s 195A visa expired in 12 months time when, he had been informed, the Minister would review his case?

The Minister did not contend, nor could he, that the applicant acted unreasonably in taking the action he did in either proceeding; and the applicant did not contend that the Minister acted unreasonably in opposing those proceedings; at least in express terms.

On the other hand, I do find the Minister's action in granting the s 195A visa to be totally inconsistent with his position up to that point in time, having regard to the following: 
(1) The initial cancellation of the applicant's TP visa and his arrest and detention for over three years;
 
(2) the Minister's sponsorship of retrospective legislation designed to validate his cancellation decision in the face of Sales ;
 
(3) the subsequent arrest and detention of the applicant for a period of six months; and
 
(4) the absence of any explanation for the Minister's grant of the s 195A visa.

The Minister's change of position, unmoved by any external event and otherwise unexplained, leads me to the view that the applicant should have his costs in NSD 17/2009 but not in SAD 52/2009. The latter proceeding was unnecessary and each party should pay its own costs.
 I certify that the preceding forty-two (42) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Edmonds. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 15 July 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: Mr C Mantziarais 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: Corrs Chambers Westgarth 
 
 Counsel for the Respondents: Mr A Markus 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondents: Australian Government Solicitor 
 Date of Submissions: 12, 19 and 26 June 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 15 July 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/747.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/997.html</AustLII>
<text>On the costs issue, the applicant referred the Court to the following principles in a case of discontinuance for futility and their application in the present case: 
(1) When a party, for its own reasons, discontinues a proceeding with leave pursuant to O 22 r 2(1)(d) of the Rules, the respondent is not automatically entitled to have the applicant pay his or her costs. Rather, costs are in the discretion of the Court under s 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ( Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513 ; Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 at [13] (Stone J)). The 'conduct of the parties in the matter and the reasons for the discontinuance can bear heavily on the exercise of the discretion as to costs' ( O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 at [13] (Finn J); Sullivan at [13] (Stone J)).
 
(2) A fortiori the significance of discretionary considerations in a case where the discontinuance is merely the procedural vehicle to terminate the dispute, and any futility in the proceedings has not been brought about by an external event, or the applicant's change of heart (cf., Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464 at [58] [59]), but by the opposing party's change in position.
 
(3) Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 at 624 625 suggests a structure for the exercise of a broad discretionary power. It does not lay down a rule which substitutes for the discretion of the Court. The critical considerations were stated by McHugh J as follows:
 
 In an appropriate case, a court will make an order for costs even when there has been no hearing on the merits and the moving party no longer wishes to proceed with the action. The court cannot try a hypothetical action between the parties. To do so would burden the parties with the costs of a litigated action which by settlement or extra-curial action they had avoided. In some cases, however, the court may be able to conclude that one of the parties has acted so unreasonably that the other party should obtain the costs of the action. In administrative law matters, for example, it may appear that the defendant has acted unreasonably in exercising or refusing to exercise a power and that the plaintiff had no reasonable alternative but to commence a litigation. Thus, for example, in R v Gold Coast City Council ; Ex parte Raysun Pty Ltd [[1971] QWN 13], the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Queensland gave a prosecutor seeking mandamus the costs of the proceedings up to the date when the respondent council notified the prosecutor that it would give the prosecutor the relief that it sought. The Full Court said that the prosecutor had reasonable ground for complaint in respect of the attitude taken by the respondent in failing to consider the application by the prosecutor for approval of road and drainage plans. 

 
 Moreover, in some cases a judge may feel confident that, although both parties have acted reasonably, one party was almost certain to have succeeded if the matter had been fully tried... But such cases are likely to be rare. 

 
 If it appears that both parties have acted reasonably in commencing and defending the proceedings and the conduct of the parties continued to be reasonable until the litigation was settled or its further prosecution became futile, the proper exercise of the cost discretion will usually mean that the court will make no order as to the cost of the proceedings. This approach has been adopted in a large number of cases. 

 
(4) Without a hearing on the merits, the Court is unable to be guided by the general rule as to costs. The difficulty cannot be resolved by embarking on a hypothetical consideration of which party would have been successful had the action proceeded. But the Court may consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the respective parties until the discontinuance ( Smith v Airservices at [46] [47]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/786.html</AustLII>
<text>On the costs issue, the applicant referred the Court to the following principles in a case of discontinuance for futility and their application in the present case: 
(1) When a party, for its own reasons, discontinues a proceeding with leave pursuant to O 22 r 2(1)(d) of the Rules, the respondent is not automatically entitled to have the applicant pay his or her costs. Rather, costs are in the discretion of the Court under s 43(2) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ( Inground Constructions Pty Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 27 ATR 513 ; Sullivan v Secretary, Department of Defence [2005] FCA 786 at [13] (Stone J)). The 'conduct of the parties in the matter and the reasons for the discontinuance can bear heavily on the exercise of the discretion as to costs' ( O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 at [13] (Finn J); Sullivan at [13] (Stone J)).
 
(2) A fortiori the significance of discretionary considerations in a case where the discontinuance is merely the procedural vehicle to terminate the dispute, and any futility in the proceedings has not been brought about by an external event, or the applicant's change of heart (cf., Smith v Airservices Australia [2005] FCA 997 ; (2005) 222 ALR 464 at [58] [59]), but by the opposing party's change in position.
 
(3) Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 at 624 625 suggests a structure for the exercise of a broad discretionary power. It does not lay down a rule which substitutes for the discretion of the Court. The critical considerations were stated by McHugh J as follows:
 
 In an appropriate case, a court will make an order for costs even when there has been no hearing on the merits and the moving party no longer wishes to proceed with the action. The court cannot try a hypothetical action between the parties. To do so would burden the parties with the costs of a litigated action which by settlement or extra-curial action they had avoided. In some cases, however, the court may be able to conclude that one of the parties has acted so unreasonably that the other party should obtain the costs of the action. In administrative law matters, for example, it may appear that the defendant has acted unreasonably in exercising or refusing to exercise a power and that the plaintiff had no reasonable alternative but to commence a litigation. Thus, for example, in R v Gold Coast City Council ; Ex parte Raysun Pty Ltd [[1971] QWN 13], the Full Court of the Supreme Court of Queensland gave a prosecutor seeking mandamus the costs of the proceedings up to the date when the respondent council notified the prosecutor that it would give the prosecutor the relief that it sought. The Full Court said that the prosecutor had reasonable ground for complaint in respect of the attitude taken by the respondent in failing to consider the application by the prosecutor for approval of road and drainage plans. 

 
 Moreover, in some cases a judge may feel confident that, although both parties have acted reasonably, one party was almost certain to have succeeded if the matter had been fully tried... But such cases are likely to be rare. 

 
 If it appears that both parties have acted reasonably in commencing and defending the proceedings and the conduct of the parties continued to be reasonable until the litigation was settled or its further prosecution became futile, the proper exercise of the cost discretion will usually mean that the court will make no order as to the cost of the proceedings. This approach has been adopted in a large number of cases. 

 
(4) Without a hearing on the merits, the Court is unable to be guided by the general rule as to costs. The difficulty cannot be resolved by embarking on a hypothetical consideration of which party would have been successful had the action proceeded. But the Court may consider the reasonableness of the conduct of the respective parties until the discontinuance ( Smith v Airservices at [46] [47]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2007/26.html</AustLII>
<text>The applicant made the following submissions on the effect of the s 195A visa on the proceedings: 
(1) The grant of the s 195A visa on 12 May 2009, removed the controversy which underlay proceedings NSD 17/2009 and SAD 52/2009. The applicant now has a visa and resides freely in the migration zone as a 'lawful non-citizen'. There is no need for an order in the nature of mandamus.
 
(2) The basis for declaratory relief has also fallen away. A suit for declaratory relief would only result in a declaration that the applicant holds a second visa; or a determination (or declaration) that he is not in possession of a second visa. Neither outcome will alter any legal right or liability of the applicant, for he is now a lawful non-citizen.
 
(3) The relief sought in the application is now futile. In such cases, the Court exercises its discretion to refuse relief ( Aala at [59]; SZBYR v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] HCA 26 ; (2007) 235 ALR 609 at [29] ), and it is responsible practice for an applicant to desist from pursuing such relief.
 
(4) At the directions hearing on 3 June 2009, the Minister appeared to invite the applicant to clarify his TP visa status, suggesting that his s 195A visa was only temporary. The applicant also has no interest in acceding to such a request; he does not favour the possession of a TP visa over his current s 195A visa. It has been, and remains, common ground that the applicant fails the 'character test' under s 501 of the Act ( Pull v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20). Any TP visa held by the applicant would be vulnerable to a new cancellation on this ground. Even if he did have such an interest, such an interest is insufficient to constitute a matter in federal jurisdiction ( Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 at [90] ).</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>