<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Windsor v Sydney Medical Service Co-operative Ltd (No. 2) [2009] FCA 704 (1 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/704.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Fox Symes &amp; Associates Pty Limited [2005] FCA 10 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2005/10.html</AustLII>
<text>An order striking out pleadings does not finally determine the rights of the parties. The proceeding remains extant (see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Fox Symes &amp; Associates Pty Limited [2005] FCA 1071) and a party is ordinarily given an opportunity to re-plead in accordance with the Rules ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission at [95]). (ii) Interlocutory orders do not found an issue estoppel</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Bond v Barry (2008) 173 FCR 106 </tocase>
<text>Jefferson Ford was considered by a Full Court of this Court in Bond v Barry (2008) 173 FCR 106 (Sundberg, Jacobson and Lander JJ) but declined to express a view on which of the competing views in Jefferson Ford of the application of s 31A of the Act was correct (at [74]). (ii) Application of the general principles to this proceeding</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Boston Commercial Services Pty Limited v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2006/1352.html</AustLII>
<text>In respect of applications for summary judgment under s 31A of the Act, the onus to demonstrate that the proceedings do not have reasonable prospects of success rests with the party seeking summary judgment. In Boston Commercial Services Pty Limited v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720 at [43] and [44] Rares J, quoting from Latham CJ in Hocking v Bell [1945] HCA 16 ; (1945) 71 CLR 430 at 441 442, likened the standard under s 31A of the Act to the common law test for determining whether a jury properly instructed could reach a verdict for a plaintiff: 
 [T]here must be a real issue of fact to be decided. And if the evidence is all one way, so that only one conclusion can be said to be reasonable, there is no function left for the jury to perform, so that the court may properly take the matter into its own hands as being a matter of law, and direct a verdict to be entered in accordance with the only evidence which is really presented in the case ... 

 
 In a case to which s 31A applies, where there is a real issue of fact to be decided in the sense identified in the above principle, and possibly where there is a real issue of law of a similar kind, it is obviously appropriate that the matter goes to trial.

A Full Court of this Court considered the application of s 31A in Jefferson Ford Pty Limited v Ford Motor Company of Australia Limited [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 (Finkelstein, Rares and Gordon JJ). Finkelstein J stated that s 31A of the Act is to be given a 'substantial operation' which requires the 'judge to conduct what might loosely be described as a preliminary trial' and to look closely to a party's 'assertion that there is a real question of law or fact to be decided' (at [23]). About factual issues Finkelstein J (at [20]) stated that the task of prediction was fraught with all kinds of difficulties including the Court, in many cases, not having before it all the material evidence, and if credit is involved the impossibility of predicting how that issue would be resolved. Even if the dispute is only a question of law, that issue may be difficult to resolve; or to predict its resolution, in the absence of detailed argument such as only occurs at a trial. Then Finkelstein J stated (at [23]) that the task of the judge is 'to decide whether the opposing party has evidence of sufficient quality and weight to be able to succeed at trial' and on questions of law the task of the judge is to determine whether the question of law is 'sufficiently strong to warrant a trial' (at [23]). Rares J favoured the test he stated in Boston Commercial and noted that that the correctness of that test did not need to be examined because 'neither party challenged that test' (at [73]). Gordon J identified a number of principles which 'inform' the application of s 31A of the Act. Among these are: (1) that s 31A is less stringent than the General Steel Industries standard; (2) that each case must be determined separately; (3) where there is a real issue of fact it is unlikely that that part of the proceeding has no prospect of success; (4) in determining whether a real issue of fact exists the Court must draw all available reasonable inferences in favour of the non-moving party (at [124] [132]). Gordon J at [126] stated that the assessment that a proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success will necessarily require: 
 1. Identification of the cause of action pleaded;
 2. identification of the pleaded facts said to give rise to that cause of action; 
 a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in support of the claim for judgment; 
 4. identification of the defence pleaded; 
 identification of any facts pleaded which are said to give rise to the defence; and 
 6. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in defence of the claim.

In SMS's submission it has 'discharged the onus to enliven the discretion to authorise a summary termination of the proceedings which s 31A envisages', per Rares J in Boston Commercial at [45]. Even accepting Mr Neil Windsor and Dr Windsor's version of the discussions on 8 and 10 January 2001 (paras 19, 21 and 23 of Ex. B (the 74 page affidavit) and paras 21, 23 and 24 of Ex. A (the 54 page affidavit)) as completely accurate, there is no reasonable interpretation of the communications between Mr Neil Windsor and SMS which is consistent with any conclusion other than that any contract for the provision of locum services by Dr Windsor was entered into between InterNEOn and SMS.

Dr Windsor pointed to the evidence at para 19 of the 74 page affidavit that is part of Ex. B in support of the case propounded in the amended statement of claim on the formation of the agreement, specifically: 
(1) That Mr Neil Windsor, on Dr Windsor's behalf, met with Mr Muldoon of SMS on 8 January 2001;
 
(2) that at the commencement of the meeting the following exchange took place:
 
Mr Muldoon said 'So you have come to negotiate with me, have you?'
 
 
[Mr Windsor said]: I guess I have.' 
 
 
(3) that Mr Windsor and Mr Muldoon on 8 January 2001 negotiated Dr Windsor's terms of engagement with SMS and reached agreement on those terms;
 
(4) that at another point during the meeting the following exchange took place:
 
[Mr Windsor said]: 'How often do you pay the locums?'
 
 
Mr Muldoon said: 'Monthly on the second Wednesday of each month. I prepare a tax invoice for the locums. I need an ABN Number, you know, to take care of this GST crap.'
 
 
[Mr Windsor said]: 'Does it have to be a personal ABN or can it be a company one?'
 
 
Mr Muldoon said: 'I don't care. It's up to the locums to take care of their tax anyway they want.'
 
 
[Mr Windsor said]: 'It might take a while to get an ABN. What are you going to do about payment?'
 
 
Mr Muldoon said: 'I will keep the money until you give me an ABN. I'm not going to deduct 50% of the pay like the tax department want us to do.'

It was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that it is inappropriate in a summary judgment application to determine the question of law whether post-contractual conduct or communications can be used to identify the parties to the contract for the provision of medical services entered into by SMS. Further, that there is evidence in support of the case pleaded in the amended statement of claim that the agreement was entered into by Dr Windsor, through the agency of her husband, Mr Neil Windsor, and Mr Muldoon of SMS on 8 January 2001; and there is no evidence by SMS as to the negotiations on 8 January 2001. It was submitted that the Court should find that SMS has not satisfied the onus of demonstrating that Dr Windsor has no reasonable prospects of prosecuting the proceedings within s 31A(2) of the Act.

In conclusion, it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that, whether the Court applies the standard adopted by Rares J in Boston Commercial , the principles identified by Gordon J in Jefferson Ford or, the tasks of the judge in considering an application under s 31A of the Act identified by Finkelstein J in Jefferson Ford , the Court should find that SMS has not satisfied the onus of demonstrating that Dr Windsor has no reasonable prospects of prosecuting the proceedings within s 31A(2) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Bowes v Fehlberg &amp; Ors (No 2) [2001] TASSC 24</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//tas/supreme_ct/2001/24.html</AustLII>
<text>Interlocutory orders, by nature, lack finality. It follows, therefore, that they are insufficient to create an issue estoppel (see Wilson v Union Insurance Co [1992] NTSC 107 ; (1992) 112 FLR 166 ; cited with approval in Bowes v Fehlberg &amp; Ors (No 2) [2001] TASSC 24 at [22] and by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Miller v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 38 ATR 51. (iii) The facts and law the subject of the 2007 notice of motion were not conducted on a final basis</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Coffey v Secretary, Department of Social Security [1999] FCA 375 ; (1999) 86 FCR 434</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/375.html</AustLII>
<text>These observations were cited with approval by a Full Court of this Court in Coffey v Secretary, Department of Social Security [1999] FCA 375 ; (1999) 86 FCR 434 at 443.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>County Securities Pty Ltd v Challenger Group Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 193 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/193.html</AustLII>
<text>Third, it was submitted that if, contrary to the foregoing submissions, I was to find that any principle coming out of Manning can apply by way of analogy to the present case, there were four reasons why it was fair and just to reconsider the matter rather than be persuaded that SMS had established the amended statement of claim was an abuse of process. These were put as follows: 
(1) Dr Windsor was self-represented on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion.
 
(2) I applied impermissible criteria in deciding the 2007 notice of motion clearly a strike-out application rather than confining myself to the pleadings; had I done the latter, I would have dismissed the 2007 notice of motion. I have already accepted this submission at [12] and [13] above.
 
(3) On the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion, the Court's attention was not drawn to the undecided question of law about whether post-contractual conduct and communications could be used to identify parties to the contract (see Dennis Pethybridge v Stedikas Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 154 ; (2007) Aust Contract R &#167;90-263 at [59] per Campbell JA (Beazley JA agreeing); Sagacious Procurements Pty Ltd v Symbion Health Ltd (formerly Mayne Group Ltd) [2008] NSWCA 149 at [99] ff per Giles JA (Hodgson and Campbell JJA agreeing); County Securities Pty Ltd v Challenger Group Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 193 at [161] per McColl JA), and at least some of the Judgment Documents fall within that category.
 
(4) The fact that on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion my attention was not drawn to admissions that were relied upon on the hearing of the current motion and, even if I did have regard to them on the earlier occasion, there is no indication on the face of the reasons for judgment that I interacted with them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>D A Christie Pty Ltd v Baker (1996) 2 VR 582</tocase>
<text>In response, it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that the principle articulated in Manning , to which I would merely observe, assuming a principle can be identified other than a preference for the view of Charles JA rather than the majority in D A Christie Pty Ltd v Baker (1996) 2 VR 582 , concerned, as did Dawson and Christie , the bringing of a second interlocutory application by an applicant or plaintiff; here, it was pointed out, on both occasions, Dr Windsor was resisting such an application and so, at best, any principle, if it can apply at all, could only be by way of analogy.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Hall v The Nominal Defendant [1966] HCA 36 ; (1966) 117 CLR 423</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1966/36.html</AustLII>
<text>An order striking out a statement of claim on the ground that it fails to disclose a reasonable cause of action is interlocutory and not a final order ( Jones v Insole (1891) 64 LT 703 , a decision of the English Court of Appeal; cited with approval by Taylor J (with whom Owen J agreed) in Hall v The Nominal Defendant [1966] HCA 36 ; (1966) 117 CLR 423 at 440, where his Honour said: 
 The same view [ie that the order was interlocutory] was taken of an order striking out a plaintiff's statement of claim on the ground that it disclosed no reasonable cause of action: Jones v Insole and of an order dismissing an action as frivolous and vexatious in In re Page .
 (Citations omitted)

In this Court, Burchett J in Weatherall v Satellite Receiving Systems (Australia) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 741 ; (1999) 92 FCR 101 at [9] after reviewing both English and Australian authorities (including Jones v Insole and Hall v The Nominal Defendant ) concluded that an order striking out a statement of claim is an interlocutory order. Burchett's J analysis in Weatherall was cited with approval by Cowdroy J in Md Abdullah Al Mamun v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 541.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Hocking v Bell [1945] HCA 16 ; (1945) 71 CLR 430 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1945/16.html</AustLII>
<text>In respect of applications for summary judgment under s 31A of the Act, the onus to demonstrate that the proceedings do not have reasonable prospects of success rests with the party seeking summary judgment. In Boston Commercial Services Pty Limited v GE Capital Finance Australasia Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1352 ; (2006) 236 ALR 720 at [43] and [44] Rares J, quoting from Latham CJ in Hocking v Bell [1945] HCA 16 ; (1945) 71 CLR 430 at 441 442, likened the standard under s 31A of the Act to the common law test for determining whether a jury properly instructed could reach a verdict for a plaintiff: 
 [T]here must be a real issue of fact to be decided. And if the evidence is all one way, so that only one conclusion can be said to be reasonable, there is no function left for the jury to perform, so that the court may properly take the matter into its own hands as being a matter of law, and direct a verdict to be entered in accordance with the only evidence which is really presented in the case ... 

 
 In a case to which s 31A applies, where there is a real issue of fact to be decided in the sense identified in the above principle, and possibly where there is a real issue of law of a similar kind, it is obviously appropriate that the matter goes to trial.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c9">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Imobilari Pty Ltd v Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited [2008] FCA 1920 ; (2008) 252 ALR 41</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1920.html</AustLII>
<text>On the hearing of the current motion it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that I impermissibly had regard to the evidence and that if I had confined myself to the terms of the pleading as I should have done in respect of a strike-out motion in reliance on O 11 r 16, the 2007 notice of motion would have been dismissed. I was referred to what was recently said by Finkelstein J in Imobilari Pty Ltd v Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited [2008] FCA 1920 ; (2008) 252 ALR 41 at [4] : 
 The fundamental thing to understand about the strike-out rule, which the language of O 11 r 16 itself makes clear, is that the rule is concerned only with the adequacy of the pleading (or to be more precise, the allegations and the causes of action asserted therein) as a matter of law. The rule does not permit or allow consideration of facts or evidence outside the pleadings: Dey v Victorian Railway Commissioners [1949] HCA 1 ; (1949) 78 CLR 62 at 91 and 109; [1999] ALR 333 at 347-8; see also General Steel Industries Inc v Commissioner for Railways (NSW) [1964] HCA 69 ; (1964) 112 CLR 125 at 129; [1964] HCA 69 ; [1965] ALR 636 at 638 (' General Steel '). Indeed, as counsel for ANZ, Mr Archibald QC, correctly noted in his submissions, the court must, for purposes of deciding the strike-out motion and deciding whether a pleading discloses a reasonable cause of action, assume the truth of the allegations in the statement of claim and draw all inferences in favour of the non-moving party because the question is whether those allegations, even if proved, cannot succeed as a matter of law: General Steel CLR at 129; ALR at 638.

The submission is clearly correct. For the reasons more fully explored at [30] below, it is not possible to regard the 2007 notice of motion as anything more than a strike-out motion. It certainly did not seek dismissal of the proceeding as an abuse of process or summary judgment in reliance on s 31A of the Act. As indicated at [35] below, if it had been necessary, I would have taken my error in this respect into account in the exercise of my discretion as to whether the justice of the matter required that the finding as to the contracting parties made on the 2007 notice of motion be reconsidered.

On 1 December 2008, Dr Windsor filed an amended statement of claim pursuant to O 13 r 3(1) of the Rules. In the amended statement of claim, Dr Windsor has reformulated her claim for damages for breach of contract and has pleaded that she entered into an agreement with SMS to provide medical services on behalf of SMS on or about 8 January 2001 (para 5).

Section 31A of the Act and O 11 r 16 of the Rules have different legislative concerns. In Imobilari , Finkelstein J (at [4] [6]) observed that s 31A of the Act is concerned with the ability to make a claim, and a court must look at the evidence to see whether a cause of action is disclosed, whereas O 11 r 16 of the Rules, on the other hand, is concerned with the adequacy of pleadings as a matter of law and not with facts or evidence outside the pleadings.

The amended statement of claim in compliance with O 11 r 2(a) of the Rules pleads the following statement of material facts upon which Dr Windsor relies: 
(1) That Dr Windsor and SMS entered into an agreement for the provision of medical services by Dr Windsor (para 5);
 
(2) that the agreement comprised certain express and implied terms (paras 6 and 7);
 
(3) that the terms of the agreement were varied (para 8);
 
(4) that the agreement, as varied, was breached by SMS (para 14); and
 
(5) that the breaches caused Dr Windsor to terminate the agreement (para 15); and
 
(6) that Dr Windsor has suffered loss (para 17).

The amended statement of claim discloses a reasonable cause of action for breach of contract by Dr Windsor against SMS. There are no grounds upon which the pleaded amended statement of claim constitutes an abuse of process. In these circumstances, it was submitted that the Court should find that SMS has not satisfied the onus of demonstrating that the amended statement of claim discloses no reasonable cause of action or is otherwise an abuse of process within O 11 r 16 of the Rules and, accordingly, refuse to strike out the amended statement of claim.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c10">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Jefferson Ford Pty Limited v Ford Motor Company of Australia Limited [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2008/60.html</AustLII>
<text>A Full Court of this Court considered the application of s 31A in Jefferson Ford Pty Limited v Ford Motor Company of Australia Limited [2008] FCAFC 60 ; (2008) 167 FCR 372 (Finkelstein, Rares and Gordon JJ). Finkelstein J stated that s 31A of the Act is to be given a 'substantial operation' which requires the 'judge to conduct what might loosely be described as a preliminary trial' and to look closely to a party's 'assertion that there is a real question of law or fact to be decided' (at [23]). About factual issues Finkelstein J (at [20]) stated that the task of prediction was fraught with all kinds of difficulties including the Court, in many cases, not having before it all the material evidence, and if credit is involved the impossibility of predicting how that issue would be resolved. Even if the dispute is only a question of law, that issue may be difficult to resolve; or to predict its resolution, in the absence of detailed argument such as only occurs at a trial. Then Finkelstein J stated (at [23]) that the task of the judge is 'to decide whether the opposing party has evidence of sufficient quality and weight to be able to succeed at trial' and on questions of law the task of the judge is to determine whether the question of law is 'sufficiently strong to warrant a trial' (at [23]). Rares J favoured the test he stated in Boston Commercial and noted that that the correctness of that test did not need to be examined because 'neither party challenged that test' (at [73]). Gordon J identified a number of principles which 'inform' the application of s 31A of the Act. Among these are: (1) that s 31A is less stringent than the General Steel Industries standard; (2) that each case must be determined separately; (3) where there is a real issue of fact it is unlikely that that part of the proceeding has no prospect of success; (4) in determining whether a real issue of fact exists the Court must draw all available reasonable inferences in favour of the non-moving party (at [124] [132]). Gordon J at [126] stated that the assessment that a proceeding has no reasonable prospects of success will necessarily require: 
 1. Identification of the cause of action pleaded;
 2. identification of the pleaded facts said to give rise to that cause of action; 
 a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in support of the claim for judgment; 
 4. identification of the defence pleaded; 
 identification of any facts pleaded which are said to give rise to the defence; and 
 6. a review of the evidence (if any) tendered in defence of the claim.

Jefferson Ford was considered by a Full Court of this Court in Bond v Barry (2008) 173 FCR 106 (Sundberg, Jacobson and Lander JJ) but declined to express a view on which of the competing views in Jefferson Ford of the application of s 31A of the Act was correct (at [74]). (ii) Application of the general principles to this proceeding

In conclusion, it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that, whether the Court applies the standard adopted by Rares J in Boston Commercial , the principles identified by Gordon J in Jefferson Ford or, the tasks of the judge in considering an application under s 31A of the Act identified by Finkelstein J in Jefferson Ford , the Court should find that SMS has not satisfied the onus of demonstrating that Dr Windsor has no reasonable prospects of prosecuting the proceedings within s 31A(2) of the Act.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c11">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Jones v Insole (1891) 64 LT 703 </tocase>
<text>An order striking out a statement of claim on the ground that it fails to disclose a reasonable cause of action is interlocutory and not a final order ( Jones v Insole (1891) 64 LT 703 , a decision of the English Court of Appeal; cited with approval by Taylor J (with whom Owen J agreed) in Hall v The Nominal Defendant [1966] HCA 36 ; (1966) 117 CLR 423 at 440, where his Honour said: 
 The same view [ie that the order was interlocutory] was taken of an order striking out a plaintiff's statement of claim on the ground that it disclosed no reasonable cause of action: Jones v Insole and of an order dismissing an action as frivolous and vexatious in In re Page .
 (Citations omitted)

In this Court, Burchett J in Weatherall v Satellite Receiving Systems (Australia) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 741 ; (1999) 92 FCR 101 at [9] after reviewing both English and Australian authorities (including Jones v Insole and Hall v The Nominal Defendant ) concluded that an order striking out a statement of claim is an interlocutory order. Burchett's J analysis in Weatherall was cited with approval by Cowdroy J in Md Abdullah Al Mamun v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 541.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c12">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Leppington Pastoral Co Pty Limited v Commonwealth of Australia (1997) 76 FCR 318 </tocase>
<text>An example of an abuse of process is where interlocutory orders, though not truly able to found an issue estoppel, may be capable of finally determining an issue of fact or law if 'it is reasonable to regard the earlier decision as a final determination of the issue' ( Re Martin &amp; Anor; Ex parte Amtron Australia Pty Limited (1996) 62 FCR 438 per Cooper J at 443) or the parties have conducted the litigation 'upon the footing that this part of the proceedings is to be then determined, to that extent, finally' ( Leppington Pastoral Co Pty Limited v Commonwealth of Australia (1997) 76 FCR 318 per Beaumont J (with whom Jenkinson and Lehane JJ agreed)) or 'a reasonable construction of the interlocutory judgment shows that a point has been the subject of a final determination' ( Northern Star Agriculture Pty Ltd v Morgan and Banks Developments Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 98 per Young CJ in Eq at [42]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c13">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Md Abdullah Al Mamun v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 541</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/541.html</AustLII>
<text>In this Court, Burchett J in Weatherall v Satellite Receiving Systems (Australia) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 741 ; (1999) 92 FCR 101 at [9] after reviewing both English and Australian authorities (including Jones v Insole and Hall v The Nominal Defendant ) concluded that an order striking out a statement of claim is an interlocutory order. Burchett's J analysis in Weatherall was cited with approval by Cowdroy J in Md Abdullah Al Mamun v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 541.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c14">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Miller v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 38 ATR 51 </tocase>
<text>Interlocutory orders, by nature, lack finality. It follows, therefore, that they are insufficient to create an issue estoppel (see Wilson v Union Insurance Co [1992] NTSC 107 ; (1992) 112 FLR 166 ; cited with approval in Bowes v Fehlberg &amp; Ors (No 2) [2001] TASSC 24 at [22] and by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Miller v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 38 ATR 51. (iii) The facts and law the subject of the 2007 notice of motion were not conducted on a final basis</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c15">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Nominal Defendant v Manning [2000] NSWCA 80 ; (2000) 50 NSWLR 139</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2000/80.html</AustLII>
<text>It was nevertheless submitted on behalf of SMS that the amended statement of claim was a transparent attempt to re-litigate issues which have already been determined against Dr Windsor: '...proceedings before a court should be stayed as an abuse of process if, notwithstanding that the circumstances of the case do not give rise to an estoppel, their continuance would be unjustifiably vexatious and oppressive for the reason that it is sought to litigate anew a case which has already been disposed of by earlier proceedings' ( Walton v Gardiner (1993) 177 CLR 378 per Mason CJ, Deane and Dawson JJ at 393). Reference was also made to Nominal Defendant v Manning [2000] NSWCA 80 ; (2000) 50 NSWLR 139 per Heydon JA at 155 157 [70] [73] and per Foster A-JA at 167 [122] [123] and P. Dawson Nominees v ASIC (No. 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466 at [36] [49].

In response, it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that the principle articulated in Manning , to which I would merely observe, assuming a principle can be identified other than a preference for the view of Charles JA rather than the majority in D A Christie Pty Ltd v Baker (1996) 2 VR 582 , concerned, as did Dawson and Christie , the bringing of a second interlocutory application by an applicant or plaintiff; here, it was pointed out, on both occasions, Dr Windsor was resisting such an application and so, at best, any principle, if it can apply at all, could only be by way of analogy.

Next it was said that in Dawson , Goldberg J articulated the principle in terms of a threshold issue (at [49]), in respect of which the applicants carried the onus. Here there was no threshold issue because there was no onus on Dr Windsor. For that reason, any principle coming out of Manning and Dawson is not apt.

Third, it was submitted that if, contrary to the foregoing submissions, I was to find that any principle coming out of Manning can apply by way of analogy to the present case, there were four reasons why it was fair and just to reconsider the matter rather than be persuaded that SMS had established the amended statement of claim was an abuse of process. These were put as follows: 
(1) Dr Windsor was self-represented on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion.
 
(2) I applied impermissible criteria in deciding the 2007 notice of motion clearly a strike-out application rather than confining myself to the pleadings; had I done the latter, I would have dismissed the 2007 notice of motion. I have already accepted this submission at [12] and [13] above.
 
(3) On the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion, the Court's attention was not drawn to the undecided question of law about whether post-contractual conduct and communications could be used to identify parties to the contract (see Dennis Pethybridge v Stedikas Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 154 ; (2007) Aust Contract R &#167;90-263 at [59] per Campbell JA (Beazley JA agreeing); Sagacious Procurements Pty Ltd v Symbion Health Ltd (formerly Mayne Group Ltd) [2008] NSWCA 149 at [99] ff per Giles JA (Hodgson and Campbell JJA agreeing); County Securities Pty Ltd v Challenger Group Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 193 at [161] per McColl JA), and at least some of the Judgment Documents fall within that category.
 
(4) The fact that on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion my attention was not drawn to admissions that were relied upon on the hearing of the current motion and, even if I did have regard to them on the earlier occasion, there is no indication on the face of the reasons for judgment that I interacted with them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c16">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Northern Star Agriculture Pty Ltd v Morgan and Banks Developments Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 98</tocase>
<text>An example of an abuse of process is where interlocutory orders, though not truly able to found an issue estoppel, may be capable of finally determining an issue of fact or law if 'it is reasonable to regard the earlier decision as a final determination of the issue' ( Re Martin &amp; Anor; Ex parte Amtron Australia Pty Limited (1996) 62 FCR 438 per Cooper J at 443) or the parties have conducted the litigation 'upon the footing that this part of the proceedings is to be then determined, to that extent, finally' ( Leppington Pastoral Co Pty Limited v Commonwealth of Australia (1997) 76 FCR 318 per Beaumont J (with whom Jenkinson and Lehane JJ agreed)) or 'a reasonable construction of the interlocutory judgment shows that a point has been the subject of a final determination' ( Northern Star Agriculture Pty Ltd v Morgan and Banks Developments Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 98 per Young CJ in Eq at [42]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c17">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>P. Dawson Nominees v ASIC (No. 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466</tocase>
<text>It was nevertheless submitted on behalf of SMS that the amended statement of claim was a transparent attempt to re-litigate issues which have already been determined against Dr Windsor: '...proceedings before a court should be stayed as an abuse of process if, notwithstanding that the circumstances of the case do not give rise to an estoppel, their continuance would be unjustifiably vexatious and oppressive for the reason that it is sought to litigate anew a case which has already been disposed of by earlier proceedings' ( Walton v Gardiner (1993) 177 CLR 378 per Mason CJ, Deane and Dawson JJ at 393). Reference was also made to Nominal Defendant v Manning [2000] NSWCA 80 ; (2000) 50 NSWLR 139 per Heydon JA at 155 157 [70] [73] and per Foster A-JA at 167 [122] [123] and P. Dawson Nominees v ASIC (No. 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466 at [36] [49].

In response, it was submitted on behalf of Dr Windsor that the principle articulated in Manning , to which I would merely observe, assuming a principle can be identified other than a preference for the view of Charles JA rather than the majority in D A Christie Pty Ltd v Baker (1996) 2 VR 582 , concerned, as did Dawson and Christie , the bringing of a second interlocutory application by an applicant or plaintiff; here, it was pointed out, on both occasions, Dr Windsor was resisting such an application and so, at best, any principle, if it can apply at all, could only be by way of analogy.

Next it was said that in Dawson , Goldberg J articulated the principle in terms of a threshold issue (at [49]), in respect of which the applicants carried the onus. Here there was no threshold issue because there was no onus on Dr Windsor. For that reason, any principle coming out of Manning and Dawson is not apt.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c18">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Pethybridge v Stedikas Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 154 ; (2007)</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2007/154.html</AustLII>
<text>Third, it was submitted that if, contrary to the foregoing submissions, I was to find that any principle coming out of Manning can apply by way of analogy to the present case, there were four reasons why it was fair and just to reconsider the matter rather than be persuaded that SMS had established the amended statement of claim was an abuse of process. These were put as follows: 
(1) Dr Windsor was self-represented on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion.
 
(2) I applied impermissible criteria in deciding the 2007 notice of motion clearly a strike-out application rather than confining myself to the pleadings; had I done the latter, I would have dismissed the 2007 notice of motion. I have already accepted this submission at [12] and [13] above.
 
(3) On the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion, the Court's attention was not drawn to the undecided question of law about whether post-contractual conduct and communications could be used to identify parties to the contract (see Dennis Pethybridge v Stedikas Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 154 ; (2007) Aust Contract R &#167;90-263 at [59] per Campbell JA (Beazley JA agreeing); Sagacious Procurements Pty Ltd v Symbion Health Ltd (formerly Mayne Group Ltd) [2008] NSWCA 149 at [99] ff per Giles JA (Hodgson and Campbell JJA agreeing); County Securities Pty Ltd v Challenger Group Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 193 at [161] per McColl JA), and at least some of the Judgment Documents fall within that category.
 
(4) The fact that on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion my attention was not drawn to admissions that were relied upon on the hearing of the current motion and, even if I did have regard to them on the earlier occasion, there is no indication on the face of the reasons for judgment that I interacted with them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c19">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Martin &amp; Anor; Ex parte Amtron Australia Pty Limited (1996) 62 FCR 438 </tocase>
<text>An example of an abuse of process is where interlocutory orders, though not truly able to found an issue estoppel, may be capable of finally determining an issue of fact or law if 'it is reasonable to regard the earlier decision as a final determination of the issue' ( Re Martin &amp; Anor; Ex parte Amtron Australia Pty Limited (1996) 62 FCR 438 per Cooper J at 443) or the parties have conducted the litigation 'upon the footing that this part of the proceedings is to be then determined, to that extent, finally' ( Leppington Pastoral Co Pty Limited v Commonwealth of Australia (1997) 76 FCR 318 per Beaumont J (with whom Jenkinson and Lehane JJ agreed)) or 'a reasonable construction of the interlocutory judgment shows that a point has been the subject of a final determination' ( Northern Star Agriculture Pty Ltd v Morgan and Banks Developments Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 98 per Young CJ in Eq at [42]).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c20">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Sagacious Procurements Pty Ltd v Symbion Health Ltd (formerly Mayne Group Ltd) [2008] NSWCA 149</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/NSWCA/2008/149.html</AustLII>
<text>Third, it was submitted that if, contrary to the foregoing submissions, I was to find that any principle coming out of Manning can apply by way of analogy to the present case, there were four reasons why it was fair and just to reconsider the matter rather than be persuaded that SMS had established the amended statement of claim was an abuse of process. These were put as follows: 
(1) Dr Windsor was self-represented on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion.
 
(2) I applied impermissible criteria in deciding the 2007 notice of motion clearly a strike-out application rather than confining myself to the pleadings; had I done the latter, I would have dismissed the 2007 notice of motion. I have already accepted this submission at [12] and [13] above.
 
(3) On the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion, the Court's attention was not drawn to the undecided question of law about whether post-contractual conduct and communications could be used to identify parties to the contract (see Dennis Pethybridge v Stedikas Holdings Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 154 ; (2007) Aust Contract R &#167;90-263 at [59] per Campbell JA (Beazley JA agreeing); Sagacious Procurements Pty Ltd v Symbion Health Ltd (formerly Mayne Group Ltd) [2008] NSWCA 149 at [99] ff per Giles JA (Hodgson and Campbell JJA agreeing); County Securities Pty Ltd v Challenger Group Holdings Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 193 at [161] per McColl JA), and at least some of the Judgment Documents fall within that category.
 
(4) The fact that on the hearing of the 2007 notice of motion my attention was not drawn to admissions that were relied upon on the hearing of the current motion and, even if I did have regard to them on the earlier occasion, there is no indication on the face of the reasons for judgment that I interacted with them.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c21">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Sea Culture International Pty Limited v Scoles [1991] FCA 523 ; (1991) 32 FCR 275</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/523.html</AustLII>
<text>The power to stay or dismiss a proceeding under O 20 r 5 of the Rules for an abuse of process is not limited to those cases in which proceedings are commenced or maintained where there is a res judicata or issue estoppel in respect of them. French J (as he then was) put it this way in Sea Culture International Pty Limited v Scoles [1991] FCA 523 ; (1991) 32 FCR 275 at 279: 
 An attempt to litigate in court a dispute or issue which has been resolved in earlier litigation in this or another court or tribunal may also, according to the circumstances, constitute an abuse of process even if not attracting the doctrines of res judicata or issue estoppel.

Nevertheless, the power to stay or dismiss must be 'very sparingly exercised and only in exceptional cases' (see Sea Culture International Pty Limited v Scoles at 279) and 'upon an examination of the relevant circumstances of the particular case before the Court' (see Spalla v St George Motor Finance Limited (No 6) [2004] FCA 1699 at [70] per French J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c22">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Spalla v St George Motor Finance Limited (No 6) [2004] FCA 1699 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2004/1699.html</AustLII>
<text>Nevertheless, the power to stay or dismiss must be 'very sparingly exercised and only in exceptional cases' (see Sea Culture International Pty Limited v Scoles at 279) and 'upon an examination of the relevant circumstances of the particular case before the Court' (see Spalla v St George Motor Finance Limited (No 6) [2004] FCA 1699 at [70] per French J).</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c23">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Spiteri v Nine Network Australia Pty Limited [2008] FCA 905</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/905.html</AustLII>
<text>I indicated my approval of these observations of Rares J in Spiteri v Nine Network Australia Pty Limited [2008] FCA 905 at [7] .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c24">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Walton v Gardiner (1993) 177 CLR 378</tocase>
<text>It was nevertheless submitted on behalf of SMS that the amended statement of claim was a transparent attempt to re-litigate issues which have already been determined against Dr Windsor: '...proceedings before a court should be stayed as an abuse of process if, notwithstanding that the circumstances of the case do not give rise to an estoppel, their continuance would be unjustifiably vexatious and oppressive for the reason that it is sought to litigate anew a case which has already been disposed of by earlier proceedings' ( Walton v Gardiner (1993) 177 CLR 378 per Mason CJ, Deane and Dawson JJ at 393). Reference was also made to Nominal Defendant v Manning [2000] NSWCA 80 ; (2000) 50 NSWLR 139 per Heydon JA at 155 157 [70] [73] and per Foster A-JA at 167 [122] [123] and P. Dawson Nominees v ASIC (No. 2) (2009) 255 ALR 466 at [36] [49].</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c25">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Weatherall v Satellite Receiving Systems (Australia) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 741 ; (1999) 92 FCR 101</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1999/741.html</AustLII>
<text>In this Court, Burchett J in Weatherall v Satellite Receiving Systems (Australia) Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 741 ; (1999) 92 FCR 101 at [9] after reviewing both English and Australian authorities (including Jones v Insole and Hall v The Nominal Defendant ) concluded that an order striking out a statement of claim is an interlocutory order. Burchett's J analysis in Weatherall was cited with approval by Cowdroy J in Md Abdullah Al Mamun v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 541.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c26">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Wilson v Union Insurance Co [1992] NTSC 107 ; (1992) 112 FLR 166 </tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nt/NTSC/1992/107.html</AustLII>
<text>Interlocutory orders, by nature, lack finality. It follows, therefore, that they are insufficient to create an issue estoppel (see Wilson v Union Insurance Co [1992] NTSC 107 ; (1992) 112 FLR 166 ; cited with approval in Bowes v Fehlberg &amp; Ors (No 2) [2001] TASSC 24 at [22] and by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Miller v Deputy Commissioner of Taxation (1997) 38 ATR 51. (iii) The facts and law the subject of the 2007 notice of motion were not conducted on a final basis</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>