<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Polaris Communications Pty Ltd (ACN 006 102 601) v Dynamic Hearing Pty Ltd (ACN 098 876 212) [2009] FCA 890 (18 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/890.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Butcher v Lachlan Elder Realty Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 60 ; (2004) 218 CLR 592</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/60.html</AustLII>
<text>Gleeson CJ, Hayne and Heydon JJ returned to the question in Butcher v Lachlan Elder Realty Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 60 ; (2004) 218 CLR 592 ( Butcher ) at [36]-[37]: 
 
 The relevant class addressed. Questions of allegedly misleading conduct, including questions as to what the conduct was, can be analysed from two points of view. One is employed in relation to "members of a class to which the conduct in question [is] directed in a general sense". The other, urged by the purchasers here, is employed where the objects of the conduct are "identified individuals to whom a particular misrepresentation has been made ..."; they are considered quite apart from any class into which they fall. Adoption of the former point of view requires isolation by some criterion or criteria of a representative member of the class ... 
 

 
 
 The former approach is common when remedies other than those conferred by s 82 (or s 87) of the Act are under consideration. But the former approach is inappropriate, and the latter is inevitable, in cases like the present, where monetary relief is sought by a plaintiff who alleges that a particular representation was made to identifiable persons, of whom the plaintiff was one.

The present case requires what in Butcher their Honours called the former approach looking at the impugned conduct through the eyes of members of the class to which it was directed in a general sense. Polaris is not complaining that it was misled by the representations in the comparison report. It is worried that whoever might have received the report could be misled. Thus it is necessary to identify the class of persons who, having received the report, are likely to be influenced by it.

The market for noise suppression devices of the kind referred to in the report consists of businesses which conduct call centres in Australia. Telstra is one such business. Mr Gherbaz, Plantronics' managing director, said the M15D was being developed for both the forthcoming Telstra RFT and for the general market. The comparison report was intended to be used and was used for the general market as well as to assist Plantronics in relation to the tender. He said the potential readers of the report would be Occupational Health and Safety (OH&amp;S) managers in organisations and call centre managers. They were the officers with whom Plantronics would deal in connection with enquiries about its devices and sales of them. Thus it was the OH&amp;S manager of Westpac who enquired of Mr Gherbaz about its products and what path to go down. He sent her a copy of the report.

The report was not made available to the general public.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 70 ; (2007) 159 FCR 397</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2007/70.html</AustLII>
<text>Plantronics relied on a passage in Mr McNeill's second affidavit in which he said that from his role in leading the design team for the M15D, he was aware that "the limiting regime provided for by limiting mode 3 causes the 125ms RMS speech average for the M15D to be limited to 95dB SPL at the drum reference point". Mr McNeill provided no reasoning or explanation to support this bald assertion. He was not in this affidavit relying on his February 2008 test, which had since his earlier affidavit been subjected to criticism by Mr Fisher. In Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 70 ; (2007) 159 FCR 397 at [108] the Full Court said: 
 
 unless a witness states in his or her evidence in chief the grounds and reasoning that have led to the opinion, the opinion is valueless. Before the Court can assess the value of an opinion, it must know the facts on which it is based. If the opinion is based on irrelevant facts or facts that are clearly not going to be proved, the opinion is likely to be valueless. It should not be for a cross-examiner to endeavour to elicit the facts or assumptions upon which an opinion is expressed, and it would be unfair to leave such matters to the cross-examiner. Except in a straightforward, uncomplicated case, where the facts are admitted or otherwise readily identified, opinion evidence would normally be rejected under s 135 if the facts or assumptions upon which the opinion is based are not expressly stated. 
 

 
 
 It is for the Court to judge the reliability of, and the weight to be given to, particular evidence. Opinion evidence, like any other evidence, must be comprehensible and reach conclusions that are rationally based. The process of inference or reasoning that leads to conclusions ought to be stated or revealed in a way that enables the conclusions to be tested and a judgment to be made about their reliability and the weight that should be given to them.

Polaris urged me to attach no weight to Mr McNeill's statement of his "awareness". This is far from being a "straightforward, uncomplicated case", and the evidence in issue is of central importance to the lowest limiting setting issue. Mr McNeill's assertion amounts to no more than that he knows something because of his expertise. I attach no weight to the assertion. Loudness and intelligibility

The difference between the two limiting settings was relied on by Polaris to show that louder sound was being heard on the M15D, which would have enhanced intelligibility compared with the sound heard at a lower level on SoundShield.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2000/12.html</AustLII>
<text>Whether conduct is misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive is a question of fact to be determined having regard to the entire context of the conduct including the background of all surrounding circumstances. One of those circumstances, in a case such as the present, is the class of persons to whom the conduct was directed. In Campomar Sociedad, Limitada v Nike International Ltd [2000] HCA 12 ; (2000) 202 CLR 45 at [103] the whole Court said: 
 
 Where [the class of consumers] are not identified individuals to whom a particular misrepresentation has been made ... but are members of a class to which the conduct in question was directed in a general sense, it is necessary to isolate by some criterion a representative member of that class. The inquiry thus is to be made with respect to this hypothetical individual why the misconception complained of has arisen or is likely to arise if no injunctive relief be granted.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Gardam v George Wills &amp; Co Ltd [1988] FCA 194 ; (1998) 82 ALR 415</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1988/194.html</AustLII>
<text>I am satisfied that the report was prepared by Dynamic in consultation with Plantronics. Mr Gherbaz suggested amendments and modifications to the document initially proposed by Dynamic. Plantronics was not a mere conduit for the carriage of information to those who received the report. The recipients would regard Plantronics as having adopted its contents, and thus as having made the representations contained in it. See Gardam v George Wills &amp; Co Ltd [1988] FCA 194 ; (1998) 82 ALR 415 at 427. I did not understand this matter to have been in dispute.

I will not at this stage make final orders. I will stand the matter over in order that the parties have an opportunity to consider the orders that should be made to give effect to these reasons, and to deal with the question of costs. If by 25 August 2009 the parties are unable to agree on the orders that should be made, Polaris should within seven days of that date file and serve a notice of the orders it proposes should be made together with an outline of submissions in support thereof, not to exceed five pages in length. Dynamic and Plantronics should each, within seven days of receipt of Polaris' notice and outline, file and serve a notice of the orders it proposes should be made together with an outline of submissions in support thereof, not to exceed five pages in length.
 I certify that the preceding two hundred and forty-two (242) numbered paragraphs are a true copy of the Reasons for Judgment herein of the Honourable Justice Sundberg. 
 
 Associate:
 
 
Dated: 18 August 2009
 
 Counsel for the Applicant: C Golvan SC and S Gatford 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicant: GSM Lawyers 
 
 Counsel for the First Respondent: R Kendall QC and M Lapirow 
 
 Solicitor for the First Respondent: Ebsworth &amp; Ebsworth 
 
 Counsel for the Second Respondent: P Crennan 
 
 Solicitor for the Second Respondent: Allens Arthur Robinson 
 Date of Hearing: 14-17, 20-23 April, 25-27 May, 4-5 June 2009 
 
 Date of Judgment: 18 August 2009 
 

 
 AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/890.html</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Gillette Australia Pty Ltd v Energizer Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 223 ; (2002) 193 ALR 629</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2002/223.html</AustLII>
<text>In Gillette Australia Pty Ltd v Energizer Australia Pty Ltd [2002] FCAFC 223 ; (2002) 193 ALR 629 the Full Court made some helpful observations about comparative advertising. Gillette and Energizer manufactured and distributed batteries. Gillette used the brand name "Duracell", and supplied alkaline batteries. Energizer used the brands "Energizer" and "Eveready". It supplied both alkaline and carbon zinc batteries. Alkaline batteries last longer but are more expensive than carbon batteries of the same size. Energizer sought to restrain Gillette's television advertisement which claimed that the Eveready Super Heavy Duty Battery (a carbon zinc battery) "just can't keep up", and that "with up to three times more power Duracell will always win", on grounds that included that the advertisement did not reveal that there was a substantial price differential between the two batteries, and thus consumers could be misled in comparing the value of the two. On that basis the trial judge granted an injunction. The Full Court allowed Gillette's appeal. Heerey J said at [20]: 
 
 The characterisation of advertising as comparative does not of itself have legal significance, or create any kind of presumption in favour of a party alleging a breach of Pt V of the TPA. There is no basis in the TPA for regarding comparative advertising as an inherently disreputable form of commercial conduct, to be viewed with suspicion by the courts. On the contrary, to the extent that comparative advertising provides consumers with accurate hard facts about competing products, it assists in the making of better informed consumer choices and thereby results in more effective competition. Of course, the more actual comparisons that are used, the more potential there is for error (and half-truth). So advertisers have to be careful ... Assertions of factual inaccuracy have to be carefully considered by courts in comparative advertising cases, no differently from any other cases.

Heerey J then rejected Energizer's contention that to compare the products without mentioning the price was not to make a full comparison and was thus unfair. His Honour said at [22]: 
 
 [The] textual basis [for the contention] is the heading of Div 1 of Pt V , "Unfair practices". But to use general notions of unfairness, which bring to mind the concept of unconscionable conduct appearing elsewhere in the TPA, is to put an unwarranted gloss on the plain words of provisions of Pt V such as ss 52(1) and 53 (a). Provided the factual assertions are not untrue, or misleading half-truths, an advertiser can lawfully compare a particular aspect of its product or service favourably with the same aspect of a competitor's product or service.

His Honour then considered an example that had been discussed in argument where airline X advertised that its economy class seats provide 20 cm more leg room than those of airline Y. If that claim is true, s 52 does not oblige airline X to provide in its advertisement detailed information as to the other factors which might influence consumers choosing between airlines. And if airline Y wanted to advertise that its fares were cheaper, its aircraft more modern, and its flights more frequent, that would be legitimate so long as "no untruths or misleading half-truths are stated": at [23].

Returning to the facts before him, Heerey J concluded at [24]: 
 
 A consumer, informed by the advertisement (correctly, it must be assumed for present purposes) that the Duracell battery lasts three times longer than the Eveready Super Heavy Duty battery, can make his or her decision at the point of sale whether the extra power of the Duracell is worth the higher price. I do not see how it could be said that such a consumer has been misled or deceived. Indeed, it would be inconsistent with the policy and objectives of the TPA to restrict a trader from publicising, truthfully, a feature of its product which is superior to the same feature of a competitor's product. 
 

 
His Honour went on to explain why that was so.

The other members of the Full Court were of the same opinion: Lindgren J at [53] (pages 646-647 point (7)) and Merkel J at [85], [91] and [93]. THE WITNESSES 
 Polaris

Trevor Guest established Polaris in 1981. It first manufactured SoundShield in 2001. Mr Guest has over 25 years experience in the sale of telecommunications equipment in Australia. He has no formal technical or scientific qualifications. However his experience in the manufacture, importation and sale of this equipment has exposed him to a wide variety of technical matters associated with sound regulation. He said he is familiar with the various technical standards that apply to telecommunication devices in Australia. He has personally installed SoundShields and other telecommunications equipment in a range of customer premises, has programmed SoundShield on numerous occasions and is familiar with the device and the settings contained within it.

Mr Guest swore four affidavits and wascross-examined at length. He came across as an honest witness. On one occasion, when he was describing a test he had done of SoundShield, he seemed to gild the lily by describing it as a comparative test of SoundShield and M15D. However, I think this was attributable to confusion on his part and was not an attempt to mislead the Court. He conceded that he was wrong to characterise his test as a comparative one. Mr Guest accepted that his lack of formal technical qualifications meant he could not express authoritative opinions about scientific, electronic and audiological matters. However, his long involvement in the acoustic protection device industry, his participation in the formulation of industry standards, and his hands on experience, provided sufficient basis for the evidence he gave as to the industry, the general effect of the standards and the mechanisms of SoundShield. I have emphasised the word "general" because Mr Guest was not seised of the detail of the standards or of the technical attributes of the various devices. The best example of this was his confusion about the headset profiles, when he was at odds with his own experts. In addition, Professor Blamey took exception to many of Mr Guest's measurements, in particular his unexplained transition between the different types of decibels dB, dBA, dB SPL at DRP as though they were all the same. Thus, on matters of a technical nature, I do not regard him as having the expertise to express opinions that can compete with those of acknowledged experts.

Ben Minski joined Polaris in 2004 as an account manager. More recently he has been the project/implementation manager of the major roll outs of SoundShields into call centres nationally. His experience includes installing over 20,000 SoundShields in approximately 80 call centres Australia wide, and he was consequently familiar with the device, the different technical settings contained within it, which settings best suit particular technical environments and users, and what happens if a device is not correctly customised to its particular environment and user. His evidence was largely uncontroversial. He was cross-examined. I thought him an honest witness, a conclusion that was confirmed by the fact that on one topic his evidence did not assist Polaris' case.

Rodney Thompson was in charge of the technical side of Polaris' business. He has tertiary electronic engineering qualifications, and experience as an engineer with Telstra and since 2006 with Polaris. He is familiar with the measurement of sound signals and signal levels generally, the various telecommunications standards in use in Australia, and what those standards mean in technical terms for the Australian telephone network and devices that operate in conjunction with it. He was cross-examined, and the concessions he made in the course of his evidence made it clear that he was giving a truthful account of matters on which he spoke.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Hoover (Australia) Pty Ltd v Email Ltd [1991] FCA 511 ; (1992) 104 ALR 369</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1991/511.html</AustLII>
<text></text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>