<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wilson v Northern Territory of Australia [2009] FCA 800 (31 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/800.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>King v Northern Territory of Australia [2007] FCA 944</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/944.html</AustLII>
<text>The area for which the determination is sought is, as mentioned above, various allotments in the locality of the town of Elliott. The determination area is part of Mudburra-Jingili country lying to the south and east of the determination area recognised in the matter of King v Northern Territory of Australia [2007] FCA 944. (Hereafter referred to as the Newcastle Waters matter.) The proximity of the determination area to that of Newcastle Waters is relevant to this proceeding as the Applicants are the same estate groups recognised as Native Title Holders by the Newcastle Waters Determination.

Schedule A of the parties minute of proposed orders describes the determination area by reference to lot and portion numbers and an accompanying map (referred to as schedule B) clearly identifies the location of all parcels. The parties' joint submission informs the Court that section 47 B of the Native Title Act 1993 (Cth) (the Act) have been met in relation to a number of the parcels, with the effect that any prior extinguishment of native title over these parcels can now be disregarded.

Section 87 of the Act sets out the Court's power to make orders sought by consent of the parties. That section requires the period of notice under s 66 of the Act to have elapsed, that a signed copy of the agreed orders has been filed with the Court, and that the Court is satisfied that the orders are within its power and appropriate to make.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lota Warria (on behalf of the Poruma and Masig Peoples) v State of Queensland (2005) 223 ALR 62</tocase>
<text>The discretion conferred by s 87(1) of the Act must be exercised judicially, and in exercising it, the Court must have regard to the object and purposes of the Act, one of the most important being the resolution of disputes by negotiation and agreement, rather than litigation Lota Warria (on behalf of the Poruma and Masig Peoples) v State of Queensland (2005) 223 ALR 62 at [7].

The words of the section make it clear that the question for the Court is whether it is appropriate to make an order in the terms of the agreement reached between the parties, with the central focus of the section being the existence of an agreement.

Satisfying the Court that it is appropriate for an order to be made should not be seen as the last hurdle to be overcome before the parties reach their ultimate goal of a consent determination of native title. Instead s 87 should be regarded as the opportunity for the Court to recognise the parties' success in reaching the ultimate goal of a negotiated agreement, and facilitating that agreement by making an appropriate determination in accordance with its terms.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Lovett on behalf of the Gunditjmara People v State of Victoria [2007] FCA 474</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2007/474.html</AustLII>
<text>As North J said in Lovett on behalf of the Gunditjmara People v State of Victoria [2007] FCA 474 at [61] : 
 
 " ... when the Court is examining the appropriateness of an agreement, it is not required to examine whether the agreement is grounded on a factual basis which would satisfy the Court at a hearing of the application. The primary consideration of the Court is to determine whether there is an agreement and whether it was freely entered into on an informed basis...."</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Munn (for and on behalf of the Gungari People) v Queensland (2001) FCA 1229</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/1229.html</AustLII>
<text>In Munn v Queensland [2001] FCA 1229 Emmett J observed that the Court's deliberations on an application under s 87: 
 "... would include a consideration of the extent to which the State is a party, on the basis that the State, or at least a Minister of State, appears in the capacity of parens patriae to look after the interests of the community generally. The mere fact that the State was a party may not be sufficient. The Court may need to be satisfied that the State has in fact taken a real interest in the proceeding in the interests of the community generally. That may involve the Court being satisfied that the State has given appropriate consideration to the evidence that has been adduced, or intended to be adduced, in order to reach the compromise that is proposed. The Court, in my view, needs to be satisfied at least that the State, through competent legal representation, is satisfied as to the cogency of the evidence upon which the applicants rely."

The terms of the agreement between the parties are in writing, the agreement is signed by or on behalf of the parties and the agreement is filed with the Court. The parties have had the benefit of independent and competent legal representation in arriving at this agreement, the terms of the order are clear and the agreement has been produced as a result of a process of negotiation. In this matter the Northern Territory is the sole respondent party. It is clear on the evidence before me that it has taken a real and significant interest in the proceedings. Before the proposed consent orders were signed the Northern Territory had Emeritus Professor Sansom, who had also been the expert anthropologist for the Northern Territory in the Newcastle Waters matter, consider the anthropological material going to the existence of native title. Professor Sansom's queries in relation to the material initially provided in this matter were subsequently answered to his satisfaction by the applicants. Furthermore, the Northern Territory Cabinet considered the proposed consent orders and instructed the Solicitor for the Northern Territory to agree to the proposed consent determination of native title. I am therefore satisfied that the interests of the community generally have been properly considered by the Northern Territory.

There can be no doubt about the jurisdiction of the Court to make the orders sought (see s 81 of the Act) and there is nothing in the agreed terms that would suggest that the power of the Court would be exceeded. The proposed order set out details of each of the matters mentioned in s 225 thus satisfying the requirements of s 94A of the Act.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>