<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>EMAS Offshore Pte Ltd v The Ship "APC Aussie 1" [2009] FCA 872 (31 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/872.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Port of Geelong Authority v The "Bass Reefer" [1992] FCA 378 ; (1992) 37 FCR 374</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1992/378.html</AustLII>
<text>Where a demise charter had been terminated before the plaintiff applied to amend to an existing writ, Foster J said in Port of Geelong Authority v The "Bass Reefer" [1992] FCA 378 ; (1992) 37 FCR 374 at 389 that, as a matter of discretion, he would not allow an amendment where some items covered by the requested amendment might arguably be maritime claims but others not. He adverted to difficulties that obviously might arise if the writ were to be amended at that time after the charterer had ceased to be a relevant person. Like his Honour, I have difficulty in seeing that the grant of the requested amendment would be just or appropriate in all the circumstances: see too r 17(1) of the Admiralty Rules .

I am of opinion that, as a matter of my discretion, I should not allow this amendment, so as to permit this claim to be made in this way at this time. The claim is, in effect, against the property of the owner of the vessel, APC Marine, when the owner will not be able to have recourse, in the circumstances, to its current demise charterer because T-D has ceased to have any connection with the vessel.

In addition, although I do not express these views for the purposes of my decision, it is desirable to say that in my view s 18 of the Act does not appear to me, at the moment, to support the present claim. That section contemplates that when an action in rem is commenced the, or a, maritime claim will be connected temporally by the coincidence of possession of a demise charterer who is liable and the cause of action asserted as a, or part of a, maritime claim. I will assume for the moment that EMAS' claim for indemnity, is a maritime claim under s 4(3)(j) or (m) in respect of towage of the barge or a claim in respect of goods, materials or services supplied to it for its operation or maintenance (i.e. necessaries). However, each of those categories is a matter about which there is a considerable amount of learning and which may or may not be correct in respect of the present proceedings.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>discussed</class>
<tocase>Tisand Pty Limited v The Owners of the Ship MV "Cape Moreton" (Ex Freya) [2005] FCAFC 68 ; (2005) 143 FCR 43</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCAFC/2005/68.html</AustLII>
<text>In Tisand Pty Limited v The Owners of the Ship MV "Cape Moreton" (Ex Freya) [2005] FCAFC 68 ; (2005) 143 FCR 43 Ryan and Allsop JJ, particularly at 68-74 [100]-[122] engaged in a substantial and learned discussion of the importance of identifying persons with a proprietary interest as owner or demise charterer in arrest proceedings, albeit that they concentrated on the question of ownership. They said that in ss 17 , 18 and 19 of the Act, the phrase "the owner" was used in a proprietary sense, reflecting the clear purpose of the Act to require that the property proposed to be arrested belong to the relevant person: The "Cape Moreton" 143 FCR at 73 [118]. Here, that approach must be adapted to the special provisions of s 18 in relation to a demise charterer being the relevant person.

At the time of the arrest of the "APC Aussie 1" , T-D was the relevant person, as the existing demise charterer. T-D was the contracting party with EMAS under the charter for her towage. But, at the present time T-D is not capable of being a relevant person in respect of the barge because the demise charter has been terminated and APC Marine, as owner, has retaken possession. T-D now has no proprietary interest in the barge, yet EMAS is seeking to extend the ambit of the security for which the arrest was obtained to a cause of action not previously contemplated in either the writ or the amended writ. If granted, the amendment would have the effect of greatly expanding the amount of security that EMAS could require for release of the " APC Aussie 1 " before its owner would be able to exercise its proprietary rights, even though the new claim involves no direct relationship between EMAS and APC Marine. There may be occasions (that were not suggested during the hearing) in which it is possible to argue that such an amendment could be appropriate. It is for that reason that I do not wish to express a final view on this question and instead have exercised my discretion to refuse the application to amend.

The reality is that EMAS seeks to utilise the earlier arrest of the barge, to bring pressure on APC Marine well after EMAS became aware of the existence of APC Marine's Singaporean writ and in circumstances in which EMAS has delayed making the application to amend until after the intervening event of APC Marine's termination of its charterparty with T-D.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Shell Oil Company v The Ship "Lastrigoni" [1974] HCA 27 ; (1974) 131 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1974/27.html</AustLII>
<text>Proceedings in Admiralty are intended to facilitate the enforcement of liabilities and not to allow pressure to be put on a person who is himself under no liability in respect of the liabilities of others: Shell Oil Company v The Ship "Lastrigoni" [1974] HCA 27 ; (1974) 131 CLR 1 at 6 per Menzies J; cp Owners of MV "Iron Amanat" v KMP Coastal Oil Pte Ltd [1999] HCA 11 ; (1999) 196 CLR 130 at 139 [22] per Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ. In my opinion, it would not be right, or just, in the present circumstances to allow the amendment to be made so as to permit APC Marine's property to stand as security for EMAS' claim to be entitled to indemnity from T-D under cl 14 of their charterparty for any claim T-D makes against EMAS based on a liability T-D may have to APC Marine.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Owners of MV "Iron Amanat" v KMP Coastal Oil Pte Ltd [1999] HCA 11 ; (1999) 196 CLR 130</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1999/11.html</AustLII>
<text>Proceedings in Admiralty are intended to facilitate the enforcement of liabilities and not to allow pressure to be put on a person who is himself under no liability in respect of the liabilities of others: Shell Oil Company v The Ship "Lastrigoni" [1974] HCA 27 ; (1974) 131 CLR 1 at 6 per Menzies J; cp Owners of MV "Iron Amanat" v KMP Coastal Oil Pte Ltd [1999] HCA 11 ; (1999) 196 CLR 130 at 139 [22] per Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow, Kirby and Hayne JJ. In my opinion, it would not be right, or just, in the present circumstances to allow the amendment to be made so as to permit APC Marine's property to stand as security for EMAS' claim to be entitled to indemnity from T-D under cl 14 of their charterparty for any claim T-D makes against EMAS based on a liability T-D may have to APC Marine.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>