<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rinka v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 886 (14 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/886.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1995/20.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273 ( Teoh ), the High Court held (McHugh J dissenting) that procedural fairness required that if a relevant decision maker proposed to make a decision inconsistent with Article 3 of the Convention, procedural fairness required the decision maker to inform the person affected and provide to that person the opportunity of presenting a case against the taking of such a course. The reason was that ratification by Australia of an international convention engendered a "legitimate expectation" that administrative decision makers would act in conformity with that convention. Mr Karp has drawn attention to the fact that the expression has perhaps fallen into disuse since Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 , see especially at [61]-[64] and [81]-[83] per McHugh and Gummow JJ, [121] per Hayne J, [148] per Callinan J. In view of the way in which the present case was argued, I need say no more of this.

Quite apart from Teoh , the Direction provided a basis for a legitimate expectation that the Minister would treat the best interests of the child as a primary consideration when deciding whether to cancel Mr Rinka's visa. This expectation was created by the fact that the letter of 20 February 2006 notifying Mr Rinka of the Minister's intention to consider cancelling his visa stated that the decision-maker would have regard to the Direction in coming to a decision.

I will first address the question whether the best interests of Mr Rinka's children were in fact treated as a primary consideration by the Minister. Briefing Paper

The briefing paper to the Minister, headed "Issues for Consideration of Possible Cancellation of a Visa under s 501(2) of the Migration Act 1958 ", was structured by reference to the Direction. Since it was plain that Mr Rinka failed to pass the character test, there was little discussion of that matter. The Minister's "Discretion" was considered under the headings "Primary Considerations", "Other Considerations" and "Other International Obligations". Three Primary Considerations were discussed: "Protection of the Australian Community", "The Expectations of the Australian Community" and "The Best Interests of the Child".</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2003/6.html</AustLII>
<text>In Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Teoh [1995] HCA 20 ; (1995) 183 CLR 273 ( Teoh ), the High Court held (McHugh J dissenting) that procedural fairness required that if a relevant decision maker proposed to make a decision inconsistent with Article 3 of the Convention, procedural fairness required the decision maker to inform the person affected and provide to that person the opportunity of presenting a case against the taking of such a course. The reason was that ratification by Australia of an international convention engendered a "legitimate expectation" that administrative decision makers would act in conformity with that convention. Mr Karp has drawn attention to the fact that the expression has perhaps fallen into disuse since Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs; Ex parte Lam [2003] HCA 6 ; (2003) 214 CLR 1 , see especially at [61]-[64] and [81]-[83] per McHugh and Gummow JJ, [121] per Hayne J, [148] per Callinan J. In view of the way in which the present case was argued, I need say no more of this.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Wan v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 568 ; (2001) 107 FCR 133</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2001/568.html</AustLII>
<text>Mr Rinka submits that the Minister failed to identify what the best interests of the children indicated she should decide with respect to the cancellation of Mr Rinka's visa, and that the Minister therefore did not treat the best interests of the children as a primary consideration in reaching her decision. In making these submission, Mr Rinka relies on Wan v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 568 ; (2001) 107 FCR 133 ( Wan ) (see, particularly, [26]-[27], [31]).

Mr Rinka submits that the concept of the best interests of the children involved consideration of their relationship with Mr Rinka. He submits that the Minister had before her the older son's letter saying that he misses his father and speaking of his exploits at soccer, yet she did not refer to this material in her statement of reasons.

Counsel for Mr Rinka accepts that this alone does not show jurisdictional error, but submits that, in combination with the "speculative" comments made by the Minister in para 81 of her statement of reasons, it does suggest that she did not give proper, genuine and realistic consideration to the material that was before her. If she did not, it would follow that the best interests of the children also could not have been given proper, genuine and realistic consideration. Consideration

Wan , on which Mr Rinka relied, concerned an appeal to the Court from a decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal (AAT) affirming a decision of the Minister to refuse to grant a permanent residence (general-spouse) visa on character grounds. It was also a "best interests of the child" case.

There were provisions of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) governing the procedure of the AAT that have no relevance in the circumstances of the present case. Nonetheless, the Full Court's holding in Wan that in order to treat the best interests of the child as a primary consideration, a decision maker must identify what those interests indicate the decision should be, is applicable. The Full Court held that the AAT did not do so. An alternative ground for the Full Court's decision was that the conclusion was inescapable that the AAT had not treated the best interests of the child as "a primary consideration".

As indicated earlier, although the Minister's statement of reasons does not say in terms that "the best interests" of Mr Rinka's children dictated that his visa not be cancelled, that is the effect of para 83. Moreover, the Minister did say that she was treating the best interests of Mr Rinka's children as a primary consideration, and it is not shown that her statement to that effect should not be accepted.

In the result, in my opinion the Minister's statement of reasons shows that the Minister treated the best interests of Mr Rinka's two children as a primary consideration, as she said she did in the first sentence of para 80.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>