<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Robbins v Sons of Gwalia Ltd [2009] FCA 96 (6 February 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/96.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Bankinvest AG v Seabrook (1988) 14 NSWLR 711</tocase>
<text>The approach to be followed in considering this application is well-settled. In Bankinvest AG v Seabrook (1988) 14 NSWLR 711 at 714, Street CJ described the question as a "nuts and bolts" management decision as to which court, in the pursuit of the interests of justice, is the more appropriate to hear and determine the substantive dispute. There is no principle to be enunciated other than the necessity of applying the specific considerations stated in the cross-vesting legislation; the primary amongst them being the pursuit of the interests of justice. Rogers A-JA, with whom Kirby P agreed, said at 727 that the only "lodestar" that a judge may steer by is what to do in the interests of justice. His Honour observed that it is inapt to speak in terms of onus.

Rogers A-JA also referred, at 729, to the expense and inconvenience which must be taken into account in determining which court is the more appropriate. His Honour also observed, at 725, that it is important to give full effect to the imaginative and detailed code laid down by the cross-vesting legislation for ensuring that throughout Australia, disputes are dealt with by the one court and that be the court which is most appropriate for the particular dispute.

In BHP Billiton Limited v Schultz [2004] HCA 61 ; (2004) 221 CLR 400 , Gleeson CJ, McHugh and Heydon JJ observed, at [7], that the criterion for transfer established in section 5 is that it is in the interests of justice that the proceedings be determined in the other court. Their Honours, at [13], referred, with apparent approval, to the remarks of Street CJ in Bankinvest . Their Honours also went on to say, at [14], that the exercise is not one of determining whether the particular court's jurisdiction has been regularly invoked; rather, the court hearing such an application is required to ensure that cases are heard in the forum dictated by the interests of justice.

A scheme has been established for the shareholder claims to be the subject of the representative action which has now been brought in the WA Supreme Court. It is in the interests of justice that account be taken of the scheme and the need to avoid unnecessary duplication of the costs. Moreover, as their Honours observed in BHP Billiton v Schultz , the interests of justice are wider than those of the parties to the proceedings and, here, it is important to take into account the interests of the creditors generally. It cannot be in the interests of the creditors of SOG to have two related proceedings running in two separate jurisdictions. The observations made by Rogers A-JA in Bankinvest also support this factor as a relevant one to take into account in determining the interests of justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>BHP Billiton Limited v Schultz [2004] HCA 61 ; (2004) 221 CLR 400</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/2004/61.html</AustLII>
<text>In BHP Billiton Limited v Schultz [2004] HCA 61 ; (2004) 221 CLR 400 , Gleeson CJ, McHugh and Heydon JJ observed, at [7], that the criterion for transfer established in section 5 is that it is in the interests of justice that the proceedings be determined in the other court. Their Honours, at [13], referred, with apparent approval, to the remarks of Street CJ in Bankinvest . Their Honours also went on to say, at [14], that the exercise is not one of determining whether the particular court's jurisdiction has been regularly invoked; rather, the court hearing such an application is required to ensure that cases are heard in the forum dictated by the interests of justice.

A scheme has been established for the shareholder claims to be the subject of the representative action which has now been brought in the WA Supreme Court. It is in the interests of justice that account be taken of the scheme and the need to avoid unnecessary duplication of the costs. Moreover, as their Honours observed in BHP Billiton v Schultz , the interests of justice are wider than those of the parties to the proceedings and, here, it is important to take into account the interests of the creditors generally. It cannot be in the interests of the creditors of SOG to have two related proceedings running in two separate jurisdictions. The observations made by Rogers A-JA in Bankinvest also support this factor as a relevant one to take into account in determining the interests of justice.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>referred to</class>
<tocase>Re Wilcox; ex parte Venture Industries Pty Limited (1996) 66 FCR 511</tocase>
<text>The other legislative provisions on which SOG and the administrators rely state the criteria for the exercise of the power to transfer proceedings in terms which may be said to be less prescriptive than under the cross-vesting legislation. The power to transfer under the Trade Practices Act is stated in discretionary terms. In Re Wilcox; ex parte Venture Industries Pty Limited (1996) 66 FCR 511 at 529, the Full Court said that: 
 [A] manifest object of the cross-vesting legislative scheme as enacted by the Commonwealth in 1987 was for the [ Trade Practices Act ] and the [ Cross-Vesting Act ] to provide separate, albeit overlapping, but additional sources ... of power ...

Under section 1337H of the Corporations Act , the Federal Court is not required to consider whether the proceedings arise out of or are related to another proceeding.

The background to these matters is set out in the affidavit of Darren Gordon Weaver sworn on 18 June 2008. Mr Weaver is one of the respondents to the proceedings and is one of the administrators of SOG. It is convenient to refer to the content of Mr Weaver's affidavit.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>