<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZIFJ v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 911 (17 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/911.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZIFJ v Minister for Immigration [2008] FMCA 1170</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2008/1170.html</AustLII>
<text>On 30 January 2006, an application was made to the Federal Magistrates Court for the judicial review of the Tribunal's decision of 22 April 2003. In the result, that application was successful: see the reasons for judgment of the Federal Magistrates Court in SZIFJ v Minister for Immigration [2008] FMCA 1170 , delivered 25 August 2008. As a result of that successful challenge, the case was remitted for hearing afresh on the merits in the Tribunal.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>SZIFJ v Minister for Immigration [2009] FMCA 501</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FMCA/2009/501.html</AustLII>
<text>On 30 December 2008, a differently constituted Tribunal affirmed, once again, the decision of the Minister's delegate not to grant the Appellant a protection visa. A further challenge by way of judicial review proceedings in the Federal Magistrates Court followed. On this occasion, the Appellant was unsuccessful. On 27 May 2009, the Federal Magistrates Court dismissed the Appellant's application for judicial review: see SZIFJ v Minister for Immigration [2009] FMCA 501.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>applied</class>
<tocase>H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348 ; (2000) 63 ALD 43</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2000/1348.html</AustLII>
<text>In that regard it should not be assumed that these grounds also can be advanced as of right. On behalf of the Minister it was highlighted, correctly, with respect, that, not having been bases of challenge in the Federal Magistrates Court to the second Tribunal's decision, leave to raise these grounds was necessary: see H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348 ; (2000) 63 ALD 43. In their joint judgement in that case (at para 7, p 45) Branson and Katz JJ draw attention to an observation earlier made in the High Court in Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1 at 7: 
 It is fundamental to the due administration of justice that the substantial issues between the parties are ordinarily settled at the trial. If it were not so, the main area for the settlement of disputes would move from the court of first instance to the appellate court tending to reduce the proceedings in the former court to little more than a preliminary skirmish.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1986/33.html</AustLII>
<text>In that regard it should not be assumed that these grounds also can be advanced as of right. On behalf of the Minister it was highlighted, correctly, with respect, that, not having been bases of challenge in the Federal Magistrates Court to the second Tribunal's decision, leave to raise these grounds was necessary: see H v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] FCA 1348 ; (2000) 63 ALD 43. In their joint judgement in that case (at para 7, p 45) Branson and Katz JJ draw attention to an observation earlier made in the High Court in Coulton v Holcombe [1986] HCA 33 ; (1986) 162 CLR 1 at 7: 
 It is fundamental to the due administration of justice that the substantial issues between the parties are ordinarily settled at the trial. If it were not so, the main area for the settlement of disputes would move from the court of first instance to the appellate court tending to reduce the proceedings in the former court to little more than a preliminary skirmish.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 ; (2008) 103 ALD 589</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1270.html</AustLII>
<text>The basis upon which the second Tribunal decision was challenged before the Federal Magistrates Court was apprehended bias on the part of the Tribunal. In this Court that ground is not repeated in the notice of appeal. Rather the notice of appeal contains two grounds which are as follows: His Honour erred in failing to find that the Second Respondent failed to take into account relevant considerations.
 
Particulars
 
 
(a) The Second Respondent failed to consider whether or not the Appellant, by reason of his status as a repatriated asylum seeker, member of the ethnic majority belonged to a particular social group for the purposes of the Convention.
 
 His Honour, bound by authorities of this Court, erred in failing to find that the Second Respondent breached section 424AA of the Migration Act and in failing to find that the Second Respondent's breach of section 424AA gave rise to jurisdictional error.
 
Particulars
 
 
(a) The Appellant asserts that a number of matters decided by this Court were wrongly decided in relation to this point, including, but not limited to SZLXI v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1270 and SZLWI v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1330.

As to ground 2, there are decisions of judges of this Court in respect of s 424AA which hold that the extending of an oral invitation to provide information in response to particulars furnished by the Tribunal is permissive, rather than a matter of obligation. See SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 ; (2008) 103 ALD 589 ; and SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 ; (2008) 171 FCR 134. The ground of appeal invites me not to follow those decisions. I would only do that if I were persuaded that they are clearly wrong. On its face, the language of s 424AA is eloquent in the contrast between the use of the word "may" in para (a), and the use of the word "must" in para (b). As a matter of construction, it seems to me that para (a) of s 424AA is, indeed, permissive. I am not persuaded, on the basis of that examination, that either of the decisions mentioned should not be followed.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 ; (2008) 171 FCR 134</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/2008/1330.html</AustLII>
<text>The basis upon which the second Tribunal decision was challenged before the Federal Magistrates Court was apprehended bias on the part of the Tribunal. In this Court that ground is not repeated in the notice of appeal. Rather the notice of appeal contains two grounds which are as follows: His Honour erred in failing to find that the Second Respondent failed to take into account relevant considerations.
 
Particulars
 
 
(a) The Second Respondent failed to consider whether or not the Appellant, by reason of his status as a repatriated asylum seeker, member of the ethnic majority belonged to a particular social group for the purposes of the Convention.
 
 His Honour, bound by authorities of this Court, erred in failing to find that the Second Respondent breached section 424AA of the Migration Act and in failing to find that the Second Respondent's breach of section 424AA gave rise to jurisdictional error.
 
Particulars
 
 
(a) The Appellant asserts that a number of matters decided by this Court were wrongly decided in relation to this point, including, but not limited to SZLXI v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1270 and SZLWI v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 1330.

As to ground 2, there are decisions of judges of this Court in respect of s 424AA which hold that the extending of an oral invitation to provide information in response to particulars furnished by the Tribunal is permissive, rather than a matter of obligation. See SZLXI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1270 ; (2008) 103 ALD 589 ; and SZLWI v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1330 ; (2008) 171 FCR 134. The ground of appeal invites me not to follow those decisions. I would only do that if I were persuaded that they are clearly wrong. On its face, the language of s 424AA is eloquent in the contrast between the use of the word "may" in para (a), and the use of the word "must" in para (b). As a matter of construction, it seems to me that para (a) of s 424AA is, indeed, permissive. I am not persuaded, on the basis of that examination, that either of the decisions mentioned should not be followed.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>