<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Combined Gunggandji People v State of Queensland [2009] FCA 979 (31 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/979.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Commissioner of Main Roads v The North Shore Gas Company Limited (1967) 120 CLR 118</tocase>
<text>Both the huts and the slab on which they stood were improvements within this definition, as were the gardens, fences and the lavatory. The definition includes things which would normally be characterized as fixtures, usually owned by the owner of the fee simple or, in the case of Crown land, the Crown. Section 361A clearly contemplates ownership of improvements by somebody other than the Crown or the holder of the fee simple title pursuant to a deed of grant. The intention cannot have been to authorize the grant of a lease to the owner of improvements who already held the fee simple title. In Commissioner of Main Roads v The North Shore Gas Company Limited (1967) 120 CLR 118 at 127, the majority of the High Court (Barwick CJ, McTiernan, Kitto and Taylor JJ) said: 
 Differences of opinion from time to time have arisen concerning the true meaning and operation of the principle expressed in the maxim "quicquid solo plantatur, solo cedit ..." but, primarily, it is applied to determine the right of the owner of land to things affixed to or imbedded in the soil. Whatever is fixed to the freehold is said to become part of it and is subjected to the same rights of property as the land itself ... . The presumption is said to be rebuttable and, it seems to us, it must be so when a statute empowers someone other than the owner of land to affix to or embed things in the soil and yet retain ownership of the things so affixed or embedded.

Section 361A seems necessarily to contemplate such a situation. As was pointed out in argument, ss 236, 237 and 238 of the Land Act 1962 also seem to have contemplated somebody other than the Crown owning improvements situated on Crown land. It has not been submitted that any person other than Mr Ludwick might own improvements erected by him on the Bukki block. Since the hearing in this matter, the Minister for Lands has indicated that he is satisfied that the two sheds stood on the land at the date of the deed of grant and that Mr Ludwick owned them. The Council is also satisfied as to those matters.

The State submits that although s 520(b) of the Land Act 1994 continues the application of s 361A to deeds of grant made prior to the commencement of that Act, it does not continue the operation of other relevant provisions of the Land Act 1962. Further, it submits that pursuant to s 511 of the Land Act 1994 , references in s 361A to provisions of the Land Act 1962 are to be taken as references to the corresponding sections in the Land Act 1994 . Counsel for Mr Ludwick submit that s 20 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1954 (Qld) (the "State Interpretation Act") preserves his rights pursuant to s 361A. Section 361A provides that the terms of any lease are to be in accordance with "the provisions of this Division", prima facie referring to Division V (Reservations in Deeds of Grant) which is contained in Part XI (Grants, Reserves and Reservations for Public Purposes). Further, s 361A expressly deprives the Minister for Lands of his capacity to refuse to approve a proposed lease pursuant to s 343 of the Land Act 1962 . The State submits that s 57 of the Land Act 1994 now imposes the requirement for ministerial approval, the effect of which would, presumably, also be negated by s 361A. The State submits that the conditions of any lease will be regulated by s 61 of the Land Act 1994 , and not by the "provisions of this Division". Mr Ludwick submits that s 343 (dealing with ministerial approval) and s 344 of the Land Act 1962 (dealing with conditions) continue to apply for the purposes of s 361A.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Abbott v Minister for Lands [1895] AC 425</tocase>
<text>The question as to whether ss 343 and 344 of the Land Act 1962 or ss 57 and 61 of the Land Act 1994 should be applied as imposing a requirement for ministerial approval of any lease and in fixing its term was, in argument, treated as dependent upon the nature of the entitlement derived by Mr Ludwick pursuant to s 361A. Broadly speaking counsel for Mr Ludwick submit that he obtained a right to a lease upon terms to be determined in accordance with the Land Act 1962. On that basis they submit that s 20(2)(c) of the State Interpretation Act applies so as to preserve such right. That section provides that the repeal or amendment of an Act does not affect a right, privilege or liability acquired, accrued or incurred thereunder. The State submits that Mr Ludwick has no accrued right to a lease but rather a "right arising from an Act" or a "right to take advantage of an enactment", such right being the right to take action in accordance with the law as it is at the time. In support of this argument the State relies upon a line of decisions commencing with Abbott v Minister for Lands [1895] AC 425 and ending with the decision of the Queensland Court of Appeal in Australand Corporation (Qld) Pty Ltd v Johnson [2008] 1 Qd R 203. I need only make brief comments concerning those cases.

In Abbott the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council, on appeal from the Supreme Court of New South Wales, considered legislation which permitted any person to tender for the conditional purchase of unsold Crown land. Such a purchase would normally have been subject to a condition requiring three years of bona fide continuous residence prior to grant of the freehold title. However, where the purchaser already held fee simple land a purchase of adjoining land would not have been subject to the condition of residence. At some stage the relevant statute was amended to remove the advantage previously available to existing landholders. The question was whether or not a landholder could purchase adjoining land upon the previous, more favourable conditions. At 431, the Judicial Committee said: 
 It may be, as Windeyer J. observes, that the power to take advantage of an enactment may without impropriety be termed a "right." But the question is whether it is a "right accrued" within the meaning of the enactment which has to be construed. 

 
 Their Lordships think not, and they are confirmed in this opinion by the fact that the words relied on are found in conjunction with the words "obligations incurred or imposed". They think that the mere right (assuming it to be properly so called) existing in the members of the community or any class of them to take advantage of an enactment, without any act done by an individual towards availing himself of that right, cannot properly be deemed a "right accrued" within the meaning of the enactment.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Australand Corporation (Qld) Pty Ltd v Johnson [2008] 1 Qd R 203</tocase>
<text>The question as to whether ss 343 and 344 of the Land Act 1962 or ss 57 and 61 of the Land Act 1994 should be applied as imposing a requirement for ministerial approval of any lease and in fixing its term was, in argument, treated as dependent upon the nature of the entitlement derived by Mr Ludwick pursuant to s 361A. Broadly speaking counsel for Mr Ludwick submit that he obtained a right to a lease upon terms to be determined in accordance with the Land Act 1962. On that basis they submit that s 20(2)(c) of the State Interpretation Act applies so as to preserve such right. That section provides that the repeal or amendment of an Act does not affect a right, privilege or liability acquired, accrued or incurred thereunder. The State submits that Mr Ludwick has no accrued right to a lease but rather a "right arising from an Act" or a "right to take advantage of an enactment", such right being the right to take action in accordance with the law as it is at the time. In support of this argument the State relies upon a line of decisions commencing with Abbott v Minister for Lands [1895] AC 425 and ending with the decision of the Queensland Court of Appeal in Australand Corporation (Qld) Pty Ltd v Johnson [2008] 1 Qd R 203. I need only make brief comments concerning those cases.

There is also a particularly useful summary of the question in Resort Management Services Ltd v Noosa Shire Council (1997) 2 Qd R 291, per McPherson JA at 298 and per Fryberg J at 301-308. I was also referred to the decision of the Queensland Court of Appeal in Australand . That matter concerned a statutory right to avoid a contract for the purchase of a prescribe interest in a managed investment scheme where the invitation to subscribe had been issued in contravention of a provision of the Corporations Law (now repealed). The provision was repealed with effect from 1 July 1998. In certain cases, the transitional provisions continued the operation of the section until 1 July 2000. On 8 September 2003 the appellants purported to avoid their contracts pursuant to the section. At first instance the primary Judge held that such avoidance was of no effect. The Court of Appeal upheld that decision. I was particularly referred to a passage in the judgment of Keane JA at [113]-[117]. That passage offers a useful commentary on the cases to which I have referred but, with great respect, it does not seem to take the matter any further.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c3">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Director of Public Works v Ho Po Sang [1961] AC 901</tocase>
<text>In Director of Public Works v Ho Po Sang [1961] AC 901, the Judicial Committee considered a matter arising under Hong Kong planning law. The law contemplated the exercise of a vice-regal discretion to permit rebuilding on land occupied by tenants of the owner. Relevantly, their Lordships observed at 922: 
 It may be, therefore, that under some repealed enactment a right has been given but that in respect of it some investigation or legal proceeding is necessary. The right is then unaffected and preserved. It will be preserved even if a process of quantification is necessary. But there is a manifest distinction between an investigation in respect of a right and an investigation which is to decide whether some right should or should not be given. Upon a repeal the former is preserved by the Interpretation Act. The latter is not.

His Honour referred to Ho Po Sang where the relevant party was held to have had only a "hope or expectation" and continued: 
 The rights conferred by the Aboriginal Lands Rights Act do not fall into this category. On the other hand the Act does not in terms expressly confer a right in the land on the applicant at the time the claim is made. It envisages that there will be an investigation by the Minister of the facts and if the facts establish that the conditions in the definition are satisfied the Minister is then bound to grant the claim. If the Minister refuses, the court on appeal again investigates the same matters but the onus is put on the Minister. As it seems to me, assuming the conditions were in fact satisfied, the Land Council did not merely have a right to have its claim investigated; it had a right to have the claim granted. If the Minister wrongly refused to grant it, it had the right to have the court grant it. The right might be said to be a conditional one, namely, conditional upon the relevant facts being established, but the right was nonetheless a right because it was conditional.

At 696 his Honour said: 
 These decisions satisfy me that a statutory right will be preserved notwithstanding the repeal or amendment of the statute even though the right can only be implemented by a non-discretionary decision of an official or a court, provided that the statutory machinery for obtaining that decision has been in set in train before the repeal or amendment.

The cases contemplate at least three distinct situations in which s 20 might be engaged. Firstly, the relevant legislation might create a right which, by force of the legislation, accrues without any qualification or requirement for further action. Such a right will survive repeal of the relevant legislation. Secondly, the legislation may confer a right upon persons having certain qualifications. Such legislation may contemplate an investigation to determine whether a particular person has the relevant qualifications. Using the language of Ho Po Sang , there may be a need for investigation to ascertain whether the requirement for such qualifications is satisfied. Such a right will also survive repeal of the relevant statute. That situation is to be distinguished from that in which an investigation is carried out for the purpose of determining whether or not a right should be granted. The former situation was considered by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in the Land Council case where it was said that a right which could only be implemented "by a non-discretionary decision of an official or a court" would survive, "provided that any statutory machinery has been set in train before the repeal or amendment." The "non-discretionary decision" seems to be the equivalent of the investigation contemplated in Ho Po Sang . Finally, where a particular procedure has been commenced, there may be a right to have the procedure completed in accordance with the statute in its unrepealed form. This was the case in Esber .

Pursuant to s 361A(2) the person "shown to own such improvements shall be entitled" to the grant of a lease. Much of the argument in this matter proceeded upon the basis that satisfaction of the Minister for Lands and the Council as to ownership of the improvements was a condition precedent to any right conferred upon the owner. However such an approach puts too much emphasis upon the form of the section and too little upon its clear intention. There can be no doubt that the intention was that the owner of improvements be entitled to a lease. It was necessary for the Council (as trustee) and the Minister for Lands to be satisfied that a particular person was the person entitled to a lease relating to the improvements in question. However that requirement seems to be a process of the kind contemplated in Ho Po Sang , namely an investigation necessary in order to give effect to an entitlement, rather than a condition precedent to such entitlement.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c4">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Mathieson v Burton (1970) 124 CLR 1</tocase>
<text>In Mathieson v Burton (1970) 124 CLR 1, the High Court was concerned with legislation which provided that following the death of a lessee of prescribed premises, a child of that lessee, over the age of 21 years, who was residing with the lessee immediately before his or her death, could, until grant of probate or letters of administration, continue to exercise the same rights of possession as the deceased lessee would have done had he or she lived. In 1968 the legislation was amended to narrow the class of protected person. The respondent to the appeal in the High Court was the daughter of a deceased lessee who had died in 1958. There had been no grant of probate or letters of administration. The daughter claimed the right to occupy the premises pursuant to the legislation in its unamended form. The High Court upheld her claim. In particular, at 23, Gibbs J said: 
 In my opinion when the Act of 1968 was passed the respondent had an existing right to continue in possession of the subject premises. That right had arisen out of, and had been defined by, reference to, facts that had occurred before the Act of 1968 was passed. On behalf of the appellant it was submitted that the so-called right was in truth merely an immunity or protection from eviction which endured only so long as the statutory provision creating it remained in force. With all respect, this submission gives insufficient force to the words of s. 83A(1); that subsection purports to create and confer a right of the same kind as the lessee would have had if he had lived and I can see no justification for ignoring these words and refusing to recognize as a right that which the legislature has expressly described as such. It is true that the right was both personal and temporary it was not capable of assignment and endured only until representation of the estate of the deceased lessee should be granted or until a court of competent jurisdiction should make an order to putting the respondent out of possession ... However, to say ... that the right "is of a qualified, limited and transitory nature" is to define or explain the nature of the right but is not to deny its existence.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c5">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>NSW Aboriginal Land Council v Minister Administering The Crown Lands (Consolidation) Act and the Western Lands Act (1988) 14 NSWLR 685</tocase>
<text>In NSW Aboriginal Land Council v Minister Administering The Crown Lands (Consolidation) Act and the Western Lands Act (1988) 14 NSWLR 685, the New South Wales Court of Appeal considered the terms of Aboriginal land rights legislation. Such legislation had provided that any transfer of land to an Aboriginal Land Council should be in fee simple. In May 1986 the Act was amended to provide that in certain circumstances, such land should be granted by way of lease in perpetuity. On 26 April 1984, the Land Council had applied to the Minister for the transfer of certain land. The Minister refused the claim. The Council appealed to the Land and Environment Court. On 3 September 1987 the Minister decided to approve the application to the extent of granting a lease in perpetuity under the amended legislation. In the Land and Environment Court, the Land Council sought a declaration that it was entitled to a transfer in fee simple. The Court of Appeal held that a statutory right would be preserved, notwithstanding the repeal or amendment of the statute, even if the right could only be implemented by a non-discretionary decision of an official or a court, provided that the statutory machinery for obtaining that decision had been set in force before the repeal or amendment. At 693-4, Hope JA, with whom the other members of the Court agreed, said: 
 In my opinion ... the power which s 36(7) confers upon the Land and Environment Court is not a discretionary power but a power which it is bound to exercise in favour of the claimant in the circumstances specified in the subsection. 

 
 What then is the nature of the right which the Land Council had after it had made its claim, when it claim was being investigated by the Minister, and when it lodged its appeal to the Land and Environment Court. It is easier first to say what it was not. It was not a mere right existing in the members of the relevant class of the community "to take an advantage of an enactment, without any act done by an individual towards availing himself of that right"..., nor was it a right to set in train an application for a grant which the Minister or on appeal, the court might, as a matter of discretion, grant or refuse. ...

The cases contemplate at least three distinct situations in which s 20 might be engaged. Firstly, the relevant legislation might create a right which, by force of the legislation, accrues without any qualification or requirement for further action. Such a right will survive repeal of the relevant legislation. Secondly, the legislation may confer a right upon persons having certain qualifications. Such legislation may contemplate an investigation to determine whether a particular person has the relevant qualifications. Using the language of Ho Po Sang , there may be a need for investigation to ascertain whether the requirement for such qualifications is satisfied. Such a right will also survive repeal of the relevant statute. That situation is to be distinguished from that in which an investigation is carried out for the purpose of determining whether or not a right should be granted. The former situation was considered by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in the Land Council case where it was said that a right which could only be implemented "by a non-discretionary decision of an official or a court" would survive, "provided that any statutory machinery has been set in train before the repeal or amendment." The "non-discretionary decision" seems to be the equivalent of the investigation contemplated in Ho Po Sang . Finally, where a particular procedure has been commenced, there may be a right to have the procedure completed in accordance with the statute in its unrepealed form. This was the case in Esber .

It is true that in the Land Council case, Hope JA added the additional requirement that any statutory mechanism have been commenced in order that the entitlement should survive repeal of the relevant statutory provision. In the present case, there is no requirement that the owner take any step for the purposes of s 361A. It was assumed in argument that the owner of improvements was to undertake the task of satisfying the Minister for Lands and the Council of his or her ownership. However the section does not say that, nor does it provide for any particular mechanism to be initiated by the owner. It is possible that Parliament contemplated that the Council or the Minister for Lands would investigate the ownership of improvements with a view to regularizing the position as to ownership and occupancy. The likelihood of such a statutory intention is increased when one considers that the legislation was, as I have said, designed to remedy some of the disadvantage suffered by a severely disadvantaged group in our society. The reference in s 361A(3) to an "application" for the Minister's approval of a lease is to an application by the Council. See s 343. I should also point out that use of the present tense "stands" in s 361A(2)(a) suggests that the entitlement arises at the date of the deed of grant.

In my view, the effect of s 361A is to confer a right upon the owner of improvements, subject only to satisfactory investigation of the question of his or her ownership. The right which an owner held pursuant to s 361A, prior to the repeal of the Land Act 1962, was a right to a lease in accordance with that Act. Such right would be within either the first or second category identified above. If the entitlement were to one lease for whatever period the Council decided upon, then that right would survive pursuant to s 20 of the State Interpretation Act. However I consider that s 361A should not be construed as authorizing the grant of only one lease.

Section 361A confers an entitlement upon a person who owns improvements on relevant land at a particular point in time. The section does not limit the period during which such a person holds that entitlement. If so entitled as at the date of the deed of grant, an owner will be so entitled for the rest of his or her life. This case provides an example of such an entitlement being addressed many years after the date of the deed of grant. It seems to have been assumed in argument that an owner is entitled to only one lease. Such an approach might not fulfil the apparent objective of allowing the owner of improvements to continue to enjoy the benefits of his or her improvements. The shorter the term of any lease, the less would be the capacity to enjoy such benefit. Section 32C(a) of the State Interpretation Act provides that words in the singular include the plural. It would be more in accordance with the intention of the section if it were read as authorizing the grant of a lease at any time during the life of a relevant person, and regardless of whether any lease had previously been granted pursuant to the section. In the event that such a lease expires during the owner's lifetime, another may be granted. The right to receive a lease is vested in the owner of improvements as at the date of the deed of grant. It cannot be transferred or pass by will or on intestacy. However, where a lease for a fixed term has been granted, and the lessee dies during the term, the right to the balance of the term will be an asset of the estate. Given that the entitlement is to receive a lease from time to time, the better view is that such lease is to be pursuant to the law as it stands at the time at which each lease is granted, and that s 361A should now be read, pursuant to s 511 of the Land Act 1994 , as referring to the relevant provisions of that Act.

Counsel for the State submits that s 361A requires that the improvements be situated on the land both at the date of the deed of grant and at the date on which any lease is granted. In my view s 361A should be construed as creating an entitlement to a lease as at the date of the deed of grant, and that subsequent removal of the improvements is irrelevant. The huts were still on the Bukki block as at date of the deed of grant. The foundation slab was, and remains, on the block, having been extended and incorporated into the larger hut. It is probable that there were also gardens, fences and a lavatory on the land at the date of the deed of grant. At least some of the fencing and gardens presently on the block probably pre-date the deed of grant. There is no doubt that there were improvements on the land on 27 October 1986, and that the slabs and, probably, some remnants of earlier fencing and gardens remain at the present time.

Section 361A(2) provides that the lease be of the land on which the improvements stand and, where the improvements involve a building or structure used as a residence, a reasonable area of land, being the immediate environs of the improvement. As to the purpose for which the land was used, the relevant time is again the date of the deed of grant. At the time that the Pollards moved on to their land at Bukki in late 1986 or early 1987, Mr Ludwick's niece was living in a small shed on the Bukki block. She resided there for about a year. It is more probable than not that either Mr Ludwick was living there as at 27 October 1986, or that his niece was so residing, or about to commence doing so. Both Mr Ludwick and Ms Yeatman said that their relationship commenced in about 1987. It is reasonable to infer that as at 27 October 1986 the land was being used as a residence. It is possible that it was vacant for a relatively short time, but more probable that it was occupied on that date. In any event a period of temporary vacancy would not detract from the fact that the improvements were being used as a residence. This is particularly so, given that when he left, Mr Ludwick apparently intended to return to the Bukki block after his sojourn at Bilma. His plans changed when he met Ms Yeatman in 1987, but it seems that he (and perhaps they) always intended to move to the Bukki block eventually.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c6">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Esber v The Commonwealth of Australia (1991) 174 CLR 430</tocase>
<text>In Esber v The Commonwealth of Australia (1991) 174 CLR 430, the High Court considered the entitlement of a former member of the Defence Force who had applied to redeem weekly payments of compensation so that he might receive a lump sum in lieu as prescribed by the relevant statute. The application was refused. The applicant applied to the Administrative Appeals Tribunal for review of the decision. After application, but before determination, the relevant provision was repealed. The repealing Act provided that proceedings instituted under the earlier legislation, but not completed upon repeal, "may be continued on and after that day and, when the proceedings are so continued, the relevant authority and the Commonwealth shall be parties to those proceedings". Reliance was placed upon s 8 of the Acts Interpretation Act 1910 (Cth) (the "Commonwealth Interpretation Act") which was, in terms, similar to s 20 of the State Interpretation Act . The majority (Mason CJ, Deane, Toohey and Gaudron JJ) held that the relevant section of the earlier Act conferred substantive rights. Their Honours said at 440: 
 If it be assumed that the appellant did not have a right to redemption in the sense first discussed, he had a right to have his claim to redemption determined in his favour if the delegate had wrongly refused his claim. To borrow a sentence from the judgment of Hope JA in NSW Aboriginal Land Council v The Minister ...: 

 
 "The right might be said to be a conditional one, namely conditional upon the relevant facts being established, but the right was nonetheless a right because it was conditional." 

 
 Once the appellant lodged an application to the Tribunal to review the delegate's decision, he had a right to have the decision of the delegate reconsidered and determined by the Tribunal. It was not merely "a power to take advantage of an enactment"... . Nor was it a mere matter of procedure ... ; it was a substantive right ... . Section 8 of the Acts Interpretation Act protects anything that may truly be described as a right, "although that right might fairly be called inchoate or contingent" ... . This was such a right. It was a right in existence at the time the 1971 Act was repealed. That being so, and in the absence of a contrary intention, the right was protected by s.8 of the Acts Interpretation Act and was not affected by the repeal of the 1971 Act.

The cases contemplate at least three distinct situations in which s 20 might be engaged. Firstly, the relevant legislation might create a right which, by force of the legislation, accrues without any qualification or requirement for further action. Such a right will survive repeal of the relevant legislation. Secondly, the legislation may confer a right upon persons having certain qualifications. Such legislation may contemplate an investigation to determine whether a particular person has the relevant qualifications. Using the language of Ho Po Sang , there may be a need for investigation to ascertain whether the requirement for such qualifications is satisfied. Such a right will also survive repeal of the relevant statute. That situation is to be distinguished from that in which an investigation is carried out for the purpose of determining whether or not a right should be granted. The former situation was considered by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in the Land Council case where it was said that a right which could only be implemented "by a non-discretionary decision of an official or a court" would survive, "provided that any statutory machinery has been set in train before the repeal or amendment." The "non-discretionary decision" seems to be the equivalent of the investigation contemplated in Ho Po Sang . Finally, where a particular procedure has been commenced, there may be a right to have the procedure completed in accordance with the statute in its unrepealed form. This was the case in Esber .</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c7">
<class>cited</class>
<tocase>Resort Management Services Ltd v Noosa Shire Council (1997) 2 Qd R 291</tocase>
<text>There is also a particularly useful summary of the question in Resort Management Services Ltd v Noosa Shire Council (1997) 2 Qd R 291, per McPherson JA at 298 and per Fryberg J at 301-308. I was also referred to the decision of the Queensland Court of Appeal in Australand . That matter concerned a statutory right to avoid a contract for the purchase of a prescribe interest in a managed investment scheme where the invitation to subscribe had been issued in contravention of a provision of the Corporations Law (now repealed). The provision was repealed with effect from 1 July 1998. In certain cases, the transitional provisions continued the operation of the section until 1 July 2000. On 8 September 2003 the appellants purported to avoid their contracts pursuant to the section. At first instance the primary Judge held that such avoidance was of no effect. The Court of Appeal upheld that decision. I was particularly referred to a passage in the judgment of Keane JA at [113]-[117]. That passage offers a useful commentary on the cases to which I have referred but, with great respect, it does not seem to take the matter any further.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c8">
<class>considered</class>
<tocase>Chang v Laidley Shire Council (2007) 234 CLR 1</tocase>
<text>In Chang v Laidley Shire Council (2007) 234 CLR 1, the High Court considered Queensland planning legislation which provided for compensation where a change in the relevant legislation caused a reduction in value of an interest in land. In considering the operation of s 20 of the State Interpretation Act, the High Court said at 34: 
 Terms like "right", "interest", "title", "power", or "privilege" when used in the context of a general interpretation provision like s 20 are to be understood by reference to the statute that has been amended or repealed. They are terms that are not used "solely in any technical sense derived exclusively from property law or analytical jurisprudence" ... .</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>