<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Groves; in the matter of ABC Learning Centres Limited (Administrators Appointed) (Receivers and Managers Appointed) [2009] FCA 915 (19 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/915.html</AustLII>
<citations>
<citation "id=c0">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Re the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs of the Commonwealth of Australia; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/HCA/1997/6.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion the parties should be left to bear their own respective costs. There has not been an adjudication upon the merits and it is not possible to say what the ultimate outcome of the proceeding would have been. In all the circumstances, the test that is to be applied to the conduct of the antagonists is one of reasonableness in the light of the nature of the particular proceeding and all the circumstances. In Re the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs of the Commonwealth of Australia; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 , McHugh J said (at 625) that where both parties appear to have acted reasonably, the proper exercise of the discretion as to costs will usually be that the Court will make no order as to costs. Similarly, in Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Limited [1993] FCA 585 ; (1993) 44 FCR 194 at 202-203, Hill J applied a test of reasonableness to the conduct of ASIC's predecessor, the Australian Securities Commission in respect of a discontinued proceeding under s 1323 of the Corporations Law and determined that each party should bear its own costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c1">
<class>followed</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Limited [1993] FCA 585 ; (1993) 44 FCR 194</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//cth/FCA/1993/585.html</AustLII>
<text>In my opinion the parties should be left to bear their own respective costs. There has not been an adjudication upon the merits and it is not possible to say what the ultimate outcome of the proceeding would have been. In all the circumstances, the test that is to be applied to the conduct of the antagonists is one of reasonableness in the light of the nature of the particular proceeding and all the circumstances. In Re the Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs of the Commonwealth of Australia; ex parte Lai Qin [1997] HCA 6 ; (1997) 186 CLR 622 , McHugh J said (at 625) that where both parties appear to have acted reasonably, the proper exercise of the discretion as to costs will usually be that the Court will make no order as to costs. Similarly, in Australian Securities Commission v Aust-Home Investments Limited [1993] FCA 585 ; (1993) 44 FCR 194 at 202-203, Hill J applied a test of reasonableness to the conduct of ASIC's predecessor, the Australian Securities Commission in respect of a discontinued proceeding under s 1323 of the Corporations Law and determined that each party should bear its own costs.</text>
</citation>
<citation "id=c2">
<class>distinguished</class>
<tocase>Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Krecichwost [2008] NSWSC 855 ; (2008) 219 FLR 235</tocase>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases//nsw/supreme_ct/2008/855.html</AustLII>
<text>As Young CJ in Eq (as Young JA then was) observed in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Krecichwost [2008] NSWSC 855 ; (2008) 219 FLR 235 in relation to a costs issue on an application under s 1323 , "[e]ach case must be decided on its own facts and merits" (at [27]). In that case, on which Mr Groves relies, his Honour ordered ASIC to pay the relevant defendant's costs. However, the circumstances were that ASIC had obtained ex-parte relief against the relevant defendant who consented to extensions of that relief. With respect, it is understandable that his Honour treated that defendant's costs as an incident of the costs of ASIC's investigation that ASIC should bear.

The present proceeding is very different. ASIC did not seek ex parte relief; its application under s 1323 was resisted by Mr Groves and Ms Collins-Rubie; they and ASIC filed and served extensive affidavit evidence; the proceeding was fixed for final hearing; and even when, at the beginning of the hearing on 27 July 2009 it was clear that ASIC did not seek to pursue Perfection Too, Mr Groves and Ms Collins-Rubie wished the hearing to proceed.

As at the beginning of the date fixed for the final hearing, the parties were still strongly in dispute. It was only progressively throughout the day that they reached agreement.</text>
</citation>
</citations>
</case>