<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>BHP Billiton Iron Ore Pty Ltd v The Automotive, Food, Metals, Engineering, Printing &amp; Kindred Industries Union of Workers [2006] FCA 1181 (31 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1181.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">judicial power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">state court invested with federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">state supreme court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">state law providing for exercise of part of supreme court's jurisdiction by masters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">whether master invested with federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">composition of supreme court state</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">the constitution (63 &amp; 64 vict.c.12), ss. 71 , 77 (iii)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">supreme court act 1980 (n.s.w.), ss. 25, 40, 111, 118</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 13">rules of the supreme court (n.s.w.) pt 60, r. 6.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">in the memorandum it was stated that the " first respondent has indicated that it will submit to such order as the court may make ". although this sentence was not grammatically correct given commissioner scott was the named first respondent, it is correct that there had been a submitting appearance filed in the supreme court on behalf of the first respondent to action 2400/2006. in the same document under the heading " hearing " it was stated that " the applicant will move the court at the special appointment listed for 8 february 2007 to grant an order absolute in the first instance for a writ of certiorari, pursuant to order 56 r 1(6) and to, by the same order, pursuant to order 56 r 13, direct that the decision of the first respondent be quashed on the return without further order ". the written submissions contained 30 paragraphs. at the end of the document was the name of counsel, indicating that counsel had prepared the outline of submissions. above the place where counsel's name was typed, there is what appears to be the signature of a solicitor from the firm representing the applicant to action 2400/2006 and the word " per " written in hand. the full bench was later advised that the written submissions were, as represented in the document, prepared by counsel. the full bench was also later advised that counsel had become involved between 6 and 8 december 2006. this was before the appellant's solicitors were engaged. it is also apparent that counsel was retained by the solicitors both in this appeal and action 2400/2006. in paragraphs [7]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">[15], the written submissions set out " the case for relief ". these paragraphs, omitting footnotes, are as follows:</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">"7. the decision made by the first respondent on 4 december 2006 was made in excess of jurisdiction.  the claim was referred to the commission, pursuant to s29(1)(b)(ii) of the ir act, on 3 march 2006. the first respondent, purporting to exercise jurisdiction under s23(1) of the ir act, heard the matter on 25 august 2006 and 24 november 2006 before issuing her decision on 4 december 2006: [the affidavit of a solicitor was then cited] the applicant, against whom the claim was brought, was at all material times a trading corporation, within the meaning of the constitution [the affidavits of a solicitor and the operations director of the appellant were then cited] and therefore a constitutional corporation, within the meaning of section 4(1) , and an employer, within the meaning of section 6(1)(a), of the wr act. the ir act is a "state or territory industrial law" within the meaning of section 4(1) of the wr act. subsection 16(1) of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) (wr act) provides that the wr act applies to the exclusion of a state or territory industrial law so far as it would otherwise apply in relation to an employer as defined in s6(1). section 16 of the wr act was inserted by schedule 1 of the workplace relations amendment (work choices) act 2005 which commenced on 27 march 2006 (the day fixed by proclamation). section 16 of the wr act is effective in excluding state industrial laws even though in some respects, such as the enforcement of contractual entitlements, the commonwealth has failed to enact any corresponding federal law. it is enough that the commonwealth parliament has indicated the relevant field it intends to cover to the exclusion of state law, in this case relations between constitutional corporations and their employees: new south wales v commonwealth of australia [2006] hca 52 ; (2006) 231 alr 1 ; (2006) 156 ir 1 at [367]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">[372]. accordingly, from 27 march 2006, by reason of section 16 of the wr act and s109 of the commonwealth constitution , the ir act, with prescribed exceptions, was excluded insofar as it would otherwise have applied to constitutional corporations and their employees. the claim did not fall within any of the prescribed exceptions so that, from 27 march 2006, the first respondent lacked jurisdiction to continue to hear and determine the matter. " in paragraph [16] of the written submissions, it was contended that although the present issue was not raised during the commission proceedings, as it was one which went to jurisdiction and could not have been cured at the hearing, the applicant was not precluded from taking the point in action 2400/2006. in the next paragraph it was submitted that as a consequence of the " ir act " being excluded in its application to constitutional corporations and their employees, the privative clause in s34(3) of the act did not apply. the submissions then contained the heading " discretionary considerations ", which comprised paragraphs [18]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">[23]. these paragraphs are as follows:</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">" 18. the starting point in the consideration of the exercise of discretion is that if it is found the tribunal exceeded its jurisdiction, certiorari will normally be granted: re carey; ex parte exclude holdings pty ltd and ors [2006] wasca 219 ; bc 200608660 at [129] per martin cj (wheeler ja agreeing); see also re refugee review tribunal; ex parte aala [2000] hca 57 ; (2000) 204 clr 82 at [51]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">[52] per gaudron and gummow jj (gleeson cj agreeing) and at [149] per kirby j where their honours approved the following statement by gibbs cj in r v ross-jones; ex parte green [1984] hca 82 ; (1984) 156 clr 185:</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] WAIRComm 334">The submissions then contained the heading " Discretionary considerations ", which comprised paragraphs [18] --- [23]. These paragraphs are as follows:- 
" 18. The starting point in the consideration of the exercise of discretion is that if it is found the tribunal exceeded its jurisdiction, certiorari will normally be granted: Re Carey; Ex Parte Exclude Holdings Pty Ltd and Ors [2006] WASCA 219 ; BC 200608660 at [129] per Martin CJ (Wheeler JA agreeing); see also Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex parte Aala [2000] HCA 57 ; (2000) 204 CLR 82 at [51] - [52] per Gaudron and Gummow JJ (Gleeson CJ agreeing) and at [149] per Kirby J where their Honours approved the following statement by Gibbs CJ in R v Ross-Jones; Ex parte Green [1984] HCA 82 ; (1984) 156 CLR 185: 
 
 "If, therefore, a clear case of want or excess of jurisdiction has been made out, and the prosecutor is a party aggrieved, the writ will issue almost as of right, although the court retains its discretion to refuse relief if in all the circumstances that seems the proper course. " 
 Here there are no discretionary reasons for withholding relief. There is no other equally efficacious remedy available to the applicant. As a consequence of the IR Act being excluded in its application to constitutional corporations and their employees, the applicant cannot appeal to a Full Bench of the Commission under s49 of the IR Act. Whereas, under s853 of the WR Act, an appeal lies to the Federal Court from a judgment of a state "court" in any matter arising under the WR ACT (sic), whether the Commission is a court for this purpose is an open question: see BHP Billiton Iron Ore Pty Ltd v AMWU [2006] FCA 1181 ; BC200606776 at [23] to [24]. On the other hand in circumstances where: 
 (a) There is a clear case for relief; 
 
 (b) The second respondent consents to the proposed orders; 
 
 (c) The first respondent has filed a submitting appearance; 
 
 the making of an order absolute in the first instance is necessary for the advancement of justice to avoid wasted costs and delay. "
 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY IMPROVEMENT ACT 2005 </title>
<title id="l1">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l2">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 78B Notice to Attorneys-General</title>
<title id="l3">WORKPLACE RELATIONS AMENDMENT (WORK CHOICES) ACT 2005 </title>
<title id="l4">WORKPLACE RELATIONS REGULATIONS 2006 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l6">WORKPLACE RELATIONS ACT 1996 </title>
<title id="l7">WORKPLACE RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 16 Act excludes some State and Territory laws</title>
<title id="l8">WORKPLACE RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 642 Definitions</title>
<title id="l9">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 </title>
<title id="l10">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 12 </title>
<title id="l11">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 16 </title>
<title id="l12">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 34 </title>
<title id="l13">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 44 </title>
<title id="l14">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 49 </title>
<title id="l15">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 85 </title>
<title id="l16">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1979 - SECT 90 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>