<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Meinhardt (Hong Kong) Ltd v William Edward Meinhardt (Deceased) &amp; Ors [2006] FCA 1106 (22 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1106.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">circumstances in which a later full court can depart from an earlier full court decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">determining ratio decidendi</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">application of minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v al shamry (2001) 110 fcr 27  migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">the application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">meaning of 'application', 'information', and 'reason, or part of the reason' in s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">appeal from magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">whether the pressure on homosexual to marry amounts to persecution for a convention reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">whether refugee review tribunal failed to consider essential element of claimpractice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">judgments of single judges of federal court not binding on federal magistrates where not exercising appellate jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">judicial comity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">insolvent transactions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">voidable transactions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">unfair preferences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">where plaintiffs sought orders that the commissioner of taxation repay monies said to be paid within six months of the relation back day</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">onus and burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">whether requirement that court be 'satisfied' that transactions were voidable prevented parties consenting to orders. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">precedent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">comity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">whether previous decision of single judge should be followed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1063">whether previous decision 'clearly or plainly wrong'.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">deceased estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">whether debt in liquidated sum due and payable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">sum advanced by company to director without terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">insolvency of estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1323">whether estate should be administered in bankruptcy.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2006] FCA 1323">As I said in my reasons on a preliminary point published on 22 August 2006 ( Meinhardt (Hong Kong) Ltd v Meinhardt (Deceased) [2006] FCA 1106) , Mr Meinhardt died on 23 November 2003. He was survived by two daughters from his first marriage, Victoria Treyvaud (the third respondent) and Sally Veall, and a son from his second marriage, William Edward Meinhardt (the second respondent). He left a will which named Timothy Jonathan Browne and Roderick Charles McKenzie as executors. The residuary beneficiaries were the second and third respondents and Ms Veall. No application for probate had been made when, on 23 November 2005, the second respondent commenced a proceeding in the Supreme Court of Victoria against the executors under s 15 of the Administration and Probate Act 1958 (Vic) ('the Administration and Probate Act ') in which he sought orders that the executors show cause why they should not renounce probate of the will and why administration of the estate should not be granted to State Trustees Ltd. On 22 December 2005 the executors commenced their own proceeding in the Supreme Court in which they applied for probate of the will. On 16 March 2006 the Supreme Court ordered that the two proceedings be heard together. On 4 July 2006, the executors issued a summons in the proceeding which they had commenced under which they sought orders that they have leave to renounce their application for probate in favour of State Trustees Ltd or another nominated corporate trustee. That proceeding, and the proceeding commenced by the second respondent, remain pending in the list of the Supreme Court. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 244 Administration of estates under this Part upon petition by creditor</title>
<title id="l2">SUPREME COURT RULES 1970 </title>
<title id="l3">ADMINISTRATION AND PROBATE ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l4">Administration and Probate Act 1958 - SECT 15 Executor etc. neglects to prove, renounce or bring in the will</title>
</legistitles>
</case>