<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Zambini v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1773 (11 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1773.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">application to strike out notice of appeal from decision of federal magistrate for abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">bankruptcy notice issued in respect of unpaid costs order made by district court judge at interlocutory hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">application by respondent to set aside bankruptcy notice dismissed by federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">court's jurisdiction to strike out a notice of appeal under s 25(2b)(aa) of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">relevance of s 31a of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">whether costs order of district court a "final order" for the purposes of s 40(1)(g) of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">whether federal magistrate failed to take into account issues, affidavits or relevant legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">whether failure by the applicant's solicitor to comply with r 2.05 and r 2.06 of the federal court (bankruptcy) rules 2005 and whether relevant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">application of s 41 of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">and exercise of judicial discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">allegation of bias on part of federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">whether notice of appeal raises arguable issues</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">whether indemnity costs warranted   held: notice of motion to strike out the notice of appeal for abuse of process successful</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">notice of appeal struck out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">costs order made at interlocutory stage by district court was a "final order" under s 40(1)(g) of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">no errors in the federal magistrate's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1016">the respondent to pay the applicant's costs of the notice of motion on a party-party basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">single judge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">application for summary judgment pursuant to s 25(2b)(aa) of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">no arguable ground of appeal or error on the part of the primary judge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 995">appeal summarily dismissed</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1016">A question arises whether, in considering s 25(2B)(aa), it is necessary for the Court to also have recourse to s 31A. In a number of cases the Court has exercised power pursuant to s 25(2B)(aa) and given summary judgment without reference to s 31A: Druett v Department of Families, Community Services &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 995 , Zambini v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1773 , Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2007] FCA 1326 , Rana v University of Adelaide (No 2) [2008] FCA 941. However in other cases the Court has linked the power under s 25(2B)(aa) to the jurisdiction of the Court under s 31A and summarily dismissed an appeal on the basis that the appellant had no reasonable prospect of success in prosecuting its grounds of appeal: Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 923 , Bishop v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 1118. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 995">2 Mr Kunc, who appears for the Department, then foreshadowed a notice of motion seeking summary judgment pursuant to s 25(2B)(aa) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ('the Act') and, in the alternative, an order that the Department be removed as a party to the proceedings pursuant to s 25(2B)(a) of the Act. A single judge of the Court has power under those sections to make the orders sought (s 25 ; Zegarac v Dellios [2007] FCA 566 at [12] ; Zambini v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1773 at [4] ; Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 923). The notice of motion for summary judgment was filed on 24 May 2007 ('the motion'). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCAFC 58">7 In my view, it does not follow that a failure to comply with Order 52 Rule 13(2) renders an appeal incompetent. If the notice is incomprehensible or entirely unrelated to the issues dealt with in the judgment, an appeal may be incompetent. Examples relied upon by Mr Nixon are indeed cases of incomprehensibility: Lindsey v Philip Morris Limited [2004] FCAFC 40 ; Kendrick-Smith v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission [2003] FCAFC 155 ; Zambini v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1773. However, in this case the notice of appeal, while prolix and not in compliance with Order 52 Rule 13(2) , is not incomprehensible. It is clear from the document as a whole that Ms Zegarac contends that his Honour erred in holding that she had not established that the judgment in the Magistrates Court was obtained by fraud. Thus, the relief sought in paragraph 1 of the motion should be refused.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 566">13 Section 25(2B)(aa) was the provision to which Mansfield J had recourse in the more recent case of Zambini v The Secretary of the Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2006] FCA 1773. That was a case in which the appellant commenced by filing a Notice of Appeal which, on my reading of it, was hopelessly inadequate. Mansfield J held that the document did not state with any specificity --- or indeed at all in any comprehensible way --- the grounds relied upon in the support of the appeal.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 25 Exercise of appellate jurisdiction</title>
<title id="l3">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>