<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 (23 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1122.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">joint tenancy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">severance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">torrens system land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">memorandum of transfer from one tenant to trustee for herself executed and delivered to transferee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">certificate of title in possession of mortgagee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">death of transferor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">whether joint tenancy severed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">whether equitable interest alienated before death</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">real property act 1900 (n.s.w.), s. 41</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 12">conveyancing act 1919 (n.s.w.), ss. 24 , 96 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">equitable assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">chose in action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">gift</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">non-compliance with statutory requirement for legal assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">purported parol assignment of debt.  gift</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">imperfect gift</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">chose in action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">non-compliance with statutory requirement for legal assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">purported parol assignment of contract debt.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">novation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">direction by creditor for payment of debt to third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">whether tripartite contract or contract for benefit of third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">rights of third party.  interpleader</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">circumstances in &amp;which proceedings available</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 3">nature of orders &amp;which may be made.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">issue estoppel precluding relitigation of an the issue determined by an earlier proceeding on the part of the present trustee of a family trust, or any subsequent trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">summary dismissal of plaintiff's claim (r 23.03 supreme court (general civil procedure) rules 2005 )</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">s 62 civil procedure act 2010</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">proceeding vexatious and an abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">court's inherent power and r 23.01(1) supreme court (general civil procedure) rules 2005</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">proceeding permanently stayed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">inherent power of a court to restrain the commencement of further proceedings which seek to relitigate matters already determined by the same court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 428">restraint order made.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">caveat</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">removal.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">appeal from orders of federal magistrates court transferring beneficial title of properties to trustee in bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether appellant beneficial owner of properties trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether document titled "declaration of trust" effective</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether document manifested intention to declare a trust</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">document ambiguous in its terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether parol evidence rule applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">appellant's subsequent conduct inconsistent with declaration of trust practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">application to adduce "further evidence" pursuant to federal court act 1976 (cth) s 27</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">further evidence relevant to creation of purported "declaration of trust"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">principles relevant to reception of further evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether evidence could have been led below</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether evidence sufficiently cogent to warrant its reception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1968">whether evidence likely to have produced different result</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1617">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1617">application for possession of land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1617">bankruptcy notice under s.139zq of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1617">valuation of property interest transferred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1617">cross claim seeking to have notice set aside.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1481">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1481">application by trustee pursuant to ss.58 and 116 of the bankruptcy act 1966</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1481">whether valid trust</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1481">equitable principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1481">relevance of evidence of bankrupt in other proceeding claiming ownership of property and no reference to trust.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1396">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1396">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1396">application to transfer proceedings to the federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1396">application dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] VSC 428">[1] 21-Dec-06 The Full Court of the Federal Court set aside the orders of Weinberg J and remitted the matter for retrial before Jessup J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] VSC 213">21 On 24 March 2005 the plaintiff commenced an application in the Federal Court (proceeding VID 235/2005) for declarations and orders that the properties were beneficially owned by the first defendant at the date of his bankruptcy, and that they had vested in the plaintiff pursuant to ss 58 and 116 of the Act. The respondents to the application were the second defendant (as first respondent) in her capacity as trustee of the Vasiliou Family Trust and the first defendant (as second respondent). 22 On 23 August 2006 Weinberg J gave judgment in favour of the plaintiff [7] . This judgment was successfully appealed against, as I refer below. 23 On 4 September 2006 the second defendant lodged a caveat no.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 1968">47 It was common ground before me that Ms Owens had the onus of establishing the existence of the trust that she asserted. The only conceivable way that she could do so, in this case, would be to have the declaration of trust not merely accepted as genuine, but also construed as manifesting the intention to declare a trust. The failure to take any steps beyond executing the document meant that no other form of trust could arise: see Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 at [13] ---[28] and the cases cited therein. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FMCA 1617">23. Mr Johnson contends that, alternatively, the effective date of transfer of ownership of the properties was when Mrs Vale signed the statutory declaration on 11 October 1996 (first affidavit of Mr Vale, Exhibit "MGV-1", pp.21-22). Mr Johnson argues that the transfer was an imperfect gift in the traditional sense: Milroy v Lord [1862] EngR 951 ; (1862) 4 De GF &amp; J 264 ; Corin &amp; Anor v Patton [1990] HCA 12 ; (1990) 169 CLR 540. In circumstances such as this, where the statutory declaration had not been carried into effect by registration of the transfer signed on 23 April 1999, Mr Johnson contends that the authorities are clear that it was an imperfect gift. Therefore, the estate of Mrs Vale would vest in Mr Sutherland as trustee of her property : s.58 of the Act. Mr Johnson relied on Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 per Weinberg J where that transfer had not been registered and the trustee sought a declaration. 75. Mr Johnson argues that the statutory declaration confirms the existence of an imperfect gift within the traditional sense of Milroy v Lord and Corin &amp; Anor v Patton . If the statutory declaration had not been subsequently carried into effect by the registration of the transfer, it would have remained an imperfect gift and the estate of Mrs Vale would have vested in Mr Sutherland as trustee of her property under the operation of s.58 of the Act: Morchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 per Weinberg J. In that case, the transfer had not been registered and the trustee sought a declaration.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FMCA 1481">102. Counsel then referred the court to the decision of Weinberg J in Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 (Marchesi at first instance). It was argued that the facts in that case were analogous to the present case. In Marchesi at first instance the question was whether the bankrupt did enough to perfect the gift of the properties in equity and the facts in that case are set out in the following paragraph from the judgment of the court: 
 
 
 "3. On 7 September 2006 Aitken Walker &amp; Strachan sent a letter to Tolhurst Druce &amp; Emmerson which letter stated, inter alia: 
 "Notwithstanding the matters raised by you, it does not appear to be in issue that Ms Owens never actually executed transfers of the properties. Your clients' claim appears to hinge upon the 20 December 2000 'Declaration of Trust' (which is a misnomer) to create an equitable interest in the properties. 
 We refer you to the High Court's decision in Corin v Patton [1990] HCA 12 ; (1990) 169 CLR 540 and to the recent Federal Court decision in Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 (23 August 2006). Having regard to the principles discussed in those cases, we consider that Ms Owens did not perfect a gift of properties to the Richardson Trust and, accordingly, the properties vested in our client upon Ms Owens' bankruptcy. 
 Unless, within 7 days of the date of this letter, your clients withdraw any claim to the properties (including the removal of any caveats lodged against title to the properties), our client proposes to commence proceedings in the Federal Court seeking appropriate declaratory relief.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCA 254">3 The trial of the proceeding was conducted before Weinberg J in April 2006. His Honour held that Mr Vasiliou's attempted gift of the properties in 1987 was not complete in equity, and that he retained the beneficial interest in the properties. As a result, he made the orders which the applicant sought: Marchesi v Apostolou [2006] FCA 1122. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2006] FMCA 1396">In respect of the security for costs issue, Mr Skinner submits that the law on this subject is settled and the issue can be dealt with on an interlocutory basis by either Court. 24. The written submissions filed by Mr Johnson on behalf of the trustee (at paragraph 19) contend that issues similar to the present case were considered in Marchesi v Apostoulou [2006] FCA 1122 per Weinberg J (" Marchesi "). Mr Heath contends that Marchesi together with Milroy v Lord [1862] EngR 951 ; (1862) 4 De GF &amp; J 264 (cited in Marchesi ) are both distinguishable from this case. Although Mr Heath acknowledges that Marchesi is broadly factually similar to the matter before this Court, he says that there are also material differences which are significant.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 58 Vesting of property upon bankruptcy--general rule</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l3">REAL PROPERTY ACT 1900 </title>
<title id="l4">REAL PROPERTY ACT 1900 - SECT 58 Power to sell</title>
</legistitles>
</case>