<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Ogawa v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Anor [2006] FCA 1694 (15 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1694.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">re minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs; ex parte applicants s134/2002  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">temporary protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">refugee review tribunal ("the tribunal") affirmed decision of delegate of the minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs ("the minister") not to grant protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">minister not bound to consider whether to exercise power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">minister decided not to exercise power under s 417 of the migration act 1958 (cth) ("the act ") to substitute for the decision of the tribunal a decision more favourable to the prosecutors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">whether decisions of the tribunal and the minister "privative clause decisions" under s 474 of the act .  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">applications for temporary protection visas by mother and children</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">first prosecutor's application asserted that she was a person to whom australia had protection obligations under the refugees convention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">application not made on basis of membership of a family unit, to one of whom protection obligations were owed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">documents before the tribunal indicated that the first prosecutor's husband held a temporary protection visa and had applied for a permanent protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">first prosecutor did not know of her husband's whereabouts or immigration status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">tribunal did not notice documents or appreciate their significance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">tribunal did not consider whether prosecutors entitled to protection visas on basis of membership of a family unit of which one person was owed protection obligations and had been granted a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">whether constructive failure to exercise jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">whether denial of procedural fairness.  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">whether jurisdictional error in decision by minister to refuse to substitute for the decision of the tribunal a decision more favourable to the prosecutors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 1">utility of relief.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 388">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 388">application for summary judgment pursuant to s 31a(2) of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 388">whether court is satisfied that party has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 388">where no reasonable prospect of establishing jurisdiction of court to hear proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 388">where no reasonable prospect of successfully demonstrating jurisdictional error or misfeasance in public office</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 388">1 There is an old adage that the road to hell is paved with good intentions. These proceedings indicate that it is not only that destination that is paved with good intentions, but also the pathway to a courthouse. By that I mean, that when one reflects upon the history of this case, and in particular the observations that Cowdroy J made in his reasons for judgment in Ogawa v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs and Migration Review Tribunal (2006) FCA 1694 , one sees there particular sources of grievance that, at a humane level, one might see Ms Ogawa having in respect of the saga of her dealing with the immigration authorities of the Commonwealth.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 351 Minister may substitute more favourable decision</title>
<title id="l2">HIGH COURT RULES 2004 </title>
<title id="l3">HIGH COURT RULES 2004 - REG 8.02 Effective date</title>
<title id="l4">HEALTH INSURANCE (PROFESSIONAL SERVICES REVIEW) REGULATIONS 1999 </title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION REGULATIONS 1994 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>