<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Vintage Developments Pty Limited v GHD Pty Limited (No 2) [2006] FCA 1437 (30 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1437.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">application for joinder</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">amended application and further amended statement of claim naming additional respondent filed within limitation period but without leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">notice of motion seeking leave for the joinder filed after limitation period expired</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">defects in compliance with the rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">pleading not a nullity and capable of commencing a cause of action within limitation period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">court has express power under the rules to grant leave for joinder after the event of the joinder: o 6 r 4</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">discretionary consideration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 531">application for joinder granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">case stated from magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">relevant principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">sufficiency of evidence that was an effective assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">limitation act 1969 (nsw) does not bar enforcement action against a debtor brought by an equitable assignee without joining the legal assignor though legal estate only got in after limitation period expired</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2000] NSWSC 210">effect of local court rules for civil claims.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">defamation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">credit reporting agency's reports to credit providers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">reports allegedly defamatory of applicants in respect of their creditworthiness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">allegation that they were refused credit by credit providers who relied on erroneous credit reports</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">respondent's computerised database</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">credit providers who subscribe (respondent's customers) enter information in the database electronically and extract information from it electronically, in each case without respondent's intervention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">whether respondent credit reporting agency communicated to subscribing credit provider the information that that credit provider extracted electronically</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">in some cases credit provider's computer rejects application for credit automatically upon receipt of adverse credit report</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">essential to cause of action in defamation that the defamatory publication be published to a human mind</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">whether publication to a human mind proved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">qualified privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">whether credit reports of credit reporting agency attracted defence of qualified privilege.   negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">credit reporting agency's reports to credit providers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">allegation that applicants refused credit by credit providers who relied on erroneous credit reports</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">respondent's computerised database</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">credit providers who subscribe (respondent's customers) enter information into the system electronically and extract information from it electronically, in each case without respondent's intervention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">whether respondent credit reporting agency communicated to subscribing credit provider the information that that credit provider extracted electronically</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">in some cases credit provider's computer rejects application for credit automatically upon receipt of adverse credit report</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">whether credit reporting agency owed a duty of care to persons seeking credit to ensure that information stored in database was accurate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 305">if so, whether breach of duty established.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">substitution of individual assignee of non-trade practices claims as first plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">substitution of personal trustee for corporate trustee as second plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">application under s 237 of the corporations act 2001 (cth) to bring derivative action in name of first plaintiff in respect of trade practices claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">first plaintiff company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">whether pt 2f.1a of the act has application to a company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">alternatively application to bring derivative action under inherent power of court.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">company created for the sole purpose of acting as trustee of a family trust</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">company deregistered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">substitution of new trustee in the proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 927">order 13 rule 2(6) federal court rules 1979 (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 73">first respondent / cross</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 73">claimant  hunter valley estates pty ltd (acn 010 857 717)  second respondent / cross</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 73">respondent</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 305">In response to Veda's Limitation Act defence submission, the applicants argue that all of the amendments to their respective pleadings take effect as from the filing of the original statement of claim (on 25 January 2006 in Mr McGary's proceeding and on 16 December 2005 in the other eight proceedings). The applicants refer to Baldry v Jackson [1976] 2 NSWLR 415 at 419 per Samuels JA, O 13 r 3A of the Federal Court Rules , and Vintage Developments Pty Ltd v GHD Pty Limited (No 2) [2006] FCA 1437 ( Vintage ). The applicants submit: Where the limitation period of one year applies any pleaded imputation after 16 December 2005 is within time, and in the case of Mr McGary, any publication after 25 January 2006 . 
 If there is a publication prior to 16 February 2003 then any subsequent publication will be within time by virtue of the savings provisions under s 14B(2) of the Limitation Act when amended with effect from 17 February 2003. All publications are of substantially the same matter. All causes of action pleaded in defamation are publications within the twelve month period prior to the commencement of the proceedings or they come within the savings provision under s 14B(2) of the Limitation Act . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 927">Vintage Developments Pty Ltd v GHD Pty Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1437 involved a successful application to amend the capacity in which an application and statement of claim had been filed from "Errol Investments Pty Ltd" to "Errol Investments Pty Ltd as Trustee for the Shellharbour Unit Trust". Evidence was adduced of minutes of a meeting of the company resolving that the contract to purchase land would be executed by the company in its capacity as trustee of the Shellharbour Unit Trust as well as a contract for the sale of land that in one place, at least, referred to the purchaser as Errol Investments Pty Ltd as Trustee for the Shellharbour Property Trust. The judge was satisfied that the reference should have been to the Shellharbour Unit Trust. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 73">1 The applicants (together 'Vintage') moved the Court for leave to amend their application and statement of claim to clarify the capacity in which the second applicant, Errol Investments Pty Ltd, brings these proceedings. Their application was partially successful: Vintage Developments Pty Limited v GHD Pty Limited (No 2) [2006] FCA 1437 (' Vintage (No 2) '). Vintage and the second ('Hunter Valley') and third ('Mr Johnston') respondents disagree as to who should pay the costs of Vintage's motion for leave to amend the pleadings. Vintage accepts that, as the party seeking leave to amend, it is appropriate that it bear some liability for costs. Vintage also acknowledges that it is liable to pay costs incurred prior to 15 September 2006, further to an agreement between the parties. Vintage's submission is that it should only be liable thereafter to pay 75% of Hunter Valley's costs and 50% of Mr Johnston's costs. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l2">TRUSTEE ACT 1925 </title>
<title id="l3">TRUSTEE ACT 1925 - SECT 6 New trustee</title>
</legistitles>
</case>