<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZICO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1803 (21 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1803.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">plaintiff s157/2002 v commonwealth of australia  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">privative clauses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether the decision by the refugee review tribunal affirming the decision of a delegate of the minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs refusing the plaintiff's application for a protection visa is a "privative clause decision" within s 474 of the migration act 1958 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 474(1) of the act is construed as ousting judicial review by the high court.  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 474 and s 486a of the act are invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 474(1)(c) of the act is directly inconsistent with s 75 of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 474(1)(a) and (b) of the act are inseparable from s 474(1)(c) of the act and are consequently invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 486a of the act will apply to a "decision" when there has been jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 486a of the act is a law incidental to the legislative power conferred by ss 51(xix) , (xxvii), (xxix) of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 486a of the act is within the express incidental power conferred by s 51 (xxxix) of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 486a of the act is inconsistent with s 75(v) of the constitution .   immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether decision affirming the decision of a delegate of the minister refusing application for a protection visa is a "privative clause decision" within s 474 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 474(1) of the act ousts judicial review by the high court pursuant to s 75 of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 2">whether s 486a of the act is constitutionally valid.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">review of decision of immigration review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">applicant incorrectly informed by officer of the tribunal that he had lost his right of review when notified of the decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether applicant was notified of the decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether application made to the court within 28 days of notification of the decision for the purposes of s.478 of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether applicant entitled to be accurately informed of his right of review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether the respondent is estopped from alleging the application was not lodged within 28 days of the notification.   statutory interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">consideration of principles of statutory interpretation to give effect to the intention of the legislature</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether a literal interpretation should be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether an interpretation which gives effect to and does not defeat or frustrate the manifest object or purpose of a provision must be preferred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether it is an implied condition of a notification for the purposes of s.478 that it not frustrate or negate the purpose of notification.   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether notification is an exercise of statutory power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 70">whether power exercised for an ulterior or improper purpose.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">entry permit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">appeal from decision refusing review of administrative decision rejecting application for permit by an illegal entrant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">whether applicant nominated by a relative (mother) under the family and other close ties (after entry) entry permit regulations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">applicant and mother given misleading and inadequate information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">meaning of nomination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">whether substantial compliance with procedural requirements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">distinction between mandatory and directory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">consideration of issues of practical fairness in the administration of the migration act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">need for an overriding discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">law reform   statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1424">distinction between mandatory and directory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 291">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 291">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 291">refusal of a protection (class xa) visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 291">no reviewable error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 291">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1109">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1109">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1109">refusal of a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1109">interlocutory dismissal of show cause application as incompetent.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 178">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 178">whether summary dismissal as an abuse of process in the federal magistrates court final or interlocutory decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 178">abuse of process because issues already decided in other proceedings by applicant procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 178">time to file appeal against interlocutory judgment of the federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 178">federal court rules o 52 r 5(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 162">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 162">review of migration review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 162">refusal of a temporary business entry visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 162">interlocutory dismissal of show cause application as incompetent.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">application to review decision of migration review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">whether tribunal failed to comply with s.359a of migration act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">jurisdictional error found</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">unexplained delay militates against discretionary relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 115">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 97">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 97">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 97">summary dismissal of show cause application as incompetent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 97">application filed out of time.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 291">The Applicants were refused their visas by a delegate of the Minister on 17 June 2003. The Applicant's applied to the Tribunal on 22 July 2003 and on 19 December 2003 after the Applicants did not attend the hearing with the Tribunal to which they invited, the Tribunal affirmed the decision under review. An application was made to the Federal Magistrates Court and on 30 March 2006 that application was dismissed as incompetent as it was filed out of time ( SZICO &amp; Ors v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 435). An appeal to the Federal Court was made and subsequently dismissed on 21 December 2006 ( SZICO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1803). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FMCA 1109">[3] 
 
 Background 
 
 
 26 April 2001 Applicant arrived in Australia 
 DIMIA 
 
 
 2 May 2001 Applicant lodged application for a protection visa 
 
 10 May 2001 Delegate refused application for a protection visa 
 
 RRT 
 
 
 24 May 2001 Applicant applied to RRT for review of delegate's decision 
 
 1 May 2003 RRT hearing 
 
 24 June 2003 RRT decision handed down 
 
 Federal Magistrates Court SZ1405 of 2003 
 
 22 July 2003 Application for an order of review lodged 
 
 29 October 2005 Application dismissed by Lloyd-Jones FM.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 541">10 The Minister submits that the Court should not treat the Notice of Appeal as an application for leave to appeal because it would be futile to do so, since such an application has no prospects of success. The Minister submits that no error of principle has been identified, and that none is apparent in relation to the finding of Lloyd-Jones FM or that of the Tribunal. The Minister also submits that the decision of Lloyd-Jones FM is not attended by sufficient doubt to warrant its reconsideration by the Court and that Lloyd-Jones FM was correct to find that the application was incompetent. The Minister cites numerous authorities for this proposition including: MZXLM v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship &amp; Anor [2007] FCA 291 at [9] per Tracey J; SZIVU v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 342 at [3] per Jessup J; Applicant S285 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 400 at [4] per Branson J; SZICO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1803 at [11] per Tamberlin J; SZBJP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1579 at [4] per Black CJ. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 178">28 In SZICO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1803 , it was decided that ss 476 and 477 of the Act operate together to limit the jurisdiction of the Federal Magistrates Court to hear such an application as that presently under consideration. It does not appear that it was argued that s 476 defines the jurisdiction of the Federal Magistrates Court and that s 477, by imposing a time limit upon the manner of its exercise, may not simply be limiting the jurisdiction. I observe that s 486A imposes similar time limits upon an application to the High Court under Chapter III of the Constitution for relief in the nature of constitutional writs. Of course, it does not arise in this matter to address whether s 486A is within power, and if it is not whether s 477 should be construed not as limiting the jurisdiction of the Federal Magistrates Court because the grant of jurisdiction by s 476 of the Act is expressed to be "subject to this section", rather than as subject to Part 8A generally, but as defining improperly the manner of its exercise.  29 In those circumstances, the decision in SZICO [2006] FCA 1803 in my view also leads to the conclusion that the alternative reason for the decision of Raphael FM is also correct.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FMCA 162">The application is approximately 12 months out of time and is plainly incompetent having regard to the principles in SZICO v The Minister for Immigration [2006] FCA 1803.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FMCA 115">The failure to apply to extend time is fatal and must result in the dismissal for want of prosecution: SZICO v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1803 at paras 10 and 11 per Tamberlin J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FCA 128">19 Because of the provisions of s 477(3) of the Act, the Federal Magistrates Court has no jurisdiction to entertain an application or an application for an extension of time outside the 28 day period unless it has been extended pursuant to s 477(2). Strict compliance with the section is required. I agree with Tamberlin J in SZICO v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1803. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2007] FMCA 97">This was confirmed recently by the Federal Court in SZICO v Minister for Immigration [2006] FCA 1803.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION LITIGATION REFORM BILL 2005 </title>
<title id="l1">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l2">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 39B Original jurisdiction of Federal Court of Australia</title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 476 Jurisdiction of the Federal Magistrates Court</title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 477 Time limits on applications to the Federal Magistrates Court</title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 478 Persons who may make application</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>