<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140 (29 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1140.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">migration law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">where applicant made references in application for review by refugee review tribunal to material provided to department in visa application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">meaning of 'information' under s 424a(1) and s 424a(3)(b)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">incorporation by reference in application for review and whether considered 'information' applicant gave for purposes of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">held objective test to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">where tribunal made positive finding of elaboration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">treatment of omissions in evidence by review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">whether considered information relevant to s 424a(1)(b) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">circumstances in which a later full court can depart from an earlier full court decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">determining ratio decidendi</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">application of minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v al shamry (2001) 110 fcr 27  migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">the application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">meaning of 'application', 'information', and 'reason, or part of the reason' in s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">whether fresh compliance with s 425 was necessary when the first tribunal hearing could not proceed and a new date allocated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">applicant consented to the tribunal deciding the review without his appearing before it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">non-attendance at tribunal hearing migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">s 424a complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 78">reason for the decision the absence of information provided not the information itself</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">application for protection visa refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">tribunal's understanding of the word 'persecution'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">s 424a of migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">whether information was 'the reason or part of the reason' for affirming the decision under review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">meaning of 'information'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">identification of the 'reason' for decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">an interpretative task</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">discretionary ground to refuse relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">whether a letter seeking ministerial intervention after the date of the delegate's decision is information given during the process that led to the decision under review within s.424a(3)(ba) of the migration act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">inconsistencies and omissions as "information"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">whether requirements of s.424aa met</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 413">interaction of ss.424aa and 424a.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1136">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1136">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1136">whether tribunal failed to disclose to the applicant information that was part of the reason for affirming the decision under review in the manner required by s.424a of the migration act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">whether failure to comply with section 424 gives rise to jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">the obligation to give a written invitation to a person to provide additional information is mandatory</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">jurisdictional error established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">whether failure to provide 'information' involved a breach of section 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">'information' relevant to the review by the rrt which might be used to decide matters adversely to the appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">breach of section 424a(1)(b)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">jurisdictional error established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">appeal upheld. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">judicial comity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">an earlier decision of the full court on similar issues should be followed unless 'plainly wrong'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">decision in szkti v minister for immigration and citizenship not 'plainly wrong' but correct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 119">decision followed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">uruguayan applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">tribunal internal enquiry as to whether there was information about any current mistreatment of unionists and leftist activists in uruguay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">tribunal researcher requested such information from uruguayan organisations including the union to which applicant belonged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">whether request for information and lack of reply was 'information' within s.424a(1) migration act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 3">whether s424a(3)(a) applicable.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">application for protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">appeal from federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">whether tribunal failed to comply with statutory obligation to give appellant information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">whether information was within exception to obligation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1031">whether appellant had given information to the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">tribunal disbelieved claim first made at hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">whether used 'information' as to an omission from the protection visa application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">whether information as to timing of claim also given to tribunal at hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">no failure under s.424a established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 865">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCAFC 174">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCAFC 174">operation of articles 1a(2) or 1c(5) of the convention relating to the status of refugees 1951</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCAFC 174">s 424a of the migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCAFC 174">information that should have been subject of the provision of particulars.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">bangladeshi fearing political and religious persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">claims disbelieved by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">confidential "dob-in" material on departmental files</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">tribunal disclaimed reliance during hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">not disclosed to applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">no apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">no denial of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">no breach of s.424a(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.10" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1575">application dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FMCA 413">It appears from the Tribunal's reasons for decision that the fact that completely false claims were made to the Department and Minister, rather than claims based on Christianity, raised concerns about the applicant's credibility. In this sense the failure to mention the Christianity claims to the Minister (or the Department) can be said to suggest recent invention by the applicant, as considered by Tamberlin J in SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140 and Allsop J in SZEEU and Others v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 at [221] --- [22] per Allsop J), and hence to constitute more than a "mere omission" and amount to information as considered by Buchanan J in SZKCQ. The same would apply to omissions from the protection visa application (but such information would be in s.424A(3)(ba)). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FMCA 1136">Weinberg J indicated that where a Tribunal used omissions in a way that went beyond " mere omissions" this "amounted to a positive use of information, as opposed to an observation made in relation to a failure to give information or make a claim " ( NBKS at [38] and see SZEEU and Others v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 , SZGGT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 435 and SZCNP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140). As his Honour stated, this would arise if the Tribunal " treats the omission as though it provides implicit support for a positive assertion that is detrimental to an applicant's case " (at [39]). In such cases s.424A may be applicable. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCAFC 119">86 His Honour however went on to say at [38]-[39]:
 '38 To the same effect is SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140. There Tamberlin J rejected a submission on behalf of the Minister that the term "information" in s 424A did not encompass a failure to mention a matter to the Tribunal. His Honour noted that in the instant case the matters raised in the original application had been used by the Tribunal to suggest recent invention by the appellant.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FMCA 3">Reference was made to NBKS v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs and Another (2006) 156 FCR 205 in which the Tribunal was said to have relied on the failure of a report by a clinical psychologist to address a particular matter in arriving at a finding adverse to the applicant. The information in that case was not merely an observable gap in the evidence in relation to a document obtained by the Tribunal. Rather, as Weinberg J observed (at [26]), Allsop J (with whom he agreed) was "of the view that the absence of any statement in [the psychologist's] report regarding the likely behaviour of the appellant in a confrontational situation was not treated by the Tribunal merely as a "gap", but as implicitly probative of the psychologist's view that there was no such danger" . Weinberg J stated (at [38]): "This amounted to a positive use of information, as opposed to an observation made in relation to a failure to give information or make a claim" . Hence the Tribunal used the omission in a way that went beyond and was distinguished from a "mere omission" (see SZCNP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140). It was contended for the applicant that, as in NBKS, the Tribunal in this case had used the absence of information (the absence of any reply to the emails) in a positive way.  Similarly Weinberg J referred to cases that indicated that where a Tribunal used omissions in a way that went beyond "mere omissions" this "amounted to a positive use of information, as opposed to an observation made in relation to a failure to give information or make a claim" (at [38] and see SZEEU , SZGGT v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 435 and SZCNP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140). While other cases concerned omissions from claims made by an applicant, in NBKS Weinberg J was of the view that such principles were applicable to omissions in other evidence before the Tribunal, at least where the Tribunal "treats the omission as though it provides implicit support for a positive assertion that is detrimental to an applicant's case" (at [39]). His Honour stated: "It makes no difference whether the omission is to be found in a prior statement of an applicant or ... in a statement provided by a third party" (at [39]). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 1476">Following that decision, the applicant had sought, unsuccessfully, to challenge the Tribunal's decision both in this Court and the High Court: see SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140 and SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affair s [2007] HCATrans 239.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCA 1031">12 The appellants arguments commence from and rely upon 'the critical passage' of the Tribunal's reasons set out above. That is supplemented by other briefer passages to similar effect. The appellant submits that the paragraph betokens jurisdictional error as being identical to the impugned reasoning in SZECF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1200 ; (2005) 89 ALD 242 at [26] - [28] - [30] and [34]; SZDKK v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1203 at [25] - [25]; SZEEU [2006] FCAFC 2 ; 150 FCR 214 per Weinberg J at [158] and Allsop J at [220]-[221]; SXSB v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 319 at [19] ; NBKS v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 174 ; (2006) 156 FCR 205 at [32] - [39] per Weinberg J at [74] per Allsop J; SZGGT V Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 435 at [72] ; SZGDB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 431 at [25]- [26] and SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140 at [17] .  21 Additionally the first respondent submits that support for the objective approach favoured by Rares J is to be found in other single judge decisions in VWBF v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 851 ; (2006) 154 FCR 302 at [44] per Heerey J; SZCNP [2006] FCA 1140 at [18] per Tamberlin J; and SZDAP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1598 at [22] per Middleton J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FMCA 865">A distinction was referred to by Weinberg J in NBKS , when referring to a judgment of Tamberlin J: 
 
 
 38 To the same effect is SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2006] FCAFC 174">38 To the same effect is SZCNP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140. There Tamberlin J rejected a submission on behalf of the Minister that the term "information" in s 424A did not encompass a failure to mention a matter to the Tribunal. His Honour noted that in the instant case the matters raised in the original application had been used by the Tribunal to suggest recent invention by the appellant. That meant that the Tribunal used the omission in a way that went beyond "mere omissions" in the sequence of facts presented by the appellant. This amounted to a positive use of information, as opposed to an observation made in relation to a failure to give information or make a claim. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs8" from="[2006] FMCA 1575">SZEEU (supra) per Weinberg J at [177], and Allsop J at [207], also Allsop J in SZEZI v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1195 at [29] and SZEIQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1801 at [25] , Applicant S301/2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCAFC 155 at [19] , and Tamberlin J in SZCNP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1140 at [17]).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 441A Methods by which Tribunal gives documents to a person other than the Secretary</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>