<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Watson v CGU Insurance Limited [2006] FCA 1630 (28 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1630.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 912">discontinuance of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 912">whether discontinuance of proceedings will lead to an incurable injustice or disadvantage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 912">whether conditions should be imposed before leave granted to plaintiff to discontinue proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">officers and employees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">duties and powers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">duty of care and diligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">consent orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">responsibilities of chairman discussed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">s 1317e requirements for specificity discussed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">s 1317f discussed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">period of disqualification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 836">factors to consider for non-executive chairman.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 795">applications pursuant to part 31 rule 7 for concurrent hearings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 795">civil penalty proceedings applying the rules of evidence and procedure for civil matters (s. 1317l)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 795">other proceedings in which a contravention of s 184 "criminal offence" is alleged with "criminal intent"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1632">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1632">application for transfer of federal court proceedings to the supreme court of new south wales pursuant to s 5(4) of the jurisdiction of courts (cross-vesting) act 1987 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1632">proceedings related to other proceedings residing in the supreme court both conditionally and unconditionally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1632">consideration of inherent potential advantages in transferring proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1632">whether appropriate and in the interests of justice that proceedings be transferred to the supreme court</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1632">32 The requirement of s 5(4) of the Cross-vesting Act is the existence of 'related proceedings' between the court in which the application is made and the court to which the matters are being sought to be transferred. The authorities on this issue establish that there do not need to be identical parties to the two, or more, proceedings before they can be considered to be 'related' for the purposes of enlivening the cross-vesting power of the court. It is enough that the proceedings have one common party and involves common issues and common questions: Watson v CGU Insurance Limited [2006] FCA 1630 ; AMP Financial Planning Pty Ltd v Green [2004] NSWSC 1099 ; (2004) 51 ACSR 693. Related Proceedings - Identical Parties, Common Facts and Common Issues </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1104">3 Sackville J was persuaded that it would be in the interests of justice for the proceeding to be transferred to the Supreme Court of New South Wales and on 28 November 2006 made orders to that effect ( Watson v CGU Insurance Limited [2006] FCA 1630). The transferred proceeding became Supreme Court of New South Wales proceedings No 50198 of 2006 ("the transferred proceedings"). Numerous interlocutory steps have been taken in the transferred proceedings but there has as yet been no final hearing.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1317H Compensation orders--corporation/scheme civil penalty provisions</title>
<title id="l2">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 </title>
<title id="l3">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 - SECT 5 Transfer of proceedings</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>