<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1171 (8 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1171.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">re refugee review tribunal; ex parte h  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">affirmation by refugee review tribunal of decision to refuse applications for protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">credibility in issue before tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">constant interruptions of and challenges to evidence of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">whether vigorous testing of evidence might lead a fair-minded lay person to apprehend bias on the part of the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">appropriate modification of test for apprehended bias when applied to administrative proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 28">whether relief under s 75(v) of the constitution should be refused on discretionary grounds.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">johnson v johnson  courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">application for disqualification for bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">statement by trial judge about evidence to be relied upon</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">whether statement gave rise to reasonable apprehension of bias.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">prejudgment of credibility of witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">personal injuries trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">statements critical of evidence of defendant's medical witnesses in previous cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">further critical statements in reserved judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=cited from="[1989] HCA 44">reasonable apprehension of bias.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">prejudgment of issue in pending litigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">writ of prohibition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">superior court of record</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">family court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 39">the constitution (63 &amp; 64 vict., c. 12), s. 75 (v.) family law act 1975 (cth), s. 21 (2).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">protection (class xa) visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">citizen of china claiming fear of persecution for reason of political opinion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">whether tribunal failed to comply with migration act 1958 (cth) s.424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">no reviewable error.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">audio recording of tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 460">where applicant requested that court should listen to audio recording of tribunal hearing.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">refusal of a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">applicant claiming political persecution in china</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">issue of the applicant's identity raised at the tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">applicant asked to provide proof of his identity and doing so</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">tribunal making no finding on applicant's identity but rejecting his credibility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">whether the tribunal breached s.425 of the migration act 1958 (cth) considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.8" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">whether the tribunal decision vitiated by apprehended bias considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.9" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">tribunal informing the applicant at the hearing, when he was unable to produce his genuine chinese id card, that the card would prove his identity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.10" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">card later produced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.11" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1320">tribunal failing to accept the card as proof of identity but finding that the applicant was involved in identity fraud.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">claim that apprehended bias infected a tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">correct test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">relevance of factors that actually influenced the outcome</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">application of test to the facts  natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1299">apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">whether tribunal's evaluation of evidence before it was unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">whether any evidence of bias on the part of the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">where appellant sought to rely on tribunal transcript not before the federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">whether tribunal entitled to make an assumption based on appellant's evidence given at the hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">whether the appellant's answer fell within the ambit of s 424a(3)(b)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 257">appeal dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">refugee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">bad faith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.4" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.5" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">findings of fact are for the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.6" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">impermissible merits review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.7" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">tribunal complied with s.424a of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.8" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.9" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1761">application dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FMCA 460">The conduct of a Tribunal itself, which can necessitate the playing of compact discs or other recordings of the Tribunal hearing, has been considered in the well-known case of Re Refugee Review Tribunal; Ex parte H [18] where the test for apprehended bias is set out in [27] and [28] and in such decisions as VFAB of 2002 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [19] and SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [20] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FMCA 1320">In Re RRT Ex Parte H the High Court upheld a complaint of apprehended bias because the Court considered, on an examination of the transcript, that the Tribunal's constant interruptions suggested the Tribunal had a preconceived view of the applicant's account. In VFAB v MIMIA the Full Court upheld a complaint of apprehended bias on the finding, based on a review of the transcript that the Tribunal had engaged in a belligerent style of questioning. Finally, in SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration [2006] FCA 1171 , Cowdroy J found that on an analysis of the transcript of the oral hearing the Tribunal Member's questioning went beyond a vigorous exchange, and this, it was held, amounted to apprehended bias. In the present case a fair reading of the transcript does not indicate that the Tribunal Member brought a closed mind to the applicant's review application generally, or to the issue of his identity specifically, being the issue identified by the Court as being a possible foundation for a bias complaint relate to. On the contrary it is clear that the Tribunal Member had real concerns about the applicant's identity.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 1299">74 At [25] his Honour cited Re RRT; Ex parte H, VFAB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 872 ; (2003) 131 FCR 102 and SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1171. His Honour then said:
 'These examples of cases where apprehended bias has been found against the Tribunal indicate that the test is a strict one. It most certainly does not involve the court putting itself in the place of the Tribunal, deciding on the facts that it would have come to a different conclusion than the Tribunal did and then finding that this is what the hypothetical lay observer would have done, and therefore he or she would have thought that the failure to do so would have indicated a propensity or possibility of a mind that was not impartial. ' (Emphasis added) </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 257">3 On 14 September 2004 the Tribunal (differently constituted) affirmed the delegate's decision. However, on 8 September 2006, Cowdroy J ordered that the decision of that Tribunal be quashed and the matter be remitted to the Tribunal for reconsideration according to law. He was satisfied that the appellants had made out the ground of apprehended bias: SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1171. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 186">35 I record that during oral submissions the second appellant, on behalf of the appellants, contended that the Tribunal had demonstrated apprehended bias. The appellants referred to SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1171. The appellants did not raise before the Federal Magistrate the issue of apprehended bias by the Tribunal. There was no ground of appeal founded on apprehended bias. The making of an allegation of bias, whether actual or apprehended, is a serious matter and the allegation must be fully particularised and evidenced. The appellants did not put into evidence the transcript of the proceedings. The Tribunal's reasons do not evidence circumstances of apprehended bias. The SZEOQ decision has no application to the facts (so far as they are in evidence) in this case. The contention has no prospects of success and I refuse the appellants leave to raise this ground as a ground of appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCA 102">15 As has been stated in SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1171 at [22] the principles relating to bias have been well established. Bias may be established if it can be demonstrated that the Tribunal member was actually biased, or if a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the Judge might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question which the Court is required to decide: see Johnson v Johnson [2000] HCA 48 ; (2000) 201 CLR 488 at [11] ; Vakauta v Kelly [1989] HCA 44 ; (1989) 167 CLR 568 at 575; R v Watson; Ex parte Armstrong [1976] HCA 39 ; (1976) 136 CLR 248 at 258-263. As was held by the Full Court of the Federal Court in SBBS v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCAFC 361 ; (2002) 194 ALR 749 at [43] --- [48], an allegation of bad faith is a serious matter involving personal fault on the part of a decision maker; such allegation is not to be lightly made and must be clearly alleged and proved; there are many ways in which bad faith can occur and it is not possible to give a comprehensive definition; the presence or absence of honesty will often be crucial; the circumstances in which the Court will find an administrative decision maker has not acted in good faith are rare and extreme; mere error or irrationality does not of itself demonstrate a lack of good faith; errors of fact or law and illogicality will not demonstrate bad faith; the Court must make a decision as to whether or not bad faith is shown by inference from what the Tribunal has done or failed to do; and it is not necessary to demonstrate that the decision maker knew the decision was wrong.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2006] FMCA 1761">This complaint is not made out. 25. In SZEOQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1171 a recent Judgment of Cowdroy J., on appeal from this Court, (and setting aside a Judgment made by this Court) His Honour said at [32]: 
 
 
 "Nicholls FM placed reliance upon the fact that, in respect of the appellant's Roma ethnicity, the Tribunal had given the appellant the benefit of the doubt and accepted that he was an ethnic Roma/Russian. There are two answers to this statement. Firstly, the comment that the appellant did not have the appearance of an ethnic Roma was not the only statement of the Tribunal member which might be seen to suggest a prejudgment of the appellant's case.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l1">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 39B Original jurisdiction of Federal Court of Australia</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>