<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZEQB v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1070 (16 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1070.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">nagv and nagw of 2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">tribunal found that appellants had genuine fear of persecution if returned to russia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">tribunal concluded that israel was a third country where appellants would have effective protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">protection visa refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">whether the tribunal failed to observe the requirements in ss 36 and 65 of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">whether each appellant was a non-citizen in australia to whom australia has protection obligations under the convention relating to the status of refugees as amended by the protocol relating to the status of refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">whether this means anything other than "refugee" within the meaning of art 1 of the convention relating to the status of refugees as amended by the protocol relating to the status of refugees.  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">international law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">construction of the convention relating to the status of refugees as amended by protocol relating to the status of refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 6">whether a non-refoulement obligation precludes removal to a safe third country.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 430 Refugee Review Tribunal to record its decisions etc.</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>