<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>GORDON CHARLIE v CAPE YORK LAND COUNCIL [2006] FCA 1418 (31 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1418.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 579">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 579">consideration of an application by indigenous respondents to dismiss an application for a compensation determination filed by walmbaar aboriginal corporation as registered native title body corporate for the purposes of the hopevale determination, pursuant to s 50(2) of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 579">consideration of the decision-making process by which the prescribed body corporate reached a decision to institute proceedings under s 61(1) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 579">consideration of the rules of the corporation, the provisions of the native title act and native title (prescribed bodies corporate) regulations 1999 as the source of the corporation's authority to commence the proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1683">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1683">further application for an interim injunction to restrain the conduct of an authorisation meeting to be held at hope vale convened by the cape york land council in connection with a native title determination application by the dingaal claim group.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 579">Proceeding QG6004 of 1998 was a claim by the Dingaal People of native title rights and a claim of connection with Lizard Island and the islands offshore from Cape Flattery (and associated waters). On 28 February 2006, Dingaal clan members convened at the Church Hall in Hopevale to consider a presentation in relation to the claim by the National Native Title Tribunal, a report and presentation by a consultant anthropologist, Dr Fiona Powell, and a presentation on future tasks to be undertaken by the Land Council. The claim group members unanimously resolved to amend the claim to include other claimant groups asserting rights in relation to the land and waters, namely, the Thanil, Nguuruumungu, Gulaal, Ngaatha and Thittaar Peoples. That resolution made necessary an amendment to the application so as to alter the area of land and waters the subject of the claim and the composition of the claim groups. The Land Council sought to convene a meeting of Dingaal members on 31 October 2006 at 11.00am at Hopevale to authorise amendments to the native title application. Gordon Charlie sought to restrain the conduct of the meeting that morning on the footing that the Charlie family incorporates a sub-group family described as the Brim family and members of that family had not been invited to the meeting nor incorporated within the claim. The Brim family members were said to be in tension with the Baru and Yoren families. Gordon Charlie was unsuccessful in his application for an injunction ( Gordon Charlie v Cape York Land Council [2006] FCA 1418). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2006] FCA 1683">5 That application was heard and determined on 31 October 2006 and the Court ordered that the Notice of Motion filed by Mr Charlie be dismissed ( Gordon Charlie v Cape York Land Council [2006] FCA 1418). The Court provided extensive written reasons on 31 October 2006 for the making of that order.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l1">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 203BB Facilitation and assistance functions</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>