<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 122 (24 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/122.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1662">1. on the front page in the second line of the the word "applicant's" should read "employee's".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">general protection claim involving dismissal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">application for compensation and pecuniary penalty for contravention of the fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">application for declarations that the respondent contravened general protection provisions of the fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether adverse action taken against employee by employer in breach of s 340(1) and s 346(1) of the fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether objective facts proved to establish contravention of workplace rights to enliven s 361 reverse onus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">s 361 reverse onus enlivened</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">no evidence adduced of decision-making process of respondent in respect of adverse actions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">s 361 reverse onus not discharged  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">jurisdictional issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether the employment agreement described as an itea is a "workplace instrument" for the purposes of s 340 of the fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">"workplace instrument" defined to be an instrument made under, or recognised by, a "workplace law" for the purposes of s 12 of the fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">where the fair work (transitional provisions and consequential amendments) act 2009 (cth) provides for the continued existence of an itea</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether the fair work (transitional provisions and consequential amendments) act 2009 (cth) regulates relationships between employers and employees so that it is a "workplace law"  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">jurisdictional issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether applicant required to plead and prove there is an itea</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">where respondent has pleaded in its defence that an itea was made and that the employee had the benefit of it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">pleading treated as an admission that the itea was an itea for the purposes of the fair work act 2009 (cth)  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">jurisdictional issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether fair work act 2009 (cth) applies to pre-1 july 2009 conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.20" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether there is a relevant "workplace law" to support the "workplace right"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.21" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">found "workplace right" not limited to an entitlement or ability that arises under the fair work act 2009 (cth)  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.22" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">whether order under s 545 fair work act 2009 (cth) may order compensation for non economic loss such as distress, hurt and humiliation  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.23" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 333">payment of interest under s 51a federal court act of australia 1976 (cth) as part of judgment sum on compensation ordered under s 545 fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">application alleging injury and termination of employment for prohibited reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">employee claimed entitlement to return to work after maternity leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">referral of matter to union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">commencing conciliation proceedings against employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">employer alleges poor performance by employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">damages for breach of contract.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">award entitlement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">maternity leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">whether award applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">whether employer receiving recurrent funding from state or federal government.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">contract of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">notice of termination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">statutory guarantee of maternity leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">whether notice of termination can run concurrent with maternity leave.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">contract of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">notice of termination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 463">mitigation.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">industrial relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">termination of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">summary dismissal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">penalty imposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">to be paid to the applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">damages for loss of earnings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1883">no damages for distress, disruption, or injured feelings.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 425">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 425">breadth of relief available for conduct in contravention of part xa of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 425">circumstances in which declaratory relief should be granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 425">principles governing the imposition of penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 425">when orders are appropriate and necessary to stop the contravening conduct and/or remedy its effects</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of compensation pursuant to s 298u of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) in respect of contraventions of s 298k</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of a penalty pursuant to s 298u</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of whether a penalty so ordered ought to be paid to the individuals affected by the conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the scope of declarations to be made.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 333">Further, in relation to the former WR Act s 298U(c), which empowered the Court to make an order requiring the person or industrial association to pay an employee or independent contractor compensation of such amount as the Court considers necessary, this Court took a broad view of the compensation that should be paid. In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 122 ; (2006) 150 IR 179 , Marshall J observed that: 
 
 'Compensation' is a broad concept which should not be interpreted in a narrow way. In an appropriate case the Court is able to order compensation for non economic loss. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FMCA 463">The Union sought an order that compensation be paid to Ms Poppas in relation to any proven breach of s.792(1). However, there is no evidence of any additional non-economic loss warranting compensation in a sum greater than that payable as damages for any breach of the Contract of Employment. [153] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 1883">Justice Greenwood also refers to the decision of Justice Marshall in Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing and Allied Services Union of Australia v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 122 ; (2006) 150 IR 179 at [11] , where Justice Marshall concluded that something more than the usual elements of distress must be demonstrated. It is submitted that the decision of Justice Marshall must be read in light of other decisions, including the decision of Justice Lee in Aitken v Construction, Mining, Energy, Timberyards, Sawmills and Woodworkers Union of Australia (WA Branch) (1995) 63 IR 1 at 9. Justice Greenwood summarised Justice Lee's position at 213 as follows: As a matter of general principle, Lee J considered that the court would have regard to 'what is reasonable in the circumstances' and would consider 'the detriment occasioned to the employee by the employer's contravention of the Act' and the extent to which 'it is reasonable to compensate the employee for such consequences'. In some cases, it may be appropriate to include in the measure of compensation a sum 'sufficient to compensate an employee for mental distress or injured feelings caused by a harsh, unjust or unreasonable termination of employment'. 
The Court is disinclined to award compensation for mental stress etc because from what follows below, the applicant will obtain payment for all the award shortfalls and her superannuation contribution entitlements. In addition, she was not out of employment for a protracted period, she did not seek re-employment with the first respondent and was refused, she did not lose entitlements accrued over a long period of employment, and there was no indication of any particular or unusual level of stress or anxiety. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 425">16 In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 122 at [4] Marshall J expressed his agreement with the views of Madgwick J. Relevantly, Marshall J highlighted the flexibility the Court possesses to, in effect, correct injustice.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2006] FCA 1302">In addition, not every termination of employment will attract compensation. In Burazin , their Honours Wilcox CJ, Von Doussa and Marshall JJ concluded that in the circumstances of that case, there were 'unusual exacerbating circumstances that make it appropriate to include in the compensation an allowance for distress unnecessarily caused to Mrs Burazin'. In Communications, Electrical, Electronic, Energy, Information, Postal, Plumbing &amp; Allied Services Union of Australia v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 122 at [11] , Marshall J concluded that something more than the usual element of distress which accompanies most terminations must be demonstrated although the notion of 'unusual and exacerbating circumstances' is not necessarily the test. In Aitken v Construction, Mining, Energy, Timberyards, Sawmills and Woodworkers Union of Australia (Western Australian Branch) (1995) 63 IR 1 at 9, Lee J made a number of observations concerning those factors which might inform whether it is 'appropriate in all the circumstances of the case to make an order requiring the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount as the court thinks appropriate' in respect of a contravention of the relevant Division of the Industrial Relations Act 1998 (Cth) ('the IR Act') for the purposes of s 170EE of the IR Act. That particular legislation also set a cap upon the amount of the compensation that might be ordered.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l1">WORKPLACE RELATIONS ACT 1996 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>