<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Intellectual Property Pty Ltd (ACN 089 962 041) v Mygroups Pty Ltd (ACN 116 583 748) [2006] FCA 15 (23 January 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/15.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">applicant exclusive dealer of mobile phone services for respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">respondent claims that commissions paid to applicant exceeded "cap" as specified in written dealership agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">notice issued by respondent requiring repayment of alleged overpayment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">applicant claims respondent gave oral assurance in pre-contractual negotiations that "cap" would not be enforced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">applicant further claims amount of overpayment miscalculated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">application for interlocutory injunction restraining respondent from requiring applicant to pay amount of alleged overpayment or treating failure to pay as grounds for termination of dealership agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">claim in promissory estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">claim for breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">whether either claim gives rise to a serious question to be tried</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">whether balance of convenience favours grant of interlocutory relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1365">whether discretionary factors operate to prevent such relief being granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">interlocutory injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">whether use of a fourfold colour scheme by the defendant is likely to mislead or deceive consumers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">whether a prima facie case for relief is shown</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">balance of convenience</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 343">interlocutory injunction refused.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] VSC 343">
 
 38 Mitre 10 claims that these circumstances are very clearly analogous to those in which an interlocutory injunction was granted in favour of Clark Rubber by Goldberg J in Intellectual Property Pty Ltd v Mygroups Pty Ltd. [9] In that case, Goldberg J restrained an operator of a foam-rubber product store in Victoria from trading whilst the store's exterior was painted in bright yellow, with red and blue lettering for signage. That was the same combination of colours used by Clark Rubber on its stores selling the same or similar products. The evidence was that Clark Rubber had 70 stores Australia-wide, 65 of which used that colour scheme. It had traded in Australia for 60 years. The selection of colours was accepted by his Honour to be, rather than functional or utilitarian, idiosyncratic. His Honour accepted that on the evidence in that case there was a serious question to be tried that: 
 
 
 ... the Clark Rubber colour scheme is quite distinctive and that it creates a strong impression with consumers who view it independently of the name 'Clark Rubber'. [10] </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 52 Misleading or deceptive conduct.</title>
<title id="l2">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 53 False representations.</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l4">FAIR TRADING ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l5">Fair Trading Act 1999 - SECT 9 Application of Australian Consumer Law</title>
<title id="l6">Fair Trading Act 1999 - SECT 12 Interpretation of Australian Consumer Law</title>
</legistitles>
</case>