<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXDQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1632 (28 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1632.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">applicant s v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">application for protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">well-founded fear of persecution for reason of membership of particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">particular social group identified as able-bodied young men from afghanistan</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether member of a particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether afghan society must perceive the particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether enmity or malignity necessary to establish persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether facts reveal law of general application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether implementation of law of general application can amount to persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 25">whether implementation of ad hoc policy can amount to persecution.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">refugee status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">interpretation of convention and protocol on refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">meaning of "particular social group"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">whether persons who had "turned queen's evidence" constituted a particular social group under convention  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">ministers discretion to set aside decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">interpretation of s115(5) and (10) of migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">whether minister has duty to consider whether it is in the public interest to set aside a decision  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">notice of deportation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">interpretation of r179 of migration regulations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">whether r179 required use of a prescribed notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">no notice prescribed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 637">notice still validly given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">judicial review sought on decision on basis to properly identify convention reason based on conjunctive of being a lower-caste hindu and landowner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">allegation tribunal engaged in suspect reasoning</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">applicant seeking to reargue merits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">s.424 invitation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">letter of advice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 838">does not import obligations under s.424b but is facultative only.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">migration act 1958 (cth) s 91r(1) , s 91s</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">application for protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">claim that appellants have well-founded fear of being persecuted for membership of particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">particular social group was wealthy middle class citizens of sri lanka</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">appellants are sinhalese</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">appellants claimed they were at risk of persecution and abduction by sinhalese military due to suspected ties with tamils and because of their particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">delegate of minister refused application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">tribunal affirmed decision of delegate and rejected appellants' claims of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">tribunal found appellants had not previously suffered serious harm and did not have well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">decision of tribunal affirmed by federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">whether jurisdictional error by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">whether failure of tribunal to identify correct social group when considering if appellants had "well-founded fear" of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">whether tribunal was distracted by appellants' ethnicity when making decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">whether tribunal needed to identify particular social group once it rejected appellants' claims of persecution   held : appeal dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 543">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">fear of persecution due to membership of a particular social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">whether the refugee review tribunal misdirected itself in identifying the relevant social group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">whether it is necessary for tribunal to make determination on membership of particular social group when the applicant has failed to establish a well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1554">whether tribunal addressed itself correctly in determining whether there was a well founded fear within the meaning of the refugee convention.  australian broadcasting tribunal v bond (bond media case) [1990] hca 33 ; (1990) 170 clr 321  canada (attorney-general) v ward (1993) 2 scr 689</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">review of migration review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">delegate refused to grant the applicant a sub class 801 permanent visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">decision affirmed by the tribunal but set aside upon judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">remitted to the tribunal for reconsideration and upon reconsideration the tribunal affirmed the earlier decision to refuse the visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">that decision was also subject to successful judicial review and remitted to the tribunal for reconsideration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1005">the reconsideration again concluded with the decision to affirm the delegate's decision.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 838">Having made those findings, the need for the Tribunal to identify the particular social group of which the applicant claimed to be a member was rendered otiose. [5] While it might be contended that the Tribunal did not consider the particular social group and adopt the two step approach as provided for in Dranichnikov [6] , it is not to the point to say that the Tribunal should have followed these steps. As his Honour Justice Finkelstein stated in MZXDQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [7] : "The Appellant contended before this Court that this was an impermissible line of reasoning. He argued that the steps outlined in Dranichnikov must be followed even if the Tribunal is of the view that the Applicant's fear is unrelated to the membership of any such group. This is plainly incorrect.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 543">The appellants submitted that this approach is contrary to Dranichnikov (2003) 197 ALR 389. However relevantly in MZXDQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1632 Finkelstein J observed: 
 [18] The Appellant contended before this Court that this was an impermissible line of reasoning. He argued that the steps outlined in Dranichnikov must be followed even if the Tribunal is of the view that the Applicant's fear is unrelated to the membership of any such group. This is plainly incorrect. Courts will frequently skip over more difficult questions if the main issue can be determined from the answer to a simpler later question: in the law of negligence, there is no need to ask whether there is a duty of care if it is obvious that there has been no damage. In this case, moving to the last step in Dranichnikov was quite proper. 

 
 ... 

 
 [25] It is entirely proper to avoid identifying the appropriate "particular social group" if it is unnecessary to do so. Dranichnikov does not demand otherwise. 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FMCA 1554">That submission was premised upon a determination by the Tribunal that the applicant's accounts of events which he alleged occurred between 6 April and 7 May 2007 lacked creditability. It submitted that it followed that because this matter could not be established there was no need to consider the "possible" Convention reason. So much was said to be consistent with an approach to Drainichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (supra) as considered by Finkelstein J in MZXDQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1632. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FMCA 1005">It was open for the Tribunal to make a finding as to whether or not the Applicant was a spouse for the purpose of the visa Application. It decided that matter against the Applicant as it was entitled to do. On so finding it was unnecessary to go on and consider claims in respect of domestic violence: MZXDQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 1632 per Finkelstein J. Standard of Proof
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
</legistitles>
</case>