<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission, in thematter of Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) (No 2) [2006] FCA 1285 (29 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1285.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">companies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">issue or offer of interests to the public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">pine plantation scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">agreements made through salesmen without advertising or initial solicitation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">whether interests</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">whether issue or offer to the public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 49">companies act 1961 (n.s.w.), ss. 76(1), 81(1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">summary dismissal of parts of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">whether no reasonable prospect of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">whether to strike out parts of application and pleadings where specific relief not sought under s.1325 of corporations act .  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">alleged misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">whether claim relates to financial services and products</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">whether exclusionary provisions of s.51af of trade practices act apply.  courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">corporations act jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 762">associated matter.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">torrens title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether mortgagee has indefeasible title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether applicant is 'tenant in possession' for purposes of s 42(2)(e) of transfer of land act 1958 (vic)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether applicant's interest falls within s 40(3)(d) of land titles act 1980 (tas)   real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether lease for life void for uncertainty of duration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether certainty of duration rule applies to periodic leases or leases for life   real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">time of creation of lease and mortgage   equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">whether applicant has equitable lease</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">competing equitable interests</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">application of principle that extent of equitable interest is commensurate with availability of specific performance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">nature of unpaid vendor's lien</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1536">tenancy by estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">no intention to create legal relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">no estate of a life tenant in possession</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">claimed interest as tenant in possession under s 42(2)(e) of the transfer of land act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 373">section 42(2)(e) transfer of land act 1958 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">representative proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">approval of settlement against one respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">where application unopposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">principles relevant to court approval</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">provision of adequate notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">whether proposed settlement is fair and reasonable and in the interests of group members as a whole</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 897">confidentiality of settlement terms</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 762">Objectively, that requires a positive act with the capacity to generate a financial return, [36] not merely the taking of steps preparatory to such an act, for example, discussions prior to giving the money to a financial services licensee, or the giving of the money itself. In Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Money For Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) &amp; Ors (No. 2) [37] the Federal Court dealt with the definition of "financial investment" in s.12BAA(4) of the ASIC Act and said as follows: [20] The key elements of the first limb of this definition are: (1) handing over (the statutory word is "gives") an asset (money or money's worth) to another person; and (2) applying or intending to apply the asset to produce an advantage for the investor (the advantage being a "financial return" or some other "benefit"). At a superficial level it is clear what is intended; a financial investment is when a person lays out money or capital for the purpose of getting a return. This is what a businessperson would understand as a "financial investment".</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 468">The applicants advance a number of arguments in support of their claim for indemnity costs. Primarily, the applicants rely on the decision of Finkelstein J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1285 ; (2006) 155 FCR 349 (' MFL (No 2) '), where his Honour considered the scheme operated by Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd and whether it amounted to a vehicle for 'financial investment' as defined in s 12BAA(4) of the Australian Securities and Investments Commission Act 2001 (Cth). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 1536">Secondly, the question of the operation of s 42(2)(e) of the TLA has been considered previously in the context of the Money for Living scheme in Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission, in the matter of Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) (No 2) [2006] FCA 1285 , where Finkelstein J made the following comments (at [24] --- [25]): 
 I base this conclusion on s 42(2)(e) of the Transfer of Land Act 1958 (Vic) and the equivalent provision in the Torrens legislation in other States. The effect of s 42(2)(e) is that the estate of a registered proprietor of land (including the proprietor of a mortgage) is subject to the rights of a tenant in possession. In this area the relevant principles are clearly established. Whilst some cross-examination occurred in the course of the trial, no issues of credit arose in relation to any witness and, in the main, the relevant sequence of events was documented. The scheme that was introduced and operated by Money for Living was described by Finkelstein J in Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission, in the matter of Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (Administrators Appointed) (No 2) [2006] FCA 1285 , and I adopt that description which accords with the evidence before me. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] VSC 373"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 897">2 In Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (admin appted) &amp; Ors (No.2) [2006] FCA 1285 , Finkelstein J described the factual background to these proceedings in the following terms:
 
 "Money for Living (Aust) Pty Ltd (admin apptd) ["MFL"] and MFL Property Holdings Pty Ltd (admin apptd) ["MFPL"] , by their directors, ... Stephen O'Neill, Gary O'Neill and Jolanta Olszewski - promoted a scheme that enticed home-owners, typically retirees or pensioners, to sell their homes in return for what the promoters described as a 'guaranteed' income and a 'guaranteed' right to live in their former home for life. Many people were induced to participate in the scheme. The idea was that the home-owners could free up and live off the equity that would otherwise be tied up in their family home. To the great misfortune of those people the scheme collapsed. The companies that purchased their homes (the purchaser was either MFL or MFLP) are insolvent and have had administrators appointed. The 'guaranteed income' is not being paid. For some, their life tenancy may be at risk. " 
 

I will describe this as the 'MFL Scheme'.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12BAA Definition of financial product</title>
<title id="l2">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12BAB Meaning of financial service</title>
<title id="l3">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12DA Misleading or deceptive conduct</title>
<title id="l4">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12DB False or misleading representations</title>
<title id="l5">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12DC False or misleading representations in relation to financial products that involve interests in land</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 206B Automatic disqualification</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1041H Misleading or deceptive conduct (civil liability only)</title>
<title id="l9">TRANSFER OF LAND ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l10">Transfer of Land Act 1958 - SECT 42 Estate of registered proprietor paramount</title>
<title id="l11">Transfer of Land Act 1928 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>