<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wakaman People 2 v Native Title Registrar and Authorised Delegate (with Corrigendum dated 5 September 2006) [2006] FCA 1198 (5 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1198.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">requirements for proper commencement of suit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">necessity to establish that applicant is authorised by all the persons in the native title claim group to make the subject applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">applications failed to establish either individual authorisation or authorisation in accordance with customary law or traditional practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">application by another group member to be a replacement applicant failed because of inability to prove his application was authorised by the claim group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">principal proceedings not well commenced and foredoomed to failure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 1637">proceeding dismissed as abuse of process.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">purchase of business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">"assumption" by purchaser of liability of vendor for or on account of annual leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether employees to be "taken over" by purchaser</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether derivation by purchaser of income in the sum of that liability in circumstances of the case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether gain constituted income according to ordinary concepts or whether amount had been received by way of insurance or indemnity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">income tax assessment act 1936 , ss. 25, 26 (j).  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether appeal to the federal court from the administrative appeals tribunal an appeal on "question of law"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">administrative appeals tribunal act 1977, s. 44.  federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">"matter" within meaning of chapter iii of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether s. 44 of the administrative appeals tribunal act 1977 confers jurisdiction with respect to a "matter"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">the content of that matter.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">aborigines</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">claimant application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">registration of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">criteria for registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">sufficiency of asserted factual basis for native title rights and interests claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">relationship to statutory requirements for contents of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">review of registrar's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">nature of review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">appeal against review decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">whether unduly onerous standard applied by reference to sufficiency of evidence in support of application  held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">registration of native title claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">application for review of native title registrar's decision refusing registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">whether registrar erred in making decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">proper construction of registrar's function under s 190c(4)(b) of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">registration of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">authorisation of a number of persons to act as an applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether native title registrar correct in deciding not to accept amended application for registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">effect of resolutions passed at authorisation meeting</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">withdrawal of members of the applicant after authorisation meeting but before registration of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether further authorisation meeting required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">proper interpretation of ' the applicant ' in s 61(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">application of the merits test in s 190b  relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">appropriate relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">registration of rights on native title registrar under s 186(1)(g)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether appropriate for native title registrar to revoke decision  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.14" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether appropriate for court to exercise its discretion to make an order for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.15" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether actions of registrar unreasonable in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.16" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 192">whether registrar unreasonably maintained his position</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCAFC 157">89 In Wakaman People No 2 v Native Title Registrar [2006] FCA 1198 ; (2006) 155 FCR 107 , Kiefel J applied the reasoning of the Full Court in Strickland [2000] FCA 652 ; 99 FCR 33 and characterised it thus (at [29]):
 The legislation does not specify the nature or the extent of the Court's review under s 190D(3) or impose any limitation upon the material that may be taken into account. Jurisdiction is conferred by s 190D(2) and (3) in the broadest of terms (at [64]). A review under s 190D is not restricted to considerations and determination of a question of law. Section 190D(4) makes it plain that the review extends to determinations of issues of fact. The NTA does not proceed upon the premise that determinations of fact in the relevant controversy have been settled by the administrative determination and that the only matter in respect of which jurisdiction is conferred upon the Court is any controversy on questions of law. 
 
 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 574">31 However while Doepel may be authority that, for the purposes of section 190C (2), the Registrar is not required to look beyond the terms of the application (cf Wakaman People No 2 v Native Title Registrar [2006] FCA 1198 ; (2006) 155 FCR 107 at 118), it does not necessarily follow that the same principle applies to the satisfaction required of the Registrar or his delegate by s 190C (4)(b). Indeed in the Wiri #2 Application, although the delegate was not satisfied as required by s 190C (4)(b), after considering each of the requirements of ss 61 and 62 the delegate was satisfied that the Application contained all the details and other information required by those sections, and accordingly complied with s 190C (2). With specific reference to the native title claim group, the delegate observed :
 There is nothing on the face of the description of the persons in the native title claim group to indicate that not all persons in the native title claim group are included in the description or that it is in fact a sub-group of the native title claim group for the area of the application. Having said that, I do have regard to information elsewhere before me in relation to this issue in my consideration of the authorisation condition under s. 190C (4)(b). But with the authority of Doepel in mind, I do not consider this information under this condition... </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 192">98 Kiefel J in Wakaman People #2 v Native Title Registrar and Authorised Delegate [2006] FCA 1198 at par 29:
 
 'In [Western Australia v Strickland [2000] FCA 652 ; (2000) 99 FCR 33] the Full Court held that the power given by s 190A to the Registrar by the NTA to make decisions in respect of the registration of an application made to the Court is the exercise of an administrative power in respect of a matter in which the Court is exercising jurisdiction. The legislation does not specify the nature or the extent of the Court's review under s 190D(3) or impose any limitation upon the material that may be taken into account. Jurisdiction is conferred by s 190D(2) and (3) in the broadest of terms. A review under s 190D is not restricted to considerations and determination of a question of law. Section 190D(4) makes it plain that the review extends to determinations of issues of fact. The NTA does not proceed upon the premise that determinations of fact in the relevant controversy have been settled by the administrative determination and that the only matter in respect of which jurisdiction is conferred upon the Court is any controversy on questions of law. The Honours said that ' the review proceeding enlivens the jurisdiction of the Court in respect of the whole matter ' ... Their Honours concluded that it was Parliament's intention that the right of review would place before the Court the controversy constituted by the issues of fact and law raised between the parties and that, upon a ground of review being established, appropriate orders may be made to do justice as between parties. '  
 

45 In Wakaman People # 2 v Native Title Registrar and Authorised Delegate [2006] FCA 1198 , Kiefel J summarised the Court's powers and functions, and said at par 29:
 
 'Whilst the applicant's case for review is based upon the identification of an error on the part of the delegate, it is not submitted that the Court is limited to a review based upon questions of law. The intervenor does not argue against that contention, given the decision of the Full Court in Western Australia v Strickland [2000] FCA 652 ; (2000) 99 FCR 33. I had previously expressed a view different to that in Strickland (in Powder v Registrar, National Native Title Tribunal [1999] FCA 913 ; (1999) 92 FCR 454) but consider that I am now bound by the decision of the Full Court.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l1">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 61 Native title and compensation applications</title>
<title id="l2">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 62 Information etc. in relation to certain applications</title>
<title id="l3">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 63 Reference of applications to Native Title Registrar</title>
<title id="l4">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 84A Intervention by Commonwealth Minister</title>
<title id="l5">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 99 Delegation by Registrar</title>
<title id="l6">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190A Registrar to consider claims</title>
<title id="l7">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190B Registration: conditions about merits of the claim</title>
<title id="l8">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190C Registration: conditions about procedural and other matters</title>
<title id="l9">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 251B Authorising the making of applications</title>
<title id="l10">NATIVE TITLE AMENDMENT ACT 1998 </title>
<title id="l11">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>