<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Dragan Vasiljkovic v Minister for Justice and Customsand Ors (with Corrigendum dated 17 October 2006) [2006] FCA 1346 (13 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1346.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">vasiljkovic v commonwealth of australia  extradition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">plaintiff remanded in custody pending determination of eligibility for surrender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">arrest warrant for plaintiff in force in croatia on charge of certain war crimes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">arrest warrant constitutes relevant "supporting documentation" for purposes of s 19 of the extradition act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">statement made by croatian investigating authorities of a well-founded suspicion that plaintiff committed the offences alleged, including recitation of evidence provided by witnesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">croatia declared to be an "extradition country" by extradition (croatia) regulations 2004 (cth), regs 3, 4</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether pt ii of the extradition act is a valid law of the commonwealth.  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">judicial power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">plaintiff detained pending determination of eligibility for surrender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">extradition act , s 19(1) provided power of an administrative nature to conduct proceedings to determine eligibility for surrender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">extradition act , s 19(5) provided that the person to whom the proceedings relate is not entitled to adduce evidence to contradict allegations that the person has engaged in the conduct constituting an extradition offence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">no prima facie evidence requirement applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether pt ii of the extradition act is invalid to the extent that it purports to confer a power to deprive an australian citizen of liberty otherwise than in exercise of the judicial power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether pt ii of the extradition act when read together with the extradition (croatia) regulations is invalid to the extent that it purports to confer a power to deprive an australian citizen of liberty otherwise than upon a finding that there exists a prima facie case against that person of the commission of the offences alleged by the state requesting extradition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether law authorising such involuntary detention requires machinery for testing the validity of the charges made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether surrender proceedings are an integer of a "matter" for the purposes of ch iii of the constitution .  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">external affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">extradition (croatia) regulations not made pursuant to any treaty between australia and croatia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether, in the absence of a treaty, the declaration by the extradition (croatia) regulations of croatia as an extradition country is invalid for want of support by s 51(xxix) of the constitution or any other legislative power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether pt ii of the extradition act and the extradition (croatia) regulations operate by reference to the conduct of the plaintiff external to australia or by reference to an untested and untestable allegation of such conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 40">whether the mere fact of a request by a foreign state makes the subject-matter of the request amenable to the exercise of the legislative power conferred by s 51(xxix).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">pasini v united mexican states  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">judicial power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">extradition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">jurisdiction of federal court to review order by magistrate that applicant, being eligible for surrender to extradition country, be committed to prison</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">provision requiring federal court to have regard only to the material before the magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">whether provision denies to the federal court power to receive evidence led to show that proceeding before it was an abuse of its process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">whether consistent with the exercise of the judicial power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">whether provision enabling curial review of administrative function amounts to purported conferral of non-judicial power.  extradition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">judicial review by federal court of magistrate's order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">provision requiring federal court to have regard only to material before the magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">whether provision invalid under the constitution as inconsistent with the exercise of federal power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 3">whether provision invalid as conferral of non-judicial power to participate in administrative function.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">powers of the commonwealth parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">external affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">war crimes legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">act creating offence for australian citizen to have committed war crimes in europe during world war ii</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">validity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">judicial power of commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">effect of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">law making person guilty of a crime by reason of having committed act which not criminal when committed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">whether intrusion into judicial power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">the constitution (63 and 64 vict c. 12), s. 51(vi) , (xxix), ch. iii</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 32">war crimes act 1945 (cth), ss. 5 , 6 (1), (3), 7 , 9 , 11 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCAfam 551">family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCAfam 551">parenting orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCAfam 551">interim orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCAfam 551">whether mother's mental state a risk to child.  family law act 1975 , ss.60cc , 61da  goode v goode (2006) fca 1346  re k guidelines [1994] famca 21 ; (1994) flc 92-461</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">extradition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">application for bail pending review of magistrate's decision under s 19 of the extradition act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">existence of special circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">flight risk</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">prospects of success in review of the magistrate's decision pursuant to s 21 of the extradition act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">presumption against the grant of bail</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1902">grant of bail in court's discretion.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FMCAfam 551">I need to follow the process which the Full Court of the Family Court has described in Goode v Goode (2006) FCA 1346 , particularly in paragraph 82. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 1902">5 Following his arrest on 19 January 2006 Mr Snedden has made three applications for bail to various magistrates. On 25 January 2006 Mr Snedden also instituted proceedings in the High Court of Australia for a writ of habeas corpus, challenging the constitutional validity of both s 15 of the Act and the Extradition (Croatia) Regulations 2004 (Cth) ('the Regulations'). On 15 June 2006 the High Court dismissed the special case: see Vasiljkovic v The Commonwealth of Australia [2006] HCA 40 ; (2006) 227 CLR 614. The remainder of those proceedings were remitted by Gummow J to this Court and became proceedings NSD118/2007. Mr Snedden also commenced proceedings on 7 July 2006 in this Court (NSD1312/2006) seeking an order in the nature of habeas corpus against the Minister and two magistrates and an order that the Minister, the Governor of Parklea Correction Centre and a magistrate be restrained from taking any steps to facilitate Mr Snedden's surrender to Croatia. An interlocutory motion of the Minister to have such proceedings adjourned pending the magistrate's determination of Mr Snedden's eligibility for surrender pursuant to s 19 of the Act was granted on 13 October 2006: see Dragan Vasiljkovic [2006] FCA 1346. Subsequently on 19 November 2007 both NSD1312/2006 and NSD118/2007 were dismissed on 19 November 2007. 2 The facts surrounding the detention of Mr Snedden have already been dealt with by this Court: see Dragan Vasiljkovic v Minister for Justice and Customs [2006] FCA 1346. For convenience the Court will set out a brief background to the proceedings hereunder.  29 But for Mr Snedden's October 2006 application to the Court (see Dragan Vasiljkovic [2006] FCA 1346) and his proceedings to review the decision of the magistrate, the extradition would in all probability have been concluded. Accordingly the extradition process is in its final stages. In Cabal 209 CLR at [62], the High Court said:
 
 In determining whether bail will be granted, one of the most important factors will be the stage which the proceedings have reached. As the case proceeds through the legal system, the chance of obtaining bail reduces, despite the existence of special circumstances. As the case against the defendant is confirmed at each step in the judicial hierarchy, the public interest in extraditing the defendant weighs more heavily against him or her. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FamCA 232">In Goode v Goode (2006) FCA 1346 the Full Court consisting of the Chief Justice and their Honours Finn and Boland JJ, heard what was the first case to be decided by the Full Court about the meaning and effect of the amendments to the Family Law Act (1975) which followed the commencement of the Shared Parental Responsibility Act (2006). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FamCA 145">21. The next question is that with regard to the parties' child. The state of the evidence is not good. The Full Court in the recent decision of Goode v Goode (2006) FCA 1346 , their Honours the chief justice, Finn and Boland JJ, said: 
 
 
 In an interim proceeding for parenting the court should: (a) identify the competing proposals; (b) identify the issues in dispute at interim hearing; (c) identify any agreed or uncontested facts; (d) consider the matters under section 60CC of the act; (e) decide whether the presumption applies; (f) if the presumption does apply decide whether it's rebutted; (g) if the presumption applies and is not rebutted, consider making an order for equal time or substantial time; (h) if equal time is not found to be considered, then make such order as the court considers fit, including considering whether there ought to be equal or substantial time. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l2">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 39B Original jurisdiction of Federal Court of Australia</title>
<title id="l3">EXTRADITION (CROATIA) REGULATIONS 2004 2004 NO. 339 </title>
<title id="l4">CRIMES ACT 1900 </title>
<title id="l5">CRIMES ACT 1900 - SECT 16 Nothing herein to affect 25 Ed III, c 2</title>
</legistitles>
</case>