<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MLC Lifetime Company Limited and MLC Limited (No 2) [2006] FCA 1367 (19 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1367.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1259">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1259">schemes to transfer or amalgamate life insurance businesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1259">applications to dispense with statutory requirement to provide policy holders with an approved scheme summary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1259">orders for dispensation granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 806">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 806">life insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 806">scheme for transfer of life insurance business between insurers confirmed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">life insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">scheme for transfer of part of life insurance business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">application to court for confirmation of scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">compliance with life insurance act 1995 (cth) and life insurance regulations 1995 (cth)    held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1">scheme confirmed without modification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">application under s 17f of the insurance act 1973 (cth) (the act) for confirmation of a scheme for the transfer of general insurance business by parent company to its wholly owned subsidiary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">dispensation order in relation to giving of approved summary of scheme to every affected policyholder sought and granted under s 17c(5) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">distinction between contract of insurance and contract of guarantee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">guarantee given by deed poll by parent company in respect of insurance liability of its subsidiary.  held : (1) contract of guarantee not a contract of insurance so that persons benefited did not have to be notified of proposed scheme as "affected policyholders"; (2) scheme confirmed. insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">application under s 17f of the insurance act 1973 (cth) (the act) for confirmation of a scheme for the transfer of general insurance business by parent company to its wholly owned subsidiary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">dispensation order in relation to giving of approved summary of scheme to every affected policyholder sought and granted under s 17c(5) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">distinction between contract of insurance and contract of guarantee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2019">guarantee given by deed poll by parent company in respect of insurance liability of its subsidiary.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">life insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">scheme to transfer part of the life insurance business of one insurer to another</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">procedural requirements complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">actuarial evidence suggested no disadvantage to policy holders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">apra did not oppose scheme confirmation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">terms of insurance contracts not altered except beneficially for taxation and social security purposes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">court's discretion to confirm not limited to supervising procedural compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">interests of policy holders are of primary concern</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">objections by some transferor insurer policy holders to transfer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">original scheme rejected for failing to accommodate valid concerns of objectors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">modified scheme with opt out facility for objectors approved courts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1327">nature of court's discretion to confirm scheme for transfer of life insurance business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">life insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">scheme for amalgamation of life insurance businesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">application to court for confirmation of scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">compliance with life insurance act 1995 (cth) and life insurance regulations 1995 (cth)  held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1012">scheme confirmed without modification</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 186">As will shortly appear, there has been no compliance with that provision. However, compliance with s 17C(2) is not a jurisdictional prerequisite to the power of the Court to confirm the scheme arising: see Re Armstrong Jones Life Assurance Ltd (1997) 74 FCR 160 at 162 per Emmett J; Re Royal &amp; Sun Alliance Life Assurance Ltd [2000] FCA 1259 ; [2000] FCA 1259 ; (2000) 104 FCR 37 at 40 per Katz J; Re Insurance Australia Ltd [2004] FCA 524 ; (2004) 139 FCR 450 at 461-463 per Lindgren J; MLC Lifetime Company Ltd and MLC Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1367 at [11] per Bennett J; Re Calliden Group Ltd [2007] FCA 2019 at [81] per Lindgren J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 1">The Court's discretion is very wide but, as Edmonds J pointed out, "it is not unfettered, and must be exercised on the evidence and having regard to the objects of the Act, principally, the protection of the interests of policyholders and prospective policyholders"; In the Application of Commonwealth Insurance Holdings Ltd and The Colonial Mutual Life Assurance Society Ltd [2007] FCA 1012 at [12] . At [13] his Honour identified two aspects to the protection of the interests of policyholders: First, there are the procedural aspects in which the Court is concerned to see that the process undertaken has been properly executed in accordance with the requirements of the Act and the Life Insurance Regulations 1995 (Cth) ('the Regulations'); and Second, there is a substantive aspect in which the Court is concerned to see that the Scheme will not be prejudicial to the interests of policyholders and that policyholders are properly safeguarded, i.e., there is not likely to be any material detriment to policyholders affected by the Scheme (see NuLife Insurance Ltd v Norwich Union Life Australia Ltd [2005] FCA 1635 at [24] per Emmett J; MLC Lifetime Company Ltd &amp; Anor (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1367 at [5] per Bennett J; Colonial Portfolio at [25] per Matthews J) Procedural steps
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 2019">81 In Re Armstrong Jones Life Assurance Ltd (1997) 74 FCR 160 , Emmett J had held that a provision in the Life Insurance Act 1995 (Cth) analogous to s 17C(2) of the Act did not lay down a condition precedent to the existence of jurisdiction in the Federal Court to confirm a scheme. In Re Royal &amp; Sun Alliance Life Assurance Ltd [2000] FCA 1259 ; (2000) 104 FCR 37 , Katz J adopted the same approach because his Honour did not think that Emmett J had been plainly wrong. In Re Insurance Australia Ltd [2004] FCA 524 ; (2004) 139 FCR 450 , although with some doubt, I adopted the same approach, namely, of following Emmett J because I did not think his Honour was plainly wrong (at [63]). A similar approach was subsequently taken by Bennett J in Re MLC Lifetime Company Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1367 at [11] . Perhaps predictably, I took the same approach in the present case in relation to the question of jurisdiction.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 1327">30 It is submitted that the approval of APRA is an important consideration. That may be accepted in the general way --- in the usual case approval of, or lack of objection by, APRA would be a necessary, but not sufficient, condition for confirmation. The statute expressly gives APRA a role in relation to Pt 9 (eg, ss 191(1) , 191 (2a), 192 and 193(3)), in addition to its other supervisory responsibilities. That role has naturally been referred to in many of the authorities (eg Re Application of Commonwealth Life Ltd [2003] FCA 637 at [13] ; Re MLC Lifetime Co Ltd and MLC Ltd (No 2) [2006] FCA 1367 at [14] ). I shall return to the position of APRA in another respect later. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 1012">There are two aspects to the protection of the interests of policyholders: 
 
 1. First, there are the procedural aspects in which the Court is concerned to see that the process undertaken has been properly executed in accordance with the requirements of the Act and the Life Insurance Regulations 1995 (Cth) ('the Regulations'); and
 2. Second, there is a substantive aspect in which the Court is concerned to see that the Scheme will not be prejudicial to the interests of policyholders and that policyholders are properly safeguarded, i.e., there is not likely to be any material detriment to policyholders affected by the Scheme (see NuLife Insurance Ltd v Norwich Union Life Australia Ltd [2005] FCA 1635 at [24] per Emmett J; MLC Lifetime Company Ltd &amp; Anor (No. 2) [2006] FCA 1367 at [5] per Bennett J; Colonial Portfolio at [25] per Mathews J) 
 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">LIFE INSURANCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">LIFE INSURANCE ACT 1995 - SECT 194 Confirmation of scheme</title>
<title id="l2">LIFE INSURANCE REGULATIONS 1995 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>