<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2006] FCA 1809 (21 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1809.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">(thirteenth respondent) file no: bs no 5969 of 2005 division: trial proceeding: originating application originating court: supreme court at brisbane delivered on: 9 november 2005 delivered at: brisbane hearing date: 21 october 2005 judge: white j orders: as per attached schedules  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">other cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">managed investment schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">scheme required to be registered not registered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">acknowledgment by operator that scheme should be wound up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">proposal by operator that operator be appointed to wind up the schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">all the investors support the proposal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">no opposition from asic</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 326">where operators undertake extensive reporting to investors and asic</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">winding up by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">where court ordered that 15 unregistered managed investment schemes operated by the respondent company be wound up pursuant to s 601ee corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">where the issue of the identity of the person to carry out the winding up was to be determined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">where asic sought an order that registered liquidators be appointed to wind up the schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">where respondent proposed to wind up the schemes subject to external control and/or supervision ordered by the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">all factors relevant to the winding up of an unregistered scheme must be balanced in determining who should be the party given the responsibility for winding up the scheme and on what terms  corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">winding up by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">where proposal to wind up unregistered managed investment schemes by transferring them to a registered scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2003] QSC 265">whether transfer of unregistered scheme to registered scheme amounts to winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">unregistered managed investment scheme in course of winding up pursuant to s.601ee by receiver appointed by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">application by receiver for direction as to appropriate method of distributing surplus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">jurisdiction to give such direction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">need for order under s.601ee(2) causing defined basis of winding up to apply</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">relevant guidance from termination provisions of trust deed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 576">allocation of loss among investors having "beneficial interest" in differing underlying investments where loss attributable to some investments only.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 451">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 451">unregistered managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 451">order for winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 451">need for orders to define framework for winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 27">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 27">corporate finance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 27">whether investment clubs run by respondents were managed investment schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 27">whether schemes should be wound up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 27">whether companies participating in the operation of the schemes should be wound up on the just and equitable ground</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 520">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 520">winding up of unregistered managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 520">scheme insolvent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 520">motion to have winding up continued by newly appointed liquidator</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">failure to register scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">proposals by investors to complete scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">land purchased and substantial number of lots sold</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">developer seeking to wind up scheme upon completion of development</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">bank finance now finalised</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">other adverse issues addressed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 692">orders in manner permitting completion of residential development the subject of the scheme approved</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 520">The plaintiffs in this proceeding have attempted to wind up an unregistered managed investment scheme ( the Scheme ) operating in contravention of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) ( CA ). The reasons for that course were outlined in my previous judgment in Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd ACN 115 352 504 v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2009] FCA 471 (Lake Coogee No 1 ) (and see also the earlier decisions of Nicholson J ( Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2006] FCA 1809 ; (2006) 60 ACSR 281 and Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] FCA 692).  The original orders granting that permission were made by Nicholson J in Lake Coogee [2006] FCA 1809 ; (2006) 60 ACSR 281 and in supplementary reasons in Lake Coogee [2007] FCA 692. In orders which I made in Lake Coogee No 1, the supplementary orders in Lake Coogee [2007] FCA 692 were amended to extend the period during which the Scheme was required to be completed but at the same time to improve the reporting of progress in the attempts to complete the Scheme to the investors in it. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 471">Before the Court are motions by the Australian Securities and Investments Commission (ASIC) to vary orders made under two previous decisions. Orders granting permission to the plaintiffs as operators to wind up a Managed Investment Scheme (the scheme) were made in two decisions of Nicholson J ( Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2006] FCA 1809 ; (2006) 60 ACSR 281 and Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2007] FCA 692). The first was on 21 December 2006 and the second on 11 May 2007. Under order 4.2 of the orders made by his Honour the scheme was required to be completed by 11 May 2009, which is next Monday. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 692">1 These reasons are given in continuation of the reasons given in Lake Coogee Estate Management Pty Ltd v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2006] FCA 1809 ; (2006) 60 ACSR 281. They should be read with those reasons. Defined terms used there are repeated in these further reasons. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 601EB Registration of managed investment scheme</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 601ED When a managed investment scheme must be registered</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 601EE Unregistered schemes may be wound up</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1012A Obligation to give Product Disclosure Statement--personal advice recommending particular financial product</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1012B Obligation to give Product Disclosure Statement--situations related to issue of financial products</title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>