<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Griffin Energy Pty Ltd v Western Power Corporation [2006] FCA 1241 (15 September 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1241.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">federal court rules order 15a rule 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">whether reasonable cause to believe that applicant has or may have right to obtain relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">asserted claims for breach of warranty, misleading or deceptive conduct and breach of fiduciary duty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">low threshold requirement for reasonable belief, however belief must amount to more than a mere possibility or speculation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">entitlement to preliminary discovery in order for applicant to ascertain defences available to respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations made as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">onus on respondent to show reasonableness of future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery appropriate in relation to future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">application for preliminary discovery otherwise denied trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">misleading or deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">application for preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">circumstantial information regarding conduct of former employees on establishing competing business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">whether o 15a r 6(b) is determined by test of "bare pleadable case"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">scope of discretion to refuse relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">commercial sensitivity of documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">relevance of delay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 133">alleged unfairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">o 15a r 6 of the federal court rules 1979 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">circumstances of departure of applicant's employees giving rise to reasonable cause to believe breach of confidence or copyright occurred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">applicant has sufficient information to decide whether to commence proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">threshold of "a bare pleadable case" met</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">o 15a r 6 not to convey advantage, but to clarify whether litigation is warranted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">extent of available relief relevant but not decisive</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">court has general discretion under o 15a r 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 2065">delay and prejudice relevant discretionary considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1331">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1331">application by a third party to be joined as a party to or permitted to intervene in an application under order 15a rule 6 of the federal court rules for discovery of documents to be made by a prospective respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">application for preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">alleged misrepresentation concerning tender for power plant generated capacity and minimum environmental compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">whether sufficient doubt in conclusion that 'reasonable cause to believe' claim may exist</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1810">whether substantial injustice if leave refused</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCAFC 133">40 The disclosure of highly sensitive confidential material to a trade rival is a routine exercise in this Court. Commercial confidentiality is protected by appropriate directions such as, typically, limiting disclosure to external lawyers and independent experts upon their giving undertakings to the Court. Without such regimes, most intellectual property litigation would be unworkable. We do not see anything in the present case to take it outside the ordinary practice. Confidentiality regimes have been seen as an answer to such concerns in preliminary discovery applications : Griffin Energy Pty Ltd v Western Power Corporation [2006] FCA 1241 at [110] ; Electricity Retail Corporation v Griffin Energy Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1810 at [51] .
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 2065">37 I am not satisfied that information of such sensitivity to Tibra should be disclosed at this early stage. The authorities, taken together, stress that the confidentiality of the information sought in a preliminary discovery application is a relevant consideration in the discretion of the Court to grant the relief, but not an overriding consideration: Griffin Energy Pty Ltd v Western Power Corporation [2006] FCA 1241 at [110] ; Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information, Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1331 at [31] - [32]. The Court has tended to permit applicants to erect suitable regimes to ensure the confidentiality of any material acquired by way of preliminary discovery. In this case, however, despite Optiver's proposal of a confidentiality regime, the exercise of the general discretion to refuse preliminary discovery is supported by two other considerations.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 1331">32 Opel's concerns could not amount to a proper discretionary consideration. I would be inclined to take a slightly more robust approach than that of Siopis J in Griffin Energy Pty Ltd v Western Power Corporation [2006] FCA 1241 at [110] , but would express my general agreement with what his Honour had to say.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2006] FCA 1810">
 The applicant (formerly Western Power Corporation (WPC), now relevantly 'ERC') seeks leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment of the Court given by Siopis J on 15 September 2006 ( Griffin Energy Pty Ltd v Western Power Corporation [2006] FCA 1241). The effect of his Honour's reasons, which was reflected in the orders that he made subsequently after the parties had conferred, was to grant to the respondent (collectively 'Griffin') an application pursuant to O 15A r 6(a) of the Federal Court Rules (FCR) for preliminary discovery. That requires it to be established that 'there is reasonable cause to believe that the applicant has or may have the right to obtain relief in the Court from a person whose description has been ascertained'. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 52 Misleading or deceptive conduct.</title>
<title id="l2">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 82 Actions for damages.</title>
<title id="l3">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 87 Ancillary orders.</title>
<title id="l4">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION ACT 1986 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>