<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105 (16 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/105.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">bankruptcy notices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">whether issue of multiple bankruptcy notices abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">election to proceed on third notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">second notice issued by respondent creditor subject of application by appellant debtor to set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">judgment on application reserved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">respondent creditor informed appellant debtor it was not proceeding with second notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">respondent creditor failed to inform federal magistrates court of election</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">judgment delivered in respondent creditor's favour</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">costs order in favour of respondent creditor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">respondent creditor subsequently began enforcing costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 215">whether conduct inconsistent with election.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 673">(i) where the notice was served in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 673">within the time specified in the notice; or  (ii) where the notice was served elsewhere</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 673">within the time fixed for the purpose by the order giving leave to effect the service;  comply with the requirements of the notice or satisfy the court that he or she has a counter-claim, set-off or cross demand equal to or exceeding the amount of the judgment debt or sum payable under the final order, as the case may be, being a counter-claim, set-off or cross demand that he or she could not have set up in the action or proceeding in which the judgment or order was obtained;  ..." 7. it is relevant to note that a bankruptcy notice will be set aside if the debtor has a "counterclaim, set-off or cross-demand equal to or exceeding the amount of the judgment debt" against the creditor and that counterclaim, set-off or cross-demand must be one that is effective against the creditor at the time of the hearing of the application to set aside the bankruptcy notice (see re geb (1983) 2 kb 340 (ca) ; re bankruptcy notice (1934) ch 431 at 440-441 (ca); guss v johnstone (2000) 74 aljr 884 at 891).  8. the applicant claims he has a cross-demand in the sum of $41,200 which exceeds the amount claimed in the schedule in the bankruptcy notice by $14,787.71.  9. it is noted that in the bankruptcy notice, a copy of which was provided to the court on the day of the hearing, the creditor relied upon a judgment obtained against the applicant in proceedings in the local court of western australia wherein a judgment and tax costs totalled $28,422.69. that judgment was given for the respondent who was the plaintiff in those proceedings and known as homestyle pty ltd. it is noted that those proceedings had commenced in the local court in 2001. it is further noted that the total debt owing arising out of that judgment is claimed to be $26,412.29 in accordance with the schedule to the bankruptcy notice which has deducted payments made or credits allowed since the date of judgment or orders.  10. the applicant claims that he has a cross-demand consistent with a writ of summons in the district court of western australia which he annexed to his affidavit. in that writ dated 7 april 2004, almost six months after the local court judgment, a claim is made by the applicant against a company "bgc constructions pty ltd". the statement of claim refers to a contract between the applicant and bgc constructions pty ltd for bricklaying services provided by the applicant during june and july 2000. the claim seems to be based upon an agreement of what is described as an assured continuity of work by the applicant with the defendant named in those proceedings. the pleadings do not refer to "bgc constructions pty ltd" as being the company formerly known as homestyle pty ltd.  11. in his affidavit after annexing the writ of summons allegedly containing details of the cross-demand, the applicant further encloses a document which he describes as -</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 293">category: no</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">application to set aside bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">assessed costs under order of industrial court of nsw</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">failure to file certificate in court with enforcement jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">no 'final' judgment to support bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">notice also invalid for failure to attach certificate of judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">cross demand exceeding amount of costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">whether notice should be set aside in absence of extension of time for compliance with notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">discretionary power to extend time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">whether automatic extension where affidavit in support did not comply with rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1817">bankruptcy notice set aside on all grounds.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">application to set aside bankruptcy notice dismissed.costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">principles.practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">varying or setting aside earlier costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">intention of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 601">consent of party favoured by earlier costs order.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">application to set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">jurisdiction and power of magistrates court of western australia to issue order of former local court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">whether action pending</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">hearing and determination of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 71">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">application for transfer to federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">factors to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">question of general importance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">costs and convenience of hearing and determination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">interests of administration of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1507">application refused.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">judgment debt arising from solicitor/client costs assessments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">counter-claim in professional negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">could not have been set up before the costs assessors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 1287">bankruptcy notice set aside.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 919">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 919">application to set aside fifth bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 919">applicant sought adjournment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 919">arguments not clearly without merit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2006] FMCA 919">matter adjourned.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 293">In my view, execution of an order for payment of costs cannot be levied, and nobody is entitled to enforce it, until, in a case like the present, the amount of the costs has been quantified upon taxation by the Taxing Master. This view I regard as consistent with the observation of Branson J in Franks v Warringah Council at [30], cited at [12] above, that " s 40(1)(g) of the Bankruptcy Act refers only to final judgments and final orders that can be enforced by a writ of execution. " It also conforms with her Honour's having pointed out in the succeeding paragraph [31] that "In each case the amount of the costs which the order required Mr Franks to pay needed first to be quantified. " See also the following dictum of Lee J in Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105 , at [16]; 
 
 Although unnecessary to decide in the instant case it may be thought that the words of Item 2 and of Note 1 of the Schedule to the Notice make it clear that costs not fixed but ordered to be paid as part of a judgment or order must be set out in Item 2 of the Schedule and a certificate of those taxed costs attached. I note that in Stec v Orfanos [1999] FCA 457 at [17] it is suggested that it is not necessary to attach a certificate of taxed costs where a judgment recited in Item 1 of the Schedule provides for costs to be taxed. But such a conclusion would not be consistent with the words used in Item 2 of the Schedule or Note 1 and, furthermore, would fail to meet the evident purpose of a bankruptcy notice prescribed by the Act and Regulations, namely, to give a debtor notice of how the amount set out in the Notice has been calculated as the amount owing. 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FMCA 1817">Those cases were applied in later cases, including by Lee J in Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105. In that case, Lee J also cited The Australian Steel Company (Operations) Pty Ltd v Lewis [2000] FCA 1915 ; (2000) 109 FCR 33 , whose correctness must be re-examined in the light of Adams v Lambert . However, Finkelstein J's judgment in Horvath was decided before Australian Steel , and applied principles expressed in judgments which remain good authority, in particular Kleinwort Benson Australia Ltd v Crowl [1988] HCA 34 ; (1988) 165 CLR 71. Applying these principles, Finkelstein J addressed the application of s.306(1) , by addressing whether the attachment of the order or judgment was an essential requirement of the Bankruptcy Act . His Honour's discussion leading to [14] in his judgment, pointed out the central importance that a recipient of a bankruptcy notice should be able to establish unambiguously from the notice itself what judgment or order was relied upon for the claimed debt. In my opinion, this reasoning remains sound, notwithstanding Adams v Lambert , and I would respectfully follow that line of cases. I note that a similar conclusion was arrived at in a considered judgment of Wilson FM in ANZ Banking Group Ltd v Menso [2006] FMCA 1522 at [66] and preceding. I am certainly not persuaded that his Honour's conclusion was clearly wrong, and should not be followed. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 601">Consistent with the history of litigation between the parties [2] there was considerable pre-hearing litigation activity in relation to the Amended Application.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FMCA 71"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2006] FMCA 1507">That is hardly surprising given the history of litigation between these parties and the respondent's predecessor prior to this bankruptcy notice: see for example Genovese v Homestyle Pty Ltd (2004) 187 FLR 13 , [2004] FMCA 673 ; Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2004] FMCA 850 ; Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 215 ; (2005) 215 ALR 440 , (2005) 3 ABC(NS) 163, [2005] FCA 215 ; Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2006] FMCA 1287">It was, therefore, not necessary for me to enter into a consideration of issues such as were addressed by Lee J in Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2006] FMCA 919">Lee J made first instance orders setting aside the fourth bankruptcy notice on 
16 January 2006 (see Genovese v BGC Construction Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 105).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 40 Acts of bankruptcy</title>
<title id="l2">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 41 Bankruptcy notices</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l4">LOCAL COURT RULES 1961 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>