<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Slick v Westpac Banking Corporation (ACN 007 457 141)(No 2) [2006] FCA 1712 (8 December 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1712.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">motion seeking orders for particular discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">whether court has a discretion under order 15 rule 8</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">factors relevant to exercise of discretion.  federal court rules , order 15 rule 8.  practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">motion seeking orders for particular discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">discretion of court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">"the court may order"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">meaning of</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1981] FCA 7">federal court rules,o. 15, r. 8. on 21st december, 1979, the applicant had commenced an action for relief based on alleged contraventions of s. 45 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth). pursuant to an order of the court as to the conduct of the action of 2nd january, 1980, the parties exchanged lists of documents. the applicant later received leave to amend its statement of claim to widen the issues in the action and the parties subsequently agreed upon a further timetable including exchange of a further list of documents and inspection thereof. affidavits verifying lists of documents were not filed. on 4th february, 1981, by notice of motion the applicant sought an order pursuant to o. 15, r. 8 of the federal court rules that each of the fifteenth, sixteenth and seventeenthnamed respondents (p.b.l. marketing pty. ltd., world series cricket pty. ltd. and publishing and broadcasting ltd.) file affidavits as to the location of certain documents.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">notices of motion seeking orders for discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">discovery sought in relation to amended application seeking orders of review of decision under administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">decision made to issue garnishee notices under taxation administration act 1953 (cth) to third party debtors of first and third applicants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">second applicant a secured creditor of first and third applicants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">order 15 rule 2 of the federal court rules applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">general disclosure obligations of parties in proceedings under the administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether adjectival relevance of documents sought to grounds of review in amended application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether claims for discovery of documents constitute "fishing"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">priority dispute between respondent and second applicant in relation to third party debts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether assertion in respondent's statement of reasons answered applicants' claims for discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether authorisation of decision-maker an issue in proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether documents sought relate to relevant considerations the subject of the amended application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether fact that documents in public domain means claim for discovery oppressive</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">whether claims of respondent relating to estoppel and waiver tenable and support claims for discovery   legislation: administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth) ss 3 , 5 (1), 13  taxation administration act 1953 (cth) s 260</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 636">5 of sch 1</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">application for further particular discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">principles governing discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether burden of discovery outweighs benefit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether discovery relevant to pleaded issues</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether sufficient evidence to support order for further discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether application constitutes 'fishing expedition'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether respondents should be directed to respond to applicant's notice to admit facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether leave should be granted to applicant to administer interrogatories</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">application for summary dismissal by respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">whether reasonable prospect of success    equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">applicant claims two reports on sea keeping of its vessels confidential</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">alleged misuse of confidential information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 368">springboard doctrine</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 636">Similar observations have been made by Judges of this Court (for example in Allstate Life Insurance Co v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Limited (No 15) [1995] FCA 1472 at [15] , Slick v Westpac Banking Corporation (No 2) [2006] FCA 1712 at [8] , Austal Ships Pty Ltd v Incat Australia Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 368 at [136] - [139]). However from the material I have before me I am unable to identify the manner in which the production of documents described in para 1(a) would be oppressive to the applicants as, for example, involving a high volume of documents as well as labour and expense. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 368">At this stage, there is no significant evidence at all in relation to the allegations concerning Higashinihon Ferries, Spanish Acciona and PATT. The oppression involved in the proposed discovery, in my view, far outweighs the benefit that might be obtained from it. As to the burden and benefit principle, see also O 15 r 8 and Molnlycke AB v Proctor &amp; Gamble Limited (No 3) [1990] RPC 498 at 503 and Slick [2006] FCA 1712 at [43]. Notice to Admit Facts
  However, in Slick v Westpac Banking Corporation (No 2) [2006] FCA 1712 at [43] , particular discovery was refused on the basis that 'the theoretical possibility that something might turn up [was] well and truly outweighed by the cost and burden to Westpac' (see also Betts [2007] FCA 1983). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 23 Making of orders and issue of writs</title>
<title id="l2">SUPREME COURT RULES 1970 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>