<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lee v Military Rehabilitation and Compensation Commission [2006] FCA 1508 (15 November 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1508.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">canute v comcare  workers compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">injury and impairment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">liability of comcare to pay compensation in respect of an injury which results in a permanent impairment pursuant to s 24 of the safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">where comcare required to determined the degree of permanent impairment resulting from an injury under the approved guide</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">where s 25(4) of the act provides that no further compensation payable in respect of a subsequent increase of less than 10 percent in the degree of impairment where comcare has made a final assessment of the degree of permanent impairment of the employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">where the worker sustained a physical injury to the back and also a mental injury being a post traumatic stress disorder</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">where the mental injury manifested itself later in time than the physical injury</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">whether s 25(4) of the act precluded comcare from being liable to pay compensation in respect of the mental injury because it resulted in an increase of less than 10 percent in the degree of impairment of the employee.  statute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">statutory construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 47">whether repugnancy arises between s 24 and s 25(4) of the act in circumstances where something is both an injury and produces a subsequent increase in the degree of permanent impairment of the employee.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">military rehabilitation and compensation commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">veteran seeking permanent impairment compensation for multiple injuries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">lumbar spinal disease declared permanent in 1986</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">post traumatic stress disorder onset in 1986</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">aggravation of back condition in 1994</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">bilateral knee pathology previously compensated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1832">decisions under review affirmed</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] AATA 1832">The 1971 Act did not provide for compensation for psychiatric conditions or lumbosacral spinal disease. The application of s 124(1) of the SRC Act to pre-1988 permanent impaired persons has been considered by the Federal Court on several occasions. In Lee v Military Rehabilitation and Compensation Commission [2006] FCA 1508 ; (2006) 92 ALD 600 , Moore J considered the decision in Department of Defence v West (1998) 85 FCR 491 and said: 
 [22] The application of s 24 of the SRC Act to individuals who developed permanent impairments before the relevant provisions of the SRC Act came into force has been considered in a number of Full Court decisions. In large measure, the submissions of the parties focused on these decisions. In West, Merkel J (with whom O'Connor J agreed) held that (at FCR 512; ALR 669 ; ALD 729): 
 
 ... where a change in a permanent impairment occurring after the commencement date is such that, quantitatively and qualitatively, it is properly to be characterised as a further or new impairment occurring after the commencement date it is compensable by a lump sum payment under [s] 24. 
 
Moore J quoted the decision in Comcare Australia (Department of Defence) v Maida [2002] FCA1284:
 
 [23] In Maida, Mansfield J accepted the following propositions as a correct summary of the law: 
 
 (i) the gradual worsening of the degree of impairment does not constitute a new impairment; 
 
 (ii) if there is no change in the patho physiological condition causing an impairment then any worsening of an existing impairment will not constitute a new impairment; and 
 
 (iii) a significant worsening may constitute a new impairment if there has been a change in the underlying patho physiological condition, so that there has been a qualitative change to the impairment --- that is, the development of a new impairment. 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 43 Tribunal's decision on review</title>
<title id="l2">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l3">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l4">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 4 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l5">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 17 Compensation for injuries resulting in death</title>
<title id="l6">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 24 Compensation for injuries resulting in permanent impairment</title>
<title id="l7">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 25 Interim payment of compensation</title>
<title id="l8">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 28 Approved Guide</title>
<title id="l9">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 43 Certain persons may request cessation of compensation payments</title>
<title id="l10">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 124 Application of Act to pre-existing injuries</title>
<title id="l11">COMMONWEALTH EMPLOYEES' REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l12">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>