<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1324 (11 October 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/1324.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">legal practitioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">solicitor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">liability to client</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">proceedings on client's behalf</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">strong likelihood of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">solicitor's negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">proceedings dismissed for want of prosecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">damages for negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">time for assessment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">consequential claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 64">evidence of events occurring since dismissal of proceedings.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">vendor and purchaser</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">sale of land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">"subject to the preparation of a formal contract of sale &amp;which shall be acceptable to my solicitors on the above terms and conditions"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">whether concluded contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">nature of sum paid as a "deposit"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 72">intention of parties.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">sale of goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">f.o.b. contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">sale of oats</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">loading on ship within prescribed time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">ship and shipping date to be nominated by buyer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">resale of oats by buyer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">ship nominated not ready to load in prescribed time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">seller's inability to carry out contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">oats purchased by buyer at increased cost</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 25">damages.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">(third party) file no/s: bs 8849 of 2008 division: trial division proceeding: trial originating court: supreme court at brisbane delivered on: 30 september 2009 delivered at: brisbane hearing date: 27-29 july 2009 judge: mcmurdo j order: it is ordered that: the plaintiff's claim be dismissed. there be judgment for the defendant on the counterclaim in the sum of $77,058.65. there be judgment for the defendant on the third party claim in the sum of $1,008,293.41.  contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">general contractual principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">construction and interpretation of contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">other matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the contract provides that neither party shall be liable for failure to perform obligations under the contract "if such ... failure is caused by circumstances beyond that party's reasonable control, including ... non-supply to [the defendant] of product"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the third party's failure to supply the defendant with product was beyond the defendant's reasonable control</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">whether the defendant's failure to perform was "caused by" the third party's failure to supply sale of goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">remedies for breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">remedies of buyer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">non-delivery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where there is no available market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the contract provides for a date for delivery of 11 february 2008</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where there was no agreed variation of the date of delivery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the plaintiff did not terminate the contract until at least september 2008</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.14" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the plaintiff, prior to the termination date, had bought some products from other suppliers in substitution for products to have been supplied under the contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.15" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">whether the damages should be assessed based on the market price as at termination or by reference to the extra cost incurred to acquire substitute products prior to termination trade and commerce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.16" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">trade practices act 1974 (cth) and related legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.17" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">consumer protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.18" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">misleading or deceptive conduct or false representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.19" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">misleading or deceptive conduct generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.20" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.21" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the defendant had represented to the plaintiff that the "worst case scenario" for delivery of the product under the contract would be 11 february 2008</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.22" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where there was a reasonable basis for that representation as at the time it was made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.23" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">where the defendant remained silent and did not correct its representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.24" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 314">whether this constitutes a breach of s 52 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) sale of goods act 1896 (qld), s 14, s 30, s 31, s 52 trade practices act 1974 (cth), s 6 , s 51a, s 52 , s 58 , s 82 agricultural and rural finance v gardiner [2008] hca 57 ; (2008) 251 alr 322 , cited european bank ltd v citibank ltd (2004) 60 nswlr 153 , cited gardiner v agricultural and rural finance pty ltd [2007] nswca 235 , followed hoecheong products co ltd v cargill hong kong ltd [1995] 1 wlr 404 , followed hyundai merchant marine co. ltd v dartbrook coal (sales) pty ltd [2006] fca 1324 ; (2006) 236 alr 115 , followed johnson v agnew [1980] ac 367 , distinguished lebeaupin v richard crispen &amp; co [1920] 2 kb 714 , cited march v stramare [1991] hca 12 ; (1991) 171 clr 506 , cited mccann v switzerland insurance australia limited (2000) 203 clr 579 , cited ogle v earl vane (1868) l.r. 3 q.b. 272 , distinguished ogle v earl vane (1867) l.r. 2 q.b. 275 , distinguished pj van der zijden wildhandel nv v tucker &amp; cross ltd [1975] 2 lloyd's rep 240, followed re voss (1873) l.r. 16 eq 155 , applied wilkie v gordian runoff ltd [2005] hca 17 ; (2005) 221 clr 522 , cited counsel: d j campbell sc, with d favell, for the plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] NSWCA 235">bruce walter gardiner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] NSWCA 235">appellantagricultural and rural finance pty ltd</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] NSWCA 235">first respondentoceania agriculture pty ltd</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] NSWCA 235">second respondent</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] QCA 128">[25] 
[39] Interfert argued that P J van der Zijden Wildhandel NV v Tucker should be distinguished on the ground that the clause construed by Donaldson J relieved from liability where performance was "prevented" by the supervening event rather than merely being "hindered" or "delayed" by that event. "
 
 [38] P J van der Zijden Wildhandel NV v Tucker was also cited with apparent approval by Kiefel J, sitting as a single judge at the Federal Court in Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd. [24] Her Honour observed that "[i]mpractability of performance is not generally recognised as a ground of discharge of a contracting party's obligations".</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] QSC 314">CATCHWORDS: CONTRACTS --- GENERAL CONTRACTUAL PRINCIPLES --- CONSTRUCTION AND INTERPRETATION OF CONTRACTS --- OTHER MATTERS --- where the contract provides that neither party shall be liable for failure to perform obligations under the contract "if such ... failure is caused by circumstances beyond that party's reasonable control, including ... non-supply to [the defendant] of Product" --- where the third party's failure to supply the defendant with product was beyond the defendant's reasonable control --- whether the defendant's failure to perform was "caused by" the third party's failure to supply SALE OF GOODS --- REMEDIES FOR BREACH OF CONTRACT --- REMEDIES OF BUYER --- NON-DELIVERY --- WHERE THERE IS NO AVAILABLE MARKET --- where the contract provides for a date for delivery of 11 February 2008 --- where there was no agreed variation of the date of delivery --- where the plaintiff did not terminate the contract until at least September 2008 --- where the plaintiff, prior to the termination date, had bought some products from other suppliers in substitution for products to have been supplied under the contract --- whether the damages should be assessed based on the market price as at termination or by reference to the extra cost incurred to acquire substitute products prior to termination TRADE AND COMMERCE --- TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 (CTH) AND RELATED LEGISLATION --- CONSUMER PROTECTION --- MISLEADING OR DECEPTIVE CONDUCT OR FALSE REPRESENTATIONS --- MISLEADING OR DECEPTIVE CONDUCT GENERALLY --- GENERALLY --- where the defendant had represented to the plaintiff that the "worst case scenario" for delivery of the product under the contract would be 11 February 2008 --- where there was a reasonable basis for that representation as at the time it was made --- where the defendant remained silent and did not correct its representations --- whether this constitutes a breach of s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) Sale of Goods Act 1896 (Qld), s 14, s 30, s 31, s 52 Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth), s 6 , s 51A, s 52 , s 58 , s 82 Agricultural and Rural Finance v Gardiner [2008] HCA 57 ; (2008) 251 ALR 322 , cited European Bank Ltd v Citibank Ltd (2004) 60 NSWLR 153 , cited Gardiner v Agricultural and Rural Finance Pty Ltd [2007] NSWCA 235 , followed Hoecheong Products Co Ltd v Cargill Hong Kong Ltd [1995] 1 WLR 404 , followed Hyundai Merchant Marine Co. Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1324 ; (2006) 236 ALR 115 , followed Johnson v Agnew [1980] AC 367 , distinguished Lebeaupin v Richard Crispen &amp; Co [1920] 2 KB 714 , cited March v Stramare [1991] HCA 12 ; (1991) 171 CLR 506 , cited McCann v Switzerland Insurance Australia Limited (2000) 203 CLR 579 , cited Ogle v Earl Vane (1868) L.R. The requirement that Dartbrook be prevented from performance, in practical terms, implies causation between the event and the inability to perform ..." [10] 
 
 [53] The defendant here argues that it might be excused under cl 7 although it was neither impossible nor impracticable for it to perform the contract by acquiring the urea from another source. [11] 
[55] Alternatively, he argues that the present clause is distinguishable, because here the parties have specified the circumstance of the "non-supply to Interfert of Product". " [8] 
 
 [52] The judgment of Donaldson J was also cited with apparent agreement by Kiefel J, sitting as a single judge of the Federal Court, in Hyundai Merchant Marine Co. Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd. [9] The defendants agreed to charter a ship from the plaintiff to transport coal to the Philippines under a contract which required delivery by them to their purchaser to be effected within a certain period.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] NSWCA 235">
 

93 Accordingly, changes in economic conditions, which significantly alter the commercial aspects of an arrangement, even though in one sense they are "beyond the control" of a party to a commercial agreement, may not fall within such a general phrase in a Force Majeure clause. Mere commercial impracticability may not be sufficient (see e.g. P J Van Der Zijden Wildhandel N.V. v Tucker &amp; Cross Limited (1975) 2 Lloyd's Rep. 240 at 242; Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Limited v Dark Brook Coal (Sales) Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1324 at [60] - [62]. ) (In the latter case the issue may be seen to turn on the word "prevent", rather than on the phrase "beyond the control" of the party. ) 
 
 

222 A case which appears to illustrate the difference between impossibility and frustration of purpose is Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1324 (Kiefel J). The defendants were joint venturers seeking to sell coal out of Newcastle, New South Wales to a Philippine company, National Power Corporation. Her Honour concluded that a sales contract had been agreed by 29 March 2004: at [52]. 
 13. Changes in economic conditions, which significantly alter the commercial aspects of an arrangement, even though in one sense they are "beyond the control" of a party to a commercial agreement, may not fall within such a general phrase in a Force Majeure clause. Mere commercial impracticability may not be sufficient: [93]. 


 
 
 P J Van Der Zijden Wildhandel N.V. v Tucker &amp; Cross Limited (1975) 2 Lloyd's Rep. 240; Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Limited v Dark Brook Coal (Sales) Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1324 referred to. 
 


 
(per Basten JA) 
 14. Performance will not be beyond the control of a party to a contract merely because performance becomes uneconomic for the supplier of goods and services. A more stringent test of supervening impossibility may need to be applied where the recipient of services asserts frustration of purpose: [227]. 


 
 
 Hyundai Merchant Marine Co Ltd v Dartbrook Coal (Sales) Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1324 ; Vidler &amp; Co (London) Ltd v R Silcock &amp; Sons Ltd [1960] 1 Lloyd's Rep 509; PJ van der Zijden Wildhandel NV v Tucker [1975] 2 Lloyds Rep 240 ; Provimi Hellas AE v Warinco AG [1978] 1 Lloyds Rep 373 (CA) ; considered. 
 


 
 Summary of findings regarding construction 
 

 
(per Basten JA)</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
</legistitles>
</case>