<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd v Vidtech Gaming Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 275 (22 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/275.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">copyright infringement in gaming machines parts and components</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">infringement inferred from circumstantial evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">authorisation of copyright infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">joint liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">claim in conversion for resale of components acquired from scrap dealer fails</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">scrap dealer not a bailee of the goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">infringement of copyright established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1495">damages and additional damages ordered.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">assessment of damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">election for compensatory damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">assessment of damages on the basis of a royalty inappropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">whether loss of sales by the copyright owner could be inferred merely from the fact of sales of infringing product</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">requirement for evidence of lost sales and value of such sales</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">additional damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">purpose of awarding additional damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 40">assessment of additional damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 487">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 487">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 487">whether partial costs order should be made in a case where the award of damages was well short of the amount claimed by the applicants but exceeded an offer made by the respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 487">whether the costs associated with the evidence of an expert should be excluded in a case where the experts' opinions were unsupported by any evidence.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1495">Although there are other innocent explanations which could have been given for the adoption of this course, Mr Andrews' email of 10 April 2005 was written shortly after an Anton Piller raid on a business associate of his, Mr David Parry: see Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd v Vidtech Gaming Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 275 ; (2006) 68 IPR 229. I cannot accept that it was mere coincidence that the adoption of the Yahoo email address and the sending of the email set out in [314] by Mr Andrews corresponded with the raids on Mr Parry's premises. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1139">&#8226; The undertakings, which are in place and have been since April 2007, are offered on a permanent basis. They are no longer made without admissions. They cover the same ground as the proposed injunctions concerning the representations; a matter referred to by Wilcox J in Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd v Vidtech Gaming Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 275 ; (2006) 68 IPR 229 at [100] . &#8226; There is no suggestion that Servier has breached the undertakings since they were given in April 2007. &#8226; It is not for the Court to consider the potential forensic benefits to either party of making orders in the form of injunctions, rather than accepting undertakings.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCAFC 40">3 This appeal does not arise because of any pedantry on the part of the respondents. Rather, it arises because the primary judge found, in our view correctly, that he lacked the evidence necessary for him to calculate the value of lost sales, if any; see Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd v Vidtech Gaming Services Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 275 ; (2006) 68 IPR 229 at [118] . His Honour then said that the "only feasible course" was to calculate damages on an accounting for profit approach. He proceeded on that basis to award $80,000 damages against Vidtech, Mr Parry and Mrs Parry and $40,000 (ie 50%) additional damages against Vidtech and Mr Parry. Both sides agree that his Honour was in error in adopting this approach because the applicants had elected to claim damages rather than an account of profits.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2006] FCA 487">1 When judgment was delivered in this matter on 22 March 2006, I reserved the matter of costs: see Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Limited v Vidtech Gaming Services Pty Limited [2006] FCA 275. I invited submissions as to the appropriate costs order.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 </title>
<title id="l1">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 13 Acts comprised in copyright</title>
<title id="l2">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 14 Acts done in relation to substantial part of work or other subject-matter deemed to be done in relation to the whole</title>
<title id="l3">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 36 Infringement by doing acts comprised in the copyright</title>
<title id="l4">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 115 Actions for infringement</title>
<title id="l5">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l6">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 52 Misleading or deceptive conduct.</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>