<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Monsanto Company v Syngenta Seeds Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 228 (17 March 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/228.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">production of documents which record trade secrets relating to ingredients of hair care products for purposes of trade practices action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">whether documents discoverable on issues raised in pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">whether court may order production of documents in possession, power or control of a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">order 15 rule 11(1)(b) federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 557">s. 23 federal court of australia act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">application for preliminary discovery under o 15a r 3 and o 15a r 6 of federal court rules (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">no supporting affidavit filed with application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">repeated failure to comply with the orders of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">refusal at hearing to take court to supporting evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">application by respondent to strike out for want of due prosecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1393">application and ancillary motions dismissed for want of prosecution and lack of supporting affidavit as required by federal court rules (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">identity discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">applicant required to produce documents to the australian competition and consumer commission by a notice under s 155 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">commission official disclosed some information obtained from those documents to third persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">whether that disclosure was a breach of s 155aaa(1) of the trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">whether any equitable duty of confidence owed by the commission and its staff to a person who produces documents to it under compulsion in response to a s 155 notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">whether foreshadowed causes of action and claims for relief have sufficient prospects of success to justify the making of a preliminary discovery order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">whether the interests of justice would be served by the making of such an order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 980">application for preliminary discovery order refused</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1393">In the exercise of the Court's discretion to grant an order under O 15A r 3, the Court must consider whether there is the prospect of the applicant succeeding in the proceedings against the person to be sued: see generally Monsanto Company v Syngeta Seeds Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 228. The claim must be more than a claim worth investigating, it must have some prospect of succeeding: see Allphones Retail Pty Ltd (ACN 008 169 090) v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2009] FCA 980 ; (2009) 82 IPR 121 at [51] - [54] . It is essential that on an application for preliminary discovery that an applicant provide evidence in support of his claim for final relief: see Wyeth v Secretary, Department of Health and Ageing [2009] FCA 313 ; (2009) 255 ALR 352 at [24] - [25]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 980">See also Monsanto Company v Syngenta Seeds Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 228 at [8] ---[11] (per Finkelstein J) where his Honour described the criterion in relation to prospects as "... a claim that is worth investigating ...". At [9], he also said that "... in most cases an applicant for identity discovery must show some prospect of success in its proposed action". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] QDC 154">Monsanto Co v Syngenta Seeds Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 228 --- cited.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">GENE TECHNOLOGY ACT 2000 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l2">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 117 Infringement by supply of products</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>