<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Harris v Trustee Commonwealth Superannuation Scheme [2006] FCA 373 (5 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/373.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">veterans' affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">veterans' entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">defence force retirement and death benefit scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">applicant survives deceased person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">applicant not living with deceased member as his wife for a continuous period up to the time of his death</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">applicant did not ordinarily live with the deceased member on a permanent and bona fide domestic basis at the time of his death</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">consideration of 'marital relationship'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">living arrangements not due to temporary absence or special circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 1013">decision under review affirmed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] SCTA 3">It is clear that, at the date of death of the Deceased Member, he was legally married to the Complainant. Under the Rules, however, this is not sufficient to establish a 'marital relationship'. In Harris v Trustee Commonwealth Superannuation Scheme [2006] FCA 373 His Honour Justice Conti, in considering the application of an earlier, but materially identical, version of Sections 8A and 8B, said;
 
... one of the two foundations for the entitlement of a person to assert the existence of a 'marital relationship' with another is that the former had been living with that other person as that other person's husband or wife for a continuous period of at least 3 years up to' a particular time for the purposes of the operation of ss 8A and 8B. The other is the alternative of having so lived 'for a continuous period of less than 3 years up to that time' but in circumstances constituting in the opinion of the Commissioner 'that the person ordinarily lived with that other person as that other person's husband or wife on a permanent and bona fide basis'. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] AATA 1013">Despite the finding that Ms Hancox was not living with Mr Stevens up to or at the time of his death she will be taken, under s 6A(5) of the Act, to have been so doing if she would have been living with him except for a period of temporary absence or absence because of special circumstances. Examples of the latter are given in the provision as being absence because of the illness, infirmity or posting of Mr Stevens. I accept the submission of Mr Dillon in relation to this provision. The absence must be from a previous state of affairs which constituted a marital relationship in accordance with the preceding components of s 6A of the Act. Where that is the case, a temporary absence of a party due, for example, to an interstate or international business trip or an absence due to the special circumstance of, say, hospitalisation, will not vitiate the existence of a marital relationship [17] . In this matter, the marital relationship did not exist at any time and s 6A(5) of the Act is not applicable. 
  As Ms Hancox was not living with Mr Stevens as his wife for any continuous period up to the time of his death, neither s 6A(2)(a) or (b) of the Act is met. This means that s 6A(1) of the Act is not satisfied and it is not necessary to consider the further requirement expressed in s 6A(1) of the Act. Nonetheless, I make brief reference to that requirement which is that the state of Ms Hancox's living with Mr Stevens as his wife for a continuous period must have been ordinarily the case and have been on a permanent and bona fide domestic basis at the time of his death [13] . That is also the second element in s 6A(2)(b) of the Act. [14]  As Ms Hancox was not living with Mr Stevens as his wife for any continuous period up to the time of his death, neither s 6A(2)(a) or (b) of the Act is met. This means that s 6A(1) of the Act is not satisfied and it is not necessary to consider the further requirement expressed in s 6A(1) of the Act. Nonetheless, I make brief reference to that requirement which is that the state of Ms Hancox's living with Mr Stevens as his wife for a continuous period must have been ordinarily the case and have been on a permanent and bona fide domestic basis at the time of his death [13] . That is also the second element in s 6A(2)(b) of the Act. [14] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2006] SCTA 194">In closing, the Tribunal wishes to record that it has considered the decision of Conti J in the Federal Court in the matter of Harris v Trustee Commonwealth Superannuation Scheme and anor [2006] FCA 373 , delivered 5 April 2006 ( Harris ) which upholds a Trustee's decision to deny the appellant a surviving spouse pension. It reviewed the facts of that case and is aware that there are some similarities. However, the Tribunal is of the view that this matter is clearly distinguishable on the facts. Without listing all of the points of difference, it is clear that, unlike the relationship in Harris, the Complainant and her husband had, for many years, been committed to each other as the married couple that they were, and, very significantly, they were living together when the Deceased Member died. They were in each other's company, and shared their living and sleeping arrangements more often than not. They shared the same motor vehicle, which was jointly owned, and they attended medical appointments together. The Complainant cooked for and cared for her husband. The Tribunal does not consider, therefore, that the Harris case is binding on it, and, for the reasons set out above, it does not regard the judicial comments therein dealing with the test in sub-s(3) of s8B to have any application to this review. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 3 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l2">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 8A Marital or couple relationship</title>
<title id="l3">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 8B Spouse who survives a deceased person</title>
<title id="l4">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 81 Entitlement to spouse's benefit under Division</title>
<title id="l5">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 82 Spouse's benefit where benefit not reduced on medical grounds and election not made under section 83 or 84</title>
<title id="l6">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 83 Election where pension not reduced on medical grounds</title>
<title id="l7">SUPERANNUATION ACT 1976 - SECT 84 Election where benefit not reduced on medical grounds and period of prospective service less than 8 years</title>
<title id="l8">SUPERANNUATION (RESOLUTION OF COMPLAINTS) ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l9">SUPERANNUATION (RESOLUTION OF COMPLAINTS) ACT 1993 - SECT 19 Tribunal not to deal with complaint unless the complainant has attempted to have the matter resolved</title>
<title id="l10">SUPERANNUATION (RESOLUTION OF COMPLAINTS) ACT 1993 - SECT 23 Right to representation in relation to a complaint</title>
<title id="l11">SUPERANNUATION (RESOLUTION OF COMPLAINTS) ACT 1993 - SECT 37 Tribunal powers--complaints under section 14</title>
<title id="l12">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l13">De Facto Relationships Act 1984 No 147 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>