<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Conor Medsystems, Inc. v The University of British Columbia (No 2) [2006] FCA 32 (3 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/32.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">revocation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">want of novelty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">obviousness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">patent for a campervan with a roof capable of being stowed or erected by spring means</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">prior publications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">claim that patentee not entitled to invention. design</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">expungement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">want of novelty or originality</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1474">entitlement.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">validity of grant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">claim that respondent's patent, granted in 1992, is invalid on grounds including inutility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">motion by respondent to strike out applicant's inutility pleadings or in alternative, orders sought for summary dismissal or summary judgment of part of proceedings alleging inutility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">whether expert evidence necessary  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">where applicant seeks discovery of all documents relevant to issue of utility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">whether documents relating to experiments conducted by respondent post-grant excluded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">whether manufacturing documents excluded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1227">discretion to limit discovery</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2006] FCA 1227">Merck also referred to the recent decision of Finkelstein J in Conor Medsystems, Inc v University of British Columbia (No 2) [2006] FCA 32 ; (2006) 68 IPR 217. His Honour considered the meaning of the words "is not entitled to the patent" which appear in the ground of revocation under s 138(3)(a) of the Act. His Honour said at [19]: 
 
 respondents also contend that, having regard to the use of the present tense in s 138(3)(a), a condition precedent to a revocation order is a finding that the patentees were not entitled to the patent at the time of the application for revocation (or perhaps at the time of the hearing). I am far from persuaded that this construction is correct and it seems to be contrary to the views of Cooper J in Stack v Brisbane City Council [1999] FCA 1279 ; (1999) 47 IPR 525 , 536 and Crennan J in JMBV Enterprises Pty Ltd v Camoflag Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 1474 , [130]-[131]. But even if this construction were correct, the way in which I would read the section is that if a person were not entitled to the patent at the time of grant then, at least in most cases, that non-entitlement would be (as here) a continuing state of affairs. So there is really nothing in the point. " 
 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 15 Who may be granted a patent?</title>
<title id="l2">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 40 Specifications</title>
<title id="l3">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 138 Revocation of patents in other circumstances</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l5">ADMINISTRATION AND PROBATE ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l6">Administration and Probate Act 1958 - SECT 32 Payment or transfer by employer of moneys etc. held on account of deceased employee</title>
<title id="l7">Administration and Probate Act 1958 - SECT 33 Liability of person fraudulently obtaining or retaining estate of deceased</title>
<title id="l8">Patents Act 1903 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>