<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Vasiliou v Marchesi [2006] FCA 37 (3 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/37.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">application to remove trustee in bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">alleged failure of trustee to act in accordance with law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">whether proper case for inquiry has been demonstrated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">no evidence before the court to justify removal practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">motion to strike out application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1471">application to have affidavits removed from court file</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">real property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">caveat</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 213">removal.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] VSC 213">12 On 29 September Gray J dismissed the appeal proceeding with costs [3] . 13 On 14 October Marshall J dismissed the removal proceeding save as to two aspects upon which he gave judgment on 20 October and dismissed the balance of the claim with costs [4] . 14 Still undaunted, on 28 November the first defendant applied (in a fresh proceeding VID 1545/2005) for an extension of time in which to apply for leave to appeal from the decision of Marshall J; Merkel J dismissed this application on 3 February 2006 [5] . 15 Then, having rolled into 2006, in January the first defendant commenced another application in the Federal Court (proceeding VID 74/2006) against Tasiopoulos and the plaintiff seeking a stay or discontinuance of his bankruptcy, removal of the plaintiff as trustee, and compensation. On 6 February Ryan J dismissed the application with costs [6] .</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 179 Control of trustees by the Court</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>