<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Expectation Pty Ltd v PRD Realty Pty Ltd &amp; Anor (No. 2) [2006] FCA 392 (7 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/392.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 360">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 360">application for further discovery immediately prior to trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 360">consideration of the case management of the re-hearing of the action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 360">directions orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 360">consideration of the principles in relation to supplementary discovery.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 2">antoun v the queen  antoun v the queen  courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 2">apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 2">judge sitting alone in criminal trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 2">standards of fairness and detachment required of a trial judge.   gleeson cj. the appellants were jointly charged with demanding money with menaces from michael savvas, with intent to steal. the trial was conducted in the district court of new south wales before judge christie, sitting without a jury. the appellants were convicted, and sentenced to terms of imprisonment. they appealed unsuccessfully to the court of criminal appeal of new south wales [1] . the sole ground of their further appeal to this court is that the trial judge conducted himself in such a way that a fair-minded observer might reasonably apprehend that he might not bring an impartial and unprejudiced mind to the resolution of the question whether the appellants ought to be convicted. that ground is conveniently summarised as "apprehended bias". the apprehended bias is said to have arisen from two aspects of the trial judge's conduct in particular: first, the manner in which he dealt with what was described as a submission of no case to answer; secondly, his manner of raising and dealing with a question of bail.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 189">courts and judicial system</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 175">trade and commerce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 175">s 52 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 175">whether representations made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 175">whether representations relied on</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">johnson v johnson  courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">application for disqualification for bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">statement by trial judge about evidence to be relied upon</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">whether statement gave rise to reasonable apprehension of bias.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 291">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 291">application that judge who heard and determined interlocutory application not sit on the final hearing on grounds of apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 291">subject matter of interlocutory hearing no longer the same as the subject matter of the proposed final hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 291">application refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">judgment overturned on appeal on a question of the exclusion of certain evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">proceeding remitted to and heard by the same trial judge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">comments made in the original judgment about the policy of evidence law and relevance of evidence the subject of the appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">evidence now admitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">same substantive verdict on retrial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 8">whether a properly informed lay observer, looking objectively at the circumstances in which the proceeding was remitted to the primary judge, might reasonably apprehend that the primary judge might not bring an impartial and unbiased mind to the resolution of the dispute between the parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">consideration of the use by the tribunal of country information said to be less relevant than more contemporary country information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">consideration of a contention of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">consideration of a claim for a well-founded fear of persecution for a convention reason based upon events of protest in australia after the arrival of the applicant to this country</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">consideration of a sur place claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 959">consideration of s 91r(3)(b) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2006] AATA 523">expectation pty ltd v prd reality pty ltd (no.2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2006] AATA 523">[2006] fca 392</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 291">The application of the test requires two things. First, the identification of what it is that might lead a judge to decide the particular questions before him or her other than on the merits. Secondly, having identified the factor or circumstance that might influence a departure from meritorious decision-making, it is "no less important" ( Ebner at [8]) to articulate the "logical connection" between that factor and the fear that the judge might not apply proper judicial method (that is, merits based decision-making) in resolving the controversy on the facts and the law ( Ebner at [8]: as to a recent example of the application of the second limb, see: Expectation Pty Ltd v PRD Realty Pty Ltd &amp; Anor (No 2) [2006] FCA 392 ; (2006) 151 FCR 160). Only when the relevant factor is identified and the logical connection articulated, can the reasonableness of the asserted apprehension of bias be assessed. This test reflects ( Ebner at [33]): 
... the general principle to be applied ... to problems of apprehended bias, whether arising from interest, conduct, association, extraneous information or some other circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCAFC 8">First, the identification of what it is that might lead a judge to decide the particular questions before him or her other than on the merits. Secondly, having identified the factor or circumstance that might influence a departure from meritorious decision-making, it is "no less important" ( Ebner at [8]) to articulate the "logical connection" between that factor and the fear that the judge might not apply proper judicial method (that is, merits based decision-making) in resolving the controversy on the facts and the law ( Ebner at [8]: as to a recent example of the application of the second limb, see: Expectation Pty Ltd v PRD Realty Pty Ltd &amp; Anor (No. 2) [2006] FCA 392 ; (2006) 151 FCR 160). Only when the relevant factor is identified and the logical connection articulated, can the reasonableness of the asserted apprehension of bias be assessed. This test reflects ( Ebner at [33]): 
... the general principle to be applied ... to problems of apprehended bias, whether arising from interest, conduct, association, extraneous information or some other circumstance.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 959">49 The Tribunal's reference to the country information upon which it relied is said to reflect a less rigorous standard for assessing prospective risk and reflects an approach on the part of the Tribunal of simply relying upon out of date and irrelevant information rather than an inquiring or analytical approach to the question before it. Two things should be noted about this contention. First, it is clear from the Tribunal's reasons that it comprehensively reviewed all of the evidence both in terms of the appellant's written evidence and the evidence of the witnesses at the hearing. Thus, the Tribunal did not simply rely upon 'old decision templates'. Rather, the Tribunal asked itself whether it could be satisfied on all the material that the appellant held a well-founded fear of persecution for a Convention reason should he return to the PRC. Secondly, to the extent that the appellant's contention raises the notion of bias on the part of the Tribunal, there is no basis for such a ground of challenge. There is no evidence of pre-judgment by the Tribunal ( Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Jia Legeng (2001) 205 CLR 507 , per Gleeson CJ and Gummow J at [71] and [72]). If the contention is one of apprehended bias rather than actual bias, no fair-minded lay observer examining the reasons of the Tribunal could reasonably apprehend bias ( Re Refugee Review Tribunal &amp; Anor; Ex parte H &amp; Anor [2001] HCA 28 ; (2001) 179 ALR 425 per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ at [27] - [32]; Ebner v Official Trustee [2000] HCA 63 ; (2000) 176 ALR 644 at 647 at [6] per Gleeson CJ, McHugh, Gummow and Hayne JJ; Expectation Pty Ltd v PRD Realty Pty Ltd &amp; Anor (No. 2) [2006] FCA 392 ; (2006) 151 FCR 160). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2006] AATA 523">Those authorities included Re Seven Network Limited v Another (2004) 182 FLR at 169 Goldberg J, Expectation Pty Ltd v PRD Reality Pty Ltd ( No.2) --- [2006] FCA 392 , Re JRL Ex Parte CJL [1986] HCA 39 ; (1986) 161 CLR 342 , Ebner v Official Trustee in Bankruptcy (2000) CLR 337 , Antoun v The Queen [2006] HCA 2 and Spalla v St George Wholesale Finance Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 416.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l2">FAIR TRADING ACT 1989 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>