<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Shahid v The Australasian College of Dermatologists [2006] FCA 414 (13 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/414.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1165">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1165">interlocutory proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1165">whether costs should be payable forthwith</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] FCA 1878">15 There remains, however, a basis upon which the discretion can properly be exercised. The discretion may be exercised where, for example, costs have been incurred " as a result of ill-considered pleadings being drawn ": see Airservices Australia v Jepperson [2006] FCA 906 at [31] per Graham J. See also Shahid v The Australasian College of Dermatologists [2006] FCA 414 at [5] ---[6] per Nicholson J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 1165">11 In Shahid v The Australasian College of Dermatologists [2006] FCA 414 at [5] - [6] I said:
 
 'The respondent relies on the reasoning in McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Ltd [1999] FCA 1639 and Sereika v Cardinal Financial Securities Ltd (formerly Inteq Custodians Ltd) [2001] FCA 687. 
 
 In McKellar , Weinberg J followed the approach taken by Branson J in Life Airbag Co of Australia Pty Ltd v Life Airbag Co (New Zealand) Ltd [1998] FCA 545 and Kiefel J in Harris v Cigna Insurance Australia Ltd (1995) ATPR 41-445. In Harris , Kiefel J accepted that an order that certain costs be taxed and paid forthwith was justified in circumstances where there had been a long delay in the course of the proceeding by the pursuit of an ill-considered and unnecessary claim. It is common ground that the making of the order sought by the notice of motion is a matter in the discretion of the Court. ' 

In Airservices Australia v Jeppersen Sanderson Inc [2006] FCA 906 at [31] - [32] Graham J said:
 
 'In lengthy and complex cases where substantial costs have been thrown away as a result of ill-considered pleadings being drawn, the power to order that costs thrown away be paid forthwith should be used less sparingly than it has in the past. Such costs should be capable of being recovered without the innocent party having to wait, possibly years, for that to occur (per Weinberg J in McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Limited [1999] FCA 1639 at [41] ). 
 
 The making of an order under Order 62 rule 3 is justified where, through no fault of a party, such as the first and second respondents in the present case, there has been substantial delay in the proceedings because an applicant has attempted a number of versions of the Application and of the Statement of Claim, additional directions hearings have taken place which should not have been necessary, interlocutory steps have been taken and applications have been brought unnecessarily given the changes to the pleadings that have occurred (see All Services Australia Pty Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd [2000] FCA 375 ; (2000) 171 ALR 330 at 333 [11] . ' </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>