<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Y v The University of Western Australia (No 2) [2006] FCA 466 (1 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/466.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">media access to affidavits in evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">affidavits filed in ex parte proceedings for interim preservation orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">exhibiting transcripts of examinations under s 19 of the asic act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">principle of open justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">objections based on speculative risks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 407">access permitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 403">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 403">interlocutory injunction industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 403">construction of terms of certified agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">public access to documentary evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">principle of open justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">electronic courtroom</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">electronic media court book</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1394">federal court rules , o 46 r 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">agreement claimed to contravene the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">confidentiality claimed for certain parts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">order prohibiting publication and restricting inspection refused.  pleading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">amendment of statement of claim.  appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">function of appeal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">ambit of discretion under s.50 considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">order made prohibiting publication and permitting inspection to certain persons upon appropriate undertakings being given.  trade practices act 1974 , ss 45 and 45a;  federal court of australia act 1976 , ss.17 and 50 .  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">agreement alleged to contravene s. 45</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">confidentiality claimed for certain parts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">order prohibiting publication and restricting inspection refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">trade practices act 1974 (cth), s. 45a.  appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.12" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">function of appellate court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.13" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">ambit of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.14" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">order prohibiting publication and permitting inspection to certain persons upon undertakings given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.15" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth), ss. 17 , 50 .  practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.16" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.17" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">application to amend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.18" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">leave to amend refused by primary judge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.19" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.20" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">whether proposed amendments ambiguous</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.21" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">whether proposed amendments added substance. the australian broadcasting commission ("the a.b.c.") instituted proceedings in the federal court of australia against the members for the time being of the australian cricket board ("the board") and three corporations ("the corporations"). in the proceedings the a.b.c. sought certain relief for alleged breaches of the provisions of the trade practices act 1974 ("the act ") in relation to a written agreement between the board and the corporations dated 30th may, 1979. in the course of the proceedings the court refused to allow the a.b.c. to amend the already amended statement of claim in two separate respects. the a.b.c. appealed to the full court of the federal court of australia against this decision (appeal no. g13 of 1980). on the 18th february, 1980, the primary court decided further that the a.b.c. should be granted unrestricted access to certain parts of the agreement which were claimed to be confidential and that, upon the agreement being tendered and received in evidence, no order restricting publication of those parts of the agreement should be made pursuant to s. 50 of the federal court of australia act 1976 . appeals were lodged against the two last-mentioned decisions by the board and the three corporations (appeals nos. g14 and g15 of 1980). the three appeals were heard together and disposed of in a single judgment.  held: per curiam</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.22" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 33">the appeal in matter g13 should be dismissed with costs because: (1) the proposed amendment to par. 5 of the amended statement of claim was ambiguous and added nothing of substance.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">particulars sought but not provided</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">undertaking sought to protect identity of unnamed persons referred to in amended statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">form of undertaking</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">order of court sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">powers of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">necessity to promptly disclose information to enable meaningful defences to be filed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1060">inspection of documents by the public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASAT 112">working with children (criminal record checking) act 2004 (wa) &#173; review of refusal of application to have a negative notice issued to a school teacher cancelled &#173; class 2 offences &#173; non&#173;conviction charges 17 years apart &#173; whether satisfied in the particular circumstances of the case that an assessment notice should issue &#173; whether unacceptable risk that applicant will cause sexual or physical harm to children in the course of carrying out child-related work &#173; best interests of children paramount consideration</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1060">The interrelationship between ss 17 and 50 and Order 46 r 6 was also explored by Siopis J in Y v University of Western Australia [2006] FCA 466 , 151 FCR 322 (" Y "). Access had there been sought to material in another case involving sexual harassment claims. His Honour referred to s 17(1) and (4) and an earlier decision of the Full Court of this Court as follows: 
 
 [18] These sections give effect to a fundamental democratic principle of open justice which requires that the Court's work is done in public and be subject to the scrutiny of the public. 
 

 
 
 [19] The question of whether damage and embarrassment and considerations of confidentiality and privacy could found the basis for the making of a suppression order was considered recently by the Full Court in the case of Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd v Williams [2003] FCAFC 217 ; (2003) 130 FCR 435. 
 

 
He then referred to a further argument and said:
 
 
 [40] As to the wider argument by Senior Counsel for the University that the failure to suppress the names of the complainants may lead to persons in general being less likely to report sexual harassment, this is a variant of the argument founded on the potential for embarrassment of a party or a witness by the disclosure of that person's name. As mentioned, the extent to which embarrassment and distress may lead to the making of a suppression order under s 50 of the Act, in any proceeding, must be assessed by reference to the application of the principles in Williams , to that proceeding. In other words, the question of whether to make a suppression order under s 50 of the Act is not to be assessed by reference to broad public policy considerations, but by reference to the extent to which, on the evidence, the administration of justice may be prejudiced in any specific proceeding by not making the order. As stated at [24], it is established on the authorities that embarrassment, standing alone, is not sufficient for the making of an order under s 50 of the Act. 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] WASAT 112">110 Counsel for the applicant referred us to a decision of Siopis J in the Federal Court in Y v The University of Western Australia (No 2 ) [2006] FCA 466 in which his Honour reviewed authorities regarding the making of suppression orders under s 50 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) where there was a statutory or other regime in place relating to the confidentiality of the matter on appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 230">This statement of principle has been applied in a number of first instance decisions of this Court: see Nicholls v Australian Federal Police (No 2) [2009] FCA 123 at [4] per Mansfield J; Re Universal Music (Australia) Pty Ltd v Sharman Licence Holdings Ltd; Ex parte Merlin BV [2008] FCA 783 at [31] - [33] per Jacobson J; Rich v Harrington [2007] FCA 1979 at [23] per Branson J; Y v University of Western Australia (No 2) [2006] FCA 466 ; (2006) 151 FCR 322 at 332 [46] per Siopis J; Re Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd; Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Carey (No 2) [2006] FCA 407 ; (2006) 232 ALR 398 at 403 [18] per French J. The earlier decision of Finkelstein J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v ABB Transmission and Distribution Ltd (No 3) [2002] FCA 609 was to a similar effect except that the reasoning was in terms at [7] confined to: 
... cases where a non-party seeks access to material which has been relied upon by the judge. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 17 Exercise of jurisdiction in open court and in Chambers</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 50 Prohibition of publication of evidence etc.</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>