<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481 (3 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/481.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">exercise of discretion conferred upon the administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">scope of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of principles governing the exercise of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">acting judicially</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of the influence of authorities dealing with the exercise of curial discretion compared with discretion exercised by an administrative tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of whether questions of law properly raised</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of the need to formulate questions of law properly</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of principles derived from calderbank v calderbank and cutts v head .  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of the exercise of discretion by an administrative tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of "without prejudice" letters of offer. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of need to formulate questions of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 33">consideration of order 53, rule 3 of the federal court rules .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">application for extension of time to file and serve notice of appeal after lapse of 21 days from order for leave to appeal from interlocutory orders of supreme court.  special reasons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">failure of appellants' solicitor to file and serve notice of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">application for extension of time refused.  federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">consideration of order 52 rule 15(2) and order 3 rule 3.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">application for leave to file and serve notice of appeal out of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">special reasons.  federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 398">rules of court order 52 rule 15; order 3 rule 3.  cases referred to</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">leave to file and serve a notice of appeal out of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">whether special reasons shown by applicants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">where applicant's solicitor filed a notice of appeal within time but it was rejected by the registry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">where notice of appeal was in respect of a judgment of february 2010, an interlocutory judgment of 21 july 2010 on a matter of procedure and a final judgment of 15 march 2011</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">no leave required to include in appeal against final judgment a ground challenging the earlier procedural order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">special reasons shown by applicants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 852">extension of time within which to appeal, where necessary, granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 823">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 823">leave to file and serve a notice of appeal out of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 823">whether special reasons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 823">solicitor's mistake</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 823">personal costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">application to extend time for filing of compensation appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">whether applicants satisfied the court that good cause for failure to lodge appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">whether error of solicitor establishes good cause</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">whether applicant must give evidence as well as solicitor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">relevant considerations in exercise of court's discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">visa cancellation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">failure to satisfy character test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">imprisonment for sexual offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">application for extension of time to file and serve a notice of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">whether applicant denied procedural fairness by tribunal relying on lack of rehabilitation and intention of appellant to undertake rehabilitation program.  held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 987">leave to file and serve a notice of appeal granted.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 852">This is not a case where there is mere inadvertence on the part of a solicitor in relation to an appeal period: compare Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481. Rather, it is plain that the solicitor concerned, for the respondents below, expressly turned his attention to the appeal period and did seek to file within time and for that matter caused a notice of appeal to be lodged within time. It is just that a combination of errors, both within the registry and on the part of the solicitor intruded in relation to the form in which that notice was lodged. It would not, in my opinion, do justice as between the parties below and for that matter those that have the benefit of the payment orders, for there not to be an extension. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCA 823">The tendency in some of the decisions we have discussed to regard a particular factor considered previously, in the light of other circumstances, as requiring the same effect to be given to it in the different situation before a court on a later occasion is a temptation which a court should resist. Decisions are not authorities upon the facts but upon principles; the facts must be regarded as unique to the particular case. 
 

 
It is in that light that I view the statements, to which the respondent draws the Court's attention, by Kiefel J in Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481 , particularly at [8]. There the general context was, as her Honour found at [10], that the applicant clearly lacked any reasonable prospects. Chronology
  The respondent does refer to the unreported decision in Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481 at [8] which I have considered above. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2011] NSWLEC 19">Da Rous is distinguishable on its facts and does not take the correct approach to the construction of s 66(3). It incorrectly considers the question as if it were a general application for an extension of time. Error by the Applicants' solicitor is not sufficient to discharge the onus on a party of demonstrating good cause. The approach in Charles v Charles (NSW Supreme Court, Young J, 25 March 1998, unreported) to whether there were special reasons to grant an extension of time to file an appeal under the Family Provisions Act 1982 (the FP Act) (since repealed) is pertinent. The decision of Kiefel J in Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481 is also relevant. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 987">Special reasons will not exist where the appeal has no reasonable prospect of success "in the sense that it is devoid of merits, or will clearly fail, or is hopeless or unarguable"; see SZJDS v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1093 at [30] , per Reeves J. Lack of prejudice to the respondent occasioned by the delay in filing a notice of appeal does not of itself provide special reasons; see Perry v Comcare [2006] FCA 481 at [8] , per Kiefel J. However, the lack of prejudice to the respondent may make the Court more likely to exercise its discretion in favour of an applicant than in a case where such prejudice exists. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 24 Appellate jurisdiction</title>
<title id="l2">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l3">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 124 Application of Act to pre-existing injuries</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>