<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>White v Huxtable, in the matter of Lake Federation Pty Ltd (receivers &amp; managers appointed) [2006] FCA 559 (20 April 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/559.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 572">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 572">receiver and manager appointed under instrument of charge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 572">application for directions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 572">whether court should give direction that receiver is justified in entering into agreement for sale of assets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 572">whether court should give direction that it would not be unlawful for receiver to enter into agreement notwithstanding that purchaser is owned and controlled by appointor of receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">company law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">court's power to give directions to controller of property of the corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">whether court should give directions that controller is justified in entering into compromise agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">whether court should give direction that controller is not prevented from entering into agreement which confers benefit on mortgagee mortgages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">principle that mortgagee cannot exercise of power of sale in favour of itself</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">scope and content of principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1065">whether principle applies when receiver enters into an agreement under which mortgagee and related entities acquire option to purchase secured property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">australasian memory pty limited v brien  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">external administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">administration with a view to executing a deed of company arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">power of court to make such order as it thinks appropriate about how pt 5.3a is to operate in relation to a particular company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">whether power to remedy defect caused by convening of creditors meeting prior to specified period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">whether power to alter time periods fixed by pt 5.3a where specific provisions for extension of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">whether power retrospectively to vary the operation of pt 5.3a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 30">whether power to affect vested rights.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 140">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 140">whether court should give a direction to privately appoint receiver and manager</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 140">appropriateness of direction when matters of commercial judgment are involved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 140">role of directions where possible future legal action may be taken.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">whether plaintiff is attacker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">discretionary factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">novel claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">defendants' opportunity to narrow scope of dispute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">whether delay in making application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 434">rule 62.02(1)(a) supreme court (general civil procedure) rules 2005 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">application for directions under s 424 corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are obliged to realise floating charge assets pursuant to s 433 corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">floating charge assets comprising of causes of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are obliged to retire</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are entitled to create a retention fund</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">declaration as to proper construction of provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] WASC 170">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] WASC 170">application by receiver and manager in relation to sale of assets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] WASC 170">relationship between appointer of receiver manager and purchaser of assets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] WASC 170">turns on own facts</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] VSC 434">24 The receivers submitted that the contention by Ms Oswal that I should take into account that the receivers could have brought an application for directions is weak for two reasons; first, because of the limitations associated with applications for directions, particularly the fact that directions that are made do not bind third parties; [20] and second, because even if the receivers had sought directions, the Court might be persuaded to order Ms Oswal to pay the costs of the application. [21] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] WASC 155">35 It has been suggested that the reported and unreported authorities reveal discordant judicial opinion on the issue of whether an order under s 479(3) of the Act, and analogously an order under s 424 of the Act, can bind third parties in relation to substantive issues: Johnson R 'The Power of the Court to Give Directions to a Liquidator - Plagued by Uncertainty? ' (2005) 13 Insolv LJ 213 , 223. The better view is that a direction under s 424 does not bind third parties in relation to substantive issues even when they are joined as defendants to the proceedings. In White v Huxtable, In the Matter of Lake Federation Pty Ltd (receivers and managers appointed) [2006] FCA 559 ; (2006) 57 ACSR 435 Young J said:
 
 A direction under s 424 of the Corporations Act is a direction only. A direction in that form does not address the question whether the receivers have acted reasonably and/or discharged their duties under s 420A. Nor is such a direction binding on the defendants in such a way as to create any kind of legal estoppel. This is so notwithstanding that the directors have been joined in the proceeding as defendants and filed material opposing the making of the direction in the original form [21]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] WASC 170">32 This is an important point. Resort cannot be had to s 424 for the purpose of seeking intervention of the court to make a commercial decision for a receiver. This point of principle has been made in numerous cases: see, for instance, Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Best &amp; Less (Wollongong) Pty Ltd (rec &amp; mgr apptd) [1992] FCA 140 ; (1992) 7 ACSR 245 , 247. The reason for this approach was explained in some detail by Young J in White v Huxtable [2006] FCA 559 ; (2006) 232 ALR 388 [35]. Essentially, commercial and business decisions must be taken by a receiver. That is their function - it is not the court's function.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 420A Controller's duty of care in exercising power of sale</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 424 Controller may apply to Court</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 447A General power to make orders</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 479 Exercise and control of liquidator's powers</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1318 Power to grant relief</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>