<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Seven Network Limited v News Limited (No 16) [2006] FCA 574 (22 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/574.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] VCAT 1316">domestic building list vcat reference no. d766/2006 domestic building</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] VCAT 1316">complex case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2007] VCAT 1316">adjournment.  applicant abigroup contractors pty ltd, body corporate no. ps 502581d (riviera apartments) (by counterclaim) respondent river street developments pty ltd joined party 187 settlement road pty ltd where held melbourne before senior member d. cremean hearing type hearing date of hearing 25 july 2007 date of order 25 july 2007 citation abigroup contractors v river street devt (domestic building) [2007] vcat 1316  order  the compulsory conference fixed for 8 august 2007 is to proceed. by 8 august 2007 the respondent must file and serve any further affidavit(s) of non-expert persons together with copies of exhibits. by 15 august 2007 the respondent must file and serve any copies of materials of an expert nature it intends to rely upon including copies of any expert report(s) complying with vcat practice note 2. by 22 august 2007 the applicant must file and serve any answering affidavit(s) together with copies of exhibits and materials of an expert nature it intends to rely upon including copies of any expert report(s) complying with vcat practice note 2. i set this matter down for hearing before senior member cremean (if available) on a date after 3 september 2007 commencing at 10.00 a.m. at 55 king street melbourne not including the whole of the week commencing 10 september 2007 or october or november 2007. allow 10 days. the parties must arrange a running transcript and a tribunal book of documents to be relied on by them appropriately indexed and numbered or as appropriate.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] VCAT 1316">In that regard I refer to the statement by the High Court of Australia in Queensland v J L Holdings (1997) 141 ALR 351 at 357 that justice is the paramount consideration. No principle of case management can supplant the aim of achieving justice: Seven Network v News Ltd (No. 16) [2006] FCA 574 at [14] per Sackville J. And as Smith J. observed in Belini v Dinmkovski [2006] VSC 17 --- natural justice and a reasonable opportunity to call evidence require that adjournments be given in appropriate cases. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 45 Contracts, arrangements or understandings in restraint of trade or commerce.</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>