<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Applicant S116/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 618 (8 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/618.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">applicant nabd of 2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">appellant, an iranian, sought a protection visa on the basis that he had converted to christianity after leaving iran</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugee review tribunal twice affirmed decision to refuse the appellant a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">relying on information contained in a country profile, the tribunal distinguished between christians in iran who quietly go about their devotions and those who actively or conspicuously proselytise, and considered that only the latter group would encounter a real chance of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal asked itself a wrong question by seeking to categorise the way in which the appellant expressed his beliefs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal addressed whether appellant had a well-founded fear of persecution on the ground of religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal had committed jurisdictional error similar to the error identified in appellant s395/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs .  international human rights law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees convention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">ground of religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">freedom of religion as a basic human right.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">appeal from magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">whether the pressure on homosexual to marry amounts to persecution for a convention reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">whether refugee review tribunal failed to consider essential element of claimpractice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">judgments of single judges of federal court not binding on federal magistrates where not exercising appellate jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 41">judicial comity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2003] FCAFC 297">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2003] FCAFC 297">whether order dismissing application for an order nisi is interlocutory</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2003] FCAFC 297">whether leave to appeal is required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">appellant s395/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  appellant s396/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">particular social group identified as homosexual men in bangladesh</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether error of law by refugee review tribunal in finding that no real chance of persecution because appellants conducted themselves discreetly and would continue to do so</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether finding had effect of requiring appellants to act discreetly to avoid persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether need to act discreetly to avoid serious harm constituted persecution.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">application to review decisions of minister's delegates refusing claim for refugee status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">application of chan v minister for immigration and ethnic affairs [1989] hca 62 ; (1989) 169 clr 379</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">'real chance' of persecution test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">whether delegates failed properly to consider real chance of persecution.   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">decisions as to 'refugee status'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">proper role of reviewing court.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the full court should regard itself as bound to apply a formula derived from niemann v. electronic industries ltd [1978] vicrp 44 ; (1978) vr 431</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">width of the discretion to grant leave to appeal under s. 24(1a) of the federal court of australia act 1976 .  patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">taking of an account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether any part of general overhead costs is allowable as a deduction in the determination of the profits made by an infringer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">principles relating to the taking of an account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the case of a side-line is an exceptional case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">reference to standard accountancy methods as indicating what must be deducted in order to determine the amount of a profit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">discussion of a line of cases establishing the approach adopted in the united states to the solution of this problem</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">onus on wrongdoer who has mixed legitimate activities with activities involving infringement of another's property right to justify the particular apportionment of costs adopted by him in his accounts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">declaration of principle that the infringer is generally at liberty to show that various categories of overhead contributed to the obtaining of the relevant profit and to show in what proportion they should be allocated in the taking of the account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.12" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">discussion of whether the profits for which the defendants must account are (in the case of a patented closure for a canister) the profits for the closures only or for the closures and canisters to which they are fitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.13" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the infringer's particular pricing policy can be relied on by him as a contribution by him to the profits unrelated to the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.14" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the profits of the whole canister and closure are fairly traceable to the use by the infringer of the invention.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">second application to tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">previous decision upheld on judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">tribunal correctly declined jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">application dismissed at show-cause hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 647">no further filings direction to registry.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] HCASL 20">The history of those proceedings can be gathered from judgments recorded as NABE of 2002 v MIMA [2002] FCA 1410 , NABE v MIMA [2003] FCA 155 , S116 of 2003 v MIMA &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 119 , S116 of 2003 v MIMA [2006] FCA 618 and Applicant S116 of 2003 v MIMA &amp; Anor [2006] HCA Trans 698.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 887">3 I should add to the reasons I have just given that this application is made against a background of the applicant having litigated in this Court, the Federal Magistrates Court and the High Court on a number of occasions: see NABE of 2002 v Minister for Immigration [2002] FCA 1410 ; NABE v Minister for Immigration [2003] FCA 155 ; Applicant S116 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration [2006] FMCA 119 ; Applicant S116 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration [2006] FCA 618 ; Applicant S116 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration [2006] HCATrans 698.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 647">The applicant's judicial review litigation was extensive, involving two excursions through the lower Courts to the High Court of Australia (see NABE of 2002 v MIMA [2002] FCA 1410 , NABE v MIMA [2003] FCA 155, S116 of 2003 v MIMA &amp; Anor [2006] FMCA 119, S116 of 2003 v MIMA [2006] FCA 618 , and Applicant S116 of 2003 v MIMA &amp; Anor [2006] HCATrans 698).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 116 Power to cancel</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>