<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bayer Bioscience NV v Deltapine Australia Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 68 (10 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/68.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">confidential information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">objection to expert witness having access to confidential information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">whether expert witness prevented from access by likelihood of working for trade rival in future</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">whether justifiable concern that confidentiality be lost</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">availability of alternative expert</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">whether contractual undertaking as to confidentiality sufficient to protect confidential information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">whether substantial injustice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">form of confidentiality regime</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">costs.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] SASC 119">The plaintiff relies on three cases [1] where proposed expert witnesses were required to give an express written undertaking of confidentiality before being permitted to inspect confidential documents discovered by another party or the like.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] NSWSC 1056">


22 By reference to that statement of principle, the company plaintiffs relied upon two decisions of the Court of Appeal of Western Australia being Hotrox Charcoal Co v Gebauer Nominees Pty Limited [2002] WASCA 293 and Gebauer Nominees Pty Limited v Cole [2008] WASSCA 38 and the Federal Court decision in Bayer Bioscience NV v Deltapine Australia Pty Limited [2006] FCA 68. Those cases extended the principle stated by Hayne J to the situation where disclosure of confidential information was to be made not to a trade rival but to an expert who may provide advice and expertise to a trade rival in the future. In the Hotrox cases and in Bayer the Court held that the nominated experts should not be given access to the confidential information.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>