<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Day v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 655 (30 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/655.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">large corporate group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">inter-group transactions undertaken over six consecutive fiscal years</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">transactions involving inter-group interest bearing borrowings principally by one group member and transfers of tax losses arising out of those borrowings to other group members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">prior primary and appellate claims by proceedings in federal court made by borrowing member against the commissioner for interest deductibility in respect of one fiscal year</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">decision at first instance and on appeal in relation to that fiscal year adverse to that single group member</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">findings made in context of those proceedings as to assessability to tax of that group member in respect of some transactions for differing fiscal years</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">after conclusion of single fiscal year further proceedings commenced by the same corporate group member together with other corporate group members in respect of transactions involving borrowings and transfers of tax losses in respect of antecedent as well as subsequent fiscal years to that resolved by federal court in favour of commissioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">whether issue estoppel, anshun estoppel and/or abuse of process should operate in favour of commissioner in respect of deductions for losses of antecedent and subsequent fiscal years</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">meaning of privies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">authority in australian courts of earlier decisions of privy council and house of lords</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 267">summary judgment application of commissioner granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">deductions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">deductibility of legal expenses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">expenditure incurred in gaining or producing your assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">expenditure incurred in the course of gaining or producing assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">occasion of expenditure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">incurred in the course of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">performance of duties of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">observance of duties of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">purpose of incurring legal expenses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">defence of income from employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">whether defence of charges is productive of assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">success or failure of legal proceedings irrelevant to deductibility of legal expenses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.14" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">whether purpose alone is test for deductibility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.15" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">apportionment of deduction: "to the extent ..." practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.16" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">issue estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.17" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">consent order giving rise to issue estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.18" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">question in statement of facts, issues and contentions finally determined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.19" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">similar but not identical questions not finally determined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.20" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 193">onus on taxpayer to demonstrate assessment excessive</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">deductibility of election expenses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">legal expenses incurred in defending a pre-selection challenge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">whether incurred in contesting an election</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">requirement that expenditure be incurred in the course of the election   words &amp; phrases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1336">"in contesting an election"    income tax assessment act 1997 s 25 -60(1)</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] HCA 53">The primary judge held that the legal expenses incurred with respect to the charges were not deductible within the meaning of sub-s (1)(a), but also held the Commissioner to be estopped from contending that to be the case so far as concerned the expenses relating to the third charges [6] . The Full Court of the Federal Court, by a majority (Spender and Edmonds JJ, Dowsett J dissenting), allowed the Commissioner's appeal on the issue of estoppel but allowed the respondent's cross-appeal, holding the expenses to have been properly deductible under s 8-1(1)(a), and remitted the matter to the Commissioner for determination according to law [7] .
  The third charges, so described, arose out of a criminal investigation undertaken by the Australian Federal Police (AFP) which involved the interception of telephonic communications with the respondent [120] . Transcripts of the intercepted communications had been provided by the AFP to the Service for use in connection with the investigation into the events leading to the charges. That step resulted in the charges against the respondent, giving rise to an inquiry under s 62 of the PSA. The legal proceedings in respect of which the professional fees were incurred were designed to secure a declaration that the provision of the transcripts to, and their use by, the Service were unlawful. Effectively, the respondent sought a decision excluding their use. He also claimed damages for the alleged unlawfulness [121] .
  The judges in the Federal Court were divided in their opinions on the issue of deductibility. Dowsett J, in his dissenting judgment in the Full Court, agreed with the primary judge, Emmett J, that the legal expenses were not deductible because the conduct the subject of the charges comprised acts unconnected to the duties to be performed by the respondent in the course of earning assessable income [14] . The misuse of the respondent's identity card was unrelated to the performance of his duties and none of the conduct referred to in the third charges was performed by the respondent in the discharge of his duties as a customs officer [15] .
  Whatever may be the entitlement of the taxpayer in other cases, the respondent's legal expenses related to circumstances disjoined from "the course of" the income-producing activity. They were purely personal to the respondent. They were correctly so classified by the primary judge [166] . Whilst it may be conceded that difficult and contestable decisions will occasionally fall to be decided by the application of the Payne criterion, the present is not such a case given that the respondent did not suggest that any of his conduct resulting in his legal representation, involved the course of the performance of his duties as a Customs officer; and 

 
 . If the foregoing conclusion is reached, derived from an application of s 8-1(1)(a) of the ITAA read in the light of Payne , the outcome causes neither inconvenience nor surprise. Emmett J's holding, that the Commissioner was estopped from asserting that the legal expenses incurred by the respondent with respect to the third charges were not deductible, was based upon an order made by the Federal Court in earlier proceedings, to which the Commissioner consented, which allowed a deduction for fees paid to one counsel for legal advice in connection with the third charges. His Honour took the view that the Court must be taken thereby to have determined the deductibility of the other legal expenses referable to those charges [13] . It is not necessary to consider that aspect of his Honour's reasoning further. The Full Court upheld the Commissioner's appeal in that regard, and the respondent does not seek to raise that aspect of the Court's decision. This appeal is concerned solely with the question of the deductibility of the legal expenses by reference to s 8-1(1).
  The third charges, so described, arose out of a criminal investigation undertaken by the Australian Federal Police (AFP) which involved the interception of telephonic communications with the respondent [120] . Transcripts of the intercepted communications had been provided by the AFP to the Service for use in connection with the investigation into the events leading to the charges. That step resulted in the charges against the respondent, giving rise to an inquiry under s 62 of the PSA. The legal proceedings in respect of which the professional fees were incurred were designed to secure a declaration that the provision of the transcripts to, and their use by, the Service were unlawful. Effectively, the respondent sought a decision excluding their use. He also claimed damages for the alleged unlawfulness [121] .
  The Commissioner's assessment of the taxable income allowed no such deduction. The respondent's objection to the assessment was disallowed. He then "appealed" to the Federal Court of Australia [100] . At first instance, the primary judge (Emmett J) found, in substance, that the expenses were not deductible [101] . On further appeal to the Full Court of the Federal Court, a majority [102] allowed the appeal and held that the expenses were deductible. Orders were made that the matter be returned to the Commissioner for re-determination according to law. By special leave, the Commissioner appeals to this Court.
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCAFC 193">2 The proceeding before the primary judge was an appeal against a decision by the Commissioner on an objection by the taxpayer against an assessment to tax for the year ended 30 June 2002. His Honour's judgment is reported at (2006) 62 ATR 530 ; [2006] FCA 655. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] AATA 1336">Because the particular expenditure in question here is on legal expenses it is useful to have regard to the following remarks of Emmett J. in Day v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [12] where his Honour said: 
"The proper characterisation of legal expenses depends upon the circumstances with which the proceedings in relation to which the expenses were incurred were concerned. It is not sufficient to limit the question to the object or purpose, whether subjective or objective, that the proceedings themselves were intended or were hoped to achieve. A distinction must be drawn between the immediate object sought to be achieved by the particular proceedings in which the legal expenses are incurred and the situation that impelled the Taxpayer to undertake them. "
 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l2">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 </title>
<title id="l3">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 - SECT 14ZZ Person may seek review of, or appeal against, Commissioner's decision</title>
<title id="l4">TELECOMMUNICATIONS (INTERCEPTION) ACT 1979 </title>
<title id="l5">TELECOMMUNICATIONS (INTERCEPTION) ACT 1979 No. 114 of 1979 - SECT 5 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>