<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited; Pendant Software Pty Limited v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 (6 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/717.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">interlocutory application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">application for injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">private hearing for a banning order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">criminal charges arising out of same facts and circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">whether banning order hearing would prejudice defence or right to silence in criminal proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">whether administrative proceedings impinge upon pending court proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1043">contempt of court.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">judicial power of commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">corporations and securities panel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">acquisition of shares and conduct in relation to shares</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">power to declare unacceptable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">power to make orders, after declaration, to protect rights or interests of persons affected by acquisition or conduct or to ensure that takeover proceeds as if acquisition or conduct had not occurred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">whether panel invested with judicial power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">the constitution (63 and 64 vict. c. 12), ss. 71 , 72</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">australian securities commission act 1989 (cth), s. 171</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 58">corporations law of victoria, ss. 731, 732, 733, 734.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">trade practices commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">powers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">to require information to be furnished and documents produced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">civil proceedings pending in respect of same matter to &amp;which commission not party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">whether power exercisable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">the constitution (63 &amp; vict. c. 12), ch. iii</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 65">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss. 155(1) , (7), 157 , 159 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">crown</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">royal commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">inquiry and report into malpractices in handling of meat</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">person charged after establishment of commission with offences relating to export of meat</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">person charged giving evidence before commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">questions about matters relevant to charge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">interference with course of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">contempt of court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">royal commissions act 1902 (cth), ss. 6 , 6dd , 7</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">evidence act 1958 (vict.), ss. 16 (b), 29, 30.  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">privilege against self-incrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">whether abrogated by statute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">royal commissions act 1902 (cth), s. 6dd</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 42">evidence act 1958 (vict.), ss. 16, 19, 29, 30.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">whether general prohibition of commencement of litigation before the end of the takeover period precludes the seeking of remedial relief during the takeover period pursuant to s 1325a(2) of the corporations act 2001 (cth) ca</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">whether a general provision gives way to a specific provision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">what were the purposes of the respective provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">what are the interests of those affected by the irregularity which it is sought to cure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">considerations taken into account in granting relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">offer would be void</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">offerees who have accepted would be deprived of the benefit of the acceptance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 677">vast majority of offerees accepting with unanimous support of directors from target company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">appeal from single judge of the federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">application for declaration of contravention of s 606 of corporations act 2001 (cth) and consequential orders for relief including divestment of shareholding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">whether first respondent as a matter of fact acquired a relevant interest in fifth respondent's securities in the appellant pursuant to a takeover bid and therefore made an acquisition exempted under s 611 , item 1 corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">whether first respondent subsequently acquired a relevant interest pursuant to s 608(1)(c) corporations act 2001 by entry into a heads of agreement by acquiring the power to dispose of or control the disposal of the relevant interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">whether by entry into the heads of agreement the first respondent acquired a relevant interest pursuant to s 608(8) of the corporations act 2001 by acquiring an enforceable right in relation to the securities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">whether by entry into a merger implementation agreement and other transaction implementation documents the fourth respondent acquired a relevant interest pursuant to s 608(1)(c) or s 608(8) of the corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 55">whether a declaration by the australian securities and investments commission modifying the effect of s 609(7) of the corporations act 2001 pursuant to s 655a of the corporations act 2001 operated to protect the first and second respondents from acquiring a relevant interest by subsequent on market acquisitions in the appellant.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">takeover bid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">application by bidder for specific performance of substantial shareholder's promise to sell into the bid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">whether commencement of proceeding precluded by s 659b of corporations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">purpose and proper construction of s 659b</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">takeovers panel's power to make a declaration of unacceptable circumstances in relation to "affairs of a company"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 318">whether conduct in relation to a contract of sale of shares by a substantial shareholder to a bidder relates to the affairs of the target company</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 677">The earlier reasons of Goldberg J are not reported but his Honour's reference in Tower Software Engineering [2006] FCA 717 ; 154 FCR 150 (at [22]) as I perceive it, could only be to the principle of statutory construction that provisions of general application give way to specific provisions when they are in conflict (less helpfully known as 'generalia specialibus non derogant': Goodwin v Phillips [1908] HCA 55 ; (1908) 7 CLR 1 , Maybury v Plowman (1913) 16 CLR 468 , per Barton CJ at 473-474 and more recently in Associated Minerals Consolidated Ltd v Wyong Shire Council (1974) 4 ALR 353 at 359).  In Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited; Pendant Software Pty Limited v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 ; (2006) 154 FCR 150 , Goldberg J considered a comparable situation in connection with remedial orders sought under s 1071F CA. His Honour held that s 659B CA was a general provision whereas s 1071 CA was a specific provision in relation to a specific remedy and the Court would not be precluded from considering the specific relief. That approach was also summarised, obiter, by Austin J (at [18]) in Lionsgate Australia v Macquarie Private Portfolio [2007] NSWSC 318 ; (2007) 210 FLR 106. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] HCATrans 572">There is a dictum in a case called Pendant Software v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 ; (2006) 154 FCR 150 where there is a dictum at paragraph 37 simply approving the decision in Glencore as to validity.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCAFC 55">364 This finding was consistent with provisional views expressed by Emmett J in Glencore International AG (2005) 220 ALR 495 particularly at 511. Those views were adopted by Goldberg J in Tower Software Engineering Pty Ltd; Pendant Software Pty Ltd v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 at [37] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] NSWSC 318">"

17 The court's powers after the end of the bid period are limited by s 659C, generally to the effect that if the Panel refuses to make a declaration of unacceptable circumstances in relation to particular conduct and the court subsequently finds that the conduct contravenes the Act, its powers are limited to dealing with any criminal offence and making an order for the payment of money. 18 Where an applicant comes to court for relief under some other provision of the Corporations Act which expressly confers jurisdiction on the court, there is a question whether that other provision prevails over s 659B so as to allow the proceeding to be commenced and maintained notwithstanding a takeover bid or proposed bid. In Re Tower Software Engineering Pty Ltd; Pendant Software Pty Ltd v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 ; (2006) 57 ACSR 653 at [22] , Goldberg J explained that at an earlier stage of the proceeding before him, he had held that there was a serious question to be tried as to whether the court had jurisdiction, notwithstanding s 659B which is a general provision, to grant interlocutory relief where the ultimate relief sought was under s 1071F , a specific provision dealing with the court's power to review the directors' refusal to register a transfer of shares. Here, however, Lionsgate does not invoke any other provision of the Corporations Act , and relies instead on its common law and equitable rights of enforcement of a contract. The Tower Software case is of no direct assistance.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2006] FCA 1378">The Panel Orders made under s 657D created rights and obligations that, prior to the making of the Panel Orders, did not exist. I do not consider that those exercises of power involve the judicial power of the Commonwealth. There is no basis, therefore, for concluding that they were not a valid exercise of power conferred on the Panel by the Corporations Act (see Tower Software Engineering Pty Limited; Pendant Software Pty Limited v Harwood [2006] FCA 717 at [36] and [37] and Albarran v Members of the Companies Auditors &amp; Liquidators Disciplinary Board [2006] FCAFC 69 at [45] and [49]). 
 CONCLUSION 
 
 It follows that each of the proceedings should be dismissed. I would be disposed to make no orders as to the costs of either proceeding but will hear the parties on the question of costs.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 47 Control of a body corporate's board</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 107 Notice in relation to top 20 members of a class</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 120 Members, directors and company secretary of a company</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 175 Correction of registers</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 606 Prohibition on certain acquisitions of relevant interests in voting shares</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 650F Freeing off-market bids from defeating conditions</title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 657A Declaration of unacceptable circumstances</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 657D Orders that Panel may make following declaration</title>
<title id="l9">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 659AA Object of sections 659B and 659C</title>
<title id="l10">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 659B Court proceedings before end of bid period</title>
<title id="l11">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 659C Court proceedings after end of bid period</title>
<title id="l12">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1071F Remedy for refusal to register transfer or transmission</title>
<title id="l13">ROYAL COMMISSIONS ACT 1902 </title>
<title id="l14">ROYAL COMMISSIONS ACT 1923 - SECT 6 Protection of commissioners</title>
<title id="l15">Evidence Act 1958 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>