<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 (16 May 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/706.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">opposition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">locus standi of opponent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">person interested</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">financial interest of holding company whose subsidiary is a person interested</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">sufficiency of notice of opposition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">whether notice must state all relevant facts as to interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">patents act 1952-1966 (cth), ss. 59, 60 (5)*</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1969] HCA 7">patents regulations, reg. 20.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">appeal to high court by commissioner of taxation from decision of board of review allowing objection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">no appearance for respondent taxpayer on hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">whether commissioner entitled without more to have appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1957 (no. 27 of 1936</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">no. 65 of 1957), s. 196 (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">appeal from a decision of a delegate of the commissioner of patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">delegate refused to grant the claimed patent on the ground that it did not involve an inventive step and thus did not meet the requirements of s 18(1)(b)(ii) of the patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">before commencement of the final hearing, an administrator was appointed to the respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">ultimately, the respondent withdrew its opposition to the grant of the claimed patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">no opposition to the grant of the patent and no evidence led in opposition to the grant of the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 465">appeal allowed and order made that the claimed patent proceed to grant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">appeal under s 60(4) of the patents act 1990 (cth) against the commissioner's decision on an opposition to a grant of patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">whether tender of evidence as to the commissioner's decision, including the material on which it was based, inadmissible in the trial in this court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">whether evidence act 1995 (cth) applies to such evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">nature of opposition proceeding before the commissioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">nature of appeal under s 60(4) of the patents act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">effect of s 160(a) of the patents act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">effect of o 58 r 8 of the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">admissibility of evidence at the trial governed by evidence act 1995 (cth)  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">admissibility of evidence as to the commissioner's decision and the material on which it was based</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">whether evidence as to the commissioner's decision irrelevant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">whether evidence as to the material on which the commissioner's decision was based inadmissible as hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">evidence about the commissioner's decision relevant as jurisdictional fact and as the opinion of a person with technical expertise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">this evidence and material on which the commissioner's decision was based is admissible under the evidence act 1995 (cth) practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.14" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">whether leave to appeal against evidentiary ruling ought to be granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.15" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">case raises a matter of public importance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.16" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 182">leave granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">appeal under s 60(4) of patents act 1990 (cth) by applicant for patent against decision of commissioner of patents upholding opposition to grant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">pursuant to leave, opponent withdrew its appearance on the appeal, did not appear on the hearing of the appeal, and submitted no evidence in support of the commissioner's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">commissioner, joined as second respondent, appeared on hearing of appeal, but only to announce that she did not wish to participate actively on the hearing of the appeal or to oppose the allowing of the appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">procedure to be followed on the hearing of the appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1267">held : appeal could be allowed without applicant's adducing evidence to displace the opposition that had succeeded before the commissioner</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 465">The making of the orders foreshadowed above will not, of course, foreclose the question of the validity of the patent in any future proceeding, such as a proceeding for revocation of the patent. Lindgren J followed Young J in European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 ; (2006) 68 IPR 539 who in turn followed a number of other authorities all to the same effect. The propositions which Lindgren J extracted from the authorities referred to at [16] of Cadbury Schweppes [2006] FCA 1267 ; 69 IPR 584 are supported by the authorities cited by Lindgren J. In the present case, there being no opposition to the making of the orders sought by the applicant and no evidence tendered in opposition to the grant of the patent claimed in the Patent Application, the reasoning of Lindgren J in Cadbury Schweppes [2006] FCA 1267 ; 69 IPR 584 compels me to make orders substantially in the terms of the orders sought by the applicant. Recently, in European Community v Cmr of Patents (2006) 68 IPR 539 ; [2006] FCA 706 , Young J dealt with a similar submission made in similar forensic circumstances. Young J accepted the submission and held that the appeal should be allowed and that the application for the patent should proceed to grant. His Honour referred to Caroma Sales Pty Ltd v Philmac Pty Ltd [1972-73] ALR 427 ; (1972) 46 ALJR 324 per Walsh J; Brickwood Holdings Pty Ltd v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [1983] VicRp 117 ; [1983] 2 VR 587 at 588---9 per King J; and Titan Mining &amp; Engineering Pty Ltd v Arnall's Engineering Pty Ltd (1988) 12 NSWLR 73 at 75---6; 86 ALR 290 at 292; (1987) 10 IPR 661 at 663 per McLelland J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 218">Ms Rubagotti for the applicant has helpfully drawn my attention to two cases each of which was concerned with an appeal under s 60(4) of the Patents Act 1990 (Cth) in respect of a successful opposition to a patent application. The first is a decision of Young J in European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 ; (2006) 68 IPR 539. It was followed by Lindgren J in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Limited v Effem Foods Pty Limited [2006] FCA 1267 ; (2006) 69 IPR 584. In that case Lindgren J said at para [17]: 
 
 It is important to note that in the light of the history of the application, and, in particular, the commissioner's acceptance of the application and the complete specification, s 61 of the [Patents Act 1990] would have obliged the commissioner to grant the patent if there had been no opposition to the grant. In substance, that is now the position on the appeal. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCAFC 182">20 Thirdly, the only evidence to be taken into account at the hearing of an appeal under s 60(4) will be the evidence tendered or admitted at the hearing: see Caroma Sales Pty Ltd v Philmac Pty Ltd [1972-73] ALR 427 at 428; Brickwood Holdings Pty Ltd v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [1983] VicRp 117 ; [1983] 2 VR 587 at 588-89 per King J; European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 ; (2006) 68 IPR 539 at 543 per Young J; and Cadbury Schweppes Plc v Effem Foods Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1267 ; (2006) 69 IPR 584 at 586 per Lindgren J. This is the evidence on which the Court acts. As Kitto J said in Kaiser Aluminum at 142-43, in relation to the same kind of proceeding under the former Patents Act 1952 (Cth), the outcome of a proceeding such as this "must be decided upon the evidence adduced before [the] Court", even if a different case than that made before the Commissioner. We return to this proposition below, which is virtually decisive of the outcome of this appeal.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2006] FCA 1267">15 Recently, in European Community v Commissioner of Patents [2006] FCA 706 , Young J dealt with a similar submission made in similar forensic circumstances. Young J accepted the submission and held that the appeal should be allowed and that the application for the patent should proceed to grant. His Honour referred to Caroma Sales Pty Ltd v Philmac Pty Ltd (1972) 46 ALJR 324 per Walsh J; Brickwood Holdings Pty Ltd v ACI Operations Pty Ltd [1983] VicRp 117 ; [1983] 2 VR 587 at 588-589 per King J; and Titan Mining &amp; Engineering Pty Ltd v Arnall's Engineering Pty Ltd (1988) 12 NSWLR 73 at 75-76 per McLelland J.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 20 Validity of patent not guaranteed</title>
<title id="l2">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 60 Hearing and decision by Commissioner</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>