<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Cheng XI Shipyard v The Ship *Falcon Trident* [2006] FCA 759 (19 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/759.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1191">admiralty and maritime jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1191">in rem proceedings under s 17 of the admiralty act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1191">challenge to jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1191">security for the claims of the plaintiffs provided by p &amp; i club letter conditional upon jurisdiction being established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1191">security for costs sought by defendant in relation to jurisdictional challenge.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">extradition proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">whether court should decline to exercise discretion under order 28 rule 3(1)(a) federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">allegations of fraud and bad faith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">applicants in custody</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2001] FCA 577">whether proceeding a defensive proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">application to review asc decision to apply to corporations and securities panel for declaration of unacceptable circumstances s 733(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">whether reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">whether jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1542">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1542">consideration of an application for security for costs under s 56 of the federal court of australia act 1976 in relation to an appeal from a decision of the delegate of the registrar of trade marks under the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1542">consideration of the implications of a cross-appeal by the opponent to the applicant's application for registration of its trade marks in the making of an order for security for costs  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1542">consideration of the evidence relied upon by an applicant seeking an order for security for costs under s 56 of the federal court of australia act 1976 in the context of an appeal from a decision of the delegate of the registrar of trade marks under the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">discretion of court if applicant ordinarily resident outside australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">no evidence of any assets within the jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">no evidence of assets in foreign jurisdiction where judgment may be registered in future</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) s 56</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 540">federal court rules 1976 (cth) o 28 r 3.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] APO 3">The opponent requested the Commissioner order a security of costs from the applicant (in a letter dated 17 November 2009). The opponent argued that in court proceedings, where an applicant is normally resident outside of Australia and has no assets in the jurisdiction, there must be a weighty reason why an order for security of costs should not be made. [1] The opponent requested that the Commissioner follow court practice and award an initial Security of Costs from the applicant (or their patent attorneys) of $30 000 to be "topped up" later as the matter proceeded. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1542">13 BAT relies upon the broad unfettered discretion conferred upon the Court by s 56 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 to order an applicant to give security for the payment of costs that may be awarded against that party. The jurisdiction is not delimited by Order 28, r 3 ( Bell Wholesale Co. Ltd v Gates Export Corporation (No. 2) [1984] FCA 34 ; (1984) 2 FCR 1 ; Chapman v Luminis Pty Ltd [2002] FCA 496 ; James v Australia &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Ltd (No. 1) (1985) 9 FCR 442). In exercising the discretion under s 56 , the practice in Australia for a very long time has been that a party who is not ordinarily resident in this country and has no assets within the jurisdiction, is normally ordered to give security for costs. These two factors are regarded as circumstances of "great weight" in determining whether such an order should be made ( Chellaram &amp; Co. Ltd v China Ocean Shipping Co. (1991) 102 ALR 321; (1991) 65 ALJR 642). The qualification upon the weight to be attributed to these factors was put by McHugh J in Chellaram at p 323 (ALR) and at p 643 (ALJR) in these terms, "... unless that party can point to other circumstances which overcome the weight of the circumstance that that person is resident out of and has no assets within the jurisdiction". These well established principles have been applied more recently in Logue v Hansen Technologies Ltd [2003] FCA 81 ; (2003) 125 FCR 590 at [38] and [39]; Tan Kah Hock v AWAP SGT 26 Investment Ltd [2008] FCA 540 [7] and [8]; Cheng XI Shipyard v The Ship "Falcon Trident" [2006] FCA 759 at [9] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 540">8 This "well-established" principle was cited by Besanko J in Cheng XI Shipyard v The Ship "Falcon Trident" [2006] FCA 759 at [9] . In that case, Besanko J ordered that security be given. His Honour concluded that although the applicant had a strong claim that it would obtain a judgment in its favour, this was not sufficient to outweigh the fact that the applicant was not resident in the jurisdiction and had no assets in the jurisdiction. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 51A Interest up to judgment</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 56 Security</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>