<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79 (10 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/79.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">johnson v johnson  courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">application for disqualification for bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">statement by trial judge about evidence to be relied upon</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 48">whether statement gave rise to reasonable apprehension of bias.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 389">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 389">opposition to creditor's petition on the basis that the bankruptcy notice was not served</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 389">bankruptcy notice left in letter box at debtor's last known address</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 389">conflicting evidence on access to mailbox located within a secured premises</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 389">application to set-aside dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">fiduciary duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">company acting as agent for a joint venture</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">whether director can act in competition with the principal  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">cross examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">cross examination by two counsel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 125">when permitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 337">bankruptcy and insolvency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 337">bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 337">whether valid service by a photocopy of a bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 337">ss 40 , 41 and 306 of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 337">regs 4.01, 4.02 and 16.01 of the bankruptcy regulations 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 114">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 114">review of a sequestration order of a registrar</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 114">proceeding can be amended by substitution of a petitioning creditor practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 114">parties to proceeding can be amended on a de novo review of a sequestration order by a registrar</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">application to review sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">debt to petitioning creditor paid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">debtor solvent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">where trustee had incurred expenses in administration of estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 498">whether bankruptcy should be annulled.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 509">security for costs of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 509">no point of principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">application by bankrupt for orders against trustee in bankruptcy under s 179 of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">where bankrupt was unsuccessful respondent in separate proceedings in federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">where bankrupt appealed prior to bankruptcy against substantive orders and costs order made in separate federal court proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">where appeals deemed to be abandoned by trustee in bankruptcy by virtue of s 60(3) of bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">where trustee in bankruptcy has decided not in interests of bankrupt estate to prosecute the appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">whether trustee in bankruptcy may apply under s 33(1) of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth) for extension of time within which to elect to prosecute appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">where trustee in bankruptcy has decided not in interests of bankrupt estate to prosecute the appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">whether trustee's decision a basis for orders under s 178 or s 179 of bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">relevant principles. held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">no basis in fact to impugn trustee's decision that not in interests of bankrupt estate to prosecute the appeals under s 178 or s 179 of bankrupcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 10">application dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 389">The issue of "the last known-address of the person" [being served] has not been raised as an issue as the evidence clearly indicates Unit 6A, 45 Ocean Avenue, Double Bay is the residential address of Mr Luke Conrad and Ms Natasha Grace, and the registered business address of Visy Insulation Pty Ltd (ACN 140 360 676 and ABN 1614 0360 676) of which Luke Conrad is the director and sole shareholder which also lists its principle place of business as Unit 6A, 45 Ocean Avenue, Double Bay. I also accept the evidence of Mr Andrew Ng-Saad that he clearly marked two separate envelopes, one for each of the debtors, which were clearly named on the outside of a standard size "DL" envelope: see Lazar v Seccombe (2005) 3ABC (NS) 727; [2005] FCA 1652 per Jacobson J at 21- 26; Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79 per Mansfield J at [22] --- [24]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCAFC 125"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 337">That service of a photocopy of a bankruptcy notice (which otherwise complies with the requirements of s 41(2) of the Bankruptcy Act and regs 4.01 and 4.02 of the Bankruptcy Regulations ) is effective service is not surprising. It is consistent with the legislative purpose of personal service of bankruptcy notices. In Re Kassab; Ex parte Commissioner of Taxation (1994) 55 FCR 305 , 315 (when dealing with the earlier legislative regime) Black CJ, Sweeney and Sheppard JJ said that the purpose of the relevant provisions of the Bankruptcy Act and Rules then in force was "to ensure that notice of bankruptcy proceedings reaches the debtor" (see also Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79 at [22] ). Here, there was no dispute that notice of the bankruptcy proceedings reached the Appellant, albeit at least in photocopy form. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCAFC 114">It is a fresh proceeding. There is no scrutiny of the original reasons for error. It would follow that the petitioning creditor is required to prove the various matters required to be proved, including those specified in s 52(1) of the Act , in the review, as recently held by Mansfield J in Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79 ; cf Emmett J in Owners --- Strata Plan No 69405 v Azizova [2005] FCA 1340 at [4] ---[5]. Lander J discussed the nature of the hearing in Pattison v Hadjimouratis (2006) 155 FCR 226 (at [148]---[156]) and concluded (at [156]):
 
 "The federal magistrate who is hearing an application for review of a sequestration order made by a Registrar must approach the task as if the application for the sequestration order was being heard for the first time. It is procedure sui generis.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FMCA 498">(See Martin v Commonwealth Bank of Australia [2001] FCA 87 , Cottrill v Wilcox [2001] FCA 866 and Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79 at [40] per Mansfield J).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCA 509">6 On 1 February 2005, Mr Moore applied in the Federal Magistrates Court to review the making of the sequestration order. That application was dismissed on 1 July 2005: Moore v Wilson [2005] FMCA 870. Mr Moore appealed to this Court from that order. On 10 February 2006 that appeal was dismissed: Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79. Mr Moore sought special leave to appeal to the High Court from that decision, but his application was deemed to be abandoned under the High Court Rules.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FCA 10">3 The bankrupt challenged the sequestration order which had been made by a Registrar of the Federal Magistrates Court. On 1 July 2005 a Federal Magistrate dismissed the bankrupt's application for review ( Moore v Wilson [2005] FMCA 870). The bankrupt appealed to this Court against the Federal Magistrate's order. On 10 February 2006 a Judge of this Court, exercising the appellate jurisdiction of the Court, dismissed the bankrupt's appeal ( Moore v Wilson [2006] FCA 79). The bankrupt then applied to the High Court for special leave to appeal from the Judge's decision. It seems that the bankrupt did not comply with those rules of the High Court which require documents to be filed by a certain date and, as a result, his application was deemed to be abandoned. At a prior hearing before me, the bankrupt told me that there were good reasons why he did not file the necessary documents and that they related to his health. He told me that he would be applying for a reinstatement of his application for special leave to appeal. Whether he has done so, or will do so, is not relevant to the issues raised by the application before me.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 43 Jurisdiction to make sequestration orders</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l3">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 11 General powers of a court</title>
<title id="l4">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 27 Parties may question witnesses</title>
<title id="l5">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 28 Order of examination in chief, cross-examination and re-examination</title>
<title id="l6">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 41 Improper questions</title>
<title id="l7">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 52 Adducing of other evidence not affected</title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 35A Powers of Registrars</title>
<title id="l10">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l11">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 - SECT 104 Registrars--additional provisions</title>
<title id="l12">BANKRUPTCY REGULATIONS 1996 </title>
<title id="l13">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 </title>
<title id="l14">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 - REG 6.06 When is service by hand required</title>
<title id="l15">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 - REG 6.07 Service by hand</title>
<title id="l16">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l17">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 2001 No. 195- RULE 31.05 Service</title>
</legistitles>
</case>