<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Applicant M67/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 76 (10 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/76.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">adverse findings of credibility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">alleged behaviour modification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">whether tribunal asked wrong question</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 74">tribunal's approach in accordance with applicant's claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">applicant nabd of 2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">appellant, an iranian, sought a protection visa on the basis that he had converted to christianity after leaving iran</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugee review tribunal twice affirmed decision to refuse the appellant a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">relying on information contained in a country profile, the tribunal distinguished between christians in iran who quietly go about their devotions and those who actively or conspicuously proselytise, and considered that only the latter group would encounter a real chance of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal asked itself a wrong question by seeking to categorise the way in which the appellant expressed his beliefs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal addressed whether appellant had a well-founded fear of persecution on the ground of religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">whether tribunal had committed jurisdictional error similar to the error identified in appellant s395/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs .  international human rights law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">refugees convention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">ground of religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 29">freedom of religion as a basic human right.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">appellant s395/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  appellant s396/2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">particular social group identified as homosexual men in bangladesh</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether error of law by refugee review tribunal in finding that no real chance of persecution because appellants conducted themselves discreetly and would continue to do so</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether finding had effect of requiring appellants to act discreetly to avoid persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 71">whether need to act discreetly to avoid serious harm constituted persecution.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 429">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 429">objection to competency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 429">interlocutory orders purported appeal from judgment of federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 429">dismissal of application due to failure to appear</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 429">application refused.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">review of a decision of the refugee review tribunal ('the tribunal')</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">whether tribunal committed an error of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">whether any evidence of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">whether comments of tribunal amounted to a requirement that the appellant change her behaviour to avoid persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 702">no error disclosed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">application for review of decision of the refugee review tribunal affirming decision not to grant protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">citizen of people's republic of china</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">claiming fear of persecution on the ground of the religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 247">allegation of bias.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 25">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 25">interlocutory relief &#8722; application for reinstatement &#8722; where application previously dismissed for non-attendance &#8722; where considerable delay in bringing the application for reinstatement &#8722; where the applicant is an infant &#8722; where the applicant's father had been misled by his migration agent &#8722; whether the applicant satisfactorily explained the reasons for the delay &#8722; whether the application has a reasonable prospect of success.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 429">8 To establish error in a case where the decision appealed from involves a dismissal for non appearance, the appellant will, among other things, need to give an explanation for his or her non appearance (adopting the test in an application for reinstatement: see Applicant M67/2003 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2006] FCA 76 per Kenny J at [13] and MZKAJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 1066 at [18] per North J). The appellant must do so to show that the order for dismissal should not have been made in all the circumstances. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 702">10 His Honour also considered the decision of SBVC v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 76 , where Finn J upheld the Tribunal's conclusion that the manner in which an appellant practised her religion did not put her at risk of persecution from the Chinese authorities, and was satisfied that decision was applicable to the matter at hand and followed that decision. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 247">As counsel for the Respondent submitted, this case is essentially on all fours with the decision in SBVC v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 76 per Finn J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FMCA 25">" 
 

See also Applicant M67/2003 v Minister for Immigration [2006] FCA 76 at [13] .</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>