<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Maurice Hayes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd ACN 063 758 181 v Energy World Corporation Ltd ACN 009 124 (with Corrigendum dated 26 June 2006) [2006] FCA 783 (22 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/783.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">formation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">sale</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">document</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">meaning</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">intention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">default</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">assertion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">abandonment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">specific performance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">laches</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">reasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">readiness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">willingness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 53">moratorium acts 1930-1950.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">consumer law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">alleged misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">alleged product substitution scheme.  tort</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">alleged interference with contractual relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">elements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">whether any damage proved.  equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">fiduciary obligations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">senior employee.  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 467">duties of officers and employees.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">independent contractors act 2006</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">jurisdiction to review services contract which is no longer on foot when application is filed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">power to vary services contract which is no longer on foot when application is filed.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract varied with retrospective effect by court's order pursuant to independent contractors act 2006</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">alleged breach occurred after retroactive date of variation but before order for variation pronounced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">whether there could be a breach of contract in such circumstances.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">breach of a contract varied under independent contractors act 2006</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">nature of relief available.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract for services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">repudiatory breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">distinction between termination of services and termination of contract.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract terminable on reasonable notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">purported acceptance of non-existent repudiation cannot amount to notice to terminate contract within a reasonable time.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract for services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract of indefinite duration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">implication of term implying right to terminate on reasonable notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">identification of reasonable period of notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.20" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contractual relationship similar to an employment relationship</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.21" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">criteria related to concepts of severance and redundancy not relevant considerations.  damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.22" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">contract for services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.23" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.24" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">damages for failure to give reasonable notice of termination.  damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.25" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.26" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">damages in the reasonable contemplation of the parties at the time of making the contract as the probable result of the breach.  jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.27" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">"matter"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.28" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">express jurisdiction under independent contractors act 2006</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.29" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">accrued jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.30" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">claim under independent contractors act 2006 and related claim for damages comprised the same matter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.31" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">associated jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.32" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">claim for damages consequent upon contractual variation pursuant to independent contractors act 2006 a federal matter associated with claim under the independent contractors act 2006 .  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.33" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">amendment of claim to include cause of action accruing after commencement of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.34" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 394">date amendment effective.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">inconsistency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">could not be corrected without rectification  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">terms of implied agreement to continue dealing after expiry of written agreement contract for services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">period of reasonable notice of termination appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 34">advantages of primary judge</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 467">Reasonable notice has to be assessed, and in a commercial context, reasonable notice is the time a party would take to make alternative contractual arrangements. [40] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FMCA 394">In Maurice Hayes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd v Energy World Corporation Ltd [2006] FCA 783 , Siopis J at first instance considered the case of a contractor company which provided the services of a sole individual, a situation similar to the one-man businesses operated by the current applicants. His Honour observed, in part of the judgment against which the subsequent appeal was unsuccessful, that factors relevant to an employment contract were of some assistance as a guide to assessing what would be reasonable notice of the termination of the contract the subject of that proceeding. However, considerations derived from the law relating to the termination of employment can only be relevant in these proceedings to the extent that they assist the Court to address the purposes which Crawford Fitting Co identified as underlying the implication of a requirement to give reasonable notice. Obtaining alternative work
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCAFC 34">
 1 This appeal from the judgment in Maurice Hayes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd ACN 063 758 181 v Energy World Corporation Ltd ACN 009 124 994 [2006] FCA 783 concerns the financial ramifications of the termination of a consultancy arrangement whereby the respondent/cross-appellant Maurice Hayes &amp; Associates Pty Ltd (the Consultant) provided the services of Mr Maurice Hayes to the appellant/cross-respondent, Energy World Corporation Ltd (the Company) (then named Energy Equity Corporation Ltd). The issues which arise on the appeal and cross-appeal are more confined than were the issues at trial.  8 The primary Judge said that there were no major factual disputes in the case as the differences between the parties related to the inferences that were to be drawn and the conclusions that were to be reached from primary facts which were not materially in dispute ([2006] FCA 783 at [5]). The facts are set out [2006] FCA 783 at [6] ---[47]. It is unnecessary to reproduce all of those facts for the purposes of this judgment but they should be taken as having been adopted by us. 
  
 25 It is submitted for the Company that the true issue is whether the conduct of the parties after 4 July 2001 showed a tacit understanding or agreement that the Consultant was to be paid at the rate of $190 000 per annum. This was said to be an objective question, relying upon Integrated Computer Services Pty Ltd v Digital Equipment Corp (Australia) Pty Ltd (1988) 5 BPR 11 ,110; and Equuscorp Pty Ltd v Glengallan Investments Pty Ltd [2004] HCA 55 ; (2004) 218 CLR 471. The primary Judge approached the matter along those lines (see [2006] FCA 783 at [162] ). It needs to be borne in mind that the Judge upheld the Consultant's claim that the Agreement was in full force and effect so far as the rate of remuneration was concerned until 30 June 2001, contrary to the position of the Company. This explains the fact that the Judge gave little weight to the pre 30 June 2001 discussions in his assessment of the relevant facts.  30 The positive finding of the primary Judge was clearly and succinctly reasoned as follows ([2006] FCA 783 at [187]):
 '... I take into account the nature of the post 30 June 2001 contract and the limited scope of the duties which Mr Hayes was required to perform thereunder. The post 30 June 2001 contract was in effect a contract whereby the applicant was to provide Mr Hayes' services to assist in relation to the asset realisation programme. It was not a senior executive position. Further, it would have been apparent to Mr Hayes that the work which would be available in that capacity under the post 30 June 2001 contract would be of a finite duration. I find that Mr Hayes was in a position to assess progressively the amount of work that was left to do in order to complete the asset realisation programme. Further, he would also have been aware from his conversation with Mr Elliott in February 2001 that the respondent under the control of EWI did not generally favour consultancy agreements. Accordingly, Mr Hayes was in a position himself to make a continuing assessment of the likely duration of the post 30 June 2001 contract. '  8 The primary Judge said that there were no major factual disputes in the case as the differences between the parties related to the inferences that were to be drawn and the conclusions that were to be reached from primary facts which were not materially in dispute ([2006] FCA 783 at [5]). The facts are set out [2006] FCA 783 at [6] ---[47]. It is unnecessary to reproduce all of those facts for the purposes of this judgment but they should be taken as having been adopted by us. 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 4 Interpretation.</title>
<title id="l2">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1974 No. 51, 1974 - SECT 52 Misleading or deceptive conduct.</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>