<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wildlife Preservation Society of Queensland Proserpine/Whitsunday Branch Inc v Minister for the Environment&amp; Heritage &amp; Ors [2006] FCA 736 (15 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/736.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">decision made under s 133 of the environment protection and biodiversity conservation act 1999 (cth) to approve proposal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the decision was ultra vires the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the minister failed to take into account the "precautionary principle"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">information "available" to the minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the minister was obliged to seek further information prior to making decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the decision was unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the result of the decision was uncertain</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 330">whether the decision was irrational or capricious</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">application for an order to review decision of delegate of the minister for the environment and water resources</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">environment protection and biodiversity conservation act 1999 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">whether proposed action is a controlled action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">whether this is a question of jurisdictional fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">whether delegate applied wrong test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">whether delegate misconstrued listed threatened ecological community environmental law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">environment protection and biodiversity conservation act 1999 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">whether proposed action is a controlled action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">coal mine</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">significance of listing as a key threatening process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">correct test for assessing impact on protected matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1480">listed threatened ecological community</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 330">I have, thus far, assumed that the Minister was required, by either or both ss 136(2) and 391(1) of the Act, to have regard to the precautionary principle when exercising his powers under ss 133 and 134. It may, however, be doubted that, having regard to the material before him, he was under any such obligation. The precautionary principle, as expressed in both ss 3A(b) and s 391(2) of the Act, is called into play where there exist "threats of serious or irreversible environmental damage": see Wildlife Preservation Society of Queensland Proserpine/Whitsunday Branch Inc v Minister for the Environment and Heritage [2006] FCA 736 ; (2006) 232 ALR 510 at 521. The findings made and the conclusions reached by the Minister, which are recorded above at [24] and [25] strongly suggest that he did not identify any threat of serious or irreversible damage to the Commonwealth marine environment which would be caused by the proposed discharge of effluent. Certainly he made no express finding to this effect. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 1480">35 A submission similar to the applicant's was rejected by Dowsett J in Wildlife Preservation Society of Queensland Proserpine/Whitsunday Branch Inc v Minister for the Environment and Heritage [2006] FCA 736 ; (2006) 232 ALR 510. It was submitted to his Honour that the purpose of the enquiry under s 75 of the Act was "to attribute legal responsibility for impacts to matters protected by Pt 3 of the EPBC Act in light of the subject, scope and objects of the Act" . In response to this submission, at [57] of his reasons, observed:
 I am not sure that the purpose of Part 3 is to attribute legal responsibility for the causation of adverse impacts. To my mind the purpose of the Act is to prevent or minimise such adverse impact. ... Causation is, of course, not mentioned in s 12 or the other analogous sections in Pt 3. However, it was submitted that there is necessarily a causal relationship between an action and any relevant impact. That is probably so, but I see no reason to introduce notions of causation into the process prescribed by s 75. It is not necessary to go beyond the language of the relevant sections. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 - SECT 5 Applications for review of decisions</title>
<title id="l2">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 - SECT 13 Reasons for decision may be obtained</title>
<title id="l3">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l4">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 - SECT 15AB Use of extrinsic material in the interpretation of an Act</title>
<title id="l5">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l6">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 3A Principles of ecologically sustainable development</title>
<title id="l7">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 12 Requirement for approval of activities with a significant impact on a declared World Heritage property</title>
<title id="l8">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 16 Requirement for approval of activities with a significant impact on a declared Ramsar wetland</title>
<title id="l9">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 18 Actions with significant impact on listed threatened species or endangered community prohibited without approval</title>
<title id="l10">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 18A Offences relating to threatened species etc.</title>
<title id="l11">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 20 Requirement for approval of activities with a significant impact on a listed migratory species</title>
<title id="l12">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 20A Offences relating to listed migratory species</title>
<title id="l13">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 67 What is a controlled action?</title>
<title id="l14">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 68 Referral by person proposing to take action</title>
<title id="l15">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 74 Inviting provision of information on referred proposal</title>
<title id="l16">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 74A Minister may request referral of a larger action</title>
<title id="l17">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 75 Does the proposed action need approval?</title>
<title id="l18">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 77 Notice and reasons for decision</title>
<title id="l19">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 183 Listing of key threatening processes</title>
<title id="l20">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 188 Amending list of key threatening processes</title>
<title id="l21">ENVIRONMENT PROTECTION AND BIODIVERSITY CONSERVATION ACT 1999 - SECT 523 Actions</title>
</legistitles>
</case>