<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Queensland Rail v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 816 (30 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/816.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">customs and excise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">diesel fuel rebate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">appeal under s 44 of administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">whether administrative appeals tribunal erred in refusing to pay claims for rebate under s 164 customs act 1901 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">where applicant engaged in dredging of channels in various ports</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">definition of "in marine transport" under s 164(7)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">whether particular uses of diesel fuel in dredging operations attracted rebate administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">construction of legislation by administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">tribunal assumed bulletin published by australian taxation office constituted departmental policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">tribunal applied bulletin when construing legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">tribunal erred in relying on bulletin in a material way</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1232">error of law in approach of the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 28">taxation law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 28">disallowance of energy grants claimed for purchase of off-road diesel fuel used in connection with rail transport</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 28">whether fuel must be used in equipment which is in or on a rail vehicle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 28">whether off-rail use for a purpose incidental to rail transport is sufficient</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">statutory interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">whether ambiguity required in order to consult statutory purpose, context, and legislative history</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">relationship between substantive and definitional provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">presumption that beneficial legislation be construed broadly</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">whether legislation is beneficial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">presumption that, where possible, all words of a statutory provision be given some work to do</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">rules versus standards</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">relevance of anomalous results</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">presumption that legislature takes judicial decisions into account when drafting statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">whether explanatory memorandum to be construed as a statutory instrument.  taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">whether purchase of off-road diesel fuel for use in equipment not located in or on a rail vehicle is entitled to a credit under s 53 of the energy grants (credits) scheme act 2003 (cth) if used for a purpose incidental to the use of a vehicle in rail transport</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1401">definition of "use in rail transport".</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCAFC 28">In Queensland Rail v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 816 ; (2006) 153 FCR 524 Dowsett J considered whether Queensland Rail was entitled to a rebate in respect of diesel fuel purchased for use in its off-rail and hi-rail operations. Hi-rail operations involve vehicles which can be used on or off rails. Pursuant to s 164(1)(ab) of the Customs Act 1901 (Cth) a rebate was available to a person who purchased diesel fuel for use by that person "in rail transport". His Honour held, at [44], that "in rail transport" meant "in a system or means of transportation or conveyance of people or goods by rail". His Honour rejected the argument that the rebate only extended to on-rail operations observing, at [38], that if Parliament intended that only on-rail activities should attract a rebate, "it would have been easy to say so". Dowsett J postulated that if the purpose of the legislation was to subsidise transport costs and to benefit the environment then there was "no apparent reason for such a narrow construction". His Honour further observed that in the context of the taxpayer carrying on an enterprise it was unlikely that Parliament "intended to draw an artificial distinction between activities on-rail and off-rail, all of which were necessary to the transport of people or goods by rail". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1401">15 The Commissioner attempts to meet this concern by speculating that the legislature may have been concerned in the rail context with hybrid vehicles such as "hi-rails," which are capable of travelling both on roads and on rail: see Queensland Rail v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 816 ; (2006) 153 FCR 524 at [19] , [23]-[24] for a description of these vehicles. Quite correctly, counsel for Asciano noted in oral argument that this speculation, even if correct, did not meet the point, because s 38 would already cover purchases for hi-rail use - when the fuel is purchased for on-rail use, it would be eligible for credit, but when the fuel is purchased for use in off-rail activities, whether on public roads or otherwise, it would be ineligible. Moreover, as Asciano submitted, the argument that the parenthetical language was included by inadvertence or out of an abundance of caution in the predecessor to s 53, (s 164(1)(ab) of the Customs Act 1901 (Cth) and s 78A(1)(ab) of the Excise Act 1901 (Cth)), was rejected by Dowsett J in Queensland Rail [2006] FCA 816 ; 153 FCR 524 at [40] for the reasons identified by Asciano above.  15 The Commissioner attempts to meet this concern by speculating that the legislature may have been concerned in the rail context with hybrid vehicles such as "hi-rails," which are capable of travelling both on roads and on rail: see Queensland Rail v Commissioner of Taxation [2006] FCA 816 ; (2006) 153 FCR 524 at [19] , [23]-[24] for a description of these vehicles. Quite correctly, counsel for Asciano noted in oral argument that this speculation, even if correct, did not meet the point, because s 38 would already cover purchases for hi-rail use - when the fuel is purchased for on-rail use, it would be eligible for credit, but when the fuel is purchased for use in off-rail activities, whether on public roads or otherwise, it would be ineligible. Moreover, as Asciano submitted, the argument that the parenthetical language was included by inadvertence or out of an abundance of caution in the predecessor to s 53, (s 164(1)(ab) of the Customs Act 1901 (Cth) and s 78A(1)(ab) of the Excise Act 1901 (Cth)), was rejected by Dowsett J in Queensland Rail [2006] FCA 816 ; 153 FCR 524 at [40] for the reasons identified by Asciano above. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS NUMBER) ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l1">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS NUMBER) ACT 1999 - SECT 41 Dictionary</title>
<title id="l2">CUSTOMS ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l3">EXCISE ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l4">EXCISE ACT 1901 - SECT 164 Regulations</title>
<title id="l5">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS NUMBER) ACT 1999 - SECT 37 Entity</title>
<title id="l6">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (AUSTRALIAN BUSINESS NUMBER) ACT 1999 - SECT 38 Enterprise</title>
<title id="l7">DIESEL AND ALTERNATIVE FUELS GRANTS SCHEME ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l8">TELECOMMUNICATIONS (INTERCEPTION) ACT 1979 </title>
<title id="l9">TRANSPORT INFRASTRUCTURE ACT 1994 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>