<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 810 (30 June 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/810.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1095">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1095">winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1095">application for order for winding up in insolvency where company already under creditors voluntary winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1095">potential advantages to creditors under alternative form of winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">application by liquidators of company in voluntary winding up for winding up by the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">effect of ss 468 and 588fj</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">possible effects of directors' and officers' insurance policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 128">whether grounds sufficient to justify winding up by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 38">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 38">whether provisional liquidator should be appointed of company in members' voluntary winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 38">whether if provisional liquidator should be appointed the person so appointed should be the liquidator in the members' voluntary winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 360">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 360">order to be made under s.600c that resolution that deed of company arrangement be terminated and company be wound up be deemed passed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 360">whether court should then consider pending application for court ordered winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 360">whether good reason for voluntary winding up to be superseded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2007] NSWSC 360">question of choice of liquidator</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] WASC 38">6 It is not in contest that the appointment of a provisional liquidator may be made in respect of a company in members' voluntary liquidation, and I refer for this purpose to Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 810 ; (2006) 153 FCR 394 a case of winding up in insolvency where the company was in creditors' voluntary winding up, at least where such a winding up in insolvency by the court was sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] SASC 218">HARRIS SCARFE LTD (IN LIQ) &amp; HARRIS SCARFE WHOLESALE PTY LTD (IN LIQ) (No 3) [2007] SASC 218 (14 June 2007) 

 [ Home ] [ Databases ] [ WorldLII ] [ Search ] [ Feedback ] Supreme Court of South Australia Decisions You are here: AustLII &gt;&gt; Databases &gt;&gt; Supreme Court of South Australia Decisions &gt;&gt; 2007 &gt;&gt; [2007] SASC 218 

 [ Database Search ] [ Name Search ] [ Recent Decisions ] [ Noteup ] [ Download ] [ LawCite ] [ Help ] HARRIS SCARFE LTD (IN LIQ) &amp; HARRIS SCARFE WHOLESALE PTY LTD (IN LIQ) (No 3) [2007] SASC 218 (14 June 2007) 
Last Updated: 14 June 2007 
 SUPREME COURT OF SOUTH AUSTRALIA 
 (Civil: Application)
 

 DISCLAIMER - Every effort has been made to comply with suppression orders or statutory provisions prohibiting publication that may apply to this judgment. The onus remains on any person using material in the judgment to ensure that the intended use of that material does not breach any such order or provision. Further enquiries may be directed to the Registry of the Court in which it was generated. HARRIS SCARFE LTD (IN LIQ) &amp; HARRIS SCARFE WHOLESALE PTY LTD (IN LIQ) (No 3) 
 

 [2007] SASC 218 
 

 Judgment of The Honourable Justice Gray 
 

 14 June 2007 
 



 
 CORPORATIONS - WINDING UP - APPLICATIONS FOR WINDING UP BY COURT 
 
 CORPORATIONS - WINDING UP - LIQUIDATORS - APPOINTMENT - IN WINDING UP BY COURT 
 
 Application for court order winding up companies, appointing liquidators, and permitting applicants to dispense with notice requirements - companies had previously been wound up and applicants had previously been appointed liquidators by voluntary resolution of the creditors - directors' insurance policy arguably would not cover a claim by a liquidator who has not been appointed by a court - whether the Court has power to order winding up of companies and appointing of liquidators where the companies have already been wound up and liquidators already appointed - whether an insurance policy that would arguably not cover a claim by a liquidator who has not been appointed by a Court provides good reason to order that the companies be wound up and liquidators appointed - Held (allowing the application): the Court has power to order the winding up of companies and appointing of liquidators where the companies have already been wound up and liquidators already appointed - an insurance policy that would arguably not cover a claim by a liquidator who has not been appointed by a Court is a relevant factor in determining whether good reason exists to order that the companies be wound up and liquidators appointed - in the circumstances good reason exists to make the orders sought. Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) s 439C , s 446A , s 459A , s 465A(b) , s 465A(c) , s 470(2)(b) , s 470(2)(c) , s 467(3)(b) , s 467B , s 472(1) , s 588M , referred to. Commissioner of Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 810 ; (2006) 153 FCR 394 ; Dean-Willcocks (in his capacity as Liquidator of Austral Pacific Group Ltd (in liq)) [2004] NSWSC 1209 ; Re Green (as liquidator of Australian Resources Limited (in liquidation)) [2004] NSWSC 1095 ; (2004) 52 ACSR 452 ; Carter &amp; Anor (as liquidators of New Tel Ltd (in liquidation)) v New Tel Ltd (in liquidation) [2003] NSWSC 128 ; (2003) 44 ACSR 661 , considered. 


 HARRIS SCARFE LTD (IN LIQ) &amp; HARRIS SCARFE WHOLESALE PTY LTD (IN LIQ) (No 3) 
 [2007] SASC 218 

 

 

 Civil 

 GRAY J 

 Introduction 
 

 
 On 26 March 2007, I made orders winding up eleven entities forming a group of companies is known as the Harris Scarfe Companies. [1] I further ordered that Samuel Charles Davies and Colin McIntosh Nicol, the applicants, be appointed liquidators.  In Commissioner of Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Ltd , [2] Besanko J, although declining to make an order in that case, observed: [3] 
 
 In my opinion, it is not necessary to make an order terminating the voluntary winding up of the company before making an order winding up the company in insolvency. It seems to me that s 467B contemplates an order winding up a company in insolvency even though the company "is already being wound up voluntarily". 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] NSWSC 360">5 On the question whether the court can and should order the winding up of a company already subject to voluntary winding up, I accept the principles referred to by Besanko J in Deputy Commissioner for Taxation v Tull Reinforcing Pty Limited [2006] FCA 810 ; (2006) 153 FCR 394 at [17] and [18]. In summary, the replacement regime of winding up by the court - and I emphasise that, for reasons given by Besanko J in his judgment, it is a replacement regime without any need to make an order terminating the voluntary winding up --- may properly be installed by the court where there is some good reason to do so. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 233 Orders the Court can make</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 439C What creditors may decide</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 459A Order that insolvent company be wound up in insolvency</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 459B Order made on application under section 234, 462 or 464</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 459C Presumptions to be made in certain proceedings</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 459P Who may apply for order under section 459A</title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 461 General grounds on which company may be wound up by Court</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 467B Court may order winding up of company that is being wound up voluntarily</title>
<title id="l9">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 482 Power to stay or terminate winding up</title>
<title id="l10">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l11">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 35A Powers of Registrars</title>
<title id="l12">FEDERAL COURT (CORPORATIONS) RULES 2000 </title>
<title id="l13">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>