<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>McIlwain v Ramsey Food Packaging Pty Ltd (No. 3) [2006] FCA 994 (3 August 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/994.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of conduct of dismissal of employees and refusal to employ persons at the south grafton abattoir</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of part xa, divisions 2 and 3</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">ss 298k(1)(a) and (d) and prohibited purposes of membership of an industrial association, entitlements to the benefit of orders of the airc, participation in proceedings before the airc as a party and by giving evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">the expression of dissatisfaction of working conditions in the context of an industrial association seeking better conditions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the circumstances required to be satisfied before a statutory presumption of a prohibited purpose arises for the purposes of s 298v. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the approach to be adopted in dealing with a 'no case to answer' submission and whether a respondent ought to be put to an election as a condition of making the submission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the basis upon which submission made and the relationship between the grounds advanced by the moving party and the need for an election. evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the utility of the report of an expert and the extent to which the report failed to meet the standards required by the guidelines for expert witnesses in proceedings in the federal court of australia issued by the chief justice on 19 march 2004</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the extent to which the report might be characterised as a piece of advocacy for a party. evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the principles governing the reception of tendency evidence both generally and for the purposes of s 97 of the evidence act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the circumstances in which inferences might be drawn from secondary facts in order to establish the fact in issue.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">high court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">reasons or grounds for judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">whether appeal lies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">the constitution (63 &amp; 64 vict. c. 12), s. 73.  income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">exemptions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">income of provident, benefit or superannuation fund established for benefit of employees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">deductions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">payments to fund from &amp;which benefits, pensions or allowances are to be provided</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">whether right of beneficiary to direct manner of investment of his share renders fund inappropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 91">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1962 (cth), ss. 23 (j) (i),* 66*.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of compensation pursuant to s 298u of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) in respect of contraventions of s 298k</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of a penalty pursuant to s 298u</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of whether a penalty so ordered ought to be paid to the individuals affected by the conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the scope of declarations to be made.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2006] FCA 1302"></sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l1">WORKPLACE RELATIONS ACT 1996 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>