<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916 (20 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/916.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 917">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 917">lump sum order for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 917">whether lump sum order should be made where taxation of costs has already commenced held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 917">costs fixed in a lump sum</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">defamation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether communications reporting on the views of co-workers about the applicant's suitability for particular work were in the circumstances defamatory</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether the communications were subject to qualified privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether malice on the part of the publisher established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">claim dismissed misfeasance in public office</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">communications reporting on suitability of applicant to return to particular work location</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether communications actuated by malice or undertaken recklessly indifferent to existence of power to make them</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">claim dismissed discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">applicant complained of sex harassment by co-worker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">both applicant and co-worker relocated to different work locations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">other workers in applicant's work area reluctant to him returning there</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">claim of sex discrimination against officers of employer and employer for treating applicant as male differently from treatment which would have been given to female in same or similar circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">claim dismissed discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">inquiry into claim of sex discrimination not continued as complaint lacking in substance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">elapse of three years and nine months between complaint and decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">decision of officer to refer complaint for public inquiry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether applicant denied procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether delay constitutes denial of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1885">whether decision of officer (not sex discrimination commissioner) to refer complaint for public inquiry effective</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 284">(1) in respect of the statement published by the third respondent to an officer of the sixth respondent in or about march 1994</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 284">(a) states whether the statement was oral or in writing, and (i) if oral, identifies as best as can be done the occasion, the place and the parties present, including the name of the officer of the sixth respondent referred to, and (ii) if in writing, identifies as best as can be done the document by date, author and addressee (b) indicates separately in respect of each of the meanings which is alleged to have been conveyed to an officer of the sixth respondent (i) the words by reason of which the particular meaning is alleged to have been communicated, and (ii) the meaning alleged to have been communicated by those words (2) in respect of the statement published by the third respondent to the second respondent on or about 28 november 1994</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">competing s.237 applications to represent defendant company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">directors eventually able to deal with defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">both applications dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">liability for costs of applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">whether gross sum should be awarded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">whether indemnity costs should be awarded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 135">whether costs should be payable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 213">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 213">order for costs of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 213">beneficiary of order seeks further order for payment of a fixed sum for counsels' fees instead of assessed costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 213">discussion of power to make further order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 213">whether power should be exercised. d.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">magistrates' courts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">dismissal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">discretion to award costs to defendant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 59">magistrates (summary proceedings) act 1975 (vict.), s.97(b).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">quantification of costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">departure from federal magistrates court scale</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">consideration of factors warranting departure from the scale</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">conduct of the respondents.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">departure from default position under order 62</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 466">consideration of factors warranting costs order to be payable forthwith.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] ACTSC 133">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] ACTSC 133">summary judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] ACTSC 133">security for costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 392">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 392">order for costs in a gross sum</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 392">further order sought seven months after initial costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 392">non-compliance with case management practice note</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1259">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1259">whether it is appropriate to order payment of gross sum costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1259">additional cost for taxation likely to impose significant burden on respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1259">appropriate to order gross sum of costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 701">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 701">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 701">gross sum costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 701">fixing of gross sum.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 917">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 917">lump sum order for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 917">whether lump sum order should be made where taxation of costs has already commenced held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 917">costs fixed in a lump sum</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 466">In broad terms, what the applicant seeks is that it has its costs on an assessed basis rather than on a scale basis, principally because the scale in these circumstances would be manifestly inadequate. The matter of the manifest inadequacy of scale costs has been addressed by previous courts, see, for instance, Vivid Entertainment LLC v Digital Sinema Australia Pty Ltd (No.2), [1] Ginos Engineers Pty Ltd v Autodesk Australia Pty Ltd [2] and Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No.3). [3] It is ultimately a matter of judgment but clearly, the most significant issue to be considered in assessing whether or not those costs might more appropriately be awarded on a scale or on a taxed basis would be reflected in the complexity of the application which is prosecuted. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] ACTSC 133"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 392">The discretion conferred by O 62 r 4(2)(c) has been frequently invoked. The purpose of the rule is "to avoid the expense, delay and aggravation involved in protracted litigation arising out of taxation" : Beach Petroleum NL v Johnson (No 2) (1995) 57 FCR 119 at 120 per von Doussa J. See also: Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd [2007] FCA 2059 at [3] per Sackville J. It is not a rule, however, confined to complex litigation: Sony Entertainment (Australia) Ltd v Smith [2005] FCA 228 at [189] per Jacobson J. There is " no particular characteristic of a case which must exist before a gross sum costs order can be made ": Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916 at [23] per Mansfield J. It is a power, by way only of example, which has frequently been exercised during the course of considering an appeal in migration cases involving the refusal of protection visas: e.g. BZAS v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 449 ; SZCAJ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCA 779 ; SZLKH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 745 ; SZNSL v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 1543. The underlying premise in migration cases for exercising the power may be the appropriateness of such an order being made where a migrant appellant is frequently unrepresented (and may even fail to appear at the hearing) and where the quantum of the costs order sought by a respondent Minister is self-evidently justifiable. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCA 1259">In my view, not only it is likely that the additional costs of taxation would impose a significant burden on the respondent without any real prospects of recovering those additional costs, but also the expense, taxation and delay occasion to the respondent is likely to be disproportionate to the amount of the costs recoverable: Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916 , at [28]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 1776">8 The Rules do not specify any criteria to be followed by a Court in determining whether to make an order under O 62 r 4(2)(c). In Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916 Mansfield J at [23] observed as follows:
 There is no particular characteristic of a case which must exist before a gross sum costs order can be made: Australasian Performing Rights Association Ltd v Marlin [1999] FCA 1006. It is a power which may be exercised whenever the particular circumstances of the case warrant it: Beach Petroleum NL v Johnson (1995) 57 FCR 119 (Beach) ; Harrison v Schipp [2002] NSWCA 213 ; (2002) 54 NSWLR 738. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] FMCA 701"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2006] FCA 1668">3 The principles upon which the power under O 62 r 4(2)(c) should be exercised are relatively straightforward. They have been discussed in a number of cases: Beach Petroleum NL v Johnson (No 2) (1995) 57 FCR 119 ( Beach ); Sparnon v Apand Pty Ltd [1998] FCA 164 ; Hadid v Lenfest Communications Inc [2000] FCA 628 and Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2006] FCA 917">13 In Dunstan v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (No 3) [2006] FCA 916 (the main costs judgment) delivered at the same time as this judgment, I referred at [22]-[24] to certain of the principles relevant to deciding whether to make a gross sum order for costs. I will not repeat them.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 43 Costs</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>