<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited (ACN 102 907 184) v Bose [2006] FCA 94 (8 February 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/94.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">application for summary judgement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">o 35a, federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">respondents in default for failure to defend the proceeding with due diligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">appropriate relief in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">orders on default</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">failure to comply with court order for discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">applicant appearing entitled to the relief on the statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">court satisfied it has power to grant the relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 856">injunctive and other orders appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">judgment entered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">whether orders should be set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">no entry of appearance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">absent party represented by solicitors to whom notice was given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">non-appearance by absent party at directions hearings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">service on solicitor rather than absent party at place of business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">order not void for uncertainty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">no consideration of evidence to support case of applicants in entering judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1664">discretionary consideration.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">appeal to high court by commissioner of taxation from decision of board of review allowing objection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">no appearance for respondent taxpayer on hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">whether commissioner entitled without more to have appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1957 (no. 27 of 1936</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 69">no. 65 of 1957), s. 196 (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">sale of counterfeit clothing items</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">where respondent claimed to be unaware of counterfeit status of goods and lack of money to pay compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">whether respondent was aware of status of goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">default judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">where no defence filed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">quantum of damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">general damages, damages for loss of reputation, damages for flagrant infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">tort of passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">infringement of trademark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">contravention of the fair trading act.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 617">assessment of costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 615">judgments and orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 239">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 239">application for default judgment pursuant to order 35a r 3(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 239">withdrawal of defence by respondents without explanation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 239">conduct justifying an award of indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">notice of motion seeking judgment on default</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">order 35a, rule 3(2)(c) federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">applies where proceeding commenced by application and statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">application for judgment on default need not be supported by evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">sufficient that application is for relief sought in statement of claim and court has jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">respondent failed to attend directions hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">no notice of appearance filed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">respondent personally served with originating process, orders of first directions hearing and notice of motion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">satisfied relief in statement of claim should be granted.  trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.11" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">infringement of registered trade mark "windows"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.12" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">injunction and ancillary relief sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.13" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">injunction granted pursuant to s 126 trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.14" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">order for delivery up of all material bearing the infringing mark granted as ancillary relief and pursuant to ss 22 and 23 federal court of australia act 1976 (cth).  consumer law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.15" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">australian consumer law (qld)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.16" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">fair trading act 1999 (qld)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.17" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.18" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">injunction sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.19" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 247">injunction granted pursuant to s 98 fair trading act 1999 (qld) and s 232 australian consumer law (qld).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1413">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1413">application for default judgment pursuant to o 35a r 3(2) of the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1413">whether appropriate to grant declaratory relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1413">whether appropriate to award costs as a gross sum payable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">election for damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">calculation of damages using method of "lost profits"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">inclusion in assessment of damages of sales lost by exclusive licensee on other products whose copyright had not been infringed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">claimable head of damage so long as sufficient causation and foreseeability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 694">insufficient evidence to calculate damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 569">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 569">application for judgment on default through failure to file defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 569">whether applicant entitled to relief sought on statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 569">whether court is satisfied it has power to grant relief sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 569">power of court to order delivery up and account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">judgment on default</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">respondents' discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">whether lists complied with orders of court as a matter of substance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">whether alleged deficiencies open to argument</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1727">whether any non-compliance such as to deprive respondents of entitlement to argument on the merits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 2010">australian competition and consumer commission v monza imports pty ltd (2001) ator 41</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 2010">843; at 43, 440; fca 1455 considered australian competition and consumer commission v nw frozen foods pty ltd (1996) atpr 41</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 2010">515 at 42, 444</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 2010">42, 445 applied australian competition and consumer commission v z-tech computers pty ltd (1997) 78 fcr 197 referred to</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 727">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 727">proceedings for infringement of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 727">no appearance or defence filed by the respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 727">orders sought pursuant to o 35a of the federal court rules by reason of default</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 727">whether restraining orders and other relief should be granted</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 617">Order 13.03A Sub Rule (2) defines when a respondent is in default and that includes failing to file and serve a document required under the Rules or comply with an order of the court in the proceedings. It also includes failure to defend proceedings with due diligence. I am quite satisfied that the respondent has failed to defend the proceedings with due diligence. She has also failed to comply with the order to file a defence and for that reason I am satisfied that she is in default and that the court can proceed under Order 13.03B(2) to judgment. As Mr Feder says in his helpful submissions: "The condition under sub-rule 13.03B(2)(c)(i) of the FMR that the applicants appeared to be entitled to relief on the statement of claim does not require proof by way of evidence of the applicants' claims. Rather it requires that on the face of the statement of claim there is a claim for relief sought and that the court has jurisdiction to grant that relief. Authorities for this approach in the Federal Magistrates Court of Australia and the Federal Court of Australia under the equivalent Federal Court Rule 35A(3)(2c), where judgment has been entered pursuant to a default application without evidence supporting the applicant's claim include: (a) Arthur v Vaupotc Investments Proprietary Limited [FCA 433] of [3] per Heerey J; (b) Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Albert [2005] FCA 1311 at [6 to 7] per Jacobson J; (c) Virgin Enterprise Limited v Australian Paper and Disposables Proprietary Limited [2006] FCA 1852 per Edmonds J at [27 to 33]; (d) Luna Park Sydney Proprietary Limited v Bowes [2006] FCA 94 per Jacobson J at [19] to [22]. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCA 615">Ms Rees seeks judgment under O 35A r 3(2) of the Federal Court Rules . That rule provides that if a respondent is in default, that the Court may: 
 
 (c) if the proceeding was commenced by an application supported by a statement of claim or the Court has ordered that the proceeding continue on pleadings --- give judgment against the respondent for that relief: 
 
 
 
 
 (i) the applicant appears entitled to on the statement of claim; and 
 (ii) the Court is satisfied it has power to grant; or 
 
 
 
 
 (d) give judgment or make any other order against the respondent; 
 

 The provisions of O 35A r 3 marked, at the time of their introduction, a departure from the former requirement that evidence needed to be put before the Court before a judgment of that kind could be given: see, for example, Luna Park Sydney Pty Ltd v Bose [2006] FCA 94 at [17] - [18] per Jacobson J. However, it has been accepted in this Court by a number of judges that the effect of O 35A r 3 is to dispense with that requirement and that it will be sufficient, instead of evidence being put before the Court, that 'on the face of the statement of claim there is a claim for relief sought and that the Court has jurisdiction to grant that relief': Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 1Cellnet LLC [2005] FCA 856 at [14] per Nicholson J citing Arthur v Vaupotic Investments Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 433 at [3] per Heerey J; see also Luna Park Sydney Pty Ltd v Bose [2006] FCA 94 at [20] per Jacobson J ; Wu v Avin Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 36 at [57] per Kenny J; Australian Communications and Media Authority v Mobilegate Ltd A company incorporated in Hong Kong (No.2) [2009] FCA 887 at [19] - [20] per Logan J; Turner; in the Matter of LA Technologies Pty Ltd (in Liquidation) [2009] FCA 805 at [13] per Gordon J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2011] FCA 239">To be entitled to a default judgment pursuant to O 35A r 3(2) it is not necessary that the Court have proof of an applicant's claim, provided there is a claim for relief which the Court has jurisdiction to grant upon the face of the statement of claim: see Arthur v Vaupotic Investments Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 433 ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 1Cellnet LLC [2005] FCA 856 ; Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited (ACN 102 907 184) v Bose [2006] FCA 94. That is, default judgment may be entered in such instances with minimal formality. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2011] FCA 247">Order 35A rule 3(2)(c) applies where, as here, the proceeding was commenced by application and statement of claim. It is now well established that an application for the relief to which the rule refers does not need to be supported by evidence; Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited v Bose [2006] FCA 94 ; Humphries v Halifax Vogel Group Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 569 ; (2008) 76 IPR 144. It is sufficient that there is a claim for the relief sought on the facts stated in the statement of claim, and that the Court has jurisdiction and power to grant that relief. In this case the relief relates to claims of infringement of trademarks, of which the applicants are the registered owners, in particular, the WINDOWS trade mark is well known as relating to computer systems software and which is sold with user manuals. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 1413">I am satisfied, on the face of the statement of claim, that it is appropriate to grant some of the relief sought by the applicants. In my view the fact that the third respondent has filed a defence is not an impediment to my taking that course. The terms of O 35A r 3(2)(c) are clear that it is to the allegations in the statement of claim to which reference should be made, not any other pleading, for the purpose of satisfying the relevant pre-conditions. In any event, the third respondent's default, coupled with his apparent attitude to the defence of the proceeding as revealed by those parts of his letter I have quoted, make it sufficiently clear that his defence will only be prosecuted with such expedition as the third respondent himself considers appropriate: see, in that connection, Luna Park Sydney Pty Ltd v Bose [2006] FCA 94 at [19] . This represents an unsatisfactory state of affairs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2010] FCA 694">For the reasons I have given this Court has the power to give a judgment for damages to be assessed and hence a power to do so under these Rules. No issue was raised before me about this but it is to be noted that under O 35A --- unlike O 35 itself --- it is only necessary that the applicant appear entitled to the relief claimed in the pleading. That difference has led to the view that proof of the claim by an applicant is not necessary under the rule: Luna Park Sydney Pty Ltd v Bose [2006] FCA 94 at [20] per Jacobson J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2009] FCA 1143">It was previously the case that there was no presumption, upon default of a respondent not filing an appearance and defence, as to the correctness of an applicant's claims. In Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited v Bose [2006] FCA 94 , Jacobson J at [16]-[18] noted that position and that O 35A now provides the foundation for a finding that, in the absence of a defence and where there is a pleading by way of statement of claim, then the facts in the statement of claim are admitted. That decision was followed by Logan J in Humphries v Halifax Vogel Group Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 569 ( Humphries ) at [7]-[9]. His Honour referred to some recent authorities which have adopted a similar approach. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2008] FCA 569">7 In Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited v Bose [2006] FCA 94 , Jacobson J at paras 16 through to and including 18 remarked as follows:
 
 
 16. It was until recently well settled that there was no presumption upon default of the respondent of the correctness of the applicant's claims: see Commissioner of Taxation v Finn [1960] HCA 69 ; (1960) 103 CLR 165. 17. It was not open to the court to make an order for default judgment except on the bringing of a motion supported by evidence as to the merits of the application: see Australian Securities Commission v McLeod (1994) 54 FCR 309 per Drummond J; see also for example Grey v Mango Prepaid Calling Cards Pty Limited [2004] FCA 1664 per Nicholson J, and Zomba Production Music v Roadhouse Productions [2001] FCA 1526 ; (2001) 190 ALR 288 per Stone J. 18. However, recent authorities indicate that the introduction of Order 35A provides the foundation for a finding that in the absence of a defence where there is a pleading by way of a statement of claim then the facts in the statement of claim are admitted. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs8" from="[2006] FCA 1727">' 

In Macquarie Bank Limited v Seagle [2005] FCA 1239 ; (2005) 146 FCR 400 ( Seagle 146 FCR), Conti J accepted a submission that so long as each element of the relevant civil wrong involved is properly and discretely pleaded in the statement of claim, the requirement of subrule (3)(2)(c)(i) will be satisfied in principle. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Dataline.Net.Au Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1427 , Kiefel J reviewed the origins of O 35A. At [45] her Honour accepted that the decisions of the Court in Arthur v Vaupotic Investments Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 433 and Luna Park Sydney Pty Ltd v Bose [2006] FCA 94 , along with the decisions of 1Cellnet FCA 856 and Seagle 146 FCR confirmed that no evidence needs to be adduced under the relevant paragraph. At [47], her Honour stated:
 
 'An approach that does not deny the prospect of any additional, or different, relief being granted under O 35A is consistent with the general provisions of O 35, which permits judgment to be given regardless of whether the particular claim for relief is made. Order 35A does not itself deny the right to relief which may arise from admissions of the matters alleged in the statement of claim.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs9" from="[2006] FCA 2010">45 Arthur v Vaupotic Investments Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 433 and Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited v Bose [2006] FCA 94 confirm that the rule permits regard to be had to the face of the statement of claim in order to determine whether the relief sought is made out. Those decisions and a number of others of this Court confirm that no evidence needs to be adduced: see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v 1Cellnet LLC [2005] FCA 856 ; Macquarie Bank Ltd and Anor v Seagle [2005] FCA 1239 ; (2005) 146 FCR 400. The statement in Chanel Limited v Ayad [2005] FCA 820 at par 21, that evidence is required on a motion for default judgment, was made by reference to the decision in ASC v Macleod , which concerned the rules prior to the introduced O 35A. The decision in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Communications Network Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 988 at par 18 appears to have proceeded upon the basis that resort to O 35A was not necessary, given findings which had already been made and which were sufficient to support the orders sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs10" from="[2006] FCA 727">7 Until O 35A was introduced into the FCR in 2004, it was not open to the Court to make an order for a default judgment, except on a motion supported by evidence as to the merits of the application: Luna Park Sydney Pty Limited v Bose [2006] FCA 94 , at [17], per Jacobson J and cases cited there. However, O 35A r 3(2)(c) permits the Court to grant relief if:
 
&#8226; a respondent is in default;
 
&#8226; the applicant appears entitled to the relief 'on the statement of claim'; and
 
&#8226; the Court is satisfied that it has power to grant the relief.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>