<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933 (28 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/933.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">application for summary judgement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">o 35a, federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">respondents in default for failure to defend the proceeding with due diligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">appropriate relief in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 36">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">motion to dismiss proceeding for non-compliance with directions to provide particulars</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">history of matter and related matters asserting same alleged claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">responses not arguably compliant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">particulars essential to enable proper defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 324">application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">dismissal of proceeding for want of compliance with court's pre-trial directions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">applicable principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">types of case where order justified</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">circumstances where appellate court will interfere with primary exercise of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 520">effect of "guillotine" order which came into effect whilst proceeding stood dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">stay of proceedingsfamily law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">value of property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">expert evidencefamily law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">companies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">receivership and/or liquidation and/or winding upfamily law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">injunctions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=citing from="[2008] FamCA 296">mareva</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">application for dismissal for want of prosecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">continued non-compliance with court's directions by the appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">failure to prosecute appeal with due diligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">appeal dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 548">indemnity costs awarded.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">stay of proceeding due to outstanding costs in related proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">respondent allowed both matters to continue concurrently in two courts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">delay in enforcement of costs orders and application for stay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">final hearing imminent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">whether continuance of proceeding would be unfairly oppressive to respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">whether administration of justice would be brought into disrepute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2020">application for stay refused.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1781">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1781">proceeding dismissed for non compliance with orders and as an abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1781">leave to appeal refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">appeal from decision of the administrative appeals tribunal to refuse an application for reinstatement of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">application for reinstatement based on substantive case having 'strong merits and a good chance of success' and the appellant having not received the notice of listing for the hearing of the substantive application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">whether tribunal erred in refusing an application by the appellant for an adjournment to explain the circumstances of its non-appearance before the tribunal in light of evidence of an email indicating service of the notice of listing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">whether given reasonable opportunity to present case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2006] FCA 1406">whether wednesbury unreasonableness in the exercise of the reinstatement discretion by the tribunal member held: the appeal be dismissed. appellant not denied procedural fairness in the circumstances where the appellants' non-appearance at the hearing was so evidently a live issue that the appropriate investigations as to this issue should have been undertaken and counsel for the appellant should have been briefed on this matter. no wednesbury unreasonableness in the tribunals finding not to accept the appellants excuse for non-attendance or in the tribunal's assessment of the merits of the case.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FamCA 296">In Joachim the Full Court approved and adopted what was stated by the majority of the Full Court of the Federal Court in Lenijamar Pty Ld and Ors v AGC (Advances) Ltd [1990] FCA 520 ; (1990) 98 ALR 200 in relation to Order 10 r.7 of the Federal Court Rules . The wording of O.10 r.7 of the Federal Court Rules and O.4 r. 1A of the Family Law Rules were very similar. See also Fisher and another v Rural Adjustment &amp; Finance Corporation of Western Australia (1995) 57 FCR 1 and Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933 . In Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 903 Besanko J said at paragraph 25 that previously the power to make self executing orders was contained in O 10, r 7 of the Federal Court Rules and the power is now contained in O 35A, r 3(1). Order 35A of the Federal Court Rules commenced on 30 August 2004.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 548">18 This statement has been referred to and adopted in many subsequent cases (see, as examples only, Wu v Avin Operations Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 36 at [48] --- [50], Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933 at [16] --- [17] and Jianshe Southern Pty Ltd v Turnbull Cooktown Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 903 at [25] ). In my respectful view it is equally apposite in the present case.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 2020">In the Federal Court discrimination matter, there were extensive interlocutory proceedings which gave rise ultimately to a judgment by Tamberlin J on 28 July 2006, in which he dismissed the proceedings on the ground that "the way in which these proceedings have been conducted amounts to an abuse of process under O 20 r 2" of the Federal Court Rules . His Honour at [3] of his judgment in Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933 said: 3 Since the commencement of the proceedings in May 2005, there have been eleven directions and interlocutory hearings and repeated failures by the applicant to cooperate in bringing the matter to a hearing. The applicant has also made several applications to the Court devoid of merit or substance. ... 
His Honour identified a persistent failure by Dr Sheikholeslami to provide particulars of specific incidents upon which her claims of unlawful discrimination depended. When dismissing her application, he awarded indemnity costs to the University. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 556">1 This is an application made by the applicant for leave to file out of time an application under the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act 1986 (Cth) (the "HREOC Act"). Previous proceedings were brought in the Court which culminated in orders being made by Tamberlin J on 28 July 2006 in which his Honour dismissed the applicant's application on an interlocutory basis: see Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933. His Honour's reasons are set out in those published on that day. Those reasons are before me. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2006] FCA 1781">
 The applicant, Roya Sheikholeslami, commenced employment with the second respondent, the University of New South Wales, on 6 June 1996. On 21 October 2004, whilst still employed, she made a complaint of discrimination occurring over a period of some four years to the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission. The discrimination was alleged to have been carried out by the first respondent, Michael Brungs, an employee of the second respondent. On 20 April 2005, the complaint was terminated. On 17 May 2005, the applicant filed an application (Form 5) and claim (Form 167) under s 46PO of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act 1986 (Cth) in the Court. On 28 July 2006, Tamberlin J dismissed the applicant's claim pursuant to both O 35A r 3(1) and O 20 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules ( Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933). The applicant was ordered to pay the costs of the respondents on a solicitor/client basis. The applicant seeks leave to appeal from the dismissal of the proceeding and the order for costs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2006] FCA 1406">27 It also follows that the manner in which the litigation had been conducted by the appellant, including being taken by surprise at such a fundamental piece of evidence, was a factor which the Tribunal could reasonably take into account in finding that the appellant had treated the Tribunal with indifference (cf Lenijamar Pty Ltd v AGC (Advances) Ltd [1990] FCA 520 ; (1990) 27 FCR 388 at 396 per Wilcox and Gummow JJ and Sheikholeslami v Brungs [2006] FCA 933 per Tamberlin J at [15]-[17]). The Tribunal was, in my view, entitled to take this history into account in considering whether it was 'appropriate' to reinstate the application within the meaning of s 42A(9) AAT Act. In this respect I note comments of Professor D Pearce in his book, Administrative Appeals Tribunal , LexisNexis, Butterworths, 2003, p 122, cited by the Tribunal in its reasons for decision.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
</legistitles>
</case>