<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Owners * Strata Plan No. 23007 v Cross, in the matter of Cross [2006] FCA 900 (14 July 2006)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2006/900.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">review of registrar's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">whether order should be set aside or annulled</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">relevant factors to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">registrar's decision set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">bankrupt sequestrated on small judgment (less than $5,000 for a hospital bill)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">bankrupt unable to properly manage own affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">bankrupt believed debt covered by his medical insurance and had advocate at anglicare pursuing alternative remedy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">bankrupt owned a one third interest in a home</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2006] FMCA 44">annulment sought solely to allow trustee to claim fees and expenses around triple the original debt.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">application to set aside sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">bankrupt solvent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">recoupment of trustee's costs for administration of bankrupt's estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">whether the bankruptcy should be annulled or be set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">substantial administration of the bankrupt's estate by the trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2005] FMCA 1163">sequestration order to be set aside.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">sequestration order made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">claim that bankruptcy notice invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">federal magistrate rejected claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">bankruptcy notice failed to comply with prescribed form</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">notice invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">official trustee incurred "costs, charges and expenses" in administering bankrupt estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">whether appropriate simply to set aside sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1338">whether bankruptcy should be annulled so that official trustee can recoup costs and expenses pursuant to s 154(1)(b) and (2) of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWCA 249">practice and procedure: litigants in person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWCA 249">district court rules pt 45</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWCA 249">test of incompetence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2003] NSWCA 249">guardians ad liteus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">powers exercised by registrars of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">review by court of registrar's exercise of power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">nature of review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">exercise of discretion to order substituted service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 167">nature of appearance in bankruptcy proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">formal defect or irregularity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">amount due on judgment debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">understatement of interest due on debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">notice demanding payment of amount comprising debt and understated interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">validity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=cited from="[1988] HCA 34">bankruptcy act 1966 (cth), ss. 41(2)(a) , 306 (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 138">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 138">creditor's petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 138">whether phrase in s. 52 (2) (a) "is able to pay his debts" means "is able and willing to pay his debts"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=cited from="[1980] FCA 138">whether phrase "it may dismiss the petition" in s. 52 (2) is mandatory or discretionary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">lunacy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">insanity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">test of mental capacity for the validity of transactions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">effect of incapacity on conveyances, powers of attorney and contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">void or voidable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=cited from="[1954] HCA 17">who may elect to avoid a voidable transaction.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 204">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 204">application for declaration pursuant to o 70 r 1 rules of the supreme court 1971 (wa) that a party to the action is incapable of managing their own affairs in these proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 204">history of psychiatric condition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 204">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.0" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">agency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.1" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">powers of attorney</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.2" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">aged donor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.3" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">whether power of attorney void for want of mental capacity of donor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.4" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">general and enduring power of attorney</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.5" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">general law test of incapacity discussed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.6" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">whether general law test affected by powers of attorney act 2003</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.7" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">survey of evidence of lay and medical witnesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.8" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.9" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">challenge to capacity of donor to grant power of attorney</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.10" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">whether review procedure under powers of attorney act 2003 is only available avenue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.11" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">held not</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.12" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">whether donor must be party to any proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.13" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 804">whether donee of challenged power of attorney has standing to maintain like challenge to other powers of attorney</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.0" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 596">self-represented plaintiff with mental illness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.1" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 596">appointment of litigation guardian.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.0" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">(third respondent) file no: 12035/08 division: trial division proceeding: appeal originating court: supreme court at brisbane delivered on: 2 june 2009 delivered at: brisbane hearing date: 15 april 2009 judge: byrne sja order: appeal allowed. the decision of the guardianship and administration tribunal made on 17 september 2008 is set aside. the proceedings are remitted to the tribunal to proceed according to law.  mental health</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.1" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">guardians, committees, administrators, managers and receivers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.2" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">other matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.3" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">guardianship and administration tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.4" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">where appeal against decision of tribunal for declaration of capacity and appointment of administrator</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.5" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">whether presumption of capacity applies to subsequent tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.6" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">whether tribunal correctly interpreted provisions of the guardianship and administration act 2000  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.7" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">acts of parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.8" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.9" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">consideration of extrinsic matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.10" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">where statutory provisions ambiguous as to application of general principles in guardianship and administration act 2000</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.11" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">whether general principle 1 (presumption of capacity) applies to declarations of capacity by tribunal  s 14a(1) acts interpretation act 1954 ss 6 , 7 , 9 , 10 , 11 , 12 , 31, 130, 146(1) and general principle 1 guardianship and administration act 2000 rr 766(1)(b), 785(1) uniform civil procedure rules 1999 guardianship and administration bill 1999</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.12" type=citing from="[2009] QSC 128">explanatory notes queensland law reform commission report no. 49 "assisted and substituted decisions: decision-making by and for people with a decision-making disability" (june 1996) a. raptis &amp; sons holdings pty ltd v commissioner of stamp duties (no. 1) [1999] 1 qdr 458 nominal defendant v ravenscroft [2007] qca 435 owners of strata plan no. 23007 v cross [2006] fca 900 ; [2006] fca 900 ; (2006) 233 alr 296 white v wilson (1806) 13 ves 87 counsel: mr s j keim sc for the appellant ms j brasch for the third respondent solicitors: carne reidy herd lawyers for the appellant the public advocate for the third respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp20.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1839">the owners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp20.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1839">strata plan no. 71569 v amin [2007] fca 1839</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">validity of the appointment of an administrator to an aboriginal corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">period of one day to show cause against appointment of an administrator was not a reasonable period as expressly required by the statute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">consequent appointment of the administrator was invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">primary judge underestimated the difficulties faced by the corporation in responding to the notice and overestimated the urgency of the situation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">no denial of natural justice where the show cause notice was based only on the decision to cease funding to the corporation and not the causes for that decision and no opportunity given to respond to those causes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">whether minister had the requisite authority to approve the appointment of the administrator where approval minuted prior to authorisation of minister in question</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">whether presumptions of continuance and regularity applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp21.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 91">whether relief futile</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] WASC 204">66 It is well-established that there is a presumption that a person of full age is capable of handling their own affairs. The burden of proof rests upon the party asserting present incapacity: Masterman-Lister v Brutton &amp; Co [17]; Murphy v Doman [36]; Allregal Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carpaolo Nominees Pty Ltd [2009] WASCA 33 , [6]. Clear evidence that a person has suffered from some form of mental incapacity for a considerable period in the past is not itself determinative, although such evidence may mean that the burden of proof is more easily discharged: Masterman-Lister v Brutton &amp; Co [17]. See also the discussion of the application of the 'presumption of continuance' to the existence of mental illnesses in Owners of Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 153 FCR 398 [67] - [73]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] NSWSC 804">


 
22 The effect and consequence of the presumption were stated by Edmonds J in Owners of Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 153 FCR 398 at [66] :
 

 
 
 "It follows that the person who asserts incapacity must prove it. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] VSC 596">34 Ordinarily, the Court will determine whether a party has the requisite capacity for the purposes of Order 15 after receiving medical evidence. However, where a party's incapacity is readily apparent from his or her behaviour inside the courtroom, the Court may be able to make the determination without the assistance of medical evidence. [19]  27 The words 'in relation to the proceeding' in r 15.01 are important because they focus on the person's ability to bring or defend a particular proceeding rather than on whether the person is able to manage his or her affairs generally or in relation to some other transaction. [10] As Chadwick LJ observed in Masterman-Lister v Brutton &amp; Co: 'The test is issue specific; and, when applied to different issues, it may yield different answers. ' [11] Accordingly, the fact that a person has been involuntarily admitted to a psychiatric facility under mental health legislation is not conclusive proof of incapacity under r 15.01, but it may be relevant to an assessment of such incapacity. [12]  27 The words 'in relation to the proceeding' in r 15.01 are important because they focus on the person's ability to bring or defend a particular proceeding rather than on whether the person is able to manage his or her affairs generally or in relation to some other transaction. [10] As Chadwick LJ observed in Masterman-Lister v Brutton &amp; Co: 'The test is issue specific; and, when applied to different issues, it may yield different answers. ' [11] Accordingly, the fact that a person has been involuntarily admitted to a psychiatric facility under mental health legislation is not conclusive proof of incapacity under r 15.01, but it may be relevant to an assessment of such incapacity. [12]  30 In Owners of Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross, [15] Edmonds J identified the following factors as relevant to determining whether one of the parties in that case (who was able to be legally represented) was a 'person under disability': 
 
(a) whether the person had the ability to understand that he or she required advice in respect of the relevant legal proceeding;
 
(b) whether the person had the ability to communicate this requirement to someone who could arrange an appointment with an appropriate advisor or, alternatively, whether he or she could arrange such an appointment of his or her own accord;
 
(c) whether the person had the ability to instruct the advisor with sufficient clarity to enable him or her to understand the situation and to advise the person appropriately; and
 
(d) whether the person had the ability to make decisions and give instructions based upon, or otherwise give effect to, such advice as might be received. [16]  30 In Owners of Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross, [15] Edmonds J identified the following factors as relevant to determining whether one of the parties in that case (who was able to be legally represented) was a 'person under disability': 
 
(a) whether the person had the ability to understand that he or she required advice in respect of the relevant legal proceeding;
 
(b) whether the person had the ability to communicate this requirement to someone who could arrange an appointment with an appropriate advisor or, alternatively, whether he or she could arrange such an appointment of his or her own accord;
 
(c) whether the person had the ability to instruct the advisor with sufficient clarity to enable him or her to understand the situation and to advise the person appropriately; and
 
(d) whether the person had the ability to make decisions and give instructions based upon, or otherwise give effect to, such advice as might be received. [16]  25 There is a presumption that a person of full age is capable of managing his or her own affairs, [5] which must include the management of litigation to which he or she is a party. The person who alleges the contrary bears the onus. [6] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] QSC 128">23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 233 ALR 296 White v Wilson (1806) 13 Ves 87 COUNSEL: Mr S J Keim SC for the appellant Ms J Brasch for the third respondent SOLICITORS: Carne Reidy Herd Lawyers for the appellant The Public Advocate for the third respondent 
 GAAT Decisions 
[1] In 1998, Hisako Bucknall suffered a stroke. 23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 233 ALR 296 , 310 [67]-[68].</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 1839">11 That appears to be one available course, but I think the preferable course is to use the power under O 35 r 7(2)(a). That power was exercised by Edmonds J in Owners of Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 153 FCR 398 , although in factual circumstances which were quite different from the present ones. I am influenced in my choice of that source of power for use in the present case by the fact that the costs of the trustee have been met and that orders for costs are not otherwise sought.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCAFC 91">45 The inference that the approval by Minister Andrews continued at all times from the signing of the minute to the appointment of the Administrator is assisted by both the presumption of continuance ( Mason v Tritton (1994) 34 NSWLR 572 per Kirby P at 587---588; Owners --- Strata Plan No 23007 v Cross [2006] FCA 900 ; (2006) 153 FCR 398 at [68] ) and the presumption of regularity ( Minister for Natural Resources v NSW Aboriginal Land Council (1987) 9 NSWLR 154 per McHugh J at 164 and Clarke A-JA at 169---170; McLean Bros and Rigg Ltd v Grice [1906] HCA 1 ; (1906) 4 CLR 835). A recent example of the drawing of such an inference in a private law context is the decision of Barrett J in Gosford Christian School Ltd v Totonjian [2006] NSWSC 725 ; (2006) 201 FLR 424 at [110] . The inference is the stronger in the case of a minister of state. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 30 General powers of Courts in bankruptcy</title>
<title id="l2">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 52 Proceedings and order on creditor's petition</title>
<title id="l3">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 95 Proof in respect of distinct contracts [see Table B]</title>
<title id="l4">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 153B Annulment by Court</title>
<title id="l5">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 154 Effect of annulment</title>
<title id="l6">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 306 Formal defect not to invalidate proceedings</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 35A Powers of Registrars</title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES 1979 </title>
<title id="l10">SUPREME COURT RULES 1970 </title>
<title id="l11">Mental Health Act 1983 No 178 </title>
<title id="l12">Mental Health Act 1990 No 9 </title>
<title id="l13">Protected Estates Act 1983 No 179 </title>
<title id="l14">PROTECTED ESTATES ACT 1983 - SECT 69 Court may dissolve partnership</title>
</legistitles>
</case>