<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] FCA 1635 (30 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1635.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">disability support pension (dsp)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant suffers from profound congenital deafness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant granted dsp in 1996 when 16 years of age</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant's dsp cancelled on 7 november 2002</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant has physical impairment of 60 points under impairment tables</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant's impairment of itself insufficient to prevent her from doing any work within next 2 years</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">applicant does not have continuing inability to work</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 864">decision affirmed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1993] AATA 283">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1993] AATA 283">disability support pension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1993] AATA 283">whether applicant has at least 20% impairment under impairment tables</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1993] AATA 283">whether applicant has a "continuing inability to work".  words and phrases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1993] AATA 283">"continuing inability to work".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">purchase of business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">"assumption" by purchaser of liability of vendor for or on account of annual leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether employees to be "taken over" by purchaser</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether derivation by purchaser of income in the sum of that liability in circumstances of the case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether gain constituted income according to ordinary concepts or whether amount had been received by way of insurance or indemnity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">income tax assessment act 1936 , ss. 25, 26 (j).  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether appeal to the federal court from the administrative appeals tribunal an appeal on "question of law"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">administrative appeals tribunal act 1977, s. 44.  federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">"matter" within meaning of chapter iii of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">whether s. 44 of the administrative appeals tribunal act 1977 confers jurisdiction with respect to a "matter"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 119">the content of that matter.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">disability support pension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">applicant's dsp cancelled</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">cancellation decision affirmed by succession of decision-makers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">applicant's fresh claim for dsp granted and payment commenced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">whether tribunal had power to backdate dsp to date of original cancellation decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">whether applicant made incorrect claim for newstart allowance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">whether applicant incapacitated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">tribunal lacked power to disturb decisions of previous decision-makers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2011] AATA 230">decision under review affirmed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of an application by the secretary of the department to set aside a decision of the administrative appeals tribunal on the footing that the tribunal had applied an incorrect test for the determination of a person's "continuing inability to work" under s 94(1)(c) of the social security act 1991 (cth) as provided for by s 94(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of when an impairment is "of itself" sufficient to prevent a person from "doing any work" independently of a program of support</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of the extent to which the test takes account of the employability of the impaired person and whether the relevant market is an open labour market for impaired persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of the authorities relating to that question in the historical context of the development of the social security legislation of the commonwealth  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of questions of law going to whether the tribunal failed to identify the correct statutory question to be applied in determining a continuing inability to work for the purposes of the social security act 1991 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 360">consideration of whether findings on the part of the tribunal were open on the evidence</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] AATA 230">Mr Croker was granted DSP in March 1994. In September 2005, the Secretary decided to cancel Mr Croker's DSP but continued payments until 6 June 2006 pending review of that decision. The cancellation decision was affirmed by the SSAT and on 13 April 2007, by the Administrative Appeals Tribunal: Croker and Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] AATA 1224. Mr Croker was unsuccessful in his appeal to the Federal Court: Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] FCA 1635. Mr Croker's appeal to the Full Court of the Federal Court has been stayed until such time as he lodges security for the respondent's costs: Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (No. 2) [2008] FCA 340. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] NSWSC 942">119 In April 2007 the AAT dismissed the defendant's appeal against the SSAT's decision to revoke his disability pension. The AAT reaffirmed the decision of the SSAT ( Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] AATA 1224). While this is not relied upon as a vexatious proceeding, in October 2007 the defendant appealed to the Federal Court from the decision of the AAT, proceedings which the plaintiff does rely upon. Branson J dismissed the appeal ( Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] FCA 1635). In March 2008 Emmett J dismissed the defendant's appeal from the order of Branson J dismissing the appeal from the AAT, and stayed the proceedings until the defendant provided security for costs in the sum of $3000 ( Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 340). 

 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 360">In Croker v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] FCA 1635 , the applicant contended that the Tribunal ought not to have considered types of employment which were insufficiently intellectually challenging for him or which were of insufficient status, in his view. Branson J dismissed that contention at [27] in these terms: 
 
 I am willing for present purposes to assume (I do not so find) that the language of the definition of "work" in s 94(5) admits of some qualification of the usual broad meaning of the word "work" (but see [ Crossland ]). However, I do not accept that the Act discloses an intention that a person with tertiary qualifications is to be regarded as a person with a continuing inability to work, and thus a person entitled to taxpayer-funded DSP, just because the person's impairment prevents him or her from undertaking professional or other high status employment. A person able to do work of a character undertaken by a very large number of Australian taxpayers (ie. customer service, call-centre or light retail work) is not, in my view, a person with a continuing inability to work within the meaning of the Act. 
 

 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l3">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 94 Qualification for disability support pension</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>