<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gudjala People 2 v Native Title Registrar [2007] FCA 1167 (7 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1167.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">members of the yorta yorta aboriginal community v victoria  aboriginals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title to land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">determination of native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title rights and interests in s 223(1) native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">possessed under traditional laws acknowledged and traditional customs observed in s 223(1)(a).  aboriginals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title to land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">determination of native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">consequences of sovereignty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether traditional laws and customs observed must originate in pre-sovereignty laws and customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">effect of development of, or changes in, traditional laws and customs since sovereignty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether proof of continuous acknowledgment and observance of traditional laws and customs required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">effect of interruption to continuous acknowledgment and observance of traditional laws and customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether substantially uninterrupted acknowledgment and observance is sufficient</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether traditional law and customs need only be presently acknowledged and observed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether continuous existence of claimant society required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">effect of cessation of claimant society on acknowledgment and observance of traditional laws and customs.  aboriginals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title to land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title rights and interests</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">section 223(1)(c) native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.19" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">meaning of rights and interests recognised by the common law of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.20" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether there are common law requirements of native title.  aboriginals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.21" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title to land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.22" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">extinguishment of native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.23" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether s 223 native title act 1993 (cth) incorporates notions of extinguishment of native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.24" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">whether concepts of "abandonment" or "expiration" of native title can be applied.  aboriginals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.25" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">native title to land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.26" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.27" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.28" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 58">oral and written testimony.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">appointment of judicial officers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">abolition of one set of inferior courts and substitution of another</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">policy to appoint stipendiary magistrates of former courts as magistrates of new courts unless unfit for judicial office</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">decision not to appoint former stipendiary magistrate set aside for failure to accord natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">reconsideration of case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">change of appointment policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">applicants to be judged on merit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">whether former stipendiary magistrate entitled to reconsideration of application on basis of former or current policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 21">local courts act 1982 (n.s.w.), s. 12.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">aborigines</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">claimant application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">registration of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">criteria for registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">sufficiency of asserted factual basis for native title rights and interests claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">relationship to statutory requirements for contents of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">review of registrar's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">nature of review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">appeal against review decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">whether unduly onerous standard applied by reference to sufficiency of evidence in support of application  held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 157">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">registration of native title claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">application for review of native title registrar's decision refusing registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">whether registrar erred in making decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 574">proper construction of registrar's function under s 190c(4)(b) of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">application for review of decision of native title tribunal registrar not to accept native title claim for registration on the register of native title claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">operation of the native title amendment act 1998 and the registration test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">whether the registrar was empowered to not accept the claim for registration where claim already registered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">whether registrar was empowered to remove the claim from the register</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">whether the registrar's decision represented a sufficient basis to remove the claim from the registrar</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">where the registrar was obliged under the legislation to test the claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">where the registrar was empowered to remove the claim by necessary implication</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">where registrar under a duty to maintain the register and remove the claim administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">application for judicial review pursuant to the adjr act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">review of decision of the native title tribunal registrar not to grant extension of time to amend native title claim and to provide new materials to support claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">whether the registrar's decision amounted to a denial of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">whether the applicants had been given a "reasonable opportunity" to provide materials</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">where timeframe allowed by delegate did not unreasonable fetter or compromise the right of the applicants to a fair hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.14" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 529">where applicants allowed a reasonable opportunity to make changes and submit materials and information</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1518">32 A noteworthy and commendable feature of the submission made by the Applicant's solicitor and of the supporting affidavit evidence was their candour. It was stated in the Applicant's written submission:
 The Applicant has not yet sought to again amend the Application since the date of the registration test decision. However such a course of action has not been dismissed by the Applicant. The Applicant cannot properly consider its position in this regard until such time as there is further anthropological research undertaken in respect of the claim. The Applicant apprehended that there were two primary reasons why the claim had failed the registration test. As put in the written submission, these were submitted to be: 
 
 (a) The initial decision of Justice Dowsett in The Gudjala People # 2 v Native Title Registrar [2007] FCA 1167 was the applicable law at the time of the registration test.. The requirements for registration testing as enunciated in that decision (particularly those as apply to s 190B(5)(a) and (b)) have been softened somewhat by the recent full court decision in that matter. (b) There was a lack of material placed before the registration test delegate such that would allow her to satisfy herself as to the requirements of a factual basis to the claim as required by s 190B(5)(c). 
 
[sic] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCAFC 157">
 

81 The appellants seek the following orders:
 
 
 1. The decision of the Federal Court in Gudjala People #2 v Native Title Registrar [2007] FCA 1167 given on 7 August 2007 at Brisbane in the State of Queensland be set aside; 
 
 2. The First Respondent accept the native title claimant application QUD 147/06 for registration on the Register of Native Title Claims; 
 
 3. The First Respondent include details of the claim in the Register of Native Title Claims effective from 1 November 2006. 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 574">18 The decision of the Registrar to accept or reject an application is a purely administrative function, the decision depending upon whether or not such application satisfies the prescribed criteria ( Gudjala People #2 v Native Title Registrar [2007] FCA 1167 at [15] ). Similarly, the decision by the Registrar or his delegate that he is, or is not, satisfied of the requirement under s 190C (4)(b) is an administrative decision under the Act. As French J said in Strickland v Native Title Registrar [1999] FCA 1530 ; (1999) 168 ALR 242 at 261 in relation to the concept of "satisfaction" of the Registrar under s 190B , 
 There is scope for evaluative judgment in an expeditious administrative process carried out by people with relevant specialist experience. It is not for the Court, in reviewing the Registrar's decision, to substitute its own view of the sufficiency of the native title rights and interests for those of the Registrar unless it can be shown that the Registrar's state of satisfaction is based upon some error of principle. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 529">33 In Gudjala People #2 v Native Title Registrar [2007] FCA 1167 ( Gudjala People ), in the context of an examination of the Registrar's duty under the Act, Dowsett J commented (at [14]):
 Sub-section 190A(1) required the Delegate to consider the Application. In effect he had to decide whether to accept it for registration pursuant to s 190. Sub-section 190A(5A) provides: 
 
 Before the [NT] Registrar has decided whether or not to accept the claim for registration, he or she may notify the applicant that the application may be amended under the Federal Court Rules . </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l1">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 23F Previous non-exclusive possession act</title>
<title id="l2">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 61 Native title and compensation applications</title>
<title id="l3">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 61A Restrictions on making of certain applications</title>
<title id="l4">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 62 Information etc. in relation to certain applications</title>
<title id="l5">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 63 Reference of applications to Native Title Registrar</title>
<title id="l6">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 82 Federal Court's way of operating</title>
<title id="l7">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190 Keeping the Register</title>
<title id="l8">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190A Registrar to consider claims</title>
<title id="l9">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190B Registration: conditions about merits of the claim</title>
<title id="l10">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190C Registration: conditions about procedural and other matters</title>
<title id="l11">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 190D If the claim cannot be registered--notice of decision</title>
<title id="l12">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 223 Native title</title>
<title id="l13">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 238 Non-extinguishment principle</title>
<title id="l14">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>