<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>CPSU, The Community and Public Sector Union v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 1397 (6 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1397.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">penalty hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">admitted contraventions of transport workers award 1998</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">underpayment of wages to employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">where multiple breaches of award arose out of single course of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">relevant considerations in determining level of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">penalty determined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of conduct of dismissal of employees and refusal to employ persons at the south grafton abattoir</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of part xa, divisions 2 and 3</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">ss 298k(1)(a) and (d) and prohibited purposes of membership of an industrial association, entitlements to the benefit of orders of the airc, participation in proceedings before the airc as a party and by giving evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">the expression of dissatisfaction of working conditions in the context of an industrial association seeking better conditions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the circumstances required to be satisfied before a statutory presumption of a prohibited purpose arises for the purposes of s 298v. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the approach to be adopted in dealing with a 'no case to answer' submission and whether a respondent ought to be put to an election as a condition of making the submission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the basis upon which submission made and the relationship between the grounds advanced by the moving party and the need for an election. evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the utility of the report of an expert and the extent to which the report failed to meet the standards required by the guidelines for expert witnesses in proceedings in the federal court of australia issued by the chief justice on 19 march 2004</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the extent to which the report might be characterised as a piece of advocacy for a party. evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the principles governing the reception of tendency evidence both generally and for the purposes of s 97 of the evidence act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 828">consideration of the circumstances in which inferences might be drawn from secondary facts in order to establish the fact in issue.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">repeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">transitional provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">proceedings instituted but not completed before repeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">right accrued under repealed act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">application for redemption of weekly compensation payments made under an act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">act repealed before hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">whether right for application to be determined under repealed act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">compensation (commonwealth government employees) act 1971 (cth), s. 49</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">commonwealth employees' rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth), ss. 30 , 124 , 127 , 129</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 20">acts interpretation act 1901 (cth), s. 8(c) , (e).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 1021">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 1021">application under ss.807 and 841 of the workplace relations act 1996 for alleged contraventions of s.792</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 1021">termination for reasons that included a prohibited reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 1021">contravention established.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">contravention of workplace relations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">alteration of position of employee for prohibited reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">employee permitted to use substantial work time for union activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">employer regarded her as ineligible for duties requiring full-time availability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">whether employer's action altered employee's position</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">employer's action not part of the operative or proximate reasons for the employee's grievance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 488">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">employment law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">alleged breaches of s 792 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">whether disciplinary process imposed for a prohibited reason or reasons   employment law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">whether lawful and reasonable direction by employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">whether employee obliged to comply with direction    contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">whether breach of employment contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">summary dismissal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">distinction between breach and repudiation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 220">whether contract repudiated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1634">2. it be declared that the respondent, represented by the australian customs service, breached clause 2.2 of the australian customs service certified agreement 2004</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1634">2007 by reason of its refusal to grant leave to mr douglas mcgill for 15 november 2005. 3. it be declared that the respondent, represented by the department of education, science and training, breached clause 119 of the stay here and grow: department of education, science and training certified agreement 2002</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1634">2005 by reason of its refusal to grant annual leave to mr declan o'connell for 15 november 2005.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 1021">It is submitted that the issue is whether Sika, in terminating Mr Vong's employment (as an individual) did so for reasons that included a prohibited reason: McIlwain v Ramsey Food Packaging [2006] FCA 828 ; (2006) 154 IR 111 at [355] referred to with approval in CPSU v Commonwealth [2007] FCA 1397 ; (2007) 241 ALR 151 at [113] per Branson J. Application under s.793(1)(j) 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FMCA 488">The applicants submitted that Ms Backhous had suffered relevant prejudice because she "lost the opportunity to have her eligibility for the solution broker position considered according to merits based criteria" , as a result of "being excluded from any merit based selection process purely by reference to her representational activities". They argued that this was comparable to the prejudice to employees identified in Community &amp; Public Sector Union v Commonwealth [2007] FCA 1397 ; (2007) 163 FCR 481. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 220">This proposition, too, was concerned with the overall effect of the sections and not with the areas of operation of the individual paragraphs of s 298K, the predecessor of s 793(1). Similar comments apply to the extract from the judgment of Wilcox J in BHP Steel to which his Honour referred in Greater Dandenong . In Finance Sector Union of Australia v Australian &amp; New Zealand Banking Group Limited (2002) 114 IR 352 , Wilcox J applied the decision in Bowling as I have explained it. See that decision at [173] and [187]. See also the decision of Branson J in The Community and Public Sector Union v The Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 1397 at [114] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 1634">1 On 6 September 2007 I published reasons for judgment in this matter: CPSU, the Community and Public Sector Union v Commonwealth of Australia [2007] FCA 1397. I concluded that the circulation of certain memoranda of advice by the Department of Employment and Workplace Relation ('the DEWR Advice') resulted in contravention by the Commonwealth of s 298K(1) of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) ('the WR Act'). I also concluded that by denying the second and fifth applicants approval to access leave on 15 November 2005 because they proposed to attend the Day of Protest organised to demonstrate opposition to proposed amendments to the WR Act, the Commonwealth breached two industrial instruments, namely the Australian Customs Service Certified Agreement 2004-2007 ('the ACS Agreement') and the Stay Here and Grow --- DEST Certified Agreement 2002-2005 ('the DEST Agreement').</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l1">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 - SECT 8 Effect of repeal</title>
<title id="l2">CUSTOMS ADMINISTRATION ACT 1985 </title>
<title id="l3">CUSTOMS ADMINISTRATION ACT 1985 - SECT 15 Staff</title>
<title id="l4">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l5">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 - SECT 4 This Act binds the Crown</title>
<title id="l6">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 - SECT 7 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l7">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 - SECT 10 APS Values</title>
<title id="l8">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 - SECT 20 Employer powers etc. of Agency Head</title>
<title id="l9">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 - SECT 22 Engagement of APS employees</title>
<title id="l10">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 </title>
<title id="l11">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 - SECT 4A Statutory Agency etc. for purposes of Public Service Act</title>
<title id="l12">WORKPLACE RELATIONS AMENDMENT (WORK CHOICES) ACT 2005 </title>
<title id="l13">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l14">WORKPLACE RELATIONS REGULATIONS 2006 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>