<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>ACCC v Kyloe Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1522 (18 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1522.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">respondent administrator of .au domain name space</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">contract for accreditation of registrar (applicant) in .au domain name space</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">scope of respondent's right to request information in relation the "registrar's business"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">does right extend to information in relation to .au domain space only or does it extend to the registrar's generic top level domain space business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">threat to suspend accreditation for failure to provide information in relation to generic top level domain space business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">appropriate use of respondent's constitution and other governing documents in construing the contract trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">assertion that request for information pursuant to right under contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">allegation that no right existed under contract therefore assertion was misleading or deceptive</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">allegation that threat to suspend accreditation for failing to provide information was misleading and deceptive as no right to request information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">allegation that the request for information and threat to suspend accreditation was unconscionable  franchising code of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">is the contract a "franchise agreement"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">do the obligations imposed on the registrar amount to a "system or marketing plan"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 808">does suspension of accreditation equate to termination of the contract under regulation 21</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">application for relief under s 87 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) for misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where applicants entered into agreements with second to fifth respondents for the sale of portable accommodation units</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where fifth respondent was a natural person and second, third and fourth respondents were corporations associated with him</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where fifth respondent made representations to first applicant that prototype portable accommodation unit was under construction in china  held: application allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">representations as to prototype materially contributed to applicants entering into agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the applicants' entry into the agreements was sufficient to establish that they suffered loss or damage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the fifth respondent was liable as being "knowingly concerned" in the contravention under s 75b(1) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">application for relief under s 87 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) for breach of s 51ad</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where applicants entered into agreements with second to fifth respondents for the sale of portable accommodation units</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where no disclosure documents provided as required if the agreements were a franchise agreement under the franchising code of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether the agreements or one or more of them was a franchise agreement or agreement to enter into franchise agreement under franchising code of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether agreement granted the right to carry on the business of offering, supplying or distributing goods or services under a system or marketing plan substantially determined, controlled or suggested by the franchisor or an associate of the franchisor within clause 4(1)(b) of the definition of franchise agreement  held: application allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">agreements provided for matters such as a centralised bookkeeping and recordkeeping computer operation, the reservation to the franchisor of the right to screen and approve promotions, the prohibition of repackaging of products, suggested retail prices by the franchisor, a comprehensive advertising and promotional program by the franchisor, the division of a state into marketing areas, the establishment of sales quotas and the restriction on the sale of products without the franchisor's consent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the fifth respondent was not liable as being "knowingly concerned" in the contravention under s 75b(1) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">application for relief under s 159 of the fair trading act 1999 (vic) for misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where applicants entered into agreements with second to fifth respondents for the sale of portable accommodation units</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where sixth respondent was a firm of solicitors and had prepared the relevant agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where the agreements or one or more of them had been held to be a franchise agreement and the disclosure obligations under the franchising code of conduct had not been complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether the sixth respondent had engaged in misleading or deceptive conduct by failing to advise the applicants that the franchising code applied.  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.20" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the applicants did not have a reasonable expectation that the sixth respondent would advise them on whether the franchising code applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.21" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the sixth respondent owed a duty of confidence to the second to fifth respondents and the failure to disclose was not deliberate.  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.22" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">application for relief under s 87 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) for breach of s 51ad</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.23" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where applicants entered into agreements with second to fifth respondents for the sale of portable accommodation units</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.24" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where the agreements or one or more of them had been held to be a franchise agreement and the disclosure obligations under the franchising code of conduct had not been complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.25" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether the sixth respondent was "knowingly concerned" in the contravention of s 51ad under s 75b(1) because they drafted the agreements.  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.26" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the sixth respondent did not know all essential matters that made up the contravention because they did not know that the franchising code of conduct applied to the agreements.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.27" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">claim for breach of retainer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.28" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where the second to fifth respondents had retained the sixth respondent to draft agreements relating to the sale of portable accommodation units</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.29" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where the agreements or one or more of them had been held to be franchise agreements and the disclosure obligations under the franchising code of conduct had not been complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.30" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether the sixth respondent had adequately advised the second to fifth respondents as to franchising code of conduct  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.31" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">uncontradicted evidence that the sixth respondent had adequately advised the second to fifth respondents.  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.32" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">application for relief under s 87 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) for breach of s 51ad</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.33" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">where the agreements or one or more of them had been held to be franchise agreements and the disclosure obligations under the franchising code of conduct had not been complied with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.34" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">whether the second to fifth respondents could claim a contribution or indemnity from the sixth respondent by reason of s 75b(1) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.35" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">s 75b(1) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) does not enable the court to make orders for contribution or indemnity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.36" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 725">the sixth respondent was not knowingly involved in the contravention of s 51ad for the purpose of s 75b(1) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">sale and purchase of business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">entry into licence agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">alleged franchise agreement.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">admission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">whether admission can be withdrawn</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">relevant principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 291">factors for consideration.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">sale and purchase of business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">entry into licence agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">alleged franchise agreement.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 255">application to strike out statement of claim.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] VCC 1762"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 725">Under the RA, clause 13(1)(a) provides that T2W must comply with the policies and procedures as required by T2SA from time to time. As I understood Madgwicks' submission, I would not, for example, interpret these clauses by having regard to what was done under them after the agreements had been entered into. Madgwicks referred to certain observations made by Tracey J in ACCC v Kyloe Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1522 ; [2007] ATPR 42-194 (" Kyloe ") at 48,224 [56]. In Kyloe , Tracey J said that it was not relevant to the question of whether there was a franchise agreement to consider whether in fact certain contractual provisions had been enforced. Tracey J said (at 48,224 [56]) that that was not relevant because: 
 
 "The judgment as to whether a particular proposed agreement is a franchise agreement falls to be made before it becomes operative.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 291">The evidence in support of the withdrawal of the admission is contained in the affidavit of the respondents' solicitor Patrick David Whight sworn on 29 March 2009. [34] Mr Whight's Affidavit: says he has taken a statement from the second respondent, Mr Ferguson, in which the second respondent will swear that he sought to set up a buying group and not a franchise under the relevant licence arrangements; [35] argues [36] that the Federal Court judgment in ACCC v Kyloe [37] requires a system or business plan imposed by the franchisor, and the assessment of whether there is a system or business plan imposed by the franchisor is to be made at a point in time before the relevant agreement becomes operative and by reference to the terms of the proposed agreement; [38] that the respondents would be prejudiced because: they would not be able to articulate their true case at hearing and that the case would be decided on an artificial and erroneous basis because: as a matter of fact it would not reflect Mr Ferguson's intentions; and 
 B as a matter of law it is strongly arguable that a buying group was established and that the criteria in clause 4 of the Franchising Code Regulations for the establishment of a franchise agreement has not been met; [39] 
 the judgment in Kyloe was delivered after the admission first appeared in the respondents defence in October 2006; [40] there was no material, analysis or advice on file which indicated that previous solicitors had turned their mind to the question of whether there was a franchise agreement, and it did not appear that any statement had been taken from Mr Ferguson or for the respondents; [41] the further amended statement of claim does not set out an allegation of a business plan or system and nor did the original pleading, and therefore the issues does not appear to have been fairly made on the pleadings and the admission appears to have been made inadvertently; [42] that the applicant would not be prejudiced because: no further or additional evidence needs to be adduced as the relevant licence agreement is annexed to affidavits filed on behalf of the applicant; the applicant has not changed its position in reliance on the admission; there is no potential for any or any significant increase in pre-trial activity or cost; whether the licence is a franchise agreement is a matter of construction of the licence agreement by reference to the Franchising Code Regulations ; [43] it would be fair and equitable to allow the withdrawal of the admission at this stage because the applicant was given leave to file a further amended statement of claim by 17 October 2008, some 11 days before the hearing then scheduled to commence on 28 October 2008, and in fact only filed 7 days before hearing on 21 October 2008; [44] and a fair hearing and resolution of the true controversy can only occur if the respondents are allowed to withdraw the admission. [45] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FMCA 255">The respondents say that paras. 41-68 do not contain material facts supporting the plea in para. 49 that the agreement to purchase the Midland business and the exclusive licences are franchise agreements, and in particular that there is no system or marketing plan as required under clause 4 of the Franchising Code of Conduct. [24] </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES (INDUSTRY CODES -- FRANCHISING) REGULATIONS 1998 </title>
<title id="l2">TRADE PRACTICES ACT 1975 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>