<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 (7 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1922.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">admissibility of opinion evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">not admissible unless opinion based on specialised knowledge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">whether rule excluding opinion evidence as to matter of common knowledge is applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">operation of s 80 evidence act 1995 (cth) ('the act')</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">requirement to consider probative value of opinion evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">whether evidence might cause or result in undue waste of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">discretion to exclude evidence under s 135 the acttrade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">competitors in retail chocolate market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">use of colour purple</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">principles relating to passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">whether exclusive reputation required under part v trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 70">whether use of colour purple likely to mislead or deceive consumers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">artistic work</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">drawing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">whether a composite photographic and written work is a drawing.misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">whether "memento" is a descriptive word</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">whether applicant had a reputation in the name "memento" and in the layout of its packaging</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">whether layout of respondents' packaging deceptively similar to applicant's packaging</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 457">whether applicant's loss caused by respondents' layout being likely to mislead or deceive.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">i &amp; l securities pty ltd v htw valuers (brisbane) pty ltd  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">misleading or deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">enforcement and remedies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">loan transaction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">mortgage over land</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">misleading and deceptive valuation of land by valuer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">failure by lender to make reasonable inquiries as to borrower's capacity to meet interest payments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">default on loan by borrower</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">proceeds of sale by mortgagee insufficient to meet borrower's obligation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">liability of valuer for loss and damage suffered by lender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">causal connection between contravention of trade practices act 1974 (cth) and loss and damage suffered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2002] HCA 41">whether damages awarded under s 82 of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) to be reduced for lender's failure to take reasonable care to protect its own interests.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">copyright and designs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether copyright subsists in a drawing of a single letter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether copyright can subsist in works protected under the trade marks act 1955</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether there is copyright in a computer printout of a written work, where the original was created on a floppy disk</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether s.77 of the copyright act 1968 can apply to photographs in a book</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether importation without licence.  judgments and orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">case part-heard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 617">whether interlocutory injunction can be given where a defence yet to be considered.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">original artistic work</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">t-shirt with design comprising words, numerals and logo arranged in a distinctive manner to suggest usa college sporting team</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">also an associated "swing tag"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">whether the designs were drawings and therefore artistic works</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">whether they were literary works because of presence of words and numerals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">distinction between literary works and artistic works</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">copying admitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">whether respondent had taken only underlying idea rather than expression</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">idea/expression dichotomy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">layout giving particular "look and feel" as artistic element</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 197">whether respondent had taken a substantial part of applicant's work by taking layout giving rise to the look and feel.held: (1) both t-shirt and swing tag were drawings and therefore artistic works, not literary works; (2) by taking layout giving rise to look and feel, respondent had taken original artistic element, and therefore a substantial part of the artistic work.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">breach of confidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">when confidentiality provision is a reasonable restraint of trade</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">factual and legal causation  copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">distinction between ideas and expression</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">causal connection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">infringement based on indirect access</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">whether declaration of unjustified threat of infringement may be had as of right equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">confidential information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">level of novelty or ingenuity required for information to be confidential</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">circumstances in which an equitable obligation of confidence is attracted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">whether detriment to the confiding party is an element of the cause of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">whether design for truck trailer load restraint system was confidential</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.13" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 803">unauthorised oral disclosure of the design to competitor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 2">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 2">appeal against dismissal by federal magistrate of copyright and trade practices claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 2">appellant rejected calderbank offer prior to trial in federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 2">appellant successful on trade practices claims on appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 2">appellant's recovery less favourable than respondents' offer</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCAFC 197">50 We would adopt the following extract from [12] of the primary Judge's reasons:
 [There is] a body of case law, which establishes that (1) whether a work will be recognized as an artistic work such as a drawing is highly fact-specific, such that no bright-line rule can be drawn; and (2) the important principle in deciding whether the work is a "drawing" is whether the work at issue can be said to have a visual rather than "semiotic" function: Miller &amp; Lang, Limited v Polak [1908] 1 Ch 433 (concluding that decorative wording and designs on Christmas cards were drawings for the purpose of the Fine Arts Copyright Act 1862 (UK); Roland Corporation &amp; Anor v Lorenzo &amp; Sons Pty Ltd [1991] FCA 617 ; (1991) 33 FCR 111 (holding that two logos consisting of a single letter each, "R" and "B," designed in a certain way were eligible for copyright protection as they were drawn with care and to obtain an effect); Anacon Corporation Ltd v Environmental Research Technology [1994] FSR 659 , at 662 (suggesting that a circuit diagram depicting how components were to be connected together could be an artistic work because it is "a thing to be looked at in some manner or other [and] is to be looked at in itself"); Lott v JBW &amp; Friends Pty Ltd (2000) 76 SASR 105 (finding that a "graphic bar" consisting of four words in a woodcut design or font that was selected from a computer program was a drawing within the meaning of the Act because it was not so simple that the time and effort in designing the graphic design could be ignored); Australian Chinese Newspapers Pty Ltd v Melbourne Chinese Press Ltd (2003) 58 IPR 1 at [107] (holding that a calligraphic rendering of a Chinese character used in a newspaper masthead was capable of constituting a "painting" under the Act because Chinese calligraphy is a visual art and played "an important cultural and aesthetic role in Chinese life of ancient origin"); Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 ; (2007) 74 IPR 484 (holding that a layout for a box label comprising a photograph and several short lines of explanatory text and numbers was not capable of constituting an artistic work).  14 Her Honour referred to the definition of "drawing" found in the Act. She described the Designs as "arrangements of text with graphical elements in a particular pattern; not a representation of an object by a pictorial line" (at [11]). She also referred to the discussion of the term "drawing" by Heerey J in Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 ; (2007) 164 FCR 369 ( Woodtree ) at [25], [27] and [28]. In Woodtree , Heerey J held that a layout for a box label comprising a photograph and several short lines of explanatory text and numbers was not capable of constituting an artistic work.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 803">124 An "artistic work" includes a "drawing ... whether [the drawing] is of artistic quality or not": s 10(1) of the Act . Each of the Krueger Sketch and the Krueger Drawings falls within the inclusive definition of a drawing, as each "is a two-dimensional work in which shapes and images are depicted by lines, often without colouring" ( Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 ; (2008) 74 IPR 484 , at [25]), performing a visual rather than "semiotic" function: Anacon Corporation Ltd v Environmental Research Technology Ltd [1994] FSR 659 at 662. The Krueger Sketch and the Krueger Drawings are, therefore, artistic works. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 447">12 First, Woodtree , cannot be studied in isolation; it is part of a body of case law, which establishes that (1) whether a work will be recognized as an artistic work such as a drawing is highly fact-specific, such that no bright-line rule can be drawn; and (2) the important principle in deciding whether the work is a "drawing" is whether the work at issue can be said to have a visual rather than "semiotic" function: Miller &amp; Lang, Limited v Polak [1908] 1 Ch 433 (concluding that decorative wording and designs on Christmas cards were drawings for the purpose of the Fine Arts Copyright Act 1862 (UK)); Roland Corporation &amp; Anor v Lorenzo &amp; Sons Pty Ltd [1991] FCA 617 ; (1991) 33 FCR 111 (holding that two logos consisting of a single letter each, "R" and "B," designed in a certain way were eligible for copyright protection as they were drawn with care and to obtain an effect); Anacon Corporation Ltd v Environmental Research Technology [1994] FSR 659 , at 662 (suggesting that a circuit diagram depicting how components were to be connected together could be an artistic work because it is "a thing to be looked at in some manner or other [and] is to be looked at in itself"); Lott v JBW &amp; Friends Pty Ltd (2000) 76 SASR 105 (finding that a "graphic bar" consisting of four words in a woodcut design or font that was selected from a computer program was a drawing within the meaning of the Act because it was not so simple that the time and effort in designing the graphic design could be ignored); Australian Chinese Newspapers Pty Ltd v Melbourne Chinese Press Ltd [2003] FCA 878 ; (2003) 58 IPR 1 at [107] (holding that a calligraphic rendering of a Chinese character used in a newspaper masthead was capable of constituting a "painting" under the Act because Chinese calligraphy is a visual art and played "an important cultural and aesthetic role in Chinese life of ancient origin"); Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 ; (2007) 74 IPR 484 (holding that a layout for a box label comprising a photograph and several short lines of explanatory text and numbers was not capable of constituting an artistic work). 9 In answering the first question, the starting point must be the definition of "drawing" found in the Act . As Cotton On correctly notes, that term is defined inclusively to include "a diagram, map, chart, or plan" (s 10(1) of the Act ). But while this definition is helpful in fleshing out what might otherwise not be considered as within the "core meaning" of drawing, it does not directly suggest that core meaning. In Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922 ; (2007) 74 IPR 484 , Heerey J accepted (at [25]) the definition of drawing given by Professor Ricketson in his treatise on copyright: namely that a drawing "is a two-dimensional work in which shapes and images are depicted by lines, often without colouring. " His Honour then went on to say (at [27]) that "the essence of a drawing remains the concept of a representation of some object by a pictorial line. "</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 2">1 In the substantive judgment on the appeal from the Federal Magistrates Court ( Woodtree Pty Ltd v Zheng [2007] FCA 1922) I upheld the appellant's appeal insofar as it was based on its claims under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) but rejected its claims for copyright infringement. I assessed damages at $3684.20. The questions of interest under s 51A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) and costs were adjourned. The parties have now filed written submissions.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 </title>
<title id="l1">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 10 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 51A Interest up to judgment</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 - SECT 3 Objects</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES ACT 1999 - SECT 42 Federal Magistrates Court to operate informally</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>