<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Meadow Springs Fairway Resort Ltd (In Liq) (ACN 084 358 592) v Balanced Securities Ltd (ACN 083 514 685) [2007] FCA 1443 (13 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1443.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">insolvency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">liquidator seeking directions from court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">jurisdiction and power of court to finally determine creditors' competing claims   trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">interest of creditors in mortgage investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">fiduciary obligation of investment companies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">whether tracing possible</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">intermingling of funds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">whether declarations of trust effective</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1031">priority of investors over unsecured creditors  hearing  melbourne, 6-10 december 1993</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2011] WASC 122">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2011] WASC 122">costs on discontinuing application under s511(1) corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2011] WASC 122">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">directions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">court appointed liquidator's application for directions under s 479(3) of the corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">jurisdiction of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">whether the court is entitled to give directions where the questions relate to disputed claims against a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">whether the court in its discretion should give directions where the questions relate to disputed claims against a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">questions going to issue whether company in liquidation entitled to indemnify itself out of trust assets that it holds on trust for unit trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">relevance of adversarial nature of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">finding that court has jurisdiction and should give directions sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">limitation on findings to those necessary to give a direction on whether liquidator justified in administering the winding up on basis that company executed guarantee at trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">application granted and directions given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">s 479(3) of the corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">judge : robson j where held : melbourne date of hearing : 15 june and 6 august 2009 date of judgment : 17 august 2009 case may be cited as : re mento developments (aust) pty ltd medium neutral citation : [2009] vsc 343 amended 18 august 2009</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">directions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">court appointed liquidator's application for directions under s 479(3) of the corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">jurisdiction of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">whether the court is entitled to give directions where the questions relate to disputed claims against a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">whether the court in its discretion should give directions where the questions relate to disputed claims against a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">questions going to issue whether company in liquidation entitled to indemnify itself out of trust assets that it holds on trust for unit trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.20" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">relevance of adversarial nature of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.21" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">finding that court has jurisdiction and should give directions sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.22" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">limitation on findings to those necessary to give a direction on whether liquidator justified in administering the winding up on basis that company executed guarantee at trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.23" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">application granted and directions given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.24" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">s 479(3) of the corporations act 2001   contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.25" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">guarantee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.26" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.27" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">whether executed personally or in capacity as trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.28" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.29" type=citing from="[2009] VSC 343">admissibility of extrinsic evidence to establish capacity</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] WASC 122">13 The liquidator submitted that:
 
(a) The conduct of the parties and the reasons for the discontinuance of an action bear heavily on the exercise of the court's discretion to award costs; see O'Neill v Mann [2000] FCA 1680 and McClure v Mayor and Councillors of the City of Stirling (No 3) [2009] WASC 247. (b) There was authority for the proposition that s 511 of the Act could be used to determine the substantive rights of a purported secured creditor provided that the creditor was joined as a defendant to the application. Consequently, the liquidator had acted reasonably in commencing the proceedings: see Re Evers Motor Company Ltd (1962) QWN 6 ; Meadow Springs Fairway Resort Pty Ltd (in liq) v Balanced Securities Ltd [2007] FCA 1443 ; 25 ACLC 1433. (c) Trifield had refused to concede that there was any uncertainty about the effect of the Deed of Rectification and had adopted an approach that was not consistent with the issues raised by the liquidator being resolved in a cost effective and efficient manner. (d) The liquidator was 'given cause to re-evaluate the benefit of the proceedings to the creditors of Citystyle' given Trifield's position regarding the s 511 procedure, the costs involved in resolving a dispute regarding the court's jurisdiction and the likely ongoing disputes over the originating process adopted by the liquidator and the relative expense and complexity of the liquidator commencing proceedings by way of a writ of summons seeking declarations. (e) The liquidator did not unreasonably delay in deciding to discontinue his application. (f) The proceedings were commenced for the benefit of the creditors of Citystyle and were only discontinued because of the uncertainty over the court's jurisdiction to effectively determine the questions raised by the liquidator.
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 1323">The receivers objected to the mandate issue being determined on an interlocutory basis. As a result, on 31 August 2009, the receivers made application to the Supreme Court of Western Australia (COR 173 of 2009) (the WA Directions Proceedings ) for, inter alia, directions as to whether they should retire or whether they are entitled to remain as receivers. As the plaintiffs in these proceedings submitted, in the WA Directions Proceedings the receivers seek directions. As a result, those proceedings raise questions about the power of the Court to make orders binding upon, or affecting the rights of, third parties: see Editions Tom Thompson Pty Limited v Pilley (1997) 77 FCR 141 at 147 and 150 per Lindgren J ( Editions Tom ); Deputy Commissioner of Taxation v Best &amp; Less (Wollongong) Pty Ltd (Rec and Mgr Apptd) [1992] FCA 140 ; (1992) 7 ACSR 245 at 246; Re BG Nathan &amp; Co Pty Limited (In Liquidation) (1991) 24 NSWLR 674 ; Re Media World Communications Ltd (Admin Apptd) v Naidoo [2005] FCA 51 ; (2005) 216 ALR 105 at [5] ; Re Lofthouse, in the matter of Riverside Nursing Care Pty Ltd (subject to deed of company arrangement) [2004] FCA 93 at [2] ; cf (in relation to ss 479(2) and 511 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Corporations Act )) Australian Securities Commission v Melbourne Asset Management Nominees Pty Ltd (Receiver and Manager Appointed) [1994] FCA 1031 ; (1994) 49 FCR 334 ; Meadow Springs Fairway Resort Ltd (In Liq) (ACN 084 358 592) v Balanced Securities Ltd (ACN 083 514 685) [2007] FCA 1443. Each plaintiff in these proceedings is now joined as a defendant in the WA Directions Proceedings. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] VSC 343">31 At the hearing, Wixart appeared and made its attitude known. Nevertheless, the liquidator maintained it was appropriate to give the directions sought, although the liquidator also repeated his submission that there is flexibility to convert the proceedings for directions into adversarial proceedings, relying on the observations of French J in Meadow Springs Fairway Resort Ltd. [26] Although invited to do so by counsel for Wixart, the liquidator requests that the application for directions be heard without amendment.  30 The liquidator submits that in any event, there is sufficient flexibility in the procedures of the Court to convert an application for directions into proceedings for the determination of substantive rights: Meadow Springs Fairway Resort Ltd (in liquidation) v Balanced Securities Ltd. [25] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 1836">14 In a number of decisions, courts have recognised that one purpose of invoking the procedure under s 479(3) and its analogues is to give the liquidator guidance on matters of law or principle and to protect him or her against accusations of acting unreasonably or improperly: cf: Sanderson v Classic Car Insurances Pty Ltd (1985) 10 ACLR 115 at 117; Onefone Australia Pty Ltd v One.Tel Ltd [2007] NSWSC 112 at [12] ; Meadow Springs Fairways Resort Ltd (In Liq) v Balanced Securities Ltd [2007] FCA 1443 at [45] - [49] per French J.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 471B Stay of proceedings and suspension of enforcement process</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 479 Exercise and control of liquidator's powers</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 511 Application to Court to have questions determined or powers exercised</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 563B Interest on debts and claims from relevant date to date of payment</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 601FC Duties of responsible entity</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1337B Jurisdiction of Federal Court and State and Territory Supreme Courts</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 23 Making of orders and issue of writs</title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l10">STAMP ACT 1921 </title>
<title id="l11">STAMP ACT 1921 - SECT 26 </title>
<title id="l12">TRANSFER OF LAND ACT 1893 </title>
<title id="l13">TRANSFER OF LAND ACT 1893 - SECT 110 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>