<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Gardiner v Repatriation Commission [2007] FCA 1290 (21 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1290.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 111">veterans' entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 111">whether the tribunal engaged in fact-finding at the stage of forming an opinion on whether the material raised a reasonable hypothesis connecting the injury, disease or death with circumstances of service.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">repatriation pension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">incapacity arising from war-caused injury or disease</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">connexion between incapacity and war service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">commission required to find incapacity war-caused unless satisfied beyond reasonable doubt that no sufficient ground for so finding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">commission required to be so satisfied if of opinion that material does not raise reasonable hypothesis connecting incapacity with service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 51">veterans' entitlements act 1986 (cth), s. 120.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">attempt to obtain property by deception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">service of statement of claim in action for damages for negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">indictment alleging that statement contained false assertions and that service constituted attempt to obtain property by deception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">immunity in respect of words used in judicial proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">validity of indictment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 48">crimes act 1900 (nsw), ss. 178ba(1), 344a (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">veterans' entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">pension claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">death of veteran from cancer of unknown aetiology</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">necessity for "reasonable hypothesis" linking death to war service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">what constitutes a reasonable hypothesis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">relevance of evidence of quantum of exposure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[1987] FCA 242">methodology of respondent's expert witness in commenting upon hypothesis advanced on behalf of applicant.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">repatriation pension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">incapacity arising out of or attributable to war service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">connexion between physical condition and war service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">satisfaction beyond reasonable doubt that grounds insufficient to grant claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">repatriation act 1920 (cth), ss. 24aa, 47, 101, 107vzzb</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 10">administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth), ss. 25 , 43 , 44 (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">defence and war</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">veterans</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">general provisions regarding entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">reasonable hypothesis test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">deledio steps</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">whether tribunal engaged in impermissible fact finding in application of s 120(3) of veterans' entitlements act 1986 (cth)  defence and war</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">veterans</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">general provisions regarding entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">reasonable hypothesis test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">deledio steps</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 521">whether tribunal used correct test in application of s 120(1) of veterans' entitlements act 1986 (cth)</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 521">28 The respondent submits that the applicant's notice of appeal raises no question of law; a finding as to whether a reasonable hypothesis has not been raised is a question of fact: Gardiner v Repatriation Commission [2007] FCA 1290. Further, the respondent submits that the applicant's challenge to the Tribunal's finding that it was satisfied beyond a reasonable doubt that the veteran's death was not war-caused (the alternative finding, and fourth Deledio step) is an attempt to challenge a question of fact. 29 If the Court finds that there is a "question of law" to be answered, the respondent contends that the Tribunal's decision was not marred by error. The question whether a reasonable hypothesis is raised is to be determined on consideration of the whole of the material before the decision-maker, as held by the High Court in Repatriation Commission v Owens (1996) 70 ALJR 904 at 904. According to the respondent, it is "well accepted" that a reasonable hypothesis requires more than a possibility, not fanciful or unreal, consistent with the known facts. The respondent relies on a line of authority to support the proposition that there must be a hypothesis pointed to by the facts, even though not proved upon the balance of probabilities: East v Repatriation Commission [1987] FCA 242 ; (1987) 16 FCR 517 at 532-3, Bull v Repatriation Commission [2001] FCA 1832 ; (2001) 34 AAR 326 at 330 and Gardiner [2007] FCA 1290.  35 It is settled that the decision-maker is not to engage in fact finding during the first three Deledio steps (ie the application of s 120(3) as affected by s 120A): Deledio 83 FCR at 97; Bull 188 ALR at 761 . It is only during the fourth Deledio step (ie the application of s 120(1)) that actual fact finding is permissible. However, the determination of whether a reasonable hypothesis has been raised by the whole of the material before the decision-maker is itself a question of a factual nature: Bey 79 FCR 373 and Gardiner [2007] FCA 1290 , and the first three Deledio steps are concerned with this very determination. This requires the decision-maker to determine a question of a factual nature, without engaging in formal or ultimate fact-finding. Such a tension makes the dividing line referred to by Allsop J above all the more difficult to discern. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 </title>
<title id="l1">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 - SECT 5C Eligibility related definitions</title>
<title id="l2">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 - SECT 6A Operational service--world wars</title>
<title id="l3">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 - SECT 120 Standard of proof</title>
<title id="l4">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 - SECT 120A Reasonableness of hypothesis to be assessed by reference to Statement of Principles</title>
<title id="l5">VETERANS' ENTITLEMENTS ACT 1986 - SECT 196B Functions of Authority</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>