<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZHYP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 (23 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/183.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">circumstances in which a later full court can depart from an earlier full court decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">determining ratio decidendi</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">application of minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v al shamry (2001) 110 fcr 27  migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">the application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">meaning of 'application', 'information', and 'reason, or part of the reason' in s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">application for review of rrt decision affirming decision of a delegate of the minister refusing to grant a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">repeat application to the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">no jurisdiction to review a decision twice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 257">abuse of process.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2010">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2010">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 2010">no jurisdictional error.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1725">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1725">consideration of an appeal from the federal magistrates court raising contentions that the refugee review tribunal failed to comply with obligations arising under s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth) and that the tribunal failed to properly consider the contentions of the appellant in conducting a review of a decision of the minister's delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">chinese applicant claiming persecution for falun gong participation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">disbelieved by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">tribunal reference to purported psb documents accompanying the visa application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">did not use "information" within s.424a(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">applicant's responses at hearing also "gave" the documents to the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1584">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">credibility finding based on delay in applying for protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">whether dating information given to tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">no breach of s.424a established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">refusal of relief for delay in seeking judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">earlier application discontinued</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">second application to court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">application to reinstate first application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1133">all relief refused.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 776">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 776">review of decision by refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 776">whether refugee review tribunal's decision affected by jurisdictional error.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1703">14 The primary judge considered an issue that arose during the hearing about s 424A of the Migration Act (which requires the Tribunal to give to the applicant, in the way that the Tribunal considers appropriate in the circumstances, clear particulars of any information that the Tribunal considers would be the reason, or a part of the reason, for affirming the decision that is under review). Referring to SZHYP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 at [9] , [11] --- [12] and NAOA v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 241 at [21] the primary judge said that it is a matter for an applicant to establish breach of s 424A. The applicant had not adduced any evidence about the course of the hearing before the Tribunal (such as the transcript). The Tribunal also noted that the applicant's claims remained those as set out in his protection visa application. The primary judge (correctly) decided that there was no issue arising on the material under s 424A for the first of these reasons (there being no evidentiary basis for any such conclusion). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FMCA 257">The applicant then appealed against his Honour's decision, and on 
23 rd February 2007 Branson J in the Federal Court dismissed the appeal with costs (see SZHYP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship ). [2] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FMCA 2010">I note the suggestion in SZHYP v The Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 that it is for an applicant to establish that s.424A applies to information. More generally, if the applicant in this case intended to take issue with the Tribunal account of what occurred in the Tribunal hearing, he had the opportunity to file and serve an affidavit containing additional evidence relied on, including a transcript of the Tribunal hearing by 4 March 2007. He did not do so. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 1725">33 As to the reliance by the Tribunal upon oral evidence given by the appellant, that matter is expressly within the exception provided for by s 424A(3)(b). Submissions have been addressed in the written submissions of the first respondent in relation to s 424A(3)(b) and, in particular, as to the question of which party bears the onus of establishing whether particular information is either within or without the section. It seems clear to me on settled authority that the appellant bears the onus of establishing the relevant matters ( SZHYP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2007) FCA 183). At [11] of the reasons of Branson J, her Honour observes:
 
 To succeed in his contention that the Tribunal failed to comply with the requirements of s 424A in respect to the information upon which its finding was based, it was necessary for the appellant to satisfy the Federal Magistrate that the Tribunal did not base its finding on information that he gave for the purposes of his application to the Tribunal.  33 As to the reliance by the Tribunal upon oral evidence given by the appellant, that matter is expressly within the exception provided for by s 424A(3)(b). Submissions have been addressed in the written submissions of the first respondent in relation to s 424A(3)(b) and, in particular, as to the question of which party bears the onus of establishing whether particular information is either within or without the section. It seems clear to me on settled authority that the appellant bears the onus of establishing the relevant matters ( SZHYP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (2007) FCA 183). At [11] of the reasons of Branson J, her Honour observes:
 
 To succeed in his contention that the Tribunal failed to comply with the requirements of s 424A in respect to the information upon which its finding was based, it was necessary for the appellant to satisfy the Federal Magistrate that the Tribunal did not base its finding on information that he gave for the purposes of his application to the Tribunal. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FMCA 1584">14. Counsel for the applicant accepted that he had an onus of proof as to whether an applicant did not "give" information to a Tribunal, so as to give rise to the exclusion under s.424A(3)(b) (see SZHYP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 at [9] and [11]). He submitted that I should prefer the applicant's evidence. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FMCA 1133">He submitted that I should conclude that the date of her arrival was information given by her to the Tribunal at the hearing, from the Tribunal's reference to "her explanation, given at hearing" for the delay, in a context where the applicant's visa application had been referred to in the written submissions of the Tribunal in the terms which I have extracted above, and where the date of her arrival was uncontentious. 43. Alternatively, if I were not positively persuaded of that fact, he submitted that the onus of proof that the exclusion in s.424A(3)(b) did not apply rests on an applicant, and that I could not be positively satisfied that the applicant did not give to the Tribunal the information that she had arrived in Australia in March 1997 (see SZEEU v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 2 ; (2006) 150 FCR 214 at [82]- [83], and other paragraphs applied by Branson J in SZHYP v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 at [9] ). 44. I accept this submission.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FMCA 776">In support of (a) above the First Respondent referred to the authorities of SZHYP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 183 at [9] , [11]-[12] and NAOA v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 241 at [21] in relation to the failure by the Applicant to adduce any evidence to the contrary of the Tribunal's observation referred to above, including any transcript.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 441A Methods by which Tribunal gives documents to a person other than the Secretary</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>