<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Telstra Corporation Limited v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 (5 September 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1398.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 174">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 174">notice to produce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 174">whether documents sought satisfy the test of apparent relevance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 115">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 115">appeal from single judge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 115">whether there is power to issue notice to produce under order 33 rule 12 where applicant for notice is a respondent to pre-action discovery under order 15a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 115">whether order 15a is a self-contained order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 115">appeal allowed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">federal court rules order 15a rule 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">whether reasonable cause to believe that applicant has or may have right to obtain relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">asserted claims for breach of warranty, misleading or deceptive conduct and breach of fiduciary duty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">low threshold requirement for reasonable belief, however belief must amount to more than a mere possibility or speculation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">entitlement to preliminary discovery in order for applicant to ascertain defences available to respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations made as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">onus on respondent to show reasonableness of future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery appropriate in relation to future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">application for preliminary discovery otherwise denied trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">misleading or deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 651">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 651">copyright in articles by journalists published under by-lines</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 651">difficulty in deciding whether they have right to obtain relief in respect of alleged infringements of particular articles by media monitoring service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 651">whether preliminary discovery should be ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 651">scope of such discovery.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 312">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 312">interlocutory application for third party discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 312">objection on the grounds of "highly confidential information" and oppressiveness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 312">consideration of whether difficulties exaggerated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1990] FCA 312">discretion of awarding costs of discovery considered.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 112">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 112">interrogatories as to state of controlling mind of a corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 112">costs where motion for further answers to interrogatories abandoned</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">client legal privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">common interest privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">time at which common interest assessed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1952">whether joint venturers have common interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">whether administrative appeals tribunal denied comcare procedural fairness in refusing leave to inspect summonsed documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">documents related to previous injury of compensation claimant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">credit of claimant main issue in proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">documents therefore not available for cross examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">tribunal must give parties a reasonable opportunity to present case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">"reasonable opportunity" includes right to test evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">tribunal's refusal potentially denied comcare opportunity to cross-examine effectively</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">whether access to documents should be denied as going only to credit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">purpose for seeking documents clearly identifiable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">not fishing to seek documents going to credit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">wrong to determine questions of inspection by whether documents ought to be admitted into evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">no need for documents to establish any specific fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.13" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">test of relevance is whether documents relate to issue in proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.14" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">discretion of tribunal under administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth) is subject to overarching obligation of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.15" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 285">procedural fairness denied</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 112">Consideration has been given during the course of argument to a number of cases, including Shop Distributive and Allied Employees Association v Karellas Investments Pty Limited [2007] FCA 959 , Telstra Corporation Limited v The Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 , Wildia Pty Ltd v Lee (1984) 9 ACLR 122 , Allied Pastoral Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation [1983] 1 NSWLR 1 , W R Carpenter Holdings Proprietary Limited v The Commissioner of Taxation of the Commonwealth of Australia [2008] HCA 33 ; [2008] HCA 33 ; (2008) 237 CLR 198 and Meth v Norbert Steinhardt &amp; Son Limited (1959) 33 ALJR 78.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 1197">Those sentiments expressed by Hely J were quoted with apparent approval by Graham J in Telstra Corporation v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 (Telstra). One finds in Graham J's judgment in the Telstra case at para 44 through to, and including, para 54, a helpful recitation of authority in relation to practice and procedure concerning notices to produce. The Sunland parties do not challenge the prima facie ability of Mr Joyce to invoke the notice to produce procedure in support of his application on 14 December 2009. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 566">I will not take time to repeat the principles in relation to the use of notices to produce and whether notices to produce may be judged to be oppressive, which I stated in Telstra Corporation Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [44-54] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCA 565">Counsel for the applicant has indicated that reasons are not required. However, I think it appropriate that reference be made to what I said in Telstra Corporation Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 , in particular at paragraphs [44] --- [54]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] FCA 334">As I have previously said in Telstra Corporation Ltd v Minister for Communications Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [47] : 
 '47. Once documents have been produced to the court, any objections to their production having been rejected, the documents are in the control of the court. At this stage the person producing the documents may state that he objects to them being handed to a party seeking access to them for inspection. Documents should not go beyond the judge against the objection of the owner unless there is a valid reason to do so. Subject to matters such as confidentiality, it is for the judge, as part of the second step, to determine whether the documents appear relevant in the sense that they relate to the subject matter of the proceedings, in which event the judge will permit inspection by one or both parties at an appropriate time. The question of their admissibility without more, in accordance with the rules of evidence, does not then arise (per Moffitt P in Waind's case at 382-385 cf per Sackville J in Seven Network Limited v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174 at [6] ). ' 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] FCA 1952">25 Paragraphs 1 and 2 of the notice of motion can be dealt with together. A notice to produce may be set aside on the ground of lack of apparent relevance. The test of apparent relevance is whether the documents are reasonably likely to add, in the end, in some way or another, to the relevant evidence. Relevance in an evidentiary/admissibility sense is not the test. See Trade Practices Commission v Arnotts Ltd (No 2) (1989) 88 ALR 90 at 101-103; Seven Network Ltd v News Ltd (No 11) [2006] FCA 174 at [6] ; Telstra Corp Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [44] - [48].</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2008] FCA 285">34 A party seeking to inspect documents does not need to demonstrate that relevant documents exist ( Telstra Corporation Ltd v Minister for Communications, Information Technology and the Arts [2007] FCA 1398 at [47] , [52] per Graham J; Alister at 451 per Brennan J). In any event, in this case there was no doubt that the summonsed documents did exist as they were produced to the Tribunal. It was also apparent that they were likely to be relevant to a issue in the proceedings. Further, it is not fishing to seek documents going to the credit of a crucial witness ( Fried at [24]).
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 6 Territories</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 55 Relevant evidence</title>
<title id="l3">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 58 Inferences as to relevance</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>