<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Forbes Engineering (Asia) Pte Limited v Mark Forbes [2007] FCA 1598 (18 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1598.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">amendment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">application for leave to file a cross-claim out of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">discretionary considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">adjournment to file further evidence, made at hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 118">whether appealable error shown.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 264">vacation of trial date</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 264">relevant principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 264">costs assessed and paid forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 264">costs in security for costs application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">application to vacate hearing dates</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">prejudice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">withdrawal of lawyers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">medical condition of lawyer with conduct of the matter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">efforts made to obtain representation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">issue of effective representation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">case management considerations.  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1582">alleged breach of industry franchising code.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FMCA 1582">This raises a further issue: do the respondents need lawyers to represent them? Strictly speaking they do not. The second respondent could self-represent, the first respondent could, with leave of the Court, be represented by the second respondent. [20] In any event, it is not, again strictly speaking the case that withdrawal of, or change of, legal representation shortly before a hearing will necessarily or even routinely warrant a court vacating hearing dates. [21] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1032">7 Mr Senathirajah, who appeared for the plaintiff, applied for the hearing of the defendants' Notice of Motion to be adjourned until at least 16 July 2008 because of the unavailability of counsel who had settled the statement of facts and contentions. While accepting that the availability of counsel would rarely be a sufficient basis for the adjournment of a hearing, Mr Senathirajah pointed out that it was only upon receipt of the defendants' letter on 18 June 2008 that the plaintiff had been put on notice of the defendants' concerns about the statement of facts and contentions, and that the defendants had permitted a further period of about a week to pass before filing the instant Notice of Motion. He submitted also that a fair defence of the statement required the attention of counsel who had settled it, and who had a detailed familiarity with the facts of the case. In this respect, Mr Senathirajah relied upon State of Queensland v J L Holdings Pty Ltd [1997] HCA 1 ; (1997) 189 CLR 146 ; upon Smith v Gannawarra Shire Council [2002] VSCA 69 ; (2002) 4 VR 344 and upon Forbes Engineering (Asia) Pte Ltd v Forbes [2007] FCA 1598. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 1637">6 I note that:
 
&#8226; One of the reasons I ordered the hearing dates vacated was because I accepted the view taken by the new solicitor for the respondents that, in light of developments following the hearing of 26 September 2007, a second further amended defence would need to be filed and served ( Forbes Engineering (Asia) Pte Limited v Mark Forbes [2007] FCA 1598 at [19] ). &#8226; The orders of 18 October 2007, which accepted that leave to amend the respondents' further amended defence had been given pursuant to O 13 r 3, and directed that a second further amended defence be filed within a short time frame, were made in light of those reasons. &#8226; I accept the submission of the respondents, and it is not in dispute, that the legal representatives for the applicants had been in possession of a copy of the proposed second further amended defence since the morning of 18 October 2007, but no objection was made by the legal representatives when I made the relevant orders, including the order of which complaint is now made, on the afternoon of 18 October 2007.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>