<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Sam v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1976 (15 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1976.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">whether tribunal failed to consider claim to persecution made by the appellant by reason of desertion from the army</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">claim not subsumed in the more general claim to persecution by reason of former membership in that army</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">appeal allowed practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">leave to speak on behalf of appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">in interest of effective, efficient and expeditious disposal of the proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 394">leave granted in unusual circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 246">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 246">invitation to attend hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 246">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 246">request for agent to appear for appellant refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 246">no general duty on part of tribunal to inquire further</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] MRTA 1251">This interpretation was made clear in Sam v MIAC [2007] FCA 1976 (Flick J, 15 November 2007), where Flick J held, on appeal from a judgment of Emmett FM, there was no error in what he characterised as Emmett FM's construction of cl.457.223(4)(a), which was that "cl.457.223(4) has the effect of requiring the sponsor at the time of the Tribunal's decision to be the same sponsor as in the Applicant's application for a 457" (at [18]). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 246">29 A Court "has an inherent right in regulating its own proceedings to allow a person, not being a party or a party's lawyer, to conduct a case on behalf of a party where it is desirable to do so in the interests of the administration of justice": Melaleuca of Australia &amp; New Zealand Pty Ltd v Duck [2005] FCA 1481 at [14] per Bennett J. Mr Laba Sarkis has been granted permission to advocate the interests of parties in other proceedings: SZFCX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 394 at [16] , 90 ALD 634 at 646---7; Sam v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 1976 at [6] .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 162">19 It must be borne in mind that once KT Entertainment failed to gain approved sponsor status, the applicant's visa application was bound to fail. This is because it is a requirement for the visa that the applicant sought that the employer nominated in the visa application as his sponsor be the same employer as at the time of the decision to grant or refuse the visa: see cl 457.223(4)(b)(ii) of Schedule 2 and cl 1223A(3)(d) of Schedule 1 of the Regulations and Sam v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1976 at [16 --- 18]. It followed that the applicant's efforts to organise an alternative sponsor would not have affected the outcome of the application. There was nothing the Tribunal could do to alter this outcome. The Tribunal was not, however, obliged to notify the applicant of this prior to giving its decision. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION REGULATIONS 1994 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>