<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Publishing and Broadcasting Limited, in the matter of Publishing and Broadcasting Limited [2007] FCA 1610 (2 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1610.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">schemes of arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">applications by two corporations for orders under s 411 of the corporations act 2001 (cth) confirming schemes of arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">ultimate objective of demerging media and gaming businesses carried on by one company into media business to be carried on by it and gaming business to be carried on by the other company (recently formed for the purpose)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">directions for convening of meetings previously made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1944">schemes supported by majorities required by s 411(4)(a)(ii) of the act.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] FCA 1944">1 On 2 November 2007 I published reasons for judgment for orders that I had made on 17 October 2007 as varied on 26 October 2007 in these proceedings: see Publishing and Broadcasting Limited, in the matter of Publishing and Broadcasting Limited [2007] FCA 1610. In proceeding NSD 1447 of 2007, I had ordered that the plaintiff, Publishing and Broadcasting Limited (PBL), convene a meeting of all holders of shares in PBL for the purpose of considering and, if thought fit, agreeing (with or without modification) to a scheme of arrangement (the PBL Scheme). In proceeding NSD 1448 of 2007, I had ordered that the plaintiff, Crown Limited (Crown), convene a meeting of all holders of shares in Crown for the purpose of considering and, if thought fit, agreeing (with or without modification) to a scheme of arrangement (Demerger Scheme).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 17 Associates of composite person that carries on a financial services business</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 256C Shareholder approval</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 260B Shareholder approval</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 411 Administration of compromises etc.</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 412 Information as to compromise with creditors</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT (CORPORATIONS) RULES 2000 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>