<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bienstein v Attorney-General [2007] FCA 1174 (8 August 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1174.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">transfer of freedom of information request</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">whether transfer valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">whether tribunal has jurisdiction to review the decision to transfer the request</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">whether a deemed decision has been made to refuse access to documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 895">tribunal has no jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">transfer of freedom of information request</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">whether transfer valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">whether tribunal has jurisdiction to review decision to transfer request</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">whether a deemed decision has been made to refuse access to documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] AATA 896">tribunal has no jurisdiction.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">project blue sky inc &amp; ors v australian broadcasting authority  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">reconciliation of conflicting provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">intention of legislature</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">presumption that provisions intended to achieve consistent goals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">leading and subordinate provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">grammatical meaning and legal meaning.  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">acts done in breach of a condition regulating a statutory power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">mandatory and directory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">purpose-based test.  media law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">television</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">regulation of programming</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australian broadcasting authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">standard prescribing australian content requirements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether inconsistent with legislative requirement that functions be performed consistently with australia's international obligations.  media law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">television</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">regulation of programming</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australian broadcasting authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.20" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">power to make standards that "relate to ... the australian content of programs"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.21" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether restricted to standards conferring preferential treatment.  trade law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.22" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australia new zealand closer economic relations trade agreement.  broadcasting services act 1992 (cth), ss 3 , 122 , 158, 160.  broadcasting services (transitional provisions and consequential amendments) act 1992 (cth), s 21.  tasker v fullwood [1978] 1 nswlr 20 at 23-24 applied.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">request for access to documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">failure to make decision within 30 days</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">deemed refusal to grant access</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">whether administrative appeals tribunal had power to order that a decision be made   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">powers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">deemed refusal to grant access to documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">whether tribunal had power to order that decision be made   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">tribunal not making orders or giving procedural directions sought by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">whether reasonable apprehension of bias in protecting ministers from freedom of information requests   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">appeal to court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">questions of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1501">nature of questions of law on which appeal can be brought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">vcat reference no. g167/2008 freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">transfer of request to ombudsman</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">when authorised</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">freedom of expression</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">whether engaged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">victorian civil and administrative tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">whether bound to act compatibly with human rights in determining review applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">obligation under statute, common law and charter to assist self-represented persons to get a fair hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">affording due assistance to self-represented persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">freedom of information act 1982 , s 18(2)(b)(ii)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">ombudsman act 1973 , s 29a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=citing from="[2009] VCAT 1195">charter of human rights and responsibilities act 2006 , ss 15(1) , 24 (1) and 38 (1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 490">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 490">deemed decisions refusing access</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 490">whether reasonable steps taken to find documents matching requests</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 490">whether documents exist</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 490">decisions affirmed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether tribunal has power to order minister to make a decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether any such decision made by minister or an authorised person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether any need for the minister to make a decision when decision refusing access already deemed to have been made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether tribunal has jurisdiction to review deemed decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">tribunal has jurisdiction.    practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether obligation to lodge statement of reasons and relevant documents under s 37 of aat act applies when decision deemed to have been made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether time to do so should be extended</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 7">whether tribunal obliged to record or arrange for recording of directions hearing.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1501">She was successful on appeal. The decision of the Tribunal on each of the applications for review was set aside and each of the cases was remitted to the Tribunal to be heard and decided again. See Bienstein v Attorney-General [2007] FCA 1174 (2007) 162 FCR 405.  The appellant's amended notice of appeal contained several other questions, in the following terms: Whether a decision deemed by the FOI Act to have been made "for the purpose of making an application to the Tribunal" may be taken in Tribunal proceedings as deemed for a different or an additional purpose. 
 Whether an FOI request directed to a Minister may lawfully be transferred or referred for processing to the Minister's Department and whether the effect of a valid transfer is to free the transferor agency or Minister of the duty to furnish to the applicant notices of acknowledgment and decision in accordance with s 15 FOI Act. 
 What, in a FOI proceeding where the adequacy of searches is in issue, constitutes compliance with s 37 AAT Act? 
 What duties did the decision in Bienstein v Attorney-General and Justice Minister [2007] FCA 1174 settle on: 
 
 
 
 (a) lawyers who appeared for the Respondents in that proceeding and their instructor(s); 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) the Attorney-General's Department and the Departmental Officer in possession of the purportedly transferred requests; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) the Respondents; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (d) the Tribunal; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (e) the Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet, where the FOI legislation is administered by the Privacy &amp; FOI policy Branch and the responsible Minister, being Cabinet Secretary, Senator Faulkner; 
 
 

 To what extent is the Tribunal competent to enforce the Applicant's rights under s 11 FOI Act in applications brought on the basis of the Respondent's failure to furnish a timely decision on the request. 
 Whether each government agency and Minister has a duty under the FOI Act to establish procedures consistent with that legislative scheme for the receipt and processing of requests in and by the said agency or Ministerial office and for the receipt and implementation of consequential Tribunal and Court decisions. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] WAICmr 29">In Bienstein v Attorney-General [2007] FCA 1174 , Gray J of the Federal Court considered the application of s.16 of the Freedom of Information Act 1982 (Cth), which relates to the transfer of an access application under that legislation. Although the wording of that provision is not identical to that of s.15 of the FOI Act, it includes the situation where an agency does not hold the requested documents. In Bienstein, Gray J said at [34]-[36] , in relation to that issue:
 
" The question whether a document is in an agency's possession can only be answered after the agency has made any necessary search for that document...a transfer can only be put into effect after an agency has conducted a search to ascertain whether or not it has the document sought ... It is true that there is not to be found in the provisions of the FOI Act any express imposition of a duty on the recipient of a request for access to documents to search its records to ascertain whether it has documents answering the description in the request. Such a duty is implicit, however. " 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] VCAT 1195">However, the tribunal possesses jurisdiction to determine all questions of fact, law and merit relevant to an application for review. If it appears an agency has purported to exercise the power of transfer in s 18(2) when it is not properly available, the tribunal possesses the jurisdiction to consider and determine that issue. If it determines the transfer to be invalid, it could then proceed with the application for review on the basis (for example) that the agency has not decided the request within the 45 day time period specified in s 21. That follows from what Gray J decided in Bienstein v Attorney-General . [5] His Honour held the federal tribunal had the jurisdiction (and therefore the responsibility) to decide whether the equivalent provisions of the federal legislation authorised the transfer decision made in that case. [6] To that question in this case I now turn. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] AATA 490"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] AATA 7">32. It is apparent from what I understand to be the Tribunal's powers that I do not regard myself as having any power to direct the Attorney-General or the Justice Minister to make decisions on the requests that Mrs Bienstein has made to them. My powers are limited to those circumstances in which they have either already made a decision or are deemed to have done so for the purpose of permitting Mrs Bienstein to make an application. In this case, it is the latter situation that prevails as Gray J recognised in his judgment. [25] That is to say, the effect of s 56(1) is that the Attorney-General and the Justice Minister have, for the purpose of enabling Mrs Bienstein to make an application to the Tribunal, been deemed to have made a decision refusing to grant access to the documents she has requested. Mrs Bienstein has made the application and, in view of s 56(1), properly done so.
 
 
  4. In considering the appeals from my earlier decisions, Gray J summarised the events to that time and the issues he had to consider in the following way:
 
" ... The Tribunal decided that it did not have jurisdiction to deal with two applications for review made by the applicant. Each of those applications for review related to a request made pursuant to the Freedom of Information Act 1982 (Cth) ('the FOI Act'), one to the Attorney-General and the other to the Minister for Justice and Customs ('the Justice Minister'), seeking access to certain documents. Both the Attorney-General's office and the Justice Minister's purported to transfer the requests to the Attorney-General's Department ('the Department'), pursuant to s 16 of the FOI Act. There is a question in each case whether these purported transfers gave rise to a deemed refusal to provide access to the documents. In each case, there is an antecedent question as to whether the purported transfer was valid, and a subsidiary question as to whether a transfer of a request absolves the original agency, to which the request is addressed, from the obligation to search for documents answering the descriptions in the request, to determine whether it has such documents in its possession. " [1]  No application for internal review was necessary under s 54 as a prerequisite to an application to the Tribunal. Accordingly, the Tribunal did have jurisdiction in relation to each application for review. " [3] 
 
 
  Similarly, s 16(4) requires an agency transferring a request to another agency in any of the circumstances outlined in s 16 to send 'the document' the subject of the request to the other agency 'if it is necessary to do so in order to enable the other agency to deal with the request'. Plainly, without having ascertained whether it has such a document, the transferor agency would not be in a position to comply with this requirement. " [2] </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l3">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 160 Postal articles</title>
<title id="l4">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 </title>
<title id="l5">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 3 Objects--general</title>
<title id="l6">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 4 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l7">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 11 Right of access</title>
<title id="l8">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 15 Requests for access</title>
<title id="l9">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 15A Request for access to personnel records</title>
<title id="l10">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 16 Transfer of requests</title>
<title id="l11">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 21 Deferment of access</title>
<title id="l12">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 22 Access to edited copies with exempt or irrelevant matter deleted</title>
<title id="l13">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 24 Power to refuse request--diversion of resources etc.</title>
<title id="l14">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 24A Requests may be refused if documents cannot be found, do not exist or have not been received</title>
<title id="l15">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 26A Consultation--documents affecting Commonwealth-State relations etc.</title>
<title id="l16">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 27 Consultation--business documents</title>
<title id="l17">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 27A Consultation--documents affecting personal privacy</title>
<title id="l18">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 29 Charges</title>
<title id="l19">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 48 Application for amendment or annotation of personal records</title>
<title id="l20">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 54 Internal review--access refusal decision</title>
<title id="l21">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 55 Procedure in IC review--general</title>
<title id="l22">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 56 Appeals--appeals to Federal Court of Australia on questions of law</title>
<title id="l23">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 58 Powers of Tribunal</title>
<title id="l24">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>