<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Trevor Close on behalf of the Githabul People v Minister for Lands [2007] FCA 1847 (29 November 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1847.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">application for determination of native title under s 87 of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">consideration of whether the parties have satisfied the criteria set out in s 87 such that the jurisdiction of the court is enlivened</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">consideration of whether it is appropriate for the court to make an order in terms of the agreement reached by the parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">the central focus is on the agreement and whether it was freely entered into on an informed basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">if the court finds this to be the case it will infer the existence of the native title that is at the heart of that agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">the court must be satisfied that the state has taken a real interest in the proceedings in the interests of the community generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">however there must be a balance between the stringency of the processes followed by the state in assessing the applicant's evidence and the need to take a flexible approach that is aimed at facilitating negotiation and achieving agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">parties filed joint submissions in support of a minute of a proposed consent determination and a statement of agreed facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1343">held that the agreement is free and informed and that the terms of the proposed orders are unambiguous and clear.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">notice of motion by applicant representing native title claim group seeking leave to discontinue native title determination application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">o 22 r 2(2) federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">whether applicant is authorised to bring notice of motion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">operation of s 251b and s 62a native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">whether conditions should be imposed upon discontinuance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 828">nature of conditions</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1343">It follows from all these considerations that the central issue in an application for a consent determination under s 87 is whether there exists a free and informed agreement between the parties. In this respect, the process followed by the State party respondent, particularly how it goes about assessing the underlying evidence as to the existence of native title, is critical. Other critical factors, all directed to the processes that lead to the agreement and what was agreed, that have been previously identified by the Court include: whether the parties have independent and competent legal representation: Munn at [29], [39] and [40] and Lovett at [39]---[40]; whether the terms of the proposed order are unambiguous and clear: Munn at [32]; and whether the agreement has been preceded by a mediation process: Nangkiriny v Western Australia [2004] FCA 1156 at [6] ; Trevor Close on behalf of the Githabul People v Minister for Lands [2007] FCA 1847 at [6] and Lovett at [41]---[42]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 828">In summary: In 2007 a native title determination was made by this Court in respect of land claimed by the Githabul People in New South Wales ( Trevor Close on behalf of the Githabul People v Minister for Lands [2007] FCA 1847). This was a consent determination to which the State of New South Wales was a party. The State of Queensland indicated at the time that it was not prepared to recognise native title rights and interests in Queensland as claimed in 2007 by the Githabul People.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l1">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 56 Determination whether native title to be held in trust</title>
<title id="l2">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 57 Determination of prescribed body corporate etc.</title>
<title id="l3">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 66 Notice of application</title>
<title id="l4">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 87 Power of Federal Court if parties reach agreement</title>
<title id="l5">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 223 Native title</title>
<title id="l6">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 225 Determination of native title</title>
<title id="l7">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 251D Land or waters on which a public work is constructed, established or situated</title>
<title id="l8">NATIVE TITLE AMENDMENT ACT 1998 </title>
<title id="l9">NATIVE TITLE AMENDMENT ACT 1998 - SECT 3 Schedule(s)</title>
<title id="l10">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l11">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l12">NATIVE TITLE (PRESCRIBED BODIES CORPORATE) REGULATIONS 1999 </title>
<title id="l13">ABORIGINAL COUNCILS AND ASSOCIATIONS ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l14">AUSTRALIAN TELECOMMUNICATIONS CORPORATION ACT 1989 </title>
<title id="l15">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l16">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l17">ELECTRICITY (CONSUMER SAFETY) ACT 2004 </title>
<title id="l18">MINING ACT 1992 </title>
<title id="l19">NATIVE TITLE (NEW SOUTH WALES) ACT 1994 </title>
<title id="l20">PETROLEUM (ONSHORE) ACT 1991 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>