<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124 (16 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/124.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">substituted service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">plaintiff resident abroad and outside the jurisdiction when proceedings commence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">whether court has jurisdiction to order substituted service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">whether proceedings for declaratory relief for contravention of provisions of corporations law are founded on a cause of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 477">whether court can and should cure failure to serve form 13a notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">allegation of contempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">application for preliminary discovery to enable party to determine whether contempt proceedings should be instituted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">whether the court accepted a party's undertaking</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">whether party resiled from an undertaking given to the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1285">whether undertaking given to court was ambiguous</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">environment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">contravention by respondent of environment protection and biodiversity conservation act 1999 (cth)  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">public interest injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">discretion whether to grant relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">futility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">environment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">contravention by respondent of environment protection and biodiversity conservation act 1999 (cth)  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">public interest injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">discretion whether to grant relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 3">futility</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1166">In Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124 at [8] , Allsop J noted that the various meanings that can be attributed to the word 'impractical' include 'practically impossible' or ' that (which) cannot be carried out or done '.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1285">2 In August 2007, a single judge of this Court dismissed an application by the appellant for judicial review of conduct associated with the development of what is known as an Australian Noise Exposure Forecast ("ANEF"): The Village Building Co Ltd v Airservices Australia [2007] FCA 124. The appellant owns land near Canberra airport, Tralee station, which it proposes to develop as residential blocks. Its capacity to do so may be curtailed by the development of a plan for the future use of Canberra airport based on an ANEF that the first respondent, Airservices Australia, is proposing to endorse. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 36">2 The proceedings have had a considerable history concerning difficulties in finding an effective means of service on the respondent, which is substantively summarised in his Honour's reasons. Ultimately his Honour granted an application for substituted service and ordered that the respondent be served with the originating process under O 7 r 9: Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124 at [6] - [14]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 3">1 These reasons should be read against the background of the earlier judgments on service: Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2004] FCA 1510 ; (2004) 212 ALR 551 , Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2005] FCA 664 (the two judgments containing my original reasons for refusing leave to serve outside Australia), Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2006] FCAFC 116 ; (2006) 154 FCR 425 (the Full Court judgment), and Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124 (my reasons on substituted service). I do not propose to repeat matters there discussed. Phrases and terms used in these reasons (if otherwise undefined or unexplained) are to be understood by reference to those earlier reasons. 26 After reserving judgment on this matter, I directed the applicant to write to the Attorney-General for the Commonwealth to ascertain whether he remained of the same view as expressed in his submissions relating to leave to serve out of the jurisdiction. In a letter dated 12 October 2007, the Attorney-General's advisors expressed the opinion that the service by the applicant was defective and that "Japan would view neither the proceedings nor any judgment arising from them as legitimate". However, in circumstances such as these, where the Full Court of this Court has ordered that the respondent be served out of the jurisdiction, and where the Japanese Government has declined to assist in that service (as outlined above), I am of the opinion that the orders of 2 February 2007 are in accordance with the Rules. In so saying, I refer to my reasons given for granting substituted service (given on 16 February 2007): see Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 3">1 These reasons should be read against the background of the earlier judgments on service: Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2004] FCA 1510 ; (2004) 212 ALR 551 , Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2005] FCA 664 (the two judgments containing my original reasons for refusing leave to serve outside Australia), Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2006] FCAFC 116 ; (2006) 154 FCR 425 (the Full Court judgment), and Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124 (my reasons on substituted service). I do not propose to repeat matters there discussed. Phrases and terms used in these reasons (if otherwise undefined or unexplained) are to be understood by reference to those earlier reasons. 26 After reserving judgment on this matter, I directed the applicant to write to the Attorney-General for the Commonwealth to ascertain whether he remained of the same view as expressed in his submissions relating to leave to serve out of the jurisdiction. In a letter dated 12 October 2007, the Attorney-General's advisors expressed the opinion that the service by the applicant was defective and that "Japan would view neither the proceedings nor any judgment arising from them as legitimate". However, in circumstances such as these, where the Full Court of this Court has ordered that the respondent be served out of the jurisdiction, and where the Japanese Government has declined to assist in that service (as outlined above), I am of the opinion that the orders of 2 February 2007 are in accordance with the Rules. In so saying, I refer to my reasons given for granting substituted service (given on 16 February 2007): see Humane Society International Inc v Kyodo Senpaku Kaisha Ltd [2007] FCA 124. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>