<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 (19 July 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1059.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">"requirement or condition" that hearing impaired child be taught in english rather than auslan, a native australian sign language</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether ability to "cope" without auslan assistance meant that child was "able to comply" with "requirement or condition", pursuant to s 6(c) of the disability discrimination act 1992 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether child would suffer "serious disadvantage" without auslan assistance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether suffering "serious disadvantage" meant child could not comply with "requirement or condition"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">human rights and equal opportunity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">appeal from federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">federal magistrate ordered separate questions for decision in the proceeding after another judge had conducted a trial but resigned from the court before giving judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">mixed questions of fact and law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">federal magistrate answered separate questions in the absence of any findings of fact or agreed statement of facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">answers hypothetical</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">error in seeking to answer questions without first making factual findings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">nature of appropriate orders in the circumstances considered discrimination legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">indirect discrimination on ground of disability alleged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">appellant serving a sentence of incarceration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">transport and accommodation as "services" in issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">requirement or condition in issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">nature of "services" discussed costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 163">appropriate costs order in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">profound deafness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">access to education</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">without an auslan teacher or an auslan interpreter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">reasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 405">disability discrimination act 1992 (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">civil and political rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">indirect discrimination on ground of disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">boy with congenital profound deafness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">mainly communicated by auslan</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">about to enter high school</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">whether in circumstances reasonable for education provider not to take more steps to provide auslan interpreting assistance for class room instruction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">such assistance provided in primary school operated by same education provider.  damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1085">merely compensatory. australian iron &amp; steel pty lt v banovic [1989] hca 56 ; (1987) 168 clr 165 at 178-79; 187, applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">state provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">discrimination on the basis of age and gender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">complaint</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">extent of power of anti-discrimination commissioner to nominate the respondent.  commissioner for police v reid [2000] tassc 181 ; (2000) 9 tas r 418 , distinguished.  anti-discrimination act 1998 (tas), ss3 and 62 .  aust dig discrimination law [17.5]  discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">state provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">discrimination on the basis of age and gender</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">conduct by the director of public prosecutions relating to the institution of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">whether such conduct amounts to the provision of services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[2003] TASSC 27">nature of director of public prosecutions' prosecutorial discretion.  barton v r [1980] hca 48 ; (1980) 147 clr 75 , applied.  r v entry clearance officer, bombay; ex parte amin [1983] 2 ac 818 ; r v immigration tribunal, ex parte kassam [1980] 1 wlr 1037 , followed.  anti-discrimination act 1998 (tas), s22.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination on ground of status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">disabled persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">direct and indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">whether intention or motive to discriminate necessary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination constituted by imposition of requirement or condition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">no contravention where requirement or condition reasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">reasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">no contravention where act done necessary to comply with provision of other legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">whether necessary that other legislation directly impose obligation to do discriminatory act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">equal opportunity act 1984 (vict.), ss. 17(1), (5), 29(2)(b), 39(e)(ii).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASAT 115">equal opportunity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASAT 115">discrimination on grounds of sex, race and age &#173; whether police officers engaged in provision of services &#173; police officers &#173; vicarious liability &#173; less favourable treatment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">contention that the body corporate has contravened the provisions of the disability discrimination act which prohibit indirect discrimination in the provision of goods and services and facilities by not permitting her access to common property with her dog</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">contends that the body corporate contravened the provision of the act by refusing to permit her to live at kookaburra park with her dog</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant has a disability as defined in section 4 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant has been directly discriminated against pursuant to section 9 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the respondent has unlawfully discriminated against the applicant pursuant to section 24(1) in the case that section 6 and 9 of the act apply</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether respondent can prove unjustifiable hardship under section 24(2) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether respondent has contravened section 5 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the respondent has contravened section 25 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant is entitled to compensation if the respondent did contravene the act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1221">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1221">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1221">indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1221">harassment.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 647">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 647">discrimination on the ground of race, colour, or national or ethnic origin</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 647">applicant arrested for trespass at university</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 647">neither arrests nor other police conduct influenced by applicant's race</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 647">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 177">appeal under s 148, victorian civil and administrative tribunal act 1998</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 177">summary dismissal of proceeding under s 75 of act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2008] VSC 177">whether proceeding frivolous, vexatious, misconceived or lacking in substance or otherwise an abuse of process.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">vcat reference no. a151/2007 anti-discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">direct discrimination on the basis of race</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">failure to give leading hand position to prisoner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">whether treatment based on race</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">nature of prison industry work</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">equal opportunity act 1995 ss 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2008] VCAT 845">8 , 10 , 14 , 42 , 102 and 134  complainant hasan alipek respondent 1 gsl custodial services pty ltd respondent 2 linda ristevski where held melbourne before c. mckenzie, deputy president hearing type hearing date of hearing 28-30 april 2008 date of order 8 may 2008 citation alipek v gsl custodial services pty ltd &amp; anor (anti-discrimination) [2008] vcat 845</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 31">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 31">indirect disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 31">whether a requirement or condition imposed on provision of prison transport and accommodation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 31">whether requirement or condition reasonable.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] WASAT 115">That distinction was questioned by Sundberg J in Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 although His Honour did not need to pursue the question (at [73]).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] NSWADT 101">182 The respondents relied in particular on the decision of Sundberg J in Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 ; (2007) 167 FCR 1 where his Honour said at [73]:
 
 
 [73] Counsel for the State suggested that the touchstone for a service should be whether the act involves helpful or beneficial activity: IW 191 CLR at 11 per Brennan C,1 and McHugh J. I accept that this is a useful test, but in a qualified way. Most activities are helpful or beneficial to someone.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] MRTA 376">'Arrangements to undergo a test' involves arrangements to sit for a test rather than simply awaiting the results of a test already undertaken. This interpretation is supported by Jagot J in MIAC v Grant [2007] FCA 1059 at paragraph 42 which states that 
 
 an applicant 'has made arrangements to undergo a language test' within the meaning of cl 485.215(c) if an applicant has arranged to take, but has not yet taken, the test. This is the natural and ordinary meaning of the words of the provision. 
 
  The Tribunal does not accept that the meaning of 'arrangement to undergo a test' extends to include the situation where an applicant has sat for an IELTS test but has not yet received the results of the test. In such a case, an applicant cannot demonstrate that he or she has 'made arrangements to undergo a test', in accordance with the requirements of cl.485.215(c), nor can he or she demonstrate that he or she has 'competent English' in accordance with cl. 485.215(b) unless he or she obtains a test score of at least 6 for each of the test components or listening, speaking, reading and writing for that test sat for prior to the lodgement of the visa application. Support for this interpretation of cl. 485.215 is found in the decision of MIAC v Grant [2007] FCA 1059 at paragraph 46 where Jagot J finds that: 
 
 Mr Grant did not satisfy the requirements of cl.485.215(c) of the Migration Regulations . At the time of the application for the visa, he had not "made arrangements to undergo a language test specified by the Minister in an instrument in writing" within the meaning of that provision. Rather, he had taken the language test but not achieved the result of competent English as required by cl.485.215(b). Hence, the fact that Mr Grant subsequently proved that he had "competent English" by the taking of a test at a later time (and before the Tribunal made its decision) is insufficient; the first requirement had not been met. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] TASADT 5">A statement made by McHugh J in Waters' case at p405 has application to our Act:
 
"Likewise, if a person is alleged to have imposed on another person a "requirement or condition" in respect of using services, the services provided must be identified with sufficient precision to enable the Board to relate the requirement or condition to those services and to determine the issues raised by s17(5) of the Act. As will appear, the line between what is a "requirement or condition" of using services and the services themselves is often a fine one calling for an exact description of the services provided. "
 
 See also Rainesford v Victoria (2007) FCA 1059 at paragraph 75 emphasising the same matter. It should be noted that the issue of whether the Council has in fact 'imposed a condition, requirement or practice' shall be dealt with later in this decision. Dealing now with contentious aspects of Mr McElwaine's submission some observations should be made about his reliance on principles derived from Waters' case. 
 The submission in relation to the footpath and access to shop fronts was developed further. It was submitted that Mrs Taylor has to identify with precision what constitutes the facility, good or service provided by the Council. The submission relied heavily on the case of Waters v Public Transport Corporation [1991] HCA 49 ; (1991) 173 CLR 349 and particular passages at p375 per Brennan J and McHugh J at p404, set out later, and more generally:
 IW v City of Perth [1997] HCA 30 ; (1997) 71 ALJR 943 Rainsford v Victoria (2005) 144 FCA 279 and (2007) FCA 1059 Commonwealth of Australia v Anti-Discrimination Tribunal [2008] FCAFC 104 ; (2008) 169 FCR 85 
 It was submitted by Mr McElwaine while the Council provides a footpath, the ability of persons to walk up and down the street on the footpath, at the relevant time, the service which the Council was providing was that of discharging a statutory duty by maintaining the footpath and the Council did not have a statutory obligation to provide a footpath which gives access to any particular premises. Mr McElwaine submitted that "the Council cannot, as a matter of law, provide a service for the purposes of the Anti-Discrimination Act 1998 which is inconsistent with, or different to, its statutory obligation under section 11 of the Roads and Jetties Act 1935 " (written submission dated 16 April, 2009). Mr McElwaine referred to Buckle v Bayswater Road Board [1936] HCA 65 ; (1936) 57 CLR 259 at 280-81 and the judgment of Dixon J commenting upon the content of the maintenance (and reconstruction) obligations of statutory authorities in respect of highways. It was considered problematic to regard a council's statutory discretion to give planning approvals as falling within that provision. The provision considered in that High Court case is distinguishable from this case and so are the facts. Mr McElwaine also referred the Tribunal to the case of Rainsford v Victoria (2007) FCA 1059. In that case there was a useful analysis of the case of IW v City of Perth and at paragraph 72 it was stated:
 
"The judgments in IW are clearly dependent on the particular fact situation of that case, but some general propositions can be identified. First, not all government functions are services, although some undoubtedly are.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] FMCA 260">The definition of services was considered in IW v City of Perth [43] . That decision was the subject of detailed analysis by Sunderberg J in Rainsford v Victoria [44] . That analysis is a useful starting point for consideration of this case. At [72] His Honour noted: "The judgments in IW are clearly dependent on the particular fact situation of that case, but some general propositions can be identified.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] NSWADTAP 85">74 We will commence this discussion of the Tribunal's judgment and of the parties' submissions by referring to the passage from Waters at 404-405 that was quoted by Sundberg J in Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 at [75] (see [56] above). 55 At first instance ( Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059) , Sundberg J held that neither of the two respondents had provided a 'service' or made a 'facility' available to the applicant. In its judgment, the Tribunal quoted from paragraphs [77 --- 79] of his Honour's judgment. But in our opinion, it is important to consider some earlier paragraphs as well. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2008] NSWADT 308">

110 On remitter to the Federal Court, in Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 Sundberg J referred to the decision of the High Court in IW , noting at [72] that the judgments were dependent on the particular fact situation of that case, but that some general propositions could be identified:
 
 
 " First, not all government functions are services, although some undoubtedly are. Second, as the difference between Dawson, Gaudron and Gummow JJ on the one hand, and Toohey and Kirby JJ on the other hand demonstrates, the way in which the service is identified is critical. It is a question of fact determined by the situation of the particular case . " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2008] NSWADT 294">11 Mr Rainsford was an inmate who complained that the prison authority had discriminated against him in the way it transported him to court and between prisons. In Rainsford v State of Victoria and GSL Custodial Services Pty Ltd , [2007] FCA 1059 at [77] and [78], Sundberg J said that prison transport is a 'fundamental integer' of the prison system, without which it 'simply could not function'. He said that it is artificial to call it a service when 'those affected have no or almost no control', and the conduct 'does not, of itself, provide ... a benefit'.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs8" from="[2008] FMCA 1221">The judicial interpretation of "services" has been minimal. In Clarke v Catholic Education Office [2003] FCA 1085 ; (2003) 202 ALR 340 although the complaint related to the terms and conditions of enrolment (under s22) , an alternate claim alleging discrimination in the provision of education services contrary to s24(1)(b) was included and Madgwick J, in finding for the Applicant in that case, did not specify under which specific provision the discrimination was found to be unlawful. The Applicant referred me to the decision of Rainsford v Victoria (2007) FCA 1059 where the Court found, in seeking to determine whether a service was provided, that the touchstone of service should be whether the act involves a "helpful or beneficial activity" although most activities are helpful or beneficial to someone. Such a concept of service accords with the Macquarie Dictionary definition as:- "1. An act or helpful activity.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs9" from="[2008] NSWADT 198">48 Ms Anderson submitted that a recent decision of Deputy President Hennessy which refused Mr Dezfouli leave to proceed with other similar claims should be persuasive to the present Tribunal. In Dezfouli v Justice Health and anor [2008] NSWADT 99 , Mr Dezfouli sought leave to proceed with previous, different, but similar in nature, disability discrimination and sexual harassment complaints against Justice Health and the Department of Corrective Services which had been declined by the President of the Anti-Discrimination Board as lacking in substance and which were partly out of time. Deputy President (Deputy President) Hennessy, declined leave to proceed; she said, 
 
 
 '11. Are the respondents providing such a service? Even if Mr Dezfouli identifies a service, which is being provided to him, that service must be a service within the meaning of that term in the AD Act . The Federal Court has decided that accommodation of prisoners in cells within a prison system is not a service for the purposes of the Disability Discrimination Act 1992 (Cth): Rainsford v State of Victoria &amp; Anor [2007] FCA 1059 ; (2007) 242 ALR 128 ; (2007) EOC 93-468 per Sunberg J at [76] to [79] . Without any findings of fact having been made about the nature of the services Mr Dezfouli says are being provided, it is not possible to determine whether those activities come within the definition of "services' in the AD Act . However, the decision in Rainsford v State of Victoria casts some doubt on the prospects of Mr Dezfouli being able to establish that he was being provided with a "service" by either of the respondents when the alleged incidents occurred...'  5 Subsequent to the Case Conference held on 20 February 2008, the Respondents made submissions dated 7 March 2008 that the Tribunal has no jurisdiction to determine Mr Dezfouli's complaints. The Respondents relied on the Federal Magistrates Court decision of Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 (' Rainsford's Case' ), paragraph 73 to support its submission that the performance of the security and custodial functions of the Respondent do not constitute a 'service' within the ADA. 
 
  31 In Rainsford v State of Victoria and GSL Custodial Services Pty Ltd, [2007] FCA 1059 , (Rainsford's Case) Sundberg J stated,
 
 
 '77 ... The prison system simply could not function without prison transport. It is an artificial use of the word service to apply it to a fundamental integer of a system over which those affected have no or almost no control. 78 The accommodation of prisoners in cells within the prison system is similarly an inherent part of incarceration. Prisoners must be housed somewhere within the prison system and that this is so demonstrates that for a prisoner to have a cell is not a helpful or beneficial activity so far as the prisoner is concerned. In so far as there is choice in the allocation of prison cells, it is a purely administrative and prison management matter. It does not, of itself, provide prisoners with a benefit. Rather, it is better described as being "part and parcel of the exercise of a statutory duty and cannot be described as the provision of a service or services", to adopt the words of Underwood J in Secretary of the Department of Justice and Industrial Relations v Anti-Discrimination Commissioner [2003] TASSC 27 ; (2003) 11 Tas R 324 at 341. ' </sentence>
<sentence id="cs10" from="[2008] FMCA 647">In relation to the complaint of breach of s.13 of the RDA, current authorities probably bind me to hold that the police were not "supplying goods or services" when performing police functions relating to her arrest, detention, and prosecution (see Rainsford v State of Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 at [64] - [81], not disturbed on appeal: Rainsford v State of Victoria [2008] FCAFC 31 at [9] ). Moreover, I have made findings above that none of the police actions when dealing with her were influenced by Mrs Paramasivam's race, colour, or national or ethnic origin. She does not suggest that they were influenced by the race, colour, or national or ethnic origin of any of her relatives or associates. This complaint is not, therefore, established on the evidence before me. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs11" from="[2008] VSC 177">He relied on the cases of Waters, [48] IW, [49] Rainsford v Victoria (Federal Court) [50] and Rainsford v Victoria (Full Federal Court).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs12" from="[2008] VCAT 845">I make a similar comment about the provision of services. Counsel for the Respondents argued that I should follow the decision of Sundberg J in Rainsford v State of Victoria [5] and find that prison industry work was not a service, but occurred pursuant to a statutory duty and was an inherent part of incarceration. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs13" from="[2008] NSWADT 122">11 Identification of the service . It is essential when alleging harassment in the provision of services that the services that are being provided are precisely defined: IW v City of Perth [1997] HCA 30 ; (1997) 191 CLR 1 at 16-17 per Brennan CJ and McHugh J. The service must come within the meaning of "service" in the AD Act. Mr Dezfouli has not defined the service that he was receiving from either of the respondents. The Federal Court has decided that accommodation of prisoners in cells within a prison system is not a service for the purposes of the Disability Discrimination Act 1992 (Cth): Rainsford v State of Victoria &amp; Anor [2007] FCA 1059 ; (2007) 242 ALR 128 ; (2007) EOC 93-468 per Sunberg J at [76] to [79] . On appeal to the Full Federal Court, doubt was expressed about that proposition, but the Court did not need to determine the issue: Rainsford v State of Victoria and anor (unreported) [2008] FCAFC 31. In the absence of any submissions about the nature of the services Mr Dezfouli says are being provided, it is not possible to determine whether a Tribunal would be likely to find that those activities come within the definition of "services" in the AD Act .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs14" from="[2008] FCAFC 31">1 Mr Rainsford, who at all relevant times has been a prisoner in Port Phillip Prison, made a complaint on 14 September 2001 to the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission ("HREOC") that he had been the subject of discrimination on the ground of disability. The disability from which Mr Rainsford claimed he suffered arose from a prolapsed disc in his back, the care for which required Mr Rainsford to perform a series of back stretches and exercises. HREOC terminated the complaint and Mr Rainsford made an application to the Federal Magistrates Court. The matter was ultimately heard by Sundberg J of this Court. His Honour dismissed the application: Rainsford v Victoria [2007] FCA 1059 ; (2007) 96 ALD 90. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs15" from="[2008] NSWADT 99">11 Are the respondents providing such a service? Even if Mr Dezfouli identifies a service, which is being provided to him, that service must be a service within the meaning of that term in the AD Act . The Federal Court has decided that accommodation of prisoners in cells within a prison system is not a service for the purposes of the Disability Discrimination Act 1992 (Cth): Rainsford v State of Victoria &amp; Anor [2007] FCA 1059 ; (2007) 242 ALR 128 ; (2007) EOC 93-468 per Sunberg J at [76] to [79] . Without any findings of fact having been made about the nature of the services Mr Dezfouli says are being provided, it is not possible to determine whether those activities come within the definition of "services' in the AD Act . However, the decision in Rainsford v State of Victoria casts some doubt on the prospects of Mr Dezfouli being able to establish that he was being provided with a "service" by either of the respondents when the alleged incidents occurred.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 </title>
<title id="l1">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 4 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l2">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 6 Indirect disability discrimination</title>
<title id="l3">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 24 Goods, services and facilities</title>
<title id="l4">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 122 Liability of persons involved in unlawful acts</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l6">CORRECTIONS ACT 1986 </title>
<title id="l7">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 1 Purposes</title>
<title id="l8">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 4 References to prisons to include transition centres</title>
<title id="l9">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 6 Order of imprisonment</title>
<title id="l10">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 8A Commissioner</title>
<title id="l11">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 21 Duties of Governor</title>
<title id="l12">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 24 Delegation by Governor</title>
<title id="l13">Corrections Act 1986 - SECT 47 Prisoners rights</title>
<title id="l14">CORRECTIONS REGULATIONS 1998 </title>
<title id="l15">EQUAL OPPORTUNITY ACT 1984 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>