<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Dale v Veda Advantage Information Services and Solutions Limited [2007] FCA 1603 (22 October 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1603.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 711">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 711">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 711">implied undertaking not to use discovered documents for a collateral or ulterior purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 711">whether discovered documents may be provided to a person funding the action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">inspection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">civil proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">documents containing notes by cabinet officers of cabinet deliberations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">application to inspect</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">public interest immunity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">inspection by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1993] HCA 24">confidential inspection by legal advisers.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 695">Effect has consistently been given in Australia to the implied undertaking identified by his Lordship; see, eg, Dale v Veda Advantage Information Services and Solutions Ltd [2007] FCA 1603. Nevertheless, express, rather than implied, undertakings as to the use of discovered documents have frequently come to be extracted in commercial litigation, especially where the documents are particularly sensitive. As Hayne, Heydon and Crennan JJ said in Hearne v Street [2008] HCA 36 ; (2008) 235 CLR 125 , at 162 [116]; 
 'The point of insisting on an express undertaking, commonly employed in relation to documents which it is particularly desired to keep secret, is to bring explicitly home to the minds of those giving it how important it is that the documents only be used for the purpose of proceedings. It does not follow that the obligation in question does not exist in more routine cases without the need for an express undertaking. ' 

 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 50 Prohibition of publication of evidence etc.</title>
<title id="l2">PRIVACY ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l3">PRIVACY ACT 1988 - SECT 18J Alteration of credit information files and credit reports</title>
<title id="l4">PRIVACY ACT 1988 - SECT 18K Limits on disclosure of personal information by credit reporting agencies</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>