<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Thompson v Big Bert Pty Ltd t/as Charles Hotel [2007] FCA 1978 (14 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/1978.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 242">continues. is that correct?</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 242">that is correct.  they are still bound by their contract of employment with qantas in relation  to all the other obligations under the manual and the eba?</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 242">that is correct.  indeed, the company qantas, continues to have obligations towards them  under their contract of employment and their eba. that is correct, isn't  it?</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FMCA 242">yes, it is."</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1321">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1321">meaning of 'casual employee'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1321">whether federal magistrate erred in finding employee was not a casual employee for the purposes of s 227 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1321">whether federal magistrate erred in finding that s 173 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) rendered a provision in a contract of employment providing for payment of a loading in lieu of paid lead entitlements to no effect  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1321">whether federal magistrate erred in the exercise of discretion in assessing penalty for contraventions of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1321">Mr Williams rejects the proposition that the Contract may be terminated at any time for any reason, saying that it "cannot seriously be suggested that the parties expected that the employment would be terminated for no reason at all (even if that were legally permissible)". Mr Williams further submits that the fact that the Contract designated a method of termination and specified a period of notice (albeit a short one) supports the proposition that the employment is not casual in nature. Casual employees, Mr Williams contends, are traditionally employed day to day whereas the period of engagement of a full-time or part-time employee is week to week as reflected in a formal period of notice for termination. Mr Williams cites Thompson v Big Bert Ltd t/as Charles Hotel [2007] FCA 1978 ; (2007) 168 IR 309 at [58] in support of this proposition. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 </title>
<title id="l1">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 - SECT 5 Definitions</title>
<title id="l2">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 - SECT 14 Discrimination on the ground of age--direct discrimination</title>
<title id="l3">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 - SECT 15 Discrimination on the ground of age--indirect discrimination</title>
<title id="l4">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 - SECT 16 Act done because of age and for other reason</title>
<title id="l5">AGE DISCRIMINATION ACT 2004 - SECT 18 Discrimination in employment</title>
<title id="l6">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 </title>
<title id="l7">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 5 Sex discrimination</title>
<title id="l8">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 7B Indirect discrimination: reasonableness test</title>
<title id="l9">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 7D Special measures intended to achieve equality</title>
<title id="l10">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 8 Act done for 2 or more reasons</title>
<title id="l11">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 14 Discrimination in employment or in superannuation</title>
<title id="l12">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l13">LONG SERVICE LEAVE ACT 1955 </title>
<title id="l14">LONG SERVICE LEAVE ACT 1955 - SECT 3 Definitions</title>
<title id="l15">LONG SERVICE LEAVE ACT 1955 - SECT 4 Long service leave</title>
<title id="l16">LONG SERVICE LEAVE ACT 1955 - SECT 5 Exemptions</title>
<title id="l17">LONG SERVICE LEAVE ACT 1955 - SECT 15 Regulations</title>
</legistitles>
</case>