<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 (19 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2028.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">defence and war</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">veterans' entitlements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">application for pension at special rate or intermediate rate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">application failed on independent ground not disputed in appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">appeal dismissed. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">remittal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">extent of review on remittal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">order that the matter be remitted to the tribunal for further consideration in accordance with law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">no express or implied limitation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">concession made at first hearing disputed during rehearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">matter remitted is the whole matter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">matter remitted is not confined to the question of law considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">specific remittal orders appropriate in ambiguous cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 156">not prevented from raising issue not raised below.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">workers' compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">degree of permanent impairment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">depression</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">isolation of compensable effects under the approved guide provided for by safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">total impairment of the appellant found to be 10 per cent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">existence of a pre-existing permanent impairment, calculated to be 5 per cent, resulting from paranoid personality traits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">administrative appeals tribunal decision that only 5 per cent of total impairment a result of the work place</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">impairment not compensable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">whether trial judge erred in finding that the administrative appeals tribunal could have regard to reports written after the date of the decision to be reviewed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 204">whether failure of the administrative appeals tribunal to have regard to documents not tendered by the appellant could constitute an error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">legislative instruments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">need for certainty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">cannot incorporate material "from time to time"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">remittal of proceeding to administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">whether it should be differently constituted  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 39">notice of contention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">commonwealth employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">employee of dsto</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">disputed medical and surveillance evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">decision that applicant no longer suffering from chest and shoulder injuries affirmed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">decision that applicant no longer suffering from depressive disorder set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">tribunal not satisfied that administrative action was reasonable, or that such action or failure to obtain a promotion or benefit made a material contribution to a psychological condition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">decision that comcare not liable for vertigo or myocardial infarction affirmed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 1031">held that comcare liable for permanent impairment for psychological condition and sexual dysfunction.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">whether applicant had one or two conditions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">whether applicant's conditions are 'permanent'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">whether whole person impairment assessment under the guide should be higher</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">what are appropriate scores under division 2 of the guide for non-economic loss</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">meaning of ' some supervision and direction in the activities of daily living'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">whether applicant's conditions caused by non-employment factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">whether applicant's overpayment debt should be waived</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 388">decision under review set aside and remitted.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">appeal from decision of administrative appeals tribunal affirming a decision of the social security appeals tribunal that applicant could be required to enter a newstart activity agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">notice of appeal failed to disclose question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">applicant sought to raise fresh ground that judgment annexing transcript of oral reasons did not constitute proper reasons for decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">reasons for decision were clear</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">other proposed fresh ground not in issue before aat</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1473">appeal dismissed as incompetent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">whether tribunal exceeded its jurisdiction by wrongly conceiving the reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">whether tribunal erred in finding other possible causes for the applicant's symptoms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">whether tribunal applied an incorrect construction of the term minor interference</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">where tribunal wrongly considered whether impairment resulted from service life rather than the degree of permanent impairment resulting from the accepted injury</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">where tribunal erred in finding that other factors could account for symptoms without evidentiary support</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">where tribunal incorrectly applied a global approach to the term minor interference with activities of daily living</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1424">where appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">right shoulder and lumbar spine injuries accepted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">permanent impairment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">degree of whole person impairment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">right shoulder claim not pressed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">2nd edition of the comcare guide</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">clinical findings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">degree of impairment less than 10 percent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 270">decision affirmed</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCAFC 39">On other occasions, there may be circumstances where there is no reason why the Tribunal whose decision is under appeal should be constituted in any different manner when an appeal is allowed and the matter remitted to it for further consideration. Indeed, in some circumstances it may well be convenient for the Tribunal to remain as previously constituted to avoid unnecessary time and expense being incurred. In Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 at [49] , [2007] FCA 2028 ; 99 ALD 303 at 314, Buchanan J declined to make a direction that the Tribunal be reconstituted and said that he saw " no reason to intrude upon the discretion of the President of the AAT ". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] AATA 1031">We think that Dr Kara's psychological condition has perpetuated the pain that he has experienced and continues to experience in the shoulder, lower back and left buttock, but whilst some medication might reasonably be needed to relieve the pain, as mentioned above, we are not satisfied that the pain is as severe or incapacitating as Dr Kara has described. We consider that the degree of permanent impairment in respect of Dr Kara's psychological condition should be assessed at 10% pursuant to Table 5.1 of the Guide. In reaching this conclusion, we have taken into account the surveillance evidence, (and to use the language of the Guide) we think that Dr Kara is capable of performing activities of daily living without supervision or assistance despite the presence of reactions to stressors of daily living with minor loss of personal and social efficiency, and despite minor distortions of thinking. We do not think that the 15% level is appropriate, because we are not satisfied that there is a need for some supervision and direction in activities of daily living. As mentioned above, Dr Davis attributed 2.5% impairment to underlying personality and constitutional factors, but Mr Cole, we think properly, conceded that this deduction should not be made. In applying the Guide, it is necessary to determine what level of impairment is due to a work-related injury: Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 ; (2007) 99 ALD 303 at [34] . We have referred above to Dr Kara's intense feelings of anger, frustration and loss, and whilst we think that these factors play a part in the degree of his permanent impairment, we find that they are themselves the result of the workplace injuries. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] AATA 388">If the Tribunal is in error in attempting to apportion the impairment between the two conditions, [15] the Tribunal makes a finding that Mr Dean is entitled to 25 per cent for both conditions in combination. 
 What are the appropriate scores under Division 2 of the Guide for any non-economic loss suffered by Mr Dean for all or any of his accepted conditions? 
  A preliminary issue was the cause of Mr Dean's conditions. Counsel for the Commission argued that the disturbance in thinking and behaviour were due principally to Mr Dean's cannabis usage, rather than his accepted conditions. [12] This argument required acceptance of the principle that the Tribunal was not bound by the earlier findings by the Commission accepting liability for Mr Dean's pain disorder and major depressive disorder. [13] The burden of persuasion on this issue fell on the Commission. [14] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 1473">21 In Croker v Sec, Dept EEWR [2008] FCA 971 , Stone J observed at [7] that these purposes are recognised in s 43(2B) of the Act, which provides that where the Tribunal is requested under s 43(2A) to give reasons, the reasons are to include the Tribunal's findings on material questions of fact and a reference to the evidence or other material on which those findings were based. Her Honour referred to a comparatively recent decision of Buchanan J in Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 ; (2007) 99 ALD 303 at 314 on this issue. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 1424">47 The relevant compensable "injury", from which the Tribunal accepted Mr Bryant suffered was a particular type of headache condition, "muscle tension type headaches", not "headaches" generally. It may be that it is possible definitively to distinguish the symptoms of "muscle tension type headaches" from those occasioned by, for example, psychological factors or sleep apnoea. Equally, it may to some extent not be possible to draw such a distinction. To the extent that it is not, the Tribunal, like the Commission, was obliged to assess impairment by reference to the totality of impairment "resulting from" the accepted injury on the footing that it was not possible to isolate from that impairment anything which did not result either from another "injury" or from a condition which could never constitute an "injury". A like approach is taken where it is not possible to isolate the impairment flowing from an aggravation of an underlying condition from that flowing from the underlying condition itself: Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 ; (2007) 99 ALD 303 at 310, [30] . It is settled that in those circumstances a body such as the Commission or the Tribunal sitting in its place is obliged to make an assessment beneficially in favour of a claimant.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] FCA 971">7 These purposes are recognised in s 43(2B) of the Act which provides that where the tribunal is requested under s 43(2A) to give written reasons, "those reasons shall include its findings on material questions of fact and a reference to the evidence or other material on which those findings were based". In Jordan v Australian Postal Corporation [2007] FCA 2028 ; (2007) 99 ALD 303 Buchanan J held at 314 that the tribunal's reasons did not include any finding of fact on a material fact and that the appropriate course was to set aside the decision and remit the matter to the tribunal for further consideration. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2008] AATA 270"></sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 20B President may give directions as to constitution of Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 43 Tribunal's decision on review</title>
<title id="l3">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l4">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l5">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 5A Definition of injury</title>
<title id="l6">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 24 Compensation for injuries resulting in permanent impairment</title>
<title id="l7">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 25 Interim payment of compensation</title>
<title id="l8">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 27 Compensation for non-economic loss</title>
<title id="l9">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 28 Approved Guide</title>
<title id="l10">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>