<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Chanel Limited v Kim [2007] FCA 2076 (20 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2076.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">project blue sky inc &amp; ors v australian broadcasting authority  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">reconciliation of conflicting provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">intention of legislature</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">presumption that provisions intended to achieve consistent goals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">leading and subordinate provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">grammatical meaning and legal meaning.  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">acts done in breach of a condition regulating a statutory power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">mandatory and directory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">purpose-based test.  media law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">television</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">regulation of programming</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australian broadcasting authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">standard prescribing australian content requirements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether inconsistent with legislative requirement that functions be performed consistently with australia's international obligations.  media law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">television</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">regulation of programming</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australian broadcasting authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">power to make standards that "relate to ... the australian content of programs"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">whether restricted to standards conferring preferential treatment.  trade law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 28">australia new zealand closer economic relations trade agreement.  broadcasting services act 1992 (cth), ss 3 , 122 , 158, 160.  broadcasting services (transitional provisions and consequential amendments) act 1992 (cth), s 21.  tasker v fullwood [1978] 1 nswlr 20 at 23-24 applied.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">application for injunction under s 126 trade marks act restraining use of trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">where allegedly infringing goods seized by customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">application for order restraining customs from releasing seized goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">whether the extension of time given by customs under s 137(1) trade marks act was valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">where failure to apply within limits specified in s 137(1) trade marks act renders extension of time invalid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1022">where circumstances warrant injunction restraining use of trade mark and retention of goods by customs</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1022">11 The other matter which flows is a question of statutory construction. That question is whether or not, in the events which transpired, there was an invalid extension of time under s 137(1). That particular issue having been drawn to my attention, it seemed to me appropriate, in the circumstances and having regard to the potentially limited timeframe for the making of an order under s 137(5), that notice of the question which had arisen be given to the respondents and also to the Chief Executive Officer of the Australian Customs Service, before any final decision was made in respect of the meaning and effect of that provision in the circumstances. I note that Sackville J followed a similar course of giving notice of a question concerning the meaning and effect of s 137(5) of the Act in Chanel Ltd v Kim [2007] FCA 2076 ; (2007) 166 FCR 1. I therefore gave directions for the giving of notice concerning the issue and the making of submissions in respect of it, to the Respondents and the Chief Executive Officer of Customs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1087">11 In deciding whether or not to grant an order directed to Customs of the kind sought by the applicant, it is relevant to consider a number of additional matters. First, that Customs does not resist the granting of the relief sought: see Chanel Ltd v Kim [2007] FCA 2076 ; (2007) 75 IPR 51 at [35] . In the present case, that is the position here. Secondly, that there is evidence in support of the applicant's contention that the goods are counterfeit: see Sabar [2007] FCA 1255 at [5] and [6]. There is evidence before the court to satisfy that aspect. Thirdly, that the respondent has not appeared in the proceedings, also what has occurred here.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 477">1 These proceedings arise out of the seizure by the Chief Executive Officer of the Australian Customs Service (' CEO ') of a consignment of 100 scarves bearing the Chanel trademark or Chanel's crossed Cs device mark. The consignment was seized pursuant to s 133 of the Trademarks Act 1995 (Cth) (' Trademarks Act '), on the ground that the scarves had applied to them a sign that in the opinion of the CEO was substantially identical with or deceptively similar to a registered trademark. In a judgment delivered on 20 December 2007 ( Chanel Limited v Kim [2007] FCA 2076) , I made orders that the CEO be restrained, until further order, from releasing the consignment of 100 scarves.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l1">ACTS INTERPRETATION ACT 1901 - SECT 15AA Regard to be had to purpose or object of Act</title>
<title id="l2">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l3">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 6 Definitions</title>
<title id="l4">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 131 Object of Part</title>
<title id="l5">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 133 Customs CEO may seize goods infringing trade mark</title>
<title id="l6">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 134 Notice of seizure</title>
<title id="l7">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 137 Action for infringement of trade mark</title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>