<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nudd v Australian Federal Police [2007] FCA 2114 (21 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2114.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">nudd v the queen  criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">miscarriage of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">competence of counsel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">alleged failure to take instructions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">alleged failure to understand elements of offence and relevant statutory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">alleged failure to be familiar with applicable judicial decisions.  appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">criminal appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">miscarriage of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">competence of counsel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">application of "proviso"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">whether denial of fair trial may sometimes without more amount to miscarriage of justice.  legal practitioners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">criminal trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">competence of counsel and of solicitor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">alleged failures to take instructions, to understand elements of offence and to consider applicable judicial decisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">extent to which, if at all, alleged incompetence contributed to any miscarriage of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 9">whether in some circumstances miscarriage of justice includes denial of fair trial according to law without more.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">application pursuant to s 5 administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth) for an order of review of the decision of the minister for home affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">applicant currently serving prison sentence for conviction of being knowingly concerned in the importation into australia of more than a commercial quantity of cocaine contrary to s 233b(1) customs act 1901 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">minister refused applicant's petition to refer case to the court of appeal of queensland under s 672a(a) criminal code 1899 (qld)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">consideration of principles in martens v commonwealth [2009] fca 207 ; (2009) 108 ald 83 relating to the exercise of the referral power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">whether minister failed to consider properly the validity of the applicant's arrest warrant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">whether the minister failed to address or consider alleged fresh evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">whether the minister failed to consider properly the process of extradition to which the applicant was subjected</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">whether the minister failed to consider properly the compliance of the trial with constitutional and other requirements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1037">whether the minister failed to review the court transcript of the applicant's trial</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1037">On 30 July 2007 the applicant made a civil application in the Queensland Supreme Court for declaratory relief. The grounds upon which Mr Nudd relied were the two grounds abandoned in his previous matter before the Queensland Court of Appeal, namely grounds relating to the validity of the arrest warrant and the ensuing extradition process. In dismissing the application, Byrne J said: 
 
 None of the several complaints of invalidity of process and impropriety of conduct on the part of officers of the Commonwealth alleged looks to have merit. But it is unnecessary to consider either the challenges to the processes and decisions that attended the issue in this State of a warrant for his apprehension of the American extradition proceedings that resulted in his return to Australia to face his trial. 
 

 
 
 The declarations sought should be refused on the footing that the grant of such relief could not serve any useful purpose. 
 

 6. Nudd v Australian Federal Police [2007] FCA 2114 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 - SECT 9A Limitation of jurisdiction to review related criminal justice process decisions</title>
<title id="l2">CUSTOMS ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l3">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l4">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 39B Original jurisdiction of Federal Court of Australia</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l6">JUSTICES ACT 1886 </title>
<title id="l7">JUSTICES ACT 1886 - SECT 57 57 Cases in which warrants may be issued</title>
</legistitles>
</case>