<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jardein Pty Ltd, in the matter of All Colour Media Printing (Victoria) Pty Ltd v Stathakis [2007] FCA 29 (29 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/29.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">austudy payments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">whether full-time student</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">cessation of study</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">whether administrative error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">claimed financial hardship</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">whether special circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">whether debt should be waived</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">ssat decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1659">aat review</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] AATA 1659">The term ' special circumstances' is not defined in the Act, however the Federal Court and the Administrative Appeals Tribunal have considered the issue in fine detail on a number of occasions. Some key principles and issues emerge: (a) each case must be judged on its merits and involve factors or circumstances outside the norm ( Re Beadle and DGSS (1984) 6 ALD 1 , also Dranichnikov v Centrelink (2003) FCAFC 133) ; (b) financial hardship must be considered, but there must be other significant factors as well ( SDSS v Hales (1958) 82 FCR 162 ); (c) the circumstances must be such that it would be unjust, unreasonable or inappropriate for the debt to be recovered ( Ivovic and DGSS (1981) 3 ALD N95) ; (d) the power to waiver is discretionary and must be based on reasons, rationality, purposiveness and morality, with discretion being exercised consistent with the spirit and purpose of legislation (see Rigney and SDFCS (2000) AATA 640 , also Kuipers and SDSS (1998) 52 ALD 663) ; (e) In the recent case of Angelakos and DEWR (2007) FCA 29 January, it was determined that the Secretary is not obliged to waive the debt even if the three conditions of Section 1237 AAD of the Act are satisfied. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>