<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Wotton v Queensland [2007] FCA 280 (2 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/280.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">high court and federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">representative proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) pt iva</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">criteria for representative proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">s 33c</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">application for extension of time to bring proceedings as a representative party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">whether such application is itself representative proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">need for substantial common issue of fact or law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">the application for extension of time not a representative proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">no substantial common issue of fact or shared by applicants and proposed group members on issue of extension of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">pt iva not engaged   human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">s 46po human rights and equal opportunities commission act 1986 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">extension of time under s 46po(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">purported representative proceeding under pt iva federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">application made out of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">no substantial common issue of fact or law for the application for extension of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">no representative proceeding commenced until court extends time under s 46po(2)   costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">proceedings discontinued by leave under o 22 r 2(1)(d)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">purported representative proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">whether proceedings commenced for improper purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">no reasonable prospect of obtaining relief sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">proceedings incompetently presented</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 758">party and party costs ordered</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 758">On 1 March 2007, shortly before his trial was to commence Mr Wotton lodged a complaint with the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (as the Australian Human Rights Commission was then called). The complaint alleged, among other matters, that the arrest, charging and prosecution of Mr Wotton contravened or would contravene the Racial Discrimination Act 1975 (Cth). Mr Wotton sought an ex parte injunction under s 46PP of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act to restrain the holding of his criminal trial: Wotton v State of Queensland [2007] FCA 280. Those proceedings purported to be instituted as representative proceedings under Pt IVA of the Federal Court of Australia Act . In refusing the ex parte relief, Moore J noted that there had been considerable delay in the lodging of the complaint with the Commission: Wotton [2007] FCA 280 at [3] - [5]. His Honour said that he would express no view about whether those proceedings could have been brought as representative proceedings. Subsequently, at his trial Mr Wotton was convicted and sentenced to a term of imprisonment.  On 1 March 2007, shortly before his trial was to commence Mr Wotton lodged a complaint with the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (as the Australian Human Rights Commission was then called). The complaint alleged, among other matters, that the arrest, charging and prosecution of Mr Wotton contravened or would contravene the Racial Discrimination Act 1975 (Cth). Mr Wotton sought an ex parte injunction under s 46PP of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act to restrain the holding of his criminal trial: Wotton v State of Queensland [2007] FCA 280. Those proceedings purported to be instituted as representative proceedings under Pt IVA of the Federal Court of Australia Act . In refusing the ex parte relief, Moore J noted that there had been considerable delay in the lodging of the complaint with the Commission: Wotton [2007] FCA 280 at [3] - [5]. His Honour said that he would express no view about whether those proceedings could have been brought as representative proceedings. Subsequently, at his trial Mr Wotton was convicted and sentenced to a term of imprisonment. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">RACIAL DISCRIMINATION ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l3">CRIMINAL CODE 1899 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>