<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 (18 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2033.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">penalty hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">admitted contraventions of transport workers award 1998</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">underpayment of wages to employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">where multiple breaches of award arose out of single course of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">relevant considerations in determining level of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1080">penalty determined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">stoppage of work because of death of employee on unrelated site</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">claim by union for employees to be paid for period of stoppage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">industrial action in support of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">whether claim reasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">admitted breaches of statutory prohibition on payment for period of industrial action and on claiming payment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">penalty agreed to by employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">whether within permissible range</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">appropriate penalty for breach by union. workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">statutory prohibition on making payment to employee for period of industrial action and on claiming such payment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">union claim that numerous employees should be paid for single period of industrial action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">employees paid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">whether one breach or multiple breaches of statute. penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">contravention of statutory prohibition on making payment to employee for period of industrial action and on claiming such payment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">agreement between applicant and employer on amount of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">whether within permissible range</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">seriousness of breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">factors to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">objects of statute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.19" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">individual and general deterrence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.20" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 65">totality principle.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1302">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of compensation pursuant to s 298u of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) in respect of contraventions of s 298k</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the assessment of a penalty pursuant to s 298u</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of whether a penalty so ordered ought to be paid to the individuals affected by the conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1302">consideration of the scope of declarations to be made.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">[ database search ] [ name search ] [ recent decisions ] [ noteup ] [ lawcite ] [ help ] n w frozen foods proprietary ltd v australian competition &amp; consumer commission [1996] fca 1134 (20 december 1996)    trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">penalties under s.76 for contraventions of part iv</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">price fixing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">effect of agreement between a.c.c.c. and corporation on joint submissions proposing particular orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">desirability of settlement of such cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">penalty cases not criminal prosecutions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">matters relevant to penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">object of ensuring compliance with the act by deterrence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">effect of undertaking by corporation of a compliance programme agreed with the commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">difficulties in comparing penalties in other cases with that proposed for the instant case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">importance of the particular market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">significance of identity of corporation to be penalised where it was a member of a group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">significance of whether a corporation has previously contravened</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">inappropriateness of diminishing the credit to be given a corporation for co-operation and admission of liability by reference to any costs saving it may achieve thereby</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">reference to u.s. law conceding the u.s. federal trade commission "a special competence in formulating remedies"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">discussion of the question for the court where penalty is the subject of an agreed joint submission.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">penalty hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">unlawful building industrial action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">admitted contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">considerations on penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 145">agreed penalty.  building and construction industry improvement act 2005 (cth) ss.37 , 38 , 69  stuart-mahoney v construction, forestry, mining and energy union [2008] fca 1426  ponzio v b &amp; p caelli constructions pty ltd (2007) 158 fcr 543  construction forestry mining &amp; energy union v coal &amp; allied operations pty ltd (no.2) [1999] fca 1714 ; (1999) 94 ir 231  australian ophthalmic supplies pty limited v mcalary-smith [2008] fcafc 8 ; (2008) 165 fcr 560</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 32">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 32">strike action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 32">penalty for breach of s.38 of building and construction industry improvement act 2005 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 32">agreement reached concerning breaches and penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">australian workplace agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">civil penalty provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">contraventions of ss.342(1) and 341 (1) of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">procedural and technical breaches only</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 31">penalty agreed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">penalty hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">unlawful building industrial action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">admitted contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">considerations on penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 786">agreed penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 989">industrial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 989">unions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 989">right of entry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 989">entry refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 989">appropriate penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">application for civil penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">breach of applicable provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">breaches admitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">agreed penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 265">considerations as to penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">conduct of employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">pre-work choices regime</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">duress applied where 5 persons to sign awa's</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">whether proceedings properly brought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 36">agreed facts and penalty factors to consider.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1355">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1355">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1355">declarations of breach of awards and workplace relations act.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 145">The principles which should be applied by the Court with respect to an agreed penalty have been set out in a number of decisions of the Federal Court [16] are well established and were referred to by the parties in their submissions. [17] The agreed penalties range between 25-30 per cent of the maximum for the contraventions. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FMCA 32">I accept the submission put by counsel for each of the parties that where the parties agree on a penalty, the court should not disturb it unless it falls outside the appropriate range. This approach is supported by recent authority. In Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 , a case also concerned with an agreed penalty for breach of industrial legislation, Tracey J came to the same view stating at para.7 of his reasons; "The court is not bound to accept and impose these proposed penalties but will do so if persuaded that, in all the circumstances, they fall within the permissible range: Cf NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Consumer and Competition Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 290-1. In Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 ; (2007) 158 FCR 543 at 565, Jessop J expressed the view, with which I respectfully agree, that the phrase "permissible range" in this context "refers to a range which would be permitted by the court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2011] FMCA 31">In Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 , a case also concerning an agreed penalty for breach by an employer of the Act, Tracey J came to the same view stating at paragraph 7 of his reasons: "The court is not bound to accept and impose these proposed penalties but will do so if persuaded that, in all the circumstances, they fall within the permissible range: NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 290-1.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FMCA 786">The submissions filed on behalf of the parties helpfully summarised the principles which should be applied by the Court with respect to an agreed penalty. In submissions filed on behalf of the applicant it was contended as follows: "23. The principles with respect to agreed penalty are that:- a) in cases where parties have agreed on proposed penalties, the Court is not bound to impose those penalties but will do so if it is satisfied that the proposed penalties fall within " the permissible range "; [14] b) in this respect, the " permissible range " of penalties refers to a range " which would be permitted by the Court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive " [15] c) there is a public interest in promoting settlement of litigation, particularly where it is likely to be lengthy. Accordingly, when the regulator and contravener have reached agreement, they may present to the Court a statement of facts and opinions as to the effect of those facts, together with joint submissions as to the appropriate penalty to be imposed; [16] d) the view of the regulator, as a specialist body, is a relevant, but not determinative consideration on the question of penalty; [17] e) in determining whether the proposed penalty is appropriate, the Court examines all the circumstances of the case. Where the parties have put forward an agreed statement of facts, the Court may act on that statement if it is appropriate to do so; [18] and f) where the parties have jointly proposed a penalty, it will not be useful to investigate whether the Court would have arrived at that precise figure in the absence of agreement. The question is whether that figure is, in the Court's view, appropriate in the circumstances of the case. In answering that question, the Court will not reject the agreed figure simply because it would have been disposed to select some other figure. It will be appropriate if within the permissible range. [19] " [20] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 989">As I observed in Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 at [7] : 
 
 "The Court is not bound to accept and impose ... proposed penalties but will do so if persuaded that, in all the circumstances, they fall within the permissible range: Cf NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 290-1. In Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 ; (2007) 158 FCR 543 at 565 Jessup J expressed the view, with which I respectfully agree, that the phrase "permissible range" in this context "refers to a range which would be permitted by the court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive. "" 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2009] FMCA 265">At paragraph [21] of exhibit "A2", the applicant referred to decisions of the Federal Court, including the decision of Jessup J in Wells v Locarno Management Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1034 and the decision of Buchanan J in Alfred v Lanscar [2007] FCA 1001 and said: "21. In cases where parties have agreed on proposed penalties, the Court is not bound to impose those penalties but will do so if it is satisfied that the proposed penalties fall within "the permissible range": Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 at [7] per Tracey J, Wells v Locarno Management Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1034 at [23] per Jessup J, Alfred v Lanscar [2007] FCA 1001 ; [2007] 167 IR 320 at [15] per Buchanan J. In this respect, the "permissible range" of penalties refers to a range "which would be permitted by the Court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive": Wells at [23] per Jessup J. As Jessup J said in Wells : 'The predictability involved in the resolution of penal proceedings in accordance with a pre-trial agreement reached by the parties is something which should, as a matter of public policy, be regarded as beneficial' (ibid). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2009] FMCA 36">It was submitted by the parties that whilst it is ultimately for the Court to fix the appropriate penalty, where the parties agree on a penalty, the Court should not disturb it unless if falls outside the appropriate range. This approach is supported by recent authority. In Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 , a case also concerning an agreed penalty for breach by an employer of the Act, Tracey J came to the same view stating at para.7 of his reasons; "The Court is not bound to accept and impose these proposed penalties but will do so if persuaded that, in all the circumstances, they fall within the permissible range: cf NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Consumer and Competition Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285 at 290-1. In Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd (2007) 158 FCR 543 at 565 Jessup J expressed the view, with which I respectfully agree, that the phrase "permissible range" in this context "refers to a range which would be permitted by the court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2008] FMCA 1355">The first respondent refers to the following passage from the decision of Justice Jessup in Wells v Locarno Management [2008] FCA 1034 at 23 as follows: "The court is not bound by the agreement of the parties as to the level of penalty which should be imposed in a case such as the present. However, the court will not depart from an agreed figure merely because it might otherwise have been disposed to award some other figure. The predictability involved in the resolution of penal proceedings in accordance with a pre-trial agreement reached by the parties is something which should, as a matter of public policy, be regarded as beneficial. Only where the agreed penalty falls outside the permissible range should the court depart from the figure agreed by the parties. In this context, the permissible range is the range which would be permitted by the court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive. See NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (1996) 71 FCR 285, 290-91; Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] ATPR 41-993, [53]; Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 ; [2007] FCAFC 65 ; (2007) 158 FCR 543 , 565; and Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 ; (2007) 169 IR 327 , 329. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs8" from="[2008] FCA 1034">23 The court is not bound by the agreement of the parties as to the level of penalty which should be imposed in a case such as the present. However, the court will not depart from an agreed figure merely because it might otherwise have been disposed to award some other figure. The predictability involved in the resolution of penal proceedings in accordance with a pre-trial agreement reached by the parties is something which should, as a matter of public policy, be regarded as beneficial. Only where the agreed penalty falls outside the permissible range should the court depart from the figure agreed by the parties. In this context, the permissible range is the range which would be permitted by the court, that is, a range within which the penalty is neither manifestly inadequate nor manifestly excessive. See NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 , 290-91; Minister for Industry, Tourism and Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd [2004] FCAFC 72 ; [2004] ATPR 41-993 , [53]; Ponzio v B &amp; P Caelli Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 65 ; (2007) 158 FCR 543 , 565; and Hills v Sutton [2007] FCA 2033 ; (2007) 169 IR 327 , 329. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>