<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission; In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd ACN 099 071 968 v Carey (No 11) [2007] FCA 21 (12 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/21.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">review of decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no failure to consider relevant facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">adverse credibility finding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">findings open to the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no failure to afford applicant procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no failure to apply the correct test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no failure to consider integers of applicant's</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no failure to consider applicant's claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 361">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">appointment of receivers to property of directors and officers of corporate group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">asset preservation orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">pending investigation by australian securities and investments commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">possible liabilities of defendants to third parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">extension of appointment of receivers and of associated orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">whether extension warranted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">whether lesser form of orders not involving court appointed receivers should be made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 35">orders for continuation of appointment of receivers made</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FMCA 361">It must be said that particular four is expressed in terms often seen in this Court. It is unfortunately the case that the mere repetition of this complaint appearing in a large number of applications put before this Court, does not assist in understanding the exact nature of the complaint. If it is a complaint about the Tribunal's choice and use of country information, and in relation to the way the Tribunal dealt with the applicant's claims to be suspected of having a political profile, then again this complaint does not succeed. Such choice, use and weight to be accorded to country information, it is a matter for the Tribunal ( NAHR v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 21 (" NAHR ")). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 35">47 In recent proceedings relating to the payment of insurance premiums by Realty in respect of property owned by other entities, Mr McMaster gave oral evidence before the Court that Westpoint Realty was not solvent. Westpoint Realty was not represented on that occasion but has subsequently appointed a voluntary administrator. As to the short reasons for judgment authorising payment by Westpoint Realty of a premium for short term insurance in relation to property belonging to other owners see: Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 11) [2007] FCA 21. The receivers were of the view prior to the appointment of the administrator that the current orders represent an appropriate regime to preserve the company's assets.  21 Other orders varying the Receiver Orders to meet particular contingencies were made on 23 November 2006 and 12 January 2007: Australian Securities and Investments Commission, In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 10) [2006] FCA 1617 and Australian Securities and Investments Commission; In the matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 11) [2007] FCA 21. 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>