<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pull v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20 (23 January 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/20.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs v nystrom  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">cancellation of visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">s 501(2) of the migration act 1958 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where minister purported to cancel a "transitional (permanent) visa" on the basis of the respondent failing the character test in s 501(6) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where respondent had a substantial criminal record</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where respondent had lived in australia since he was 27 days old</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where respondent held an "absorbed person visa"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether the respondent also held a "transitional (permanent) visa"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether as a matter of construction the act allowed the respondent to hold both an "absorbed person visa" and a "transitional (permanent) visa".  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">decision of minister under s 501(2) or s 503 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether there was a misdescription of a visa which invalidated the minister's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether a failure to take into account relevant considerations invalidated a decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether the minister's cancellation of a "transitional (permanent) visa" and disregard of the "absorbed person visa" amounted to jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where s 501f(3) would operate to cancel both visas.  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">statutory construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">expressum facit cessare tacitum</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where s 201 of the act excludes certain persons from the scope of the minister's power to deport pursuant to s 200 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">where the respondent was a person covered by s 201 and also not an object of the power to deport pursuant to s 200</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether s 201 of the act confers a protection against deportation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether the subject matter of ss 200 , 201 and 501 of the act is the same, dealing with the removal of persons who have been convicted of offences from australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether the minister's lack of power to deport the respondent under s 200 limits the minister's power to cancel a visa under s 501</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 50">whether s 501 repugnant to ss 200 and 201 so as to necessitate s 501 being read subject to ss 200 and 201 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 121">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 121">decision to cancel transitional (permanent) visa on character grounds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 121">where appellant arrived in australia aged 27 days old</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 121">where minister failed to consider whether appellant held absorbed person visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 121">where minister failed to consider effect of cancellation on absorbed person visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">minister's discretion to cancel visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">whether impermissibly fettered by application of direction no 17</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">inference to be drawn in absence of reasons for minister's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">effect of references in briefing paper furnished to the minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">whether cancellation of visa of resident in australia from the age of 18 months a valid exercise of the power conferred by s 501(2) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 106">whether deportation of appellant a valid exercise of power with respect to aliens under s 51(xix) of the constitution .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">minister cancels visa under s 501(2) of the migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">scope of minister's discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">whether the provision should be read down to exclude considerations that are 'punitive' in character</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">whether any potential conflict with chapter iii of the constitution by purporting to rest judicial power in the minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">whether decisions giving weight to the need to protect the community are punitive in character  migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">minister cancels visa under s 501(2) of the migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">best interests of the children</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 151">whether minister under obligation to make further inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">cancellation of visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">failure to pass character test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">purported cancellation of 444-special category visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">national of new zealand living in australia since 1981</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">whether deemed holder of absorbed person's visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">whether ceased to be an immigrant at 2 april 1984</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">criteria of absorption into community</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">child</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">part of family unit migrating to australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">cancellation of non-existent deemed visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">visa actually held not subject to ministerial decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">cancellation decision invalid  constitutional law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.14" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">limits of immigration power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.15" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">cessation of immigrant status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.16" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">membership of community</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.17" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">absorption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.18" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">criteria</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.19" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">child</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.20" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 137">part of family unit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">shaw v minister for immigration and multicultural affairs  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">powers of the parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">naturalisation and aliens</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">applicant born in united kingdom</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">applicant entered australia in 1974</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">applicant did not acquire australian citizenship</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">cancellation of applicant's visa by minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether power of cancellation validly extended to applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether applicant an "alien" for purposes of s 51(xix) of the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether applicant's statutory status as "british subject" at time of entry into australia inconsistent with classification as "alien"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether applicant a "subject of the queen" for purposes of s 117 of the constitution .  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">powers of the parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether applicant subject to removal under power with respect to immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether applicant subject to removal under power with respect to external affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 72">whether implied nationhood power relevant.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 747">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 747">where non-discontinuing party changes position rendering a significant component of the proceedings redundant and the other significant component practically futile</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 747">whether the discontinuing party should have his costs of the application.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">cancellation of visa by minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">substantial and serious criminal record of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">application for review, prohibition and certiorari</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">limited to jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged failure to give weight to essential factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged absence of evidence on which to reach conclusion as to view of australian public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged failure to consider recent untested criminal charges migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged violent and unlawful arrest, detention and removal including alleged deprivation of opportunity to obtain legal advice and representation regarding the minister's visa cancellation decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">no finding made to support alleged claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">return residence (class bb) visa, subclass 155 (five year resident return)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">discretion to cancel visa where applicant fails character test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">substantial criminal record</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">ministerial direction no. 21</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">primary and other considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">applicant had difficult childhood and lack of education in vietnam</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">applicant accepted into australia as a refugee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">applicant became addicted to heroin</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">evidence of support from family and employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">held that tribunal can have regard to information elicited in cross-examination or in amplification of material previously provided notwithstanding that it had not been given to the respondent at least 2 business days before the hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">meaning of "non-disclosable information"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.12" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">extent to which tribunal should consider merits of potential action for breach of confidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.13" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">held that certain information not to be non-disclosable since it had previously been disclosed to the applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.14" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">weight to be attached to non-disclosable information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.15" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1319">decision under review affirmed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">appeal from decision of administrative appeals tribunal affirming decision of delegate of first respondent minister to cancel applicant's visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">where applicant citizen of new zealand holding special category visa in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">where applicant convicted of serious criminal offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">where minister cancelled applicant's visa pursuant to s 501(2) of migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">where applicant purported to appeal under s 44 of administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">whether appeal under administrative appeals tribunal act competent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">whether power conferred by s 501(2) of migration act 1958 (cth) limited or supplanted by terms of s 200 and s 201 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">whether power to cancel visa exercised used for punitive purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">whether tribunal member failed to give proper consideration to relevant matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">whether tribunal member took expectations of australian community into account.  held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">appeal under s 44 of administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth) incompetent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">decision excluded from scope of s 44 even if in excess of jurisdiction or resulting from failure to exercise jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">s 501 of migration act 1958 (cth) not limited by s 200 and s 201</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.14" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">no evidence tribunal member exercised power for improper or punitive purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.15" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">tribunal member gave proper consideration to matters identified by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.16" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">tribunal member did take expectations of australian community into account</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.17" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 80">appeal dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 747">(4) At the directions hearing on 3 June 2009, the Minister appeared to invite the applicant to clarify his TP visa status, suggesting that his s 195A visa was only temporary. The applicant also has no interest in acceding to such a request; he does not favour the possession of a TP visa over his current s 195A visa. It has been, and remains, common ground that the applicant fails the 'character test' under s 501 of the Act ( Pull v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20). Any TP visa held by the applicant would be vulnerable to a new cancellation on this ground. Even if he did have such an interest, such an interest is insufficient to constitute a matter in federal jurisdiction ( Griffith University v Tang [2005] HCA 7 ; (2005) 221 CLR 99 at [90] ).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 54">111 Ground 1(b), if not expressly abandoned was certainly not pursued at the hearing. As I perceived it, Mr Morrison appeared to acknowledge through counsel that as in the case of M238 of 2002 [2003] FCAFC 260 at [59] and as had also occurred in Pull [2007] FCA 20 , while the Minister did not have specific evidence before him as to the expectations of the Australian community in relation to the factors outlined in these grounds, nevertheless, the Minister formed his own evaluative judgement as he was entitled to do. It was not necessary for the Minister to make specific reference to every item which Mr Morrison would wish the Minister to record. Further, it does appear to me in substance again that this is an attack on the merits of the decision rather than a ground of judicial review.  110 Similarly, in the present situation there is no doubt that the Minister was aware and recorded the fact that Mr Morrison had children and stepchildren and in considering the matter of the best interests of the children he recorded that the children would suffer hardship relating to the loss of a father figure and that his removal from Australia would cause hardship to the children. He recorded that it would possibly be difficult for Mr Morrison's family to cope financially and for Ms Roberts to cope with six children. As in the case of Pull [2007] FCA 20 (in relation to the Tribunal), the Minister clearly took into account the hardship relating to Mr Morrison's children and clearly gave genuine consideration to that issue.  109 In Pull v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20 at [42] a similar claim was made. The applicant in Pull considered that the Tribunal (the Administrative Appeals Tribunal) had not given genuine and proper consideration to the expectations of the Australian community because the Tribunal member did not refer to certain matters including that the applicant had 'two daughters who are Australian citizens and there is no evidence to suggest that they will ever be able to renew their relationship with the applicant'. At the time that those proceedings were commenced, s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) did not (by reason of s 483 of the Act) apply to a privative clause decision. Therefore, it followed that to succeed the applicant was required to show that the Tribunal committed a jurisdictional error. As observed by Besanko J at [43]:
 
 There can be no doubt that the Tribunal member considered the expectations of the Australian community and it does not follow that simply because he did not mention or place emphasis on particular matters identified by the applicant that he failed to give the matter genuine and proper consideration. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] AATA 1319">I refer also to Deputy President McMahon's comment in Re Leha and Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2000] AATA 1054 at [34] , that there would also be a general expectation in the community that the Act will be administered fairly and humanely. It is also relevant to take into account that the applicant has already been punished by the Courts by which he was convicted, and his visa should not be cancelled in order to impose some further form of punishment: Pull v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20 at 43, per Selway J at first instance; Re Suardana and Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (1980) 2 ALD 830 at 832 --- 833. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 80">Therefore, it fails. ' 
 

The reasoning of Gummow and Heydon JJ was to similar effect (at [60]-[70]). I applied this reasoning in the recent decision of Pull v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2007] FCA 20 at [31] - [33] (' Pull '). That case was also a case where the visa holder was not liable to deportation under s 200 of the Act.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l3">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 51 Legislative powers of the Parliament [see Notes 10 and 11]</title>
<title id="l4">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l5">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 78B Notice to Attorneys-General</title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l7">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 82 When visas cease to be in effect</title>
<title id="l8">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 200 Deportation of certain non-citizens</title>
<title id="l9">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 201 Deportation of non-citizens in Australia for less than 10 years who are convicted of crimes</title>
<title id="l10">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 483 Section 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975</title>
<title id="l11">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 499 Minister may give directions</title>
<title id="l12">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 501 Refusal or cancellation of visa on character grounds</title>
<title id="l13">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 502 Minister may decide in the national interest that certain persons are to be excluded persons</title>
<title id="l14">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l15">MIGRATION REFORM (TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS) REGULATIONS </title>
</legistitles>
</case>