<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>I.G.T. (Australia) Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2009 (13 December 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/2009.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">whether extension of time for patent valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">whether commissioner misconstrued s 70 of the patents act in extending the term of the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">registration and listing of goods under the therapeutic goods act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">whether the first regulatory approval date is the date on which substance was entered into the part of the therapeutic register relating to registered goods or the date on which the substance was entered into the therapeutic register relating to listed goods  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">leave to appeal required for an appeal under s 158 of the patents act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 190">whether clear prima facie error required in the reasons of the primary judge</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 73">17 Section 25(2) of the Federal Court Act , under which applications for leave to appeal may be heard and determined by a single Judge or by a Full Court, has so provided for many years. However, it was not until August 2005 that r 2AA was inserted into O 52 of the Rules of Court. That rule sets up a presumption that an application of the kind referred to in s 25(2) of the Federal Court Act will be heard by a single Judge. Save for the unopposed matter which came before Buchanan J in IGT (Australia) Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Technologies Australia Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 2009 , counsel were unable to refer me to any judgment of a single Judge of the court disposing of an application for leave under s 195(2) of the Act or under s 158(2) of the Patents Act . I note that Woolworths was argued in May 2005, some months before the introduction of r 2AA. Pfizer was argued on 21 November 2006, but the judgment as reported does not indicate how the matter came to be heard by a Full Court, rather than a single Judge. One may, with respect, pause to wonder whether, when they used the term "clear prima facie case of error", their Honours in Woolworths and Pfizer had consciously in mind the disposition of an application for leave by a single Judge of the court.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 158 Appeals</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>