<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston [2007] FCA 386 (26 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/386.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">powers of commonwealth parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">restrictive trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">retail price maintenance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">judicial power of commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">power to grant injunction restraining persons from engaging in retail price maintenance practice invested in commonwealth industrial court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">whether within judicial power of the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">freedom of inter-state trade and commerce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">prohibition of retail price maintenance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">whether permissible regulation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">the constitution (63 &amp; 64 vict. c. 12), ss. 51 (i.), (xx.), 71 , 92</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">trade practices act 1965-1971 (cth), ss. 66b (2), 90aa.  restraint of trade</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">restrictive practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">retail price maintenance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">withholding of supply of goods to retailer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">withholding "for the reason that" retailer likely to sell below recommended price</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">reason for withholding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">price specified as price below &amp;which the goods not to be sold</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">whether a recommended price a "specified" price</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">power of industrial court to make restraining order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[1972] HCA 69">trade practices act 1965-1971 (cth), ss. 66b (2), 90aa.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">leases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">deductions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">improvements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">land used for the purpose of producing assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">premium</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">assent to the grant of a lease</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1970] HCA 51">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1963 (cth), ss. 83, 88.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">exemptions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">trust seeking endorsement as a charitable institution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">whether trust satisfied sole purpose test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">proof of application for purpose for which established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">debit balances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">use of fund in interest offset transaction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">overpayment to trustees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">uncommercial loans</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">distribution to individuals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">jurisdictional issues</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">effective date of endorsement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2008] AATA 275">decision under review is set aside.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 40">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 40">access</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 40">whether csiro exempt from operation of freedom of information act 1982 (cth) in respect of particular documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 40">whether documents requested in respect of its commercial activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 40">(cth) freedom of information act 1982 ss 3(1) , 3 (2), 4 (1), 7 (2), 7 (2aa), 7 (3), 7 (4), 11 (1), 43a, div 1 of pt ii of schedule 2.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1685">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1685">whether australia post exempt from operation of freedom of information act 1982 in relation to mail contractor management manual</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1685">whether manual in respect of its commercial activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1685">decision affirmed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">whether csiro exempt from operation of freedom of information act 1982</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">whether documents required are in request of its commercial activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">whether documents are in relation to documents in respect of its commercial activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">respondent exempt from operation of freedom of information act 1982 in relation to documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2007] AATA 1569">further consideration adjourned.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 546">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 546">disposition of the question of reserved costs arising out of judgment in australian postal corporation v johnston [2007] fca 386</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] AATA 275">The "is applied" criterion in the opening lines of ITAA s 97 s50-60, unlike those in the immediately following paragraphs, does not include any adverbial qualification requiring exclusivity of purpose. Purpose is itself a frequently used criterion in many different legal contexts. Concerted trade conduct is proscribed where it is engaged in for "real" or "dominant" purpose of causing loss to another: News Ltd v Australian Rugby Football League Ltd (1996) 135 ALR 33. Legislative provisions commonly render documents immune from disclosure under Freedom of Information legislation where they were brought into existence for the purpose of commercial activities: Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston [2007] FCA 386 ; (2007) 94 ALD 586 at Greenwood J (FCA). Expenses incurred in relation to the use of property "for the purpose of producing assessable income" may be deductible for income tax purposes: National Mutual Life Association v Commissioner of Taxation [1970] HCA 51 ; (1970) 122 CLR 13 at 22 per Gibbs J. In all these contexts exclusivity of purpose is not required. Often it is sufficient if the relevant purpose was an operative and substantial reason for the conduct in question: Mikasa (NSW) Ltd v Festival Stores [1972] HCA 69 ; (1972) 127 CLR 617 per Barwick CJ at 634; Secretary, Department of Treasury and Finance v Dalla-Riva [2007] VSCA 11 FOI Act Buchanan JA at [13]; Hook v Rolfe (1986) 7 NSWLR 40 at 44, 45. Sometimes the purpose criterion will be interpreted to refer to the dominant or main purpose of the hypothesised conduct. In that context it is particularly apt to note that in determining whether an entity was "established" for a purpose that gave rise to an income tax exemption, it has been held that the enquiry is to determine the main object or purpose of the entity's activities in the relevant income year: Royal Australian College of Surgeons v Commissioner of Taxation [1943] HCA 34 ; (1943) 68 CLR 436. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCAFC 40">18 There was, according to the Tribunal, a difference between Bennett J's analysis in Australian Broadcasting Corporation v The University of Technology, Sydney [2006] FCA 964 ; (2006) 154 FCR 209 ( ABC ) and Greenwood J's approach in Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston [2007] FCA 386 ; (2007) 94 ALD 586 ( Australia Post ). The Tribunal considered that its preferred construction was consistent with Australia Post and not with ABC , although the differences in approach would not have led to different outcomes in the current case. In the event this latter conclusion was incorrect, the Tribunal went on at the end of its reasons to consider "the matter from both points of view".</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] AATA 1685">50. In Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston , [52] Greenwood J considered the meaning of the expression " for the purposes of " in the context of s 7(4) of the FOI Act. His Honour was concerned with whether Australia Post was exempt from the operation of the FOI Act in relation to a list of licensed post offices (LPOs) on the basis that the list was in respect of its commercial activities. He posed the question in this way:
 
" The sole question to be determined by the tribunal was whether the list is a document in respect of Australia Post's commercial activities by determining whether the document was brought into existence in the course of or for the purposes of the carrying on of those activities. That test required the Tribunal to determine, on the evidence, the purposes for which the list was brought into existence; whether there was one or more purposes; and if more than one purpose, including a purpose of carrying on Australia Post's commercial activities, whether that purpose was a substantial purpose. " [53] 
 
 
  The same is true of the other services within its reserved services. This is consistent with the conclusion reached by Greenwood J in Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston . [57] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] AATA 1569">Greenwood J decided Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston [60] some nine months after Australian Broadcasting Corporation v The University of Technology, Sydney . " [70] 
 
 
95. " [61] 
 
 
 The applicable law 
 
 
83.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 546">
 
1 On 26 March 2007 the court delivered judgment in Australian Postal Corporation v Johnston [2007] FCA 386 and reserved the question of the costs of the appeal by way of an application pursuant to s 44(1) of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 with submissions to be received in relation to the disposition of the costs by Monday 2 April 2007. The court allowed the appeal, set aside the decision of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal and affirmed the decision under review. The applicant has filed submissions with the court and does not seek an order that the respondent pay its costs of the appeal.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">AUSTRALIAN POSTAL CORPORATION ACT 1989 </title>
<title id="l2">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l3">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 44 Disqualification</title>
<title id="l4">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 </title>
<title id="l5">FREEDOM OF INFORMATION ACT 1982 - SECT 7 Exemption of certain persons and bodies</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>