<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 (14 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/346.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">rural press limited v australian competition and consumer commission  australian competition and consumer commission v rural press limited  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">exclusionary provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">arrangement between regional newspaper publishers providing that one would withdraw newspaper services from the prime circulation area of the other</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether provision had purpose of preventing, restricting or limiting supply of services to, or acquisition of services from, particular persons or classes of persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss 4d, 45 (2)(a)(i), 45 (2)(b)(i).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">where regional newspaper publisher threatened to circulate new newspaper in prime circulation area of a second regional newspaper publisher, unless second publisher ceased circulation of its own newspaper in first publisher's prime circulation area</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">where second publisher subsequently ceased circulation of newspaper in first publisher's prime circulation area</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether an "arrangement"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether arrangement had purpose or effect of substantially lessening competition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss 45(2)(a)(ii) , 45 (2)(b)(ii).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">accessorial liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether officers of newspaper publisher were "involved in" publisher's contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether officers participated in or assented to contraventions with actual knowledge of essential elements constituting the contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss 75b(1), 76 (1), 80 (1).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">misuse of market power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">whether publisher took advantage of market power in its prime circulation area in threatening to enter prime circulation area of second publisher</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">trade practices act 1974 (cth), s 46(1).  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 75">form of declarations.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">appeal from federal magistrates court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">requirements under section 789 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">meaning of intent to coerce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">liability of state union branches under part 16 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">appellate jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">findings of fact based on credibility assessment by court at first instance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">review of evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">appellable error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 13">approach to be taken by appellate court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of a pecuniary penalty to be imposed on three respondent unions in respect of contraventions of s 767(1) and s 768(1) of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) arising out of entry by officials of the unions to premises at the abbot point coal terminal on 13 february 2009 and entry to those premises by officials of two respondent unions on 5 march 2009</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of the criteria to be applied in determining the amount of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of previous contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of the objects of the legislation, the counter-factual, context and circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of whether a pecuniary penalty ought to be paid to the applicant or to the commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of whether an order for costs ought to be made in favour of the applicant under s 824 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 865">consideration of the continuing application of that act by operation of the fair work (transitional provisions and consequential amendments) act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">freedom of association</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">false or misleading representation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">standard of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">hearing on liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 355">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">certified agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">coercion of contractor to make a certified agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">whether union delegate represented to contractor that certified agreement was mandatory to work on unionised construction site</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">whether false or misleading representation made about contractor's obligation to join an industrial association industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">organising to take action, or threatening to organise or take action, with intent to coerce another person not to engage, allocate particular responsibilities to, or have particular duties or responsibilities designated to, a building contractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">whether union delegates engaged in such conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1267">whether negotiations or discussions with management amount to such conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">freedom of association</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">pt.16 workplace relations act 1996</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">protections under s.793(1) require freedom of association nexus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">workcover nsw not a "person or body" referred to in s.793(1)(j)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">reverse onus of proof under s.809(1) will not operate unless there is an allegation which satisfies the criteria of the provision allegedly contravened.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">meaning of "no reasonable prospects of success"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">application for leave to amend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.8" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">amendment would have no reasonable prospects of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.9" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">amendment futile</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.10" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 845">leave refused.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 197">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 197">representation made by union officer about employees' obligation to join union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 197">finding by primary judge that union official did not understand what he said was wrong</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 197">whether contravention of s 298sc requires that representation was intentionally false or misleading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 197">whether representation that is false or misleading in fact contravenes s 298sc</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">union officials seeking to enter enterprise bargaining agreement under div 2 of pt vib of the workplace relations act with developer-contractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">threat of disruption to work and disruptive conduct with intent to coerce developer-contractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">whether unlawful, illegitimate or unconscionable pressure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">liability of unions for conduct of officials  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">freedom of association</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">whether false and misleading representation made about a person's obligation to join an industrial association  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">restrictive trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">secondary boycotts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">conduct of union officials which hindered or prevented services being acquired by contractor from subcontractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">subcontract terminated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">whether with purpose or likely effect of injuring subcontractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.12" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">liability of unions for conduct of officials tort</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.13" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">inducing breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.14" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">union officials inducing breach of contract for services made between contractor and subcontractor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.15" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">union officials' knowledge of existence of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.16" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">vicarious liability of unions for actions of its officials</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.17" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1047">nature of contract</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCAFC 13">First, s 783(c) was also apt to refer to the conduct carried out by Mr Manna. His conduct was taken to be the conduct of the New South Wales branch if it was carried out by him as an "officer of [the New South Wales branch] acting in that capacity" (s 779(2) of the WR Act). On the evidence Mr Manna had been an officer of the CFMEU and the New South Wales branch almost continuously for about 29 years. In that capacity he concerned himself with questions of union membership. I do not accept, on the facts of the present case, that he could not have been acting in the capacity of an officer of the New South Wales branch when he did something with respect to membership of the CFMEU or vice versa (cf. Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 ; (2007) 158 FCR 193 ; [2007] FCA 346 ; (2007) 161 IR 317 at [45] - [46]). In the present case it seems clear that the two associations were involved in a joint enterprise so far as the encouragement of union membership was concerned and Mr Manna was their joint officer for that joint purpose. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 865">In Alfred v Quirk [2008] AIRC 781 a CFMEU organiser, Mr Quirk, was found at [44] to have abused a right of entry to a worksite at Castle Hill to hold discussions with employees by refusing to produce at the lunch huts his entry permit for the inspection of the employer's site manager, Mr Sukkar, in breach of s 765 of the Act. The CFMEU was not a party to the proceeding. Reliance is also placed on Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 ; (2007) 161 IR 317 (in which the CFMEU was a party) (the substantive proceeding) and Hadgkiss v CFMEU (2007) IR 385 (the penalty proceeding) as an example of conduct on the part of the CFMEU and CFMEU (Qld) through an organiser, Mr Oskam, which is said to bear the same essential characteristics of misrepresentation central to the contraventions in issue in these proceedings. In the Hadgkiss case, Mr Oskam made false and misleading statements to employees of a company concerning their obligation to join the Union, in contravention of s 298SC of the Act which was taken, by operation of the Act, to be conduct of the Unions. The applicant and the intervener in these proceedings say that this case is analogically relevant as the contravening conduct affecting John Holland involved misrepresentations by the officials to the employees of the right of the officials to enter the X50 worksite and hold discussions with those employees. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 355">In this case a finding of a contravention of s.790 should not be made lightly and clear, cogent and strict proof is required ( Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346).  In Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 at paragraph 9-11 it was said: "9 The civil standard of proof applies and the Court must be satisfied that a case has been proved on the balance of probabilities. Section 140(2) of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) provides: '(2) Without limiting the matters that the court may take into account in deciding whether it is so satisfied, it is to take into account: (a) the nature of the cause of action or defence; and (b) the nature of the subject-matter of the proceeding; and (c) the gravity of the matters alleged. ' 10 And in Briginshaw v Briginshaw [1938] HCA 34 ; (1938) 60 CLR 336 (at 362) Dixon J said that: 'The seriousness of an allegation made, the inherent unlikelihood of an occurrence of a given description, or the gravity of the consequences following from a particular finding are considerations which must affect the answer to the question whether the issue has been proved.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 1267">10 No issue arises in this proceeding whether Mr Fry made the relevant representation in good faith because he did not give evidence of his intention. Objectively, the representation was false. No obligation lay on Mr Anton to join the CFMEU before commencing work on the construction side of the Hamilton site. Consequently, the breach of s 298SC(c) of the WR Act against Mr Fry is established. The CFMEU is vicariously liable for Mr Fry's representation as a consequence of the operation of ss 298B(2)(b) and 349 of the WR Act as they applied at the relevant time: see Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 ; (2007) 158 FCR 193 at 202-203 per Kiefel J.
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FMCA 845">Section 778 identifies that the object of Pt.16 is to provide protections for employers, employees and independent contractors so that they are free to become or not to become members of industrial associations and can exercise their freedom of association rights. As Kiefel J said in Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Limited [2007] FCA 346 ; (2007) 158 FCR 193 at 194 [3] : One of the principal objects of the WRA is to ensure freedom of association .... Part XA [now Pt.16] of the WRA is concerned with that freedom ... </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCAFC 197">60 The judgment under appeal ( Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346) dealt with an allegation that the third appellant (a union delegate) (and through him the first appellant, a Federal union and second appellant, a State union) made false and misleading statements to three employees of the second respondent (Sunland). The events in question are alleged to have occurred in September 2004 at a factory operated by Sunland where the three employees were working. Evidence was given that the union delegate told the employees that it was necessary for them to be in the unions and also that the other employees at the factory would go on strike if they were not. The union delegate's version of events was to the effect that he did no more than encourage membership. At the conclusion of the conversation each of the three employees applied to join both the Federal and State unions. 22 It was argued before the primary judge that it was an essential element of a contravention of s 298SC that the maker of the statement intends to make a false or misleading representation, relevantly, about a person's obligation to join an industrial association. The primary judge found that a reference to a statement being false or misleading does not necessarily imply that it was made knowingly and that the state of the mind of the person who made the statement was irrelevant to the question whether there had been a contravention of s 298SC: Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 at [34] .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FCA 1047">74 There are some questions as to the proper construction of the section. It is contended for the respondents that intention to make a false and misleading representation is a necessary element of the offence. There is no direct authority in favour of that proposition. It is submitted that the reasoning in relation to other sections included in Pt 10A would be applicable (cf BHP Iron Ore Pty Ltd v Australian Workers' Union [2000] FCA 430 ; (2000) 102 FCR 97 at [77] ; Australian Workers' Union v BHP Iron-Ore Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 3 ; (2001) 106 FCR 482 at [70] ---[78]). Indeed, such authority as exists is against the proposition contended for by the respondents ( Hadgkiss v Sunland Constructions Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 346 at [31] ---[34]; Hadgkiss v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (No 3) (2007) 160 IR 263 , [2007] FCA 87 at [288] ---[289]; see also Riley McKay Pty Ltd v Bannerman (1977) 15 ALR 561 ; (1977) 31 FLR 129 per Bowen CJ at 134; Given v CV Holland (Holdings) Pty Ltd (1977) 15 ALR 439 ; (1977) 29 FLR 212). The presence of s 4(7) also tends against it. There is also a question as to whether the section only applies where the false or misleading representation about another's obligation to join an industrial association must be made to that other person. Graham J was of the opinion that the section was not so limited ( Hadgkiss v Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (No 3) (2007) 160 IR 263 ; [2007] FCA 87 at [287] ---[291]). Although not raised here, there may also be a question as to the meaning of "obligation" --- does it refer to legal obligation or practical obligation? </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 140 Civil proceedings: standard of proof</title>
<title id="l3">WORKPLACE RELATIONS AMENDMENT (WORK CHOICES) ACT 2005 </title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l5">WORKPLACE RELATIONS REGULATIONS 2006 </title>
<title id="l6">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1999 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>