<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGKX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 (29 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/461.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">decision of minister's delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">protection visa sought on basis that appellant was a practitioner of falun gong</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">where minister's delegate made adverse findings on credibility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">where minister's delegate failed to put information to the appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">whether denial of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">whether failure to have regard to information supplied by appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">whether minister's delegate failed to consider future risk of harm to appellant in circumstances where appellant's claim to be an active proponent of falun gong in australia had been accepted. practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">fresh evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">new grounds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 134">whether expedient in the interests of justice.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 263">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 263">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">re the minister for immigration and multicultural affairs; ex parte durairajasingham  immigration law and administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">refugee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">refugee review tribunal decision refusing to grant protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">application in original jurisdiction of high court for prerogative relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether tribunal failed to take into account relevant considerations and evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether tribunal failed to consider all available inferences from evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether s 430(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth) required the tribunal to refer to evidence contrary to its findings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether a breach of s 430(1) amounts to a jurisdictional error grounding prerogative relief.  constitutional law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">role of the high court under the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">extent of high court's jurisdiction to grant certiorari pursuant to s 75(v) of the constitution .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">review of decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">whether the tribunal failed to address or deal with an aspect of the applicant's claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">whether the tribunal did not deal with a "very important piece of evidence"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">whether the tribunal overlooked evidence from a psychiatrist</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">whether the tribunal rejected the applicant's claims because of assertions in a letter received by the tribunal from an unknown person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 253">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 547">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 547">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 547">jurisdictional error conceded by minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 547">no appearance by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 547">matter remitted.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">review of decision by refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">whether refugee review tribunal's decision affected by jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">whether the refugee review tribunal made findings unsupported by evidence or material before it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">whether the refugee review tribunal had regard to corroborating documentary evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 427">whether the refugee review tribunal accorded the applicant procedural fairness.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">review of decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">whether jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">protection (class xa) visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">whether the tribunal gave proper consideration to potentially corroborative material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">the proper characterisation of such material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">whether the tribunal had a duty to enquire into the authenticity of such material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">beneficial construction of tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">the operation of s.420 of the act in light of s.422b of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1268">procedural fairness.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">review of decision of the refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">no failure to take into account a relevant consideration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">failure to mention a piece of evidence does not constitute jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">no requirement to invite applicants to comment about information not specifically about the applicants nor about any other specific person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">no failure to accord the applicants procedural fairness at general law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1689">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">no failure to consider material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 1515">according little weight to evidence does not amount to rejection of the evidence.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 253">In SZDXZ &amp; Ors v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2007] FMCA 1689 (in particular at [23] to [58]) I considered authorities relevant to the issue of the difference between a claim, or an aspect of a claim, and corroborating evidence ( Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs v Bhardwaj [2002] HCA 11 ; (2002) 209 CLR 597 ; (2002) 187 ALR 117 ; (2002) 76 ALJR 598 , Coal and Allied Operations Pty Ltd v Australian Industrial Relations Commission and Ors [2000] HCA 47 ; (2000) 203 CLR 194 ; (2000) 174 ALR 585 ; (2000) 74 ALJR 1348 , SZGKX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 , Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v Yusuf [2001] HCA 30; (2001) 206 CLR 323 ; [2001] HCA 30 ; (2001) 180 ALR 1 ; (2001) 75 ALJR 1105 , NAHI v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 10 , Applicant WAEE v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 184 (" Applicant WAEE "), Minister for Immigration and Ethnic Affairs v Guo [1997] HCA 22 ; (1997) 191 CLR 559 ; (1997) 144 ALR 567 ; (1997) 71 ALJR 743 , Minister for Aboriginal Affairs v Peko-Wallsend Ltd [1986] HCA 40 ; (1986) 162 CLR 24 ; (1986) 66 ALR 299 ; (1986) 60 ALJR 560 , Paul v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1196 ; (2001) 113 FCR 396 (" Paul "), Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1802 ; [2001] FCA 1802 ; (2001) 194 ALR 244 (" Htun "), VQAB v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 104 , MZWBW v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2005] FCAFC 94 (" MZWBW "), Singh v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCA 1113 , MZXGP v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs &amp; Anor [2006] FCA 1314 , Mayadeen v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural &amp; Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1522 and Monserrat Gonzales Karras v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs; Teresa Pasini Cabal v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [1998] FCA 1705). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FMCA 547">The basis for the first respondent's concession is the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court of Australia in SZGXK v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 ; [2007] FCA 461 ; [2007] 94 ALD 604. The citation which appears to be intended is in fact the judgment of a single justice, Conti J in SZGKX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 , which needs to be understood in the light of his Honour's statement at [31]: "The present claim to refugee status bears a somewhat contextual uniqueness.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 427">In relation to the principles referred to in Durairajasingham , counsel for the Applicant referred to SZGKX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 (" SZGKX ") where Conti J stated at [23]: "As I would read the thrust of the foregoing dictum of McHugh J in Durairajasingham, his Honour's emphasis appears to be on the need for the tribunal to make clear the nature and extent of its reasons for rejection of evidence placed before it going to material issues in proceedings, which, if accepted would be susceptible to producing an ultimate outcome different to that which was reached" [Emphasis added] 
Counsel for the Applicant also referred to paras. [22]-[27] in SZGKX . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FMCA 1268">Dr Azzi further relies on the authority of SZGKX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 ; 94 ALD 604 at [24] to submit that Conti J, in dealing with similar issues to the present case, (that is, whether the Tribunal had regard to a newspaper article corroborating the appellant's claim to fear persecution for political reasons), rejected the Minister's argument that s.430 of the Act does not impose a duty on the Tribunal to deal with adverse material and that " it is not open to a court to infer from the fact that evidence adverse to the findings made by a Tribunal has not been mentioned that it has not been properly considered. " He points to the following passage from that case in support of this submission: [McHugh J's] observations do not provide sufficient support for the Minister's submission. As I would read the thrust of the foregoing dictum of McHugh J in Durairajasingham, his Honour's emphasis appears to be on the need for the Tribunal to make clear the nature and extent of its reasons for rejection of evidence placed before it going to material issues in the proceedings, which, if accepted, would be susceptible to producing an ultimate outcome different to that which was reached. Counsel for the Minister further submitted in any event that the Tribunal did have 'regard to the "material supplied by the appellant" and specifically referred to "various media reports from Sri Lanka" submitted by the appellant', and reliance was placed in that regard by the Minister upon page seven of the Tribunal member's reasons for decision, which included the following observations: '[t]he applicant also submitted other documents to the delegate, including:... 4. Various media reports from Sri Lanka ...The delegate found that the threats that the Applicant alleged he had received were not politically-motivated and therefore not Convention related. ' However, the issue remains as to adequacy or otherwise of the consideration afforded to the specific evidentiary material (at [23]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 916">43 Mr Varess referred to the decision of McHugh J in Re Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs: Ex parte Durairajasingham (2001) 168 ALR 407 ; [2000] HCA 1 at [64] and [65] (' Durairajasingham') where his Honour observed that the obligation in s430(1)(c) and s 430 (1)(d) of the Act required the Tribunal to state whether it had rejected or failed to accept evidence going to a material issue in the proceedings where rejection of evidence is one of the reasons for the decision. He also referred to the decision of Justice Conti in SZGKX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 at [23] (' SZGKX ') where his Honour referred to McHugh J's decision in Durairajasingham and observed that the Tribunal therefore needed to make clear the nature and extent of its reasons for rejecting evidence before it which, if accepted, would be capable of producing an ultimate outcome different to that which was reached. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FMCA 1689">That being so, it follows that the Tribunal did not conduct a review as required by the Act and the September decision was, thus, not a 'decision on review' for the purposes of ss.367 and 368 of the Act . " 
 
 
 
 
 2) Coal and Allied Operations Pty Ltd v Australian Industrial Relations commission and Ors [2000] HCA 47 ; (2000) 203 CLR 194 (" Coal and Allied Operations ") per Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Hayne JJ at [28]: 
 
 
 
 
 "A decision under that sub-section [s.170MW(3)(b) of the Workplace Relations Act 1996 ] would involve appealable error if, for example, regard was had to irrelevant material, relevant material was disregarded, or, although there was some factual material by reference to which the decision-maker might be satisfied, he or she mistook those facts. " 
 
 
 
 
 3) SZGKX v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 (" SZGKX "), a matter on appeal from this Court. In that case, the Court, per Conti J, saw the relevant issue as (at [23]): 
 
 
 
 
 "However, the issue remains as to the adequacy or otherwise of the consideration afforded to the specific evidentiary material. " 
 
 
 
 
 The evidence in question was a newspaper article that supported the applicant's claims to have been assaulted in circumstances deriving from his claimed profile.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2007] FMCA 1515">The applicant also referred to SZGKX v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 461 where, at [23], Conti J discussed McHugh J's reasons for judgment in Durairajasingham in the following terms: ... his Honour's emphasis appears to be on the need for the Tribunal to make clear the nature and extent of its reasons for rejection of evidence placed before it going to material issues in the proceedings, which, if accepted, would be susceptible to producing an ultimate outcome different to that which was reached. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 430 Refugee Review Tribunal to record its decisions etc.</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>