<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>The University of Western Australia v Gray (No 14) [2007] FCA 410 (20 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/410.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">whether knowing and voluntary disclosure of advice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">whether conduct inconsistent with maintenance of confidentiality and privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">answers by witness for applicant in cross examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">stated reliance upon legal advice in the forming of belief as to factual matters underpinning decision to commence proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">belief as to factual matters relevant to answers to defences of laches, acquiescence and limitations act defences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">production ordered of redacted version of advice disclosing factual matters relied upon and inferences offered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 423">legal opinions as to strength or weakness of causes of action, options and recommendations excluded.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] FCA 423">13 The question whether the mere filing of the affidavit referring to the existence of the Advice amounted to a waiver of privilege was the subject of the ruling which I gave on 20 March 2007 --- University of Western Australia v Gray (No 14) [2007] FCA 410. I do not propose to depart from that ruling here. I observe in so saying that Barrett J in Austress v Marlin (2002) NSWSC 958 held that legal professional privilege could not be maintained in respect of the contents of an affidavit filed in proceedings and served on other parties even if not read in evidence. His Honour distinguished that case from cases in which the filing of affidavits in one set of proceedings was said not to involve any consent to their use in another. The cases he distinguished on this basis were Abigroup v Akins (1997) 42 NSWLR 623 ; (1998) 43 NSWLR 539 ; Nilsen Industrial Electronics Pty Ltd v National Semi-Conductor Corporation (1994) 48 FCR 337 ; ACCC v Telstra Corporation Limited [2000] FCA 28 ; (2000) 96 FCR 317 and State Bank of South Australia v Smoothdale (No 2) [1994] FCA 1314 ; (1995) 53 FCR 125. His Honour said at [8]:-
 
 I am satisfied that the principles in the cases to which I have referred do not apply where it is sought to use in particular proceedings affidavits or witness statements served by one's opponent in those same proceedings. The purpose of the communication, in a case such as that is to inform the recipient of the evidence the serving party intends to lead. That communication cannot carry with it any form of restriction upon the use the recipient may make of the material, save that it must be used for the proper purpose of the particular proceedings.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">LIMITATION ACT 1935 </title>
<title id="l1">LIMITATION ACT 1935 - SECT 38 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>