<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 444 (29 March 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/444.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">application for access pursuant to s 263 of the income tax assessment act 1936 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">matter remitted from a full court of the federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">documents prepared by non-agent third party on the client's instructions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">whether documents prepared for the dominant purpose of obtaining legal advice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1247">whether certain documents privileged in whole or in part on the ground that the nature of legal advice sought or given might be inferred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">esso australia resources limited v the commissioner of taxation  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">whether test for privilege is "dominant purpose" test or "sole purpose" test.  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">client legal privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">test for</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">whether "dominant purpose or sole purpose".  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">influence on common law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">evidence act 1995</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">applicable in three australian jurisdictions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">whether enactments affect development of common law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">significance of non-enactment in other jurisdictions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 67">relevance (if any) of act to application to review past authority of high court.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">palmer v the queen  criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">sexual offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">cross-examination of accused as to whether complainant had motive to lie</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">relevance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">inviting jury to speculate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">risk of reversal of onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">whether judge's directions capable of neutralising prejudicial effect of cross-examination.  criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">sexual offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">unsafe and unsatisfactory verdict</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 2">alibi.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1031">[ database search ] [ name search ] [ recent decisions ] [ noteup ] [ lawcite ] [ help ] australian flight test services pty ltd v the minister for industry, science and technology &amp; ors [1996] fca 1031 (20 november 1996)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">production of document for inspection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">report to department of public health on injury received by inmate of psychiatric centre</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[1976] HCA 63">report obtained inter alia with intention of forwarding it to legal adviser if proceedings instituted against commission for damages for default.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">litigation privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether confidentiality is required in order for litigation privilege to attach to a communication with a third-party witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether dominant purpose is to be assessed from standpoint of party causing the communication to be created practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether findings of fact in one proceeding are admissible as evidence in a subsequent proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">doctrine of stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether previous decision compels similar or same result where similar or same facts are found and applicable legal principles have not changed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">ratio decidendi</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether ratio of a case included all rulings on all issues necessary to the ultimate decision costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">subpoenas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1668">whether respondent to a subpoena is entitled to indemnity costs in relation to successful defence of motion to compel subpoenaed document based on legal professional privilege claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">cartel conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">visy companies and amcor companies held 90 per cent of the corrugated fibreboard packaging market in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">between january 2000 and october 2004 visy and amcor engaged in price-fixing and market sharing contrary to s 45 of trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">amcor received conditional immunity from action by the australian competition and consumer commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">commission brought action against visy companies and three of its senior officers four categories of contraventions: over-arching understanding in 2000 to maintain market share and increase prices; annual price increase understandings each year for 2000 to 2003, customer price understandings and compensation understandings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">respondents admitted liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1617">parties submitted an agreed statement of facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">civil penalty proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">request for further and better particulars of defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">whether self-incrimination or penalty privilege apply to pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">whether privilege waived by filing a defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">extent of waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">witness statements and affidavits obtained by plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1620">whether protected from inspection by litigation privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">application for leave to appeal from an interlocutory decision of a judge of the court to the full court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">whether litigation was reasonably anticipated by the accc on 15 december 2004</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">whether accc could only reasonably anticipate litigation when the commissioners had resolved to commence legal proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">whether the dominant purpose of the creation of the documents was for use in litigation as distinct from investigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">whether documents relating to the grant by the accc of immunity and/or leniency to amcor were discoverable or only relevant as to credit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">whether the primary judge erred in refusing the applicants' request to cross-examine mr williams</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 147">application for leave to appeal dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 696">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 696">consideration of an application for reinstatement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 696">reinstatement sought for the purposes of a pending appeal in a proceeding to which the deregistered entity was a party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 696">consideration of the standing of the accc in an application pursuant to s 601ah(2) of the corporations act 2001 (cth) and whether, in the circumstances, reinstatement is just.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1668">3 In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 444 ; (2007) 239 ALR 762 ( Visy No 2 ), Heerey J was asked to consider claims of litigation privilege made with respect to 216 ACCC documents, including the Hodgson Interview transcript now at issue: Visy No 2 at [6]. His Honour found that litigation was reasonably anticipated as at 15 December 2004 - that is, prior to the Hodgson interview on 17 December 2004: Visy No 2 at [78]-[93]. Heerey J also found that the documents and communications in question were generated for the dominant purpose of amassing and assessing evidence to be used in contemplated civil penalty proceedings for price fixing against Visy: Visy No 2 at [97]-[101]. The Full Court of this Court upheld the judgment on appeal: Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd v ACCC [2007] FCAFC 147 ; (2007) 161 FCR 122. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 1617">8 The Commission has not proceeded against those on the Amcor side of this cartel because in late 2004 Amcor approached the Commission and admitted liability. The Commission applied its Leniency Policy for Cartel Conduct, published in 2003, under which the first party to disclose a cartel of which the Commission is unaware will receive an immunity, provided it is not the "clear leader", gives full and frank disclosure, and continues to cooperate with the Commission. In unrelated litigation Amcor had sued former executives and obtained a Court order for a search of their premises. Incriminating material, including tape recordings of conversations, was discovered and on its solicitors' advice Amcor approached the Commission. Details of these events will be found in my earlier judgment on an interlocutory application: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 444 at [7] - [52]. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2007] FCA 1620">34 But the matter is not at large. In Adler v Australian Securities and Investments Commission (2003) 179 FLR 1 Giles JA, who delivered the judgment of the New South Wales Court of Appeal, rejected a submission that ASIC was required to act with the same degree of fairness and detachment as a prosecutor. Giles JA said (at 151) that the duties of prosecutors "have been developed in the particular circumstances of criminal proceedings. By declaring that these proceedings are to be conducted as civil proceedings, the legislature has plainly declined to pick up the concepts. " In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 444 ; [2007] ATPR 42-157 Heerey J dealt with the same point in short order. He said (at 47,046): "This is a civil proceeding. These documents are either discoverable or not in accordance with the law relating to discovery and legal professional privilege. That law confers rights on all litigants, whether they are model ones or not. " This reasoning was affirmed on appeal: Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [2007] FCAFC 147 , [112].</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCAFC 147">116 Justice Heerey found that the pleas raised allegations far removed from the serious issues of fact and law already raised. He said that to allow the plea to stand had the potential of raising countless side issues as to the conduct of a former employee of Amcor. He said the evidence was likely to be excluded as resulting in an undue waste of time: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2007] FCA 444 at [110] .
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 696">Having regard to the statutory role of the ACCC, it is a person aggrieved with standing to make an application for reinstatement ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Australian Securities and Investments Commission [2000] NSWSC 316 ; (2000) 174 ALR 688 at 692-693 [24] --- [26]; 34 ACSR 232 ; 19 ACLC 341 ; [2000] NSWSC 316 per Austin J (' ACCC v ASIC) . The conclusion reached by his Honour in that case is consistent with the recent observations of Heerey J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Visy Industries Holdings Pty Ltd (No. 2) [2007] FCA 444 at [92] , in these terms:
 
 'There is also the particular role and responsibility of the ACCC. It is not like a commercial corporation which will decide (quite properly) whether or not to commence litigation solely in terms of what will be to the benefit of its own interests. The ACCC exists to give practical effect to the objective as stated in s 2 [Trade Practices Act] to enhance the welfare of Australians through the promotion of competition and fair trading and provision for consumer protection.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 111 Evidence about character of co-accused</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 135 General discretion to exclude evidence</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>