<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 (5 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/503.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] WASC 58">application for the inspection of books</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] WASC 58">the right of a company director at common law to inspect books</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] WASC 58">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2002] WASC 83">corporations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2002] WASC 83">application for inspection of breach of company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2002] WASC 83">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] NSWSC 495">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] NSWSC 495">documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] NSWSC 495">inspection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] NSWSC 495">members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] NSWSC 495">inspection of company documents by members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 48">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 48">application for costs against a non party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 48">jurisdiction to award costs against non-parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 48">discretion to award costs against non-parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">s 237</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">requirements of s 237(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">whether it is probable that a company would not itself bring proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 31">rebuttable presumption in s 237(3)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">courts and judges</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">adverse findings as to credit made in a related judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">whether reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">recusal   legislation: corporations act 2001 (cth) ss 181</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1390">183 , 237 , 247a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">application for interlocutory injunction to enforce clause in shareholders deed allowing inspection of respondent company's books by member</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">whether interlocutory injunction would have the practical effect of finally determining the issues in the proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">relevant principles  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">application for interim injunction under s 1324(1) of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">whether there is a relevant connection between the grant of interim injunction and final relief sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">whether s 247a qualifies power in s 1324  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">application for inspection of books under s 247a of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">good faith and proper purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1273">held: application granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 763">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 763">derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 763">leave to commence proceedings under s 237 corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 763">consideration of requirements under s 237(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">proceedings against company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">leave required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">section 500(2) corporations act 2001 (cth)  winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">proceedings to inspect books of a registered investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">leave required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">section 500(2) corporations act 2001 (cth)  members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">inspection of books</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">insurance policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 51">section 247a corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2007] WASC 207">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2007] WASC 207">application by the plaintiff for orders pursuant to s 247a of the corporations act 2001 (cth) to inspect and make copies of certain books of the defendants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2007] WASC 207">whether the plaintiff makes this application in good faith and for a proper purpose</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] NSWSC 495">The relevant boundary is suggested by a comparison of cases in which proper purpose has been established and those in which it has not. These are conveniently collected in an article by Christos Mantziaris, "The member's right to inspect the company books: Corporations Act , s 247A" (2009) 83 ALJ 621 quoted by Le Miere J in Snelgrove v Great Southern Managers Australia Ltd [2010] WASC 51 at [66] : 
 
"The court has recognised the following purposes as proper inspection purposes: 
 
1. To allow a member to investigate prima facie irregularities in the company's financial accounts or transactions - for example, the creation of parallel financial records ( Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583) , or a loan transaction between companies with a large number of common directors ( Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115). 2. To allow a member to investigate the conduct of the directors in relation to 'the whereabouts and commercial benefit [to] the company of the profit and cash flow' of the company for a certain periods ( United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 404 at [27] , [29]-[30]; Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [57 ] -[59], [64], [66]). To allow a member to investigate prima facie irregularities in the company's financial accounts or transactions - for example, the creation of parallel financial records ( Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583) , or a loan transaction between companies with a large number of common directors ( Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115). 2. To allow a member to investigate the conduct of the directors in relation to 'the whereabouts and commercial benefit [to] the company of the profit and cash flow' of the company for a certain periods ( United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 404 at [27] , [29]-[30]; Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [57 ] -[59], [64], [66]). 3. To allow a member to investigate other reasonably suspected breaches of duty ( Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd (1987) 12 ACLR 357 (affirmed Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd [No 2] [1988] 1 Qd R 606) ; McNeill v Hearing &amp; Balance Centre Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 942 at [17] ; Humes Ltd v Unity APA Ltd [No 1] [1987] VicRp 42 ; [1987] VR 46 7 ; [1987] VicRp 42 ; (1986) 11 ACLR 641).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCAFC 48">Finally, on the question of notice to Mr Gilmour, Mr Vinciguerra gave notice of intention to claim costs of the appeal from Mr Gilmour in written submissions filed a few days before the appeal was heard. In reality, the possibility would or should have occurred to Mr Gilmour at the time of initiating the appeal (and it is not said that he was taken by surprise) because a similar claim was pursued and acceded to in relation to the earlier contested application for access to the books of the Company ( Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503). Further even if the warning had been given before the commencement of the appeal, it is most improbable that the Company or Mr Gilmour would have been deterred from pursuing the appeal (cf HPM (at [9])). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2011] FCAFC 31">In 2006, Mr Vinciguerra applied to the primary judge for orders pursuant to s 247A CA requiring MGCC to permit him to inspect its books. In April 2007 (in proceedings not under appeal: Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583) , orders were made to that effect. The books of MGCC were inspected by Mr Trevor Gorey, a chartered accountant. In late 2007, Mr Gorey provided Mr Vinciguerra with a report as to the outcome of his investigation ( the Gorey Report ). He considered that MGCC had paid more than $2 million in expenses that should not have been paid. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 1390">Earlier, in November 2006, Mr Vinciguerra had applied for orders pursuant to s 247A of the Corporations Act to inspect the books of MGCC. In Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 I made orders allowing that inspection. The application was supported by a draft statement of claim. In accordance with the orders a Mr Trevor Gorey, an accountant, inspected the books of MGCC and provided Mr Vinciguerra with a report regarding the results of the investigation.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 1273">The applicant notes that the requirement of good faith and a proper purpose in s 247A(1), which it is necessary to demonstrate before the Court can make an inspection order under that subsection, is a composite notion: see Vinicigurra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [62] --- [65], Gilmour J; recently followed in Areva NC (Australia) Pty Ltd v Summit Resources (Australia) [2007] WASC 207 ( Areva NC) , Martin CJ. I should follow that line of authority. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2010] FCA 763">As I earlier mentioned in accordance with the orders in Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 , Mr Gorey inspected the books of the defendant and provided the plaintiff with a report regarding the results of his investigations, the Gorey Report.  In November 2006, the plaintiff applied for orders pursuant to s 247A of the Act requiring the defendant to permit him to inspect its books. On 22 May and 5 June 2007 respectively I made orders in favour of the plaintiff permitting that inspection with costs: Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583. In accordance with those orders Mr Gorey inspected the books of the defendant and provided the plaintiff with a report regarding the results of his investigation (the Gorey Report).  However, the actions taken by the plaintiff, in the overall, appear to me to be reasonable whatever ill-advised words he may earlier have spoken. I accept the plaintiff's submission that on the issue of good faith the objective facts and circumstances speak louder than the plaintiff's words: Ehsman v Nutectim International Pty Ltd [2006] NSWSC 887 ; (2006) 58 ACSR 705 at 717 [51] per Austin J. The objective facts are that the plaintiff: 
 
 (a) raised concerns regarding the defendant's affairs; 
 

 
 
 (b) successfully obtained an order pursuant s 247A of the Act to inspect the defendant's books. To do so, the plaintiff satisfied the Court that he was acting in good faith: Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [78] ; 
 

 
 
 (c) caused Mr Gorey, a forensic accountant, to inspect the defendant's books; 
 

 
 
 (d) received the Gorey Report; 
 

 
 
 (e) provided the defendant with a draft statement of claim based on the Gorey Report; and 
 

 
 
 (f) sought leave to commence a derivative action in respect of allegations raised in that statement of claim. 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2010] WASC 51">68 The court may refuse the application on discretionary grounds even if it is satisfied that the applicant is acting in good faith and that the inspection is to be made for a proper purpose: Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 [37]. The nature and extent of the company's insurance cover is not in itself a matter in dispute in the action which the plaintiffs are contemplating commencing against the company. However that is not a condition for the exercise of the power under s 247A. The disclosure of the existence and extent of the relevant insurance cover is likely to assist the plaintiffs in determining whether or not to commence or proceed with the proposed action. If the company does not have insurance which covers the plaintiffs' claims or the quantum of the cover is such that it is likely to be substantially exhausted in legal costs then the plaintiffs may well not proceed with the proposed action. That would prevent the resources of the parties and public resources being wasted. The thrust of the approach to litigation enshrined in the case management rules of this court and other superior courts in Australia is to avoid waste of time and cost and to ensure as far as possible proportionate and economical litigation. It is an appropriate exercise of the discretion of the court to make an order granting access to the plaintiffs to the company's relevant insurance policies.
  In this case the liquidators argue that the plaintiffs do not seek inspection of the relevant insurance policies for a proper purpose. It is helpful to consider the circumstances in which courts have granted or refused access having regard to the applicant's purposes. Mantziaris C, 'The Members Right to Inspect the Company Books: Corporations Act , s 247A' (2009) 83 ALJ 621 , 633 summarises some precedents concerning orders for inspection under s 247A: 
 
 The court has recognised the following purposes as proper inspection purposes: 
 To allow a member to investigate prima facie irregularities in the company's financial accounts or transactions - for example, the creation of parallel financial records ( Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583) , or a loan transaction between companies with a large number of common directors ( Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115). To allow a member to investigate the conduct of the directors in relation to 'the whereabouts and commercial benefit [to] the company of the profit and cash flow' of the company for a certain periods ( United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 404 at [27] , [29]-[30]; Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [57] - [59], [64], [66]). To allow a member to investigate other reasonably suspected breaches of duty ( Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd (1987) 12 ACLR 357 (affirmed Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd [No 2] [1988] 1 Qd R 606) ; McNeill v Hearing &amp; Balance Centre Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 942 at [17] ; Humes Ltd v Unity APA Ltd [No 1] [1987] VicRp 42 ; [1987] VR 467 ; (1986) 11 ACLR 641). It is helpful to consider the circumstances in which courts have granted or refused access having regard to the applicant's purposes. Mantziaris C, 'The Members Right to Inspect the Company Books: Corporations Act , s 247A' (2009) 83 ALJ 621 , 633 summarises some precedents concerning orders for inspection under s 247A: 
 
 The court has recognised the following purposes as proper inspection purposes: 
 To allow a member to investigate prima facie irregularities in the company's financial accounts or transactions - for example, the creation of parallel financial records ( Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583) , or a loan transaction between companies with a large number of common directors ( Cescastle Pty Ltd v Renak Holdings Ltd (1991) 6 ACSR 115). To allow a member to investigate the conduct of the directors in relation to 'the whereabouts and commercial benefit [to] the company of the profit and cash flow' of the company for a certain periods ( United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 404 at [27] , [29]-[30]; Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583 at [57] - [59], [64], [66]). To allow a member to investigate other reasonably suspected breaches of duty ( Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd (1987) 12 ACLR 357 (affirmed Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd [No 2] [1988] 1 Qd R 606) ; McNeill v Hearing &amp; Balance Centre Pty Ltd [2007] NSWSC 942 at [17] ; Humes Ltd v Unity APA Ltd [No 1] [1987] VicRp 42 ; [1987] VR 467 ; (1986) 11 ACLR 641). To allow a member to value the members' shares, so as to: (i) negotiate a fair exit price from the company ( Tinios v French Caledonia Travel [1994] FCA 1154 ; (1994) 13 ACSR 658) , or (ii) to examine the effect of a corporate debt transaction on the value of the shareholding ( United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd [2003] NSWSC 404 at [20] - [23]; see also United Rural Enterprises Pty Ltd v Lopmand Pty Ltd (2003) 45 ACSR 271 ; [2003] NSWSC 405).</sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2007] WASC 207">39 It is now established that the reference in s 247A(1) to good faith and a proper purpose is the expression of a composite notion, rather than separate and divisible concepts (see Barrack Mines Ltd v Grants Patch Mining Ltd [1988] 1 Qd R 606 ; Knightswood Nominees Pty Ltd v Sherwin Pastoral Co Ltd (1989) 15 ACLR 151 ; Vinciguerra v MG Corrosion Consultants Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 503 ; (2007) 61 ACSR 583). I agree with the view expressed by Gilmour J in Vinciguerra to the effect that the same composite approach should be taken to the requirement under s 247A(5) of the Act that the applicant be acting in good faith and for a purpose connected with an application for leave under s 237 or bringing or intervening in proceedings pursuant to that leave. When an application for inspection is brought in reliance upon a pending or foreshadowed application under s 237 of the Act, it is appropriate to consider the basis for the substantive application for leave to intervene in the context of the necessary assessment of whether the applicant is acting in good faith and for a purpose connected with that substantive application - see Vinciguerra ; Caveat Pty Ltd v Baillie [2002] WASC 83 , [24] - [25]; and Chuen v Laredo Pty Ltd [2005] WASC 58 , [59]. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 9 Dictionary</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 21 Carrying on business in Australia or a State or Territory</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 232 Grounds for Court order</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 233 Orders the Court can make</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 234 Who can apply for order</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 236 Bringing, or intervening in, proceedings on behalf of a company</title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 237 Applying for and granting leave</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 247A Order for inspection of books of company or registered managed investment scheme</title>
<title id="l9">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 247B Ancillary orders</title>
<title id="l10">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 247C Disclosure of information acquired in inspection</title>
</legistitles>
</case>