<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Elderslie Finance Corporation Limited v Newpage Pty Ltd (No 4) [2007] FCA 500 (4 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/500.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 61">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 61">insolvency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 61">winding up on insolvency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 61">appointment of liquidator practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 61">application for mareva injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">roumald charles parsons v the queen  criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">dishonestly obtaining property belonging to another by deception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">whether cheque is property belonging to another</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">whether bank cheque is property belonging to another.  criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">dishonestly obtaining property belonging to another by deception with intention of permanent deprivation of property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">whether person capable of intending to permanently deprive another of cheque.  cheques</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">nature of cheque</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">mandate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1999] HCA 1">contract.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 39">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 39">ex parte application for freezing order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 39">circumstances where freezing order appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 39">whether order would prevent frustration or abuse of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1030">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1030">approval of compromise on application by liquidator under s 477(2a) of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1030">necessity of liquidator's obtaining court's approval and jurisdiction of court to grant approval</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1030">meaning of expression " a debt to the company" in s 477(2a)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1030">whether order should be made that compromise remain confidential. held: (1) claim based on voidable transaction was not "a debt to the company" but claim of a loan by the company was; (2) a suppression order in relation to terms of compromise should be made.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 39">Other than the claims of the applicants as to the conduct of the respondents in 2003 and 2004, which are not substantiated otherwise than in the affidavits of Mr Zabusky, this is not a case where, for example, there is compelling evidence that funds previously have been inappropriately dissipated (cf Elderslie Finance Corporation Ltd v Newpage Pty Ltd (No 4) [2007] FCA 500 , Bridges Financial Services Pty Ltd v Brown [2008] FCA 992). No evidence has been produced to me that the respondents are in any way at risk of disappearing or dissipating their assets, other than the suspicions of the applicants. Indeed in his affidavit sworn 30 January 2009 and filed in Court this morning, Mr Zabusky identified extensive properties in Europe and Africa, including real properties, which he submitted were assets of the respondents potentially available to satisfy a judgment against the respondents. I am fortified in this conclusion by the fact, as demonstrated both by the submissions of the applicants and the publicly-available decisions of the Supreme Court of Queensland in related litigation, the respondents have submitted themselves to the Supreme Court of Queensland over a period of several years (as is clear from such decisions as Virgtel Ltd v Zabusky [2006] QSC 66 , Virgtel Ltd v Zabusky [2006] QSC 241 , Virgtel Ltd v Zabusky [2008] QSC 213 and Virgtel Ltd v Zabusky (No 2) [2008] QSC 316) ; have, I understand from the submissions of the applicants, paid significant sums of money into the trust account of their solicitors as ordered by the Supreme Court; and currently retain solicitors in Queensland. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 1030">3 Several judgments have been previously delivered in this proceeding, including mine of 4 April 2007 ( Elderslie Finance Corporation Limited v Newpage Pty Ltd (No 4) [2007] FCA 500). I refer to the accounts of the background facts given in all of those judgments, in particular, the one just mentioned.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 180 Care and diligence--civil obligation only</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 181 Good faith--civil obligations</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 182 Use of position--civil obligations</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 588 Outstanding property of defunct registrable body</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1317H Compensation orders--corporation/scheme civil penalty provisions</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>