<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>National Auto Glass Supplies (Australia) Pty Limitedv Nielsen &amp; Moller Autoglass (NSW) Pty Limited (No 5) [2007] FCA 569 (13 April 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/569.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">defamation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">publication of a facsimile in all states of australia and the australian capital territory by a company conveying defamatory innuendos about persons associated with a competitor business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">publication of a 'whistleblower' letter to the australian taxation office</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">publication of an email to two officers of the principal supplier of the competitor business located in the special administrative region of hong kong and in another location within the people's republic of china</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">availability of presumption as to the law, if any, in respect of defamation in the special administrative region of hong kong and elsewhere in the people's republic of china</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">availability of defences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">compensatory, aggravated and exemplary damages  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1625">claims for defamation run in parallel with claims for representations said to constitute misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 582">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 582">discretion to limit the use to be made of evidence following its admission where an order has been made excusing a witness under cross-examination from giving further evidence in the case</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2007] FCA 1625">The third respondent closed his case shortly after 11.30 am on 19 April 2007. The applicants did not have any case in reply. When the second respondent was excused from giving further evidence on 13 April 2007 (see National Auto Glass Supplies (Australia) Pty Limited v Nielsen &amp; Moller Autoglass (NSW) Pty Limited (No 5) [2007] FCA 569) an order was made, on the applicants' application, that no further use may be made of any part of the affidavit or oral evidence of the second respondent (see National Auto Glass Supplies (Australia) Pty Limited v Nielsen &amp; Moller Autoglass (NSW) Pty Limited (No 7) [2007] FCA 582). At times during the course of the hearing each of the second and third respondents made remarks which manifest a degree of bitterness about the predicament in which the first respondent found itself and which they attributed to the applicants' conduct. They undoubtedly had a sense of grievance that the first applicant had not been competing with the first respondent on a level playing field.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2007] FCA 582">4 The applicants have by Notice of Motion filed on 12 April 2007 moved the Court today for an order that the oral and affidavit evidence given in the proceedings by the second respondent be excluded from the evidence received in the proceedings. This application has been made following the making of an order earlier today on the second respondent's application to be excused from giving further evidence in the case, which was successful (see National Auto Glass Supplies (Australia) Pty Limited v Nielsen &amp; Moller Autoglass (NSW) Pty Limited (No 5) [2007] FCA 569). The relief sought has been sought in accordance with s 136 of the Evidence Act 1995 (Cth) which provides:
 
 
 '136 The court may limit the use to be made of evidence if there is a danger that a particular use of the evidence might: 
 
 
 
 
 
 (a) be unfairly prejudicial to a party; or 
 
 (b) be misleading or confusing. ' </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 11 General powers of a court</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 41 Improper questions</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 58 Offences by witness</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>