<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Jeremy Jones, and on behalf of the Executive Council of Australian Jewry v The Bible Believers Church [2007] FCA 55 (2 February 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/55.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">civil and political rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">racial vilification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">artistic work</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">likely to offend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">insult, humiliate or intimidate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">whether published 'reasonably and in good faith'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">onus of proof with respect to exemption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">whether subjective or objective test or combination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">'reasonably'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">'good faith'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">newspaper cartoon</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">satirising indigenous conflict with respect to return of 19 th century aboriginal leader's head from england to western australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">whether covered by artistic work exemption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">public discussion and comment exemptions statutory interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">exemptions and provisos</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 16">relevance to exceptions or provisos involving characterisation or normative judgments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">human rights and discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">racial discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">racial vilification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">proceedings to enforce determination of human rights and equal opportunity commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">hearing de novo of original complaint</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">representative claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">necessity for class to be closed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">entitlement of applicant alone to institute proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether jews in australia constitute a group of people with common "ethnic origin"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether non-password protected website caused material to be `communicated to the public'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">meanings of the words offend, insult, humiliate, or intimidate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">ordinary meaning</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether publication of material on website reasonably likely to offend or intimidate jews in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">objective test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">real effects</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether "ethnic origin" one factor in the content of material on website  racial vilification</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">applicable principles in determining whether material reasonably likely to offend, insult, humiliate or intimidate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">principles of defamation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">objective test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether imputations would be conveyed to an ordinary reasonable reader  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.20" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.21" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">summary judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.22" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">repeated failure of respondent to file a defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.23" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">respondent unwilling to cooperate in bringing proceeding to trial  relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.24" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">injunctions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.25" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">utility of injunction to restrain internet publication</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.26" type=cited from="[2002] FCA 1150">whether apology or retraction should be ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">sexual harassment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">various allegations of conduct constituting sexual harassment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether employee sexually harassed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether conduct constituted "unwelcome conduct of a sexual nature"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether claims made out on evidence   human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">sex discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">female employee complained about sexual harassment in robust work environment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">complaints dealt with inadequately</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">employee subsequently given warnings about unsatisfactory work performance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">employment purportedly terminated on basis of unsatisfactory work performance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether warnings about unsatisfactory work performance warranted in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether purported termination of employment for sufficient reason, or whether related to her complaints about sexual harassment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 680">whether employer discriminated against employee on grounds of her sex</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">racial discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">jones v dunkel considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 897">damages.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1512">racial discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1512">where messages posted on to an internet discussion forum contained material causing offence and distress to the applicant because of his jewish race and ethnicity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1512">the party posting the offensive material did so in breach of pt ii of the racial discrimination act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1512">whether organisation which controls and manages the internet website also acted unlawfully by publishing or allowing material to be published</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1512">organisation's failure to remove material was an 'act' reasonably likely to offend the applicant but cannot be shown to be attributable to his race or ethic origin</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">finding of unlawful discrimination within the meaning of s 6 and s 9(1)(f) disability discrimination act 1992 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">whether an order for an apology from the minister for health is appropriate in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">quantum of damages payable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1236">interest</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 680">There are a number of reasons for that. In the first place, in my view, the adverse findings made against the respondents in respect of the conduct concerning them individually is sufficient recognition for Ms Poniatowska of the inappropriateness of that conduct. The imposition upon those respondents, who variously denied the conduct specifically attributed to them or in some respects denied its significance, would put them in the position of requiring them to apologise for conduct which they did not accept that they had severally engaged in: see for instance the observations of Branson J in Jones v Toben (2002) 71 ALD 629 at [106]; Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55 at [65] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FMCA 897">In Silberberg v The Builders Collective of Australia Inc [56] [2007] FCA 1512 , also a racial discrimination case, Gyles J made no award of damages, only for costs and for certain restraints to be imposed. Similar orders were made by Conti J in Jeremy Jones, and on behalf of the Executive Council of Australian Jewry v The Bible Believers Church [2007] FCA 55. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] NSWADTAP 32">24 The Federal cases include determinations of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (HREOC) and judgments of the Federal Court. Important cases are Bryl and Kovacevic v Nowra and Melbourne Theatre Company [1999] HREOCA 11 ; [1999] EOC 93-022 (HREOC) ( Bryl ); Creek v Cairns Post Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 1007 (Kiefel J); Bropho v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2002] FCA 1510 , a judicial review proceeding (RD Nicholson J) relating to the primary decision by HREOC; and, on appeal against the judicial review outcome, Bropho v Human Rights &amp; Equal Opportunity Commission &amp; Anor [2004] FCAFC 16 ; (2004) 135 FCR 105 (French , Carr, Lee JJ)) ( Bropho ). There are also a series of cases where a leader of the Jewish community in Australia, Jeremy Jones, has laid complaints against purveyors of 'No Holocaust' views in respect of various remarks they have made about Jewish people. These cases include Jones &amp; ors v Toben (2000) EOC [93-110] (HREOC); on judicial review, Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 (Branson J); on appeal against the judicial review outcome, Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 (Carr, Kiefel, Allsop JJ); Jones v Scully [2002] FCA 1080 ; (2002) 120 FCR 243 (Hely J); and Jones v The Bible Believers Church [2007] FCA 55 (Conti J). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCA 1512">19 At all material times, the Messages on the Forum were able to be downloaded and received by any member of the public without restriction. The uploading or posting of the Messages by the second respondent was an act of publication done by him. Branson J held in Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 , (2002) 71 ALD 629 at [73] ---[75] that:
 
 "the act of placing text and graphics on a website which is not password protected is an act of publication, or perhaps more accurately an act which causes repeated publications, in that it allows individuals to access the website with a browser to read that text and see those graphics. " 
 

That was unaffected by the appeal ( Toben v Jones [2003] FCAFC 137 ; (2003) 129 FCR 515). That act plainly caused words to be communicated to the public within s 18C(2)(a) and so was not in private. (See also Conti J in Jones v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55. ) </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 1236">13 While courts in human rights cases have sometimes ordered that apologies be made (for example, De Simone v Bevacqua (unreported, Supreme Court of Victoria, McDonald J, 15 September 1994), Zheng v Beamish [2004] FMCA 61 , Oberoi v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2001] FMCA 34) , like many other judges before me, I consider that a court-ordered apology serves little purpose: Jones on behalf of the Executive Council of Australian Jewry v The Bible Believers' Church [2007] FCA 55 at [65] , Rawcliffe v Northern Sydney Central Coast Area Health Service [2007] FMCA 931 at [101] , Jones v Toben [2002] FCA 1150 at [106] , Jones v Scully [2001] FCA 879 ; (2001) 113 FCR 343. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l1">RACIAL DISCRIMINATION ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l2">RACIAL DISCRIMINATION ACT 1975 - SECT 18C Offensive behaviour because of race, colour or national or ethnic origin</title>
<title id="l3">RACIAL DISCRIMINATION ACT 1975 - SECT 18D Exemptions</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>