<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Morrison v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 723 (14 May 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/723.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">cancellation of visa by minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">substantial and serious criminal record of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">application for review, prohibition and certiorari</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">limited to jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged failure to give weight to essential factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged absence of evidence on which to reach conclusion as to view of australian public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged failure to consider recent untested criminal charges migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">alleged violent and unlawful arrest, detention and removal including alleged deprivation of opportunity to obtain legal advice and representation regarding the minister's visa cancellation decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 54">no finding made to support alleged claim</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 54">71 As observed by French J in Morrison [2007] FCA 723 at 23, if it were the case that the removal was effected precipitately in order to deprive the applicant of access to the Court then that may constitute a collateral purpose outside the proper exercise of the power to detain and remove. In short it would be a very serious matter. However, before it is possible to reach any conclusion on that possibility, it is necessary to examine the evidence on the other side of the ledger for the Minister. 
  3 Mr Morrison sought an urgent interim injunction to prevent his removal from Australia on 8 May 2007. That motion was heard by French J who dismissed it: Morrison v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 723. Two days later Mr Morrison filed an application for review which has since been amended on various occasions. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l1">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 39B Original jurisdiction of Federal Court of Australia</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 198 Removal from Australia of unlawful non-citizens</title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 499 Minister may give directions</title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 501 Refusal or cancellation of visa on character grounds</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>