<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Applicant S1983 of 2003 v Minister for Immigrationand Citizenship [2007] FCA 854 (8 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/854.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">section 422b of the migration act not applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">whether lack of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">whether failure by the tribunal to take relevant considerations into account</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">whether tribunal misunderstood applicant's claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1589">whether tribunal acted unreasonably, drew inferences that were not available, misapplied the test for well-founded fear, asked a wrong question or erred in the manner in which it used independent information.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FMCA 1589">The Tribunal as reconstituted (T 2 ) held a further Tribunal hearing. The applicant's migration agent submitted country information and other documents in support of the applicant's claims. By decision of 7 July 2006 T 2 affirmed the decision of the delegate of the first respondent. The applicant again sought judicial review. On appeal from this Court Branson J of the Federal Court of Australia made orders quashing the second Tribunal decision and again remitting the matter for redetermination (see Applicant S1983 of 2003 v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2007] FCA 854). It is that reconsideration that is the subject of these proceedings.  The affidavit of Associate Professor Jayaraman was admitted into evidence in the proceedings before Branson J in the Federal Court (see Applicant S1983 v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 854) in relation to the distinction between the concepts of Sindhi and Dalit. Professor Jayaraman attested to his experience, evidence and independence and the fact that he had been asked to be an " expert witness. " Branson J had regard to this evidence in finding that the previous Tribunal (T 2 ) had proceeded on the basis that it was essentially the same to be a Sindhi and a Dalit when this was not the case and hence that it had misunderstood and so failed properly to deal with the claims advanced by the applicant (at [53]). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 144 Matters of common knowledge</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 27 Evidence on appeal</title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 91 Order of dealing with visas</title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 91R Persecution</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>