<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Forest v Queensland Health [2007] FCA 936 (22 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/936.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">"requirement or condition" that hearing impaired child be taught in english rather than auslan, a native australian sign language</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether ability to "cope" without auslan assistance meant that child was "able to comply" with "requirement or condition", pursuant to s 6(c) of the disability discrimination act 1992 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether child would suffer "serious disadvantage" without auslan assistance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 100">whether suffering "serious disadvantage" meant child could not comply with "requirement or condition"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">offer of enrolment by a school to a deaf student conditional on the acceptance of a 'model of learning support' that excluded the provision of auslan (australian sign language) interpreting services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">reasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 197">disability discrimination act 1992 (cth) ss 6 , 22</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">medical practitioner employed by public hospital</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">vision impairment due to diabetes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">failure to provide aids</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">termination of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">whether applicant discriminated against on ground of disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">whether requirement of independent assessment of visual disability reasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">refusal to allow independent eye specialist to provide report to employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">whether termination "because of" disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">whether treatment less favourable than treatment that would be given to a person without the disability in "circumstances that are the same or are not materially different"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">assessment of damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 485">interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">purvis v new south wales (department of education and training)  discrimination law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">suspension and subsequent exclusion from school of pupil who repeatedly assaulted teachers and other pupils</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">where pupil's behaviour a consequence of brain damage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">whether pupil discriminated against on the ground of disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">meaning of "disability"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">whether obligation to provide reasonable accommodation or make reasonable adjustments for persons with a disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">whether treatment of pupil was less favourable than treatment that would be given to a person without the disability in "circumstances that are the same or are not materially different"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">whether comparator is a person who does not engage in violent behaviour</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">whether pupil received less favourable treatment "because of" his disability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[2003] HCA 62">disability discrimination act 1992 (cth), s 5(1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2002] FMCA 95">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2002] FMCA 95">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2002] FMCA 95">discrimination on the basis of restriction on assistance dog</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2002] FMCA 95">access to premises</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[2000] FMCA 5">s 9 disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[2000] FMCA 5">guide dogs, hearing assistance dogs and trained animals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination on ground of status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">disabled persons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">direct and indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">whether intention or motive to discriminate necessary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">discrimination constituted by imposition of requirement or condition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">no contravention where requirement or condition reasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">reasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">no contravention where act done necessary to comply with provision of other legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.10" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">whether necessary that other legislation directly impose obligation to do discriminatory act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.11" type=cited from="[1991] HCA 49">equal opportunity act 1984 (vict.), ss. 17(1), (5), 29(2)(b), 39(e)(ii).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">sex discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">whether the decision to select the second respondent for an overseas posting in the department of foreign affairs and trade was unlawful under s. 14 (2) of the sex discrimination act 1984 as constituting an act of sex discrimination within the meaning of s. 5 (2) of that act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">construction of s. 5 (2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">meaning of "requirement or condition"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">meaning of "substantially higher proportion"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">appropriate denominator or base pool to be used to determine "proportion"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">meaning of "reasonable having regard to the circumstances of the case"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">observations on the contrast between the australian legislation and british and u.s. legislation in respect of indirect discrimination.  public service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.9" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">equal opportunity program</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.10" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">s. 22b of the public service act 1922</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.11" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">meaning of "program" in sub-s. 22b (1).  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.12" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 342">meaning of "to have regard to" one or more particular matters.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 115">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 115">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 115">direct and indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 115">elements of direct and indirect discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 115">test for substantially higher proportion of persons without the disability complying or being able to comply with a requirement or condition.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">whether each party should bear their own costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">whether costs should be paid on an indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">the effect of a decision of the full court delivered during these proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">effect of applicant's legal representation being provided on a pro bono basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">rule against discouraging meritorious claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">effect of respondent's conduct during the proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">effect of various offers to settle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">further discretionary considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">whether there was high-handed conduct by the applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.11" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">whether the applicant had any prospect of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.12" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">whether the applicant's conduct occasioned loss of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.13" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 741">time for payment.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">contention that the body corporate has contravened the provisions of the disability discrimination act which prohibit indirect discrimination in the provision of goods and services and facilities by not permitting her access to common property with her dog</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">contends that the body corporate contravened the provision of the act by refusing to permit her to live at kookaburra park with her dog</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant has a disability as defined in section 4 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant has been directly discriminated against pursuant to section 9 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the respondent has unlawfully discriminated against the applicant pursuant to section 24(1) in the case that section 6 and 9 of the act apply</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether respondent can prove unjustifiable hardship under section 24(2) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether respondent has contravened section 5 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the respondent has contravened section 25 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 260">whether the applicant is entitled to compensation if the respondent did contravene the act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.0" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.1" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">disability discrimination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.2" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">nurse with epilepsy and secondary sleep deprivation and paranoid ideation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.3" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">rostered with night and day shifts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.4" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">request for accommodation for disability refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.5" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">indirect discrimination found</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.6" type=citing from="[2007] FMCA 931">compensation for distress awarded.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 115">A difficulty arises however concerning the nature of the comparator group. This case like Forest v Queensland Health (supra) presents with an applicant with an unusual condition. In Forest v Queensland Health (supra) Her Honour at first instance determined " that commonsense dictates that the majority of people in the community...would have no difficulty accessing the premises without an animal and do not require an assistance dog to be able to access the respondent's premises. Accordingly for the purposes of section 6, I am prepared to hold that a substantially higher proportion of persons without the applicant's disability are able to comply with the requirement or condition imposed by the respondent in this case [47] ". In so proceeding Her Honour rejected a submission that in respect of the comparator group she did not require evidence of the proportion of people with the applicant's disability who would have difficulty complying with the requirement or condition of the respondent. That approach was rejected by the Full Court.  The approach to be adopted in determining the matter of "requirement or condition" for the purpose of s6 was examined in Forest v Queensland Health (supra). In particular at page 164 and 165 at paragraph [53] Her Honour Collier J helpfully collected the relevant principles and supporting authority. [43] At [53] Her Honour stated: "The concept of "requirement or condition" within the meaning of s6 or its State equivalents has been considered in a number of cases. Relevant principles include: it is only if the alleged discriminator can be said to have required, in the sense of "obliged" or "compelled" the aggrieved person to do something, that it could be said to have imposed a requirement or condition with which it required compliance: Drummond J in Sluggett v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2002] FCA 987 ; (2002) 123 FCR 561 at 566, cf Heerey J in Fetherston v Peninsula Health [2004] FCA 485 at [81] ; whether the alleged discriminator has imposed a requirement or condition on persons wishing to, inter alia, use services or access premises, is a question of fact (Dawson and Toohey JJ in Waters 173 CLR at 394; Sackville and Stone JJ in Catholic Education Office v Clarke [2004] FCAFC 197 ; (2004) 138 FCR 121 at 143) and will take its colour from the particular setting in which it is said a prohibition against discrimination created by the DD Act has been infringed by indirect indiscrimination: Sluggett 123 FCR at 577; a requirement or condition may be implicit in the conduct which is said to constitute discrimination: Mason CJ and Gaudron J in Waters 173 CLR at 360; Clarke 138 FCR at 143; [2007] FCA 936 ; (2007) 161 FCR 152 at 165; the requirement or condition in each case will depend on the facts of that particular case, however it should be construed to include any form of qualification or prerequisite, and formulated with some precision: Clarke 138 FCR at 143; the notion of "requirement or condition" would seem to involve something over and above that which is necessarily inherent in the goods or services provided: Mason CJ and Gaudron J in Waters 173 CLR at 361; Clarke 138 FCR at 142. So, as Mason CJ and Gaudron J pointed out in Waters 173 CLR at 361: ...it would not make sense to say that a manicure involves a requirement or condition that those availing themselves of that service have one or both of their hands. the expression "requirement or condition" should be given a generous interpretation and the alleged discriminator should not be permitted to evade the statutory prohibition on indirect discrimination by defining its services so as to incorporate the alleged requirement or condition: Dawson and Toohey JJ in Waters 173 CLR at 394; Clarke 138 FCR at 143. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FMCA 741">The applicant says that but for her failure to adduce evidence of the comparator group she would have succeeded in her application. The need for this form of evidence first became apparent following the Full Court decision in State of Queensland (Queensland Health) v Che Forest (2008) 168 FCR 532 ; [2008] FCAFC 96. The single judge decision relied upon by the applicant had held there was no need to expressly adduce evidence of the comparator group. In my view that approach was reasonably open at the time of the trial, upon a fair reading of the authorities of the Federal Court at first instance in Forest v Queensland Health [2007] FCA 936 and Catholic Education Office v Clarke [2004] FCAFC 197 ; (2004) 138 FCR 121. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] NSWADT 119">123 The concept of unjustifiable hardship requires a consideration of whether the hardship is of such a nature or degree as to be unjustifiable following a weighing of relevant factors. Further, it necessarily implies that some hardship is justifiable: Hills Grammar School v Human Rights &amp; Equal Opportunity Commission [2000] FCA 658 ; (2000) 100 FCR 306 at [48] ; Forest v Queensland Health [2007] FCA 936 ; (2007) 161 FCR 152 at [157] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FMCA 260">The approach to be adopted in determining the matter of "requirement or condition" for the purpose of s.6 was examined in Forest v Queensland Health (supra). In particular at page 164 and 165 at paragraph [53] Her Honour Collier J helpfully collected the relevant principles and supporting authority. [13] At [53] Her Honour stated: "The concept of "requirement or condition" within the meaning of s6 or its State equivalents has been considered in a number of cases. Relevant principles include: . it is only if the alleged discriminator can be said to have required, in the sense of "obliged" or "compelled" the aggrieved person to do something, that it could be said to have imposed a requirement or condition with which it required compliance: Drummond J in Sluggett v Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2002] FCA 987 ; (2002) 123 FCR 561 at 566, cf Heerey J in Fetherston v Peninsula Health [2004] FCA 485 at [81] ; . whether the alleged discriminator has imposed a requirement or condition on persons wishing to, inter alia, use services or access premises, is a question of fact (Dawson and Toohey JJ in Waters 173 CLR at 394; Sackville and Stone JJ in Catholic Education Office v Clarke [2004] FCAFC 197 ; (2004) 138 FCR 121 at 143) and will take its colour from the particular setting in which it is said a prohibition against discrimination created by the DD Act has been infringed by indirect indiscrimination: Sluggett 123 FCR at 577; a requirement or condition may be implicit in the conduct which is said to constitute discrimination: Mason CJ and Gaudron J in Waters 173 CLR at 360; Clarke 138 FCR at 143; [2007] FCA 936 ; (2007) 161 FCR 152 at 165; the requirement or condition in each case will depend on the facts of that particular case, however it should be construed to include any form of qualification or prerequisite, and formulated with some precision: Clarke 138 FCR at 143; the notion of "requirement or condition" would seem to involve something over and above that which is necessarily inherent in the goods or services provided: Mason CJ and Gaudron J in Waters 173 CLR at 361; Clarke 138 FCR at 142. So, as Mason CJ and Gaudron J pointed out in Waters 173 CLR at 361: ...it would not make sense to say that a manicure involves a requirement or condition that those availing themselves of that service have one or both of their hands. the expression "requirement or condition" should be given a generous interpretation and the alleged discriminator should not be permitted to evade the statutory prohibition on indirect discrimination by defining its services so as to incorporate the alleged requirement or condition: Dawson and Toohey JJ in Waters 173 CLR at 394; Clarke 138 FCR at 143. "  The applicant's case rests to a significant degree upon the matter of the requirement of a dog trained to assist her in the alleviation of the effects of her disability. That issue can only be considered properly and effectively in this case in light of a precise factual decision as to the disability held by the applicant. [4]  A difficulty arises however concerning the nature of the comparator group. This case like Forest v Queensland Health (supra) presents with an applicant with an unusual condition. In Forest v Queensland Health (supra) Her Honour at first instance determined " that commonsense dictates that the majority of people in the community...would have no difficulty accessing the premises without an animal and do not require an assistance dog to be able to access the respondent's premises. Accordingly for the purposes of section 6, I am prepared to hold that a substantially higher proportion of persons without the applicant's disability are able to comply with the requirement or condition imposed by the respondent in this case [19] ". In so proceeding Her Honour rejected a submission that in respect of the comparator group she did not require evidence of the proportion of people with the applicant's disability who would have difficulty complying with the requirement or condition of the respondent. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FMCA 931">Forest v Queensland Health [2007] FCA 936 at [69] ).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 </title>
<title id="l1">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 3 Objects</title>
<title id="l2">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 4 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l3">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 5 Direct disability discrimination</title>
<title id="l4">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 6 Indirect disability discrimination</title>
<title id="l5">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 7 Discrimination in relation to associates</title>
<title id="l6">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 8 Discrimination in relation to carers, assistants, assistance animals and disability aids</title>
<title id="l7">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 9 Carer, assistant, assistance animal and disability aid definitions</title>
<title id="l8">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 11 Unjustifiable hardship</title>
<title id="l9">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 23 Access to premises</title>
<title id="l10">DISABILITY DISCRIMINATION ACT 1992 - SECT 24 Goods, services and facilities</title>
<title id="l11">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l12">ASSOCIATIONS INCORPORATION ACT 1981 </title>
<title id="l13">GUIDE DOGS ACT 1972 </title>
<title id="l14">GUIDE DOGS ACT 1972 - SECT 3 3 Definitions</title>
</legistitles>
</case>