<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Murdaca v Accounts Control Management Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 964 (22 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/964.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">whether federal court has power to set aside a sequestration order on appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">power not limited by the bankruptcy act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">order on appeal has the result that no valid sequestration order was made. bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">service of bankruptcy notice not proved to the required standard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">evidentiary onus lies with serving party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">service must be strictly proved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">document exchange</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">document exchange number</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">document exchange facility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">delivery to one branch of a document exchange facility does not constitute effective contemporaneous service of that document when the recipient maintains a facility at another branch of a document exchange facility</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">service of creditor's petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">personal service required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">appearance at a court proceeding is taken to satisfy requirement for personal service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">no facility for conditional appearance in bankruptcy rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">an order for sequestration can be made despite non-compliance with the rules regarding service of a creditor's petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 73">a bankruptcy notice may be signed on behalf of or in the name of firms, partnerships and corporations.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">failure to comply with bankruptcy notice based on default judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">whether court should go behind the judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">debt incurred for professional services rendered at request of the debtor in relation to a business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">whether debtor contracted as agent for a company or personally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">whether debtor merely manager of the business or conducting it on his own behalf as lessee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1359">whether appointment of a receiver manager of the business and control of the proceeds from its realisation by the family court prevented execution on the judgment.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">application to set aside bankruptcy notice on ground that notice overstated amount due</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">recipient of notice claimed entitlement to set-off of an amount less than the judgment debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">notice that disregards such a set-off and claims full amount of judgment debt conforms with statutory form of notice and is valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">recipient of notice cannot avoid act of bankruptcy by quantifying set-off and tendering payment of amount demanded in notice less amount of set-off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">too late, once notice served, for recipient to obtain partial stay of execution of judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">application dismissed.   bankruptcy act 1914 (eng.)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">ss. 1(g), 4(1)(a)   bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">ss. 40(1)(g) , 41 (1)(a), 41 (5), 41 (6), 44 (1)(a)  federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">o 37, r 6(2); o 37, r 10  property law act 1974 (qld)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1377">s 84</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1262">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1262">bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1262">setting aside notice on basis of existence of a stay of judgment debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1262">whether requirement contained in court rule that a judgment creditor get leave to issue execution on judgment debt after lapse of 6 years creates a "stay" for purposes of bankruptcy act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1262">whether bankruptcy act requires only that judgment not be stayed as at time of issue or at time of service as well.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">creditor's petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">notice of opposition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">whether unexecuted mortgage offered as security for debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">whether sufficient security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">effect of instalment order made by district court as stay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">whether bankruptcy notice capable of amendment in substantive way</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">whether amendment should be sealed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 938">discretionary refusal of sequestration.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 249">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 249">creditor's petition for sequestration orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 249">s.40(1)(g) of bankruptcy act 1966</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 249">local court ordered judgment debt be paid by instalments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 249">whether judgment was one "the execution of which had not been stayed".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 91">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 91">bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 91">whether stay of execution on judgment granted after service of bankruptcy notice, but before expiry of its period, invalidates bankruptcy notice.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">high court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">stay of supreme court order pending application for special leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">jurisdiction to grant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">preservation of subject-matter of litigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[1986] HCA 84">factors relevant to exercise of discretion to grant stay.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">new trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">verdict regularly obtained</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">fresh evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">availability and character of evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">reason for non-production on first trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">standard necessary before court will interfere</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">presentation of fresh evidence to appellate court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=cited from="[1955] HCA 16">necessity for fullest detail.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 310">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 310">application to stay proceedings pending appeal to high court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">application to set aside a bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">whether valid service of bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">whether circumstances such as to go behind judgment/order on which bankruptcy notice based</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">whether counter-claim asserted by corporation constituted counter-claim of debtor within s.40(1)(g) of the bankruptcy act 1966 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 86">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">application for an extension of time to comply and to set aside bankruptcy notices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">matters settled prior to hearing except for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">creditor pursued appropriate course to recover outstanding levies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 941">costs awarded to creditor.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">creditor's petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">application by debtor for adjournment to allow further proceedings to be taken in another court in relation to judgment on which debt claimed by petitioning creditor was based</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">alternatively debtor proposed to seek pre-action discovery with a view to setting aside same judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">refusal by primary judge to stay sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">nature of discretion to grant adjournment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">whether favourable exercise entailed by assumption of a genuine arguable case in the other court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.7" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">whether short adjournment should have been granted to enable debtor to file further affidavits and written submissions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.8" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">relevance of capacity of trustee in bankruptcy to pursue relief in the other court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.9" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">whether assumption of existence of an arguable case in other court continued to be made when primary judge exercised discretion whether or not to make a sequestration order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.10" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">matters relevant to the exercise of that discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.11" type=citing from="[2007] FCAFC 167">evidence required to establish prior legal assignment by petitioning creditor of chose in action which gave rise to judgment debt.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 310">There is precedent for this Court granting an order staying proceedings under a sequestration order until the hearing or earlier determination of an application to the High Court for special leave to appeal. In Murdaca v Accounts Control Management Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 964 , such a stay was granted by Branson J. Her Honour reasoned that such an application is, or at least is akin to, an application for a stay to preserve the subject matter of litigation, pending the application for special leave to appeal being determined. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FMCA 86">As pointed out in Wiltshire-Smith , generally speaking the relevant time for the existence or non-existence of a stay is the date of the application for the issue of a bankruptcy notice (see s.41(3)(b) of the Bankruptcy Act ). Insofar as the concept " the execution of which has not been stayed " also relates to the time at which the Bankruptcy Notice was served, there was no stay of execution or stay on the orders in force at the time of service of the notice and there is authority to suggest that a bankruptcy notice is not stayed, or set aside, by reason of orders made for payment of a judgment debt by instalments and a stay of execution made after service of the bankruptcy notice (see Re Schekeloff; Ex parte Schekeloff v The Hopkins Group Pty Limited (1989) 22 FCR 407 ; [1989] FCA 91 , but cf Murdaca v Accounts Control Management Services Pty Ltd (2007) 5 ABC(NS) 251; [2007] FCA 964 at [15] ). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 941">However, Mr Wilson referred to the decision in Murdaca v Accounts Control Management Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 964 per Branson J and especially at [15] which states: In my respectful view, the correctness of the decision in Schekeloff is open to reasonable question. It is at least arguable, in my view, that a debtor does not commit an act of bankruptcy by not complying with a demand to pay a judgment debt which becomes unenforceable during the period allowed for compliance with the demand --- albeit that the debt had been due and payable at the dates of issue and service of the bankruptcy notice. 
Mr Wilson submits that Mr and Mrs Caporale's applications have merit based on Branson J's reasons. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2007] FCAFC 167">7 The appellant had applied under s 52(3) of the Act for the sequestration order to be stayed for a period of 21 days. As the fourth order recounted above indicates, that application was also refused. As Branson J recently pointed out, the appropriate order to be sought in such circumstances would be a stay of proceedings under the sequestration order: Murdaca v Acounts Control Management Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 964 at [2] . See also de Robillard v Carver [2007] FCAFC 73 at [125] . Appended to the reasons published on 18 April 2007, explaining the orders of 23 March was a further order that the time in which to appeal from the making of the sequestration order should run from 18 April 2007.
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 37 Power of Court to rescind orders etc.</title>
<title id="l2">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 40 Acts of bankruptcy</title>
<title id="l3">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 41 Bankruptcy notices</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 25 Exercise of appellate jurisdiction</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 27 Evidence on appeal</title>
<title id="l7">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 </title>
<title id="l8">JUDICIARY ACT 1903 - SECT 35A Criteria for granting special leave to appeal</title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>