<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Limited(Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935 (15 June 2007)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2007/935.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] NSWSC 363">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] NSWSC 363">voluntary administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] NSWSC 363">administrators seek substantial extension of convening period for second meeting</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] NSWSC 363">complex group of companies with substantial assets presenting potential for advantageous dealing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] NSWSC 363">extension granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">extension of time for convening second creditors' meeting pursuant to s 439a(6) of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">reasons justifying extension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">complex liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">balancing test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">position of creditors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 30">extension granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 70">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 70">administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 70">application to extend convening period for creditors' meeting</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 70">whether circumstances justify extension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 70">extension granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1933">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1933">extension of convening period for second meeting of creditors of company in administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1329">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1329">second extension of convening period for second meeting of creditors of companies in administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1329">parliamentary intention of maintaining tight time limits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1329">purpose of company administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1328">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1328">second extension of convening period for second meeting of creditors of company in administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1328">interrelation with administration of other companies in corporate group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2007] FCA 1328">role of trustee for unsecured noteholders</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 30">In order for the administrators to carry out their function properly, it is necessary that they should have sufficient time to investigate the affairs of the companies under administration and to provide sensible information and advice to the creditors: Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935 at [1] . That includes sufficient time to investigate and carry out a sale process in which structured 'due diligence' procedures are adopted: Re Diamond Press at [11], Re Hans Continental Smallgoods Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1933 at [21] . It also includes time to pursue a possible recapitalisation. In Re Chemeq Ltd; ex parte McMaster [2007] WASC 154 an extension of six months was allowed for this purpose. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] NSWSC 585">


 
16 This "balancing test" has been applied frequently in later cases: for example Re Georges, Midas Australia Pty Ltd (admin apptd) [2009] FCA 38 ; Re Hayes; Estate Property Group Ltd [2007] FCA 935). If the approach is to "balance" the expectation of speedy administration against the risk of prejudice, there cannot be any predisposition in favour of speedy administration, for that would skew the balancing process. Rather, the cases suggest that where the administrator proves a substantial ground in any of the categories that I have set out, and there is no specific evidence of prejudice, an extension commensurate with the administrator's task will be granted, notwithstanding that the Explanatory Memorandum suggested that extensions would not be granted frequently.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 70">Against this background, it can be seen that these proceedings raise what Gyles J described in Re Hayes ; Estate Property Group Ltd (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935 at para 1, hereafter, Hayes' case, as: 
 ...the familiar tension between, on the one hand, the objective of having the first stage of administration dealt with promptly so as not to unduly interfere with the rights of those whom a moratorium affects and, on the other hand, giving worthwhile information to the creditors so that sensible decisions can be made at the meeting. It is well understood that in complex administrations these two objectives can often be in collision. If they are in collision then, in many cases, priority will be given to obtaining sensible information and advice from the administrators to enable the creditors to have the material before them to make an informed decision. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 1933">24 In Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Ltd (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935 , Gyles J took a slightly different approach from that which was adopted in the cases referred to above. His Honour made orders extending the convening period for up to 60 days but he reserved consideration of any application to further extend the period if a case were made out for such a further extension. His Honour said he would then exercise the power provided for by s 447A. (See also Hall, in the matter of Australian Capital Reserve Ltd (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1328 at [1] ). The effect of the approach taken by Gyles J, if adopted in the present case, would be for an extension of time to be dealt with in stages and that is a matter I have considered carefully in considering the application that was made to me this morning. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2007] FCA 1329">1 On 15 June 2007 I made orders extending the convening period for the meeting of creditors required to be held under s 439A of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Act) to midnight 23 July 2007 in relation to a number of companies, being the members of what is known as the Estate Property Group (the Group), together with some ancillary orders on the application of the administrators of the companies in the Group (the Administrators) ( Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935). In a related application concerning Australian Capital Reserve Limited (Administrators Appointed) (ACR), on 12 June 2007 orders were made extending the "decision period" provided for by s 441A(1)(b) of the Act to the last day of the convening period for a number of companies in the Group ( Australian Capital Reserve Limited (Administrators Appointed) v High Tower Investments Pty Limited (Administrators Appointed); in the matter of High Tower Investments Pty Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1028). On 13 July 2007 the convening period for the second meeting of creditors of those companies was further extended to midnight on 31 August 2007 utilising the provisions of s 447A(1) of the Act to achieve that result and certain ancillary orders were made. I indicated then that I would give reasons for those orders in due course. These are those reasons. These reasons should be read with those in Hall, in the matter of Australian Capital Reserve Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1328 to be delivered contemporaneously. The background to these reasons is set out in the various judgments to which I have referred and need not be repeated.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2007] FCA 1328">1 On 12 June last I made orders under s 447A of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) (the Act) in relation to an extension of the "decision period" provided for by s 441A(1)(b) ( Australian Capital Reserve Limited (Administrators Appointed) v High Tower Investments Pty Limited (Administrators Appointed); in the matter of High Tower Investments Pty Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1028). On 15 June last I made orders extending the convening period for the meeting of creditors required to be held under s 439A of the Act to midnight on 23 July 2007. I reserved consideration of any application to further extend that period indicating that, if a case were made out, I would exercise the power provided for by s 447A to achieve that end. Reasons for that decision were given together with reasons in relation to an extension of the convening period in relation to the related Estate Property group of companies (the Group) ( Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Ltd (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 935). Those various judgments, together with the judgment relating to the Estate Property group of companies to be handed down contemporaneously with these reasons ( Hayes, in the matter of Estate Property Group Limited (Administrators Appointed) [2007] FCA 1329) , explain the background to this application, which need not be repeated here.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 439A Administrator to convene meeting and inform creditors</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 439B Conduct of meeting</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 441A Where chargee acts before or during decision period</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 447A General power to make orders</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>