<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited (ACN 004 069 649) [2008] FCA 1542 (16 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1542.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">discretion of court if applicant ordinarily resident outside australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">no evidence of any assets within the jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">no evidence of assets in foreign jurisdiction where judgment may be registered in future</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) s 56</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 540">federal court rules 1976 (cth) o 28 r 3.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">'viagra'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">reputation in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">'herbagra' deceptively similar to and likely to deceive or cause confusion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">appeal allowed intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">whether reputation should be taken into account in relation to s 44 of the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">if not, marks not deceptively similar intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">mark not likely to deceive or cause confusion because of connotation  intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">standard of proof in appeal from opposition proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">opponent must establish ground of opposition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1663">no need to 'clearly' establish ground</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">application by respondent to action for order that applicant give security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">federal court act 1976 (cth), s 56</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">federal court rules , o 28 r 3</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">factors relevant to exercise of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">apparent strength of applicant's case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">where applicant resident outside jurisdiction and has no assets in jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 759">held, in circumstances, appropriate to order security for costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">application to review asc decision to apply to corporations and securities panel for declaration of unacceptable circumstances s 733(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">whether reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=cited from="[1991] AATA 211">whether jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">jurisdiction of court to make order against limited liability company which is an applicant in proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">matters relevant to exercise of judge's discretion.  federal court of australia act 1976 , sub-sec. 56(1), s. 59 , order 28 of the rules  judiciary act 1903 , s.79  companies code 1981 (q.)  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">bases of jurisdiction to make orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth), ss 56(1) , 59</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.8" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">federal court rules 1979 (cth), o. 28</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.9" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 34">companies code 1981 (qld), s. 553. held: (1) the jurisdiction of the federal court to make orders for security for costs under the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth), s. 56(1) was not limited to the circumstances envisaged by o. 28.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">registered user</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">application for registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">exclusive licensee of trade mark in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether registrar entitled to impose condition that user will not make notification under s. 103 of trade marks act 1955 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether intention of user to achieve objects other than saving of mark from invalidation a ground for refusing registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether applicant must manufacture goods for &amp;which registration sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether distributor can be registered as user</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether use of mark by applicant must indicate a connexion between user and goods to exclusion of registered proprietor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.9" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">whether registration of user likely to deceive public</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.10" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.11" type=cited from="[1977] HCA 56">trade marks act 1955 (cth), ss. 6 (1), 74, 103, 114 (f).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of an application for further security for the costs to be incurred by the respondent in the preparation for trial and the conduct of the trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the application in the context of an appeal by the applicant from a decision of the delegate of the registrar of trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the costs attributable to resisting the appeal and isolating those costs referable to the respondent's cross-appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the disaggregation of the costs so as to focus on those "at risk" costs generated by the appeal rather than those costs referable to the respondent's cross-appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the questions raised by the cross-appeal, the field of issues alive and the scope of evidence relevant to the issues</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of whether a notice to produce issued by the applicant in the proceedings is oppressive and ought to be set aside  intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of an application for security for costs by a cross-appellant in a trade mark appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the scope of the issues raised by the appeal itself</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the issues, questions to be addressed and evidence directed to the matters in issue raised by the appeal as compared with matters in issue arising upon the cross-appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1372">consideration of the principles to be applied in the circumstances of an appeal and cross-appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">no assets in jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">whether litigation conducted in breach of the overarching purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">whether delay has resulted in prejudice to applicants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1209">further security ordered.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">application for security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">broad power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">unfettered discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">rules do not confine discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">application made month before hearing of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 796">security granted in reduced amount</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 703">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 703">consideration of an appeal by the trade mark owner from a decision of the registrar to remove a trade mark from the register on the ground of non-use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 703">consideration of s 92(4)(b) of the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 703">consideration of whether the trade mark owner has used the mark in relation to the services for which it is registered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 703">consideration of the meaning to be attributed to the services as specified</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 68">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 68">consideration of an application by a respondent for an order for security for costs of and incidental to appeal proceedings under s 104 of the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 68">consideration of an application by the applicant in those proceedings for an order that the respondent provide security for the applicant's costs of and incidental to the proceeding</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1372">The present application for security for costs is the second application for security made by the respondent. The first application was determined by orders made on 16 October 2008: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542 ; (2008) 79 IPR 286 (the " NVS v BAT decision"). On 16 October 2008, the applicant was ordered to give security within 30 days of the order in an amount of $20,000 by way of an Australian bank guarantee or bond (in a form acceptable to the respondent or fixed by the Court) for the respondent's costs of and incidental to responding to the grounds of appeal relied upon by the applicant in its appeal from the decision of the Registrar's Delegate of 31 July 2008. By [38] of the NVS v BAT decision the amount of $20,000 was formulated as security for the costs incurred by BAT of and incidental to responding to NVS's grounds of appeal "up to and including the completion of the preparation of statements of evidence". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 1209">It has been held that the practice in Australia has ' for a very long time' required that a party who is not ordinarily resident and who has no assets within the jurisdiction ' is normally ordered to give security for costs': see NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (ACN 004 069 649) [2008] FCA 1542 ; (2008) 79 IPR 286 at [13] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 796">The expression in r 3(1)(a), namely that an applicant is " ordinarily resident outside Australia " has no technical or special meaning: Logue v Hansen Technologies Ltd [2003] FCA 81 at [38] , [2003] FCA 81 ; 125 FCR 590 per Weinberg J. The purpose of ordering security in such circumstances has been summarised by Gummow J in Energy Drilling Inc v Petroz N.L. (1989) ATPR 40-954 as follows at 50,422: 
 
 The purpose of ordering security for costs against an applicant ordinarily resident outside the jurisdiction is to ensure that a successful respondent will have a fund available within the jurisdiction of this Court against which it can enforce the judgment for costs, so that the respondent does not bear the risk as to the certainty of enforcement in the foreign country and as to the time and complexity of the action there which might be necessary to effect enforcement: ... On the other hand, the mere circumstance that an applicant is resident outside the jurisdiction does not necessarily invite an exercise of discretion in favour of ordering security, the question being how justice will best be served in the particular case: ... (citations omitted) 
 

 
See also: Austin, Nichols &amp; Co Inc v Lodestar Anstalt [2009] FCA 1228 at [21] per Lindgren J. The fact that an applicant is ordinarily resident outside Australia is a factor, it has been said, which should be given " great weight ": P S Chellaram &amp; Co Ltd v China Ocean Shipping Co [1991] HCA 36 ; (1991) 102 ALR 321 at 323 per McHugh J. See also: B W Offshore Ltd v Anzon Australia Limited [2009] FCA 1133 at [30] . The " practice in Australia for a very long time has been that a party who is not ordinarily resident in this country and has no assets within the jurisdiction, is normally ordered to give security for costs ": NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Co v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd [2008] FCA 1542 at [13] per Greenwood J. But the fact that an applicant is ordinarily so resident may not be sufficient in itself to " induce the court to exercise its discretion to make an order ": CBS Records Australia Ltd v Telmak Teleproducts (Aust) Pty Ltd , supra at 284 to 285 per Bowen CJ. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 703">Having regard to the powers conferred on the Court under s 197 of the Act, an appeal proceeding under s 104, like an appeal under s 56 of the Act, is a hearing conducted de novo on material properly placed before the Court: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542 ; Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks [2001] FCA 333 ; (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] FCA 1228">In NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (ACN 004 069 649) [2008] FCA 1542 ; (2008) 79 IPR 286 ( NV Sumatra ), Greenwood J made an order that the applicant, NV Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company (NVS) provide security for certain costs that might be awarded against it in favour of the respondent, British American Tobacco Australia Services Ltd (BAT), notwithstanding the fact that NVS was the registered proprietor of 29 trade marks in Australia and the applicant in a number of pending applications to register trade marks. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2009] FCA 68">The application before this Court under s 104 is an application in the original jurisdiction of the Court. Having regard to the powers conferred upon the Court under s 197 of the Act, it is plain that it is not necessary on appeal under s 104 to determine whether the decision of the Registrar was correct when made. In that sense, the appeal proceeding is a hearing conducted "afresh" or de novo (like an appeal proceeding under s 56 of the Act: N.V. Sumatra Tobacco Trading Company v British American Tobacco Australia Services Limited [2008] FCA 1542) on material properly placed before the Court ( Blount Inc. v Registrar of Trade Marks [1998] FCA 440 ; (1998) 83 FCR 50 at 58-9; [1998] FCA 440 ; 40 IPR 498 at 506; Soncini v Registrar of Trade Marks (2001) 109 FCR 548 ; [2001] FCA 333 ; 51 IPR 411 ; Ostrowski-Meissner v Registrar of Trade Marks [2006] FCA 951 ; (2006) 69 IPR 291 at [7] and [8]). Section 197 is in these terms: On hearing an appeal against a decision or direction of the Registrar, the Federal Court may do any one or more of the following:
 
 (a) admit further evidence orally, or on affidavit or otherwise;
 (b) permit the examination and cross-examination of witnesses, including witnesses who give evidence before the Registrar;
 (c) order an issue of fact to be tried as it directs;
 (d) affirm, reverse or vary the Registrar's decision or direction;
 (e) give any judgment, or make any order, that, in all the circumstances, it thinks fit;
 (f) order a party to pay costs to another party. 

 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 56 Security</title>
<title id="l2">FOREIGN JUDGMENTS ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l3">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l4">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 43 Trade mark likely to deceive or cause confusion</title>
<title id="l5">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 44 Identical etc. trade marks</title>
<title id="l6">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 55 Decision</title>
<title id="l7">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 56 Appeal</title>
<title id="l8">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 60 Trade mark similar to trade mark that has acquired a reputation in Australia</title>
<title id="l9">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 197 Powers of Federal Court</title>
<title id="l10">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>