<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZLSW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1321 (18 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1321.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">pakistani applicant claiming persecution by government narcotics agents and fundamentalist islamic group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">disbelieved by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">no error in failure to obtain translation of foreign language documents tendered by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">no other jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 498">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">szbyr v minister for immigration and citizenship  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the appellants were refused a visa under s 36(2) of the migration act 1958 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the appellants gave a statutory declaration to the refugee review tribunal ("the tribunal")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the tribunal affirmed the decision not to grant a visa partly on the basis of discrepancies between the statutory declaration and the appellants' oral evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether relief was available to the appellants.  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">s 424a of the act , read with s 441a , requires that an applicant be given written notice of particulars of any information that would be a reason or a part of the reason for affirming a decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether s 424a applied to the appellants' statutory declaration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">temporal scope of s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether the tribunal breached s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether the tribunal committed jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">meaning of "information"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether "information" included discrepancies or inadequacies in previously submitted evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">meaning of "reason, or a part of the reason".  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">constitutional writs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">certiorari and mandamus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">impact of discretionary considerations governing availability of relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether relief should be denied on discretionary grounds for lack of a convention nexus.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">whether tribunal failed to consider substance of claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">whether tribunal failed to distinguish between the indonesian national army and the indonesian authorities. administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">construction of reasons for decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">whether the accidental omission of the word 'not' in tribunal's reasons sufficiently clear for the relevant sentence to be construed as if that word appeared in it.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">application for order nisi remitted to federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">application (amended with leave) expressly claimed constitutional writs in terms of orders absolute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">proceedings at first instance conducted as if applications for orders absolute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">judgment given on that basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 171">whether leave required.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">typographical error in reasons of tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">whether inference can be drawn as to conclusions of tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">where no corrigendum issued</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">where tribunal member not called to give evidence. migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">failure to consider substance of claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">tribunal did not address applicant's membership of social groups</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">whether tribunal had dealt with all "essential integers" of the applicant's claims. words &amp; phrases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2003] FCA 1153">'plausible'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">re the minister for immigration and multicultural affairs; ex parte durairajasingham  immigration law and administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">refugee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">refugee review tribunal decision refusing to grant protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">application in original jurisdiction of high court for prerogative relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether tribunal failed to take into account relevant considerations and evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether tribunal failed to consider all available inferences from evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether s 430(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth) required the tribunal to refer to evidence contrary to its findings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">whether a breach of s 430(1) amounts to a jurisdictional error grounding prerogative relief.  constitutional law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">federal jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">role of the high court under the constitution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[2000] HCA 1">extent of high court's jurisdiction to grant certiorari pursuant to s 75(v) of the constitution .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">application to review decisions of minister's delegates refusing claim for refugee status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">application of chan v minister for immigration and ethnic affairs [1989] hca 62 ; (1989) 169 clr 379</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">'real chance' of persecution test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">whether delegates failed properly to consider real chance of persecution.   administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">decisions as to 'refugee status'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[1996] HCA 6">proper role of reviewing court.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">appellants claimed they had been issued with summonses in china</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">tribunal informed appellants summonses not on file</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">summonses actually on file but not translated into english</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">whether tribunal had obligation to find summonses and translate them</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">whether tribunal in any event considered appellants' claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">whether tribunal misunderstood claims of appellants to be members of a "local family church"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1050">application of s 91r migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">duty to make inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">adequate inquiries undertaken</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">duty to obtain translation of documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">circumstances in which duty may arise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">duty does not arise   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">attempt to rely upon a ground of appeal abandoned before the federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1542">leave to raise as ground of appeal refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">lebanese applicant claiming fear of persecution by hezbollah</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">disbelieved by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">no breach of s.424(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">findings open on the evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">no general duty on tribunal to obtain translations or make inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">no jurisdictional error established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1140">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">rrt decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">bangladeshi applicant claiming political persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">claims not made in visa application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">delay in raising them before tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">tribunal rejected claims as recent invention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">whether conclusion affected by fraud of migration agent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">fraudulent conduct not established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">no jurisdictional error by tribunal in consideration of corroborative documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">no duties on tribunal to inquire or obtain translations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">no jurisdictional error in tribunal's application of s.91r(3)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.11" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 44">application dismissed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 1050">Second, the facts clearly demonstrate that the relevant summonses, while apparently included in the material before the Tribunal, were not translated into English. As a general proposition, while s 414 of the Act requires the Tribunal to review decisions of the Minister, it is not for the Tribunal to arrange to have material on the file translated where the relevance of the material is not explained: Cabal v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 546 at [25] . In this case, in light of the obligation on the appellants to make their own case, it could not be expected that the Tribunal would take the appellants through the file on a document by document search in an endeavour to locate the summonses when they were not apparent, in English, on the face of the file. To the extent that the Tribunal was obliged to ask the appellants about the location of the summonses because the appellants' case clearly relied in part on the existence of those documents, I consider that the Tribunal discharged that obligation when it put to the first appellant that it had not seen the summonses and outlined the documents on the file. That this is so is also clear from: The fact that, when the Tribunal specifically asked the appellants about the whereabouts of the summonses, the final answer given to the Tribunal was that the appellants would need to ask their migration agent. To that extent, there is no evidence (unlike, for example, in SZLSW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1321 ; (2008) 103 ALD 580) that the Tribunal was taken to the summonses and the relevance of those documents explained despite the lack of translation. In those circumstances it is not surprising that the Tribunal should have concluded that the summonses were not in the material before it. The fact that relevant documentation from the Tribunal which was before the appellants referred to the need for material upon which the appellants were relying to be translated into English (for example, Section E of the Application for Review, the letter of 1 December 2008 from the Tribunal to the appellants' migration agent, the letter of 15 December 2008 from the Tribunal to the first appellant, the letter of 20 August 2009 from the Tribunal to the appellants). That the appellants recognised this need is illustrated by the fact that the statement of the first appellant annexed to the Application for Review dated 15 November 2008 includes an English translation initialled by the first appellant. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 1542">The second reason why this final Ground of Appeal should be rejected is that, in the present proceeding, the now Appellant had been expressly invited by the Tribunal to draw its attention to any particular document that he specifically sought to rely upon. He apparently declined that invitation. The reasons for decision of the Tribunal thus record that it asked the Appellant " whether there was anything he particularly wanted to refer it to within the large amount of material submitted ...". And that arose, it is to be recalled, in a context where the now Appellant had been requested to provide documents to the Tribunal in advance of the hearing and yet only produced many of the documents on the day of the hearing itself. A claimant cannot complain of any inadequacy of an opportunity to be heard, or of any failure to take into account a particular matter, in circumstances where he produces a vast number of documents at a hearing before the Tribunal and fails to avail himself of an opportunity to draw the Tribunal's attention to a particular matter or matters contained within those documents. Even where a document is not translated, there may be no error where the Tribunal in fact takes into account a point sought to be made by a claimant in reliance upon untranslated documents: SZLSW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 1321 at [16] , 103 ALD 580 at 584. Where the " gist " of a document which is otherwise untranslated is understood, there may be no error: S14/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1153 at [49] per Moore J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 1140">Nor do I accept that the Tribunal was under any obligations itself to obtain translations of the documents which were not in English. It is well established that the Tribunal is under no such general obligation (see the authorities I cited in SZLSW v Minister for Immigration [2008] FMCA 498 , upheld by Rares J in SZLSW v Minister for Citizenship &amp; Immigration [2008] FCA 1321). In the present circumstances, it was open to the Tribunal to expect the applicant and his solicitor to present translations, if indeed the contents of these documents formed an important part of his case. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FMCA 44">As with the general powers of the Tribunal to make its own inquiries into evidence, the authorities establish that only exceptionally will a Tribunal have any obligation to obtain translations so as to have regard to the contents of foreign language documents submitted by an applicant (see the line of authority I cited in SZLSW v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2008] FMCA 498 at [36] , upheld by Rares J in SZLSW v Minister for Citizenship &amp; Immigration [2008] FCA 1321). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 414 Refugee Review Tribunal must review decisions</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424 Tribunal may seek information</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>