<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Travelex Limited v Commissioner of Taxation (Corrigendum dated 4 February 2009) [2008] FCA 1961 (19 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1961.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">goods and services tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">apportionment of credits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">whether full input tax credits available to taxpayer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">taxpayer acquired services in a taxable supply by way of a feasibility study as to whether it should acquire debts and recover them</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">taxpayer carrying on enterprise of acquiring debts and recovering them, acquisition of debts a financial supply</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">taxpayer also acquired services relating to recovery of debts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">whether input credits disallowed as relating to the making of a financial supply (the acquisition of the debts) which would be input taxed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 126">whether credits disallowed where acquisition of recovery services related to the financial supply (the acquisition of the debts) a new tax system (goods and services tax) act 1999 (cth), ss 11 -15(2)(a), 11 -5, 11 -20, div 132 a new tax system (goods and services tax) regulations 1999 (cth), regs 70-5.02, 40-5.09</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">by-laws and regulations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">operation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">requirement to notify in gazette</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">availability for purchase</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">effect on validity of non-compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">acts interpretation act 1901 (cth), s. 48 (1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">rules publication act 1903 (cth), s. 5 (3)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">ordinances and regulations (notification) act 1972 (cth), s. 4 (1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">banking act 1974 (cth), s. 4 (1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">banking (foreign exchange) regulations , regs 6, 42.  constitutional law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">powers of commonwealth parliament</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">currency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">law prohibiting taking australian currency or foreign currency out of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">the constitution (63 &amp; 64 vict. c. 12), s. 51 (xii.)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[1979] HCA 53">banking act 1974 (cth), ss. 3 , 4 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">a new tax system (goods and services tax) act 1999</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">s 38-190</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">conversion of australian dollars into foreign currency for use outside australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">whether transaction attracts gst</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 133">whether transaction a "supply in relation to rights"</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] HCA 33">

 At first instance, Emmett J concluded [13] that the rights which are the incidents of being the holder or owner of bank notes issued by a foreign country "are not relevantly connected with the supply constituted by the ... currency transaction, such that it can be said that the supply of the bank notes was a supply made in relation to those so-called rights". There is not a supply "in relation to rights" "where the supply of rights is merely integral, ancillary or incidental to another dominant part of the supply, the supply being characterised by the dominant part" [7] . The appellant, however, put an alternative submission: that whether or not the Fijian bank notes had the characteristics of promissory notes, the Reserve Bank of Fiji Act 1983 (Fiji), ss 22, 24, 26 and 27, endowed their possessors with equivalent rights [30] . Emmett J concluded [6] that there could be a supply "in relation to rights" only "if the essential character or substance of the supply, or of a separately identifiable part of the supply, is one of rights". " [43] 
 In the Full Court, Stone J and Edmonds J, for reasons which differed in some respects, agreed generally with the primary judge. At first instance, Emmett J rejected Travelex's arguments and dismissed [5] the proceeding. This submission appealed to the trial judge, who said that the rights which the holder of the Fijian bank notes had could not be said [33] :
 
 
 "to be the subject of any transfer or assignment by Travelex, merely because they are incidents that pass with ownership or possession of the bank notes. Rather, as noted earlier, Emmett J identified [14] the supply as "a supply of the physical notes", and concluded that "[t]he incidents of being the holder or owner of those bank notes were simply the consequences of becoming holder or owner". A supply that does not bind the parties in some way was said [25] to be "not a supply that is made in relation to rights". At first instance, Emmett J distinguished between rights that are "the essential character or substance of the supply, or of a separately identifiable part of the supply" and those that are "merely integral, ancillary or incidental to another dominant part of the supply" [24] .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCAFC 133">28 This appeal raises a question of construction in relation to the A New Tax System (Goods and Services Tax) Act 1999 (Cth) ( GST Act) . The facts which give rise to this question are not in dispute. They are as deposed to in an affidavit made on 21 December 2007 by Mr Geoffrey Urquhart, an employee of the appellant, and as set out fully in [2]-[7] of the reasons of the primary judge; Travelex Limited v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 1961. For present purposes a brief account will suffice.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (GOODS AND SERVICES TAX) ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l1">CUSTOMS ACT 1901 </title>
<title id="l2">CUSTOMS ACT 1901 - SECT 113 Entry of goods for export</title>
<title id="l3">CUSTOMS ACT 1901 - SECT 185 Power to board and search etc. ships and aircraft</title>
<title id="l4">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (GOODS AND SERVICES TAX) REGULATIONS 1999 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>