<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lifetime Investments Pty Ltd v Commercial (Worldwide) Financial Services Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1150 (6 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1150.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">contempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">breaches of the court's orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">appeal against findings of contempt pursuant to s 112ap of the family law act 1975 (cth) and the imposition of two sentences of imprisonment with respect to such contempts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">terms of settlement entered into by the husband and wife providing for the husband's appeal to be allowed and the trial judge's orders set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">whether appropriate to allow "settlement" of contempt proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">need to balance the avoidance of the undermining of the administration of justice by condoning breaches of the court's orders, and the limit to the public interest which thus arises by virtue of the inter partes nature of the breaches</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">in the circumstances of the case, disposal of the appeal as urged would be inappropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">merits of the husband's appeal considered.  family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">contempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that the trial judge erred in finding beyond reasonable doubt that the husband's action constituted a flagrant challenge to the authority of the court within the meaning of s.112ap(1)(b)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that the trial judge's exercise of discretion in relation to the findings of contempt was vitiated by the failure to refer to any relevant fact or circumstance or by reliance upon any irrelevant facts or circumstances or by placing excessive weight on any matter or by any discernible error of principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">an absence of significant or enduring adverse consequences for the other party does not preclude the application of s 112ap , nor does the attribution, or absence, of a "motive" to the husband for his actions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">correct standard of proof in relation to the evidence supporting the finding of flagrancy applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">adverse findings in relation to the credit of the husband reasonably supported by the evidence.  family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">procedural fairness and natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that husband denied procedural fairness by refusing to allow affidavit evidence where deponent unavailable for cross-examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that any purported failure to particularise the wife's claims as to the conduct constituting flagrancy in any way prejudiced the husband.  not established that the trial judge's orders in any way precluded the husband from making an application for reduction of sentence pursuant to s 112ap(7).  family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">sentence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that the trial judge's exercise of discretion in relation to sentence was vitiated by the failure to refer to any relevant fact or circumstance or by reliance upon any irrelevant facts or circumstances or by placing excessive weight on any matter or by any discernible error of principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">appropriate standard of proof applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">no distinction in principle between a contempt constituting a flagrant breach to the authority of the court involving interim as opposed to final orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.23" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">not established that his honour applied incorrect principle by imposing a custodial sentence upon the husband as opposed to a fine or other penalty upon the basis of his wealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.24" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">consideration of the husband's purported contrition was not in error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.25" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">character of the husband not impermissibly taken into account to the husband's detriment or as in any way "aggravating" the offence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.26" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">whether sentences were manifestly excessive or unreasonable, or plainly unjust</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.27" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">established that circumstances of the case rendered custodial sentences inappropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.28" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">challenge to the severity of the sentences imposed upon the husband upheld.  family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.29" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">re-exercise of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.30" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">re-exercise of the discretion of the trial judge carried out by reference to the facts and circumstances of the case at the present time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.31" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">the husband's appeal against the sentences imposed upon him allowed, sentences of imprisonment set aside, and no sanctions imposed.  family law act 1975 (cth) s 112ap ; s 94(2b)(b)  family law rules 2004</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.32" type=citing from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">r 15.14  abalos v australian postal commission [1990] hca 47 ; (1990) 171 clr 167  abduramanoski v abduramanoska (2005)191 flr [2005] famca 88 ; 360; (2005) flc 93-215 ; (2005) 33 fam lr 1  allesch v maunz (2000) 203 clr 172; 173 alr 648  asic v michalik [2004] nswsc 1259 ; (2004) 52 acsr 115  attorney-general v times newspapers ltd [1974] ac 27</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FamCAFC 154">The husband's Counsel, referring to Lifetime Investments Pty Limited v Commercial (Worldwide) Financial Services Pty Limited [2008] FCA 1150 , submitted as follows: 
Justice Spender was there dealing with an Amended Notice of Motion seeking that the first and second respondents be committed to prison for contempt however his Honour noted that the parties had arrived at a settlement and held:- 
 
 "Having regard to the above communications, in my view there is no utility in proceeding to determine a matter which has been overtaken by the further negotiations and agreements reached between the parties. It is not the function of the court to give advisory opinions on disputed questions of fact, where there is no current controversy concerning what had previously been claimed by way of relief in a dispute between the parties. The Amended Notice of Motion in addition to Orders of Committal sought consequential orders concerning the proceeds of cattle sales and the restitution of funds obtained by the grant of the Davis mortgage, matters which I infer from the correspondence are caught by the settlement agreement. 
 
 For these reasons it is not appropriate to make any order on the Amended Notice of Motion. The Amended Notice of Motion seeking that relief is therefore dismissed. In those circumstances it is appropriate that the court make no order as to costs. "  In Lifetime Investments Pty Limited v Commercial (Worldwide) Financial Services Pty Limited [2008] FCA 1150 , also concerning a Notice of Motion seeking relief in relation to contempt allegations, Spender J said (at [12]), in a passage to which we have earlier referred: Having regard to the above communications, in my view, there is no utility in proceeding to determine a matter which has been overtaken by the further negotiations and agreements reached between the parties. It is not the function of the court to give advisory opinions on disputed questions of fact, where there is no current controversy concerning what had previously been claimed by way of relief in a dispute between the parties. ... For these reasons, it is not appropriate to make any order on the Amended Notice of Motion. The Amended Notice of Motion seeking that relief is therefore dismissed. ... </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>