<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Surfing Hardware International Holdings Pty Limited v McCausland [2008] FCA 1522 (14 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1522.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">hearing rule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">cross-summons filed prior to hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">whether reasonable opportunity to contest cross-summons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">inconsistent pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">concession of existence of lease by claim that it should be set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">denial of existence of lease</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">whether prejudice suffered by the appellantcosts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">general rule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">cross-summons partly successful</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">costs awarded against cross-defendant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">serious allegation of improper conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">relief in cross-summons awarded without examination of allegation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">no finding of misconduct in making allegation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">whether grounds for interfering with exercise of discretionlandlord &amp; tenant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">leases and tenancy agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">special conditions of lease</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">conditions highly favourable to tenant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">tenant to become beneficial owner of two-thirds interest in leased property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.20" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">tenant entitled to rental rebates for various services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.21" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">whether conditions unjust in the circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.22" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">[&lt;i&gt; contracts review act 1980 &lt;/i&gt;] (nsw), s 7(1) procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.23" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">application to re-open hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.24" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">application for equitable set-off and defence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.25" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">not field or served prior to day of judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.26" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">whether application ought to have been entertainedwords &amp; phrases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.27" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">"residential tenancy agreement"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.28" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 403">"special conditions"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 380">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 380">application to set aside bankruptcy notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 380">where applicant claimed he had a cross claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 380">whether applicant could have set up this claim in the proceedings in which judgment was obtained</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 380">where applicant alleged negligence on the part of his solicitors in the original proceedings.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] NSWCA 403">2. No inconsistency arose in the respondent's factual pleadings and supporting affidavit evidence such as to render the respondent's claims impermissible: [33]---[34]. Issitch v Worrell [2000] FCA 477 ; 172 ALR 586 ; Surfing Hardware International Holdings Pty Ltd v McCausland [2008] FCA 1522 ; 171 FCR 533 ; CGU Insurance Ltd v Lawless [2008] VSCA 38 ; 15 ANZ Ins Cas 61-755 ; Brailsford v Tobie [1889] 10 ALT 194 , referred to. 

  30 Brailsford is an example of a case in which a party has not been allowed to plead two inconsistent sets of facts where he or she knows one set of facts to be false. However, the principle, as explained in the Full Court of the Federal Court in Issitch v Worrell [2000] FCA 477 ; 172 ALR 586 at [32] , (Drummond J, Spender and Katz JJ agreeing) is that a party can "as a general rule plead inconsistent sets of facts in the alternative ..., but not where one of those sets must be known to the party to be false". That principle was applied by Foster J in Surfing Hardware International Holdings Pty Ltd v McCausland [2008] FCA 1522 ; 171 FCR 533 at [54] - [59].</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] NSWSC 630">35 No good reason has been advanced at the hearing of the s 500(2) application as to why the First Cross-Claim, at least so far as relates to the Palandri companies, should be brought in the New South Wales proceedings instead of as a defence in the Western Australian proceedings. The facts before me (including, in particular, the temporal sequence of notices of demand, UPF proceedings, undertakings and responses to the demands, Western Australian proceedings, and First Cross-Claim) warrant the inference that the dominant purpose of bringing the cross-claim against the Palandri companies in the New South Wales proceedings is to assist the foreshadowed application to cross-vest the Western Australian proceedings to New South Wales. That also points to the conclusion that the First Cross-Claim constitutes an abuse of process: Surfing Hardware International Holdings Pty Ltd v McCausland [2008] FCA 1522 ; (2008) 171 FCR 533 at [86] per Foster J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 380">Although I have not been addressed in any substantive way about how the claim under s.106 might have been brought in the original proceedings, I note that in Surfing Hardware International Holdings Pty Ltd v McCausland [2008] FCA 1522 , Foster J acknowledged at [12]: "[t]he power to declare a void or vary unfair contracts and related arrangements pursuant to the provisions of section 105 and 106 of the Industrial Relations Act 1996 is the exclusive province of the IRC. Absent of removal of such proceedings into the Supreme Court of New South Wales pursuant to the provisions of section 8(1) of the Jurisdiction of Courts (Cross Vesting) Act 1987 (NSW), the Supreme Court has not jurisdiction in respect to such matters". 
It would appear from this that his Honour accepts that there is a procedure whereby a s.106 cross claim can be heard in the Supreme Court. The above being the case, the cross claim could have been set up in the proceedings in which the judgment was obtained and the only ground that seems to be left to the applicant is his claim that his solicitors were negligent in not telling him about the availability of a s.106 cross claim. Regrettably that will not avail him. In Malcolm Colin Walton v The National Mutual Life Association of Australasia Ltd [1994] FCA 1114 , the Full Bench of the Court, Jenkinson, Burchett and Whitlam JJ, said at [6]:
 
 "At the hearing of the appeal it was also suggested that the appellant may have been able to set up a cross demand because of his solicitor's negligence. No authority was cited to support the proposition that such a case can be maintained and it is sufficient for us to say that the negligent failure of a solicitor in fact to set up a cross demand would not make the cross demand one which a debtor " could not have set up " within the meaning of section 40(1)(g). " 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 181 Good faith--civil obligations</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 182 Use of position--civil obligations</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1317H Compensation orders--corporation/scheme civil penalty provisions</title>
<title id="l4">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 </title>
<title id="l5">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 - SECT 5 Transfer of proceedings</title>
<title id="l6">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 - SECT 8 Orders by Supreme Court of a Territory</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l8">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1996 </title>
<title id="l9">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 8 Definition of industrial instrument</title>
<title id="l10">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 105 Definitions</title>
<title id="l11">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 106 Power of Commission to declare contracts void or varied</title>
<title id="l12">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1996 - SECT 108A Employment contracts in respect of which applications cannot be made</title>
<title id="l13">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 </title>
<title id="l14">JURISDICTION OF COURTS (CROSS-VESTING) ACT 1987 - SECT 8 Orders by Supreme Court</title>
</legistitles>
</case>