<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Carantinos v Magafas [2008] FCA 1107 (31 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1107.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">application that respondent's costs of certain issues be paid on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">discussion of applicable principles.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">legislative scheme for progress payments under construction contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">challenge to validity of state legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">whether balance of convenience favours grant of interlocutory relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">monetary adjustment available if application succeeds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 117">weakness of challenge to validity of state legislation also relevant to whether an injunction should be granted.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 117">The statement of claim pleads reliance upon section 45D of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) and also seeks to raise a constitutional matter, with respect to which, on the same day, notice was given under section 78B of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth). The constitutional matter said to be raised by the proceedings in this Court is to the effect that certain provisions in the BCIP Act are invalid for reason of inconsistency with s 22 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). Section 22 of the Federal Court of Australia Act grants to this Court power to grant all remedies to which parties appear to be entitled, so that as far as possible matters in controversy may be completely and finally determined. It is a grant of power rather than of jurisdiction (see e.g. Carantinos v Magafas [2008] FCA 1107 at [3] ). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 </title>
<title id="l1">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 27 Bankruptcy courts</title>
<title id="l2">BANKRUPTCY ACT 1966 - SECT 52 Proceedings and order on creditor's petition</title>
<title id="l3">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l4">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 77 Power to define jurisdiction</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 22 Determination of matter completely and finally</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 23 Making of orders and issue of writs</title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 32AA Proceedings not to be instituted in the Court if an associated matter is before the Federal Magistrates Court</title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>