<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>IGT v Commissioner of Patents [2008] FCA 15 (17 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/15.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">[ database search ] [ name search ] [ recent decisions ] [ noteup ] [ lawcite ] [ help ] a goninan &amp; co ltd v the commissioner of patents &amp; anor [1997] fca 424 (23 may 1997)   patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">opposition proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">application for second extension of time for filing of evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">factors to be taken into account</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">public interest considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">whether the commissioner of patents is under a duty to grant an extension of time where evidence relevant to the opposition proceedings is immediately available</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1997] FCA 424">whether the commissioner is bound to consider the significance of evidence on which the party seeking an extension wishes to rely in opposition proceedings.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] APO 24">The Federal Court decision, IGT v Commissioner of Patents , [2008] FCA 15 , though warns against elevating the significance of the evidence to a determinative factor effectively excluding consideration of other matters. 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] APO 23">On 17 January 2008 consent orders were issued by the Federal Court setting aside the decision and remitting the matter back to the Commissioner ( IGT v Commissioner of Patents [2008] FCA 15). The reason for setting aside the decision was that:
 
"that the delegate ... could be taken to have elevated the significance of the evidence to a determinative factor effectively excluding consideration of other matters. I emphasise that I do not find that this was the legal effect of the delegate's remark. However, the possibility of error which [IGT and Aristocrat] have accepted, is sufficient to support the consent order which is now sought". </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l2">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 210 Commissioner's powers</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l4">PATENTS REGULATIONS 1991 </title>
<title id="l5">PATENTS REGULATIONS 1991 - REG 5.10 Conduct of proceedings to which this Chapter applies</title>
</legistitles>
</case>