<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Arc Energy Limited, In the matter of Arc Energy Limited [2008] FCA 1396 (8 August 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1396.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">intervener in application for approval of scheme of arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">appropriate for intervener to bring court's attention to litigation instituted by it against plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">relevant to whether scheme ought be approved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">intervener then pressed for adjournment and further meeting of members purportedly to protect interests of proxy voters who had not been informed directly by the plaintiff of litigation brought against it by the intervener</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1412">adjournment sought for ulterior purpose.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 1412">1 These reasons concern the issue of costs following my judgment on the merits in this matter: In the matter of Arc Energy Limited [2008] FCA 1396 ("Arc Energy"). The reasons in that judgment give relevant context and background to these reasons. I heard oral submissions as to costs after judgment was delivered but gave Arc Energy Ltd ("Arc") and Buru Energy Ltd leave to put in further written submissions directed to the case of Re Crusader Limited (1996) 1 Qd R 117 cited by Oil Basins. Arc submits that Oil Basins Limited ("Oil Basins") ought pay the Plaintiff's costs of responding to the application filed by Oil Basins during the afternoon of Thursday, 7 August 2008, which occupied much of the hearing on the afternoon of Friday, 8 August 2008. It also opposes Oil Basins' application for a costs order in its favour. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 5 General territorial application of Act</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 16 Exclusions</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 411 Administration of compromises etc.</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 413 Provisions for facilitating reconstruction and amalgamation of Part 5.1 bodies</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 414 Acquisition of shares of shareholders dissenting from scheme or contract approved by majority</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>