<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Medic-Care Company Ltd v Hamilton Pharmaceutical Pty Limited (ACN 008 204 635) (No 4) [2008] FCA 1038 (10 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1038.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">expert witness report</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">rejection of evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">independent assessment of fair and reasonable costs pursuant to legal profession act 1987 (nsw)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">instructions by practitioner to expert regarding assumptions to be made in determining costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">whether administrative decisions tribunal erred in rejecting expert witness reportlegal practitioners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">legal profession act 1987 (nsw)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">certificate by costs review panel as to fair and reasonable costs pursuant to part 11</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">determination of professional misconduct pursuant to part 10 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">s 208kf costs certificate not binding in disciplinary proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">costs certificate issued under part 11 not determinative of what was fair and reasonable for purposes of professional misconductlegal practitioners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">legal profession act 1987 (nsw)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">professional misconduct pursuant to part 10 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">whether costs 'grossly excessive' is to be determined by evidence and the administrative decisions tribunal may invoke its own professional experiencelegal practitioners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">legal profession act 1987 (nsw) s 208q</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">professional misconduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">deliberate charging of grossly excessive amounts of costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">requirement that practitioner personally implicated in either knowingly overcharging or was reckless as to whether or not excessive costs had been charged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2007] NSWCA 130">whether administrative decisions tribunal erred in finding practitioner guilty of professional misconduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">business records exception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">evidence act 1995 (cth) s 69</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">meaning of 'prepared or obtained' in s 69(3)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1357">meaning of 'in contemplation of' in s 69(3).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">conveyancing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">sham transactions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether loan and mortgage transactions bona fide</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether loan and mortgage transactions liable to be set asideconveyancing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether the loan and mortgage transactions and discharge of mortgage and sale transactions constitute an alienation of property within the meaning of s37a of the conveyancing act 1919</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether there was an intent to defraud creditors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">meaning of "creditors" in s37a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether bona fide purchaser for value and without noticeestoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether a defendant could be precluded from asserting an entitlement to repayment of loan and rely on a mortgage in light of what was said in courtequitable lien or charge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether the plaintiff held an equitable lien or entitled to a charge in equity to secure payment for work done on a house, when subsequent judgment otherwise frustrated by sham transactions, to prevent consequences of unconscionable conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">equitable lien as an alternative to a constructive trust as a remedy for unconscionable conductconspiracy to injure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether the loan and mortgage transactions constituted a conspiracy against the plaintiff</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1187">whether plaintiff suffered any damage.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1083">evidence [121]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1083">documentary evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1083">statutory provisions relating to business records</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1083">source of knowledge asserted fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 1083">representations in contemplation of or in connection with proceedings.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 303">admissibility of documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 303">business records</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 303">whether prepared or obtained "for the purpose of" or "in connection with" proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 303">discretion to reject evidence if admission "unfairly prejudicial".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">torts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">malicious prosecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">absence of reasonable and probable cause for prosecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">where evidence given by investigating police officer to police royal commission that his evidence that the appellant had made admissions demonstrating guilt was fabricated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">nature of subjective belief required from prosecutor concerning case to be prosecuted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">whether reasonable basis for prosecutor's belief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">whether material capable of forming reasonable basis limited to that admissible in evidence[&lt;br&gt;]evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">rule against hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">business records exception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">exclusions from exception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">whether statement made in the course of evidence before police royal commission excluded from exception as a "representation" "obtained" "in connection with" "an australian proceeding"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">general discretion to exclude evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 316">whether discretion should have been exercised to exclude evidence of statement</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] NSWCA 316">89 That rationale was cited by Hamilton J in Lewis v Nortex Pty Ltd (in Liq); Lamru Pty Ltd v Kation Pty Ltd [2002] NSWSC 1083 at [4] , and followed by this passage:
 

 
"(5) This links with what Barrett J has said to be the policy of the section in Vitali v Stachnik supra at [12]: 
 

 
"The purpose of the exclusion is, as I see it, to prevent the introduction through this exception to the hearsay rule of hearsay material which is prepared in an atmosphere or context which may cause it to be self-serving in the sense of possibly being prepared to assist the proof of something known or at least apprehended to be relevant to the outcome of identifiable legal proceedings. "
 

 
(6) The point, as I apprehend it, is that the contemplation or existence of any proceedings may lead even persons of good intent to make purely self serving statements that may, without the exclusory provisions of subs (3), be admissible through the scheme of s 69. From this natural tendency to make self serving statements springs the policy that statements made in those circumstances ought be excluded from the ambit of s 69 which is, in general terms, generous towards the admission of statements contained in documents that meet the criteria of the section. (7) It is not, as Mr Motbey has suggested to me, a requirement of subs (3) that a conclusion be reached that the creator of the document had the purpose of making self serving statements, whether true or false. It is, rather, that the possibility, bearing in mind human nature, to make self serving statements in such circumstances, leads the Act to exclude all statements made in such circumstances as a precaution against purely, and particularly false, self serving statements being taken into evidence. "
 

 
Evidence given on oath is in a different category. (See also Finn J in Australian Medic-Care Company Ltd v Hamilton Pharmaceutical Pty Ltd (No 4) [2008] FCA 1038 ; 170 FCR 9 at [8] --- [15]. ) 26 In Australian Medic-Care Company Ltd v Hamilton Pharmaceutical Pty Ltd (No 4) [2008] FCA 1038 ; (2008) 170 FCR 9 at [8] Finn J said:
 

 
"It is well accepted that the hearsay rule contained in s 69(2) is founded on the "rationale of reliability" of business records generally. The exception to that subsection is founded on a "rationale of unreliability" of representations made in the circumstances envisaged by subs (3). "</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 69 Exception: business records</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 135 General discretion to exclude evidence</title>
<title id="l3">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 136 General discretion to limit use of evidence</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>