<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Luck v Chief Executive Officer of Centrelink (includes corrigendum dated 20 March 2009) [2008] FCA 1879 (10 December 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1879.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">application for extension of time to lodge application under administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">decision to "stand-down" employees following declarations under s.43a of the telecommunications act 1975</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">principles relevant to granting extension of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">undue delay.  administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 , s.11  telecommunications act 1975 , s.43a  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">application for extension of time to lodge application under administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">decision to "stand down" employees following declarations under s. 43a of the telecommunications act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">principles relevant to granting extension of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">undue delay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">relevance of public interest and prejudice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth), s. 11</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 91">telecommunications act 1975 (cth), s. 43a. during a period of industrial dispute the respondent "stood down" certain employees and made directions under s. 43a of the telecommunications act 1975 (cth) that those employees should not be paid their salary for the relevant period. following the end of the dispute the applicants' union commenced inquiries and sought legal advice as to the validity of the order to "stand down". the applicants gave no notice to the respondent of any intention to bring proceedings. the applications for extension of time (within which to lodge applications for orders to review) were lodged about eighteen months after the "stand down" orders.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCAFC 54">68 The relevant passage from his Honour's judgment (in Luck v Chief Executive Officer of Centrelink [2008] FCA 1879) was as follows (at [16]):
 I have been unable to identify any provision in any of the Acts to which Ms Luck referred in her application which empowered the second respondent or any of her delegates to make any of the impugned decisions. Nor is there any evidence that the Second Respondent or a delegate of the second respondent had, in fact, made any of the impugned decisions. She is not a necessary party to the proceeding and she should be removed as a party. I will so order.  54 The primary Judge dismissed the appellant's application for an extension of time in which to seek review of the decisions made on 31 July 2006 and 10 August 2007, the alleged failure to review the 10 August 2007 decision, and the conduct relating to the making of the two decisions mentioned. His Honour's reasons are found at Luck v Chief Executive Officer of Centrelink [2008] FCA 1879. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE DECISIONS (JUDICIAL REVIEW) ACT 1977 - SECT 11 Manner of making applications</title>
<title id="l2">PUBLIC SERVICE ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>