<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Alfred v Wakelin (No. 2) [2008] FCA 1543 (17 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1543.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">industrial action by workforce contrary to greenfields certified agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">whether union and its representatives were party to, or concerned in, industrial action by attending workforce meetings and advising against it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">whether union and representatives liable for breach of dispute resolution procedures of certified agreement industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">whether conduct of job representative elected pursuant to a certified agreement attributable to union agency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 87">whether job representative elected pursuant to a certified industrial agreement agent for union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">contracts  principal and agent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">actual authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">ostensible authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">agent entrusted with document signed by principal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">other party relies on copy of that document</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 375">whether relevant representation of authority made or permitted by principal.  legislation cited:  decision:  1. appeal dismissed with costs 2. cross-appeal dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">pacific carriers limited v bnp paribas  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">carriage of goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">carriage by sea</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">delivery of goods without surrendering bills of lading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">indemnity to carrier.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">construction and interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">relevant principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">objective interpretation of commercial documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">letters of indemnity executed by trader in favour of carrier relating to unloading cargo without bills of lading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">where documents also signed by officer of the respondent bank</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">whether letters of indemnity purported to bind the respondent as an indemnifying party.  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">agency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">ostensible authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">documents of the kind commonly relied upon and intended to be relied upon by third parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 35">whether the assumption made by the appellant that the respondent was party to the letters of indemnity was induced or assisted by the respondent's conduct in such a way that it would be unjust to permit the respondent to depart from the assumption.    gleeson cj, gummow, hayne, callinan and heydon jj. the issues in this appeal are narrower than the claims and cross-claims litigated before hunter j in the supreme court of new south wales [1] , or those aspects of the matter that went to the court of appeal [2] .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">restrictive trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">arrangement or understanding restricting dealings or affecting competition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">attempt to control and to induce others to control discounts on steel products</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">nature of arrangement or understanding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">capacity in which servants of corporations acted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">features of an attempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">relevance of intention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">corporate liability under trade practices act 1974 .  trade practices act 1974 , ss.45(2)(a) , 76 (1)(b), 76 (1)(d), 84 (1) and (2).  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">restrictive trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">arrangement or understanding having effect of lessening competition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">attempting or inducing others to attempt to enter into such arrangement or understanding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">elements of attempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">capacity in which servants of corporations acted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">corporate liability for acts of servants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.15" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">whether statute extends common law principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.16" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">relevance of intention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.17" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss. 45(2)(a) , 76 (1)(b), 76 (1)(d), 84 (1) and (2). the first respondent was the parent company of the second respondent (the subsidiary company). both companies carried on business in western australia as steel merchants. the third respondent was the regional manager of the parent company's western merchandising division, a position which carried overall responsibility for the group's marketing activities in western australia. he was also a director of the subsidiary company but its day to day activities were under the control of its own manager. concerned at the declining profitability of the group's operations and of the steel industry generally, the third respondent convened a meeting of several steel merchants at which both he and the manager of the subsidiary company were present. at that meeting discussion took place on the desirability of reducing the current level of discounts being offered in the industry so as to improve profit margins. the third respondent urged that some agreement be reached on discounts because it was impossible to continue operating at current prices. the manager of the second respondent announced that his company's next price list would involve a significant reduction in discounts. the trade practices commission sought orders under s. 76(1)(b) and (d) of the trade practices act 1974 that the respondents pay pecuniary penalties provided by the subsection. it alleged that the first respondent, by reason of the actions of its regional manager and the manager of the second respondent, had attempted to contravene or had attempted to induce others to contravene s. 45 (2)(a) of the act, and alleging that the second respondent, by reason of the actions of same two persons, had also made similar attempts. orders were also sought against the third respondent alleging that his actions constituted an attempt by him to induce the second respondent (the subsidiary company) to contravene s. 45(2)(a). the commission in reliance upon s. 84(2) claimed that the conduct of the third respondent and the manager of the second respondent was conduct for which the two companies should be held liable. the respondents argued, inter alia, that there was no expectation that other steel merchants would follow suit in reducing discounts, and that an expectation of achieving the intended purpose is an essential element of an attempt to contravene s. 45(2)(a).  held: (1) in an application under s. 76(1) alleging an attempted contravention of s. 45 , it is necessary to show that the person involved had the relevant intention, that is, that he acted with the purpose of bringing about a result</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.18" type=cited from="[1983] FCA 93">in this case an arrangement or understanding that had the purpose or would have or be likely to have the effect of substantially lessening competition. however, it is not necessary that there be an expectation in the mind of the person that his object will be achieved.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether conduct constituted industrial action in contravention of s 494 of the workplace relations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether conduct of union delegates and officials can be taken to be conduct of union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether authorisation or agreement of the employer under s 420(1)(e) can be given after conduct has occurred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether applicant made false or misleading statements contravening s 401.  torts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether tort of interference with trade or business a part of common law of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">whether tort of inducing breach of contract made out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">vicarious liability of employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">nuisance.  contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">"four hour rule"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">contractual obligations of the employee under contract of employment where the employer cannot discharge its contractual obligation to pay the employee for at least four hours by operation of s 507 of the workplace relations act .  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">secondary boycott</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.12" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">meaning of conduct "in concert"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.13" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">"dominant purpose" practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.14" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">role of the court where "gap" exists in legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.15" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 470">scope of the power to make an order for compensation to remedy the effects of industrial action.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">unlawful industrial action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">breaches of workplace relations act 1996 (cth) and building and construction industry improvement act 2005 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">related unions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 267">totality principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">notice of motion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">application to vary and set aside judgment and orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">whether any misapprehension of the facts   industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 224">whether failure to withdraw notice of motion was an unreasonable omission</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 470">The predecessor to s 4(5) was s 4(8) of the pre-Work Choices WR Act , which was identical in its terms. In Alfred v Wakelin (No. 2) [2008] FCA 1543 ; (2008) 176 IR 430 at [80] Jagot J said: 
 ... Section 4(8) is an aid to interpretation. This section operates so that where the words "engaging in conduct" (or their equivalent) appear elsewhere in the Act the meaning to be given to those words is extended to include being directly or indirectly a party to or concerned in the conduct. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 267">On 17 October 2008 I made the following declarations ( Alfred v Wakelin (No 2) [2008] FCA 1543): Declares that each of the fifth, sixth and seventh respondents, by reason of the stoppages of work at the Lake Cowal gold mine between 6.30 am on 15 October 2005 and 6.30 am on 18 October 2005 and between 11.00 am on 10 November 2005 and 6.30 am on 11 November 2005, contravened s 38 of the Building and Construction Industry Improvement Act 2005 (Cth). 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 224">By notice of motion filed on 18 February 2009 the sixth and seventh respondents (the national body and New South Wales branch of the Australian Workers' Union, referred to below as the AWU) seek orders varying and, in part, setting aside the orders I made on 17 October 2008 and the reasons for decision published on the same date ( Alfred v Wakelin (No 2) [2008] FCA 1543). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY IMPROVEMENT ACT 2005 </title>
<title id="l1">BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY IMPROVEMENT ACT 2005 - SECT 38 Unlawful industrial action prohibited</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>