<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Oobi Baby Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1488 (7 October 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1488.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">cartel conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">visy companies and amcor companies held 90 per cent of the corrugated fibreboard packaging market in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">between january 2000 and october 2004 visy and amcor engaged in price-fixing and market sharing contrary to s 45 of trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">amcor received conditional immunity from action by the australian competition and consumer commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">commission brought action against visy companies and three of its senior officers four categories of contraventions: over-arching understanding in 2000 to maintain market share and increase prices; annual price increase understandings each year for 2000 to 2003, customer price understandings and compensation understandings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">respondents admitted liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1617">parties submitted an agreed statement of facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">civil penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">contravention of s 10 of the petroleum retail marketing sites act 1980 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">parties present joint submissions on the appropriate pecuniary penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">direction under federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) asking whether the court must consider whether the proposed amount is within the permissible range and, if so, impose the "agreed" penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 72">powers and responsibilities of court faced with joint submission on penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">[ database search ] [ name search ] [ recent decisions ] [ noteup ] [ lawcite ] [ help ] n w frozen foods proprietary ltd v australian competition &amp; consumer commission [1996] fca 1134 (20 december 1996)    trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">penalties under s.76 for contraventions of part iv</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">price fixing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">effect of agreement between a.c.c.c. and corporation on joint submissions proposing particular orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">desirability of settlement of such cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">penalty cases not criminal prosecutions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">matters relevant to penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">object of ensuring compliance with the act by deterrence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">effect of undertaking by corporation of a compliance programme agreed with the commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">difficulties in comparing penalties in other cases with that proposed for the instant case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">importance of the particular market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">significance of identity of corporation to be penalised where it was a member of a group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">significance of whether a corporation has previously contravened</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">inappropriateness of diminishing the credit to be given a corporation for co-operation and admission of liability by reference to any costs saving it may achieve thereby</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.14" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">reference to u.s. law conceding the u.s. federal trade commission "a special competence in formulating remedies"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.15" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1134">discussion of the question for the court where penalty is the subject of an agreed joint submission.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 153">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 153">alleged price fixing arrangements made at overseas meetings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 153">accc and certain respondents jointly seek proposed declarations, injunctions and penalties on basis of agreed facts and admissions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 153">whether appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">alleged price fixing arrangements made at overseas meetings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">accc and certain respondents jointly seek proposed declarations, injunctions and penalties on basis of agreed facts and admissions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">whether jointly proposed penalties appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">no evidence of profits from contraventions, effect on market or loss caused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">whether making of declarations should be deferred until after proceedings against continuing respondents completed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 17">proposed declarations do not mention continuing respondents directly or by necessary implication</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">therapeutic goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">civil penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">relevant matters to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">agreement as to facts and penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">need to ensure a penalty is " appropriate "</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">scrutiny given to agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">forfeiture</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1545">declaratory relief</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 153">The Court is empowered to make an order for a gross sum order for costs under O 62 r 4(2)(c) of the Federal Court Rules . Similar orders have been made in other proceedings commenced by the ACCC and resolved by consent ( ACCC v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1976 ; ACCC v British Airways plc [2008] FCA 1977 ; ACCC v Oobi Baby Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1488 ; April (No 5 )). The Parties submit that it is appropriate for an order that APP Singapore and Indah Kiat pay the amount of $300,000 in respect of the ACCC's costs of and incidental to this proceeding as against them. I am of the view that this is a very reasonable sum taking account of the history of these proceedings. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 17">The Court is empowered to make an order for a gross sum order for costs under O 62 r 4(2)(c) of the Federal Court Rules . Similar orders have been made in other proceedings commenced by the Commission and resolved by consent ( Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Qantas Airways Ltd [2008] FCA 1976 ; (2008) 253 ALR 89 ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v British Airways plc [2008] FCA 1977 ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Oobi Baby Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1488). The Parties submit it is appropriate for an order to be made that AIMS Australia and AFPT Singapore pay the amount of $250,000 in respect of the Commission's costs of and incidental to this proceeding as against the April respondents. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 263">Section 76 relevantly provides as follows:
 
 (1) If the Court is satisfied that a person: 
 (a) has contravened any of the following provisions: 
 (i) a provision of Part IV ...; [or] 
 ... 
 (b) has attempted to contravene such a provision; 
 ... 
 the Court may order the person to pay to the Commonwealth such pecuniary penalty, in respect of each act or omission by the person to which this section applies, as the Court determines to be appropriate having regard to all relevant matters including the nature and extent of the act or omission and of any loss or damage suffered as a result of the act or omission, the circumstances in which the act or omission took place and whether the person has previously been found by the Court in proceedings under this Part or Part XIB to have engaged in any similar conduct. 

 
 (1A) The pecuniary penalty payable under subsection (1) by a body corporate is not to exceed ... for each [relevant] act or omission ...---$10,000,000. 

 The principles regarding the imposition of pecuniary penalties, including penalties jointly proposed by the parties, were recently considered by Lindgren J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Qantas Airways Ltd [[2008] FCA 1976 at [16]- [27] ] and Finkelstein J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Oobi Baby Pty Ltd [[2008] FCA 1488 at [9]]. Finkelstein J summarises the position as follows: 
 
 So far as the penalties were concerned many cases have examined the Court's task in considering a joint position on penalties. The applicable principles are authoritatively dealt with in NW Frozen Foods Pty Ltd v Australian Competition and Consumer Commission [ [1996] FCA 1134 ; (1996) 71 FCR 285 ] and Minister for Industry, Tourism &amp; Resources v Mobil Oil Australia Pty Ltd .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 1545">See: Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Admiral Mechanical Services Pty Ltd [2007] FCA 1085 at [13] ---[18] per Nicholson J. Most recently, it has been said that the " upshot of the authorities is that the Court should not depart lightly from a joint position put forward by the parties. The inquiry to be undertaken is not whether the Court would have arrived at the same figure as the parties, but whether the proposal fixes an appropriate amount 'within the permissible range' of penalties that might properly be imposed ": Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Oobi Baby Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 1488 at [9] per Finkelstein J. See also: Beaton-Wells C, 'Judicial Scrutiny of Penalty Agreements to Increase' (2005) 13 TPLJ 59. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>