<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Lindholm, in the matter of Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited (Administrators appointed) (Receivers and Managers appointed) [2008] FCA 1425 (17 September 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1425.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">securities lending agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">contract to lend shares</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">ownership of shares</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether securities lending agreement constitutes secured loan or purchase-and-sale</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether reference may be had to economic effect of transaction in determining legal character</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether contract is to be construed with reference to its purpose, background, context, and market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether same contract may be construed differently if entered into in different market or by different participants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">implied term</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether it is reasonable and equitable to imply a term requiring shares acquired to be held and retained    corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether administrator or receiver is analogous to liquidator   equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">claim for equitable interest in shares transferred on documents purporting to give full title to broker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether equity of redemption can exist after outright transfer of title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 594">whether equitable charge over undefined shares may exist absent appropriation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">deed of company arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">compromise scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">proof of debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">contingent creditor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">no breach as at commencement of administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1155">proof admissible</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 102">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 102">proof of debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 102">correct procedure for conversion of foreign debt claims into australian currency.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">arbitration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">foreign awards and agreements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">stay available to party to agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">"party" includes "person claiming through party"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">liquidator</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">whether claim through company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1990] HCA 8">arbitration (foreign awards and agreements) act 1974 (cth), s. 7(2) , (4).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">schemes of arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">acquisition of shares and cancellation of rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">application for meeting under s 411(1) corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">factors to consider at meeting stage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">independent expert's opinion of the schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">performance risk</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">exclusivity period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">no-talk and no shop</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">deemed warranty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">information for shareholders and rightsholders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 4">sections 411 and 412 corporations act 2001 (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">arrangements and reconstruction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">scheme for acquisition of stapled securities consisting of shares in a company and units of two managed investment schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">acquisition to be achieved by part 5.1 scheme and amendment of constitutions of managed investment schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">consideration consisting of partnership interests in bermuda limited partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">certain foreign holders to receive wholly cash consideration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">other holders may elect to receive cash instead of partnership interests but limited to 4,000 such interests</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">whether these provisions are class-creating</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">whether s 411(17) implications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">schemes of arrangement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">orders convening meeting</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">role of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">exclusivity clauses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 367">corporations act 2001 (cth) s 411.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 231">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 231">proposed demerger</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 231">application for convening of a meeting of shareholders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 231">function of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] VSC 231">s 411 of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] VSC 4">
 
 14 The effect of the authorities in relation to the function of the Court in relation to applications such as this was summarised by Davies J in Re Orica Limited: [16] 
 
 
 "7. The function of the Court on an application to convene a meeting essentially is: 
 (a) to consider whether the scheme booklet that will be provided to the shareholders sufficiently discloses the detail and effect of the scheme to enable shareholders to make an informed decision on how to vote; 
 (b) to consider procedural matters about the calling and conduct of the meeting; 
 (c) to ascertain whether the Australian Securities and Investments Commission ('ASIC') has had reasonable opportunity to examine the proposed scheme; 
 (d) to consider whether there may be matters that may make it unlikely that the scheme would be capable of a grant of approval by the Court if, in due course, its approval is sought and so make it futile to put the scheme to the shareholders for their vote. [17] 
 8. It is not the function of the Court on an application for a order convening a meeting to consider the business or commercial efficacy of the proposed scheme, as that is a matter for the shareholders nor is it the Court's role to express a view on whether the proposed scheme should be approved, if the requisite majority of votes is obtained. [18] An order of the Court that the meeting be convened is not an indication that the Court has a view as to the merits of the scheme or as to how shareholders should vote. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] NSWSC 1104">13 I pause, at this point, to note the function of the court at this stage of a Part 5.1 matter, that is, the stage at which the proponent of a scheme of arrangement between a company and its members (or a class of them) asks the court to make orders under s 411(1) with respect to the convening of a meeting or meetings. By analogy, the function with respect to judicial advice in a matter of the present kind is the same. A recent statement of the relevant principle may be found in the judgment of Davies J in Re Orica Ltd [2010] VSC 231. Her Honour said at [7] and [8}:
 

 
 
 "[7] The function of the Court on an application to convene a meeting essentially is: 
 (a) to consider whether the scheme booklet that will be provided to the shareholders sufficiently discloses the detail and effect of the scheme to enable shareholders to make an informed decision on how to vote; 
 (b) to consider procedural matters about the calling and conduct of the meeting; 
 (c) to ascertain whether the Australian Securities and Investments Commission ('ASIC') has had reasonable opportunity to examine the proposed scheme; 
 (d) to consider whether there may be matters that may make it unlikely that the scheme would be capable of a grant of approval by the Court if, in due course, its approval is sought and so make it futile to put the scheme to the shareholders for their vote: FT Eastman and Sons Pty Ltd v Metal Roof Decking Supplies Pty Ltd (1977) 3 ACLR 69 , 72 (Street CJ); Australian Securities Commission v Malborough Gold Mines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485 ; Lindholm, Re Opes Prime Stockbrocking Limited (Administrators appointed)(Receivers and Managers Appointed) [2008] FCA 1425 ; (2008) 171 FCR 473 ; Re CSR Limited [2010] FCAFC 34 ; Re Foundation Health Care Limited [2002] FCA 742 ; (2002) 42 ACSR 252. [8] It is not the function of the Court on an application for a order convening a meeting to consider the business or commercial efficacy of the proposed scheme, as that is a matter for the shareholders nor is it the Court's role to express a view on whether the proposed scheme should be approved, if the requisite majority of votes is obtained: Re Sonodyne International Limited (1994) 15 ACSR 494 , 497. An order of the Court that the meeting be convened is not an indication that the Court has a view as to the merits of the scheme or as to how shareholders should vote. " </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] VSC 367">Essentially the Court is concerned with whether the procedural and substantive requirements for the calling and conduct of a meeting will be met. The Court will consider: 
 (a) whether the scheme booklet that will be provided to the shareholders sufficiently discloses the detail and effect of the scheme and other matters that are material for shareholders to know about to be able to make an informed decision on how to vote; 
(b) whether the contemplated procedure complies with the procedural requirements for the calling and the conduct of the meeting; and 
(c) whether the Australian Securities and Investment Commission ("ASIC") has been given proper notice of the application and had reasonable opportunity to examine the proposed scheme. [3] 
9 It is not the function of the Court on an application for an order convening a meeting to consider the business or commercial efficacy of the proposed scheme. That is a matter for the shareholders. Nor is it the Court's role at this stage of the process to express a view on whether the scheme should be approved by the Court, if the requisite majority of votes is obtained.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] VSC 231">7 The function of the Court on an application to convene a meeting essentially is: 
(a) to consider whether the scheme booklet that will be provided to the shareholders sufficiently discloses the detail and effect of the scheme to enable shareholders to make an informed decision on how to vote; 
(b) to consider procedural matters about the calling and conduct of the meeting; 
(c) to ascertain whether the Australian Securities and Investments Commission ("ASIC") has had reasonable opportunity to examine the proposed scheme; 
(d) to consider whether there may be matters that may make it unlikely that the scheme would be capable of a grant of approval by the Court if, in due course, its approval is sought and so make it futile to put the scheme to the shareholders for their vote. [1] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] SASC 342">Held: The ordinary meaning of "administrator" appearing in cl 7.4 is wide enough to include a liquidator --- by appointing a liquidator, the defendant threatened to cease business, which is a default event --- the defendant's negotiations with the third party and the entry into the Sale and Purchase Deed on 30 September 2009 were not a disposal of the shares and not default events for the purposes of cl 7.4(e) --- the plaintiff complied with the pre-requisites for the valid exercise of the option to purchase the shares at $1 per share --- the defendant's notice of sale was served after the plaintiff exercised its default option and is therefore ineffective. Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) s 439C(a) , s 477(1)(a) , s 506 , referred to. Lindholm, in the matter of Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited [2008] FCA 1425 ; Meridian Global Funds Management Asia Ltd v Securities Commission [1995] UKPC 5 ; [1995] 2 AC 500 ; Duke Group Ltd (in liq) v Pilmer [1999] SASC 97 ; (1999) 73 SASR 64 ; J &amp; H Manktelow Pty Ltd v Alloway Grazing Pty Ltd [1975] 1 NSWLR 385 ; Moorgate Mercantile Co Ltd v Twitehings [1977] AC 890 ; The Lutetian [1982] 2 Lloyds Rep 140 ; Demagogue Pty Ltd v Ramensky [1992] FCA 557 ; (1992) 39 FCR 31 ; GPT Re Ltd v Lend Lease Real Estate Investments Ltd [2005] NSWSC 964 ; Beneficial Finance Corporation Ltd v Multiplex Constructions Pty Ltd [1995] 36 NSWLR 510 ; Ballas v Theophilos [No 2] [1957] HCA 90 ; (1957) 98 CLR 193 ; Permanent Trustee Australia Ltd v Woolworths (Qld) Ltd; in the matter of an application by Woolworths (Q'Land) Pty Ltd BC9805880; THL Robina Pty Ltd v The Glades Golf Club Pty Ltd [2004] QSC 461 ; Sims Metal Ltd v Wanless Metal Industries Pty Ltd BC9700743; Laybutt v Amoco Australia Pty Limited [1974] HCA 49 ; (1974) 132 CLR 57 , considered. ITC LIMITED v TIMBERCORP LIMITED (IN LIQUIDATION) 
 [2009] SASC 342 
 
 
 CIVIL 
 
 
 KOURAKIS J The plaintiff (ITC) undertakes forestry operations in the Albany region of Western Australia for the purposes of producing and exporting woodchips. Until recently the defendant (Timbercorp) held and managed extensive agri-business operations throughout Australia including forestry and other horticulture. In Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited (Administrators Appointed) [7] Finklestein J observed: 
 
 In my view, whether the issue of 'analogy' is approached from the perspective of the nature of the appointee or from the principal consequence of the appointment, the result must be the same: a liquidator is not analogous to either an administrator or a receiver appointed by a secured creditor. The function of a liquidator --- whether called a liquidator, a trustee, a receiver, a curator or a syndic --- is to preside over the death of a company. An administrator appointed in rescue proceedings strives for the opposite result (even though the company may yet in the end die). A receiver appointed by a secured creditor does neither of those things, being largely unconcerned about the fate of the company. From any perspective, the offices are poles apart. [8] 
 
  In Opes Prime Stockbroking Limited (Administrators Appointed) [7] Finklestein J observed: 
 
 In my view, whether the issue of 'analogy' is approached from the perspective of the nature of the appointee or from the principal consequence of the appointment, the result must be the same: a liquidator is not analogous to either an administrator or a receiver appointed by a secured creditor. The function of a liquidator --- whether called a liquidator, a trustee, a receiver, a curator or a syndic --- is to preside over the death of a company. An administrator appointed in rescue proceedings strives for the opposite result (even though the company may yet in the end die). A receiver appointed by a secured creditor does neither of those things, being largely unconcerned about the fate of the company. From any perspective, the offices are poles apart. [8] 
 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 435A Object of Part</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 436A Company may appoint administrator if board thinks it is or will become insolvent</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 436B Liquidator may appoint administrator</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 436C Chargee may appoint administrator</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 437A Role of administrator</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 437D Only administrator can deal with company's property</title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 439A Administrator to convene meeting and inform creditors</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 440C Owner or lessor cannot recover property used by company</title>
<title id="l9">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 440D Stay of proceedings</title>
<title id="l10">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 440F Suspension of enforcement process</title>
<title id="l11">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 444A Effect of creditors' resolution</title>
<title id="l12">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 444D Effect of deed on creditors</title>
<title id="l13">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 447D Administrator may seek directions</title>
<title id="l14">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 468 Avoidance of dispositions of property, attachments etc.</title>
<title id="l15">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 513A Winding up ordered by the Court</title>
<title id="l16">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 513C Section 513C day in relation to an administration under Part 5.3A</title>
<title id="l17">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 554 General rule--compute amount as at relevant date</title>
<title id="l18">PAYMENT SYSTEMS AND NETTING ACT 1998 </title>
<title id="l19">PAYMENT SYSTEMS AND NETTING ACT 1998 - SECT 5 Definitions</title>
<title id="l20">PAYMENT SYSTEMS AND NETTING ACT 1998 - SECT 14 Effectiveness of close-out netting contracts</title>
<title id="l21">PAYMENT SYSTEMS AND NETTING ACT 1998 - SECT 15 Declaration that section 14 does not apply</title>
<title id="l22">CORPORATIONS REGULATIONS 2001 </title>
<title id="l23">CORPORATIONS REGULATIONS 2001 - REG 5.6.23 Creditors who may vote</title>
</legistitles>
</case>