<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>E. &amp; J. Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Limited (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005 (27 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/1005.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">substantial identity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">deceptive similarity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">goods of the same description</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">non-use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">obstacle to use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">discretion not to remove trade mark even though non-use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">use " in good faith "</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">no special facts or circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 934">evidence of internet search</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">application for summary judgment made under s 31a of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">whether defences had no reasonable prospects of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">defences to allegation of trade mark infringement could not succeed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">defences to allegations of copyright infringement, passing off, and contraventions of the fair trading act 1999 (vic) and the trade practices act 1974 (cth) raised questions of fact to be determined at trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">application successful in part.    intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">whether marks appearing on the respondents' products were deceptively similar to the applicant's trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 256">whether cancellation of registered trade mark under s 88 of the trade marks act 1955 (cth) could operate retrospectively.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">whether the registered trade mark should be removed from the register for non-use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">meaning of "used...in the course of trade...by a person"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">whether there was an intention to use or authorisation to use the trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">whether the actual use of the mark was likely to deceive or cause confusion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">prospective operation of an order to remove a trade mark from the register</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">deceptive similarity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">goods of the same description  trade marks act 1995 (cth), ss 6 , 7 , 8 , 10 , 13 , 17 , 92 , 100 , 101 , 120 , 123 , 127  trade marks act 1955</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 27">1958 (cth), s23(1)(b)   blackadder v good roads machinery company inc [1926] hca 57 ; (1926) 38 clr 332 applied ; carnival cruise lines inc v sitmar cruises limited [1994] fca 936 ; (1994) 120 alr 495 applied ; estex clothing manufacturers pty limited v ellis and goldstein limited (1967) 116 clr 254 followed ; mid sydney pty ltd v australian tourism co ltd (1998) 90 fcr 236 referred to ; jackson &amp; co v napper (1886) 35 ch d 162 cited ; polo textile industries pty ltd v domestic textile corporation pty ltd [1993] fca 203 ; (1993) 42 fcr 227 followed ; re the registered trade mark "yanx" [1951] hca 28 ; (1951) 82 clr 199 applied ; riv-oland marble co (vic) pty ltd v settef spa (1988) 19 fcr 569 discussed ; settef spa v riv-oland marble co (vic) pty ltd (1987) 10 ipr 402 followed ; southern cross refrigerating co v toowoomba foundry pty ltd (1954) 91 clr 592 followed ; s &amp; i publishing pty ltd v australian life saver pty ltd [1999] fca 316 ; (1998) 88 fcr 354 referred to ; transport tyre sales pty ltd v montana tyres rims and tubes pty ltd [1999] fca 329 ; (1999) 93 fcr 421 followed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">applications for removal of respondent's trade marks from register in respect of certain goods and services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">applications made on both grounds in s 92(4) of the trade marks act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">whether applicant a person aggrieved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">respondent made general allegation of trade mark infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">applicant was a person aggrieved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">whether applications complied with trade marks regulations 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">supporting statutory declaration did not make reference to intention to use the trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">applications did not comply with the regulations for the purposes of the ground in s 92(4)(a) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">respondent has shown use of the trade marks on some computer peripheral devices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">separate description of goods for which use established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">convergence between computer related goods and consumer electronic products</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">brand extension</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">discretion in s 101(3) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">discretion exercised to maintain trade mark registrations in their current form with respect to the removal goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">no use of the trade marks in respect of the removal services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">no suggestion of convergence of services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 135">trade marks removed from the register in respect of the removal services</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 256">Such considerations influenced the decision of Flick J in E. &amp; J. Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Limited (No 2) (2008) 78 IPR 334 ; [2008] FCA 1005. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCAFC 27">The primary judge published reasons on 20 June 2008 ( E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Australia Pty Limited [2008] FCA 934) which first addressed the question of infringement and secondly addressed the use of the registered mark by the registered owner in the context of determining whether the mark should be removed from the Register. Further reasons were published on 27 June 2008 ( E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Australia Pty Limited (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005) which concerned the day on which the removal from the Register should take effect. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 135">The exercise of the discretionary power to remove a mark under s 101(2) of the Act is as at the date upon which the Court makes the order for removal ( E &amp; J Gallo Winery v Lion Nathan Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1005 ; (2008) 78 IPR 334 at [4] per Flick J). This is a hearing de novo and the parties have adduced evidence in this hearing directed to the exercise of discretion. As it happens, the date for consideration of the evidence is not determinative of the outcome. The evidence relied upon by Pioneer KK is of confusion during the relevant period, of convergence of computer and audio-visual technologies and of brand extension by other companies operating in the computer and audio-visual fields that was evident in that period and predicted at that time to continue. The evidence with respect to post-relevant period convergence and potential for confusion has simply validated that prediction. The facts relevant to the exercise of the discretion
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 79 Renewal within 6 months after registration expires</title>
<title id="l2">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 98 Trade mark restored to Register if notice of opposition filed within extended time</title>
<title id="l3">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 101 Determination of opposed application--general</title>
<title id="l4">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 127 Special case--plaintiff not entitled to damages etc.</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>