<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZGWN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 238 (24 July 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/238.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">test to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">leave to raise a new ground of appeal refused migration law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">s 425(1) does not confer upon an applicant a unilateral right to secure an adjournment of proceedings so that particular evidence can be presented</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 149">s 425(1) complied with as long as applicant is given a meaningful opportunity to give evidence and present arguments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 328">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 328">application for protection visa by chinese nationals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 328">jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 328">the decision of the refugee review tribunal affected by apprehended bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 328">also lack of satisfaction reached by the refugee review tribunal not lawful, but arbitrary and capricious.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">applicant naff of 2002 v minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">non-compliance with statutory duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">tribunal concerned by inconsistencies in applicant's evidence at oral hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">tribunal said it would give the applicant a chance to respond in writing to its concerns</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">whether tribunal's failure to do so involved a failure to complete the review process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">whether failure involved a breach of the duty to conduct a review under s 414(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">whether failure involved a breach of the duty to hear from the applicant under s 425(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 62">whether reviewable error where absence of evidence from the applicant about effect of failure.  migration act 1958 (cth), ss 56 , 414 (1), 415 (1), 425 (1), 427 (1)(b), 420 , pt 7 divs 2-7a.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">rules of the supreme court 1971 (wa) , o 56 r 3administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">prerogative writs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">application for a writ of certiorari</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">whether minister of local government acted lawfully in suspending local council</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">whether the minister for local government is required to afford procedural fairness to the applicant councillors before suspension under part 8 of the local government act 1995 (wa) administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">prerogative writs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">application for a writ of prohibition to prohibit inquiry panel established by minister of local government, pursuant to s 8.20 of local government act 1995 (wa) , from proceeding to hear inquiry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">whether conduct of members of inquiry panel gave rise to a reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=cited from="[2001] WASC 276">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">re minister for immigration and multicultural affairs; ex parte epeabaka  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">affirmation by refugee review tribunal of decision to refuse application for protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">public statements made by tribunal member on personal internet home page about truthfulness of applicants for refugee status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">whether pt 7 of migration act 1958 (cth) constitutes a code excluding the common law rules of natural justice and in particular the ostensible bias rule.  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.8" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">reasonable apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.9" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">whether a reasonable party or member of the public might apprehend that decision of tribunal member was affected by a prejudiced mind</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.10" type=cited from="[2001] HCA 23">whether ostensible bias may be inferred from statements made after a decision.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">accused primitive native unable to speak english</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">confession made by accused in native dialect to native interpreter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">instantaneous translation into english by interpreter to patrol officer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">patrol officer without knowledge of native dialect</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">evidence from interpreter at trial that translation full and correct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">evidence by patrol officer of interrogation and confession translated into english</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">objection that evidence inadmissible as hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.9" type=cited from="[1960] HCA 70">admissibility.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">whether inadequate interpretation by translator</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">whether applicant effectively prevented from giving evidence because of inadequate interpretation of key witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">whether presence of legal representation before the tribunal cured inadequate interpretation by providing opportunity to be heard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">breach of s 39 administrative appeals tribunal act 1975</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 992">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">review of migration review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">refusal of partner visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">adverse credibility findings by the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">disclosure of adverse information by the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">whether the tribunal breached s.359a of the migration act 1958 (cth) considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">interpretation errors at the tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">whether the tribunal breached s.360 of the migration act considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 7">whether further hearing required to deal with adverse information emerging after the hearing considered.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">protection (class xa) visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">application for review of rrt decision affirming a decision of a delegate of the minister refusing to grant the applicants a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">applicants are citizen of the people's republic of china claiming fear of persecution for reasons of their religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">allegation of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.7" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">apprehension of bias</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.8" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">interpreter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.9" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">whether applicants were deprived of procedural fairness due to errors on the part of the interpreter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.10" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">credibility issues.  practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.11" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1649">where proceeding reopened to allow further submissions.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">grounds of appeal drafted by migration agent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">no instructions by appellant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">alleged bias on part of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">argument not raised before federal magistrates court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">allegation that decision of federal magistrate neither " fair " nor " reasonable "</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">provision of proper interpreter services</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp18.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1898">appeal dismissed  attorney-general for the state of new south wales v quin (1990) 170 clr 1 applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">whether breach of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">applicant unwell</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">applicant failed to attend tribunal hearing due to illness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">tribunal gave opportunity to provide explanation and further information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">tribunal made aware of reason for non-attendance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">tribunal refused to reschedule hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">tribunal then proceeded to make its decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">no jurisdictional error. evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">federal magistrate accepted evidence of illness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">no medical evidence lead</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">cross-examination of witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp19.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 1789">medical opinion not required.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 992">In my view, the evidence of Ms Yu-Lin was effectively precluded from being properly presented because of the inadequacy of the translator. I am satisfied that the interpretation was so inadequate that it prevented the applicant from putting before the Tribunal the evidence she desired to rely upon, and that the evidence was significant to the applicant's case: see, eg Tobasi v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2002] FCA 1050 ; (2002) 122 FCR 322 ; Perera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 507 ; [1999] FCA 507 ; (1999) 92 FCR 6 ; and SZGWN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 238 per Gilmour J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 200">I do not propose to adjourn the appeal to permit evidence and argument on the second issue. The issue of interpretation generally was canvassed at some length by the learned Federal Magistrate. Detailed consideration was given to the question of quality of translation. It has been accepted that some errors in translation occur in practically all circumstances partly because of the difficulty of finding direct correlations for expressions used in the respective languages. It is equally clear that if the translation errors are of significant dimension going to the heart of the issues, there will not have been a fair hearing. See for example: SZGWN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 238. Unlike SZGWN , the specific translation difficulties said to have occurred in this case have not been raised on the notice of appeal, have not been supported by any evidence, have not been identified with the slightest precision and have not been said to occur in an area of the case which was critical to its disposition. I will therefore not allow an adjournment of the appeal. ANALYSIS 
 Grounds 1 and 2 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 7">The Tribunal was put on notice of this alleged inadequacy in the course of the hearing. The statutory obligation under s.360 to "invite" the applicants to appear before it to give evidence and present arguments lay with the Tribunal. It is a continuing obligation: Applicant NAAF of 2002 v Minister for Immigration [2004] HCA 62 ; (2004) 221 CLR 1 at [26]- [27]. The applicant contends that, being on notice of the potential errors in the interpretation the Tribunal should have extended an invitation to the applicant to attend a further hearing so that she could give evidence, with better interpretation. The failure by the applicant to ask for a further hearing did not affect that obligation if it existed. See SZGWN v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 238 at [47] .  Despite being on notice of the potential errors in the interpretation it extended no such invitation to the appellant to attend a further hearing so that he could give evidence, with adequate interpretation. The failure by the appellant to ask for a further hearing did not affect that obligation. See SZGWN v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2008] FCA 238 at [47] . In this case the question is whether the standard of interpretation by the interpreter was such that the applicants and their witnesses were prevented from giving their evidence effectively or at all. The applicants note the observations of Ryan J (with whom Tamberlin and Middleton JJ agreed) in WALN v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2006] FCAFC 131 at [29] : To succeed on this ground the appellant must establish that he was effectively prevented from giving his evidence; see Perera (above) at [38]---[41]. In fact, a reading of the whole of the transcript reveals that the standard of interpretation was good, and consistently good throughout the hearing. It would be surprising if a hearing lasting that long did not result in some instances of confusion, instances where questions and answers needed to be clarified, and the odd occasion where a question or answer was misinterpreted. However, this in no way comes close to a situation where the standard of interpretation would draw the Court to the conclusion that "here the standard of interpretation at the Tribunal hearing was so inadequate that the appellant was effectively prevented from giving evidence at the Tribunal" for the purposes of s 360 of the Act: see Appellant P119 at [17]; Singh v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1376 ; (2001) 115 FCR 1 at 6 [27] ; Perera v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [1999] FCA 507 ; (1999) 92 FCR 6 at [38] - [41]; SZGWN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 238. 
 The 'second limb' 
 
 The second limb identified in Appellant P119 of 2002 is not conceded by the Minister to amount to a separate stand alone 'limb' or species of jurisdictional error in connection with alleged faulty or bad interpretation at a Tribunal hearing. That limb --- if it can be so described - requires demonstration of demonstration of a "material error" of fact resulting in a conclusion that "the decision-making process had occurred": see Soltanyzand v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1168 at [18] .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FMCA 1649">It is submitted that the applicants by forwarding in writing a transcript together with their complaints about the failure of interpreting and the actions of the Tribunal in sorting through errors of admissions was an appropriate response by the Tribunal. I was referred to the comments of Kenny J in Perera v Minister for Immigration &amp; Multicultural Affairs [11] . Counsel for the Minister submitted that if interpretation errors are made, then they are able to be rectified. It is submitted that it was open to the Tribunal to take that approach. I was also referred to a decision of my own in SZGWN &amp; Anor v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [12] . However, that decision was subsequently reversed on appeal ( SZGWN and SZGWO v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [13] ) and, for that reason, I made the decision to reopen the matter and hear further submissions.  Counsel for the Minister submitted that there is nothing in SZGWN [28] that alters the well established principles in relation to s 425 and translation errors, nor is there anything that alters the principles in relation to apprehended bias. She also put that the applicants' further submission did not add in any substantial way to the case that had already been argued at the previous hearing. The details of interpreting errors were not developed in any way to take matters further. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 1898">11 Even if an argument as to bias had not been raised before the Federal Magistrate, leave to now raise such an argument on appeal would have been refused: cf SZGWN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 238 at [120] , [2008] FCA 238 ; 103 ALD 144 at 174 per Gilmour J. Leave may be granted where it is expedient in the interests of justice to do so. But it is well accepted that a " reasonable apprehension " of bias must be " firmly established ": Re JRL, Ex parte CJL [1986] HCA 39 ; (1986) 161 CLR 342 at 352 per Mason J. The circumstances more relevant to an application in respect to proceedings before the Refugee Review Tribunal, where proceedings are heard in private, has been addressed by Gleeson CJ, Gaudron and Gummow JJ as follows in Re Refugee Review Tribunal, Ex parte H [2001] HCA 28 , 179 ALR 425: 
 [27] The test for apprehended bias in relation to curial proceedings is whether a fair-minded lay observer might reasonably apprehend that the judge might not bring an impartial mind to the resolution of the question to be decided. That formulation owes much to the fact that court proceedings are held in public. There is some incongruity in formulating a test in terms of "a fair-minded lay observer" when, as is the case with the tribunal, proceedings are held in private. [28] Perhaps it would be better, in the case of administrative proceedings held in private, to formulate the test for apprehended bias by reference to a hypothetical fair-minded lay person who is properly informed as to the nature of the proceedings, the matters in issue and the conduct which is said to give rise to an apprehension of bias. Whether or not that be the appropriate formulation, there is, in our view, no reason to depart from the objective test of possibility, as distinct from probability, as to what will be done or what might have been done. To do otherwise, would be to risk confusion of apprehended bias with actual bias by requiring substantially the same proof. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] FCA 1789">23 I make the assumption as to the correctness of SCAR [2003] FCAFC 126 ; 128 FCR 553 even though SCAR has not met with universal approval: see, eg, Appellant P119/2002 v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCAFC 230 ; NALQ v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCAFC 121 ; Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs v SZFDE [2006] FCAFC 142 ; (2006) 154 FCR 365 ; SZJZY v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 280 ; SZGWN v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 238. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 11 Visa applicable to 2 or more persons</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 21 Failure to comply with section 18 notice</title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 91R Persecution</title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424 Tribunal may seek information</title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 425 Tribunal must invite applicant to appear</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>