<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission; in the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd ACN (099 071 968) v Carey (No 19) [2008] FCA 38 (31 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/38.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">protective orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">appointment of receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">freezing orders by way of alternative</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">extension of existing orders subject to replacement of receiver by freezing orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">orders unopposed and largely consented to</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1718">proposed orders within power and appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">securities industry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">investigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">asic commences investigation into apparently fraudulent investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">company involved is incorporated in new zealand</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">director of new zealand company served while in australia with a notice to produce documents under s.33 asic act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">director claims asic has no jurisdiction to compel production of documents by new zealand company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">asic obtains ex parte orders under s.1323(1) and (3) of corporations act requiring director to deliver up passport and not depart from australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">director claims court has no power under s.1323 to detain a person in australia for the purpose of assisting asic in its investigations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">principles discussed. held: it is within the purposes of protecting the interests of aggrieved persons, within the meaning and operation of s.1323(1), that a person be detained in australia to assist asic in its investigations into a possibly fraudulent scheme involving australian investors.acts cited: australian securities and investments commission act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">s.33 corporations act, 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2002] NSWSC 684">s.79 , s. 911a , s. 1041f , s. 1041g , s. 1041h , s. 1041i , s. 1323 (1), (3), s. 1324 (1), (4)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">corporations [324]</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">supervision, regulation and correction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">order prohibiting person from leaving australia without the consent of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 1180">whether consent ought be granted.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 20">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 20">corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 20">ss 1323(1)(j) &amp; (k)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 20">application for surrender of passports pending conduct of asic investigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 20">likelihood of defendants seeking to avoid future obligations as a result of investigation</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 20">It is, as others before me have remarked, a serious matter to interfere with a person's freedom of movement and such a step is not to be lightly undertaken; Australian Securities and Investments Commission; in the mater of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 19) [2008] FCA 38 ; (2008) 65 ACSR 421 at 427 per French J. However, it is also a serious matter for the aggrieved persons that they should not be deprived of any opportunity to be compensated in one way or another should the defendants be found to be culpable for their loss. It is, as French J has commented, a matter of risk assessment and management. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1423">8 French J has described the function to be performed under s 1323(1) as essentially one of risk assessment and management: see Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Carey (No. 3) [2006] FCA 433 ; (2006) 232 ALR 577 at 587 [26] and 588 [30]. It, therefore, involves balancing the interests, on the one hand, of the aggrieved persons referred to in s 1323(1) and, on the other hand, the interests of a respondent in avoiding undue interference in his or her affairs. Where, as here, it is sought to interfere with a person's freedom of movement, it is to be borne in mind that such a step is not lightly to be undertaken: see Australian Securities and Investments Commission; in the matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No. 19) [2008] FCA 38 ; (2008) 65 ACSR 421 at 427 at [32] per French J (and the authorities therein). 
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 19 Notice requiring appearance for examination</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1323 Power of Court to prohibit payment or transfer of money, financial products or other property</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 23 Making of orders and issue of writs</title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>