<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>McDonald's Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 37 (31 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/37.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">consideration of an application to strike out reliance by the commissioner of taxation upon s 468 of the corporations act 2001 (cth) in support of an amended assessment, on the ground that reliance by the commissioner upon the section would result in procedural unfairness in the conduct of an appeal from an objection decision of the commissioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">consideration of whether the commissioner is entitled to raise a new matter not relied upon in issuing an amended assessment or making a decision on the taxpayer's objection to the assessment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">consideration of the taxpayer's entitlement to raise and rely upon events occurring after the date of the commissioner's objection decision practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">consideration of an application for leave to amend grounds of objection to an amended assessment issued by the commissioner of taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1426">consideration of the adequacy of the commissioner's appeal statement for the purposes of order 52b, rule 5(2)(a)(iv)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1270">taxation and revenue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1270">consideration of whether a taxpayer engaging in a sequence of transactions by reason of which the taxpayer did not realise a capital gain upon disposal of a cgt asset nevertheless engaged in a sequence of transactions constituting a scheme to which part iva of the income tax assessment act 1936 (cth), applies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1270">consideration of the notions of 'scheme', 'obtaining a tax benefit', 'purpose', the application of an exclusion by reason of s 177c(2)(a) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1270">consideration of principles governing the determination of an amount of additional tax by way of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1270">consideration of ss 226 and 222c of the act as those provisions applied prior to the repeal of part vii of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 299">the two ministers and the commonwealth, by their present application to secure a "summary judgment", seek to have these proceedings stopped at this point as a matter of law, without the need to look at the evidence. they say that, even assuming that the allegations in mr hicks' claim are accepted, there is no reasonable prospect of success. part of the application by the ministers and the commonwealth for summary judgment is on the basis that this court cannot enter into a consideration of a case which may result in a finding that an action of a state other than australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 299">here, the united states</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 299">is unlawful. they say that there are no proper standards by which the court can resolve the issues raised by mr hicks because delicate questions of diplomatic negotiation between australia and the united states are involved and a finding by a court may impact on these relations.the question of mr hicks' internment is said to be "political" in nature and is one concerning foreign relations and these are areas into which the court should not intrude because the decision will involve standards which are "non-justiciable" and which a court cannot properly apply.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 34">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 34">power to issue amended assessments when appeals on objections against original assessments before the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 34">whether payments by a company are dividends paid out of profits and assessable income under ss 108/109c and 44 (1) of the income tax assessment act 1936 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 34">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 34">alternatively whether part iva applies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">application to strike out statement of claim and cross-claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">proper approach to meaning of "reasonable prospect of success" in s 31a of the federal court act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">requirement of actual knowledge of falsity of representation for accessory liability under s 75b of the trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1416">application allowed in part</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">commissioner of taxation (cth) v sun alliance investments pty limited (in liquidation)  income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">capital gains and losses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">reduced amount of any consideration in respect of the acquisition of an asset</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">royal and sun alliance insurance australia holdings limited ("rsa") formed by merger of the royal group and the sun alliance group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">rsa deemed by operation of s 160zzs of the income tax assessment act 1936 (cth) ("the 1936 act ") to have acquired shares in two wholly owned subsidiaries on date of merger for a consideration equal to the market value of those shares on that date</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">reconstructed accounts of subsidiaries showed unrealised accretions to the value of their assets at the merger date</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">subsidiaries subsequently declared and paid dividends to rsa which attracted a rebate of tax payable on the dividends</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">rsa disposed of its shares in the subsidiaries and claimed capital losses on the disposals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">losses sought, in part, to be transferred to taxpayer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">whether, pursuant to s 160zk of the 1936 act , the consideration in respect of rsa's deemed acquisition of shares in the subsidiaries was required to be reduced by a rebatable dividend adjustment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">whether dividends distributed by the subsidiaries were attributable to profits derived by them before rsa's deemed acquisition of shares in those subsidiaries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">whether unrealised accretions to the value of assets must have permanent character in order to be profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=cited from="[2005] HCA 70">whether unrealised profits can be said to be derived.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">taxes and duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">goods and services tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">plaintiffs' proceedings for declarations as to liability under a new tax system (goods and services tax) act 1999 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">commissioner's application for summary termination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether proceedings raised a matter for the purpose of the judiciary act 1903 (cth), s 39(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">hearing reopened to allow production of signed copies of notice of assessments under the taxation administration act 1953 (cth), s 22 and a declaration under a new tax system (goods and services tax) act 1999 (cth), s 165-40(a)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">privative provision in the taxation administration act 1953 (cth), s 59 that production of signed copies of notices of assessment and declarations conclusive evidence that properly made and accept in proceedings in federal court or aat under pt ivc that amounts and particulars are correct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether the copies invoked the privative provision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether the notice of assessments was tentative</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether the privative provision excluded the ingredients making up the net amounts in the tax periods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether ingredients included the position under a new tax system (goods and services tax) act 1999 (cth) of related companies, the non-receipients of notices of assessment or declarations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=cited from="[2005] NSWSC 388">whether in exercise of discretion the court should decline to deal further with the matter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">appeal from commissioner's disallowance of taxpayer's objection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">requirement of federal court rules that commissioner file statement outlining succinctly the commissioner's contentions and the facts and issues in the appeal as the commissioner perceives them</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">whether document filed by commissioner complies with rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">elements of complying statement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">relevance to contents of statement that onus on an appeal lies on taxpayer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">relevance of fact that material omitted from statement available to taxpayer from other documents emanating from commissioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 335">costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1128">[ database search ] [ name search ] [ recent decisions ] [ noteup ] [ lawcite ] [ help ] commissioner of taxation v kerry matthew stokes [1996] fca 1128 (24 december 1996)   income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1128">three notices of amended assessment each notifying a different taxable income and tax payable issued on same day to the same taxpayer in respect of the one year of income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1128">whether alternative and inconsistent assessments valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[1996] FCA 1128">no assessment made as no definitive liability ascertained and each purported assessment tentative.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">scheme to reduce tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">tax benefit in connexion with scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">commissioner's power to cancel benefit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">scheme identification of facts by commissioner as scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">whether binding on power to cancel benefit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">reasonable expectation of inclusion of amount in taxpayer's assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">purpose of entering scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.8" type=cited from="[1994] HCA 43">income tax assessment act 1936 (cth), ss. 177a(1) "scheme", (5), 177c(1)(a), 177d, 177f(1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">workers' compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">commonwealth employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">claim for compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">determination by commissioner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">appeal by claimant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">revocation by commissioner of determination pending appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">substitution of new determination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">magistrate refusing to entertain appeal on ground that the determination had been nullified</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">appeal to high court against magistrate's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">whether special leave to appeal necessary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.10" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 28">commonwealth employees' compensation act 1930-1956, ss. 4 (1), 6 (2), 20.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">income tax (cth.)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">amended assessment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">objection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">condition precedent to power to amend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">failure to make full and true disclosure of material facts and consequential avoidance of tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=cited from="[1956] HCA 62">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1955, ss. 170 (2), 173, 177 (1), 190 (b).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">applications for leave to appeal an interlocutory judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">onus in proceedings borne by applicant for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">tests for the grant of leave not made out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">purported election to have applications dealt by the full court of the federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">no right of election exists under the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 395">applications dismissed with costs</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] FCA 395">1 These are applications for leave to appeal against an interlocutory judgment ( McDonald's Australia Ltd v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 37) where the applicant ('McDonald's') sought relief at first instance that the primary judge described as novel. The proceedings at first instance are, in each case, an appeal against a decision made by the Commissioner adverse to McDonald's. Each proceeding is at an early stage --- no evidence has been filed and there has been no discovery. Nevertheless, in each case, McDonald's sought summary judgment. It relied on s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) ('the Act). Section 31A provides, so far as is here relevant:
 
 '(1) The Court may give judgment for one party against another in relation to the whole or any part of a proceeding if: 
 (a) the first party is prosecuting the proceeding or that part of the proceeding; and 
 (b) the Court is satisfied that the other party has no reasonable prospect of successfully defending the proceeding or that part of the proceeding. 
 
 ... 
 
 
 
 (3) For the purposes of this section, a defence ... need not be: 
 
 
 (a) hopeless; or 
 (b) bound to fail; 
 for it to have no reasonable prospect of success. ' </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">A NEW TAX SYSTEM (GOODS AND SERVICES TAX) ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 31A Summary judgment</title>
<title id="l3">INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT ACT 1936 </title>
<title id="l4">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 </title>
<title id="l5">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 - SECT 5 Tenure of Commissioner and Second Commissioners</title>
<title id="l6">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 - SECT 14ZZO Grounds of objection and burden of proof</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>