<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 435 (20 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/435.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 374">criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 374">sentencing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 374">various breaches of s 155 of trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 374">refusing or failing to comply with a notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 374">aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring the commission of an offence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">merits review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">no failure to consider applicant's claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">no breach of section 425</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">no jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 515">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">application to review decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">whether tribunal erred in considering the applicant's activities in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">whether failure to have regard to relevant consideration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">whether failure to comply with s.424a of the migration act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 652">whether tribunal erred in considering delay in application for a protection visa.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 436">criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 436">sentencing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 436">refusing or failing to comply with a notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 436">s 155 of trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FMCA 515">I respectfully agree with her Honour's consideration of these authorities and understood her Honour's reference to the word "determinative" above to be used in the sense that it was the ultimate or the only issue used by the Tribunal in rejecting the applicant's claims (see also [70] to [72] of her Honour's consideration and the reference to SZGGT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2008] FCA 435 at [60] to [64] per Rares J (" SZGGT ")). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FMCA 652">As Rares J stated in SZGGT v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2008] FCA 435 at [60] --- [64] (albeit in the context of considering s.424A of the Act): " A conclusion of fabrication and elaboration of claims is substantively different from a finding that the Tribunal was not satisfied as to the claims " (at [60]) In SZEOP v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 807 Rares J elaborated on this distinction in circumstances where a Tribunal s.424A letter had put to an applicant his migration history and explanation for delay in applying for a protection visa, suggesting the delay was relevant because it cast doubt on the genuineness, or at least the depth, of his claimed fear of persecution if he returned to his home country. However in the Tribunal decision in SZGGT the Tribunal had regard to the delay (together with other factors) in finding that the applicant's claim to be a homosexual was not credible. Rares J was of the view that the relevance of delay as a reason for concluding that the applicant had fabricated a claim to be homosexual, as distinct from casting doubt on the genuineness or depth of his claimed fear of persecution, had to be explained to him under s.424A(1)(b). The importance of this case for present purposes is the clear distinction drawn between findings of genuineness (or depth) of a claimed fear of persecution and findings as to the credibility of an applicant (and hence in relation to fabrication of claims). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FCA 436">3 The circumstances of Micheal Rana's wrongdoing are set out in the reasons for judgment in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Rana [2008] FCA 435.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CRIMES ACT 1914 </title>
<title id="l1">CRIMES ACT 1914 - SECT 16A Matters to which court to have regard when passing sentence etc.</title>
<title id="l2">CRIMES ACT 1914 - SECT 20 Conditional release of offenders after conviction</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>