<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>National Tertiary Education Industry Union v Central Queensland University [2008] FCA 481 (11 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/481.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">award</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">termination of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">failure to hold discussions with union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">failure to provide written information to union</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">whether breaches of a single term or separate terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 374">whether to be paid to applicant or to organisation.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">breaches of terms of award</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">failure to pay wages, annual leave entitlements etcetera</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">whether employees had become independent contractors. penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">extent to which breaches of one term relating to several employees "arose out of a course of conduct" and therefore shall be treated as constituting a single breach. amount of underpayments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">whether amounts paid in excess of the award in some weeks should be taken into account. costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">whether court empowered to order payment of expenses of applicant's witnesses.  conciliation and arbitration act 1904</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">ss. 116, 119, 120, 197a  federal court of australia act 1976</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">s. 43  master and servant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">whether contractor an employee.  conciliation and arbitration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">underpayment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">subsequent payments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">whether may be applied in reduction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 306">conciliation and arbitration act 1904 (cth), s. 119(3). sawmill workers who performed all their work at the sawmill, supplied no tools themselves but had all the raw materials and equipment supplied to them, who did not perform work for any other person, and who were subject to instructions as to the actual method of performing the work and who were each a part of the organisation of the sawmill were employees.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">criminal law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">single transaction involving more than one step each of &amp;which was an offence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">convictions of more than one such offence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">evasion of duty involving steps each contravening a provision of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">customs act 1901-1960 (cth), ss. 234, 241.*  customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">maximum penalty not less than thrice the value of goods "in respect of" &amp;which offence committed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">whether offences "in respect of" goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">customs act 1901-1960 (cth), ss. 234, 240.*  customs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">smuggling</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.15" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">goods imported</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.16" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">misdescription of goods in documents and entries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.17" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">true character of goods concealed by misdescription</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.18" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">lesser rate of duty attracted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.19" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">goods released by the customs to importers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.20" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">whether "smuggling"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.21" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">whether clandestine introduction of goods necessary to constitute "smuggling"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.22" type=cited from="[1968] HCA 90">customs act 1901-1960 (cth), ss. 4* ("smuggling"), 233 (1) (a).*</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">breach of wra provision regarding payment of accrued annual leave upon termination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">whether directors were "persons involved" in the breach</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">matters relevant to penalty considered where breach was deliberate and ongoing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">anshun estoppel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">where earlier proceedings in district court brought by respondents to recover money owing by the applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">where earlier judgment awarded unpaid annual leave entitlement following counter-claim for breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">entitlement still unpaid at time of hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">where company directors not party to earlier proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 845">whether claim for penalty under the wra could and should have been brought in earlier proceedings.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">contraventions of terms of workplace agreements giving rise to contraventions of a civil remedy provision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">consideration of penalty to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">whether contraventions within "course of conduct" under fair work act 2009 (cth), s 557</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">consideration of meaning and effect of s 557</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">relevant considerations in determining quantum of penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">whether to impose maximum penalty for each contravention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 652">consideration of totality principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 362">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 362">wilful breach of workplace relations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 362">appointment of bargaining agent pursuant to s335 wra</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 362">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 362">matters relevant to quantum of penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">award</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">breach of clauses of a notional agreement preserving a state award</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">breach of three clauses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">proper approach to fixing penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">need for consideration of the circumstances of the particular case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">importance of deterrence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">totality principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCAFC 170">consideration of appropriate recipient of penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1028">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1028">where breaches of award and workplace relations act admitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1028">penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1028">whether multiple breaches should be considered single course of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 1028">application of totality principle.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 845">The penalty which I would impose upon Planpac International Pty Ltd is of 250 penalty units or $27,500.00. The penalty I would impose severally upon each of the second and third respondents is 55 penalty units or $6,500.00. These penalties shall be paid to the applicant within 28 days. The respondents have argued that the penalties should be paid to the Consolidated Revenue Fund but, in my view, it is appropriate that the penalties should be paid to the complainant who has carried the burden of bringing the proceedings. This is the approach that has been taken with some regularity in the Federal Court; National Tertiary Education Industry Union v Central Queensland University [2008] FCA 481 at [50] . 
 I certify that the preceding thirty-six (36) paragraphs are a true copy of the reasons for judgment of FM Raphael FM 
 
 
 Associate: 
 
 
Date: 4 November 2010
 
 [1] Annexure A to Affidavit of Bruce Hume James sworn 15 August 2010. AustLII: Copyright Policy | Disclaimers | Privacy Policy | Feedback 
 URL: http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FMCA/2010/845.html 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 652">I do feel obliged, given the submissions made on behalf of the QR respondents, to make particular reference to an earlier judgment of mine in relation to National Tertiary Education Industry Union v Central Queensland University [2008] FCA 481. There was, there, a more modest penalty outcome to that which I propose in this case. The circumstances were very different. There was genuine contrition, evidenced by a timely plea of guilty. There was obvious embarrassment to the chief executive officer, who gave evidence at the penalty hearing, in what had occurred. There had been no ignoring in that case of a need to consult, but rather a conflation of quite differently worded obligations. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FMCA 362">The applicant submits that the court should order pursuant to section 841 of the Act that the penalty be paid to it. It contends that such an order is usually warranted where an industrial organisation brings proceedings for a contravention of the Act to protect the legitimate interests of its members; CF Finance Sector Union v Commonwealth of Australia (2005) 47 IR 462 at 482 --- 483; Rojos v Esselte Australia Pty Ltd (No.2) [2008] FCA 1585 at [68] --- [69]; National Tertiary Education Industry Union v Central Queensland University (2008) FCA 481. In my view this is an appropriate case for the exercise of the discretion in this instance in favour of the applicant. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCAFC 170">68 In National Tertiary Education Industry Union v Central Queensland University [2008] FCA 481 at [50] Logan J expressed his agreement with the above observation of Wilcox J, while in McIlwain v Ramsey Food Packaging Pty Ltd at [103] Greenwood J had expressed approval of the observation of Finkelstein J.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FMCA 1028">In Gibbs v The Mayor, Councillors and Citizens of the City of Altona (1992) 37 FCR 216 Gray J stated at 223: The object of s 178(2) appears to be that a party bound by an award and pursuing a course of conduct involving repeated acts or omissions, which would ordinarily be regarded as giving rise to a series of separate breaches, should not be punished separately for each of those breaches. If such a party has pursued a course of conduct which gives rise to breaches of several different obligations, there is no reason why it should be treated as immune in respect of its breach of one obligation, merely because it has acted in breach of another. This reasoning leads to the conclusion that each separate obligation found in an award is to be regarded as a "term", for the purposes of s 178 of the Act. The ascertainment of what is a term should depend not on matters of form, such as how the award maker has chosen to designate by numbers or letters the various provisions of an award, but on matters of substance, namely the different obligations which can be spelt out. For these reasons, I incline to the view that each separate obligation imposed by an award is to be regarded as a "term", for the purposes of s 178 of the Act. If the different terms impose cumulative obligations or obligations that substantially overlap, it is possible to take into account the substance of the matter by imposing no penalty, or a nominal penalty, in respect of breaches of some terms, but a substantial penalty in respect of others. 
(See also Kelly v Fitzpatrick [2007] FCA 1080 ; (2007) 166 IR 14 at [17] ; McIver v Healey [2008] FCA 425 at [16] --- [18] and National Tertiary Education Union v Central Queensland University [2008] FCA 481 at [42] --- [43]). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CRIMES ACT 1914 </title>
<title id="l1">CRIMES ACT 1914 - SECT 4AA Penalty units</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l3">CENTRAL QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY ACT 1998 </title>
<title id="l4">CENTRAL QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY ACT 1998 - SECT 4 4 Establishment of university</title>
<title id="l5">CENTRAL QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY ACT 1998 - SECT 8 8 Functions of council</title>
<title id="l6">CENTRAL QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY ACT 1998 - SECT 32 32 Vice-chancellor</title>
</legistitles>
</case>