<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd ACN 099 071 968 v Carey (No 20) [2008] FCA 45 (1 February 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/45.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">real estate agents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">renewal of triennial certificate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">board refused renewal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">tribunal overturned board's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">whether tribunal committed error of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">whether tribunal's finding unreasonable in wednesbury sense</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">turns on own facts  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">time for commencing an appeal from tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2010] WASCA 109">whether rules of the supreme court 1971 (wa) o 3 r 3 applies to an appeal from the tribunal</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] WASCA 109">48 The appellant advances four grounds of appeal. Three of those grounds are supported by particulars. The grounds of appeal, excluding the particulars, are:
 
 1.1 The [Tribunal] erred in law in holding that [Carey] remained a person of good character and a fit and proper person to hold a licence under the [REBA Act], which holding was not reasonably open on the undisputed facts found by the Tribunal and the undisputed evidence and material before the Tribunal, which should have led the Tribunal to conclude that [Carey] was not a person of good character and repute and not a fit and proper person to hold a licence. ...

 2.1 The Tribunal erred in law in holding that ASIC did not seek any renewal of undertakings freezing the assets of [Carey] which expired on 30 June 2006 (Reasons at [8] &amp; [82]) and in further holding (implicitly) that no allegations of serious misconduct were made against [Carey] (Reasons at [95]) in that those determinations were not reasonably open to the Tribunal on the evidence. ...

 3.1 The Tribunal erred in law in holding that the findings and observations of French J in Australian Securities &amp; Investment Commission: In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 20) [2008] FCA 45 could not be fairly used to support a conclusion that [Carey] was not a fit and proper person to hold a real estate agent's licence and should have held that those findings could be taken into account and should have taken them into account so as to conclude that [Carey] was not a person of good character and repute and not a fit and proper person to hold a licence. 4.1 The Tribunal erred in law in holding that [Carey] remained a person of good character and a fit and proper person to be licensed under the REBA Act, which holdings were not reasonably open having regard to [the matters before the Tribunal]. 
  40 In Australian Securities and Investments Commission; In the Matter of Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd v Carey (No 20) [2008] FCA 45 French J made an observation concerning a joint venture proposed by Silkchime Pty Ltd, a company controlled by Carey, and Richstar Enterprises Pty Ltd, a company controlled by Carey's sister. The proceedings before French J involved an application by a receiver of Silkchime for directions from the court in relation to whether he ought to consent to the joint venture. In his judgment, his Honour referred to a notice issued by Carey threatening to terminate the joint venture as a piece of 'cosmetic nonsense'. He also said that he did not consider that the proposed joint venture was in the best interests of the preservation of Silkchime's assets or those who might have claims against Silkchime.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1323 Power of Court to prohibit payment or transfer of money, financial products or other property</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>