<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v PRK Corporation Limited [2008] FCA 403 (28 March 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/403.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">price-fixing understanding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">whether communications between competitors concerning retail petrol price increases constitute evidence of an understanding that provides for the fixing or controlling of prices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">whether participation in the communications and increasing the retail price of petrol constitute giving effect to the understanding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">consideration of circumstances in which a servant's or agent's conduct in making and giving effect to a price-fixing understanding is binding on the principal courts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">submission of no case to answer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">whether respondents should not be permitted to make no case submissions at the conclusion of the applicant's case unless all of the respondents elect not to call evidence evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">whether the ahern principle applies to persons involved in a contravention of s 45(2) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">consideration of circumstances in which admissions of a servant or agent in relation to past events are admissible against the principal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1678">consideration of circumstances in which false denials may constitute evidence of consciousness of guilt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">consumer protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">misleading or deceptive conduct by corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">liability of persons aiding, abetting, counselling or procuring or party to contravention by corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">whether knowledge of material facts necessary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">whether knowledge that facts constitute contravention necessary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1985] HCA 65">trade practices act 1974 (cth),ss. 52, 75b, 82</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">further affidavit material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">viable cause of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">effect of amendment of statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">additional individual plaintiffs added</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">effect of amending legislation on cause of action in pending proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">trade practices act 1974 , ss. 4 , 4d, 45 , 80 , 82</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">federal court of australia act 1976 , s. 56</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1978] FCA 1">high court rules, o. 29, r. 1. after the defendants had obtained an order that the plaintiff company give security for costs in an action under the trade practices act 1974 , the plaintiffs pursuant to leave reserved adduced new evidence on affidavit. the new evidence considerably strengthened the plaintiff company's prospects of succeeding against certain defendants. after the action had commenced, s. 45 of the trade practices act 1974 was amended with effect from 1st july, 1977. the plaintiff company sought to amend its statement of claim to allege that the defendants had continued and were continuing to give effect to a certain unlawful contract, arrangement or understanding. application was also made for leave to add certain individual shareholders in the plaintiff company as plaintiffs in the action.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">competition law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">allegation of global agreement, arrangement or understanding having effect of substantially lessening competition in market in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">what is required in a pleading by way of allegation that market was in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">relationship with allegation of global market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether pleading embarrassing. trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">competition law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">allegation of agreement, arrangement or understanding containing "exclusionary provision" and having effect of substantially lessening competition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">reliance on same facts for each of these allegations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether pleading embarrassing. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">representative proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">definition of represented group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">need for clear definition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">need for potential group members to know whether they were within, or outside, the group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.14" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether definition inadequate if potential group members required to make enquiries. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.15" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.16" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">statement of claim in competition proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.17" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">allegations as to existence of global and australian markets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.18" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">allegations as to making, and giving effect to, cartel arrangements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.19" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether primary judge should have struck out statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.20" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether discretionary judgment in a matter of practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.21" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether sufficient doubt to justify hearing appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.22" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 85">whether injustice would result from leaving judgment undisturbed.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCAFC 85">79 In its written submissions, the applicant contended that para 36 "was in conformity with what was required by Justice Sackville in ruling on a similar strike out application in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v PRK Corporation Ltd [2008] FCA 403 at [61] - [68], namely identifying unambiguously the matters known to each of the respondents". We do not agree. What it is alleged that each of the respondents knew is the subject of considerable ambiguity in para 36, most probably because, if we may so observe without disrespect to those involved, the paragraph was added as a kind of catch-all without any adequate attention being given to the facts which were said to give rise to a particular respondent, presumptively not otherwise involved in a contravention of s 45 , not only being concerned in the contravention of another respondent, but knowingly being so. These matters should not, in our view, be left to the surmise of the reader, as para 36 does.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 523">1 In a judgment delivered on 28 March 2008, I dealt with motions filed by the respondents seeking to strike out the whole or portion of the amended statement of claim: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v PRK Corporation Limited [2008] FCA 403. I directed the applicant (' ACCC ') to file and serve a further amended statement of claim within 28 days. I also directed that the filing and service of the further amended statement of claim be without prejudice to the entitlement of any of the respondents to file a motion seeking orders striking out the whole or portion of the further amended statement of claim. Otherwise, the motions were dismissed.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 21 Declarations of right</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>