<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZBJH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 501 (21 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/501.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">migration law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">where applicant made references in application for review by refugee review tribunal to material provided to department in visa application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">meaning of 'information' under s 424a(1) and s 424a(3)(b)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">incorporation by reference in application for review and whether considered 'information' applicant gave for purposes of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">held objective test to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">where tribunal made positive finding of elaboration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">treatment of omissions in evidence by review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">whether considered information relevant to s 424a(1)(b) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 435">appeal allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">whether well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">particular social group accepted as single women in albania without male protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">whether appellant faced a real chance of being sexually assaulted or trafficked by reason of her membership of that group</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 104">adequacy of state protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v respondents s152/2003  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">applications for protection visas by de facto husband and wife nationals of ukraine</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">well-founded fear of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">husband claimed to suffer religious persecution as jehovah's witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">refugee review tribunal found that incidents of which husband complained were individual and random incidents and did not amount to persecution, and that the chance that he would suffer persecution in future was remote</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">tribunal rejected claim that state encouraged or condoned persecution of jehovah's witnesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">whether full court of federal court erred in concluding that tribunal committed jurisdictional error in failing to consider a different claim of whether the husband might suffer future harm from private individuals because of religious belief and whether the government of ukraine was able in a practical sense to stop such harm occurring</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">absence of evidence before tribunal to support a conclusion that ukraine did not provide level of protection required.  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">applications for protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">relevance of attitude or capacity of state to whether fear of harm well-founded, to whether there is persecution, to whether a person is outside country of nationality owing to well-founded fear of persecution and to unwillingness of person to seek protection of state</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">protection theory and accountability theory</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">non-state actor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">harm by non-state actors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">persecution by non-state actors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.16" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">state complicity in persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.17" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">persecution tolerated or condoned by state</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.18" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">failure of state protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.19" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">unwilling or unable to provide protection.  international law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.20" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">treaty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.21" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.22" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">refugees convention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.23" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">"persecution"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.24" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">different theories of persecution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.25" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">meaning of treaty provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.26" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">proper approach to meaning</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.27" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">primacy of text</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.28" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">approaches of courts in countries of refuge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.29" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">protection theory and accountability theory</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.30" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 18">whether a third theory applicable.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1188">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1188">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1188">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1188">whether error in assessing claim on basis of membership of a particular social group.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">refusal of a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">applicant claiming persecution in china on various bases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">tribunal finding no convention nexus with the harm experienced by the applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">no reviewable error found</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 831">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 642">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 642">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 642">refusal of a protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 642">interlocutory dismissal of show cause application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2008] FMCA 642">no arguable case.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">migration law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">appellant a filipino muslim homosexual male</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">appeal from decision of federal magistrates court affirming decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">whether tribunal erred in failing to consider discrete basis for protection in appellant's being both muslim and a male homosexual</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">whether serious harm feared</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">whether relocation finding of tribunal conclusive where discrete basis for protection not considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">appeal upheld</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 556">matter remitted to tribunal</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1188">The appellant submitted that the Tribunal would fall into jurisdictional error if it did not assess the appellant's claim as it was presented to the Tribunal. The appellant relied on the observations of Lander J in SZBJH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 501 , particular at [40]-[42]. As Lander J pointed out at [40]: 
 
 "... The appellant claimed refugee status by reason of being a member of a particular social group.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 942">The RRT again found the appellant not to be a credible witness. Again it rejected his claims and affirmed the decision of the delegate. It indicated that the issue raised by the letter was not used in a manner adverse to the appellant, although, being a forgery, it gave no support to his claims. A further application was then made by the appellant to the FMCA. On this occasion, on 3 August 2007, the application for judicial review was refused ( SZBJH v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [2007] FMCA 1395). The FMCA concluded that no jurisdictional error had been identified and that, accordingly, the application for judicial review should be refused. The appellant appealed to this Court. On 21 April 2008 a judge of this Court allowed the appeal and remitted the matter again to the RRT ( SZBJH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 501) . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2008] FMCA 831">I accept that it would be a jurisdictional error for the Tribunal to consider a particular social group claim in terms materially different from those put by an applicant or fairly arising from the material [15] . The Tribunal accepted that a particular social group claim might arise from the material in terms of "persons who returned to the PRC after remaining abroad for extended periods". Contrary to the Minister's submissions, the Tribunal did not in its decision exclude the applicant from that group.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FMCA 642">Having regard to the applicant's reference to a protest involving Jats I have considered whether there could be any arguable case of jurisdictional error in this matter based upon the recent Federal Court decision in SZBJH v Minister for Immigration [2008] FCA 501. In that case his Honour Lander J found that the Tribunal had fallen into error in failing to consider a particular social group claim based upon Punjabi Sikh Jat landowners in the terms in which that particular social group had been put forward by the applicant. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FCA 556">However, it was obliged to deal with a discrete basis for protection put forward by him ( Dranichnikov v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs (2003) 197 ALR 389 , (2003) 77 ALJR 1088 at [24], [95]; Htun v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural Affairs [2001] FCA 1802 ; (2001) 194 ALR 244 at [42] ). Put another way, the Tribunal did not identify the correct social group. Considering the greater class does not necessarily deal with the lesser ( SZBJH v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 501 at [35] ---[42]). The appellant's contention was, and is, that a male Muslim homosexual was in a different, and more vulnerable, position than other male homosexuals in the Philippines. That contention was not considered. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424 Tribunal may seek information</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 427 Powers of the Refugee Review Tribunal etc.</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>