<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 (10 January 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/5.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">substituted service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">order for leave to serve out of jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">service out of jurisdiction unable to be effected</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">mother and sister living in jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">co-directors of company with proposed respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">solicitors instructed by company and mother and sister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">proposed respondent entering and re-entering jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">substituted service by delivery to mother's address</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2035">copy to solicitors for company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1730">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1730">consent orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1730">whether within power of court to make</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1730">whether appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">resale price maintenance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">application for injunctions, declarations and pecuniary penalties arising out of the operation of a scheme whereby products were distributed through a network of sales representatives</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">penalties to be imposed for contravening conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 1212">factors to be considered in determining appropriate penalties.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">consumer protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">advertisement dealing with the effects of environmental tobacco smoke found to be misleading and deceptive</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">question of relief to which respondent (the applicant at first instance) entitled</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">no claim made other than for injunctive relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">injunctive relief granted by primary judge set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether applicant should be permitted to amend application to seek declaratory relief.  remedies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">declaratory relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">consumer protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether power to grant declaratory relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether injunctive relief different from that granted by primary judge should be substituted therefor.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">disposal of costs at first instance and on appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether costs should be ordered on indemnity basis.  appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">admission of fresh evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.15" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether respondent should be given leave to rely on fresh evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.16" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">finality principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.17" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">evidence not evidence in existence at time of trial.  appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.18" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.19" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">validity or construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.20" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 83">whether appellant should be given leave to argue questions relating to the validity or construction of s.52 of the trade practices act 1974 upon the basis of decisions of the high court of australia in australian capital television pty. limited v. commonwealth of australia (no.2) [1992] hca 45 ; (1992) 108 alr 577 and nationwide news pty. limited v. wills [1992] hca 46 ; (1992) 108 alr 681.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">therapeutic goods act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">civil penalty proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">respondents found to have supplied and manufactured or aided and abetted in the supply and manufacture of counterfeit therapeutic goods and goods that have not been registered pursuant to therapeutic goods act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">pecuniary penalties imposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">declarations of contravention made  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">agreed statement of facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">effect of section 191 evidence act  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 597">applicant granted leave to proceed against company in liquidation on the condition that the applicant does not enforce an order for the payment of money by that respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">registered designs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">validity of</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether designs reasonably clear and succinct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether designs new and distinctive when compared with prior art base. intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">registered designs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">infringement of</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether alleged infringing products embodied designs that were substantially similar in overall impression to registered designs. intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">registered designs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">infringement of</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">joint liability for</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">personal liability of director of infringing company. trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.12" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">prescribed consumer product safety standard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.13" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">goods supplied in trade or commerce</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.14" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether goods complied with standard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.15" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">sufficiency of proof. damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.16" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">conduct amounting to infringement of design and contravention of trade practices legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.17" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether damages available under both heads</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.18" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">where damages not awarded under trade practices legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.19" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">costs consequences. trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.20" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">contraventions by companies of legislative norms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.21" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">directors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.22" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">accessorial liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.23" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether knowingly involved. practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.24" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.25" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether appropriate to deny successful respondent his costs with respect to period before he swore to his non-involvement in conduct by company of which he had been director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.26" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">offer of compromise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.27" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 55">whether party entitled to costs incurred after service of offer of compromise on an indemnity basis.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">price fixing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">consent orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">pecuniary penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">deterrent factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">no prior contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">lack of awareness of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">no implementation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">no assets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">deregistered company re-registered for proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 549">natural person no assets.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">price fixing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">consent orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">pecuniary penalties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">deterrent principle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">relevant factors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">small business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">admission of contravention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.8" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">cooperation with accc</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.9" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">no prior contraventions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.10" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">lack of awareness of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.11" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">disadvantaged by anti-competitive agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.12" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 20">little or no risk of re-offending</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 597">In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2006] FCA 1730 at [6] Nicholson J listed a number of ways in which that support might be manifested by declarations sought including the matters referred to in [23] above. In addition his Honour referred to the deterrent effect of declarations and that they may be of assistance in clarifying the law. Nicholson J's list was adopted by French J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 at [48] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCAFC 55">315 Her Honour referred to the classes of cases identified by French J in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 ; (2008) 30 ATPR 42-212 at [48] and said that the case before her did not fall within any of them. She said it was inappropriate to make declarations having regard to the fact that the representations meant different things to different classes of consumers and the fact that the Australian Design Rules "suffer from their own problems". I think the reference to the problems with the Australian Design Rules is a reference to the industry's misunderstanding of the effect of obtaining a CRN. The primary judge concluded by saying there was "little, if any, utility in making the declarations" and there was the possibility that the making of any declaration would "create more confusion or itself be misleading".</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 141">There is, in my view, a more fundamental reason why the Court should not grant the relief sought --- the claims failed. During the course of argument, Counsel for the Applicant could not refer me to any authority or principle which would support the making of a declaration in circumstances where the claims had failed. After the hearing, the Applicant referred me to the decision of the Full Court of the Federal Court in Tobacco Institute of Australia Limited v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc (No 2) [1993] FCA 83 ; (1993) 41 FCR 89 at 99-100 as authority for the proposition that the Court has power to make a declaration in a case brought by a member of the public provided that the person had an arguable case for an injunction notwithstanding that the member of the public had suffered no damage and the case was not one appropriate for injunctive relief. In Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 at [48] , French J summarised the cases in the following terms: 
There may be a question about their utility given that these reasons set out the findings of fact and the contraventions which underpin the injunctive relief which has been granted and the pecuniary penalties which are to be imposed. However, as Nicholson J pointed out in Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v The Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union [2006] FCA 1730 ; (2007) ATPR 42-140 at [6] such declarations: 
 
 Are an appropriate vehicle to record the Court's disapproval of the contravening conduct: Tobacco Institute of Australia Ltd v Australian Federation of Consumer Organisations Inc [1993] FCA 83 ; (1993) 41 FCR 89 at 100; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Chen [2003] FCA 897 ; (2003) 132 FCR 309 at [36] . Serve to vindicate the ACCC's claim that the respondents contravened the Act: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Goldy Motors (2000) 23 ATPR 41-801 at [34]. May be of assistance to the ACCC in the future in carrying out the duties conferred upon it by the Act: Goldy Motors 23 ATPR at [34]. Are of assistance in clarifying the law: Goldy Motors 23 ATPR at [34]; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Chaste Corporation Pty Ltd (in liq) [2005] FCA 1212 at [146] . May inform consumers of the dangers arising from a respondent's contravening conduct: Chen 132 FCR at [48]; and
 May deter corporations from contravening the Act: Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Midland Brick Co Pty Ltd (2004) 207 ALR 329 at [22].
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2008] FCA 549">3 The facts of the case have been set out in an earlier judgment relating to the first four respondents given on 10 January 2008: Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos (No 2) [2008] FCA 5. Injunctive orders were made by consent and penalties imposed after argument in respect of those respondents. Declarations offered by consent were stood over pending the finalisation of the proceedings against all respondents. In a further judgment, delivered on 17 January 2008, I made injunctive orders against the fifth and sixth respondents and again imposed penalties. Declaration orders proposed by consent were stood over until the finalisation of the proceedings as a whole: Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 3) [2008] FCA 20. The matter has come back before the Court for disposition as against the seventh and eighth respondents. Statements of agreed facts have been filed. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2008] FamCAFC 87">IN THE FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 
 WESTERN AUSTRALIA DISTRICT REGISTRY WAD312 OF 2006 

 BETWEEN: AUSTRALIAN COMPETITION AND CONSUMER COMMISSION 
 Applicant AND: KOKOS INTERNATIONAL PTY LTD (ACN 009 404 611) 
 First Respondent 

 CHUL WOO KIM 
 Second Respondent 

 IAE EDU NET PERTH PTY LTD (ACN 109 963 304) 
 Third Respondent 

 YOUNG GIL PAE 
 Fourth Respondent 

 SANG-HONG JUNG T/A NANURI EDUCATION CENTRE (BN 088 22 876) 
 Fifth Respondent 

 REBEKAH CABALT 
 Sixth Respondent 

 STUDY OVERSEAS NOW PTY LTD (ACN 106 865 310) 
 Seventh Respondent 

 JUDGE: FRENCH J DATE: 17 JANUARY 2008 PLACE: PERTH 

 REASONS FOR JUDGMENT 
 
1 These proceedings were commenced by the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission (ACCC) against three companies and a business, which were involved in 2004 and 2005, in the provision of educational consultancy services in Perth to students of Korean origin. The proceedings arise out of alleged contraventions of s 45 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) (the Act) and the Competition Code of Western Australia (the Code), by reason of an oral and written agreement, made between the companies and the business not to offer discounted tuition fees to students for whom they operated as go-betweens or brokers in arranging their enrolment in various schools, colleges and universities. 2 The detailed background to the proceedings has already been set out in the judgment, which I delivered on 10 January 2008: Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5. At that time injunctive orders were made by consent against the first to fourth respondents. Pecuniary penalties were imposed on them after consideration of agreed statements of fact and submissions by the parties. They do not dispute the orders sought so far as they relate to declaratory relief and so far as they relate to the proposed injunctions and, in the case of Ms Jung, the proposed requirement to attend at a trade practices compliance seminar. The only issue that remains is the determination of pecuniary penalties. 5 The general principles governing the imposition of pecuniary penalties under the Act and the Code, were canvassed in Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v Kokos International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 5 and I will not repeat them here, save to emphasise the significance of their deterrent purpose. I also observe the necessity to take account of relevant distinctions between different contraveners in the context of the deterrence principle, which informs the penalties that are imposed. 6 As with each of the other parties who have been dealt with, it is not disputed that Ms Jung and Ms Cabalt were unaware that they were breaking the law by entering into, and being involved in, the implementation of the agreements not to offer discounted tuition fees.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 21 Declarations of right</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 23 Making of orders and issue of writs</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l4">COMPETITION POLICY REFORM (WESTERN AUSTRALIA) ACT 1996 </title>
<title id="l5">COMPETITION POLICY REFORM (WESTERN AUSTRALIA) ACT 1996 - SECT 4 </title>
<title id="l6">COMPETITION POLICY REFORM (WESTERN AUSTRALIA) ACT 1996 - SECT 55 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>