<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tidswell Financial Services Limited (ACN 010 810 607) v Sovereign Capital Limited (ACN 085 821 218) [2008] FCA 586 (29 April 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/586.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 257">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 257">allegation of misleading or deceptive conduct, unconscionable conduct, breach of contract and cross-claim of breach of contract.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 257">venue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 257">application to have the proceeding heard in another registry of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 257">matters for consideration.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FMCA 257">However, as indicated, it may be that once further pre-trial procedures and preparation for the trial have taken place the position may change. Dollar Sweets may wish to re-agitate the issue of change of place of proceeding in relation to the place of hearing (see Omiros per Gray J, Tidswell Financial Services Limited (ACN 010 810 607) v Sovereign Capital Limited (ACN 085 821 218) [2008] FCA 586 and cf the approach taken by the Federal Court in WG and B Manufacturing v Telsa Farad Pty Ltd [1999] FCA 859). It is normally desirable for the one judicial officer to take charge of a case from its inception, deal with all interlocutory applications and, where possible, hear the trial. However, in the particular circumstances of this case, while taking that factor into account, given that I accept that it is not possible to make a properly informed decision on all matters relevant to the question of venue for the hearing at this stage of the proceedings, this factor should not be such as to mean that there could not be a change of venue for the trial if it emerges that that is the most appropriate course to adopt. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 48 Change of venue</title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>