<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXPW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 689 (20 May 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/689.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 480">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 480">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 480">set aside previous orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 480">failure to appear.  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 480">circumstances justifying order.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">delay sought by applicant to obtain updated country information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">information not relevant to judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">non-appearance by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FMCA 2044">application dismissed pursuant to r.13.03a(3) of the federal magistrates court rules 2001 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">appeals</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">leave to appeal from an interlocutory judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the full court should regard itself as bound to apply a formula derived from niemann v. electronic industries ltd [1978] vicrp 44 ; (1978) vr 431</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">width of the discretion to grant leave to appeal under s. 24(1a) of the federal court of australia act 1976 .  patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">taking of an account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether any part of general overhead costs is allowable as a deduction in the determination of the profits made by an infringer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">principles relating to the taking of an account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the case of a side-line is an exceptional case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">reference to standard accountancy methods as indicating what must be deducted in order to determine the amount of a profit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">discussion of a line of cases establishing the approach adopted in the united states to the solution of this problem</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">onus on wrongdoer who has mixed legitimate activities with activities involving infringement of another's property right to justify the particular apportionment of costs adopted by him in his accounts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">declaration of principle that the infringer is generally at liberty to show that various categories of overhead contributed to the obtaining of the relevant profit and to show in what proportion they should be allocated in the taking of the account of profits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">discussion of whether the profits for which the defendants must account are (in the case of a patented closure for a canister) the profits for the closures only or for the closures and canisters to which they are fitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the infringer's particular pricing policy can be relied on by him as a contribution by him to the profits unrelated to the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=cited from="[1991] FCA 655">whether the profits of the whole canister and closure are fairly traceable to the use by the infringer of the invention.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">consideration of a notice of appeal from a decision of the federal magistrates court of australia refusing an application to set aside orders dismissing an applicant's application for relief in relation to a decision of the refugee review tribunal affirming a decision of the first respondent's delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">consideration of whether the order appealed from is an interlocutory or final order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">consideration of whether the notice of appeal should be treated as an application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">consideration of whether leave to appeal should be granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 953">consideration of whether the grounds of appeal should be treated constructively as a contention that the federal magistrate fell into error by failing to find error on the part of the tribunal</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 953">The principles governing granting or withholding leave to appeal are well known: D&eacute;cor Corporation Pty Ltd and Anor v Dart Industries Inc [1991] FCA 655 ; (1991) 104 ALR 621 at 622 per Sheppard, Burchett and Heerey JJ; MZXPW v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2008] FCA 689 per Tracey J; MZXPF v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2007] FCA 1765 per Spender J; SZDWE v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2004] FCA 1498 per Jacobson J at [4] and [5]. There are two questions. First, whether in all the circumstances the decision is attended with sufficient doubt to warrant its being reconsidered by the Full Court. Second, whether substantial injustice would be done if leave were refused supposing the decision to be wrong. In the present case, the question is whether the exercise of the discretion by the Federal Magistrates Court conferred by rule 16.05(2)(a) of the Federal Magistrates Court Rules to set aside (or not) orders made in the absence of a party, miscarried. The exercise of the discretion was informed by three considerations: whether the absence of the applicant from the hearing was satisfactorily explained; whether arguable grounds of jurisdictional error were demonstrated; and whether any prejudice might arise to the respondent in setting aside the dismissal order. The final question did not arise in the opinion of FM Cameron having regard to his findings in relation to the first two questions which were that the failure to appear was not satisfactorily explained and arguable grounds of jurisdictional error were not demonstrated. Background
 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL MAGISTRATES COURT RULES 2001 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>