<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858 (12 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/858.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">appointment of receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">costs of preservation and realisation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">cost of action for benefit of all interested parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 448">priorities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">managed investment schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">unregistered scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">court ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">effect of "winding up"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">procedure for winding up</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">receiver appointed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">powers of receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">whether powers should be the same as those of a company liquidator equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">order for accounts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">managers and trustees of managed investment scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">whether accounting parties practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">accounts and inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.14" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">when ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.15" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">whether inquiry can be delegated by court to a receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.16" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">nature of inquiry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.17" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">receivers and managers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.18" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.19" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">obligation to provide</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.20" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">when obligation may be dispensed with</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.21" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">courts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.22" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">concurrent jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.23" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1415">whether federal court has power to discharge receiver appointed by a supreme court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">award jurisdiction against non-party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">receiver and manager conducting litigation through insolvent company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">supreme court act 1867 (q), s. 58</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 28">rules of the supreme court of queensland o. 91, r.1.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">motion for costs by successful respondents on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">proceedings originally brought by applicants for directions under s 424 of corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">applicants receivers of property of various companies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">respondents joined as such to provide contradictors to proceedings to determine which company or companies employed the respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 59">costs payable out of property in the hands or under control of applicants as receivers.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">application for directions under s 424 corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are obliged to realise floating charge assets pursuant to s 433 corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">floating charge assets comprising of causes of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are obliged to retire</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">whether the receivers are entitled to create a retention fund</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 155">declaration as to proper construction of provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">costs :</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">application by plaintiff for protective costs order limiting costs recoverable by either party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">civil enforcement of poeo act in relation to discharge of waste water into river</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">application prior to points of defence or evidence of defendant being filed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">purpose of protective costs order in public interest cases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">factors to consider in making protective costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">whether litigation public interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">protective costs order made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">whether proposed appeal has sufficient prospects of success to warrant grant of leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">whether arguable case that primary judge made appealable error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">costs of application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">where respondents seek order under r 42.25 uniform civil procedure rules that costs of application not be paid out of trust assets</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2008] NSWCA 165">where question of whether proceedings brought in proper execution of trust will depend on outcome of ultimate proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 974">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 974">company in administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 974">company is a defendant in hostile litigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2008] FCA 974">whether plaintiff's costs should be costs in the administration</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 59">An approach taken in a fund case, as distinct from ordinary civil litigation, has been to apply the principle enunciated by Kekewich J in Re Buckton; Buckton v Buckton [1907] 2 Ch 406 , and the cases following it. That principle being that if a trustee, beneficiary, or personal representative brings an action relating to the construction of the trust, instrument or some other issue arising in the administration of the trust, or as regards the propriety of any action taken or to be taken by the representative party, those costs may ordinarily be viewed as necessarily incurred for the benefit of the trust estate and are to be paid on a solicitor and own client basis or an indemnity basis. In Australian Securities and Investments Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858 ; (2008) 169 FCR 497 , Finkelstein J held that these principles which the Chancery Courts developed in relation to representative parties could be extended to receivers, liquidators and administrators (at [10]). His Honour held that the principles had also been extended beyond fund cases (at [14]). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] WASC 155">Hence, leaving aside the allegations in COR 223 of 2009, an order that the plaintiffs' costs of the action be costs in the receivership is an appropriate one. That would be so, even if the receivers had not succeeded, but had made the application reasonably. See ASIC v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858 ; (2008) 248 ALR 766 at [8] - [10]. The effect of the proposed order in the present case is that when the costs of the receivership are ultimately accounted, the costs in COR 173 of 2009 shall be allowed as costs of the receivership, subject to any contrary finding or order made in COR 223 of 2009. The reservation in relation to the outcome of COR 223 of 2009 accords with the directions made by the Court, which made a similar reservation.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] NSWLEC 150">The Indian band commenced proceedings claiming that they had aboriginal title to the lands in question and that the forestry legislation was unconstitutional. They made an application for an interim costs order on the grounds of their extremely difficult financial situation. The order sought required the Minister to pay the group's costs of the litigation in advance (also known as a pre-emptive costs order per Finkelstein J in Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858). On appeal to the Supreme Court of Canada, the highest court of appeal, LeBel J (with whom a majority of the court agreed) identified at [40] criteria required to be satisfied in order to justify an award of interim costs, being that the party could not genuinely afford to pay for the litigation, that the claim was prima facie meritorious and that the issues were of public importance and had not previously been resolved. At [41] her Honour stated that a court should also be mindful of the position of the defendant and ensure that an order would not impose an unfair burden upon them.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCA 512">In the second set of reasons for judgment to which Mr Vaughan referred, that being those in Australian Securities and Investment Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858 ; (2008) 169 FCR 497 , which were published on 12 June 2008, his Honour said, at 499 [3]; 
 'The Mews land, which was registered in the name of WRVM, was the only substantial asset of the scheme, no village ever having been constructed. The receivers took possession of the land and found a purchaser to whom, with court approval, WRVM sold the land. As AVS and Rental Fleets refused to discharge their mortgage, it was necessary to make an order to that effect so that the sale could be completed. The order was made on the application of Messrs McMaster and Mentha: Australian Securities and Investment Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 3) [2008] FCA 448 ; (2008) 246 ALR 580. The receivers were also ordered to hold the net proceeds of sale pending the resolution of all claims on those proceeds. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] FCA 141">In addition to what I will call the traditional costs orders, the Applicant sought an interim costs order of the kind discussed by Jacob J in Mars UK Ltd v Teknowledge Ltd [1999] EWHC 226 ; [2000] FSR 138. Putting to one side the question of whether in an appropriate case, such an order might be able to be made under s 43 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) in the absence of a specific power to do so (as exists in the United Kingdom), I do not consider that this is an appropriate case to make such an order for the same reasons that I rejected the idea that I should award costs to the Applicant as some percentage of its total costs or by identifying particular steps in the preparation. The number of parties and issues in this case makes that task not only arbitrary but, I suspect, unfair. This is not an appropriate case to make such an order (for a discussion on the position of such orders in Australia, see Australian Securities and Investments Commission v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (In Liq) and Others (No 4) [2008] FCA 858 ; (2008) 169 FCR 497 at [18] - [21] per Finkelstein J). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2008] NSWCA 165">30 Another matter relied upon in oral submissions by Mr Blake was that in a recent decision, Australian Securities and Investments Commission in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Limited v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Limited (in liquidation) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858. Finkelstein J had shown what Mr Blake submitted was a more favourable attitude to the making of pre-emptive costs orders than had previously been the case. That decision had not been given at the time of the primary judge's decision, and hence was not drawn to his attention. Quite apart from whether it is an error for a primary judge to fail to take into account a development in the law that had not occurred at the time he made his decision, it is not submitted that GDK stands for a legal principle that the primary judge can be seen, in retrospect, to have misapplied.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2008] FCA 974">3 In ordinary civil litigation the rule is that, special reasons apart, costs follow the event: that is, the loser pays. The corollary of this rule is that the loser does not get his costs paid. But, like many other rules, this one has its exceptions. For example, the Court of Chancery developed special rules about costs in relation to disputes involving trusts. The position is that if a trustee seeks advice from the court as regards how the trust instrument should be interpreted, or how the trust should be administered, to enable him to properly to execute his duties he will have his costs paid out of the trust estate: In re Beddoe; Downes v Cottam [1893] 1 Ch D 547 ; In re Buckton; Buckton v Buckton [1907] 2 Ch D 406. Those rules apply to beneficiaries who bring an action for the benefit of the trust estate: McDonald v Horn [1995] ICR 685 ; Laws v National Grid Plc [1998] PLR 295 ; In the Matter of the British Airways Pension Schemes [2000] PLR 311. They have been extended to cover actions brought by other fiduciaries, such as liquidators, receivers and administrators: Australian Securities and Investments Commission, in the matter of GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) v GDK Financial Solutions Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 4) [2008] FCA 858. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
</legistitles>
</case>