<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Futuretronics.com.au Pty Limited v Graphix Labels Pty Ltd (No 3) [2008] FCA 896 (12 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/896.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">infringement of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">compensatory damages pursuant to s 115(2) copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">methods of measuring damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">no economic loss established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">no injury to reputation established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">nominal damages awarded to vindicate invasion of proprietary right copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">infringement of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">additional damages pursuant to s 115(4) copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">matters to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">not preconditions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">meaning of "flagrancy of infringement"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">second respondent knew or was wilfully blind to fact that he should not have used artworks as he did</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">flagrant infringement copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">infringement of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">additional damages pursuant to s 115(4) copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">conduct after infringement or after respondents informed they had allegedly infringed applicant's copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">conduct in relation to defence of proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">such conduct relevant to costs and not to additional damages contract law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">breach of implied term</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">no damage established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 746">nominal damages awarded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">identification of terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">implied terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where applicant company marketed for sale "skins"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where applicant arranged for first respondent company to manufacture skins</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where no agreement as to price</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where no agreement as to minimum term or quantity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where first respondent subsequently manufactured and marketed skins for itself in competition with applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether informal contract between applicant and first respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether implied term of any contract that first respondent would not manufacture skins except to supply applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where alleged implied term unlimited as to time and circumstances of operation held: no binding contract except upon the placing of an actual order by the applicant and acceptance of the order by the first respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">not necessary for the reasonable or effective operation of contract to imply term intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where skins product bore artwork</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where copyright in artwork owned by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where first respondent licensed to reproduce artwork pursuant to arrangement to manufacture skins for applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where first respondent reproduced artwork in brochure for its own use</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where first respondent gave spares of skins product bearing artwork to third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether reproduction of artwork a breach of copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.19" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether giving of spare product a breach of copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.20" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether breach of implied term of license that first respondent not to use artwork or spare product except for the purposes authorised by applicant held: reproduction of artwork in brochure breach of copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.21" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">giving spare product to third party did not breach copyright act 1968 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.22" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">giving spare product to third party breach of implied term of license employment law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.23" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">duties of employee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.24" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent employee of first respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.25" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent former employee of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.26" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where confidentiality agreement between second respondent and applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.27" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent arranged future employment with first respondent while employed by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.28" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent, while still employed by applicant, emailed first respondent regarding future plans for forthcoming employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.29" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent, after cessation of employment with applicant, pursued business opportunity to sell skins product to customer of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.30" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where second respondent, after cessation of employment with first respondent, disclosed to third party name of applicant's supplier</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.31" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether second respondent breached contract of employment with applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.32" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether second respondent breached confidentiality agreement with applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.33" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether second respondent breached fiduciary duties owed to applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.34" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether second respondent breached employee's duties under s 182 or s 183 corporations act 2001 (cth) held: email communications from second respondent to first respondent while still employed by applicant did not reveal confidential information nor contain any business opportunity diverted from applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.35" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">no evidence that applicant company time misused by second respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.36" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">email communications did not constitute breach of contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.37" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">email communications did not constitute breach of confidentiality agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.38" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">email communications did not constitute breach of fiduciary duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.39" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">email communications did not constitute breach of corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.40" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">business opportunity pursued was not business opportunity open to applicant while second respondent employed by applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.41" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">second respondent did not use confidential information in pursuit of business opportunity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.42" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">second respondent did not deliberately memorise the name of the customer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.43" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">second respondent entitled to use know-how obtained in course of former employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.44" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">name of customer within know-how since not deliberately copied or memorised</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.45" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">second respondent's pursuit of business opportunity did not breach confidentiality agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.46" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">pursuit of business opportunity did not breach fiduciary duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.47" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">pursuit of business opportunity did not breach corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.48" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">name of applicant's supplier not confidential at common law or in equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.49" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">disclosure of name of supplier did not breach fiduciary duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.50" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">disclosure of name of supplier did not breach corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.51" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">applicant failed to prove that name of supplier was not generally known outside the company or generally known</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.52" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">name of supplier not confidential within the confidentiality agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.53" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">disclosure of name of supplier did not breach confidentiality agreement practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.54" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.55" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">privilege against self-exposure to penalty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.56" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">application to amend application and statement of claim on first day of trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.57" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where pre-trial discovery and production made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.58" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where amendments introduce new causes of action against respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.59" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where new causes of action include breach of civil penalty provision of corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.60" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where new causes of action pleaded on basis of documents discovered and produced pre-trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.61" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where amendments opposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.62" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">where respondents allege that production of documents would have been resisted on grounds of privilege against self-exposure to penalty had breaches of corporations act 2001 (cth) been pleaded initially</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.63" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">whether amendments should be allowed held: privilege against self-exposure to penalty arises because answers or documents tending to expose a person to a penalty are sought, not because proceedings exposing a person to a penalty are commenced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.64" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">respondents had opportunity to claim privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.65" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">privilege waived</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.66" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1621">amendments allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 844">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 844">applicant recovered less than $100,000</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 844">application to recover costs in full</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 844">applicable principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">"one-third off" rule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">where the court has found breach of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">whether proceedings could more suitably have been brought in another court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">where a small amount of damages is claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1371">where an injunction is also sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">review of decision of taxing officer pursuant to federal court rules o62 r44(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">rules providing for payment into court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">consent orders for payment out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">whether constitute an "awarded judgment"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">copyright action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">whether proceedings could have been more suitably brought in another jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">"one-third off" rule : o62 r36a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1994] FCA 1353">costs of counsel attending mediation.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">application that respondent's costs of certain issues be paid on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">discussion of applicable principles.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">discretion of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">award on solicitor and client' or indemnity' basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">whether application vexatious</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">form of order.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 913">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 913">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 913">award on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 913">conduct of party in litigation unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 913">failure to comply with court orders and re-litigation of issues without additional material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">1 the for the judgment should read: intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">infringement of trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">respondent imported mobile phones bearing 'nokia' trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">mobile phones seized by customs before reaching market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">consent judgment declaring importation an infringement but not otherwise dealing with applicant's allegations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">assessment of damages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">no evidence of loss suffered by infringing conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">nominal damages awarded. costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">proceeding in which injunctions, declarations and orders for delivery up made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">damages also claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">nominal damages only awarded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.11" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">whether appropriate that successful applicant's costs not be reduced by one-third</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.12" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 20">federal court rules , o 62 r 36a.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 913">It is true that this claim could, theoretically, have been brought in the Federal Magistrates Court. This is because s 131D of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) gives that Court jurisdiction in civil proceedings arising under that Act which would have included this case. However, the complexity of copyright proceedings is such that the general position has been that claims under it are properly commenced in this Court. The current case involved the question of the joinder of the foreign copyright owner, injunctive relief, an account of profits and infringement. To my mind it would have been unrealistic to have expected such a case to be conducted before the Federal Magistrates Court. That conclusion is consistent with a line of cases which confirm the appropriateness of this Court as a venue for copyright disputes: see the authorities collected by Besanko J in Futuretronics.com.au Pty Ltd v Graphix Labels Pty Ltd (No 3) [2008] FCA 896 at [11] - [13]. In those circumstances it is appropriate to make an order that O 62 r 36A(1) does not apply to these proceedings. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 20">25 In Sony , which was also a trade marks case, Emmett J said ([2001] FCA 1852 at [15]):
 The amount of damages that I propose to order is well below $100,000. However, as I have indicated, the principal relief sought in these proceedings was injunctive relief. The applicants have been successful in their claims for injunctive relief. Having regard to the technicalities that are involved in the Trade Marks Act 1995 , it is appropriate that claims for infringement of trade marks be brought in the Federal Court. The Federal Court has experience and expertise in dealing with matters involving intellectual property generally and trade mark infringement in particular. In Futuretronics (No 3) , which was a copyright and contract case, Besanko J said ([2008] FCA 896 at [12]):
 For a number of years this Court has taken the view that copyright litigation is appropriately commenced in this Court even if the monetary claim is small. I refer to LED Builders Pty Ltd v Hope [1994] FCA 1353 ; (1994) 53 FCR 10 , Fasold v Roberts (unreported, Sackville J, 11 September 1997 MG942 of 1992), Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Pashalidis [2000] FCA 1815 and Australian Performing Right Association Ltd v Metro on George Pty Ltd [2004] FCA 1371 ; (2004) 64 IPR 57.  24 Against the prospect that I might make an award of damages in a sum less than $100,000, the applicant sought an order avoiding the operation of O 62 r 36A of the Federal Court Rules . It was submitted that "this is an appropriate course in relation to matters involving infringement of intellectual property rights", in which respect the applicant relied upon Sony and upon Futuretronics.com.au Pty Ltd v Graphix Labels Pty Ltd (No 3) [2008] FCA 896. Rule 36A provides as follows:
 
 
 (1) Where a party is awarded judgment for less than $100,000 on a claim (not including a cross-claim) for a money sum or damages any costs ordered to be paid, including disbursements, will be reduced by one-third of the amount otherwise allowable under this Order unless the Court or a Judge otherwise orders. 
 
 
 
 (2) If the Court or a Judge is of the opinion that a proceeding (including a cross-claim for a money sum or damages) brought in this Court could more suitably have been brought in another court or in a tribunal and so declares, then any costs to be paid, including disbursements, will be reduced by one-third of the amount otherwise allowable under this Order. 
 
 (3) This rule does not apply to a proceeding under the Admiralty Act 1988 . </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMIRALTY ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l1">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 </title>
<title id="l2">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 36 Infringement by doing acts comprised in the copyright</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>