<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Billy Patch and Others on behalf of the Birriliburu People v State of Western Australia [2008] FCA 944 (20 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/944.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">consent determination of native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">whether determination should be made pursuant to s 87 or s 87a of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">statutory preconditions of s 87a and s 87 satisfied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">appropriate to make the orders sought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1025">orders made pursuant to s 87a or, in the alternative, s 87a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">consent determination covering part of the area of the native title determination application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">proposed native title holder group different from description of native title claim group in application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">whether proceedings affected by possible defect in authorisation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">whether order should be made pursuant to s 84d(4)(b) of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">whether determination should be made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">requirements of s 87</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">whether proposed consent determination within power and appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">statutory preconditions of s 87 satisfied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 518">appropriate to make orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">native title</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">consent determination covering part of the area of the native title determination application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">proposed native title holder group different from description of native title claim group in application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">whether proceedings affected by possible defect in authorisation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">whether order should be made pursuant to s 84d(4)(b) of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">whether determination should be made pursuant to s 87 or s 87a of the native title act 1993 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">requirements of s 87a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">whether proposed consent determination within power and appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">statutory preconditions of s 87a satisfied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 516">appropriate to make orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1334">first schedule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1334">description of the determination area</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 518">The Wanjina-Wunggurr Dambimangari Application has not been further amended since leave was granted on 27 April 1999. The description of the native title claimant group in the application includes some, but not all, of the members of the Wanjina-Wunggurr Community in Schedule 9 of the determination made by Sundberg J in Neowarra [2004] FCA 1092. The difference is that the Wanjina-Wunggurr Dambimangari claimant group description omits to mention the names of the apical ancestors included in the first and second sections of Schedule 9 of the Wanjina-Wunggurr Willinggin determination. In these circumstances, the Court is not limited to making a determination in the form sought in the application and could proceed to make a determination in such form as it sees fit based on the evidence, provided the application is valid: Patch v Western Australia [2008] FCA 944 at [18] . The parties contend that I should make my determination referable to an expanded native title claimant group. I consider this to be appropriate in the circumstances. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCA 516">The Wanjina-Wunggurr Uunguu Application has not been further amended since leave was granted on 23 May 2000. The description of the native title claimant group in the application is close to, but not identical with, the reference to the members of the Wanjina-Wunggurr Community referred to in Schedule 9 of the determination made by Sundberg J in Neowarra [2004] FCA 1092. The difference is that the claimant group description in the Wanjina-Wunggurr Uunguu Application omits to mention the names of 13 apical ancestors included in the second section of Schedule 9 of the Wanjina-Wunggurr Willinggin determination. In these circumstances, the Court is not limited to making a determination in the form sought in the application and may proceed to make a determination in such form as it sees fit based on the evidence, provided the application is valid: Patch v Western Australia [2008] FCA 944 at [18] . The parties contend that I should make my determination referable to an expanded native title claimant group. I consider this to be appropriate in the circumstances. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 1334">A similar situation where the final description of the native title holders was altered between application and determination arose in Billy Patch and Others on behalf of the Birriliburu People v State of Western Australia [2008] FCA 944. French J at [18] accepted the submission of the parties that, provided the application is valid, the Court may proceed to make a determination in such form as it sees fit based on the evidence. The parties to this proceeding make a similar submission in relation to this case. I accept that submission.  In assessing the appropriateness of a proposed determination the Court is not required to undertake an inquiry into the merits of the claim: Billy Patch and Others on behalf of the Birriliburu People v State of Western Australia [2008] FCA 944 at [13] per French J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCA 358">
For a brief period, s 87(1)(d) was inserted into the NT Act to provide that the Court could not make an order under s 87 unless satisfied that an order in, or consistent with, the terms of an agreement could not be made as a consent determination under s 87A. It was introduced by the Native Title Amendment Act 2007 (Cth) and repealed by the Native Title Amendment (Technical Amendments) Act 2007 (Cth), and so in force between 15 April 2007 and 21 July 2007: see the discussion by French J in Billy Patch and Others on behalf of the Birriliburu People v State of Western Australia [2008] FCA 944 at [7] . As there discussed, the benefit of an order under s 87A --- in addition to the facilitation of it by requiring the consent of those whose interests are only directly affected --- is twofold. The claim area is automatically amended, so that the unresolved area remains as the claim area: s 64(1B), and secondly the claim as so amended does not have to go back through the registration test: s 190A(1A), and the claim as amended remains registered: s 190(3)(a)(iii). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 </title>
<title id="l1">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 1 Short title [see Note 1]</title>
<title id="l2">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 2 Commencement [see Note 1]</title>
<title id="l3">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 23C Confirmation of extinguishment of native title by previous exclusive possession acts of Commonwealth</title>
<title id="l4">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 47 Pastoral leases held by native title claimants</title>
<title id="l5">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 47A Reserves etc. covered by claimant applications</title>
<title id="l6">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 47B Vacant Crown land covered by claimant applications</title>
<title id="l7">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 56 Determination whether native title to be held in trust</title>
<title id="l8">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 57 Determination of prescribed body corporate etc.</title>
<title id="l9">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 61A Restrictions on making of certain applications</title>
<title id="l10">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 87A Power of Federal Court to make determination for part of an area</title>
<title id="l11">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 94A Order containing determination of native title</title>
<title id="l12">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 225 Determination of native title</title>
<title id="l13">NATIVE TITLE ACT 1993 - SECT 251D Land or waters on which a public work is constructed, established or situated</title>
<title id="l14">NATIVE TITLE AMENDMENT ACT 1998 </title>
<title id="l15">NATIVE TITLE AMENDMENT ACT 2007 </title>
<title id="l16">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l17">AUSTRALIAN TELECOMMUNICATIONS CORPORATION ACT 1989 </title>
<title id="l18">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l19">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l20">LAND ADMINISTRATION ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l21">LAND ADMINISTRATION ACT 1997 - SECT 46 </title>
<title id="l22">MINING ACT 1978 </title>
<title id="l23">TITLES (VALIDATION) AND NATIVE TITLE (EFFECT OF PAST ACTS) ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l24">TITLES (VALIDATION) AND NATIVE TITLE (EFFECT OF PAST ACTS) ACT 1995 - SECT 12I </title>
<title id="l25">TITLES (VALIDATION) AND NATIVE TITLE (EFFECT OF PAST ACTS) ACT 1995 - SECT 12J </title>
<title id="l26">TITLES (VALIDATION) AND NATIVE TITLE (EFFECT OF PAST ACTS) ACT 1995 - SECT 14 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>