<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Securities &amp; Investments Commission v Oxford Investments (Tasmania) Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 980 (30 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/980.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2005] QSC 324">australian securities and investments act 2001 (cth);</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">5</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">8, 12</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">15 may, 10</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">12, 16</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">19 june, 4, 5 &amp; 14 august, 1</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">2, 4</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=citing from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">5 &amp; 25 september 2008</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2008] NSWSC 1224">358 The questions are, first, whether the statements made by Mr Goulding and Mr Geagea contained a recommendation or statement of opinion and, secondly, whether that recommendation and statement of opinion was intended to influence a person in making a decision in relation to a particular financial product or could reasonably be regarded as having been intended to have such an influence. As to the second of these propositions, I have little trouble in inferring that the statements were made with the intention to influence persons to make particular decisions and they could certainly be regarded as having been intended to have such an influence. It is perhaps a nicer question as to whether what was said could be characterised as a recommendation or a statement of opinion. There do not seem to be decisions that are directly on point in the context of this provision. However, it does seem to me that there are decisions that endorse the taking of a practical and substantive approach to legislative provisions of this type. They include the decisions of Carnwath J (as his Lordship then was) in the Chancery Division of the High Court of Justice in Re Market Wizard Systems (UK) Ltd [1998] 2 BCLC 282 ; of Moynihan J in the Supreme Court of Queensland in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Online Investors Advantage Incorporated (2005) 194 FLR 449 ; and of Heerey J in the Federal Court in Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Oxford Investments (Tasmania) Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 980. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 5 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l2">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12BA Interpretation</title>
<title id="l3">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12BAB Meaning of financial service</title>
<title id="l4">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12DA Misleading or deceptive conduct</title>
<title id="l5">AUSTRALIAN SECURITIES AND INVESTMENTS COMMISSION ACT 2001 - SECT 12GH Conduct by directors, employees or agents</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 79 Involvement in contraventions</title>
<title id="l8">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 761A Definitions</title>
<title id="l9">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 761D Meaning of derivative</title>
<title id="l10">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 764A Specific things that are financial products (subject to Subdivision D)</title>
<title id="l11">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 766A When does a person provide a financial service?</title>
<title id="l12">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 766B Meaning of financial product advice</title>
<title id="l13">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 911A Need for an Australian financial services licence</title>
<title id="l14">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 911B Providing financial services on behalf of a person who carries on a financial services business</title>
<title id="l15">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>