<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 (27 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/983.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">body seeking endorsement as a charitable institution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">whether body instituted to promote or advance a charitable purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">body seeking endorsement conducted profitable commercial activities and directed profits towards advancement of religion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">necessity to examine the purpose of the body's formation, its constitution and activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">importance of subjective motivations of directors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">whether body pursued its objectives principally in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 171">profits donated for overseas evangelisation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">central bayside general practice association limited v commissioner of state revenue  taxation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">charities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">pay-roll tax exemption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">meaning of "charitable body"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">whether privately-established non-profit organisation is a "charitable body" for purposes of pay-roll tax exemption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">whether organisation precluded from being characterised as "charitable body" because of its relationship with commonwealth government</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] HCA 43">whether involvement in implementation of government policy precludes organisation from being characterised as "charitable body".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">gattellaro v westpac banking corporation  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">judicial notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">whether judicial notice can be taken that institutions such as the respondent use a standard form of guarantee.  guarantee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">consequence of person named as co-surety not being shown to have executed guarantee.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">high court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">determination of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">appellants' ground of appeal succeeds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">notice of contention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">whether respondent should have leave to amend contentions sought in motion filed immediately before appeal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 6">whether outstanding issues should be determined in intermediate appellate court.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1998] AATA 333">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1998] AATA 333">exempt income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1998] AATA 333">whether a society, association or club established for community service purposes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1998] AATA 333">whether society, association or club established for political purposes or lobbying purposes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1998] AATA 333">association of women's organisations with some individual members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">exempt income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">charitable institution</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">body publishing law reports not for profit of members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">income tax and social services contribution assessment act 1936-1962 (cth), s. 26 (e).  charities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">charitable purposes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1971] HCA 44">body publishing law reports otherwise than for profit of members.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 42">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 42">s 50-10 of the income tax assessment act 1997 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 42">whether entity established to facilitate face-to-face banking services in rural town without face-to-face banking services was established for "community service purposes"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">exemption</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">not-for-profit corporation established to facilitate the provision of face-to-face banking services in a rural town lacking such a service</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">whether established for "community service purposes"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">s 50-10 income tax assessment act 1997 (cth)  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">judicial notice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">non-local geographical location</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 862">published map</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">association of public health providers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">fringe benefits tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">whether rebatable employer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">whether exempt from income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 473">whether established for community service purposes.  fringe benefits tax assessment act 1986 s 65j(1)(j)  income tax assessment act 1997 s 50-10, 50-70</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">trusts and trustees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">charitable trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">schemes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">administrative scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">where plaintiff holds property upon constructive charitable trust and no trust instrument</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">where plaintiff seeks an order that the trust be administered in accordance with an administrative scheme</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">whether purposes of remain charitable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">where scheme will facilitate commercial dealings of trustee and permit winding up of trust and transfer of assets to corporation for same charitable purposes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=citing from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">held: trust to be administered in accordance with administrative scheme.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">power of a partner to bind the partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">determining the "business of the kind carried on by the firm" for the purpose of s 5 partnership act 1892</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether "business of the kind carried on by the firm" is necessarily the business actually carried on by the partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">meaning of "the usual way" in which the business is carried on</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether a judge can inform themselves using "common sense" of the business ordinarily carried on by a type of partnership firm</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">role of judicial notice in deciding this</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.9" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.10" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">power of a partner to bind the partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.11" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">ostensible authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.12" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether the ostensible authority of a partner is limited to what is necessary to carry on the partnership business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.13" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">distinction between what is necessary to carry out a particular task and what is necessary to carry out the business of the partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.14" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.15" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">partners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.16" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">relevance of registration under business names act 1962 to proof of identity of partners</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.17" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">difference between statutory facilitation of proof of identity of partners under business names act 1962 and business names act 2002</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.18" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">appeal and new trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.19" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.20" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">general principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.21" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">interference with judge's findings of fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.22" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">limitations on an appellate court's ability to assess the evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.23" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">limitations extending beyond the trial judge's assessments of demeanour</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.24" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">advantages of a trial judge in weighing the account of a witness against contemporaneous documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.25" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.26" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">general contractual principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.27" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.28" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">identification of parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.29" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether an objective bystander would conclude that a party to the contract was purporting to act on behalf of the partnership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.30" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">contracts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.31" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">general contractual principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.32" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">formation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.33" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether a party can be held to an improbable promise where another party believes that the fulfilment of the promise was possible</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.34" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether such a contract can exist</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.35" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.36" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">witnesses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.37" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">failure to call</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.38" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">inferences to be drawn</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.39" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">whether a jones v dunkel inference is open on the facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.40" type=citing from="[2009] NSWCA 240">no requirement for the trial judge to draw an adverse inference</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCAFC 42">The trial judge identified the following principles as presently relevant: The kind of community service referred to in s 50-10 is a practical or tangible help, benefit or advantage conferred on the community or an identifiable section thereof: Navy Health Ltd v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2007] FCA 931 ; (2007) 163 FCR 1 at [83] and [84]; Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; (2008) 170 FCR 318 at [163] and [164]. A service provided for reward is not a community service, at least where there is no element of subsidisation: Navy Health at [83]. Community service purposes include the purpose of providing a community service, although the purposes contemplated are not limited solely to the act of provision.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 862">Subject to one matter, which I return below, this accords not only with the ordinary meaning of the word "service" but also with the reference in the explanatory memorandum to activities, facilities and projects all of which suggest that the assistance to be rendered is practical, tangible or real. The only other judge to have examined the question in any detail apart from Jessup J is French J in Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; (2008) 170 FCR 318. Although his Honour did not need to reach a concluded view he did say (170 FCR at 355 [163]-[164]): 
 
 The concept of "community service" does seem to import the notion of the delivery of some practical "help, benefit or advantage" in the sense used by Jessup J. That criterion is not necessarily met by an organisation whose purpose is to change practices and attitudes in such a way as to facilitate the entry and advancement of women within the profession generally. 
 

 
 
 The matter is not without difficulty and it is unnecessary to reach a concluded position on it. It is sufficient unto the day that I have found that VWL is a charitable institution, that it attracts the relevant exemption and that its appeals must therefore be allowed. 
 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] AATA 473">Such a requirement, I consider, is not satisfied merely because, in this case, the operations of the applicant had a tendency to promote the efficiency of the armed forces, thereby benefiting the community as a whole. 
 

 
 
 14. In Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2008) FCA 983 , French J noted that an organisation may be beneficial to the community without delivering a "community service" in the sense contemplated by that term as explained in the Explanatory Memorandum. His Honour thought that the concept of "community service" imported the notion of the delivery of some practical help, benefit or advantage in the sense used by Jessup J in the passage first extracted above and went on to observe that [t]hat criterion is not necessarily met by an organisation whose purpose is to change practices and attitudes in such a way as to facilitate the entry and advancement of women within the profession generally. 
 

15.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] HCATrans 154">Your Honour Justice French dealt with it in Victorian Women Lawyers' Association v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; (2008) 170 FCR 318 at paragraphs 127 to 129.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] NSWSC 1474">4 It is well established that the advancement of education is one of the recognised categories of charity [see Commissioners for Special Purpose of Income Tax v Pemsel [1891] UKHL 1 ; [1891] AC 531 , 583], and that the provision of education for lawyers, including their professional development and advancement, is within that category [see Incorporated Council of Law Reporting of (Queensland) v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [1971] HCA 44 ; (1971) 125 CLR 659 ; [1972] ALR 127 ; and College of Law (Properties) v Willoughby Municipal Council ] . That the institution conducts business and commercial activities does not deprive it of its charitable character, so long as those activities are associated with or ancillary to the charitable purpose [see for example Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; (2008) 250 ALR 516 , [130] - [132]; Commissioner of Taxation v Word Investments Ltd (2007) 243 ALR 44 , [22] - [24]]. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2009] NSWCA 240">273 French J (as his Honour then was) noticed, but did not decide the difference of opinion in Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Federal Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; (2008) 170 FCR 318 at 345 [114] - [115]. Nor does the argument in the present case make it necessary to decide it here.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2008] HCA 55">[158] Thus charities favourable to the professional interests of lawyers have often been well received. For example, charities concerned with the law, including law reporting and women lawyers' interests, have generally enjoyed a favourable response. See, for example, Incorporated Council of Law Reporting [1971] HCA 44 ; (1971) 125 CLR 659 and Victorian Women Lawyers' Association Inc v Commissioner of Taxation [2008] FCA 983 ; [2008] ATC 20-035. [159] The Industry Commission Report. See above, these reasons at [118].</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT </title>
<title id="l1">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - CLAUSE 5 Operation of the Constitution and laws [see Note 3]</title>
<title id="l2">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 10 Application of State laws</title>
<title id="l3">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 23 Voting in the Senate</title>
<title id="l4">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 50 Rules and orders</title>
<title id="l5">COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA CONSTITUTION ACT - SECT 118 Recognition of laws etc. of States</title>
<title id="l6">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l7">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 144 Matters of common knowledge</title>
<title id="l8">INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT ACT 1936 </title>
<title id="l9">INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l10">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 </title>
<title id="l11">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 3 Objects</title>
<title id="l12">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 4A Meaning of family responsibilities</title>
<title id="l13">SEX DISCRIMINATION ACT 1984 - SECT 14 Discrimination in employment or in superannuation</title>
<title id="l14">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 </title>
<title id="l15">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l16">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l17">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 144 Matters of common knowledge</title>
</legistitles>
</case>