<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (in Liq) v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd (includes corrigendum dated 30 June 2008) [2008] FCA 927 (19 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/927.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">application to bring proceedings on behalf of company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">statutory derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">whether applicant acting in good faith in bringing proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">whether in the best interests of the company that applicant be granted leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">whether statutory derivative action available in circumstances of liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">statutory interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2008] NSWCA 52">reading down a defined term in relation to a particular part of the legislative scheme.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">assignment of legal rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">company a previously claimed relief against respondent in supreme court of queensland under trade practices act and in tort and equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">action dismissed by supreme court for non-compliance with directions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">applicant commenced present proceeding claiming to be assignee of company c which allegedly was assignee of claims from a under assignment dated 1 june 2002</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">a ordered to be wound up on 10 march 2003</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">whether first assignment in truth effected before winding up order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">whether assignment effective in law to assign claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1532">trial of separate question</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">statutory derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">application for leave under s 237 of the corporations act 2001 (cth) to bring an action in the name of a company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">whether pt 2f.1a of the act has application when company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 586">whether in the best interests of company that leave be granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">application to amend pleadings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">capacity of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">acts as trustee rather than on its own behalf</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">leave to amend granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">whether "otherwise order" provision of o 13 r 3a applies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">amendment pre-dates expiry of limitation period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">application to substitute applicant for incoming trustee pursuant to o 6 r 10(2) and o 6 r 11(1)(d)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">substitution or addition of party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">interest or liability not yet passed to incoming trustee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1437">leave refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 317">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 317">corporations act 2001 (cth) part 2f.1a , s. 237</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 317">application by shareholder in a company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 317">leave may be given to bring proceedings pursuant to s237 where company is in liquidation in extraordinary circumstances.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">application for leave to bring proceedings on behalf of company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">statutory jurisdiction applicable to companies generally</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">inherent power of court in relation to companies in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">relevant criteria discussed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">position of liquidator qua costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1007">protection of insolvent company against costs consequences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">duties of directors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">whether director owes comprehensive fiduciary duty to individual shareholder</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">no facts pleaded to show ascendancy, influence, vulnerability or reliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">statutory derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">whether available when company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">s.237 criteria</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">meaning of "best interests"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">court's powers as to costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.10" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">possibility of order as to costs (or for security for costs) immediately proceedings brought</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.11" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.12" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">leave to proceed against company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.13" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 745">applicable section where winding up sourced in s.446a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">derivative action to assert company's claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">whether part 2f.1.a of corporations act applies to company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">whether court's inherent power to authorise creditor or contributory to assert rights of company in liquidation survives part 2f.1.a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">whether part 2f.1.a applies where general law derivative action commenced before 13 march 2000</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">discretionary considerations under part 2f.1.a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">application for leave to amend statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">delay and prejudice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">new claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.10" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">limitation of actions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.11" type=cited from="[2003] NSWSC 7">whether amendment with leave relates back to time of filing of summons when no new party is joined</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 822">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 822">statutory derivative action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 822">application in a liquidation situation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 822">scope for the general law assisted by s477(6) and s511 corporations act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 705">company law-winding up-liquidators-exceptions to rule in foss v harbottle</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 705">-contributories motion to bring a derivative cross action and to be permitted to seek leave to set aside a default judgment and to conduct a derivative defence-whether action may be brought or continued or defended by a contributory in the name of company if this is in the interests of justice-whether any such a rule applies to companies in liquidation-considerations applicable to control by the court of company in liquidation-contributory authorised to use companies name as co</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 705">defendant and as cross claimant.acts cited:  corporations act 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 705">sections 236 &amp; 237 decision: application for leave to bring derivative action to be granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[2001] NSWSC 705">short minutes to be brought in.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">liquidation proceedings to assert the company's claim, brought by another person</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">appointment of receiver to bring proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">when appropriate; equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">court-appointed receiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1999] NSWSC 1143">grounds for appointment of receiver to conduct litigation when company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">alleged misleading and deceptive representation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">unassignable right to claim damages under ss.82 and 87 of the trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">loan made on security of second mortgage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">whether reliance upon negligent valuation of property development</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">whether duty to disclose information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 286">duty of mortgagee to ascertain value when exercising power of sale.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">joinder of third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">application by third party to be joined to the proceeding on the basis of a purported assignment of certain choses in action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">application by contributory for court to give leave under its implied power to permit proceeding to be brought on behalf of company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">exercise of implied power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">relevant factors  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">application of ss 236 and 237 when company in liquidation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">application by a contributory for leave to continue proceeding in the name of the company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.10" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">implied power of court to grant leave  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.11" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">assignment not valid basis for joinder</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.12" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">exercise of implied power not appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.13" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 35">ss 236 and 237 not operable where company in liquidation.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">duties of a "controller" under s 420a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">whether duties breached</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">assignment of statutory cause of action   mortgages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">duties of mortgagee in possession</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">whether duties breached</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">adoption of proper process of sale</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">equitable and statutory remedies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">assignment of cause of action and remedies available</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 773">taking account on wilful default</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 35">The Court does have power in the course of a winding up of a company to permit proceedings to be brought on behalf of that company by a creditor or a member. Although it has been described as a power in the Court's inherent jurisdiction, in this Court it would be an implied power rather than an inherent power: Jackson v Sterling Industries Ltd [1987] HCA 23 ; (1987) 162 CLR 612 at 630. Although in the ordinary case it is the liquidator who has the authority to prosecute a proceeding in a Court, the Courts have held that there is a residual power in the Court to authorise members or creditors to conduct litigation in the name of the company: Cape Breton v Fenn (1881) 17 Ch D 198 ; Aliprandi v Griffith Vintners Pty Ltd (In Liq) (1991) 6 ACSR 250 ; Russell v Westpac Banking Corporation [1994] SASC 4479 ; (1994) 61 SASR 583 ; Carpenter v Pioneer Park Pty Ltd [2008] NSWSC 551 ; (2008) 71 NSWLR 577 ; Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; 249 ALR 591. In Cape Breton v Fenn 17 Ch D 198 , it was said that the principle is akin to the right of a beneficiary under a trust to bring a suit to recover trust property where the trustee neglects or refuses to do so.  The causes of action relied upon by the applicant in this case include contraventions of the Trade Practices Act, breaches of fiduciary duty and breaches of contract. EGR accepted on this application that the causes of action arising out of s 82 of the Trade Practices Act are personal and cannot be assigned: Salfinger v Niugini Mining (Australia) Pty Ltd (No 3) [2007] FCA 1532 ; Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (in liq) v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; 249 ALR 591. During argument, counsel accepted as the amended notice of motion is framed that the assignment could, if valid, only be effective in assigning any cause of action or chose in action in contract. It follows therefore that if the assignment were valid EGR could only prosecute that part of the proceedings relating to a claim of breach of contract and leave to the applicant to prosecute the cause of action under the Trade Practices Act and in equity.  Mr Hoile argued that the orders sought should be made even if the assignments were not valid or ineffective. EGR contended that this Court retained an inherent power to permit proceedings to be taken in the name of a company by its contributories and creditors and relied upon a decision of Gilmour J in Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (in liq) v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; 249 ALR 591.  There was no objection by the respondents or the applicant or counsel for the liquidators. When Mr Hoile sought to amend the notice of motion he announced that his client no longer relied upon s 236 to intervene in the proceedings, accepting that a decision of the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Chahwan v Euphoric Pty Ltd [2008] NSWCA 52 ; (2008) 245 ALR 780 stood for the proposition that s 236 had no operation where the company for which the member seeks to intervene is in liquidation: see also Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (in liq) v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; (2008) 249 ALR 591. Having regard to the decision in Chahwan [2008] NSWCA 52 ; 245 ALR 780 , Mr Hoile was right to abandon any reliance upon s 236. I would have been bound to follow the decision of the Court of Appeal unless I was of the opinion that it was plainly wrong: Australian Securities Commisssion v Marlborough Gold Mines Ltd [1993] HCA 15 ; (1993) 177 CLR 485. Although the point now does not arise for decision, I would have followed the decision in any event because, in my opinion, the decision is right. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] SASC 262">Corporations Act 2001 ss 588FB , 588FDA , 9 ; Supreme Court Rules 2006 (SA) r 232, referred to. Ceneavenue Pty Ltd &amp; Ors v Martin &amp; Ors (2008) 67 ACSR 130 ; [2008] SASC 158 , applied. Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (In liq) &amp; Anor v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; (2008) 249 ALR 591 ; Lewis (as liquidator of Doran Constructions Pty Ltd (in liq)) &amp; Anor v Doran &amp; Ors 219 ALR 555 ; [2005] NSWCA 243 ; Law of Company Liquidation McPherson, 5th ed, considered. STRAZDINS &amp; COOPER (AS LIQUIDATORS OF THE SMART COMPANY P/L (IN LIQ)) v TOMAZOU &amp; ENTERPRISE GLOBAL RESOURCES P/L 
 [2010] SASC 262 
 
 JUDGE WITHERS . By summons and statement of claim filed on 18 June 2010 The Smart Company Pty Ltd (In Liquidation) ACN 061 975 344, Andre Janis Strazdins and Nicholas David Cooper sought orders against Dorothea Tomazou by way of declaration that a Deed of Assignment of 6 April 2010 was invalid and void ab initio , alternatively, that it had not been executed properly under s 127 of the Corporations Act 2001 (Cth) ("CA"), and in the further alternative declarations that it was a void transaction pursuant to s 588FE(2) , (3), (4) and (6A) of the CA. Costs were sought on an indemnity basis. It was submitted by the plaintiffs, and accepted by the defendants, that The Smart Company was incapable at law of assigning those statutory causes of action. Reliance was placed on the decision of Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd (In liq) &amp; Anor v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; (2008) 249 ALR 591. I understand there to be no contest about that assertion. Accordingly, at best for the defendants the First Deed of Assignment could assign part only of the chose-in-action. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 773">Mijac submitted that the question of the effect of the assignment was a new question of law not previously pleaded and about which they had no notice. I reject that contention. The question of the effect of assignment is a question of law that cannot be put aside from consideration and moreover, it was one of the questions that the parties agreed required resolution. Turning then to the substantive argument, Mijac sought to rely upon a number of cases where it had been found that certain "personal" causes of action for example, under Pt V of the TPA may be assigned by a liquidator pursuant to s 477(2)(c) of the Corporations Act or by a trustee in bankruptcy pursuant to ss 134(1)(a) and 135(1)(a) of the Bankruptcy Act . That may well be the case. However, as the Respondents correctly submitted, these cases either reinforced or failed to address (as was discussed at [31] to [34] above) the proposition that an assignee will not be able to recover where they themselves have suffered no loss or damage: see Brookfield v Davey Products Pty Ltd (1996) 14 ACLC 303 at 305. Thus, in the circumstances of this case, no remedy is available to Mijac regarding the statutory causes of action. Moreover, s 477(2)(c) of the Law does not permit a statutory cause of action not otherwise assignable to be assigned: Pritchard v Racecage Pty Ltd (1997) 72 FCR 203 at 218-221; UTSA Pty Ltd v Ultra Tune Australia Pty Ltd [1997] 1 VR 667 at 698; Pearl Coast Divers Pty Ltd v Cossack Pearls Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 927 ; (2008) 249 ALR 591 at [6] - [8]. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 2 Commencement [see Note 1]</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 237 Applying for and granting leave</title>
<title id="l3">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 </title>
<title id="l4">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 - SECT 10 Exclusion of liability</title>
<title id="l5">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 </title>
<title id="l6">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 - SECT 10 </title>
<title id="l7">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 - SECT 79 </title>
<title id="l8">FAIR TRADING ACT 1987 - SECT 82 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>