<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Campaign Master (UK) Ltd v Forty Two International Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 979 (27 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/979.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">patrick stevedores operations no 2 pty ltd &amp; ors v  maritime union of australia &amp; ors  high court and federal judiciary</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">power under s 298u of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth) and s 23 of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) to grant interlocutory injunctions to restrict purported termination of labour supply agreements, termination of employment of employees, obtaining stevedoring services, engaging in conduct having the effect of termination employment of employees, and engaging in conduct having the effect of the divestment of assets or dealing with assets otherwise than in the ordinary course of business.  equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">equitable remedies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">mareva injunctions and other interlocutory injunctions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether within jurisdiction of the federal court of australia to grant injunction with the effect of fettering discretion of administrators appointed under pt 5.3a of the corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether effect of such injunction requires company to trade while insolvent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether injunction necessary to prevent frustration of process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether confined to maintaining status quo at the time of making application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether available to protect the subject matter of litigation conferring greater rights than when application made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether serious question to be tried</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether appropriate on balance of convenience</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">effect on third parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">exercise of supervisory jurisdiction.  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">companies</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">management and administration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">appointment of administrators under pt 5.3a of the corporations law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">powers and duties in administration of company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">personal liability in administration of company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">jurisdiction of court fettering discretion of administrators</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">jurisdiction of court to make orders compelling administrators to retain employees and to trade while insolvent contrary to responsibilities under the corporations law.  industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">commonwealth</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">stevedoring industry</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.23" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether restructuring of companies so as to remove assets from employer company with the effect of dismissing, injuring or altering the position of employees by reason of their membership of a union contravenes pt xa of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.24" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">nature of interlocutory injunctive relief available under s 298u of that act. tort</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.25" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">joint or several tortfeasors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.26" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">conspiracy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.27" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether interlocutory injunction an appropriate remedy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.28" type=cited from="[1998] HCA 30">whether interlocutory mandatory injunction an appropriate remedy.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 474">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 474">penalties under part iv of the trade practices act 1974 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 474">statutory injunctions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 474">construction of s. 80 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 474">appropriateness and form of a permanent injunction.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">federal court of australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">injunctions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">consent orders including undertakings about future conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">undertaking extending beyond court's power to restrain conduct by injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss. 45 , 45a, 80 , 86</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 48">federal court of australia act 1976 (cth), ss. 22 , 23 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">whether hearsay evidence of statements by persons overseas should be permitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">the extent to which the proposed evidence was first hand or more remote hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">no independent evidence corroborating any hearsay version</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">whether undue prejudice to the respondent.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">application to take evidence by video link</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">requirement to make out a case for such an order where it is opposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">discussion of the possible difficulties associated with video evidence.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">consideration of application for further security.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCA 1306">On 27 June 2008 I rejected an application by the applicant for interim interlocutory orders ( Campaign Master (UK) Ltd v Forty Two International Pty Ltd [2008] FCA 979). I ordered that the applicant pay the respondents' costs of the notice of motion which sought the interlocutory relief. On 25 July 2008 I rejected an application by the applicant to vary the costs order ( Campaign Master (UK) Ltd v Forty Two International Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 1140). On the same day I directed that a notice of motion filed by the respondent seeking security for costs be heard on 8 August 2008. On 8 August 2008 the parties provided consent orders to the effect that the applicants pay into Court $90,000 as security for the respondent's estimated costs up to and including the filing and service of the respondents' affidavits. By notice of motion filed on 2 September 2009, the respondents have now made an application for increased security for costs. It is clear from s 56 of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) that such a course is within the Court's discretion. It is also clear that the parties' earlier agreement about security for costs left such a course open, although there is an issue about whether any further security should take into account costs already incurred or be limited to security for future costs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2008] FCA 1140">I ordered that the applicant pay the costs of a notice of motion filed on 19 June 2008 ( Campaign Master (UK) Limited v. Forty Two International Pty Limited [2008] FCA 979).</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>