<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Barrett Property Group Pty Ltd v Carlisle Homes Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 930 (17 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/930.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">alleged copyright in substantial part of house plans and built houses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">al fresco quadrant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">subsistence of copyright</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">whether "logical development" of existing plans of third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">whether substantial part</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">whether actual copying</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">significance of lies as to derivation of respondent's design</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 375">whether sufficient similarity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">categories of discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether discovery sought by both parties appropriate given pleadings and prior findings of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether discovery by the applicant at this stage of the proceedings premature</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">affidavit of disclosure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether affidavit of disclosure appropriate in addition to discovery by respondent in circumstances where discovery concerns extent of liability and form and quantum of pecuniary relief.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 485">In its written outline of submissions, Optus submitted that: 
(1) The provision of an affidavit of disclosure in terms of Schedule 'B' (see [19] above) is a conventional course in cases involving the infringement of intellectual property rights and misuse of confidential information. Reference was made to a number of authorities including: LED Builders Pty Ltd v Eagle Homes Pty Ltd (1996) 70 FCR 436 at 451; Dr Martens Australia Pty Ltd v BATA Shoe Company of Australia Pty Ltd (1997) 75 FCR 230 at 235 --- 236; Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] SASC 386 at [7] , [20] and Polyaire Pty Ltd v K-Aire Pty Ltd (No 4) [2007] SASC 36 ; Dias Aluminium Products Pty Ltd v Ullrich Aluminium Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] FCA 1400 ; (2005) 225 ALR 569 at [14] per Crennan J; Barrett Property Group Pty Ltd v Carlisle Homes Pty Ltd (No 2) [2008] FCA 930 ; as well as the orders made by Heerey J in that matter on 28 April 2008; and orders made by Allsop J on 9 November 2007 in proceeding NSD 1089 of 2000 between Doric Productions Pty Ltd and Lockwood Security Products Pty Ltd; Nokia Corporation v Liu [2009] FCAFC 138 ; (2009) 179 FCR 422 at [39] read with [7]. (2) In circumstances such as the present, where the Court has found that Telstra has misused Optus' confidential information, the purpose of the affidavit is to assist Optus to quantify an account of profits. Reference was made to the observation of the Full Court ([2010] FCAFC 21) at [41]: 
 
 
 
 'Optus is entitled to make an informed election between damages for breach of clause 15 and an account of profits.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>