<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Direct Share Purchasing Corporation Pty Ltd v AXA Asia Pacific Holdings Ltd [2008] FCA 935 (19 June 2008)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2008/935.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">register of members</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">request for copy of register under s 173(3) corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">fee for providing electronic copy of register</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">"a reasonable amount that does not exceed the marginal cost to the company of providing a copy"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">register maintained by agent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">marginal cost to company substantially higher than marginal cost to agent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 15">whether amount charged reasonable</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] FCAFC 15">25 The primary judge found that the marginal cost to Computershare of providing a copy of AXA's register was "not great" but that the marginal cost to AXA was "substantial" (see Direct Share Purchasing Corporation Pty Ltd v AXA Asia Pacific Holdings Ltd [2008] FCA 935 ; (2008) 67 ACSR 99 at [17] ). His Honour considered that the marginal cost to Computershare of producing a copy of the register on CD Rom was less than $100 but that the marginal cost to AXA was in excess of $17,195.39 (at [20]), notwithstanding that AXA did nothing more than receive the CD Rom from Computershare and give it to Direct.  46 It is of course true that a "reasonable amount" need not be the "lowest possible price" (see Fung [2006] NSWSC 1345 ; (2007) 14 ANZ Ins Cas 61-730). However, the learned primary judge did not fall into the error of finding that it had to be. Rather, his Honour held that the fee had to have been negotiated in circumstances where AXA was attempting to secure the lowest possible price ( Direct [2008] FCA 935 ; (2008) 67 ACSR 99 at [22] ). It is a fundamental principle of tort law that the plaintiff is entitled to be restored, so far as money can, to the position he was in before the defendant's negligence ( Fung [2006] NSWSC 1345 ; (2007) 14 ANZ Ins Cas 61-730 at [11] ), however there is no such overriding principle in the context of s 173 of the Act.  27 The primary judge considered that, in determining what constitutes a "reasonable amount" to charge for a copy of the register, ordinarily one would begin by examining the market price for CD Roms containing a register. However, his Honour found that there was no evidence of any market for the supply of such a product ( Direct [2008] FCA 935 ; (2008) 67 ACSR 99 at [21] ). AXA challenged that conclusion on the appeal. His Honour also considered that, in the absence of a market price, the price paid by the supplier of a product can be a useful guide as to what is a reasonable fee. However, his Honour considered that that price would "only be useful if it were arrived at in negotiations where the supplier was attempting to purchase the product at the lowest possible price" (at [22]). AXA contended that his Honour erred in so concluding and that negotiation for the lowest possible price is not the relevant criterion. AXA contended that the only relevant limitation is one designed to counter extravagance or unreasonableness: see Fung v Stocovaz [2006] NSWSC 1345 ; (2007) 14 ANZ Ins Cas 61-730 at [38] .</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 152 Reserving a name</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 154 Exception to requirement to have ACN on receipts</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 173 Right to inspect and get copies</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 174 Agent's obligations</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 177 Use of information on registers</title>
<title id="l6">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1306 Form and evidentiary value of books</title>
<title id="l7">CORPORATIONS REGULATIONS 2001 </title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>