<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Media Ocean Limited v Optus Mobile Pty Limited (No 6) [2009] FCA 1319 (5 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1319.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">amendment of pleading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">action for damages for medical negligence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">inadequate post-operative care</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">hearing adjourned part-heard after two days</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">plaintiff qualifying further expert witness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">application to amend to allege negligent performance of surgery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">court procedures rules 2006 , rr 21, 502, 503</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">whether fresh cause of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">principles to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2011] ACTSC 67">application to amend refused.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] ACTSC 67">59. I have been taken by counsel in submissions to subsequent decisions in which these principles have been applied, including Media Ocean Ltd v Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (No 6) [2009] FCA 1319 per Jagot J; Ginger Roger Pty Ltd v Parrella Enterprises Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCA 128 per Collier J; and in the Court of Appeal of this court, Tran v Calvista Australia Pty Ltd [2010] ACTCA 5. Each case turns on its own facts, and it is for the court to take account of the balancing considerations on each side in determining an application to amend. Consideration of the issues </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] SASCFC 59">There has been much consideration of Aon in later decisions, both at the interlocutory single judge level and at the intermediate court level. There have been in the order of 200 published judgments where Aon has influenced the decision. Although not all of those involve applications to amend pleadings, a substantial number do. In those proceedings, the circumstances surrounding the applications to amend are varied. Unsurprisingly, different results have ensued. Applications to amend raising points of substance, prior to the setting of a date for trial, have almost always without exception, [105] been allowed. [106] Appropriate orders to address prejudice have been made. [107] Applications to amend at or immediately prior to or during trial have often been refused, [108] however, even very late applications to amend have been allowed. [109] </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>