<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited [2009] FCA 1088 (25 September 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1088.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">appeal and new trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">judgment for summary dismissal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">judgment expressed to be by consent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">claim for indemnity under business loss insurance policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">whether interpretation of policy justifying summary judgment open to doubt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">whether judgment truly by consent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">whether substantial injustice for insured to lose claim on policy without right of appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 592">problems caused by attempting to take short cuts in resolving proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1439">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1439">application to further amend statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1439">where the court had previously identified method of pleading causation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1439">whether the applicant properly pleaded causation.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">insurance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">business interruption policy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">indemnity for loss of weekly turnover</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">how calculated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">meaning of "paid or payable"  procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">summary judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">possibility of repleading</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">summary judgment denied  procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">interlocutory application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">when an interlocutory decision can be reconsidered  contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1093">post-contract facts not to be considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">no substantial injustice if leave not granted supposing the decision wrong</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">determination of separate question before trial not appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">mixed question of fact and law not capable of resolution without all relevant facts found or admitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">resolution of separate question would not lead to judgment in favour of insurer as insurer claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">answer to question would not affect evidence to be led at trial and might be reconsidered by the trial judge in light of evidence and other matters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 161">leave to appeal denied</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 592">Following argument on these questions, on 25 September 2009 his Honour published reasons for judgment. See Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited [2009] FCA 1088. The respondent had advanced a method of calculation that involved what it called a notional running account and required calculation over the entire period of loss, with a calculation then to allocate amounts to each week of that period. At [14] of his reasons for judgment, his Honour rejected that construction. His Honour held that, because the requirement of the policy was to pay for each week, the necessary calculation was to be done on a weekly basis and not on the basis of a running account. At [15], his Honour said that there were issues that remained to be resolved at the trial, namely, whether there is a causal connection between the incidents and the loss claimed and whether turnover, and therefore actual average weekly turnover, ought to be calculated by reference to total invoiced sales or cash receipts or a combination of both plus work in progress. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 1439">Under the Policy, the cover provided that "for each week [QBE] will pay [TRS] ... in respect of loss of Turnover". Finkelstein J found at [14] in Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1088 , this meant that the calculations are to be made on a weekly basis. That conclusion was found to be reinforced by a number of aspects of the Policy: the introduction to the Policy which referred to "weekly loss of Turnover"; and where a loss arises, it must be paid within "seven days whenever practicable". 
The Policy provided indemnity for losses incurred on a week by week basis. The issues in this proceeding have been the subject of previous consideration by Finkelstein J and by the Full Court of the Federal Court: see Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited [2009] FCA 1088 , QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited v Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 161 and Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited (No 2) [2010] FCA 1093.  TRS submitted that its formulated claim for loss of turnover had adopted the template set out in the reasons for decision of Finkelstein J at [6] above. QBE opposed TRS being granted leave to further amend its statement of claim to formulate its claim for loss of turnover on the basis that in relation to the second, third and fourth steps, each of the methodologies pleaded by TRS were defective: in relation to what TRS describes as its Primary Methodology , QBE submitted that TRS had not amended its pleading to plead a case which framed the case suggested by Finkelstein J (see [6] above) and, in any event, it was evident from TRS' own materials that it could not properly do so; and as noted earlier (see [6] above) TRS had retained, as its Alternative Methodology , a pleaded case which Finkelstein J decided in Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1088 could not be sustained. 
I will deal with each methodology in turn. Primary Methodology
  A number of matters should be noted about the contents of this Annexure. The Weekly Turnover was based on the value of the invoices issued in each week less the value of the credit notes issued in each week: see paragraphs 3.8 and 3.9 of the Report prepared by Deloitte dated 5 November 2010. The weekly turnover and, therefore, the weekly loss or gain fluctuated widely. In some weeks, (eg week 4), TRS made a substantial gain compared to the average weekly turnover. In other weeks, there was an increased loss compared to the average weekly turnover because TRS had issued credit notes (see, for example, weeks 24 and 27); During the period of interruption from 31 August 2007 to 21 September 2007 when the slipway was closed for repairs as a result of the September 2006 incident (see [27] of the FAC), the actual turnover was $1,152,277. A similar result applies for the period when TRS pleads that the slipway was closed due to the November 2006 incident. TRS filed a witness statement which explained that TRS adopted three different types of chargeable jobs; fixed price - where the customer pays a fixed price for completion of the work; estimate / budget --- where the work is completed on a labour and material charge basis but it is expected that the job will be completed + / - 15% of the budget / estimate and cost plus --- where the work is completed on a labour and material charge basis. As a result of the differing contractual and payment terms with different customers, there are three different types of invoicing practices adopted: 
4.1 Milestone invoicing --- where the customer may only be able to be invoiced when particular milestones are achieved (for example, completion of particular work);
 
4.2 Progress invoicing --- either on a dollar value or time basis (or both) as agreed with the customer (for example, every two weeks value of work in progress); and / or
 
4.3 Completion invoicing --- where invoices are raised on completion of the work. Finally, although not determinative (cf [14] of Finkelstein J in Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1088) as a global and not a weekly figure, TRS' turnover was in fact greater during the period of indemnity compared to the same period immediately preceding the incidents.  As it turns out, there was not a loss of Turnover in each week during the indemnity period covered by each policy. In some weeks TRS's actual Turnover exceeded its Actual Average Weekly Turnover. ... 
 
 
 
 ... 
 
 

 There was and remains a dispute about the approach to TRS' calculation of its loss. Some aspects of the issue have been considered by Finkelstein J. First, one of the questions ( Question 4 ) his Honour reserved for determination was to test QBE's approach to the calculation of loss. The question and answer was as follows: 
 
 
 Question 4: 
 
 

 
 
 
 Upon the assumption that: 
 
 

 
 
 
 (a) the Actual Weekly Turnover and Average Weekly Turnover figures pleaded in Annexures D, G and H to the Applicant's Claim are correct (as corrected by paragraphs 21-23 of the Supplementary Report of Stephen Munro Gibson dated 10 June 2009); 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) the allegations pleaded in paragraphs 1, 2, 4 to 15, 22 to 26, and 32 to 36 of the Applicant's Claim are established; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (c) the Respondent has paid a total sum of $2,000,000 to the Applicant in respect to the claims made in the proceedings; and 
 
 

 
 
 
 (d) the Applicant's claims pursuant to the 2005 renewal (as defined in paragraph 5 of the Applicant's Claim) and the 2006 renewal (as defined in paragraph 8 of the Applicant's Claim) are as pleaded in Annexures D, G, H and I to the Applicant's Claim (as corrected by paragraphs 21-23 of the Supplementary Munro dated 10 June 2009); 
 
 

 
 
 
 upon the proper construction of the 2005 renewal and the 2006 renewal, is the Applicant entitled to any and if so what amount under the 2005 renewal and/or the 2006 Renewal in respect to loss of Turnover under the said policies? 
 
 

 
 
 
 Answer: The Applicant is entitled to loss of Turnover under: 
 
 

 
 
 
 (a) the 2005 Renewal for the weeks ending 12 April 2007 to 25 October 2007 in respect to the September 2006 Incident; 
 
 

 
 
 
 (b) the 2006 Renewal for the weeks ending 22 February 2007 to 5 April 2007 and 1 November 2007 to 14 February 2008 in respect to the November 2006 Incident; 
 
 

 
 
 
 calculated in accordance with the methodology identified in the reasons for judgment, subject to proof of the loss of Turnover and the causal connection required by the terms of each of the policies . 
 
 

 
 
 
 (Emphasis added. ) 
 
 

 After Finkelstein J explained his answer to Question 4 (in Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1088 at [14] ), he identified the issues that remained to be resolved (at [15]) to be "(a) whether there is a causal connection between the incidents and the loss claimed and (b) whether Turnover, and therefore Actual Average Weekly Turnover, ought be calculated by reference to total invoiced sales or cash receipts, or a combination of both, plus work in progress". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 1093">The effect of this answer was to reject QBE's approach to the calculation of loss of Turnover. The reasons which were delivered explain why: Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Ltd [2009] FCA 1088. In those reasons I said (at [14]): 
 
 The cover provided by the policy makes clear that "for each week [the respondent] will pay [the applicant] ... in respect of loss of Turnover" (emphasis added). This means the calculations are to be made on a weekly basis.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCAFC 161">10 Consistent with QBE's proposal the primary judge dealt with the separate questions before any other issue in the proceeding. His Honour delivered reasons for judgment on 25 September 2009 ( Tropical Reef Shipyard Pty Ltd v QBE Insurance (Australia) Limited [2009] FCA 1088). The primary judge rejected QBE's submission that the policy required TRS to give credit for the weeks in which its actual sales after the alleged incidents exceeded its actual average weekly sales unaffected by the alleged incidents. At [14] of the reasons for judgment, his Honour said:
 It is not possible to accept the respondent's construction.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>