<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Van Der Velde v Ng (No. 3) [2009] FCA 1563 (22 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1563.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1100">mortgages</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1100">discharge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1100">whether mortgagee's costs of defending suit to set aside mortgage were a contingent liability of the mortgagor secured by the mortgage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 1100">whether mortgagor obliged to provide security for contingent liability in order to obtain discharge.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 594">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 594">consideration of a separate question of the basis upon which an order for costs might be made on the application of the third respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 594">consideration of whether the costs of the proceedings incurred by the third respondent fall within the notion of "enforcement expenses" for the purposes of clause 20 of the mortgage entered into between the first respondent and the third respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 594">consideration of the principles to be applied in determining the basis upon which a mortgagee ought to have its costs as against the mortgagor of the proceedings having regard to the terms of the mortgage itself</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 35">corporate insolvency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 35">consideration of whether particular arrangements for the transfer of trust property and the ultimate transfer of that trust property constitute transactions rendered voidable by operation of s 588fe of the corporations act 2001 (cth) and whether the transfer of the property is rendered void by operation of s 468 of the act  family law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 35">the interaction between s 90ac of the family law act 1975 (cth) and ss 588fa , 588fb and 588fda of the corporations act 2001 (cth)  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCAFC 35">whether the court should exercise its discretion under s 30ai of the federal court of australia act 1976 (cth) to receive further evidence on appeal</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 594">It follows that Ms Ng's declaration under clause 1.5(b) was incorrect as the liquidators and Riby (in liquidation) enjoyed "rights affecting the property" by reason of the disposition of the property to Ms Ng in the circumstances as found: Van Der Velde v Ng (No. 3) [2009] FCA 1563 and Ng v Van Der Velde [2011] FCAFC 35. It also follows that Ms Ng's declaration that she had not contravened the Corporations Act was incorrect. Ms Ng's declaration at 1.5(d) was incorrect by reason of the false answers she gave as to her bankruptcy and Shancom. For the same reasons Ms Ng's declaration at clause 1.5(e) was incorrect. By failing to tell Rams of the caveat of 14 September 2007 and failing to take steps to remove it and assert her absolute title to the property (as she contended in the proceedings later commenced by the applicants), Ms Ng failed to comply with clause 10 of the mortgage. Each of these matters placed Ms Ng in default for the purposes of clauses 18(b) and (c) of the mortgage from the outset of the grant of the mortgage as to the incorrect declarations and in default from the period when Ms Ng ought reasonably to have taken steps to seek to remove the caveat (for example, within one month of notice to her of the caveat).  Ms Ng did not appear at the trial. The procedural matters relating to the obligations the parties were required to discharge leading up to the trial and the events at trial are set out in Van Der Velde v Ng (No. 3) [2009] FCA 1563 and Ng v Van Der Velde [2011] FCAFC 35.  It is not relevant to recite in these reasons the precise content of each of the many contentions on the part of the applicants concerning the grounds upon which the various pleaded transactions were said to be voidable transactions. Those matters are set out in the reasons for judgment in Van Der Velde v Ng (No. 3) [2009] FCA 1563 having regard to the Third Further Amended Statement of Claim framing the various causes of action; the evidence going to those matters; the findings in the primary judgment; and, the reasons of the Full Court in Ng v Van Der Velde [2011] FCAFC 35. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCAFC 35"></sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 9 Dictionary</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 468 Avoidance of dispositions of property, attachments etc.</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 513A Winding up ordered by the Court</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 588FE Voidable transactions</title>
<title id="l5">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 588FF Courts may make orders about voidable transactions</title>
<title id="l6">FAMILY LAW ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l7">FAMILY LAW ACT 1975 - SECT 9 Transitional</title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>