<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kerr v American Express Australia Limited [2009] FCA 1219 (28 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1219.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">appeal from sequestration order made by federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">sequestration order based on judgment debt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">allegation that original order giving rise to judgment debt obtained by fraud and collusion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">allegation that appellant denied natural justice by not being afforded opportunity to object to affidavits of debt and search</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1490">allegation that federal magistrate wrongly refused adjournment of proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">application for leave to appear as a mckenzie friend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">general rule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">policy considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">good grounds required to be shown before court will grant leave</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2002] NSWCA 219">application dismissed. d</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">application for review of decision affirming delegates refusal to grant protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">citizen of togo</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">arrived in australia on 'visitor visa'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">on-shore application for protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">fear of persecution due to involvement in student or opposition politics</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">fear of being mistaken for activist identical twin brother</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">identical twin brother recognised as refugee in hong kong</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">well founded fear of persecution not made out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 20">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">review of decision to affirm delegates decision to refuse visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">national of bangladesh</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">well-founded fear of persecution because of political affiliations and activities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">applicant's credibility challenged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">political party that applicant worked for now ruling party in bangladesh</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">issues to be determined properly identified by tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">no legal basis on which to interfere with tribunal's decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">appeal dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 28">costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">bankruptcy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">creditors petition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">application by a mckenzie friend to appear for respondent debtor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">leave granted limited to adjournment application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">application for adjournment to allow the appearance of an expert witness to address court on alleged "syntax fraud" in petition documentation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1204">status of funds deposited at offices of the legal representatives of the applicant by respondent debtor.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FMCA 20">At the hearing, Mr. Davies was "represented" by Mr. H. Ford. I understand that Mr. Ford is legally qualified but not yet admitted to practice. I also understand that he is a migration agent and has acted in that capacity for a number of years. I gave Mr. Ford leave to appear on Mr. Davies's behalf for the purposes of the hearing before me. [3] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FMCA 28">Before dealing with the Tribunal's decision, I should note that I allowed Mr Ford to appear and make submissions on Mr Smith's behalf, notwithstanding that, as I understand it, Mr Ford is not formally admitted to practice. In effect, Mr Ford appearance was as a "Mackenzie friend. " [2] </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FMCA 1204">Mr Bedrossian, counsel for the applicant, indicated that he did not object to Ms Williams appearing as a McKenzie friend for the purpose of the adjournment application only. Mr Bedrossian brought the Court's attention to the decision in Kerr v American Express Australia Ltd [2009] FCA 1219 at [5] where Collier J stated: [5] It is clear that a power of attorney as held by Mr Kerr from Ms Kerr does not provide a lawful basis for a non-lawyer to act for a party in litigation in a Federal Court (cf Slack v Bottoms English Solicitors [2003] FCA 1337). However the court has discretion to grant leave to a person who is not a qualified legal practitioner to represent a litigant. Such a person is commonly known as a "Mackenzie friend". I note that I consider it inappropriate that an application should be made by Mr Kerr to represent Ms Kerr without Ms Kerr being present. However I understand that in previous proceedings in this court Mr Kerr has represented Ms Kerr in her absence. For the purposes of today's hearing, which is procedural only, I am prepared to entertain Mr Kerr's application to represent Ms Kerr. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>