<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Stratford Sun Limited v OM Holdings Limited [2009] FCA 1245 (4 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1245.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">application for preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">circumstantial information regarding conduct of former employees on establishing competing business</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">whether o 15a r 6(b) is determined by test of "bare pleadable case"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">scope of discretion to refuse relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">commercial sensitivity of documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">relevance of delay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCAFC 133">alleged unfairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">application for discovery under o15a r 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">principles to be applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">whether sufficient evidence of the necessary elements of the potential causes of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">consideration of whether the proportionate liability provisions in pt ivaa of the wrongs act 1958 (vic) (' wrongs act ') apply to the pleaded causes of action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">where pt ivaa provisions are applicable according to its own terms</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">where commonwealth legislation "otherwise provides"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">provisions are not picked up by s 79 of the judiciary act 1903 (cth) statutory construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1216">where contributing fault plea not available to respondents under certain provisions of the corporations act 2001 (cth) and australian securities and investments commission act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">application for discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">order 15a r 6 of the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">whether there is reasonable cause to believe applicant has or may have right to obtain relief against respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">whether even after making all reasonable enquiries applicant has insufficient information to decide whether to commence proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 288">whether there is reasonable cause to believe respondent is likely to have documents relating to whether applicant has right to obtain relief.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">federal court rules order 15a rule 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">whether reasonable cause to believe that applicant has or may have right to obtain relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">asserted claims for breach of warranty, misleading or deceptive conduct and breach of fiduciary duty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">low threshold requirement for reasonable belief, however belief must amount to more than a mere possibility or speculation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">entitlement to preliminary discovery in order for applicant to ascertain defences available to respondent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations made as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">onus on respondent to show reasonableness of future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">preliminary discovery appropriate in relation to future representations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">application for preliminary discovery otherwise denied trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">misleading or deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">representations as to future financial circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1360">burden of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">federal court rules , o 15a, r 6</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">whether reasonable cause to believe the applicant may have a right to obtain relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[1999] FCA 710">whether applicant has insufficient information to enable a decision to be made to commence proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 414">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 414">whether the defendant corporation should be restrained from putting certain resolutions to the annual general meeting of the defendant scheduled to occur in the immediate future</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 414">whether alleged breaches of the asx listing rules, the corporations act 2001 (cth) and the general law gave rise to one or more serious questions to be tried</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 414">whether the balance of convenience and justice favoured the grant or refusal of injunctive relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 414">injunctions refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1153">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1153">application under o 15a r 6 of federal court rules for preliminary discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1153">conditions to be satisfied for relief and applicable principles</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1153">application of principles to facts.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">application for information discovery  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">applicant did not pursue application.  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">application for leave to use affidavits filed in opposition to application for information discovery in any subsequent proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">where information in affidavits proposed to be read in open court and not claimed to be confidential  held: application allowed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">in the interests of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">to facilitate expeditious disposition of subsequent proceeding.  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">application for costs of application for information discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">where applicant did not pursue application for information discovery because second respondent filed affidavits shortly prior to final hearing providing it with necessary information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">where information related to patent infringement and patent application in relation to alleged infringing product was publicly available  held: application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">order that applicant pay respondents' costs of application if proceeding for patent infringement not brought within 2 months</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 558">if application brought within 2 months then costs of application to be costs in the cause of that proceeding.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 414">I say that these remarks were made somewhat tongue in cheek because the lawyers for Stratford Sun are based in Perth (although they have a Sydney presence) and it was known to those lawyers that OMH had generally been represented in the past by lawyers based in Perth. Indeed, there had been a prior piece of litigation between the same parties which had been commenced and dealt with in the Perth Registry of this Court ( Stratford Sun Ltd v OM Holdings Ltd [2009] FCA 1245 ; (2009) 74 ACSR 698). Litigation in New South Wales on such short notice was inevitably going to present logistical difficulties for OMH. It does seem to me, by way of general observation, that there was a fair bit of tactical manoeuvring occurring yesterday and in the days leading up to yesterday when the correspondence which I have referred to and extracted at [36]---[47] above was being exchanged. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 1153">An example of the application of this requirement is provided by the case of Stratford Sun Ltd v OM Holdings Ltd [2009] FCA 1245 ; (2009) 74 ACSR 698 at [60] --- [61] per Siopis J, where his Honour observed: 
 
 'Thus, while it is the case that O 15A r 6 permits fishing, nevertheless, there must be an evidentiary foundation, which will permit a belief or tilting of the mind towards the existence of the factual premise upon which the potential cause of action being contemplated by the applicant, is found. 
 

 
 
 In my view, the case made by the applicant does not, on the evidence before the court, rise above the level of speculation or conjecture. ' 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 558">Finally, the respondents submit that there is evidence supporting a conclusion that I cannot exclude the possibility that the applicant's application for information discovery has been brought for an improper purpose, namely, to damage or harm the respondents' commercial interests. The respondents put the submission in this way because they accept that, in the absence of cross-examination of the deponents of the affidavits, I cannot make a positive finding of an improper purpose. I reject this submission because I do not think that, on the evidence before me, there is anything to suggest that the applicant had an improper purpose in bringing this application. The case relied on by the respondents, Stratford Sun Limited v OM Holdings Limited [2009] FCA 1245 ; (2009) 74 ACSR 698 , was a very different case. In that case, Siopis J was not satisfied that the applicant had identified with sufficient specificity the benefit it would obtain from any relief founded on the breach alleged (see 708 [66]). By contrast, there is nothing in this case to suggest that the applicant is not seeking to protect the legal rights it has as a result of the registration of its patent. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 15 General</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 17 Associates of composite person that carries on a financial services business</title>
<title id="l3">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 793C Enforcement of operating rules</title>
<title id="l4">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1324 Injunctions</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>