<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 1460 (9 December 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1460.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 1393">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 1393">construction of patent for simulating flames with common application in domestic room heaters</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 1393">whether the respondents' domestic room heaters infringed some of the claims in the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 1393">whether the patent is invalid and should be revoked</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">patent infringement proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">respondents resisting allegation of infringement and cross-claiming for revocation on ground of invalidity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">respondents successful on infringement point but unsuccessful on validity point</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">how costs should be apportioned</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 52">whether respondents entitled to costs generally or only on issues upon which they succeeded.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">calderbank letter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">refusal of offer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">whether refusal unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">variety of factors relevant to assessment of unreasonableness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1056">indemnity costs refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 424">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 424">offer of compromise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] VSC 424">whether wholly successful defendant entitled to costs on indemnity basis.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">whether costs should be assessed on an indemnity or solicitor/client basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">where a calderbank offer allegedly made by respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">applicant's failure to accept the offer not unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">whether a 'compromise' in the relevant sense where the offer is for application to be withdrawn and each party to bear its own costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">application that respondent's costs of certain issues be paid on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">discussion of applicable principles.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 526">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 526">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 526">whether leave to amend its statement of claim should be granted to a patentee to raise new types of infringement of its patent after a separate trial on liability but before the damages trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 526">whether consequential orders for further discovery should be made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">whether in a patent infringement case, in circumstances where the trial of all questions of liability (including the determination of claims for injunctive relief) were heard and determined before all claims for pecuniary relief, the patentee is entitled without more to seek to recover damages in respect of the importation, sale and/or distribution of additional devices which are alleged to infringe the patent even though those devices were not considered by the court at the liability stage and were not the subject of any findings of infringement at that stage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">in the present case, the patentee had specifically identified the articles which allegedly infringed the patent and conducted the trial and subsequent appeal upon the basis that these were the only articles said to have infringed the patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">the patentee did not reserve the right to enlarge the type of its infringing articles at the damages stage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 357">in the events which have happened and in light of the form of the patentee's statements of claim, additional infringements not permitted to be litigated at the damages stage</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 93">category: no</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 526">Subsequently, disputes arose between the applicant, on the one hand, and the respondents, on the other hand, as to the extent to which the respondents were obliged to provide discovery. It became apparent that, at the heart of the parties' disagreement about discovery was a difference of opinion as to whether, in addition to the specific models of heaters which were found by the Full Court to have infringed the Patent, the applicant was entitled to pursue the respondents in respect of other models of heaters which had not to date been considered either by me at trial or by the Full Court on appeal. I considered that there was a question of principle which underlay the parties' dispute concerning discovery. I took the view that the best way of resolving that question of principle was to order in each of the extant proceedings that a separate question be heard separately from and before any further trial of any of those proceedings. Accordingly, on 17 March 2011, I made an order in the following terms in each of proceedings NSD 1681 of 2006, NSD 43 of 2007 and NSD 2056 of 2007: Pursuant to O 29 r 2(a) of the Federal Court Rules , the following question be heard separately from and before any further trial in the proceedings, namely: 
 
 
 
 Whether, upon the basis of the pleadings as they currently stand and in light of the judgments of this Court in Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1393 , Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 1460 , Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd [2010] FCAFC 75 and Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCAFC 93 , it is open to the applicant to claim damages for infringement of its patent being Australian Patent No 621713 in respect of the importation, distribution or sale of electric flame heaters bearing model numbers [there was here inserted the relevant model numbers]. 
 
 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FCA 357">Subsequently, disputes arose between the applicant, on the one hand, and the respondents, on the other hand, as to the extent to which the respondents were obliged to provide discovery. It became apparent that, at the heart of the parties' disagreement about discovery was a difference of opinion as to whether, in addition to the specific models of heaters which were found by the Full Court to have infringed the Patent, the applicant was entitled to pursue the respondents in respect of other models of heaters which had not to date been considered either by me at trial or by the Full Court on appeal. I considered that there was a question of principle which underlay the parties' dispute concerning discovery. I took the view that the best way of resolving that question of principle was to order in each of the extant proceedings that a separate question be heard separately from and before any further trial of any of those proceedings. Accordingly, on 17 March 2011, I made an order in the following terms in each of proceedings NSD 1681 of 2006, NSD 43 of 2007 and NSD 2056 of 2007: Pursuant to O 29 r 2(a) of the Federal Court Rules , the following question be heard separately from and before any further trial in the proceedings, namely: 
 
 
 Whether, upon the basis of the pleadings as they currently stand and in light of the judgments of this Court in Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1393 , Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 1460 , Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd [2010] FCAFC 75 and Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCAFC 93 , it is open to the applicant to claim damages for infringement of its patent being Australian Patent No 621713 in respect of the importation, distribution or sale of electric flame heaters bearing model numbers [there was here inserted the relevant model numbers]. 
 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCAFC 93">3 The four proceedings were heard together as, although the parties in each proceeding were different, the issues were broadly the same: Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 1393 at [2] . The primary Judge found that the respondents' heaters did not infringe the patent, and made orders dismissing each application. His Honour also determined that the patent was not invalid, and dismissed the cross-claims. In substance, his Honour ordered Bitech to pay the respondents' costs in relation to infringement. His Honour reserved the question of costs in the proceeding against Flameglow pending the determination of an appeal, as Flameglow had been placed in liquidation, and its cross-claim based on unjustifiable threats remained unresolved: see Bitech Engineering v Garth Living Pty Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 1460 at [34] - [62] and the orders made by the primary Judge in NSD 105 of 2007 on 3 February 2010. His Honour also granted leave to Bitech to prosecute an appeal against Flameglow while the company was in liquidation. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 19 Businesses of a particular kind</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 500 Execution and civil proceedings</title>
<title id="l3">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l4">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 19 Certificate of validity</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>