<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>MZXTA v Minister for Immigration &amp; Citizenship [2009] FCA 1186 (19 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1186.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">applications to tribunal to reschedule hearings and provide extensions of time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">tribunal required medical evidence of inability to attend or respond</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">psychologists report provided</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">not medical evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">no breach of s.425</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2008] FMCA 1201">real and meaningful invitation to appear.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">migration law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">appeal from decision of federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether any appealable error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether migration review tribunal complied with its obligations under s 360 of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">burden of proof on judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether negligence of migration agent established</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">relevance of s 361 of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">effect of mistranslation of sponsor's statement to interviewing officer where interviewing officer also the delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether supposed admissions made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether perception of interviewing officer/delegate seriously mistaken on account of mistranslation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">tribunal relied on account of interviewing officer/delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">whether the tribunal acted unreasonably in failing to make enquiries of interviewing officer/delegate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">exceptional case</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1318">finding of jurisdictional error upheld</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs v sglb  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">expert medical advice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">psychological state of applicant assumed to be possible explanation for unsatisfactory evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">whether denial of procedural fairness by failing to order further psychological assessment of applicant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">whether denial of procedural fairness by accepting that applicant suffered stress disorder</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">whether denial of procedural fairness by acceptance of effects of disorder on applicant without expert medical advice.  statutes</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">privative clause</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2004] HCA 32">whether putative errors of the refugee review tribunal fell within the operation of s 474 of the migration act 1958 (cth).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">application for stay of deportation order pending hearing of application under judicial review act for review of minister's decision to deport</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">whether applicant must establish a serious question to be tried</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">relevance of grave consequences flowing from refusal or grant of stay.  administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 para.5(1)(e) and (g), sub-s.5(2)  migration act 1958 para.6a(1)(e), sub-s.7(2) and s.18  immigration and aliens</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">prohibited immigrants</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">deportation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">minister's discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">possible grant of temporary entry permit</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">possible entry permit on compassionate grounds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">information not provided to minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">applicant misled by departmental officers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">minister's duty to initiate inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">whether decision "unreasonable"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.14" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">migration act 1983 (cth), ss 6a(1)(e), 18.  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.15" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.16" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.17" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">"failure" to take into account</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.18" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">relevant information not before decision-maker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.19" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">whether duty to initiate inquiries</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.20" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">prohibited immigrant misled by departmental officers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.21" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">relevant information not provided</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.22" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">deportation order by minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.23" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">decision "unreasonable"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.24" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 326">administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth), s 5(2)(g). held: (1) the minister's decision to deport the applicant pursuant to s 18 of the migration act 1983 was not so unreasonable that no reasonable person could have come to it. this was so, even taking into account the information which the applicant could have provided to departmental officers, for inclusion in a report to the minister, if he had not been led to think it was irrelevant.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">application for permanent residence in australia by spouse of person having permanent resident status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">validity of decision to refuse application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">failure of minister to take into account relevant material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">unreasonableness of decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">ambit of material relevant for consideration in determining reasonableness.  migration act 1958 ss. 6 , 6a  administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 s.5  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">judicial review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">immigration and aliens</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">review of minister's decision refusing an application for a permanent entry permit to australia, spouse having permanent resident status</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">whether minister had failed to take into account relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">whether exercise of power was so unreasonable that no reasonable person could have so exercised the power</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">taking of further evidence to adduce facts not before the minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth), ss 5(1)(e) , 5 (2), 5 (2)(a), 5 (2)(b), 5 (2)(f), 5 (2)(g), 6 (2), 13</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.15" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">migration act 1958 (cth), ss 6 , 6a. in an application for review of a decision of the minister for immigration and ethnic affairs made in 1984 refusing an application for a permanent entry permit to an applicant who was the spouse of a permanent resident on the basis that the applicant's marriage had been assessed as being one where the parties did not genuinely intend to continue living as a married couple in australia, it being the minister's policy to refuse permanent entry permits in such cases.  held: (1) that relevant considerations which should have been taken into account were not, thus making the minister's decision invalid pursuant to s 5(2)(b) of the administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (the act), such considerations being:  (i) a report made in 1981 by an interviewing officer in suva expressing an opinion that the marriage relationship was genuine, such report being part of the history of the relationship, all of which was relevant in determining the quality of the marriage as at the date of the minister deciding the application. although the report was not presented to the minister, it was on the departmental file and was accordingly to be regarded as being constructively before him.  peko-wallsend ltd v. minister for aboriginal affairs (1985) 59 alr 51 , referred to.  (ii) statutory declarations of neighbours and acquaintances as to the applicant leading a normal married life and a letter of a social worker as to the applicant's wife living at home with the applicant, such documents being available to the minister, but there being nothing to indicate that he had taken any account of them.  (2) that in determining whether an administrative decision made under statutory authority falls within s 5(2)(g) of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.16" type=cited from="[1985] FCA 47">(a) the court should construe that paragraph in the light of the common law principle of which that paragraph is a legislative enactment, that principle being stated by lord diplock in bromley london borough city council v. greater london council (1983) 1 ac 768 to be the invalidation of administrative decisions "that looked at objectively are so devoid of any plausible justification that no reasonable body of persons could have reached them" and by menzies j in parramatta city council v. pestell [1972] hca 59 ; (1972) 128 clr 305 to be the invalidation of an administrative decision "based on an opinion which could not be justified on any reasonable grounds".  perkins v. cuthill [1981] fca 44 ; (1981) 34 alr 669 ; plegas v. mccabe (unreported, federal court of australia, lockhart j, 3 august 1984; willara pty ltd v. mcveigh (1984) 54 alr 65 ; re w (an infant) (1971) ac 682 ; associated provincial picture houses v. wednesbury corporation [1947] ewca civ 1 ; (1948) 1 kb 223 ; secretary of state for education and science v. tameside metropolitan borough council [1976] ukhl 6 ; (1977) ac 1014 ; borkovic v. minister for immigration and ethnic affairs (1981) 39 alr 186 ; hamblin v. duffy [1981] fca 38 ; (1981) 50 flr 308 ; mixnam's properties ltd v. chertsey urban district council (1964) 1 qb 214 , referred to.  (b) the court is entitled to consider those facts which were known to the decision-maker actually or constructively together only with such additional facts as the decision-maker would have learned but for any unreasonable conduct by him where such facts are obtainable from material that is readily available.  (3) that, having taken further evidence relating to the matters arising out of the interviews by the departmental officer, and having reviewed and analysed the evidence and the manner in which the decision was reached by the minister, and bearing in mind the strength of the case required before it may be said that a decision falls within s 5(2)(g) of the act, the minister's decision was "devoid of any plausible justification" and that it accordingly be set aside pursuant to that paragraph of the act and the matter remitted to the minister for further consideration. in reaching this decision the court took into account, inter alia, the following matters:  (i) the existence of the statutory declarations and the social worker's letter asserting that there was a normal marriage relationship, the declarants and writer thereof being apparently credible and independent and such documents asserting a conclusion contrary to that formed by the minister and the fact that the minister had not further investigated the statements contained in those documents as he ought to have done.  (ii) that the only matters tending to show lack of intention to live together were the circumstances of the marriage four years earlier and more importantly, interviews by a departmental officer of the applicant and his wife, such interviews containing inconsistencies in their recollection of details in their daily lives, the minister believing that such inconsistencies indicated that the wife did not live with her husband. the interviewing officer should have given the applicant an opportunity to deal with those matters which excited an adverse reaction in the officer before permitting those matters to be used in a manner adverse to the applicant in the decision-making process.  (iii) the interviews which were relied upon by the minister as the primary method of determining the genuineness of the relationship were rushed and short and in any case, neither a verbatim record nor at least contemporaneous notes of the interviews were made and kept, as ought to have been done.  hearing  sydney, 1985, february 5-6, 26.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">protection (class xa) visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">review of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">citizen of india claiming fear of persecution for reason of political opinion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">where applicant did not attend tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 405">whether tribunal failed to consider all aspects of the applicant's claim.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">refusal of protection visas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">applicants claiming political persecution in india</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">principal applicant failing to attend tribunal hearing and tribunal proceeding to make a decision without an oral hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 265">no arguable case of jurisdictional error.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">where applicant did not attend the tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 324">no jurisdictional error.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 323">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 323">visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 323">protection visa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 323">review of refugee review tribunal decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 323">where applicant did not attend tribunal hearing.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 181">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 181">application to set aside orders dismissing an application for review of a decision of the refugee review tribunal and an application that the matter be transferred to the federal court of australia pursuant to rule 13.03c(1)(c) of the federal magistrates court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 181">whether in interests of justice to set aside orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 181">explanation for the applicant's non-appearance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 181">whether futile to set aside orders.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FMCA 405">The Tribunal had complied with s. 426A which gives the Tribunal a wide discretion ( MZXRTA v Minister for Immigration [9] at [71]; affirmed on appeal in MZXTA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [10] ). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FMCA 265">Section 426A provides the Tribunal with a discretion. This discretion has been described as a wide one (see MZXTA v Minister for Immigration [2008] FMCA 1201 at [71] , and affirmed on appeal to the Federal Court in Australia in MZXTA v Minister for Immigration [2009] FCA 1186 ; [2009] 112 ALD 89). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2011] FMCA 324">It was also submitted that the letter sent to the Applicant complied with subsection 425A(4) of the Act by containing a statement as to the effect of s.426A. This latter section provides the Tribunal with a discretion as to whether to proceed with the hearing in the absence of the Applicant or to adjourn it to another occasion. The discretion is a wide discretion (see MZXTA v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [8] at [71], affirmed on appeal in MZXTA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [9] ). Conclusions 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2011] FMCA 323">It was also submitted that the letter sent to the Applicant complied with subsection 425A(4) of the Act by containing a statement as to the effect of s.426A. This latter section provides the Tribunal with a discretion as to whether to proceed with the hearing in the absence of the Applicant or not. The discretion is a wide discretion (see MZXTA v Minister for Immigration &amp; Anor [9] at [71], affirmed on appeal in MZXTA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [10] ). Conclusions
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FMCA 181">Nor is the evidence before the court such as to suggest that the applicant was unfit to appear before the Tribunal or that the Tribunal should have made further enquires in that respect (cf Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs v SGLB (2004) 78 ALJR 992 ; [2004] HCA 32 and see MZXTA v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship and Another (2009) 112 ALD 89; [2009] FCA 1186). As in MZXTA, there is nothing in the material before the court to suggest that any " obligation or discretion that the Tribunal was under, or able to exercise, in respect of ss 424A , 425 or 426A was not discharged or properly exercised " (at [30]). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 65 Decision to grant or refuse to grant visa</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 351 Minister may substitute more favourable decision</title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 417 Minister may substitute more favourable decision</title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424 Tribunal may seek information</title>
<title id="l5">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 425 Tribunal must invite applicant to appear</title>
<title id="l7">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 426 Applicant may request Refugee Review Tribunal to call witnesses</title>
<title id="l8">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 426A Failure of applicant to appear before Tribunal</title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>