<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Limited (No 2) [2009] FCA 196 (10 March 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/196.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 755">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 755">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 755">circumstances under which indemnity costs will be ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 755">calderbank offers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 755">whether offer by respondents to accept substantial amount by way of costs if applicant discontinues proceeding constitutes a calderbank offer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 341">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 341">application for indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 341">calderbank letter sent by appellant prior to proceedings below offering settlement in terms "verdict in favour of the council with each party to bear its own costs"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 341">whether genuine offer of compromise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] NSWCA 341">whether discretion to award indemnity costs should be exercised.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">whether costs should be assessed on an indemnity or solicitor/client basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">where a calderbank offer allegedly made by respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">applicant's failure to accept the offer not unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 1212">whether a 'compromise' in the relevant sense where the offer is for application to be withdrawn and each party to bear its own costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2001] NSWCA 145">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2001] NSWCA 145">calderbank letter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2001] NSWCA 145">in substance, invited capitulation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2001] NSWCA 145">appeal was arguable and decided by majority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2001] NSWCA 145">no special costs order. nd.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">application that respondent's costs of certain issues be paid on indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 536">discussion of applicable principles.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">apportionment of costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">party unsuccessful on some issues</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">principles governing apportionment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">case management considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">bullock or sanderson orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 42">indemnity costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">discretion of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">award on solicitor and client' or indemnity' basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">whether application vexatious</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=cited from="[1988] FCA 202">form of order.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">calderbank offers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">defendants seeking indemnity costs or solicitor and client costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">whether the offers were a genuine attempt at compromise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">whether it was unreasonable for the plaintiff to reject the offers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">whether allegations of wilful misrepresentation being unreasonable or having no proper factual basis requires a special costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=citing from="[2011] VSC 117">continuation of claims for wilful misrepresentation where no reasonable prospect of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">application for leave to discontinue proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">no reasonable prospect of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">application for leave dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">substantive application dismissed.  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">award on solicitor and client or indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">where applicant seeks leave to discontinue proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">whether action commenced or continued where no prospect of success.  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 761">application for damages and injunctive relief for alleged misuse of market power under s 46 of the trade practices act.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 506">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 506">whether inadequacy of decision maker's statement of reasons has a bearing on costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 506">whether indemnity costs should be ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 506">whether refusal of calderbank offer was unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 506">whether indemnity costs appropriate because proceeding was brought and maintained for ulterior or extraneous purpose.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 456">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 456">whether indemnity costs or party and party costs are appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 456">whether apportionment of costs is appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 406">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 406">whether indemnity costs are appropriate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 406">whether calderbank offers are genuine offers and whether rejection is unreasonable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 406">party and party costs amended</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">costs sought on an indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">limitation period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">difficulties raised in correspondence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">offer of compromise   legislation: federal court of australia act 1976 (cth), ss 43 , 59 (1), 59 (2) federal court rules , o 23 rr 2</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 286">4   cases cited: alpine beef pty ltd v trycill pty ltd [2010] fca 136 , cited colgate-palmolive pty ltd v cussons pty ltd [1993] fca 536 ; (1993) 46 fcr 225 , cited</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] VSC 117">[11] It was expressed clearly and set out why the plaintiff's claim against the second and third defendants would not succeed.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 761">There are many cases in this court to the same effect including: Cook v Pasminco Ltd (No 2) [2000] FCA 1819 ; (2000) 107 FCR 44 at [65] ; Vasram v AMP Life Ltd [2002] FCA 1286 ; Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Limited (No 2) [2009] FCA 196 at [9] ; J-Corp Pty Ltd v Australian Builders Labourers Federated Union of Workers, Western Australian Branch (No 2) (1993) 46 IR 301 at 303. The language used in these cases held to justify an indemnity costs order was that the particular case "had no prospect of success" in Cook ; "was seriously flawed" in Vasram and "was hopeless" in J-Corp . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 506">Some of these authorities, together with other authorities for the same proposition, were considered by Goldberg J in Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Limited (No 2) [2009] FCA 196. Relying on the reasoning of the New South Wales Court of Appeal in Leichardt Municipal Council v Green [2004] NSWCA 341 , Goldberg J did not agree with the proposition that an invitation to an applicant to discontinue proceedings with no order as to costs is not a genuine attempt to resolve the proceeding by way of a compromise, for the purposes of considering the consequences of an offer made in a Calderbank letter. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 456">There are authorities to the effect that a defendant's offer to settle on the basis that each party bears it's own costs is not a Calderbank offer and in any event may not be considered a genuine offer of compromise: see Dresna Pty Ltd v Linknarf Management Services Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 2) [2006] FCA 755 at [20] ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 192 ; (2002) 201 ALR 618 at [59] - [60] ; McKerlie v State of New South Wales (No 2) [2000] NSWSC 1159 ; Vasram v AMP Life Limited [2002] FCA 1286 at [12] ; and Fyna Foods Australia Pty Ltd v Cobannah Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2004] FCA 1212 at [10] . It seems to me that the correct approach is to look at the extent of the offer of compromise, viewed with all the other relevant circumstances, to determine whether the rejection of the offer was unreasonable: see Aljade at [78] to [81] per Redlich J; Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 196 at [15] per Goldberg J; Fyna Foods at [11]; Vasram at [13]; Nutrientwater Pty Ltd v Baco Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCA 304 and Rosemin Pty Ltd v Gasp Jeans Chadstone Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCA 406. This is how I have proceeded to consider this application for indemnity costs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 406">There are authorities to the effect that a respondent's offer to settle on the basis that each party bears it's own costs is not a Calderbank offer and in any event may not be considered a genuine offer of compromise: see Dresna Pty Ltd v Linknarf Management Services Pty Ltd (in liq) (No 2) [2006] FCA 755 at [20] ; Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd (No 2) [2002] FCA 192 ; (2002) 201 ALR 618 at [59] - [60]; McKerlie v New South Wales (No 2) [2000] NSWSC 1159 ; Vasram v AMP Life Limited [2002] FCA 1286 at [12] ; and Fyna Foods Australia Pty Ltd v Cobannah Holdings Pty Ltd (No 2) [2004] FCA 1212 at [10] . It seems to me that the correct approach is to look at the extent of the offer of compromise viewed with all the other relevant circumstances to determine whether the rejection of the offer was unreasonable: see Aljade and Malaysian Kuwaiti Investment Co SDN BHD (MKIC) v Oversea-Chinese Banking Corp Ltd (OCBC) [2004] VSC 351 at [78] to [81] per Redlich J; Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 196 at [15] per Goldberg J; Fyna Foods at [11]; Vasram at [13] and Nutrientwater Pty Ltd v Baco Pty Ltd (No 2) [2010] FCA 304. This is how I will proceed to consider this application for indemnity costs. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2010] FCA 286">Viewed as at 5 August 2009, the offer then made cannot be characterised as anything other than a genuine assessment as to risks inevitably confronted in any litigation; it cannot be characterised as an attempt to force upon the Applicant what has been referred to in other litigation as an invitation " to capitulate ": Szencorp Pty Ltd v Clean Energy Council Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 196 at [14] per Goldberg J. As at 5 August 2009, it is considered that the Applicant should have been in a position where it could assess its prospects of success --- any assessment taking into account such strengths as were perceived to be present together with an assessment of the difficulties, including those which had previously been raised in correspondence. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 232 Grounds for Court order</title>
<title id="l2">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 233 Orders the Court can make</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l4">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 43 Costs</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>