<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited (No. 2) [2009] FCA 1391 (26 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1391.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">intervenors</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">application for leave to intervene</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">court's power to permit intervention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">criteria guiding the court's discretion whether to permit intervention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">whether contribution of industry body would be 'useful and different' to that of the parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 393">application stood over generally and leave granted to renew application during course of hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">order 52 r 14aa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">application for leave to be heard as amici curiae</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">consideration of distinction between an amicus curiae and an intervenor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">difference between non-lawyer entities seeking to become involved in litigation and legal practitioners invited by the court to assist it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">matters taken into account in determining the terms and conditions of leave to intervene</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 178">held: leave granted pursuant to o 52 r 14aa to intervene in appeals on certain conditions and with certain rights and liabilities</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 24">3) [2010] FCA 24 
 
 Citation: Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited (No. 3) [2010] FCA 24 
 
 Parties: Roadshow Films Pty Ltd (ACN 100 746 870) and the parties in attached Schedule I v iiNet Limited (ACN 068 628 937) 
 
 File number: NSD 1802 of 2008 
 
 Judge: COWDROY J 
 
 Date of judgment: 4 February 2010 
 
 Catchwords: INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY --- Copyright Authorisation --- Internet Service Provider provided internet to subscribers --- allegations made to Internet Service Provider that those using its internet service were infringing copyright --- whether persons using the internet service of the respondent infringed copyright by making available online, electronically transmitting and making copies of applicants' films --- whether the respondent authorised the infringement which occurred --- whether the respondent provided the means of infringement --- whether the respondent had the power to prevent the infringements which occurred --- whether the respondent sanctioned, approved, countenanced the infringements which occurred --- whether s 276 of the Telecommunications Act 1997 (Cth) led to a finding that the respondent did not have the power to prevent infringement 
 INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY --- Copyright Authorisation --- whether s 112E of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) prevented the respondent from being found to have authorised --- whether the respondent had knowledge of the infringements which occurred 
 INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY --- 'Safe Harbour' Provisions --- whether the respondent complied with the provisions of Division 2AA of Part V of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) --- what constitutes a repeat infringer policy --- whether respondent had a repeat infringer policy --- whether respondent had implemented repeat infringer policy 
 
 Legislation: Broadcasting Services Act 1992 (Cth)
 Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) ss 10 , 14 , 22 (6), 22 (6A), 37 , 86 , 100A , 101 , 101 (1A), 104, 112E, 115, 116AA, 116AC, 116AD, 116AE, 116AF, 116AG, 116AH(1), 116AH(2), 116AI, 119(a), 135ZWA
 Copyright Amendment (Digital Agenda) Act 2000 (Cth)
 Copyright Amendment (Digital Agenda) Bill 1999 (Cth)
 Copyright Amendment Regulations 2004 (No. 1) (Cth)
 Copyright, Designs and Patent Act 1988 (UK) s 45(1)
 Copyright Legislation Amendment Act 2004 (Cth)
 Copyright Regulations 1969 (Cth) reg 20B, 20I, 20J, 20K, 20L, 20M, 20X
 Criminal Code 1995 (Cth) s 137.2
 Digital Millennium Copyright Act 1998 (US) s 202
 Telecommunications Act 1997 (Cth) ss 7 , 87 , 270 , 276 , 279 , 280 , 289 , 290 
 Telecommunications (Consumer Protection and Service Standards) Act 1999 (Cth) s 128(5) 
 Telecommunications (Interception and Access) Act 1979 (Cth)
 United States Code (US) Title 17 s 512
 US Free Trade Implementation Act 2004 (Cth) 
 
 Cases cited: Apand Pty Limited v The Kettle Chip Company Pty Limited (1994) 62 FCR 474 followed
 Australasian Performing Right Association Limited v Jain (1990) 26 FCR 53 followed/distinguished
 Australasian Performing Right Association Ltd v Metro on George Pty Ltd and Others (2004) 61 IPR 57 followed/distinguished
 Australian Tape Manufacturers Association Ltd and Others v The Commonwealth of Australia (1993) 177 CLR 480 followed
 Avel Proprietary Limited v Multicoin Amusements Proprietary Limited and Another [1990] HCA 58 ; (1990) 171 CLR 88 followed
 C J Redman Constructions Pty Ltd v Tarnap Pty Ltd [2006] NSWSC 173 referred to
 Canadian Pacific Tobacco Limited and Another v Stapleton [1952] HCA 32 ; [1952] HCA 32 ; (1952) 86 CLR 1 referred to
 CBS Songs Ltd and Others v Amstrad Consumer Electronics PLC and Another [1988] UKHL 15 ; [1988] AC 1013 referred to
 Commercial Union Assurance Company of Australia Ltd v Ferrcom Pty Ltd and Another (1991) 22 NSWLR 389 distinguished
 Computermate Products (Aust) Pty Ltd v Ozi-Soft Pty Ltd and Others (1988) 20 FCR 46 followed
 Cooper v Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others [2006] FCAFC 187 ; (2006) 156 FCR 380 followed/distinguished
 Corbis Corporation v Amazon.com, Inc 351 FSupp2d 1090 (WD Wash 2004) considered
 The Corporation of the City of Adelaide v The Australasian Performing Right Association Limited [1928] HCA 10 ; (1928) 40 CLR 481 considered
 CSR Limited v Eddy [2005] HCA 64 ; [2005] HCA 64 ; (2006) 226 CLR 1 referred to
 E-Talk Communications Pty Ltd &amp; Anor v Universal Music Pty Ltd &amp; Ors [2007] HCATrans 313 considered
 Falcon v Famous Players Film Company [1926] 2 KB 474 cited
 Harlan Ellison v Stephen Robertson 189 FSupp2d 1051 (CD Cal 2002) considered
 Harlan Ellison v Steven Robertson [2004] USCA9 94 ; 357 F3d 1072 (9th Cir 2004) considered
 In Re: Aimster Copyright Litigation [2003] USCA7 320 ; 334 F3d 643 (7th Cir 2003) questioned
 In Re: Aimster Copyright Litigation 252 FSupp2d 634 (ND Ill 2002) considered
 Moorhouse &amp; Angus and Robertson (Publishers) Pty Ltd v University of New South Wales (1974) 3 ALR 1 distinguished
 Nationwide News Pty Ltd and Others v Copyright Agency Limited (1996) 65 FCR 399 followed
 Nominet UK v Diverse Internet Pty Ltd and Others [2004] FCA 1244 ; (2004) 63 IPR 543 cited
 Perfect 10, Inc v CCBill, LLC 340 FSupp2d 1077 (CD Cal 2004) considered
 Perfect 10, Inc v CCBill, LLC [2007] USCA9 172 ; 481 F3d 751 (9th Cir 2007) considered
 Perfect 10, Inc v Cybernet Ventures, Inc 213 FSupp2d 1146 (CD Cal 2002) considered
 Performing Right Society, Limited v Ciryl Theatrical Syndicate, Limited [1924] 1 KB 1 cited
 Recording Industry Association of America Inc v Verizon Internet Services Inc [2003] USCADC 251 ; 351 F3d 1229 (DC Cir 2003) referred to
 Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited (No 2) [2009] FCA 1391 referred to
 Roadshow Films Pty Ltd and Others (ACN 100 746 870) v iiNet Limited (ACN 068 628 937) [2009] FCA 332 ; (2009) 81 IPR 99 referred to
 Sony Corporation of America v Universal City Studios Inc [1984] USSC 14 ; 464 US 417 (1984) cited
 TCN Channel Nine Pty Ltd v Network Ten Pty Ltd (No 2) [2005] FCAFC 53 ; (2005) 145 FCR 35 cited
 Telstra Corporation Limited v Australasian Performing Right Association Limited [1997] HCA 41 ; (1997) 191 CLR 140 discussed
 Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Cooper and Others [2005] FCA 972 ; (2005) 150 FCR 1 followed/distinguished
 Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd and Others v Sharman License Holdings Ltd and Others [2005] FCA 1242 ; (2005) 65 IPR 289 followed/distinguished
 The University of New South Wales v Moorhouse and Another (1975) 133 CLR 1 followed
 WEA International Inc and Another v Hanimex Corporation Ltd (1987) 17 FCR 274 followed 
 
 Date of hearing: 6 --- 9, 12 --- 15 October 2009, 2 --- 6, 9 --- 11, 13, 19, 24, 26 November 2009 
 
 Place: SYDNEY 
 
 Division: GENERAL DIVISION 
 
 Category: Catchwords 
 
 Number of paragraphs: 636 
 
 Counsel for the Applicants: Mr A. J. L. Bannon SC with Mr J. M. Hennessy and Mr C. Dimitriadis 
 
 Solicitor for the Applicants: Gilbert + Tobin 
 
 Counsel for the Respondent: Mr R. Cobden SC with Mr R. P. L. Lancaster SC and Mr N. R. Murray 
 
 Solicitor for the Respondent: Herbert Geer 
 IN THE FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA 
 NEW SOUTH WALES DISTRICT REGISTRY GENERAL DIVISION 
 NSD 1802 of 2008 
 BETWEEN: ROADSHOW FILMS PTY LTD (ACN 100 746 870) 
 First Applicant 
 THE PARTIES IN THE ATTACHED SCHEDULE I 
 Second Applicant to Thirty-Fourth Applicant AND: IINET LIMITED (ACN 068 628 937) 
 Respondent 
 JUDGE: COWDROY J DATE OF ORDER: 4 FEBRUARY 2010 WHERE MADE: SYDNEY 
 
 THE COURT ORDERS THAT: 
 
 The Amended Application be dismissed. The diss_connect group was an email list set up by the Internet Industry Association ('IIA'), the industry group for the internet industry. The Court rejected an application for such group to intervene in these proceedings on 26 November 2009: see Roadshow Films Pty Ltd v iiNet Limited (No. 2) [2009] FCA 1391. The email list was set up for interested ISPs to share information regarding interactions with rights holders and copyright issues. Major ISPs represented in the list included the respondent, Telstra, Optus, Internode and AAPT. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 </title>
<title id="l1">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 101 Infringement by doing acts comprised in copyright</title>
<title id="l2">COPYRIGHT ACT 1968 - SECT 112E Communication by use of certain facilities</title>
<title id="l3">COPYRIGHT AMENDMENT (DIGITAL AGENDA) ACT 2000 </title>
<title id="l4">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l5">US FREE TRADE AGREEMENT IMPLEMENTATION ACT 2004 </title>
<title id="l6">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>