<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268 (9 November 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1268.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of whether an application pursuant to s 44(1) of the administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 raises a question of law for determination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of the formulation of grounds said to give rise to a question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of the approach to discerning within a document prepared and filed by a self-represented litigant raises questions said to constitute a question of law whether expressed inelegantly or otherwise</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of whether the application is to be dismissed pursuant to s 31a(2) of the federal court of australia act 1976 on the footing that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of whether the application should be dismissed pursuant to s 31a(2) of the federal court of australia act 1976 on the footing that the applicant has no reasonable prospect of successfully prosecuting the proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 672">consideration of the importance of the resolution by trial of contested questions of fact and questions of law and the relationship between the resolution of issues by trial and an application under s 31a(2) of the federal court of australia act 1976 .</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">appeals on a question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">nature of an appeal pursuant to s 44(1) of administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">where purported questions of law invite broad enquiry as to the construction and operation of statutory provisions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">where purported questions seek to characterise a question of fact as a question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">where purported questions invite court to examine evidence and other material before the tribunal and conduct a rehearing on aspects of the controversy determined by the tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">whether convenient to make for court to make findings of fact under s 44(7).  workers' compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">commonwealth employees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">meaning of 'injury' under commonwealth employees' compensation act 1930 (cth) and compensation (commonwealth government employees) act 1971 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">whether mere experiencing of event or condition necessary for development of a disease contracted by gradual process constitutes 'injury'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">s 101(2)(a) of commonwealth employees' rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">whether inchoate or contingent liabilities in respect of a disease contracted by gradual process transferred to administering authorities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">interaction of safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth) and veterans' entitlements act 1989 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 27">whether compensation payable in relation to service of defence force member where provision made for the payment of pension.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">income tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">ascertainment of assessable income</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">distinction between income and capital</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">compensation received</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">termination of agreement for manufacture and sale of motor vehicle engine components over period of years</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">whether compensation for termination a compensation for abandonment of part of the taxpayer's profit-making structure.  income tax assessment act 1936</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 456">s.25</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">constitutional law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">exempt documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">communications between government and salaried legal advisers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">freedom of information act 1982 (cth), s.42(1).  practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[1987] HCA 25">communications between government and salaried legal advisers.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">application to extend time</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">application to extend time to file a notice of appeal from decision of administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">whether there is satisfactory explanation for delay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">whether draft notice of appeal raises bona fide question of law for determination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">draft notice of appeal raises appellable grounds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 28">application for leave to file notice of appeal allowed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">newstart allowance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">participation failures</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">whether participation failures</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">whether three within 12 months</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">whether reasonable excuse</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">held no reasonable excuse</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 273">eight week non payment period properly imposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">applicant in receipt of newstart allowance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">four participation failures within a 12 month period</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">whether the two consecutive eight week non payment periods imposed are permitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">proof of valid delegation of employment services providers and delegation of employees as officers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">whether applicant had a reasonable excuse</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 109">decision affirmed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">social security</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">applicant did not enter into a newstart activity agreement on 3 occasions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">insisted that the agreements be drafted in quantum language</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">job network provider refused to alter the text or the language of the agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">conduct of applicant amounted to newstart participation failures</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">no reasonable excuse for committing the participation failure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">reasonableness of the excuse as understood or believed by the applicant irrelevant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">proof of delegation by an officer of the respondent to the job network provider made available and considered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2009] AATA 914">decision affirmed</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 28">There is no obligation upon a Tribunal to put to a party its thought processes and an erroneous finding of fact is not sufficient to constitute an error of law: see Waterford at 77; Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268 per Finn J at [31]. Nor was there any obligation for the Tribunal to ' put to ' Mr Evans that his testimony would not be accepted. The Tribunal was required to make its determination on the evidence before it. As its reasons reflect, it was simply not satisfied that the evidence before it disclosed the existence of an agreement between Mr Evans and his parents. Such finding does not constitute an error of law. Accordingly the Court is satisfied that no leave should be granted to appeal on the above ground. Ground 2 --- The Exclusion of Evidence
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] AATA 273">The reasonableness of appointments made under an agreement such as a Newstart activity agreement was considered by Mansfield J in 
 Secretary, Department of Employment, Education and Youth Affairs v Ferguson. [18] His Honour noted that appointments would need to be made with appropriate notice, that appointments conflicting with one another would lead to only one of them requiring attendance, and that attendance would need to be judged in substantive rather than absolute terms (e.g. arriving a few minutes late would not constitute a failure to attend). In Mr Roberts' case adequate notice was given, there were no conflicting appointments, and he simply did not attend the appointments. In 
 Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [19] Finn J, in circumstances broadly parallel to those before me, noted that intransigence on the part of the person required to enter into a Newstart activity agreement did not render the requirement to enter into such an agreement unreasonable. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] AATA 109">More specifically, the decision in Re Kronen was the subject of a Federal Court Appeal (refer Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268). Although the decision was primarily concerned with the issue of the negotiation of terms of an activity agreement, Finn J was aware that there were three non payment periods by reason of multiple participation failures. His Honour noted that the Tribunal had made a finding of repeated failures on the part of the applicant to enter into activity agreements and he did not discern any error of law infecting the cancellation decision .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2009] FCA 1546">The applicant seeks leave to appeal from the order made by the Court (Finn J) on 9 November 2009: Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268 (the dismissal decision). On that date, the Court dismissed the applicant's application by way of appeal on a question of law under s 44 of the Administrative Appeals Tribunal Act 1975 (Cth) (the AAT Act). The order was made under s 31A of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) and so is an interlocutory order: Kowalski v MMAL Staff Superannuation Fund Pty Ltd [2009] FCAFC 117. Consequently, leave to appeal is necessary by reason of s 24(1A) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2009] AATA 914">There is nothing in law which permits the applicant to negotiate with the respondent concerning the terms of an NAA (refer Re Dunn and Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2007] AATA 1031). Indeed it would appear that the applicant did not propose any negotiation of the written language of each of the NAA but rather attempted to impose a unilateral insistence failing which he would, and did, refuse to enter into each NAA. (Refer also Kronen v Secretary, Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations [2009] FCA 1268 , decided after the hearing but before delivery of this decision. Finn J at paragraphs 38-45 discussed the word negotiate appearing in s 605(3). In any event, for the reasons given above, the conduct of the applicant probably was not one of negotiating but rather of insistence of the NAA's being drafted in a language of his choosing). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 31A Summary judgment</title>
<title id="l4">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l5">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 44 Age pension not payable if pension rate nil</title>
<title id="l6">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 593 Qualification for newstart allowance</title>
<title id="l7">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 601 Activity test</title>
<title id="l8">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 605 Newstart Employment Pathway Plans--requirement</title>
<title id="l9">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 606 Newstart Employment Pathway Plans--terms</title>
<title id="l10">SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1991 - SECT 615 Newstart allowance not payable if person fails to attend interview etc. in certain circumstances</title>
<title id="l11">SOCIAL SECURITY (ADMINISTRATION) ACT 1999 </title>
<title id="l12">SOCIAL SECURITY (ADMINISTRATION) ACT 1999 - SECT 64 Effect of failing to comply with requirement to attend Department etc.</title>
<title id="l13">SOCIAL SECURITY (ADMINISTRATION) ACT 1999 - SECT 80 Cancellation or suspension determination</title>
<title id="l14">SOCIAL SECURITY (ADMINISTRATION) ACT 1999 - SECT 82 Cancellation or suspension for failure to take action to obtain foreign payment</title>
<title id="l15">SOCIAL SECURITY (ADMINISTRATION) ACT 1999 - SECT 131 Secretary may continue payment pending outcome of application for review</title>
<title id="l16">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>