<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Nelson v Comcare [2009] FCA 1149 (8 October 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/1149.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] AATA 214">workers' compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] AATA 214">claim employment contributed to a condition in a material degree</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] AATA 214">entitlement to compensation for medical treatment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] AATA 214">incapacity payments</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] AATA 214">psychological injury</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">decision of administrative appeals tribunal setting aside two reviewable decisions under safety, rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether tribunal made findings of fact in support of which there was no evidence or forgot or ignored evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal did not make findings of fact in support of which there was no evidence or forget evidence in relation to first reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether tribunal failed to consider submissions of substance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal not obliged to refer to every aspect of evidence or submissions supporting its view</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether compensable injuries found were properly the subject of a claim under the safety, rehabilitation and compensation act or properly considered to be the same injury as that originally notified</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal did not explain how additional conditions arose out of claimed injury</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal accepted respondent no longer suffered from effects of injury as originally notified and claimed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal did not give sufficient reasons for decision that compensable injuries were related to claimed injury</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">tribunal failed to consider important alternative explanation in relation to second reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">finding of material fact for which there was no evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">both reviewable decisions to be remitted to tribunal administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">applicant appeals under s 44 of administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth), s 5 of administrative decisions (judicial review) act 1977 (cth) and s 39b of judiciary act 1903 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">grounds of appeal same</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether court has jurisdiction under both applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether judicial review be limited to question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">whether court should exercise discretion to restrict to questions of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">comcare v etheridge (2006) applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.19" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 236">applications heard simultaneously</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">whether injury was contributed to or aggravated in a material degree by employment under s4(1) of the safety rehabilitation and compensation act 1988 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">effect of word "material" upon definition of "disease"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">requirements before remitting matter to tribunal.  statutory interpretation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">resort to textual material</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 15">"material" intended to require something more than "a mere contributing factor".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">appeal under s44 of the administrative appeals tribunal act 1975 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">administrative appeals tribunal affirming decision of migration agents registration authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether notice of appeal complies with the requirements of order 53 rule 3 of the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">what constitutes a question of law administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">review of decision of migration agents registration authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">suspension of migration agent's registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">breach of code of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether response to notice of intention to cancel business visa is an "application"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether alleged question of law assumed particular construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">relevance of alleged recommendation by conduct advisory panel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether consideration of the recommendation a question of fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether adequate reasons given</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">whether the reasoning process for reaching conclusions and findings of material questions of fact was exposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 50">level of satisfaction required for finding breach of code of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">application for judicial review of decision of administrative appeals tribunal rejecting in part a claim for compensation under s.29 compensation (australian government employees) act 1971 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">distinction between "aggravation" and "acceleration" within the meaning of s.29(1)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">whether decision maker must consider acceleration independently of aggravation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">whether period of compensable incapacity following an acceleration of a pre-existing degenerative disease could be finite in some cases and open-ended in others</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">whether tribunal's finding as to termination of compensable period lacked a proper foundation in the absence of evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 116">onus of proof regarding date of termination of compensable period.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">decision to exercise discretion to grant partner visa to applicant despite her failure of character test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">whether tribunal failed to address a clearly articulated submission of the minister in its reasons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">whether the tribunal's reasons addressed the prospect that the visa applicant may engage in fraudulent non-migration conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">held</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">the tribunal made general findings in relation to ' any misconduct ' and ' the law '</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">such findings addressed the prospect of both migration and non-migration offences</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">the minister's submission was addressed by the tribunal's reasons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 37">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 614">compensation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 614">commonwealth employees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 614">aggravation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 614">decisions under review are set aside</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">veterans' affairs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">application remitted from federal court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">veteran died after vrb decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">claim by estate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">multiple hypotheses</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">whether death from liver cancer connected with alcohol dependence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">applicant's representative did not call evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2010] AATA 298">decision of vrb affirmed</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 37">The above principle is well established: see Nelson v Comcare [2009] FCA 1149 at [50] per Foster J; Zoia v Secretary, Department of Employment and Workplace Relations [2008] FCA 988 at [29] per Siopis J; Comcare v Rowe [2002] FCA 1034 ; (2002) 35 AAR 410 at [12] per Merkel J; Australian Postal Corporation v Hughes [2009] FCA 1057 ; (2009) 111 ALD 579 at [60] ; Casarotto v Australian Postal Corporation [1989] FCA 116 ; (1989) 86 ALR 399 at 402-403 per Hill J. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] AATA 614">On 19 March 2008 the Tribunal decided to affirm the decisions of the Respondent that are the subject of the applications for review. The Applicant appealed the Tribunal's decisions and in a judgment by Foster J of the Federal Court on 8 October 2009, the Tribunal's decisions were set aside and remitted to the Tribunal to be determined according to the law: Nelson v Comcare [2009] FCA 1149. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] AATA 298">The expression material degree was discussed by Davies J in Repatriation Commission v Bendy [1989] FCA 170 ; [1989] FCA 170 ; (1980) 18 ALD 144 at 146. His Honour decided that the expression refers to a contribution of a causal nature and any de minimis contribution which was tenuous or did not influence the events was immaterial and was to be ignored. More recently Finn J in Comcare v Sahu-Khan (2007) FCA 15 at paragraphs 15-17 (and in reference to Bendy ) decided the expression in a material degree requires an evaluation of all relevant contributing factors for the purpose of asking whether the employees employment did or did not contribute materially to the suffering of the ailment. In Nelson v Comcare [2009] FCA 1149 Foster J discussed the concept of material contribution and aggravation, and by reference to other decisions of the Federal Court and decided that an ailment was aggravated if it was made more severe by the employment. For the purposes of this analysis we are satisfied that the word employment may be substituted for the word service as it appears in subsection (d). </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 </title>
<title id="l1">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 4 Extension to external Territories</title>
<title id="l2">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 14 Disclosure of interests by members</title>
<title id="l3">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 19 Divisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l4">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 20 Arrangement of business</title>
<title id="l5">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 21 Constitution of Tribunal for exercise of powers</title>
<title id="l6">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 21A Reconstitution of Tribunal at the request of a party</title>
<title id="l7">ADMINISTRATIVE APPEALS TRIBUNAL ACT 1975 - SECT 44 Appeals to Federal Court of Australia from decisions of the Tribunal</title>
<title id="l8">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 </title>
<title id="l9">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 4 Interpretation</title>
<title id="l10">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 14 Compensation for injuries</title>
<title id="l11">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 16 Compensation in respect of medical expenses etc.</title>
<title id="l12">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 19 Compensation for injuries resulting in incapacity</title>
<title id="l13">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 20 Compensation for injuries resulting in incapacity where employee is in receipt of a superannuation pension</title>
<title id="l14">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 21 Compensation for injuries resulting in incapacity where employee is in receipt of a lump sum benefit</title>
<title id="l15">SAFETY, REHABILITATION AND COMPENSATION ACT 1988 - SECT 21A Compensation for injuries resulting in incapacity if employee is in receipt of a superannuation pension and a lump sum benefit</title>
<title id="l16">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>