<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Garage Wholesalers Pty Ltd ACN 109 969 059 v Engineering Software Solutions Pty Ltd ACN 109 359 499 [2009] FCA 361 (16 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/361.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">finance broker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">finance brokers control act 1975 (wa)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">finance broker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">definition</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">whether carrying on business as such</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">licensing requirement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">financial advisor and arranger of major project capital</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">whether carrying on business as finance broker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">information memorandum</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">to be circulated to prospective financiers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">fee for preparation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">part of agreement for services including arrangement of project finance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">whether preparation of memorandum is service provided in capacity as a finance broker</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">whether fee recoverable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">construction of finance brokers control act 1975</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">protective and penal aspects</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">preliminary issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">illegality</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[1993] FCA 293">whether within preliminary issue.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">leave for agent, not being a legally qualified practitioner, to appear on behalf of a company</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">0.4 r.14 federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">the nature of the discretion pursuant to 0.4 r.14</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">considerations taken into account in deciding whether to exercise the discretion.  trade practices act 1974  federal court rules : 0.4 r.14  practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">application for company to be represented by an agent not being a solicitor or counsel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">nature of the discretion conferred upon the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1984] FCA 232">federal court rules 1979 (cth), o. 4, r. 14. held: (per smithers and keely jj., sweeney j. not deciding) o. 4, r. 14(2) which relevantly provides that a corporation may not without the leave of the court commence or carry on any proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor, confers a discretion upon the court to grant leave, which discretion will be exercised in favour of a company where there is sufficient reason.  (2) (per smithers and keely jj., sweeney j. not deciding.) where a refusal to grant leave would leave the company unable to continue its proceedings, the loss of skilled legal assistance to the court should be a factor which carries no weight in the exercise of the discretion.  adam p. brown male fashions pty ltd v. philip morris incorporated (1981) 148 clr 170 mcgrath v. dobie [1890] viclawrp 133 ; (1890) 16 vlr 646 ; o'toole v. scott (1965) ac 939 ; hubbard association of scientologists international v. anderson [1972] vicrp 37 ; (1972) vr 340 ; tritonia ltd v. equity and law life assurance society (1943) ac 584 ; frinton and walton urban district council v. walton and district sand and mineral co. ltd (1938) 1 all er 649 ; london county council and london tramways co. (1897) 13 tlr 254 ; scriven v. jescott (leeds) ltd (1908) 53 sol. j. 101; federated engine-drivers' and firemen's association of australasia v. broken hill proprietary co. ltd [1913] hca 71 ; (1913) 16 clr 245 ; house v. the king [1936] hca 40 ; (1936) 55 clr 499. 4</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">application for leave pursuant to o 4 r 14(2) for applicant corporation to carry on proceeding otherwise than by a solicitor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">applicant corporation seeks leave for sole director and shareholder to conduct litigation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">principles relevant to grant of leave by court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">capability of sole director to conduct proceedings on behalf of applicant corporation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">apparent impecuniosity of both applicant corporation and sole director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">requirement for interpreter to assist sole director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">substantive issues involving narrow but difficult questions of law in substantive proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">no legal qualifications or training of sole director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">discrepancies in previous evidence as to financial position of applicant compared with current financial position</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">lack of explanation or evidence as to financial position of applicant corporation and sole director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">no other applicant represented by counsel in proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">trial of substantive issues estimated to be three weeks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">litigation strenuously opposed by respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">sole director the applicant's principal witness in substantive proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.15" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 878">scandalous allegations by sole director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">alleged held position of network communications officer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">applicant required to participate in the workplace change process for restructure of university's information technology department</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">applicant did not express interest in new position</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">unilaterally transferred to another position</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">claim that university contravened s.52 and s.53b of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">claim dismissed.  accrued jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">contention that when trade practices claim found not to be made in trade and commerce, the accrued jurisdiction in tort and contract fails</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">exercise of discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">tort and contract claim should be heard.  tort and contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">claim of variation of contract of employment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.11" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">incorporation of variation by reference</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.12" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">breach of implied term of trust and confidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.13" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">negligent advice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.14" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 964">claim dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 763">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 763">transfer of proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 763">opposition of parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 763">court acting on its own motion</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 878">First, there is no material before me which demonstrates in any way that Mr Yahalom is capable of conducting the proceeding on behalf of the applicant. There are no documents before me prepared by Mr Yahalom, either pursuant to directions of this Court or otherwise, which, for example, are "quite clear and comprehensive" as was considered to be the case by McKerracher J in Garage Wholesalers Pty Ltd v Engineering Software Solutions Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 361 at [4] . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FMCA 964">I am satisfied that the principle was clearly articulated in Beck v Spalla [2005] FCAFC 82 at [25] per Hill, Finn and Kenny JJ: ...It is well established that when the Federal Court has jurisdiction to determine a federal matter, it has authority to determine the whole controversy and not merely that part of it which attracted federal jurisdiction: Moorgate Tobacco Co Ltd v Philip Morris Ltd [1980] HCA 32 ; (1980) 145 CLR 457 at 472. It is equally well accepted that if the federal question is decided adversely, is struck out, or is found not necessary to be decided the matter does not cease to be in the jurisdiction of the Court: Burgundy Royale Investments Pty Ltd v Westpac Banking Corporation (1987) 18 FCR 212 ; Unilan Holdings Pty Ltd v Kerin [1993] FCA 420 ; (1993) 44 FCR 481 and Moorgate at 476 (see generally, the article by Allsop J: "Federal Jurisdiction and the Jurisdiction of the Federal Court of Australia in 2002", (2002) 23 Australian Bar Review 29 at 41 ff). 
A number of reported transfers have been made from the Federal Court to the Federal Magistrates Court under s.32A(b) of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth), see Garage Wholesalers Pty Ltd v Engineering Software Solutions Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 361 at [7] - [8] per McKerracher J:
 
 [7] Section 32AB of the Federal Court of Australia Act 1976 (Cth) (the Act) provides for discretionary transfer of proceedings on the application of a party or on the Court's own initiative. Section 32AB(6) provides that the following considerations are to be taken into account: 
 (a) any Rules of Court made for the purposes of subsection (4); and 
 (b) whether proceedings in respect of an associated matter are pending in the Federal Magistrates Court; and 
 (c) whether the resources of the Federal Magistrates Court are sufficient to hear and determine the proceeding; and 
 (d) the interests of the administration of justice. 
 [8] Further O 82 r 4---8 of the Rules outlines considerations which may be taken into account in addition to the factors to which the Court must have regard under s 32AB(6) of the Act.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2009] FCA 763">The power conferred by s 32AB has been exercised on a number of occasions and in diverse situations. In Garage Wholesalers Pty Ltd v Engineering Software Solutions Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 361 , McKerracher J transferred a proceeding alleging a contravention of s 52 of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). His Honour considered that the proceeding involved a claim for a moderate amount and that it was likely that it could be dealt with more expeditiously and less formally in the Federal Magistrates Court. See also Kurniadi v Loh [2002] FCA 1021 , 193 ALR 253. A further instance is provided by Ozluk v Australian Turkish &amp; Kurdish Community Services Co-Operative Ltd [2008] FCA 352 where Graham J transferred an application brought pursuant to s 46PO of the Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission Act 1986 (Cth). See also Beetham v Cortra Pty Ltd [2003] FCA 150. In Melville v Macquarie University [2006] FCA 1761 Madgwick J transferred an application brought under the Workplace Relations Act 1996 (Cth) for unlawful termination of employment. See also Sheikholeslami v University of New South Wales [2006] FCA 712 ; Rixon v Business Parcell Express Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 969. Applications arising under the Migration Act 1958 (Cth) have also been the subject of orders made pursuant to s 32AB: Nadu v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2002] FCA 571 ; Hong Bo Su v Minister for Immigration and Multicultural and Indigenous Affairs [2003] FCA 1355. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 32AB Discretionary transfer of civil proceedings to the Federal Magistrates Court</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>