<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339 (9 April 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/339.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">whether the usual order as to costs should be made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">whether the matter was one to which the workplace relations act applied</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">held that each proceeding was a matter arising under the workplace relations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">held that the prohibition against the ordering of costs contained in s 824(1) of the act applies in each the proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">held that the fact that each matter was something of a test case would not require a departure from the ordinary rule as to costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 58">no order as to costs made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1470">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1470">appeals from decisions of federal magistrates court summarily dismissing proceedings on the basis that they had no reasonable prospects of success</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1470">statutory construction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1470">meaning of provisions in pt 16 of the workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1470">freedom of association.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">where first amended statement of claim and second further amended statement of claim struck out</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">where proceeding commenced on 8 march 2006 before pre-reform act was amended by workchoices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">where s 347 of pre-reform act repealed on 27 march 2006 and superseded by s 824(2) workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">whether an order for costs is determined under s 347 and or s 824(2) workplace relations act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">s 824(2) deemed applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">whether applicant acted unreasonably for the purposes of s 824(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">costs determined costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">where costs hearing adjourned for failure of applicant to comply with the court's directions as to the filing and service of submissions relating to costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 879">whether respondent entitled to costs thrown away</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">union delegates</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">redundancy and retrenchment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">dismissal for prohibited reasons</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">reverse onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">presumption not displaced</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1452">reinstatement.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">litigation guardian</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">procedure for appointing a litigation guardian under div 11.2 of the federal magistrate rules 2001</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">whether federal magistrate entitled to make stay orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">discussion of procedural requirements where court considers litigation guardian may be needed administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">where federal magistrate stayed proceedings pending appointment of a litigation guardian or psychiatric evidence that litigation guardian not required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">whether federal magistrate failed to provide appellant with adequate notice and opportunity to be heard</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.8" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">whether appellant denied procedural fairness practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.9" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">unrepresented litigant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.10" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 114">procedure where issue of summary dismissal emerges where also an issue of litigant's capacity to conduct proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">costs of notice of motion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">meaning of 'proceeding' under s 824 of workplace relations act 1996 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">whether notice of motion instituted vexatiously or without reasonable cause</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">whether notice of motion an unreasonable act or omission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 745">application for costs refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">industrial relations act 1988</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">interpretation of award</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">application for particulars of allegations of serious misconduct against university professor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">whether committee of inquiry denied natural justice to professor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">whether proceeding is properly characterised as a proceeding in a matter arising under the industrial relations act 1988 for purposes of s. 347</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">whether proceeding instituted "without reasonable cause"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[1989] FCA 166">whether university entitled to costs.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">industrial law (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">conciliation and arbitration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">industrial dispute</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">registered organization</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">eligibility for membership</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">workers involved in labour in or in connexion with metalliferous mining</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">engagement of project engineers by uranium mining companies to construct works</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">labour employed by engineers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">whether engaged in activities in connexion with metalliferous mining</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=cited from="[1978] HCA 51">conciliation and arbitration act 1904 (cth), s. 4 (1) "industrial dispute".</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">application for</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">no vexatious or unreasonable conduct demonstrated warranting costs order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">penalty hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">under payment of wages, long service leave and allowances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">limited co-operation with investigating authority</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2011] FMCA 261">bearing on penalty.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 268">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 268">practice &amp; procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 268">application for costs under s.570 fair work act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=citing from="[2010] FMCA 268">where proceeding discontinued after first directions hearing.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">industrial law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">adverse action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">industrial activity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">whether decision by employer to take adverse action taken for proscribed reason(s)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">whether employer's reasons for taking adverse action relevant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 284">construction of ss 340, 346 of fair work act 2009 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 28">workplace relations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 28">alleged dismissal for a prohibited reason</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 28">spurious grounds of appeal costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 28">orders for the payment of legal and professional costs and disbursements in connection with the appeals in accordance with s 824 of the workplace relations act.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FWA 2225">15 [2009] FCA 339 (9 April 2009). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] FMCA 261">It contends that in the result the costs in preparing the case were thrown away. Before coming to examine the respondents' contentions closely, it is first necessary to consider the principles relevant to the exercise of this power. Subsection 1 has the mandatory effect of directing that a party to a proceeding must not be ordered to pay costs unless the proceeding is instituted vexatiously or without reasonable cause. In Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd , [3] Moore J observed at [53] that: 
 "In considering whether a proceeding was instituted vexatiously or without reasonable cause for the purpose of section 824(1) it is necessary to distinguish between the situation where an applicant has merely been unsuccessful on the case he or she has sought to propound and the situation where the applicant's case was entirely misconceived. In relation to the former category, an application is not commenced without reasonable cause simply because the applicant's arguments are rejected by the Court. However, in relation to the latter category it is likely that it can be said that the proceeding was instituted without reasonable cause such that a costs award is appropriate. " 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] QDC 497">Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339 --- cited. "
 
 [170] That passage was cited by Moore J in Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339 at [53] , as part of a summary of the principles applicable in relation to s 824 which was approved by the full Federal Court on appeal: [2010] FCAFC 28 at [40] .</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] QIRComm 126"></sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FMCA 268">The respondent has helpfully provided me with a copy of a decision of Moore J in Dowling v Fairfax Media Publication Pty Ltd (2009) FCA 339 where his Honour deals at [52 --- 54] with an application for costs.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2010] FCA 284">In all of the cases to which I was referred which had been decided under the equivalent provisions of the IR Act and the WR Act and others which I have examined, the court proceeded on the basis that evidence of the employer's subjective reasons for taking the impugned action was relevant in deciding whether the employer had taken the action because of the existence of one or more of the circumstances in which such action was impermissible. See, for example, Bowling v General Motors Holden Pty Ltd (1975) 8 ALR 197 at 205-6 (s 5); Maritime Union of Australia v Geraldton Port Authority [1999] FCA 899 ; (1999) 93 FCR 34 at 69, 83-5 (ss 298K-298L); Australian Municipal, Administrative, Clerical and Services Union v Ansett Australia Ltd [2000] FCA 441 ; (2000) 175 ALR 173 at 187-192 (ss 298K-298L); Elliott v Kodak Australasia Pty Ltd [2001] FCA 807 ; (2001) 108 IR 23 at 30-1(ss 298K-298L); Finance Sector Union of Australia v Australia and New Zealand Banking Group Ltd [2002] FCA 631 ; [2002] FCA 631 ; (2002) 120 FCR 107 at 143-4 (ss 298K-298L); The United Firefighters Union of Australia v Metropolitan Fire and Emergency Services Board (2003) 123 IR 86 at 113-5 (ss 298K-298L); Seymour v Saint-Gobain Abrasives Pty Ltd [2006] FCA 1452 ; (2006) 161 IR 9 ( "Seymour" ) at 13-14 (ss 792-793); Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339 ; (2009) 182 IR 28 at [40] (ss 792-793). It is to be noted that the approach remained the same after the criminal offences were replaced by a civil penalty regime. Counsel for Mr Barclay did not cite any authority which supported the contrary proposition which they urged on the court. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2010] FCAFC 28">54 Both proceedings were heard before his Honour Justice Moore in March of 2009. In April 2009, his Honour delivered judgment and made orders that in each proceeding the application was to be dismissed. Consequential costs orders were also made: Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339 , 182 IR 28.  40 The primary judge recorded the relevant principles to be applied in respect of costs in his reasons for judgment (see Dowling v Fairfax Media Publications Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 339) at [49] - [56]. His Honour proceeded to say at [57] in respect of the claims made by the appellant in proceeding NSD 1744 of 2008:
 '... There was at the time these proceedings were commenced, and this remains the case, no conceivable basis for joining the non-executive directors or prosecuting the claim against them. It was not more than fanciful speculation to think that they may have been involved in the termination. Joining them and prosecuting the case against them was an unreasonable act. ...' 

 
The primary judge proceeded to order that the appellant pay the costs of the said non-executive directors in proceeding NSD 1744 of 2008. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 11 General powers of a court</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 27 Parties may question witnesses</title>
<title id="l3">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 40 Witness called in error</title>
<title id="l4">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 41 Improper questions</title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l6">INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT 1988 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>